<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="3M Company"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/26/business/26mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Profit Falls to $928 Million, as Sales Rose 9.6 %<date>Published: January 25, 2011</date><text>The 3M Company said on Tuesday that profitability suffered last quarter as more spending for advertising and research ate into margins, and warned that rising costs for raw materials would put pressure on its bottom line.3M, the diversified manufacturer known for its tape and other office products, also reported a fourth-quarter profit of $928 million, or $1.28 a share, compared with $935 million, or $1.30 a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 9.6 percent, to $6.7 billion, lifted by especially strong growth in Asia and Latin America. Analysts, on average, had expected 3M, which is based in St. Paul, to report a profit of $1.27 a share on sales of $6.6 billion, Thomson Reuters said. In a sign of 3M’s caution, it said it planned to hold back discretionary spending to protect its margins in the face of rising raw material costs, higher pension costs and tax rates, and a lackluster economic recovery in the United States, where a high unemployment rate and chronic weakness in the housing market have soured consumer sentiment. Even so, 3M raised its forecast for 2011 earnings to a range of $5.95 to $6.20 a share, up from a previous forecast of $5.90 to $6.10. It earned $5.63 a share in 2010. 3M shares closed down $1.82, or 2 percent, at $88.50.The 3M Company said on Tuesday that profitability suffered last quarter as more spending for advertising and research ate into margins, and warned that rising costs for raw materials would put pressure on its bottom line.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/26/opinion/26rich.html?ref=3mcompany">Who Killed the Disneyland Dream?<date>Published: December 25, 2010</date><text>OF the many notable Americans we lost in 2010, three leap out as paragons of a certain optimistic American spirit that we also seemed to lose this year. Two you know: Theodore Sorensen, the speechwriter present at the creation of J.F.K.’s clarion call to “ask what you can do for your country,” and Richard Holbrooke, the diplomat who brought peace to the killing fields of Bosnia in the 1990s. Holbrooke, who was my friend, came of age in the Kennedy years and exemplified its can-do idealism. He gave his life to the proposition that there was nothing an American couldn’t accomplish if he marshaled his energy and talents. His premature death — while heroically bearing the crushing burdens of Afghanistan and Pakistan — is tragic in more ways than many Americans yet realize.But a third representative American optimist who died this year, at age 91, is a Connecticut man who was not a player in great events and whom I’d never heard of until I read his Times obituary: Robbins Barstow, an amateur filmmaker who for decades recorded his family’s doings in home movies of such novelty and quality that one of them, the 30-minute “Disneyland Dream,” was admitted to the National Film Registry of the Library of Congress two years ago. That rare honor elevates Barstow’s filmmaking to a pantheon otherwise restricted mostly to Hollywood classics, from “Citizen Kane” to “Star Wars.” “Disneyland Dream” was made in the summer of 1956, shortly before the dawn of the Kennedy era. You can watch it on line at archive.org or on YouTube. Its narrative is simple. The young Barstow family of Wethersfield, Conn. — Robbins; his wife, Meg; and their three children aged 4 to 11 — enter a nationwide contest to win a free trip to Disneyland, then just a year old. The contest was sponsored by 3M, which asked contestants to submit imaginative encomiums to the wonders of its signature product. Danny, the 4-year-old, comes up with the winning testimonial, emblazoned on poster board: “I like ‘Scotch’ brand cellophane tape because when some things tear then I can just use it.” Soon enough, the entire neighborhood is cheering the Barstows as they embark on their first visit to the golden land of Anaheim, Calif. As narrated by Robbins Barstow (he added his voiceover soundtrack to the silent Kodachrome film in 1995), every aspect of this pilgrimage is a joy, from the “giant TWA Super Constellation” propeller plane (seating 64) that crosses the country in a single day (with a refueling stop in St. Louis) to the home-made Davy Crockett jackets the family wears en route. To watch “Disneyland Dream” now as a boomer inevitably sets off pangs of longing for a vanished childhood fantasyland: not just Walt Disney’s then-novel theme park but all the sunny idylls of 1950s pop culture. As it happens, Disney’s Davy Crockett, the actor Fess Parker, also died this year. So did Barbara Billingsley, matriarch of the sitcom “Leave It to Beaver,” whose fictional family, the Cleavers, first appeared in 1957 and could have lived next door to the Barstows. But the real power of this film is more subtle and pertinent than nostalgia. When the Barstows finally arrive at the gates of Disneyland itself and enter its replica of Main Street, U.S.A. — “reconstructed as it might have been half a century earlier,” as the narration says — we realize that the America of “Disneyland Dream” is as many years distant from us as that picture-postcard Main Street was from this Connecticut family. The almost laughably low-tech primitivism of the original Disneyland, the futuristic Tomorrowland included, looks as antique in 2010 as Main Street’s horse-drawn buggies and penny-candy emporium looked to the Barstows. Many of America’s more sweeping changes since 1956 are for the better. You can’t spot a nonwhite face among the family’s neighbors back home or at Disneyland. Indeed, according to Neal Gabler’s epic biography of Disney, civil rights activists were still pressuring the park to hire black employees as late as 1963, the same year that Martin Luther King Jr.’s march on Washington and Betty Friedan’s “Feminine Mystique” started upending the Wonder Bread homogeneity that suffuses the America of “Disneyland Dream.” But, for all those inequities, economic equality seemed within reach in 1956, at least for the vast middle class. (Michael Harrington’s exposé of American poverty, “The Other America,” would not rock this complacency until 1962.) The sense that the American promise of social and economic mobility was attainable to anyone who sought it permeates “Disneyland Dream” from start to finish. The Barstows exemplified that postwar middle class. Robbins Barstow’s day job was as a director of professional development for a state teachers’ union. His family wanted for nothing, but finances were tight. Once in California they cheerfully stretch their limited expense money ($300 for the week) by favoring picnics over restaurants. As they dive into the pool at the old Huntington Sheraton, the grand Pasadena hotel where they’re bivouacked, they marvel at its reminders of “bygone days of more leisurely and gentle upper-class style and elegance.”</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/29/business/29mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Company Reports Higher Profit on 11% Sales Gain<date>Published: October 28, 2010</date><text>The 3M Company reported a higher quarterly profit on Thursday, lifted by strong sales to the consumer electronics industry. But it reduced the top end of its full-year forecast and said rising raw materials costs and other pressures were cutting into margins, sending the company’s shares sharply lower.3M, a diversified manufacturer that also makes a variety of medical products, also posted slower organic sales growth than in previous quarters. Last flu season, 3M had a surge in sales of surgical masks, but it did not expect to have the sales it enjoyed last year because of the H1N1 virus scare. It said the long economic downturn also appeared to be discouraging patients from undergoing elective procedures that use its products. The company also pointed to what it characterized as temporary “turbulence” in the flat-panel TV market. Third-quarter sales had a double-digit drop, and TV manufacturers are expected to clear out their swollen LCD TV inventories during the fourth quarter. 3M makes optical film used in the screens. Nicholas Heymann, an analyst at Sterne Agee, said that would hurt 3M’s fourth-quarter results. 3M posted a third-quarter profit of $1.1 billion, or $1.53 a share, up from $971 million, or $1.35 a share, a year earlier. The company, whose products include Post-it notes as well as industrial and electronics products, said sales rose 11 percent, to $6.9 billion, with double-digit sales increases in three of its six units. Analysts on average expected 3M to report a profit of $1.51 a share on sales of $6.83 billion, according to Thomson Reuters. The company said it now expected a full-year profit of $5.70 to $5.74 a share, down from a previous estimate of $5.70 to $5.80 a share. It said the reduction was related to a series of acquisitions during the quarter, including its $900 million purchase of Cogent, a maker of identification systems used to screen travelers at border crossings. 3M’s shares, which hit a 52-week high earlier this week, fell 6.4 percent on Wall Street, closing at 84.56.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/10/08/3m-gains-52-of-cogents-stock/?ref=3mcompany">3M Gains 52% of Cogent's Stock<date>October 8, 2010, 4:32 pm</date><text>The 3M Company said on Friday that it had received 52 percent of Cogent‘s shares in its tender offer for the fingerprint identification company, despite opposition from some shareholders who thought 3M should make a higher bid than $10.50 a share. In the days preceding Thursday’s midnight deadline for 3M’s offer, Cogent’s shares traded above the offering price as arbitragers and other investors anticipated a higher bid. Those hopes seemed dashed on Friday, as Cogent fell 4 cents, to close at $10.49. 3M said that Cogent shareholders tendered 46.4 million shares and that it was extending the offer for all of the company’s outstanding shares until Oct. 22 at midnight. Cogent’s chief executive, Ming Hsieh, helped ensure the success of 3M’s offer to gain majority control of the company by declaring before the deadline that he would tender his nearly 39 percent stake. On Thursday, the Deal Professor examined the issues involved in 3M’s tender offer for Cogent. Go to Press Release from 3M » Go to Related Article from The Deal Professor »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/31/business/31cogent.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Buy Cogent to Expand Its Security Business<date>Published: August 30, 2010</date><text>The 3M Company agreed to buy Cogent, a manufacturer of fingerprint identification systems for governments and companies, for $943 million to expand its security services products.The offer is for $10.50 a share, 3M said Monday in a statement, or 18 percent more than Cogent’s closing price on Friday. The price includes about $513 million in acquired cash. Cogent makes fingerprint and palm print identification systems that allow customers to electronically capture print images, encode prints into files and compare a set of fingerprints and palm prints to a database containing potentially millions of prints. With Cogent, 3M is tapping into the $4 billion global biometric market that it said was projected to grow more than 20 percent annually. 3M, a maker of IDs and laminates to protect against tampering, will add Cogent, which had $130 million in revenue last year, to its security systems division. “It does fit their long-term strategy of enhancing their product lines by looking at emerging growth areas, security being one of those,” said Jeff Windau, an analyst in St. Louis with Edward Jones. Shares of Cogent rose $2.18, or 24 percent, to close at $11.09 on Monday. 3M, the maker of Post-it Notes and Scotch tape, fell $1.35, to $79.65. 3M, based in St. Paul, said the acquisition would reduce earnings by 9 to 10 cents a share in the year after the transaction. Excluding items like the anticipated integration expenses, the deal will add as much as 2 cents a share over the same period, 3M said. Cogent employs about 500 people and has operations in Ohio and Virginia, as well as in Austria, Britain, Canada and China. Ming Hsieh, Cogent’s chief executive and founder, will be part of the combined business, 3M said, without providing further details.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/08/31/3m-to-acquire-people-tracker/?ref=3mcompany">3M to Acquire People-Tracker<date>August 31, 2010, 7:40 am</date><text>3M said Tuesday that it had agreed to buy Attenti Holdings, an Israeli supplier of technology to track people remotely, for $230 million in cash. Attenti, owned by a group of investors lead by Francisco Partners, makes devices and systems that help monitor people’s movement as they await trial, serve time on probation, or reside in senior care centers. It supplies companies and government agencies all over the world. The deal represents another move in the security business for 3M, which on Monday announced it was buying Cogent, a maker of biometric recognition systems. Go to 3M Statement » Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Related Article from Bloomberg News via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/28/business/media/28adco.html?ref=3mcompany">At 30, Post-it Notes Are the Office Product That Works at Home<date>Published: July 27, 2010</date><text>IN a new commercial for Super Sticky Notes by Post-it, the 3M brand, scheduled to begin next Monday, a Jack Russell terrier eyes an orange note with a drawing of a bone that is affixed several feet above on a kitchen wall. After a few jumps, he sinks his teeth into the note, then hangs suspended by it.“Post-it Super Sticky Notes hold on stronger, and longer, but of course remove cleanly,” says a voiceover. In another spot, a boy sees a drawing of a soccer ball on an out-of-reach Post-it Note, gets a step stool and ends up hanging by the note as well. The new hyperbolic ads are among several that highlight home uses for Post-it products, which were originally intended for offices. As part of its 30th anniversary this year, the brand is doing much to emphasize nonoffice uses. On Tuesday, it will unveil a billboard in Grand Central Terminal consisting of more than 100,000 Post-it Notes by the artist Eric Daigh, based on the winning entry of a collage poster contest, a joint effort by Allison T. Hilgert, 17, of Crystal River, Fla., and Ysanne Taylor, 16, of Hernando, Fla. Both attend Lecanto School of Art at Lecanto High School in Florida. The actress Angela Kinsey from, naturally, “The Office” will appear. “The product has found its way into homes through the office channel,” said William Smith, vice president for the office supply division at 3M. “And this billboard component gets young people involved and gets to the educational arena and to a whole generation of users coming up.”  The company declines to reveal annual revenue for the brand, but its consumer products and office division, which includes Post-it and several other popular brands like Scotch Magic Tape and Scotch-Brite scouring sponges, posted revenue of $3.47 billion in 2009, according to public financial filings. The Post-it brand spent $2.8 million on advertising in 2009, less than a third of the $8.6 million it spent in 2008, according to the Kantar Media unit of WPP. In 1967, a 3M scientist, Spencer Silver, invented a glue with a slightly granular surface that prevented complete adhesion, but the company could not find an application for the underachieving adhesive. Then, in the early 1970s it introduced the Post-it Bulletin Board, essentially a photograph of a cork bulletin board coated with the substance and to which pieces of scrap paper could be attached. “Sales were disappointing,” noted a 2005 article about the brand in The Rake magazine. “Part of the problem was that it wasn’t just documents that stuck to the board’s surface; dust did, too. Perhaps more importantly, there just wasn’t much demand for a better bulletin board.” Then Art Fry, another 3M scientist, was practicing with his church choir and grew frustrated that slips of paper he used as bookmarks kept falling out of his hymnal. So, using some of Mr. Silver’s adhesive, he made sticky bookmarks, which evolved into notepaper. Notepads produced for internal use at 3M were a hit, but when they were tested in four markets in 1977, shoppers showed little interest. The next year the company descended upon Boise, Idaho, for what was known internally as the Boise Blitz. Free samples were widely distributed to offices, and so habit-forming was the product that more than 90 percent of Boiseans given samples said they would buy it. When the brand was officially introduced in 1980, using just yellow pads, the company again circulated free samples liberally, including to chief executives of Fortune 500 companies and their secretaries. Today, more than 1,000 Post-it products are sold in 150 countries, and the notes have permeated popular culture: A Post-it Note is what a boyfriend of Carrie Bradshaw uses to dump her in a 2003 episode of “Sex and the City,” what the characters of Meredith Grey and Derek Shepherd use to write their wedding vows on in the season finale of “Grey’s Anatomy” in 2009; and what the main characters in “Romy and Michele’s High School Reunion” in 1997 claim to have invented since graduation.  YouTube, meanwhile, features many videos that capture reactions when the unsuspecting discover that their cars, offices or bedrooms have been covered with thousands of Post-it Notes. At first the product was intended only for affixing to paper, but consumers had their own ideas. “Suddenly we were looking at a lot of vertical applications and substrates besides paper,” said Tony Clinch, technical director of the office supplies division at 3M. Introduced in 2003, Super Sticky notes were meant to withstand gravity and stay attached to computers, doors and other surfaces not originally considered. Using ethnographic studies, the company observes how products are used in homes, and develops products to better suit evolving uses. New or innovative products, like Post-it labels that feature full adhesive backs, introduced last year, and recycled pads with a plant-based adhesive that were introduced this year, aim to keep the brand ahead of imitators, like store brands made by Staples and Office Depot. “Mothers will tell us, ‘If I want my daughter to see it, I leave it on her bedroom door,’ ” said Sherry Trepp, marketing research manager of the office supplies division at 3M. “Every family has a spot in the kitchen where they communicate — we call it the command center. For some it’s horizontal on a counter, for some it’s vertical on a cupboard, and for some it’s vertical on the refrigerator because that’s where the children go right after school.” On its Web site, a “Post-it Everywhere” section suggests uses at home, in school and “on the go.” “It’s still tilted to the office channel and still primarily an office product,” said Mr. Smith of 3M. “But it has migrated out of the office and into many aspects our life.”</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/23/business/23mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Reports a 43% Rise in Profit<date>Published: July 22, 2010</date><text>The 3M Company, which makes a wide variety of industrial and consumer products, said Thursday that its quarterly net income rose 43 percent and raised its full-year outlook.The company, which makes products that range from Post-it stickers to film for flat-screen TVs, said its profit rose to $1.12 billion, or $1.54 a share, from $783 million, or $1.12 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose to $6.73 billion from $5.72 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters expected a profit of $1.48 a share on revenue of $6.66 billion, and stock in 3M, which is based in St. Paul, rose $2.45, to $84.75 a share. The chief executive, George W. Buckley, said 3M began seeing an economic recovery in June 2009, but he cautioned that economic growth could slow later this year if stimulus spending tapered off faster than the economy picked up. “This isn’t a double-dip per se, it’s just a soft spot, and very normal as economic growth takes a breather for a while and adjusts to new circumstances such as higher interest rates, lowering stimulus, or commodity inflation,” he said. “All are very normal in my view.” Most of the revenue growth came in Asia, which was up 42 percent, and Latin America and Canada, which were up 21 percent. Sales in the United States rose 9 percent, and sales in Europe rose 4 percent, held back by the weak euro. Operating profits at the industrial and transportation unit, its biggest division, rose 66 percent to $476 million. The division includes renewable energy, auto parts, and industrial adhesives. The company said operating profit at all of the businesses in that unit improved. The company now expects full year earnings of $5.65 to $5.80 a share. Wall Street was expecting $5.63.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/28/business/28mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Raises Its Profit Forecast After a Strong Quarter<date>Published: April 27, 2010</date><text>The 3M Company, which makes products ranging from Post-it notes to protective films for iPads, raised its outlook for the year on Tuesday after reporting first-quarter earnings rose 80 percent on strong sales in Asia. The company, based in Maplewood, Minn., now expects earnings of $5.40 to $5.60 a share, excluding a charge related to the new health care law. It forecast $4.90 to $5.10 a share previously. 3M is benefiting from a broader global footprint and sales of a myriad of everyday products. The company makes films for LCD TVs and hand-held devices like the iPad; more than 1,000 products for cars, including abrasives and paint finishings; and a number of health care products including inhalers and stethoscopes. 3M earned $930 million, or $1.29 a share, compared with $518 million, or 74 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a one-time charge related to tax changes in the new health care law, first-quarter earnings were $1.40 a share. Revenue rose 25 percent, to $6.35 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters expected a profit of $1.21 a share on revenue of $5.94 billion. Sales growth was strongest in emerging economies. Sales climbed 54.1 percent in the Asia-Pacific region, which includes China. Sales in all six 3M business segments grew by double-digit percentages.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/30/business/30subsidy.html?ref=3mcompany">Companies Push to Repeal Provision of Health Law<date>Published: March 29, 2010</date><text>An association representing 300 large corporations urged President Obama and Congress on Monday to repeal a provision of the health care overhaul that prompted AT&amp;T, Caterpillar and other companies to announce substantial charges for the current quarter.The association, the American Benefits Council, said the provision — which reduces the tax deductions for companies with drug coverage for their retired employees — would deal a significant blow to corporate profits and would discourage companies from hiring more workers. AT&amp;T announced last week that it was taking a $1 billion charge because of the provision. Deere &amp; Company announced a $150 million charge, Caterpillar a $100 million charge, and 3M a $90 million charge. Many companies said they were taking these charges now, before the current quarter ended, to comply with accounting rules. But some corporate critics asserted that the companies’ rapid response to the health legislation was aimed at pressing the administration to repeal the provision. James A. Klein, the president of the American Benefits Council, called the provision “a serious mistake that is having negative and unintended consequences.” White House officials defended the provision, saying it was a deliberate effort to eliminate what they said was an unusually generous tax loophole. They said the overall health care overhaul would save businesses more than $150 billion over the next decade by reducing health care inflation. “We’re confident that the benefits are going to accrue and strengthen business’s bottom line,” said Linda Douglass, the communications director for the White House Health Reform Office. When Congress and President George W. Bush enacted a prescription drug plan for seniors in 2003, the legislation encouraged companies to continue providing prescription coverage to retirees, instead of shifting retirees to Medicare Part D, by having the government give those companies large subsidies for each retiree — and also allowing them to deduct those subsidies from their income taxes. Under the health care overhaul, the federal government will continue providing those subsidies — amounting to 28 percent of a drug plan’s costs — but companies will lose the tax break. In a telephone news conference on Monday, Mr. Klein cited a study by Towers Watson, a consulting firm, saying the loss of the deduction would cost companies $14 billion in future years. “Particularly in this economic environment, it makes no sense to impose this type of a hit on companies’ financial statements,” Mr. Klein said. The provision takes effect in 2013, but accounting rules require companies to take immediate charges equal to the current value of any known hit to future profits. Defending the provision, White House officials said it was rare for companies to obtain a tax-free federal subsidy and be able to deduct it as well. These officials added that the health care legislation contained a $5 billion subsidy for companies that maintain health plans to early retirees. “Let’s put these changes into perspective,” Ms. Douglass said. “While accounting rules required companies to book this cost upfront, there are a whole set of benefits that will accrue to companies over time that they’re not booking upfront.” Federal officials estimate that the provision will raise $4.5 billion to $5 billion in revenue over 10 years, but Mr. Klein maintained that it would cost the government more than it raised. About 6.3 million retirees — an estimated two-thirds of them from the private sector — are covered by employer drug plans. Mr. Klein cited a study by the Moran Company, a health care consulting group, estimating that as a result of the legislation, drug coverage would be altered for 1.5 million to 2 million retirees. Many companies, he said, will stop providing drug coverage to retirees and will instead push them into Medicare Part D, causing the government to pay for their coverage. AT&amp;T said in a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission, “As a result of this legislation, including the additional tax burden, AT&amp;T will be evaluating prospective changes to the active and retiree health care benefits offered by the company.” Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, criticized the charges by the companies, asserting that the health reform would save companies more money than it cost them. Mr. Waxman sent AT&amp;T, Caterpillar and Deere a sharp letter, questioning the charges and saying he wanted top officials from those companies to testify at an April 21 hearing he has scheduled on the issue. Mr. Waxman and Bart Stupak, a Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the House Commerce Committee’s subcommittee on oversight and investigations, wrote to AT&amp;T’s chairman, Randall L. Stephenson, “The new law is designed to expand coverage and bring down costs, so your assertions are a matter of concern.” Their letter said AT&amp;T’s moves “appear to conflict with independent analyses,” including a finding by the Business Roundtable, an association of chief executives, that health care reform would reduce insurance cost trends for businesses by more than $3,000 for each employee over the next 10 years. Responding to such criticism, Mr. Klein said: “These announcements are required under accounting rules, and we should all expect more of such announcements in coming days and weeks. We’re very troubled that these announcements have been challenged by officials in Obama administration and Congress.” Many employer plans for retiree drug coverage are part of union contracts. In December, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.’s legislative director, Bill Samuel, joined Mr. Klein in writing to Senator Harry Reid, the majority leader, urging the Senate not to enact this provision. Gerry Shea, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.’s chief strategist on health care, stopped short of calling for a repeal of the provision. “We’re very concerned about the disruption that could be caused because of this, with people being pushed out of employer plans,” he said. “With all the changes we’re looking at because of the new health legislation, we feel you don’t need this.” Mr. Klein argued that the provision would undercut Mr. Obama’s job creation plans. “If companies are going to take a hit like this on their financial statements that will certainly hurt their ability to borrow in the marketplace and make the type of investments that will retain and create jobs,” he said. But White House officials said the provision would not affect job creation because it does not take effect for three years and any charge for a given year would not be large.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/business/29mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Beats Profit Expectations and Raises Its 2010 Forecast<date>Published: January 28, 2010</date><text>The 3M Company, the diversified manufacturer, posted higher-than-expected quarterly earnings on Thursday and raised its forecast for 2010, citing strong demand for all its products. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Matt Rourke/Associated Press The company reported strong demand for its products. But its shares fell, caught up in a stock market sell-off that was especially hard on industrial companies. 3M, probably best known for its trademark brands like Post-it notes and Scotch tape, reported fourth-quarter net income of $935 million, or $1.30 a share, up from $676 million, or 97 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of $1.21 a share, according to Thomson Reuters. Revenue increased 11 percent, to $6.1 billion, above Wall Street forecasts for $5.77 billion. The company, which makes a variety of products including adhesives, abrasives, stethoscopes and insect repellent, said the results were driven by a 15.7 percent jump in sales of display and graphics products, like the coatings found on high-definition TVs and computer monitors. Strong sales of health care products, including masks used to prevent infections from the H1N1 flu virus and other pathogens, contributed to the results. 3M raised its forecast for 2010 earnings to a range of $4.90 to $5.10 a share, up from $4.85 to $5 a share. Analysts were expecting $4.57, according to Thomson Reuters. Despite the better-than-expected results and the raised forecast, 3M shares fell as weaker-than-expected economic data on durable goods and jobless claims raised fears that the recovery might be faltering. The economic news pulled down the broader market, including shares of other industrials like Caterpillar and Deere. 3M shares, which rose ahead of the results to a two-year high, edged lower as the market fell. The stock fell $1.55, or 1.9 percent, to close at $80.75 on the New York Stock Exchange. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 29, 2010, on page B2 of the New York edition.The 3M Company, the diversified manufacturer, posted higher-than-expected quarterly earnings on Thursday and raised its forecast for 2010, citing strong demand for all its products. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Matt Rourke/Associated Press The company reported strong demand for its products. But its shares fell, caught up in a stock market sell-off that was especially hard on industrial companies. 3M, probably best known for its trademark brands like Post-it notes and Scotch tape, reported fourth-quarter net income of $935 million, or $1.30 a share, up from $676 million, or 97 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of $1.21 a share, according to Thomson Reuters. Revenue increased 11 percent, to $6.1 billion, above Wall Street forecasts for $5.77 billion. The company, which makes a variety of products including adhesives, abrasives, stethoscopes and insect repellent, said the results were driven by a 15.7 percent jump in sales of display and graphics products, like the coatings found on high-definition TVs and computer monitors. Strong sales of health care products, including masks used to prevent infections from the H1N1 flu virus and other pathogens, contributed to the results. 3M raised its forecast for 2010 earnings to a range of $4.90 to $5.10 a share, up from $4.85 to $5 a share. Analysts were expecting $4.57, according to Thomson Reuters. Despite the better-than-expected results and the raised forecast, 3M shares fell as weaker-than-expected economic data on durable goods and jobless claims raised fears that the recovery might be faltering. The economic news pulled down the broader market, including shares of other industrials like Caterpillar and Deere. 3M shares, which rose ahead of the results to a two-year high, edged lower as the market fell. The stock fell $1.55, or 1.9 percent, to close at $80.75 on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/03/opinion/03pubed.html?ref=3mcompany">Times Standards, Staffers or Not<date>Published: January 2, 2010</date><text>Mary Tripsas, an associate professor at the Harvard Business School, has been writing a monthly column in The Times called “Prototype,” about corporate innovation, her academic specialty. Last Sunday, she highlighted the 3M Company’s customer innovation center at its headquarters in St. Paul. Skip to next paragraph Chuck Kennedy/McClatchy-Tribune Clark Hoyt More Public Editor Columns » E-mail: public@nytimes.com Phone: (212) 556-7652 Address: Public Editor The New York Times 620 Eight Avenue. New York, NY 10018 Today, an editor’s note in the paper says that, had The Times known that 3M paid Tripsas’ expenses to Minnesota in November, the column would not have been published as it was written. Tripsas violated a policy against accepting travel or anything else of value from the subjects of coverage. She will no longer be writing for The Times. Last week, The Times parted company with Joshua Robinson, a prolific young freelancer who represented himself as a Times reporter while asking airline magazines for free tickets to cities around the world for an independent project he was proposing with a photographer. And the byline of Mike Albo, another freelancer who was one writer of the “Critical Shopper” column, disappeared from the paper in the fall, after  separate from his work at The Times  he accepted an expenses-paid junket to Jamaica, organized by Thrillist, a consumer e-letter, and sponsored by JetBlue and other corporations. These cases illustrate how hard it is for The Times to ensure that freelancers, who contribute a substantial portion of the paper’s content, abide by ethics guidelines that editors believe are self-evident and essential to the paper’s credibility but that writers sometimes don’t think about, or don’t think apply to their circumstances, or believe are unfair or unrealistic. Some writers do not read the guidelines carefully, and although they are encouraged to raise possible conflicts of interest with an editor, some don’t tell and are not asked. Transgressions are heavily chewed over on the Web, doing no good for the reputation of a paper trying to protect its integrity from even the appearance of improper influence. Tripsas’ problem was uncovered by www.nytpick.com, an anonymous Web site devoted to critiquing The Times, and Albo’s was revealed by Jeff Bercovici, the media columnist for DailyFinance, another online site. Robinson’s case was brought to my attention by someone at an airline who was approached by him and his collaborator. The standard freelance contract states, “You will not accept free transportation, gifts, junkets or commissions/assignments from current or potential news sources.” Before being paid, freelancers must fill out a conflict-of-interest questionnaire. But Philip Corbett, the standards editor, said, “We haven’t done enough,” and he said top editors plan to discuss this week how to get greater compliance with the ethics rules, spelled out in a 54-page booklet that all contributors to The Times, staff and freelance, are expected to read and obey. Despite all the precautions, the cases of Tripsas, Robinson and Albo show how differing views of ethics, a failure to read or remember the fine print and a failure to communicate can lead to embarrassment all around. Tripsas, who accepts speaking fees from companies to share the findings of her academic research and conducts executive education at companies that pay Harvard for her services, now realizes that she was probably ineligible to write for The Times from the start. But the newspaper recruited her for the expertise she gained through her academic work, and she said she did not read the contract carefully or consider its full implications. “I should have,” she said. The trip to 3M was arranged before she began working for The Times in August, she said, and she wasn’t thinking about a column when she flew to St. Paul. Instead, she and other professors were going to learn about 3M’s customer-centered culture. Only after she saw 3M’s innovation center did she propose a column to her editor, Patricia Kranz. Tripsas said, “It should have computed that there might have been, from the journalistic point of view, a conflict.” But from her point of view, she was doing academic research, as she normally did, and there was nothing remarkable about allowing 3M to pick up the $820 bill for air fare and a hotel. The money could just as easily have come from her Harvard research budget, she said. “It wouldn’t have changed what I wrote,” she said. Tripsas made clear in her proposal to Kranz that she had visited 3M, but she didn’t mention who paid for her trip. “It just didn’t even occur to me,” Tripsas told me. Kranz said the fact that a trip was involved never registered with her, let alone the question of who paid for it. “She and I both overlooked a thing we shouldn’t have overlooked,” Kranz said. Robinson, two years out of college and highly regarded by Times editors for whom he has freelanced, said that he never connected his Times work with the approach he made to airline magazines seeking free international travel in exchange for articles and photos. He said he called himself “a reporter for The New York Times”  which he is not  only to establish his “street cred” with those he was soliciting, and not to imply he was on the newspaper staff. “It was an honest mistake,” he told me. “To me, this was so far removed from anything I do for The Times, it didn’t seem applicable.” 1 2 Next Page » The public editor can be reached by e-mail: public@nytimes.com. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on January 3, 2010, on page WK8 of the New York edition.Mary Tripsas, an associate professor at the Harvard Business School, has been writing a monthly column in The Times called “Prototype,” about corporate innovation, her academic specialty. Last Sunday, she highlighted the 3M Company’s customer innovation center at its headquarters in St. Paul. Skip to next paragraph Chuck Kennedy/McClatchy-Tribune Clark Hoyt More Public Editor Columns » E-mail: public@nytimes.com Phone: (212) 556-7652 Address: Public Editor The New York Times 620 Eight Avenue. New York, NY 10018 Today, an editor’s note in the paper says that, had The Times known that 3M paid Tripsas’ expenses to Minnesota in November, the column would not have been published as it was written. Tripsas violated a policy against accepting travel or anything else of value from the subjects of coverage. She will no longer be writing for The Times. Last week, The Times parted company with Joshua Robinson, a prolific young freelancer who represented himself as a Times reporter while asking airline magazines for free tickets to cities around the world for an independent project he was proposing with a photographer. And the byline of Mike Albo, another freelancer who was one writer of the “Critical Shopper” column, disappeared from the paper in the fall, after  separate from his work at The Times  he accepted an expenses-paid junket to Jamaica, organized by Thrillist, a consumer e-letter, and sponsored by JetBlue and other corporations. These cases illustrate how hard it is for The Times to ensure that freelancers, who contribute a substantial portion of the paper’s content, abide by ethics guidelines that editors believe are self-evident and essential to the paper’s credibility but that writers sometimes don’t think about, or don’t think apply to their circumstances, or believe are unfair or unrealistic. Some writers do not read the guidelines carefully, and although they are encouraged to raise possible conflicts of interest with an editor, some don’t tell and are not asked. Transgressions are heavily chewed over on the Web, doing no good for the reputation of a paper trying to protect its integrity from even the appearance of improper influence. Tripsas’ problem was uncovered by www.nytpick.com, an anonymous Web site devoted to critiquing The Times, and Albo’s was revealed by Jeff Bercovici, the media columnist for DailyFinance, another online site. Robinson’s case was brought to my attention by someone at an airline who was approached by him and his collaborator. The standard freelance contract states, “You will not accept free transportation, gifts, junkets or commissions/assignments from current or potential news sources.” Before being paid, freelancers must fill out a conflict-of-interest questionnaire. But Philip Corbett, the standards editor, said, “We haven’t done enough,” and he said top editors plan to discuss this week how to get greater compliance with the ethics rules, spelled out in a 54-page booklet that all contributors to The Times, staff and freelance, are expected to read and obey. Despite all the precautions, the cases of Tripsas, Robinson and Albo show how differing views of ethics, a failure to read or remember the fine print and a failure to communicate can lead to embarrassment all around. Tripsas, who accepts speaking fees from companies to share the findings of her academic research and conducts executive education at companies that pay Harvard for her services, now realizes that she was probably ineligible to write for The Times from the start. But the newspaper recruited her for the expertise she gained through her academic work, and she said she did not read the contract carefully or consider its full implications. “I should have,” she said. The trip to 3M was arranged before she began working for The Times in August, she said, and she wasn’t thinking about a column when she flew to St. Paul. Instead, she and other professors were going to learn about 3M’s customer-centered culture. Only after she saw 3M’s innovation center did she propose a column to her editor, Patricia Kranz. Tripsas said, “It should have computed that there might have been, from the journalistic point of view, a conflict.” But from her point of view, she was doing academic research, as she normally did, and there was nothing remarkable about allowing 3M to pick up the $820 bill for air fare and a hotel. The money could just as easily have come from her Harvard research budget, she said. “It wouldn’t have changed what I wrote,” she said. Tripsas made clear in her proposal to Kranz that she had visited 3M, but she didn’t mention who paid for her trip. “It just didn’t even occur to me,” Tripsas told me. Kranz said the fact that a trip was involved never registered with her, let alone the question of who paid for it. “She and I both overlooked a thing we shouldn’t have overlooked,” Kranz said. Robinson, two years out of college and highly regarded by Times editors for whom he has freelanced, said that he never connected his Times work with the approach he made to airline magazines seeking free international travel in exchange for articles and photos. He said he called himself “a reporter for The New York Times”  which he is not  only to establish his “street cred” with those he was soliciting, and not to imply he was on the newspaper staff. “It was an honest mistake,” he told me. “To me, this was so far removed from anything I do for The Times, it didn’t seem applicable.” 1 2 Next Page » The public editor can be reached by e-mail: public@nytimes.com.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/27/business/27proto.html?ref=3mcompany">Seeing Customers as Partners in Invention<date>Editors' Note: January 3, 2010Published: December 26, 2009</date><text>Editors' Note Appended IMAGINE a planetarium-style presentation about the future of technology, followed by a tour of dozens of hands-on exhibits  whether of sandlike microparticles that flow like liquid in a beaker, pictures that appear three-dimensional or concrete that floats. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image 3M A 3M innovation center is at company headquarters in St. Paul. Add to Portfolio Hershey Co Pitney Bowes Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Visteon and 3M Working with Visteon, 3M used its lighting and film technologies in a concept vehicle Enlarge This Image Jake Wyman Leslie Abi-Karam, an executive vice president at Pitney Bowes, said that working with customers “will alter our development trajectory.” Is it the latest science museum, or a new Disney attraction? No, it’s the “World of Innovation” showroom, a cornerstone of the 3M Company’s customer innovation center at its headquarters in St. Paul. In a world of online user communities, social media, interactive blogs and other technological means for companies to elicit customer feedback, you might think that face-to-face interaction is a thing of the past. Think again. As a company, 3M is at the forefront of a movement that appears to be gaining traction: customer innovation centers, typically located near company research facilities, that provide a forum for meeting with corporate customers and engaging them directly in the innovation process. When many people hear the name 3M, they may think only of canary-colored Post-it notes. But the company is applying wide-ranging technical expertise to a portfolio of products including transportation systems, dental and medical devices and electronics. One of its latest is a pocket-sized LED projector that connects to cellphones, P.D.A.’s and digital cameras. The company opened its first customer innovation center in Sumitomo, Japan, in 1997, followed by others throughout the world, including sites in Brazil, Germany, India, China and Russia. This month, it announced that it would open its 23rd center next year, in Dubai. The idea behind the centers is to foster innovation by combining a richer understanding of customer needs with creative links among 3M technologies. “Being customer-driven doesn’t mean asking customers what they want and then giving it to them,” says Ranjay Gulati, a professor at the Harvard Business School. “It’s about building a deep awareness of how the customer uses your product.” Professor Gulati recently completed a book, “(Re) (Organize) for Resilience,” about how to make customers the center of a business. A typical customer day at a 3M center begins with a team from a visiting company presenting an overview of their business to a group of 3M marketing and technology experts who pepper them with open-ended questions. The goal is to understand “what our customers are trying to accomplish, not what they say they need,” says John Horn, vice president for research and development at 3M’s industrial and transportation business. Next is a visit to the “World of Innovation” showroom. The company has more than 40 of what it calls technology platforms  core technologies in areas like optical films, reflective materials, abrasives and adhesives  that can potentially be combined and applied to meet a range of needs in different markets. By exposing customers to these platforms, 3M hopes to prompt the type of novel connections  like using dental technology to improve car parts  that drive innovative solutions. “We never show completed products,” Dr. Horn says. “Doing that would constrain people’s thinking.” Does it work? Dr. Horn says that “the innovation center experience isn’t just about making everyone feel good.” It has helped 3M to establish productive, long-term customer relationships. For instance, 3M and the Visteon Corporation, an automotive supplier that is one of its customers, have worked together in the development of a next-generation concept vehicle that incorporates 3M technologies not originally developed with automotive applications in mind. Visteon’s visit to the innovation center, combined with follow-up collaboration, led to the idea of using 3-D technology from 3M for navigation displays, Thinsulate materials to reduce noise and optical films to hide functional elements of the dashboard unless the driver wants them displayed. The Hershey Company opened a customer innovation center aimed at retailers in 2006. Like 3M, it has a showroom  in this case, a tasting room  where corporate scientists discuss trends and retailers can sample products under development and offer feedback. Another part of the center is a mock store where Hershey illustrates merchandising ideas. Hershey hopes to make shopping easier by organizing the candy aisle by how the products are used (candy dish, gift-giving or family movie night) instead of by product line. By walking retailers through the sample merchandising set-up, Hershey can better communicate the concept than it could through a slide presentation, says Michele G. Buck, Hershey’s global chief marketing officer. Pitney Bowes, which opened its first customer innovation center this month in Shelton, Conn., uses a different model. The centerpiece is its new IntelliJet color printing system, which expands on the company’s strength in mail applications by allowing customers to integrate them with print operations. Customers are encouraged to load their own applications onto the system and to experiment. “We’re hoping to get at things they wouldn’t have thought about,” says Leslie Abi-Karam, an executive vice president who heads the mailing solutions management division of Pitney Bowes. “In the long run, we expect that working with customers in our innovation center will alter our development trajectory.” The terms “customer driven” and “solutions” seem to be in every manager’s lexicon. But as Professor Gulati notes, “it’s an execution problem.” Companies, he says, “aren’t generally structured to access, absorb or utilize customer insights since they are organized by product, not by customer.” By focusing on the customer, innovation centers may be a way to turn good managerial intentions into concrete, valuable products. Mary Tripsas is an associate professor in the entrepreneurial management unit at the Harvard Business School. Editors' Note: January 3, 2010 The Prototype column last Sunday, about customer innovation centers, reported on a program at the 3M Company’s headquarters in St. Paul and described the company as being “at the forefront of a movement” in which corporations meet face to face with customers to elicit feedback. After the column was published, The Times learned that 3M had provided travel and accommodations for the freelance writer during a visit to the company’s headquarters in November. Times policy prohibits reporters from accepting such expenses or other payment from companies they cover. Had the editors known of the circumstances of the trip, the column would not have been published in that form. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on December 27, 2009, on page BU3 of the New York edition.Editors' Note Appended IMAGINE a planetarium-style presentation about the future of technology, followed by a tour of dozens of hands-on exhibits  whether of sandlike microparticles that flow like liquid in a beaker, pictures that appear three-dimensional or concrete that floats. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image 3M A 3M innovation center is at company headquarters in St. Paul. Add to Portfolio Hershey Co Pitney Bowes Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Visteon and 3M Working with Visteon, 3M used its lighting and film technologies in a concept vehicle Enlarge This Image Jake Wyman Leslie Abi-Karam, an executive vice president at Pitney Bowes, said that working with customers “will alter our development trajectory.” Is it the latest science museum, or a new Disney attraction? No, it’s the “World of Innovation” showroom, a cornerstone of the 3M Company’s customer innovation center at its headquarters in St. Paul. In a world of online user communities, social media, interactive blogs and other technological means for companies to elicit customer feedback, you might think that face-to-face interaction is a thing of the past. Think again. As a company, 3M is at the forefront of a movement that appears to be gaining traction: customer innovation centers, typically located near company research facilities, that provide a forum for meeting with corporate customers and engaging them directly in the innovation process. When many people hear the name 3M, they may think only of canary-colored Post-it notes. But the company is applying wide-ranging technical expertise to a portfolio of products including transportation systems, dental and medical devices and electronics. One of its latest is a pocket-sized LED projector that connects to cellphones, P.D.A.’s and digital cameras. The company opened its first customer innovation center in Sumitomo, Japan, in 1997, followed by others throughout the world, including sites in Brazil, Germany, India, China and Russia. This month, it announced that it would open its 23rd center next year, in Dubai. The idea behind the centers is to foster innovation by combining a richer understanding of customer needs with creative links among 3M technologies. “Being customer-driven doesn’t mean asking customers what they want and then giving it to them,” says Ranjay Gulati, a professor at the Harvard Business School. “It’s about building a deep awareness of how the customer uses your product.” Professor Gulati recently completed a book, “(Re) (Organize) for Resilience,” about how to make customers the center of a business. A typical customer day at a 3M center begins with a team from a visiting company presenting an overview of their business to a group of 3M marketing and technology experts who pepper them with open-ended questions. The goal is to understand “what our customers are trying to accomplish, not what they say they need,” says John Horn, vice president for research and development at 3M’s industrial and transportation business. Next is a visit to the “World of Innovation” showroom. The company has more than 40 of what it calls technology platforms  core technologies in areas like optical films, reflective materials, abrasives and adhesives  that can potentially be combined and applied to meet a range of needs in different markets. By exposing customers to these platforms, 3M hopes to prompt the type of novel connections  like using dental technology to improve car parts  that drive innovative solutions. “We never show completed products,” Dr. Horn says. “Doing that would constrain people’s thinking.” Does it work? Dr. Horn says that “the innovation center experience isn’t just about making everyone feel good.” It has helped 3M to establish productive, long-term customer relationships. For instance, 3M and the Visteon Corporation, an automotive supplier that is one of its customers, have worked together in the development of a next-generation concept vehicle that incorporates 3M technologies not originally developed with automotive applications in mind. Visteon’s visit to the innovation center, combined with follow-up collaboration, led to the idea of using 3-D technology from 3M for navigation displays, Thinsulate materials to reduce noise and optical films to hide functional elements of the dashboard unless the driver wants them displayed. The Hershey Company opened a customer innovation center aimed at retailers in 2006. Like 3M, it has a showroom  in this case, a tasting room  where corporate scientists discuss trends and retailers can sample products under development and offer feedback. Another part of the center is a mock store where Hershey illustrates merchandising ideas. Hershey hopes to make shopping easier by organizing the candy aisle by how the products are used (candy dish, gift-giving or family movie night) instead of by product line. By walking retailers through the sample merchandising set-up, Hershey can better communicate the concept than it could through a slide presentation, says Michele G. Buck, Hershey’s global chief marketing officer. Pitney Bowes, which opened its first customer innovation center this month in Shelton, Conn., uses a different model. The centerpiece is its new IntelliJet color printing system, which expands on the company’s strength in mail applications by allowing customers to integrate them with print operations. Customers are encouraged to load their own applications onto the system and to experiment. “We’re hoping to get at things they wouldn’t have thought about,” says Leslie Abi-Karam, an executive vice president who heads the mailing solutions management division of Pitney Bowes. “In the long run, we expect that working with customers in our innovation center will alter our development trajectory.” The terms “customer driven” and “solutions” seem to be in every manager’s lexicon. But as Professor Gulati notes, “it’s an execution problem.” Companies, he says, “aren’t generally structured to access, absorb or utilize customer insights since they are organized by product, not by customer.” By focusing on the customer, innovation centers may be a way to turn good managerial intentions into concrete, valuable products. Mary Tripsas is an associate professor in the entrepreneurial management unit at the Harvard Business School. Editors' Note: January 3, 2010 The Prototype column last Sunday, about customer innovation centers, reported on a program at the 3M Company’s headquarters in St. Paul and described the company as being “at the forefront of a movement” in which corporations meet face to face with customers to elicit feedback. After the column was published, The Times learned that 3M had provided travel and accommodations for the freelance writer during a visit to the company’s headquarters in November. Times policy prohibits reporters from accepting such expenses or other payment from companies they cover. Had the editors known of the circumstances of the trip, the column would not have been published in that form.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/26/business/worldbusiness/26anger.html?ref=3mcompany">Hurt by Economy, Europeans Vent Their Anger<date>Published: March 25, 2009</date><text>LONDON  Tempers are flaring across Europe as the economic pain deepens and more people lose their jobs. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis — The Essentials Enlarge This Image Danny Lawson/Press Association, via Associated Press On Wednesday, the suburban Edinburgh home of RBSs ex-chief was damaged. Enlarge This Image Michel Euler/Associated Press Workers in France held a 3M executive. Just ask Fred Goodwin, the former chief executive of the ailing Royal Bank of Scotland, whose house and car were vandalized early Wednesday. Or Luc Rousselet, the manager of a 3M factory in France, who was barricaded in an office for a second day by workers demanding better severance packages for 110 employees who are being laid off. While such instances are scattered so far, the angry mood threatens to overshadow the Group of 20 summit meeting next week in London, where world leaders hope to find approaches to the financial crisis. Several protests are planned in London’s financial district, and the police are warning financial institutions to bolster security, cancel unnecessary meetings and keep employees inside. Bankers are being advised to wear “casual clothing” so they do not attract attention. “A recession has all sorts of knock-on effects,” said Christopher Husbands, a professor of sociology at the London School of Economics. “Crimes go up, relationships break down and there are instances of civil disturbance.” A nationwide strike in France last week, which drew at least 1.2 million people, was peaceful. But the government remains worried about an outbreak of violence similar to that last month in Guadeloupe, a French overseas territory, and in Greece in December. The sense of frustration among those who lost their jobs or savings or a large part of their pension funds is fueled by reports of executives continuing to reap large rewards, as demonstrated by the outrage in the United States over bonuses paid at the American International Group. Europeans have long pointed out that pay packages of top executives in the United States are simply out of whack with the rest of the world, but their hopes of avoiding a public outcry were doused by the latest reports of inflamed local passions. In Scotland, vandals smashed at least three windows on the ground floor of Mr. Goodwin’s house in an affluent suburb of Edinburgh and damaged a black Mercedes S600 parked in the driveway. Mr. Goodwin was not in the house at the time and no one was hurt, but the incident alarmed Britain’s business community. A spokesman for Prime Minister Gordon Brown, who is in the United States, said “there could be no excuse for people breaking the law.” Mr. Goodwin attracted criticism for keeping his pension, worth £703,000 a year, or $1.03 million, despite a string of ill-timed acquisitions on his watch that led to the bank’s being brought under government control. He rejected calls to surrender the payment, and the government is considering legal options. It was the first such attack on a property owned by a banking executive since the financial crisis started, but some neighbors told local newspapers they were surprised it did not happen earlier. The author of an e-mail message sent anonymously to a local newspaper on Wednesday claimed responsibility for the damage and said: “We are angry that rich people, like him, are paying themselves a huge amount of money and living in luxury while ordinary people are made unemployed, destitute and homeless.” Though Mr. Goodwin resigned in October, the bank continues to pay £290 a month for security at his house. Because of the bank’s losses, Mr. Goodwin, once hailed as a skilled deal maker who turned a small bank into a global financial services operation, became the target of public scorn and a symbol of the decline of Britain’s banks. “People are looking for someone to blame as they feel the crisis on a day-to-day basis and experience feelings of injustice and anger as they ask themselves, ‘What have I done to contribute to this?’ ” said Sheri Jacobson, a psychotherapist who is clinical director of Harley Therapy in London. “For those who are the target of the scorn it’s extremely difficult, because for a long time they were the champions and they worked hard, and they also look at the situation, saying, ‘My intentions were good.’ ” Some executives have already decided to forgo their bonuses, but companies continue to hand out hefty payoffs for executives of failed companies, setting off public outcries. In contrast to politicians in the United States, those in Europe have stopped short of proposing taxes to claw back large executive bonuses, but even the leader of the employers’ federation in France denounced the severance package proposed for the chief executive of Valeo, an auto parts maker. In a speech this week, President Nicolas Sarkozy of France called on everyone to return to their “values.” He criticized both the irresponsible business sector as well as those who chose “intimidation” and “threaten the security of property and people.” He got another whiff of the public mood Wednesday, when employees from a French plant owned by the German tire maker Continental marched through Paris and burned tires near Élysée Palace to protest the planned closing of a factory in the Oise region with 1,120 employees. Striking workers at a French plant of 3M went even further, taking their boss hostage Tuesday. Such actions are rare but not unheard of in France; earlier this month, a similar situation at a Sony factory ended peacefully after one night. A few dozen workers at the 3M plant in Pithiviers took turns standing guard Wednesday outside factory offices, The Associated Press reported. The workers did not threaten any violence and the atmosphere was calm. Workers said they would bring Mr. Rousselet mussels and French fries for dinner, The A.P. said. “We recognize that there are social worries given the current situation,” Christine Lagarde, the French economy minister, told a small group of journalists. “But France has strong assets to deal with it, particularly our social safety nets.” Mark Malloch Brown, a British Foreign Office minister, told the BBC this month that he expected protesters to win more sympathy from the general public than usual. “You know, frankly, there’s enough anger out there amongst all of us who are watching what’s happening on bankers’ salaries and bonuses,” he said. “Hard-liners are going to have a sympathy they haven’t had for quite a while.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on March 26, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.LONDON  Tempers are flaring across Europe as the economic pain deepens and more people lose their jobs. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis — The Essentials Enlarge This Image Danny Lawson/Press Association, via Associated Press On Wednesday, the suburban Edinburgh home of RBSs ex-chief was damaged. Enlarge This Image Michel Euler/Associated Press Workers in France held a 3M executive. Just ask Fred Goodwin, the former chief executive of the ailing Royal Bank of Scotland, whose house and car were vandalized early Wednesday. Or Luc Rousselet, the manager of a 3M factory in France, who was barricaded in an office for a second day by workers demanding better severance packages for 110 employees who are being laid off. While such instances are scattered so far, the angry mood threatens to overshadow the Group of 20 summit meeting next week in London, where world leaders hope to find approaches to the financial crisis. Several protests are planned in London’s financial district, and the police are warning financial institutions to bolster security, cancel unnecessary meetings and keep employees inside. Bankers are being advised to wear “casual clothing” so they do not attract attention. “A recession has all sorts of knock-on effects,” said Christopher Husbands, a professor of sociology at the London School of Economics. “Crimes go up, relationships break down and there are instances of civil disturbance.” A nationwide strike in France last week, which drew at least 1.2 million people, was peaceful. But the government remains worried about an outbreak of violence similar to that last month in Guadeloupe, a French overseas territory, and in Greece in December. The sense of frustration among those who lost their jobs or savings or a large part of their pension funds is fueled by reports of executives continuing to reap large rewards, as demonstrated by the outrage in the United States over bonuses paid at the American International Group. Europeans have long pointed out that pay packages of top executives in the United States are simply out of whack with the rest of the world, but their hopes of avoiding a public outcry were doused by the latest reports of inflamed local passions. In Scotland, vandals smashed at least three windows on the ground floor of Mr. Goodwin’s house in an affluent suburb of Edinburgh and damaged a black Mercedes S600 parked in the driveway. Mr. Goodwin was not in the house at the time and no one was hurt, but the incident alarmed Britain’s business community. A spokesman for Prime Minister Gordon Brown, who is in the United States, said “there could be no excuse for people breaking the law.” Mr. Goodwin attracted criticism for keeping his pension, worth £703,000 a year, or $1.03 million, despite a string of ill-timed acquisitions on his watch that led to the bank’s being brought under government control. He rejected calls to surrender the payment, and the government is considering legal options. It was the first such attack on a property owned by a banking executive since the financial crisis started, but some neighbors told local newspapers they were surprised it did not happen earlier. The author of an e-mail message sent anonymously to a local newspaper on Wednesday claimed responsibility for the damage and said: “We are angry that rich people, like him, are paying themselves a huge amount of money and living in luxury while ordinary people are made unemployed, destitute and homeless.” Though Mr. Goodwin resigned in October, the bank continues to pay £290 a month for security at his house. Because of the bank’s losses, Mr. Goodwin, once hailed as a skilled deal maker who turned a small bank into a global financial services operation, became the target of public scorn and a symbol of the decline of Britain’s banks. “People are looking for someone to blame as they feel the crisis on a day-to-day basis and experience feelings of injustice and anger as they ask themselves, ‘What have I done to contribute to this?’ ” said Sheri Jacobson, a psychotherapist who is clinical director of Harley Therapy in London. “For those who are the target of the scorn it’s extremely difficult, because for a long time they were the champions and they worked hard, and they also look at the situation, saying, ‘My intentions were good.’ ” Some executives have already decided to forgo their bonuses, but companies continue to hand out hefty payoffs for executives of failed companies, setting off public outcries. In contrast to politicians in the United States, those in Europe have stopped short of proposing taxes to claw back large executive bonuses, but even the leader of the employers’ federation in France denounced the severance package proposed for the chief executive of Valeo, an auto parts maker. In a speech this week, President Nicolas Sarkozy of France called on everyone to return to their “values.” He criticized both the irresponsible business sector as well as those who chose “intimidation” and “threaten the security of property and people.” He got another whiff of the public mood Wednesday, when employees from a French plant owned by the German tire maker Continental marched through Paris and burned tires near Élysée Palace to protest the planned closing of a factory in the Oise region with 1,120 employees. Striking workers at a French plant of 3M went even further, taking their boss hostage Tuesday. Such actions are rare but not unheard of in France; earlier this month, a similar situation at a Sony factory ended peacefully after one night. A few dozen workers at the 3M plant in Pithiviers took turns standing guard Wednesday outside factory offices, The Associated Press reported. The workers did not threaten any violence and the atmosphere was calm. Workers said they would bring Mr. Rousselet mussels and French fries for dinner, The A.P. said. “We recognize that there are social worries given the current situation,” Christine Lagarde, the French economy minister, told a small group of journalists. “But France has strong assets to deal with it, particularly our social safety nets.” Mark Malloch Brown, a British Foreign Office minister, told the BBC this month that he expected protesters to win more sympathy from the general public than usual. “You know, frankly, there’s enough anger out there amongst all of us who are watching what’s happening on bankers’ salaries and bonuses,” he said. “Hard-liners are going to have a sympathy they haven’t had for quite a while.”</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/22/business/22mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">Earnings at 3M Improve by 3.2%<date>Published: October 21, 2008</date><text>The 3M Company reported a 3.2 percent increase in quarterly earnings, sending shares higher as the results contrasted with generally negative earnings sentiment in the markets Tuesday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio 3M Company Go to your Portfolio » 3M’s broad lineup of businesses  from high-tech industrial products like chemicals used in aircraft maintenance to consumer goods like Post-it notes  makes it a bellwether of the economy. With domestic demand slowing, 3M has been relying on foreign markets for growth. 3M, based in St. Paul, posted third-quarter net income of $991 million, or $1.41 a share, compared with $960 million, or $1.32 a share, in the period a year earlier. Excluding special items, 3M reported earnings of $1.42 a share, which topped analysts’ estimates of $1.38 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Revenue rose 6.2 percent, to $6.56 billion, from $6.18 billion a year earlier, short of analysts’ estimates of $6.67 billion. 3M lowered its outlook slightly, forecasting 2008 earnings of $5.40 to $5.48 a share, an 8 to 10 percent increase, instead of the minimum 10 percent increase it had previously predicted. Analysts expect 2008 earnings of $5.45 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. The company is cutting costs and eliminating more than 1,000 jobs in the United States, Europe and Asia. Shares of 3M closed at $60.04, up $2.53, or 4.4 percent. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 22, 2008, on page B3 of the New York edition.The 3M Company reported a 3.2 percent increase in quarterly earnings, sending shares higher as the results contrasted with generally negative earnings sentiment in the markets Tuesday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio 3M Company Go to your Portfolio » 3M’s broad lineup of businesses  from high-tech industrial products like chemicals used in aircraft maintenance to consumer goods like Post-it notes  makes it a bellwether of the economy. With domestic demand slowing, 3M has been relying on foreign markets for growth. 3M, based in St. Paul, posted third-quarter net income of $991 million, or $1.41 a share, compared with $960 million, or $1.32 a share, in the period a year earlier. Excluding special items, 3M reported earnings of $1.42 a share, which topped analysts’ estimates of $1.38 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Revenue rose 6.2 percent, to $6.56 billion, from $6.18 billion a year earlier, short of analysts’ estimates of $6.67 billion. 3M lowered its outlook slightly, forecasting 2008 earnings of $5.40 to $5.48 a share, an 8 to 10 percent increase, instead of the minimum 10 percent increase it had previously predicted. Analysts expect 2008 earnings of $5.45 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. The company is cutting costs and eliminating more than 1,000 jobs in the United States, Europe and Asia. Shares of 3M closed at $60.04, up $2.53, or 4.4 percent.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/25/business/25mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">Weak Dollar Helps 3M, but Maybe Too Much<date>Published: April 25, 2008</date><text>The diversified manufacturer 3M reported better-than-expected quarterly profit on Thursday, but its shares fell on investor concern that the weak dollar accounted for too much of the company’s growth. 3M, whose products include cellphone circuits and Post-it notes, said foreign currency conversion accounted for 6.1 percentage points of its 8.9 percent rise in quarterly sales. Also, the company backed away from a previous goal of 5 to 8 percent volume growth this year excluding the effect of the weak dollar. It said the goal was unrealistic in “today’s economic world.” Investors scrutinize results from big manufacturers like 3M, which makes products for both industry and consumers, to gain insight into the health of the American economy. The company’s first-quarter net income was $988 million, or $1.38 a share, beating analysts’ average forecast of $1.35 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Foreign currency translation accounted for 7 cents a share. Sales totaled $6.5 billion, topping analysts’ average forecast of $6.32 billion. But organic growth disappointed, falling domestically and coming in weaker than expected internationally, said a Morningstar analyst, Adam Fleck. Shares of 3M fell $1.50, to $79.13, on the New York Stock Exchange. More Articles in Business »The diversified manufacturer 3M reported better-than-expected quarterly profit on Thursday, but its shares fell on investor concern that the weak dollar accounted for too much of the company’s growth. 3M, whose products include cellphone circuits and Post-it notes, said foreign currency conversion accounted for 6.1 percentage points of its 8.9 percent rise in quarterly sales. Also, the company backed away from a previous goal of 5 to 8 percent volume growth this year excluding the effect of the weak dollar. It said the goal was unrealistic in “today’s economic world.” Investors scrutinize results from big manufacturers like 3M, which makes products for both industry and consumers, to gain insight into the health of the American economy. The company’s first-quarter net income was $988 million, or $1.38 a share, beating analysts’ average forecast of $1.35 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Foreign currency translation accounted for 7 cents a share. Sales totaled $6.5 billion, topping analysts’ average forecast of $6.32 billion. But organic growth disappointed, falling domestically and coming in weaker than expected internationally, said a Morningstar analyst, Adam Fleck. Shares of 3M fell $1.50, to $79.13, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/22/business/22nocera.html?ref=3mcompany">Emerald City of Giving Does Exist<date>Published: December 22, 2007</date><text>Correction Appended My philanthropic tour of Minneapolis began on the banks of the Mississippi River, where the Great Northern Railroad once transported flour from the giant mills of General Mills and Pillsbury. The Great Northern is long gone  merged into the Burlington Northern almost 40 years ago, and though the mills are still standing, they have long since been converted to other uses, as General Mills moved to the suburbs, and, in time, acquired its rival Pillsbury. Bill King, the head of the Minnesota Council on Foundations  and my tour guide  pointed out the mills as we got into our car. As well he should have. One lasting legacy of the Great Northern is the Northwest Area Foundation, which was founded by James J. Hill, the Great Northern’s founder. As of March 2007, it had $500 million in assets and is devoted primarily to antipoverty efforts. Indeed, Minneapolis and St. Paul have an abundance of foundations that were started by the founders or top executives of many of its biggest companies, like 3M and Target. General Mills, meanwhile, was an early member of an organization begun in the mid-1970s called the Five Percent Club  in which Minneapolis-St. Paul corporations agreed to set aside 5 percent of their pretax income for philanthropy. Believe it or not  and it is a little hard to believe, given the modern emphasis on maximizing profits and pleasing Wall Street  the club still exists. Now known as the Keystone Club, it has 214 members, and 134 of them donate at the 5 percent level. (The others give away 2 percent of their profits.) Last year, General Mills donated more than $57 million, second only to Target, which gave away nearly $160 million. “Here’s the new Guthrie,” said Mr. King as we began the tour. The Guthrie Theater, the city’s fine regional theater, recently moved into a sparkling new building by the river  one of five major arts organizations that have recently built new buildings or major additions. All of them were built, in no small part, with corporate contributions. We drove a little farther. “This is where the bridge collapsed,” he said, pointing directly in front of us. He was speaking, of course, of the Interstate 35W bridge, which collapsed in August. “When it fell, there was an immediate response from corporations,” Mr. King continued. “And a fund for victims was set up by the Minneapolis and St. Paul Foundations.” The latter groups solicit donations from local people who want to be involved in philanthropy but lack the means to set up their own foundations. Combined, the two foundations have over $1.5 billion in assets and are major forces in the Twin Cities. We headed north. “North Minneapolis has long been a low-income neighborhood,” Mr. King said. “We have had wonderful success over all as a community, but we still have lots of problems. But we keep working at it.” We drove past a storefront that said, in bright lettering, “The Cookie Cart.” “This is a cookie business that is run by kids in the community,” Mr. King said. “It helps them learn skills that can really be useful. It has been around for 10 or 15 years.” Among the companies backing it are Wells Fargo, U.S. Bancorp and The Star Tribune. As we neared a school, Mr. King told me about a Medtronics-funded program that began years ago as a $75,000 pilot program to help children get interested in science. The company now spends more than a $1 million a year on it. And on, and on. We drove under a walking bridge, the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, built with donations from the Whitney family and others. In a neighborhood called Hawthorne, Mr. King explained that in 1996, after The New York Times noted that some people were calling Minneapolis “Murderapolis,” General Mills began investing in the neighborhood, with redevelopment and other efforts, including something called the Hawthorne Huddle, a monthly meeting that brought together residents and city officials to hash out solutions to problems. Ask anybody in the world of corporate philanthropy and they’ll tell you: Minneapolis-St. Paul is like no place else, a bastion of giving in an age when most companies are cutting back. “It is an unusual city in regards to corporate giving,” said former Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich. In the 1970s, John D. Rockefeller III said in a speech to the Minneapolis Chamber of Commerce that he had heard so much about “the public spirit of its business community, about your remarkable Five Percent Club that I feel a bit like Dorothy in the Land of Oz. I had to come to the Emerald City myself to see if it really exists.” So did I. And sure enough, it does exist. But why here? If you put this question to people in Minneapolis, you hear all kinds of theories. “When you live in such a harsh climate, you understand the need for the common good,” said Emmett D. Carson, the former president of the Minneapolis Foundation. Others suggested that the area’s corporate generosity grew out of the Scandinavian culture that took hold in this region, with its deep Lutheran roots. Christina L. Shea, the senior vice president for external relations at General Mills, thought it had to do with enlightened self-interest. “How do you attract high-powered talent?” she asked. A large part of the answer, she believed, had to do with building communities in which talented people wanted to live. Steve Rothschild, a former General Mills executive who left the company to found an antipoverty group called Twin Cities Rise, said he thought that Minneapolis-St. Paul companies have long viewed their responsibilities broadly. “Most Twin Cities companies have a stakeholder model, not a shareholder model,” he said. There is probably some truth to all of these theories. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: December 28, 2007 The Talking Business column in Business Day on Saturday, about corporate philanthropy in Minneapolis-St. Paul, misstated the names of two organizations involved in charitable work in the area. They are the Minnesota Council on Foundations, not the Minneapolis Council on Foundations, and Twin Cities Rise, not Twin Cities Rising. The column also referred incorrectly to financing of a pedestrian bridge over an interstate highway. The bridge  the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, which crosses I-94 to connect the Walker Art Center to the city’s park system  was built with donations from the Whitney family and others. Dayton-Hudson, a predecessor to the Target Corporation, did not build the bridge. More Articles in Business »Correction Appended My philanthropic tour of Minneapolis began on the banks of the Mississippi River, where the Great Northern Railroad once transported flour from the giant mills of General Mills and Pillsbury. The Great Northern is long gone  merged into the Burlington Northern almost 40 years ago, and though the mills are still standing, they have long since been converted to other uses, as General Mills moved to the suburbs, and, in time, acquired its rival Pillsbury. Bill King, the head of the Minnesota Council on Foundations  and my tour guide  pointed out the mills as we got into our car. As well he should have. One lasting legacy of the Great Northern is the Northwest Area Foundation, which was founded by James J. Hill, the Great Northern’s founder. As of March 2007, it had $500 million in assets and is devoted primarily to antipoverty efforts. Indeed, Minneapolis and St. Paul have an abundance of foundations that were started by the founders or top executives of many of its biggest companies, like 3M and Target. General Mills, meanwhile, was an early member of an organization begun in the mid-1970s called the Five Percent Club  in which Minneapolis-St. Paul corporations agreed to set aside 5 percent of their pretax income for philanthropy. Believe it or not  and it is a little hard to believe, given the modern emphasis on maximizing profits and pleasing Wall Street  the club still exists. Now known as the Keystone Club, it has 214 members, and 134 of them donate at the 5 percent level. (The others give away 2 percent of their profits.) Last year, General Mills donated more than $57 million, second only to Target, which gave away nearly $160 million. “Here’s the new Guthrie,” said Mr. King as we began the tour. The Guthrie Theater, the city’s fine regional theater, recently moved into a sparkling new building by the river  one of five major arts organizations that have recently built new buildings or major additions. All of them were built, in no small part, with corporate contributions. We drove a little farther. “This is where the bridge collapsed,” he said, pointing directly in front of us. He was speaking, of course, of the Interstate 35W bridge, which collapsed in August. “When it fell, there was an immediate response from corporations,” Mr. King continued. “And a fund for victims was set up by the Minneapolis and St. Paul Foundations.” The latter groups solicit donations from local people who want to be involved in philanthropy but lack the means to set up their own foundations. Combined, the two foundations have over $1.5 billion in assets and are major forces in the Twin Cities. We headed north. “North Minneapolis has long been a low-income neighborhood,” Mr. King said. “We have had wonderful success over all as a community, but we still have lots of problems. But we keep working at it.” We drove past a storefront that said, in bright lettering, “The Cookie Cart.” “This is a cookie business that is run by kids in the community,” Mr. King said. “It helps them learn skills that can really be useful. It has been around for 10 or 15 years.” Among the companies backing it are Wells Fargo, U.S. Bancorp and The Star Tribune. As we neared a school, Mr. King told me about a Medtronics-funded program that began years ago as a $75,000 pilot program to help children get interested in science. The company now spends more than a $1 million a year on it. And on, and on. We drove under a walking bridge, the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, built with donations from the Whitney family and others. In a neighborhood called Hawthorne, Mr. King explained that in 1996, after The New York Times noted that some people were calling Minneapolis “Murderapolis,” General Mills began investing in the neighborhood, with redevelopment and other efforts, including something called the Hawthorne Huddle, a monthly meeting that brought together residents and city officials to hash out solutions to problems. Ask anybody in the world of corporate philanthropy and they’ll tell you: Minneapolis-St. Paul is like no place else, a bastion of giving in an age when most companies are cutting back. “It is an unusual city in regards to corporate giving,” said former Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich. In the 1970s, John D. Rockefeller III said in a speech to the Minneapolis Chamber of Commerce that he had heard so much about “the public spirit of its business community, about your remarkable Five Percent Club that I feel a bit like Dorothy in the Land of Oz. I had to come to the Emerald City myself to see if it really exists.” So did I. And sure enough, it does exist. But why here? If you put this question to people in Minneapolis, you hear all kinds of theories. “When you live in such a harsh climate, you understand the need for the common good,” said Emmett D. Carson, the former president of the Minneapolis Foundation. Others suggested that the area’s corporate generosity grew out of the Scandinavian culture that took hold in this region, with its deep Lutheran roots. Christina L. Shea, the senior vice president for external relations at General Mills, thought it had to do with enlightened self-interest. “How do you attract high-powered talent?” she asked. A large part of the answer, she believed, had to do with building communities in which talented people wanted to live. Steve Rothschild, a former General Mills executive who left the company to found an antipoverty group called Twin Cities Rise, said he thought that Minneapolis-St. Paul companies have long viewed their responsibilities broadly. “Most Twin Cities companies have a stakeholder model, not a shareholder model,” he said. There is probably some truth to all of these theories. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: December 28, 2007 The Talking Business column in Business Day on Saturday, about corporate philanthropy in Minneapolis-St. Paul, misstated the names of two organizations involved in charitable work in the area. They are the Minnesota Council on Foundations, not the Minneapolis Council on Foundations, and Twin Cities Rise, not Twin Cities Rising. The column also referred incorrectly to financing of a pedestrian bridge over an interstate highway. The bridge  the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, which crosses I-94 to connect the Walker Art Center to the city’s park system  was built with donations from the Whitney family and others. Dayton-Hudson, a predecessor to the Target Corporation, did not build the bridge.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/13/business/13mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Expecting Strong 2008, Aided by Big Gains Abroad<date>Published: December 13, 2007</date><text>The 3M Company said on Wednesday that it expected double-digit sales and earnings growth in 2008 and forecast profit slightly above the average Wall Street estimate. The company expects its growth to come from international markets and the weaker dollar. It forecast moderately softer world economic growth next year, with the United States continuing to be slow but still growing. The second half of the year is likely to be stronger than the first, and the company forecast strong and sustainable growth in developing economies like Brazil, Russia, India and China. It also expects no relief in the residential housing market in the United States. Shares of 3M rose $2.01, to $86.66. 3M expects 2008 earnings of $5.44 to $5.47 a share. Analysts’ average estimate is $5.42, according to Reuters Estimates. The company said it expected sales from existing businesses to grow 5 percent to 8 percent next year, while acquisitions would contribute about 3 percent to revenue growth. It said current exchange rates suggest the weak dollar would add up to 3 percent to sales growth. Almost two-thirds of its sales next year will be generated overseas, said the chief executive, George W. Buckley. That exposure is the highest in the industrial group, an analyst at JPMorgan, Stephen Tusa, said in a research note. “The forecast is stronger than expected,” Mr. Tusa wrote. “The upside relative to our expectations comes from both top line and margin.” More Articles in Business »The 3M Company said on Wednesday that it expected double-digit sales and earnings growth in 2008 and forecast profit slightly above the average Wall Street estimate. The company expects its growth to come from international markets and the weaker dollar. It forecast moderately softer world economic growth next year, with the United States continuing to be slow but still growing. The second half of the year is likely to be stronger than the first, and the company forecast strong and sustainable growth in developing economies like Brazil, Russia, India and China. It also expects no relief in the residential housing market in the United States. Shares of 3M rose $2.01, to $86.66. 3M expects 2008 earnings of $5.44 to $5.47 a share. Analysts’ average estimate is $5.42, according to Reuters Estimates. The company said it expected sales from existing businesses to grow 5 percent to 8 percent next year, while acquisitions would contribute about 3 percent to revenue growth. It said current exchange rates suggest the weak dollar would add up to 3 percent to sales growth. Almost two-thirds of its sales next year will be generated overseas, said the chief executive, George W. Buckley. That exposure is the highest in the industrial group, an analyst at JPMorgan, Stephen Tusa, said in a research note. “The forecast is stronger than expected,” Mr. Tusa wrote. “The upside relative to our expectations comes from both top line and margin.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/27/business/27mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M’s Second-Quarter Profit Rises 3.9%<date>Published: July 27, 2007</date><text>MINNEAPOLIS, July 26 (AP)  The 3M Company, the manufacturer of products including Scotch tape and coatings for flat-panel televisions, said Thursday that its second-quarter profit rose 3.9 percent on strong performance across its businesses. The company said it earned $917 million, or $1.25 a share, up from $882 million, or $1.15 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose to $6.14 billion, up 7.9 percent from $5.69 billion a year earlier. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial were expecting earnings of $1.18 a share on sales of $6.05 billion. 3M raised its forecast for the full year and said it now expects to earn $5.40 to $5.60 a share, up from its prior estimate of $5.20 to $5.45. Growth has been helped by a string of small acquisitions. In the last quarter alone it bought two electrical suppliers and acquired most of the assets of a Chilean manufacturer of disposable surgical drapes and gowns. It also bought Diamond Productions, which makes tools for cutting and shaping stone and glass, and said it would buy a passport-reader manufacturer, Rochford Thompson Equipment. The chief executive, George W. Buckley, said he expected the pace of acquisitions to continue this year. 3Ms industrial and transportation division brought in $359 million in operating profit, up from $320 million a year ago. Display and graphics, which includes 3Ms business of making optical films for liquid crystal display screens, had operating profit of $352 million, up from $237 million a year ago. Its health care division earned $279 million, up from $261 million last year. Shares of 3M rose 43 cents, to $90.05. More Articles in Business »MINNEAPOLIS, July 26 (AP)  The 3M Company, the manufacturer of products including Scotch tape and coatings for flat-panel televisions, said Thursday that its second-quarter profit rose 3.9 percent on strong performance across its businesses. The company said it earned $917 million, or $1.25 a share, up from $882 million, or $1.15 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose to $6.14 billion, up 7.9 percent from $5.69 billion a year earlier. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial were expecting earnings of $1.18 a share on sales of $6.05 billion. 3M raised its forecast for the full year and said it now expects to earn $5.40 to $5.60 a share, up from its prior estimate of $5.20 to $5.45. Growth has been helped by a string of small acquisitions. In the last quarter alone it bought two electrical suppliers and acquired most of the assets of a Chilean manufacturer of disposable surgical drapes and gowns. It also bought Diamond Productions, which makes tools for cutting and shaping stone and glass, and said it would buy a passport-reader manufacturer, Rochford Thompson Equipment. The chief executive, George W. Buckley, said he expected the pace of acquisitions to continue this year. 3Ms industrial and transportation division brought in $359 million in operating profit, up from $320 million a year ago. Display and graphics, which includes 3Ms business of making optical films for liquid crystal display screens, had operating profit of $352 million, up from $237 million a year ago. Its health care division earned $279 million, up from $261 million last year. Shares of 3M rose 43 cents, to $90.05.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/28/garden/28post-it.html?ref=3mcompany">While You Were Out, the Post-it Went Home<date>Published: June 28, 2007</date><text>THE romance between Shirley M. Knappe, 83, and Frank Sterling Long, 88, began electronically, with poetic early-morning e-mail messages from Mr. Long to Ms. Knappe, who live in an assisted-living facility in Coral Springs, Fla. But now that they have been married for three years, their day-to-day affairs are tracked on Post-it notes, which Ms. Knappe corrals onto the kitchen cabinets above the toaster oven: her activities in yellow, his in blue. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Michael Brands for The New York Times Note to Self Rhonda Britten, a life coach, suggests that her clients leave Post-it notes with intentions for themselves around the house. I thought I was going to be knitting and reading when I came here seven years ago, Ms. Knappe said. But when Frank came along after my husband died, we decided to join forces. It was a real love story. We have so much fun together. I developed the system to keep all our activities straight. Ms. Knappe was speaking last Thursday as she and her husband were on their way to a wine tasting, which was marked on a blue Post-it (group activities are in blue, Mr. Longs color, because my memory is better than his, she said). Their ID numbers for the Wheel Watchers Club, the Wheel of Fortune shows lottery, are on Post-its, along with everyones cellphone numbers and my odds and ends, like the name of Franks daughters cat, Millard, said Ms. Knappe, who had paused to consult the note in question. The couple is working on a mystery novel set in an assisted-living facility. Post-it notes may be a plot device, Ms. Knappe suggested. In 1980, when the 3M company introduced the Post-it, no one could have foreseen the effect the 3-by-5-inch Valium-colored rectangle would have on domestic life. Its beginnings were folkloric: 40 years ago, Spencer Silver, a scientist at 3M, discovered the imperfect adhesive that would adorn the Post-it; it took another six years for Art Fry, another 3M scientist, to find the application for this half glue, which came in a flash of inspiration after the bookmarks for his church hymnal kept falling out. And for years Post-its were marketed primarily for this purpose  as tools for capturing a thought or for marking a spot on a document, among other typically office-bound tasks  even as they were steadily migrating out of the office and into peoples homes (and garages), onto vertical surfaces like cabinets, refrigerators, dashboards, mirrors, walls, toilet seat lids, bathroom scales and the edges of pet food bowls. The notes migratory tendencies are why 3M scientists developed Post-it Super Sticky notes in 2003, with a stronger glue that hangs on tighter to those nubby, homey, largely vertical surfaces. (Artists and pranksters have used the colored ones like mosaic tiles  an online search for Post-it Elvis will provide one impish example  as have decorators like Jonathan Fong, who made a randomly patterned Post-it wall for a family room in California and photographed the result for his book Walls That Wow: Creative Wall Treatments Without Fancy-Schmancy Painting.) Post-its crept into the Museum of Modern Art in 2004, beckoned there by Paola Antonelli, curator of architecture and design, who named the Post-it one of her Humble Masterpieces in a show and, later, in a book of the same name, inducting them, along with the white T-shirt and the rubber band, into the design hall of fame. Hypertext on a refrigerator door, Ms. Antonelli wrote, the Post-it shook the world. The 3M company would not say what percentage of its annual profits came from Post-it notes or what kind of growth the brand has enjoyed. But according to the NPD Group, a research firm that tracks retail trends, the category known as self-stick notes, which is dominated by Post-it notes, accounted for $106 million in sales at office superstores like Staples between June 2006 and May 2007, a 13.5 percent increase from the year before. And next month the company will sail further into the not yet fully charted, topographically fraught home environment with its first official home collection, the Samba line of hot Latin colors and patterns, the better to accessorize the conversation you may be having, via Post-it notes, with your memory, your loved ones or your inner vixen. (Post-its are big with life coaches as a vehicle for affirmations.) 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Home &amp; Garden »THE romance between Shirley M. Knappe, 83, and Frank Sterling Long, 88, began electronically, with poetic early-morning e-mail messages from Mr. Long to Ms. Knappe, who live in an assisted-living facility in Coral Springs, Fla. But now that they have been married for three years, their day-to-day affairs are tracked on Post-it notes, which Ms. Knappe corrals onto the kitchen cabinets above the toaster oven: her activities in yellow, his in blue. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Michael Brands for The New York Times Note to Self Rhonda Britten, a life coach, suggests that her clients leave Post-it notes with intentions for themselves around the house. I thought I was going to be knitting and reading when I came here seven years ago, Ms. Knappe said. But when Frank came along after my husband died, we decided to join forces. It was a real love story. We have so much fun together. I developed the system to keep all our activities straight. Ms. Knappe was speaking last Thursday as she and her husband were on their way to a wine tasting, which was marked on a blue Post-it (group activities are in blue, Mr. Longs color, because my memory is better than his, she said). Their ID numbers for the Wheel Watchers Club, the Wheel of Fortune shows lottery, are on Post-its, along with everyones cellphone numbers and my odds and ends, like the name of Franks daughters cat, Millard, said Ms. Knappe, who had paused to consult the note in question. The couple is working on a mystery novel set in an assisted-living facility. Post-it notes may be a plot device, Ms. Knappe suggested. In 1980, when the 3M company introduced the Post-it, no one could have foreseen the effect the 3-by-5-inch Valium-colored rectangle would have on domestic life. Its beginnings were folkloric: 40 years ago, Spencer Silver, a scientist at 3M, discovered the imperfect adhesive that would adorn the Post-it; it took another six years for Art Fry, another 3M scientist, to find the application for this half glue, which came in a flash of inspiration after the bookmarks for his church hymnal kept falling out. And for years Post-its were marketed primarily for this purpose  as tools for capturing a thought or for marking a spot on a document, among other typically office-bound tasks  even as they were steadily migrating out of the office and into peoples homes (and garages), onto vertical surfaces like cabinets, refrigerators, dashboards, mirrors, walls, toilet seat lids, bathroom scales and the edges of pet food bowls. The notes migratory tendencies are why 3M scientists developed Post-it Super Sticky notes in 2003, with a stronger glue that hangs on tighter to those nubby, homey, largely vertical surfaces. (Artists and pranksters have used the colored ones like mosaic tiles  an online search for Post-it Elvis will provide one impish example  as have decorators like Jonathan Fong, who made a randomly patterned Post-it wall for a family room in California and photographed the result for his book Walls That Wow: Creative Wall Treatments Without Fancy-Schmancy Painting.) Post-its crept into the Museum of Modern Art in 2004, beckoned there by Paola Antonelli, curator of architecture and design, who named the Post-it one of her Humble Masterpieces in a show and, later, in a book of the same name, inducting them, along with the white T-shirt and the rubber band, into the design hall of fame. Hypertext on a refrigerator door, Ms. Antonelli wrote, the Post-it shook the world. The 3M company would not say what percentage of its annual profits came from Post-it notes or what kind of growth the brand has enjoyed. But according to the NPD Group, a research firm that tracks retail trends, the category known as self-stick notes, which is dominated by Post-it notes, accounted for $106 million in sales at office superstores like Staples between June 2006 and May 2007, a 13.5 percent increase from the year before. And next month the company will sail further into the not yet fully charted, topographically fraught home environment with its first official home collection, the Samba line of hot Latin colors and patterns, the better to accessorize the conversation you may be having, via Post-it notes, with your memory, your loved ones or your inner vixen. (Post-its are big with life coaches as a vehicle for affirmations.) 1 2 Next Page »</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/27stox.html?ref=3mcompany">Shares End Mixed Despite Strong Results<date>Published: April 27, 2007</date><text>Stocks ended mixed yesterday as strong profit reports from companies like Apple Inc. and 3M failed to galvanize Wall Street. Still, a modest advance gave the Dow Jones industrial average another record close, a day after it crossed 13,000. Better-than-expected profit news, which helped vault the Dow into record territory Wednesday, continued, but with less effect than in the previous session. Apple said its fiscal second-quarter profit rose 88 percent amid robust sales of iPods and Macintosh computers. Reports from 3M, a Dow component, and Ford Motor also pleased investors. Once you go through what people consider a milestone, you are often going to have a little rest, said Ron Kiddoo, chief investment officer at Cozad Asset Management. Earnings are lending support to the market. Obviously, there are some disappointments, but theyre much above what people were expecting. The Dow settled up 15.61 points, to 13,105.50, after hitting a fresh trading high of 13,132.80. It was the Dows 18th rise in the last 20 sessions and its 36th record close since the start of October. Broader indexes ended mixed. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index, which has in recent sessions crept closer to its record high of 1,527.46, reached in March 2000, slipped 1.17 points, to 1,494.25. The Nasdaq composite index rose 6.57 points, to 2,554.46. The economic calendar is busier next week, and the question on investors minds is whether forthcoming data will prove the markets recent rally was justified or overdone. So far, 22 of the 30 Dow components have reported earnings, with 16 of those reports topping expectations. Exxon Mobil released better-than-expected earnings yesterday, and its shares rose 63 cents, to $80.55. Microsofts fiscal third-quarter results, which the company announced after the closing bell yesterday, also came in ahead of expectations. Microsoft finished up 11 cents, at $29.10, and rose in after-hours electronic trading. In other corporate news, Apples profit report beat analysts estimates, and the stock at times surpassed $100 a share. Apple closed up $3.49, at $98.84. The 3M Company, whose products include Scotch tape and coatings for flat-panel televisions, reported a stronger profit than Wall Street predicted, sending the stock up $3.48, to $80.45. Ford reported a narrower-than-expected loss for the first quarter; its stock rose 32 cents, to $8.20. Wendys International, which said late Wednesday that it was considering a possible sale of the company, rose $5.31, to $37.99. Covansys, a provider of information technology services, rose $6.49, to $33.29, after it agreed to be acquired by Computer Sciences for $1.3 billion. Computer Sciences slipped 14 cents, to $55.83. Harman International Industries, which makes audio equipment, agreed to be taken private in an $8 billion deal. The company, which also said its fiscal third-quarter profit rose 11 percent, jumped $19.94, to $122.50. The Labor Department said yesterday that applications for jobless benefits fell last week by 20,000, the biggest decrease in nearly two months. Federal Reserve banks in Chicago and Kansas City, Mo., said manufacturing activity rose in their respective regions. Today will bring more weighty data, particularly the Commerce Departments initial estimate of first-quarter gross domestic product. Light sweet crude settled down 78 cents, at $65.06 a barrel, on the New York Mercantile Exchange. The price of the benchmark 10-year Treasury note fell 11/32, to 99 14/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction of the price, rose to 4.70 percent, from 4.65 percent. Following are the results of yesterdays auction of five-year Treasury notes: More Articles in Business »Stocks ended mixed yesterday as strong profit reports from companies like Apple Inc. and 3M failed to galvanize Wall Street. Still, a modest advance gave the Dow Jones industrial average another record close, a day after it crossed 13,000. Better-than-expected profit news, which helped vault the Dow into record territory Wednesday, continued, but with less effect than in the previous session. Apple said its fiscal second-quarter profit rose 88 percent amid robust sales of iPods and Macintosh computers. Reports from 3M, a Dow component, and Ford Motor also pleased investors. Once you go through what people consider a milestone, you are often going to have a little rest, said Ron Kiddoo, chief investment officer at Cozad Asset Management. Earnings are lending support to the market. Obviously, there are some disappointments, but theyre much above what people were expecting. The Dow settled up 15.61 points, to 13,105.50, after hitting a fresh trading high of 13,132.80. It was the Dows 18th rise in the last 20 sessions and its 36th record close since the start of October. Broader indexes ended mixed. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index, which has in recent sessions crept closer to its record high of 1,527.46, reached in March 2000, slipped 1.17 points, to 1,494.25. The Nasdaq composite index rose 6.57 points, to 2,554.46. The economic calendar is busier next week, and the question on investors minds is whether forthcoming data will prove the markets recent rally was justified or overdone. So far, 22 of the 30 Dow components have reported earnings, with 16 of those reports topping expectations. Exxon Mobil released better-than-expected earnings yesterday, and its shares rose 63 cents, to $80.55. Microsofts fiscal third-quarter results, which the company announced after the closing bell yesterday, also came in ahead of expectations. Microsoft finished up 11 cents, at $29.10, and rose in after-hours electronic trading. In other corporate news, Apples profit report beat analysts estimates, and the stock at times surpassed $100 a share. Apple closed up $3.49, at $98.84. The 3M Company, whose products include Scotch tape and coatings for flat-panel televisions, reported a stronger profit than Wall Street predicted, sending the stock up $3.48, to $80.45. Ford reported a narrower-than-expected loss for the first quarter; its stock rose 32 cents, to $8.20. Wendys International, which said late Wednesday that it was considering a possible sale of the company, rose $5.31, to $37.99. Covansys, a provider of information technology services, rose $6.49, to $33.29, after it agreed to be acquired by Computer Sciences for $1.3 billion. Computer Sciences slipped 14 cents, to $55.83. Harman International Industries, which makes audio equipment, agreed to be taken private in an $8 billion deal. The company, which also said its fiscal third-quarter profit rose 11 percent, jumped $19.94, to $122.50. The Labor Department said yesterday that applications for jobless benefits fell last week by 20,000, the biggest decrease in nearly two months. Federal Reserve banks in Chicago and Kansas City, Mo., said manufacturing activity rose in their respective regions. Today will bring more weighty data, particularly the Commerce Departments initial estimate of first-quarter gross domestic product. Light sweet crude settled down 78 cents, at $65.06 a barrel, on the New York Mercantile Exchange. The price of the benchmark 10-year Treasury note fell 11/32, to 99 14/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction of the price, rose to 4.70 percent, from 4.65 percent. Following are the results of yesterdays auction of five-year Treasury notes:</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/31/business/31mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Earnings Are Weaker Than Expected<date>Published: January 31, 2007</date><text>The diversified manufacturer 3M posted a weaker-than-expected quarterly profit yesterday and said global economic growth was slowing, setting off a 5.1 percent decline in its share price. The company, which makes products like Scotch tape, Post-it notes, Thinsulate insulation and other items, also forecast a 2007 profit that was below expectations. 3Ms chief executive, George Buckley, cited slightly moderating economic growth worldwide. He said 3Ms earnings growth would be slow in the first quarter, pick up in the second quarter and accelerate in the second half of the year. 3M executives cited the sluggish housing market in the United States as causing lower demand for products ranging from its optical films used in liquid-crystal-display televisions to roofing granules used in shingles for houses. The slowdown in roofing granules alone cost the company 5 cents a share in earnings over the second half of the year, Mr. Buckley said. 3Ms net income in the fourth quarter rose 58 percent, to $1.2 billion, or $1.57 a share, from $746 million, or 97 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a $354 million gain, largely from the sale of its drug business, it earned $1.10 a share, 4 cents below analysts expectations. Sales rose 8.6 percent from last year, to $5.78 billion, slightly above Wall Streets expectations. 3M, based in St. Paul, expects 2007 earnings of $5.20 to $5.45 a share, including a net gain for a reorganization of 60 to 70 cents a share. Excluding one-time items, it expects a profit of $4.60 to $4.75 a share. 3M shares fell $4.02, to $74.94 a share. More Articles in Business »The diversified manufacturer 3M posted a weaker-than-expected quarterly profit yesterday and said global economic growth was slowing, setting off a 5.1 percent decline in its share price. The company, which makes products like Scotch tape, Post-it notes, Thinsulate insulation and other items, also forecast a 2007 profit that was below expectations. 3Ms chief executive, George Buckley, cited slightly moderating economic growth worldwide. He said 3Ms earnings growth would be slow in the first quarter, pick up in the second quarter and accelerate in the second half of the year. 3M executives cited the sluggish housing market in the United States as causing lower demand for products ranging from its optical films used in liquid-crystal-display televisions to roofing granules used in shingles for houses. The slowdown in roofing granules alone cost the company 5 cents a share in earnings over the second half of the year, Mr. Buckley said. 3Ms net income in the fourth quarter rose 58 percent, to $1.2 billion, or $1.57 a share, from $746 million, or 97 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a $354 million gain, largely from the sale of its drug business, it earned $1.10 a share, 4 cents below analysts expectations. Sales rose 8.6 percent from last year, to $5.78 billion, slightly above Wall Streets expectations. 3M, based in St. Paul, expects 2007 earnings of $5.20 to $5.45 a share, including a net gain for a reorganization of 60 to 70 cents a share. Excluding one-time items, it expects a profit of $4.60 to $4.75 a share. 3M shares fell $4.02, to $74.94 a share.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/10/business/10drug.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Sell Drug Business for $2 Billion in 3 Deals<date>Published: November 10, 2006</date><text>MINNEAPOLIS, Nov. 9 (AP)  The 3M Company, the diversified manufacturer of products ranging from Post-it notes to weather-stripping, said Thursday that it was selling its branded drug business for nearly $2.1 billion in three separate deals. The company said the deals followed a review of strategic options for its drug-making units worldwide. It said it expected the sale to close in the fourth quarter. Graceway Pharmaceuticals Inc. of Bristol, Tenn., will buy 3Ms pharmaceutical operations in the United States, Canada and Latin America for $875 million. The Swedish drug maker Meda is buying the European pharmaceutical unit for $857 million, and an investment group led by Ironbridge Capital and Archer Capital has agreed to acquire its drug operations in the Asia Pacific region, Australia and South Africa for $349 million. The businesses include the skin cancer treatment Aldara as well as the drugs Minitran, Difflam, Duromine and Tambocor. The 3M Company, which is based in St. Paul, announced in April that it would try to sell the pharmaceutical unit, believing it would be worth more to a dedicated pharmaceutical company with the sales force to make it grow. The company said then that pharmaceuticals were about 20 percent of its health care division, where sales grew 4.7 percent in the first nine months of this year, slower than any other 3M unit. The division employs about 1,050 employees worldwide, including about 330 in the European division, according to Meda. About 70 percent of those employees will be given a chance to stay with the acquiring companies, 3M estimated. Meda said the acquisition of 3Ms European unit would strengthen its product portfolio and add about $280 million in annual sales, pushing it toward its goal of becoming the leading specialty pharmaceutical company in Europe. Archer Capitals director, Ben Frewin, said the company looked at several pharmaceutical companies over the last few years and bought 3Ms unit because of its diverse, high-growth products, strong market positions and growing geographic reach. More Articles in Business »MINNEAPOLIS, Nov. 9 (AP)  The 3M Company, the diversified manufacturer of products ranging from Post-it notes to weather-stripping, said Thursday that it was selling its branded drug business for nearly $2.1 billion in three separate deals. The company said the deals followed a review of strategic options for its drug-making units worldwide. It said it expected the sale to close in the fourth quarter. Graceway Pharmaceuticals Inc. of Bristol, Tenn., will buy 3Ms pharmaceutical operations in the United States, Canada and Latin America for $875 million. The Swedish drug maker Meda is buying the European pharmaceutical unit for $857 million, and an investment group led by Ironbridge Capital and Archer Capital has agreed to acquire its drug operations in the Asia Pacific region, Australia and South Africa for $349 million. The businesses include the skin cancer treatment Aldara as well as the drugs Minitran, Difflam, Duromine and Tambocor. The 3M Company, which is based in St. Paul, announced in April that it would try to sell the pharmaceutical unit, believing it would be worth more to a dedicated pharmaceutical company with the sales force to make it grow. The company said then that pharmaceuticals were about 20 percent of its health care division, where sales grew 4.7 percent in the first nine months of this year, slower than any other 3M unit. The division employs about 1,050 employees worldwide, including about 330 in the European division, according to Meda. About 70 percent of those employees will be given a chance to stay with the acquiring companies, 3M estimated. Meda said the acquisition of 3Ms European unit would strengthen its product portfolio and add about $280 million in annual sales, pushing it toward its goal of becoming the leading specialty pharmaceutical company in Europe. Archer Capitals director, Ben Frewin, said the company looked at several pharmaceutical companies over the last few years and bought 3Ms unit because of its diverse, high-growth products, strong market positions and growing geographic reach.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/16/business/16mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Will Expand Buyback<date>Published: August 16, 2006</date><text>The 3M Company, the maker of products ranging from Post-it Notes to electronic road signs, said yesterday that it planned to buy back an additional $1 billion of its stock. A previous $2 billion buyback will be completed ahead of schedule, so its board authorized the new repurchase plan, the company said. The repurchased shares will be used to support the companys stock-based employee compensation plans and for other corporate purposes, 3M said. The new buyback runs through Feb. 28, 2007. Stock in 3M, which is based in St. Paul, rose $1.16, to $69.78 a share. More Articles in Business »The 3M Company, the maker of products ranging from Post-it Notes to electronic road signs, said yesterday that it planned to buy back an additional $1 billion of its stock. A previous $2 billion buyback will be completed ahead of schedule, so its board authorized the new repurchase plan, the company said. The repurchased shares will be used to support the companys stock-based employee compensation plans and for other corporate purposes, 3M said. The new buyback runs through Feb. 28, 2007. Stock in 3M, which is based in St. Paul, rose $1.16, to $69.78 a share.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/26/business/26stox.html?ref=3mcompany">Late Surge in Technology Saves the Day<date>Published: July 26, 2006</date><text>Shares rose yesterday as a last-minute surge in technology shares offset a disappointing outlook from United Parcel Service and weaker-than-expected results from 3M. Traders said that with 90 minutes left before the close, investors started buying tech shares, which they saw as undervalued after a series of disappointing earnings from companies including Dell. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 52.66 points, or 0.48 percent, to end at 11,103.71. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index gained 7.97 points, or 0.63 percent, to finish at 1,268.88. The Nasdaq composite index climbed 12.06 points, or 0.58 percent, to close at 2,073.90. Another catalyst for the late rally came from AT&amp;T, which reported a quarterly profit that exceeded analysts forecasts. Its shares jumped 4.2 percent and led the gainers in both the Dow and the S.&amp; P. 500. AT&amp;T also raised its forecast for the full year. AT&amp;T shares rose $1.17, to $28.95 on the New York Stock Exchange. On the Nasdaq, shares of SanDisk, a maker of flash memory products, soared 14.7 percent, to $46.11, a day after it reported stronger-than-expected earnings. The stock was also upgraded by Robert W. Baird &amp; Company. Shares of Texas Instruments, the biggest maker of chips for cellphones, rose 4 percent, or $1.11, to $28.95, a day after the company posted higher quarterly earnings. An index of semiconductor stocks rose 1.1 percent. Adding to the late afternoon rally was a drop of 1.7 percent in crude oil futures prices. The September crude contract fell $1.30, to settle at $73.75, on the view that the fighting between Israels army and Hezbollah in Lebanon would not spread to other countries in the region. Economic data added to the more favorable view for stocks. The Conference Board said its index of consumer confidence rose unexpectedly in July from June. A separate report showed that existing-home sales slowed last month, but less than economists had forecast. Earlier in the day, Scott Davis, the chief financial officer for U.P.S., said there were a lot of signs the economy is moderating. The company posted weaker-than-expected profit and warned that its third-quarter results would miss expectations. Shares of U.P.S. fell 10.3 percent, or $8.20, at $71.80, climbing off a session low of $67.25. U.P.S. was the heaviest weight on the S.&amp; P. 500. 3M, the diversified manufacturer, gave investors a reason for caution when its quarterly profit missed Wall Streets forecasts. 3Ms chief executive, George Buckley, said he saw signs of uncertainty creeping into the economy. Shares of 3M fell 5 percent, or $3.58, to $68.11 and topped the decliners in the Dow. The Dow Jones transportation average, which includes U.P.S., fell 1.8 percent, to 4,488.29, after earlier falling as low as 4,391.48. Transportation stocks are especially sensitive to fluctuations in oil prices. Treasury security prices fell yesterday as data on consumer confidence and existing-home sales surpassed Wall Street forecasts. The price of the benchmark 10-year note fell 5/32, to 10015/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 5.06 percent, from 5.04 percent on Monday. Here are the results of yesterdays auction of four-week Treasury bills and of inflation-protected securities: More Articles in Business »Shares rose yesterday as a last-minute surge in technology shares offset a disappointing outlook from United Parcel Service and weaker-than-expected results from 3M. Traders said that with 90 minutes left before the close, investors started buying tech shares, which they saw as undervalued after a series of disappointing earnings from companies including Dell. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 52.66 points, or 0.48 percent, to end at 11,103.71. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index gained 7.97 points, or 0.63 percent, to finish at 1,268.88. The Nasdaq composite index climbed 12.06 points, or 0.58 percent, to close at 2,073.90. Another catalyst for the late rally came from AT&amp;T, which reported a quarterly profit that exceeded analysts forecasts. Its shares jumped 4.2 percent and led the gainers in both the Dow and the S.&amp; P. 500. AT&amp;T also raised its forecast for the full year. AT&amp;T shares rose $1.17, to $28.95 on the New York Stock Exchange. On the Nasdaq, shares of SanDisk, a maker of flash memory products, soared 14.7 percent, to $46.11, a day after it reported stronger-than-expected earnings. The stock was also upgraded by Robert W. Baird &amp; Company. Shares of Texas Instruments, the biggest maker of chips for cellphones, rose 4 percent, or $1.11, to $28.95, a day after the company posted higher quarterly earnings. An index of semiconductor stocks rose 1.1 percent. Adding to the late afternoon rally was a drop of 1.7 percent in crude oil futures prices. The September crude contract fell $1.30, to settle at $73.75, on the view that the fighting between Israels army and Hezbollah in Lebanon would not spread to other countries in the region. Economic data added to the more favorable view for stocks. The Conference Board said its index of consumer confidence rose unexpectedly in July from June. A separate report showed that existing-home sales slowed last month, but less than economists had forecast. Earlier in the day, Scott Davis, the chief financial officer for U.P.S., said there were a lot of signs the economy is moderating. The company posted weaker-than-expected profit and warned that its third-quarter results would miss expectations. Shares of U.P.S. fell 10.3 percent, or $8.20, at $71.80, climbing off a session low of $67.25. U.P.S. was the heaviest weight on the S.&amp; P. 500. 3M, the diversified manufacturer, gave investors a reason for caution when its quarterly profit missed Wall Streets forecasts. 3Ms chief executive, George Buckley, said he saw signs of uncertainty creeping into the economy. Shares of 3M fell 5 percent, or $3.58, to $68.11 and topped the decliners in the Dow. The Dow Jones transportation average, which includes U.P.S., fell 1.8 percent, to 4,488.29, after earlier falling as low as 4,391.48. Transportation stocks are especially sensitive to fluctuations in oil prices. Treasury security prices fell yesterday as data on consumer confidence and existing-home sales surpassed Wall Street forecasts. The price of the benchmark 10-year note fell 5/32, to 10015/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 5.06 percent, from 5.04 percent on Monday. Here are the results of yesterdays auction of four-week Treasury bills and of inflation-protected securities:</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/22/business/22mmm.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Earnings Increase 17%; Strong Results Companywide<date>Published: April 22, 2006</date><text>MINNEAPOLIS, April 21 (AP)  The 3M Company, the maker of Scotch tape, skin cream and furnace filters, said on Friday that its first-quarter earnings jumped 17 percent on strong growth across its businesses. It also gave a bullish forecast and raised earnings guidance for the year. Shares rose $2.57, to $85.17, a new high for the year. 3M earned $899 million, or $1.17 a share, up from $771 million, or 97 cents a share, during the period a year ago. Revenue of almost $5.6 billion was up 8 percent from $5.17 billion. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial expected earnings of $1.14 a share on revenue of $5.58 billion. Both the analysts' estimate and 3M's results include 2 cents a share for stock-based compensation in the latest quarter. 3M predicted second-quarter earnings in the range of $1.14 to $1.17 a share, including 8 cents for stock options. Analysts on average had been expecting $1.15 a share. For the full year, 3M predicted it would earn $4.55 to $4.65 a share. Analysts were expecting $4.61. An analyst with Deutsche Bank North America, David Begleiter, said investors had been looking for organic sales growth, meaning growth from existing businesses instead of acquisitions. "This quarter was really very strong evidence that the focus on growth is gaining traction," Mr. Begleiter said. The chief financial officer, Patrick D. Campbell, said raw-material prices for 3M rose about 4 percent compared with the quarter last year. 3M did not raise its own prices to compensate, but Mr. Campbell said cost controls in other areas kept the increases from hurting profits. The company, based in Maplewood, Minn., is well known for its Post-it notes and also makes branded drug products related to dermatology, women's health, cardiology and respiratory medicine. But the pharmaceutical business requires more high-risk long-term investments than 3M's other businesses, and the company said earlier this month that it would look to sell it. Analysts have speculated it could fetch about $3.5 billion. More Articles in Business »MINNEAPOLIS, April 21 (AP)  The 3M Company, the maker of Scotch tape, skin cream and furnace filters, said on Friday that its first-quarter earnings jumped 17 percent on strong growth across its businesses. It also gave a bullish forecast and raised earnings guidance for the year. Shares rose $2.57, to $85.17, a new high for the year. 3M earned $899 million, or $1.17 a share, up from $771 million, or 97 cents a share, during the period a year ago. Revenue of almost $5.6 billion was up 8 percent from $5.17 billion. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial expected earnings of $1.14 a share on revenue of $5.58 billion. Both the analysts' estimate and 3M's results include 2 cents a share for stock-based compensation in the latest quarter. 3M predicted second-quarter earnings in the range of $1.14 to $1.17 a share, including 8 cents for stock options. Analysts on average had been expecting $1.15 a share. For the full year, 3M predicted it would earn $4.55 to $4.65 a share. Analysts were expecting $4.61. An analyst with Deutsche Bank North America, David Begleiter, said investors had been looking for organic sales growth, meaning growth from existing businesses instead of acquisitions. "This quarter was really very strong evidence that the focus on growth is gaining traction," Mr. Begleiter said. The chief financial officer, Patrick D. Campbell, said raw-material prices for 3M rose about 4 percent compared with the quarter last year. 3M did not raise its own prices to compensate, but Mr. Campbell said cost controls in other areas kept the increases from hurting profits. The company, based in Maplewood, Minn., is well known for its Post-it notes and also makes branded drug products related to dermatology, women's health, cardiology and respiratory medicine. But the pharmaceutical business requires more high-risk long-term investments than 3M's other businesses, and the company said earlier this month that it would look to sell it. Analysts have speculated it could fetch about $3.5 billion.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/03/national/03bush.html?ref=3mcompany">Make Industries' Tax Breaks Permanent, President Urges<date>Published: February 3, 2006</date><text>MAPLEWOOD, Minn., Feb. 2  President Bush went Thursday to a center of American innovation, the 3M Company, which invented Scotch Tape and Post-it notes, to call for permanent tax breaks for industries that invest in research and development and to improve Republican chances in a pivotal state in a midterm election year. Mr. Bush also renewed his promise from the State of the Union address to reduce oil imports from the Mideast, even as the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries objected and after Energy Secretary Samuel W. Bodman said Mr. Bush's words should not be taken literally. In a conference call with reporters on Wednesday, Mr. Bodman said the goal of replacing 75 percent of Middle East oil imports to the United States with ethanol and other energy sources by 2025, a headline from the State of the Union address, was "purely an example" of what might be done. On Thursday, Mr. Bush went even further in calling for independence from Middle East oil in a speech on scientific innovation and research. "I'm confident that we'll be able to say to the American people when this research is complete that the United States is on our way to no dependence on oil from the Middle East," Mr. Bush said to applause from several hundred employees and Republican supporters at 3M headquarters here. Mr. Bush's trip to this St. Paul suburb was part of his annual post-State of the Union travels to try to pound home the major themes of the address in the big news media markets and competitive political races. This year, Republicans have their sights on Minnesota, where there is an open Senate seat and Gov. Tim Pawlenty, a Republican, faces a tough challenge from Democrats. Mr. Bush will spend much of this year on similar trips as he tries to help his party hang on to its slim majority in Congress. Mr. Pawlenty was in the audience at 3M, and Mr. Bush singled him out by telling the crowd that the governor had offered him lutefisk, a smelly local Scandinavian specialty. Mr. Bush said he had told Mr. Pawlenty, "No, I think I'll eat on Air Force One." The theme of the speech was the "American Competitiveness Initiative," a White House slogan for proposals in the State of the Union address to try to improve the teaching of mathematics and science, train workers, aid universities and increase federal support for research and development. The initiative, aimed at quelling voters' fears that America is losing an edge to economic powerhouses like China and India, would cost $5.9 billion next year and $136 billion over 10 years. Of the 10-year cost, the White House has said $86 billion would help make permanent the tax breaks for industries when they invest in research and development. The breaks expired Dec. 31. More Articles in National &gt;MAPLEWOOD, Minn., Feb. 2  President Bush went Thursday to a center of American innovation, the 3M Company, which invented Scotch Tape and Post-it notes, to call for permanent tax breaks for industries that invest in research and development and to improve Republican chances in a pivotal state in a midterm election year. Mr. Bush also renewed his promise from the State of the Union address to reduce oil imports from the Mideast, even as the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries objected and after Energy Secretary Samuel W. Bodman said Mr. Bush's words should not be taken literally. In a conference call with reporters on Wednesday, Mr. Bodman said the goal of replacing 75 percent of Middle East oil imports to the United States with ethanol and other energy sources by 2025, a headline from the State of the Union address, was "purely an example" of what might be done. On Thursday, Mr. Bush went even further in calling for independence from Middle East oil in a speech on scientific innovation and research. "I'm confident that we'll be able to say to the American people when this research is complete that the United States is on our way to no dependence on oil from the Middle East," Mr. Bush said to applause from several hundred employees and Republican supporters at 3M headquarters here. Mr. Bush's trip to this St. Paul suburb was part of his annual post-State of the Union travels to try to pound home the major themes of the address in the big news media markets and competitive political races. This year, Republicans have their sights on Minnesota, where there is an open Senate seat and Gov. Tim Pawlenty, a Republican, faces a tough challenge from Democrats. Mr. Bush will spend much of this year on similar trips as he tries to help his party hang on to its slim majority in Congress. Mr. Pawlenty was in the audience at 3M, and Mr. Bush singled him out by telling the crowd that the governor had offered him lutefisk, a smelly local Scandinavian specialty. Mr. Bush said he had told Mr. Pawlenty, "No, I think I'll eat on Air Force One." The theme of the speech was the "American Competitiveness Initiative," a White House slogan for proposals in the State of the Union address to try to improve the teaching of mathematics and science, train workers, aid universities and increase federal support for research and development. The initiative, aimed at quelling voters' fears that America is losing an edge to economic powerhouses like China and India, would cost $5.9 billion next year and $136 billion over 10 years. Of the 10-year cost, the White House has said $86 billion would help make permanent the tax breaks for industries when they invest in research and development. The breaks expired Dec. 31.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/28/business/28heltzer.html?ref=3mcompany">Harry Heltzer, 94, Inventor of Reflective Signs, Dies<date>Published: September 28, 2005</date><text>Harry Heltzer, who began at the 3M Company as a $12-a-week manual laborer, invented one of the company's most profitable products and rose to be its top executive, died on Sept. 21 at his home in Lenoir, N.C. He was 94. A granddaughter, Deborah Heltzer, confirmed the death. Mr. Heltzer's invention was a new way of making reflective signs for use on highways. It went on to become a market leader. As head of 3M, a diversified technology and manufacturing company founded as the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, Mr. Heltzer expanded the company to 150 countries, directly investing in new businesses abroad instead of just selling products. From 1966 to 1972, years in which he was at the top of the company, earnings rose sharply. Nearly a third of that increase came after he rose from president to chairman and chief executive in October 1970. Mr. Heltzer was fond of pointing out that none of 3M's 30,000 products, the most famous of which is Scotch tape, generated more than 5 percent of its total revenue. "It's all nickel and dime stuff," he said in a newspaper interview in the 1970's. "But those nickels and dimes, they sure do add up." Mr. Heltzer was born in Cincinnati on Aug. 22, 1911, and moved to Minneapolis as a child. He graduated from the University of Minnesota in metallurgical engineering, then went to work for 3M as a laborer in its abrasives department. His first job was unloading roofing granules from boxcars for 35 cents an hour. His wife, Elizabeth, told The Star Tribune of Minneapolis for its obituary article that he liked to say, "I asked for a job, and they gave me a job and a shovel." In 1937, he was assigned to a project to make the center striping on highways more reflective at night than was possible with the standard white or yellow paint. A Minnesota highway official had suggested painting glass beads onto the stripe. The first problem Mr. Heltzer encountered was a lack of glass beads small enough to use. He proceeded to make his own, often through novel methods. One was to drop molten glass from his window. He finally fashioned an acceptable double-coated tape with beads on one side, but he could not make it stick to the road during a Minnesota winter. So he used the process he developed to make a material for signs, which was sold as Scotchlite reflective sheeting. Later he developed a glass-bead reflective compound for highway striping that would stick to the road's surface. He was awarded six patents for reflective highway products. In 1961, Mr. Heltzer was named a vice president of 3M; in 1965, a board member; and, in 1966, president. In 1970, he was elected chairman and chief executive. Mr. Heltzer resigned in 1975, at age 64, one year before 3M's official retirement age. That year, 3M, Mr. Heltzer and two other executives consented to a federal court order barring them from violations of securities laws in connection with illegal campaign contributions. In 1973 he had pleaded guilty to contributing $30,000 in company funds to President Richard M. Nixon's presidential campaign in 1972. In a scheme that began before Mr. Heltzer rose to the top of the company, 3M had kept an illegal slush fund of more than $600,000, which it used to make more than $400,000 in illegal political donations. Mr. Heltzer disbursed the money during his time as chief executive. "I should have been a lot smarter than I was," Mr. Heltzer said in an interview with The New York Times in 1975. "By just not asking the proper questions at the right time, I kind of fell into what seemed to be the practice of the times." Mr. Heltzer was chairman of the International Road Federation, the Highway Users Federation for Safety and Mobility and the Automotive Safety Foundation. He was a director of the National Safety Council and a member of the National Highway Safety Advisory Committee. In addition to his wife, the former Elizabeth Kent, Mr. Heltzer is survived by a son, James, of Bemidji, Minn.; a daughter, Maryhelen Hauge, of Maple Grove, Minn.; five grandchildren; and two great-grandchildren. More Articles in Business &gt;Harry Heltzer, who began at the 3M Company as a $12-a-week manual laborer, invented one of the company's most profitable products and rose to be its top executive, died on Sept. 21 at his home in Lenoir, N.C. He was 94. A granddaughter, Deborah Heltzer, confirmed the death. Mr. Heltzer's invention was a new way of making reflective signs for use on highways. It went on to become a market leader. As head of 3M, a diversified technology and manufacturing company founded as the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, Mr. Heltzer expanded the company to 150 countries, directly investing in new businesses abroad instead of just selling products. From 1966 to 1972, years in which he was at the top of the company, earnings rose sharply. Nearly a third of that increase came after he rose from president to chairman and chief executive in October 1970. Mr. Heltzer was fond of pointing out that none of 3M's 30,000 products, the most famous of which is Scotch tape, generated more than 5 percent of its total revenue. "It's all nickel and dime stuff," he said in a newspaper interview in the 1970's. "But those nickels and dimes, they sure do add up." Mr. Heltzer was born in Cincinnati on Aug. 22, 1911, and moved to Minneapolis as a child. He graduated from the University of Minnesota in metallurgical engineering, then went to work for 3M as a laborer in its abrasives department. His first job was unloading roofing granules from boxcars for 35 cents an hour. His wife, Elizabeth, told The Star Tribune of Minneapolis for its obituary article that he liked to say, "I asked for a job, and they gave me a job and a shovel." In 1937, he was assigned to a project to make the center striping on highways more reflective at night than was possible with the standard white or yellow paint. A Minnesota highway official had suggested painting glass beads onto the stripe. The first problem Mr. Heltzer encountered was a lack of glass beads small enough to use. He proceeded to make his own, often through novel methods. One was to drop molten glass from his window. He finally fashioned an acceptable double-coated tape with beads on one side, but he could not make it stick to the road during a Minnesota winter. So he used the process he developed to make a material for signs, which was sold as Scotchlite reflective sheeting. Later he developed a glass-bead reflective compound for highway striping that would stick to the road's surface. He was awarded six patents for reflective highway products. In 1961, Mr. Heltzer was named a vice president of 3M; in 1965, a board member; and, in 1966, president. In 1970, he was elected chairman and chief executive. Mr. Heltzer resigned in 1975, at age 64, one year before 3M's official retirement age. That year, 3M, Mr. Heltzer and two other executives consented to a federal court order barring them from violations of securities laws in connection with illegal campaign contributions. In 1973 he had pleaded guilty to contributing $30,000 in company funds to President Richard M. Nixon's presidential campaign in 1972. In a scheme that began before Mr. Heltzer rose to the top of the company, 3M had kept an illegal slush fund of more than $600,000, which it used to make more than $400,000 in illegal political donations. Mr. Heltzer disbursed the money during his time as chief executive. "I should have been a lot smarter than I was," Mr. Heltzer said in an interview with The New York Times in 1975. "By just not asking the proper questions at the right time, I kind of fell into what seemed to be the practice of the times." Mr. Heltzer was chairman of the International Road Federation, the Highway Users Federation for Safety and Mobility and the Automotive Safety Foundation. He was a director of the National Safety Council and a member of the National Highway Safety Advisory Committee. In addition to his wife, the former Elizabeth Kent, Mr. Heltzer is survived by a son, James, of Bemidji, Minn.; a daughter, Maryhelen Hauge, of Maple Grove, Minn.; five grandchildren; and two great-grandchildren.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/07/business/07boeing.html?ref=3mcompany">Boeing Pay Is a Match for Chief<date>Published: July 7, 2005</date><text>CHICAGO, July 6 - Boeing agreed to pay its new chief executive, W. James McNerney Jr., a total compensation package that could top $53 million to wrest him away from 3M, Boeing said Wednesday. The package essentially replaces the one that Mr. McNerney held at 3M, and to collect its full value he will have to stay at Boeing at least six years, company officials said. Skip to next paragraph W. James McNerney left 3M to become chief executive of Boeing. In addition, now that Mr. McNerney has left 3M he can begin to sell 3M stock options valued at nearly $30 million. His Boeing compensation includes an annual salary of $1.75 million and a maximum bonus of $4 million, as well as more than $25 million in restricted stock awards and $22 million in supplemental retirement benefits, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. He will also get the use of company aircraft, club memberships, a leased car and a financial services allowance. Mr. McNerney's total cash compensation for 2005 will be no less than $4.7 million, including a guaranteed bonus. The chief executives of the seven largest aerospace companies, including Boeing, earned a median salary and bonus last year of $3.9 million, according to Equilar, a compensation analysis firm in San Mateo, Calif. Mr. McNerney, an outside director at Boeing, agreed last week to take the job after saying previously that he wanted to stay at 3M. With a proven track record on Wall Street and aerospace experience as the former president of General Electric's aircraft engines division, Mr. McNerney, 55, had been among Boeing's top choices for the job. Mr. McNerney has said that he decided to jump to Boeing in part because he yearned to return to the aircraft industry. He has also said he wanted to close out his career at a higher-profile company that presents a bigger management challenge. Boeing had more than twice the revenue of 3M last year, at $52.5 billion, and more than double the employees, at 159,000. "He is, in the unanimous judgment of our board members, the ideal person to lead Boeing," Lewis E. Platt, the company's lead director, said in a statement Wednesday. Mr. Platt, who served as the chairman of Boeing during the search, said last week that Mr. McNerney's pay package would be comparable to what he made at 3M. "It was simply a lateral move, paywise," he said. Boeing does appear to have sought to match Mr. McNerney's package at 3M, which paid him a combined salary and bonus of $5.1 million last year. At Boeing, he will make at least $4.7 million in salary and bonus, and up to $5.8 million, depending on his performance. Boeing also replaced a mix of stock options, restricted stock and performance-based compensation at 3M with 391,000 restricted shares of Boeing. The shares will vest over three to six years on the same schedules as their 3M equivalents, a Boeing spokeswoman, Anne Eisele, said. Boeing also agreed to pay Mr. McNerney a supplemental pension, currently valued at $22 million, in two lump sums. An $11 million portion vested as of July 1, his first day of work. The other $11 million will vest over five years, starting next January. If Mr. McNerney were to leave Boeing before finishing three years there, he would forfeit the entire $22 million, which he would be eligible to receive at 62, Ms. Eisele said. To realize the full value of his compensation package, including his restricted stock, he would have to stay at Boeing for six years. "No one here is looking at this as a three-year contract," Ms. Eisele said. "He has said he wants to stay at Boeing for the rest of his career. He doesn't seem to be a short timer." Mr. McNerney arrives at a time when Boeing is finding success with its commercial aircraft after years of lackluster sales. Orders for the 787 Dreamliner are lifting the company's prospects and helping it to outperform Airbus, its major rival. The Dreamliner has drawn nearly twice as many orders as the Airbus A380. But the company's corporate suites in Chicago have been stained with scandal after its last two chief executives were forced to leave. Harry C. Stonecipher resigned this year after admitting having an affair with a female subordinate. His predecessor, Philip M. Condit, resigned after 38 years at the company amid disclosures of a conflict of interest involving Boeing and an Air Force official who was seeking a job with the company while overseeing Pentagon procurement contracts. Mr. McNerney could not be reached yesterday. He said in an interview last week that the ethical challenges at the company had not been fully put to rest. "You earn your reputation every day so it is never over," he said. He also said last week that his initial focus at Boeing would be to sharpen operations and execute plans already in place rather than serve as a grand visionary. Mr. McNerney had been 3M's chief since 2001 and previously held top positions at G.E., where he was a leading candidate to succeed John F. Welch Jr. He did not land that job but was picked up by 3M, where he increased profits and share price. "He brought some needed discipline over there," said Frederick M. Zimmerman, a professor of engineering and technology management at the University of St. Thomas in St. Paul, the city where 3M is based. "But some people have complained that he sacrificed the long term for the short term in ways that 3M'ers aren't used to." By leaving 3M, Mr. McNerney will soon be able to sell as many as 2.3 million stock options worth $29.7 million at 3M's closing price yesterday of $72.83. This figure assumes that the number of stock options Mr. McNerney is able to sell in the market today is the same number he held at the end of last year, based on proxy filings. A representative of 3M could not be reached late Wednesday to comment on the stock options. Eric Dash contributed reporting from New York for this article. More Articles in Business &gt;CHICAGO, July 6 - Boeing agreed to pay its new chief executive, W. James McNerney Jr., a total compensation package that could top $53 million to wrest him away from 3M, Boeing said Wednesday. The package essentially replaces the one that Mr. McNerney held at 3M, and to collect its full value he will have to stay at Boeing at least six years, company officials said. Skip to next paragraph W. James McNerney left 3M to become chief executive of Boeing. In addition, now that Mr. McNerney has left 3M he can begin to sell 3M stock options valued at nearly $30 million. His Boeing compensation includes an annual salary of $1.75 million and a maximum bonus of $4 million, as well as more than $25 million in restricted stock awards and $22 million in supplemental retirement benefits, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. He will also get the use of company aircraft, club memberships, a leased car and a financial services allowance. Mr. McNerney's total cash compensation for 2005 will be no less than $4.7 million, including a guaranteed bonus. The chief executives of the seven largest aerospace companies, including Boeing, earned a median salary and bonus last year of $3.9 million, according to Equilar, a compensation analysis firm in San Mateo, Calif. Mr. McNerney, an outside director at Boeing, agreed last week to take the job after saying previously that he wanted to stay at 3M. With a proven track record on Wall Street and aerospace experience as the former president of General Electric's aircraft engines division, Mr. McNerney, 55, had been among Boeing's top choices for the job. Mr. McNerney has said that he decided to jump to Boeing in part because he yearned to return to the aircraft industry. He has also said he wanted to close out his career at a higher-profile company that presents a bigger management challenge. Boeing had more than twice the revenue of 3M last year, at $52.5 billion, and more than double the employees, at 159,000. "He is, in the unanimous judgment of our board members, the ideal person to lead Boeing," Lewis E. Platt, the company's lead director, said in a statement Wednesday. Mr. Platt, who served as the chairman of Boeing during the search, said last week that Mr. McNerney's pay package would be comparable to what he made at 3M. "It was simply a lateral move, paywise," he said. Boeing does appear to have sought to match Mr. McNerney's package at 3M, which paid him a combined salary and bonus of $5.1 million last year. At Boeing, he will make at least $4.7 million in salary and bonus, and up to $5.8 million, depending on his performance. Boeing also replaced a mix of stock options, restricted stock and performance-based compensation at 3M with 391,000 restricted shares of Boeing. The shares will vest over three to six years on the same schedules as their 3M equivalents, a Boeing spokeswoman, Anne Eisele, said. Boeing also agreed to pay Mr. McNerney a supplemental pension, currently valued at $22 million, in two lump sums. An $11 million portion vested as of July 1, his first day of work. The other $11 million will vest over five years, starting next January. If Mr. McNerney were to leave Boeing before finishing three years there, he would forfeit the entire $22 million, which he would be eligible to receive at 62, Ms. Eisele said. To realize the full value of his compensation package, including his restricted stock, he would have to stay at Boeing for six years. "No one here is looking at this as a three-year contract," Ms. Eisele said. "He has said he wants to stay at Boeing for the rest of his career. He doesn't seem to be a short timer." Mr. McNerney arrives at a time when Boeing is finding success with its commercial aircraft after years of lackluster sales. Orders for the 787 Dreamliner are lifting the company's prospects and helping it to outperform Airbus, its major rival. The Dreamliner has drawn nearly twice as many orders as the Airbus A380. But the company's corporate suites in Chicago have been stained with scandal after its last two chief executives were forced to leave. Harry C. Stonecipher resigned this year after admitting having an affair with a female subordinate. His predecessor, Philip M. Condit, resigned after 38 years at the company amid disclosures of a conflict of interest involving Boeing and an Air Force official who was seeking a job with the company while overseeing Pentagon procurement contracts. Mr. McNerney could not be reached yesterday. He said in an interview last week that the ethical challenges at the company had not been fully put to rest. "You earn your reputation every day so it is never over," he said. He also said last week that his initial focus at Boeing would be to sharpen operations and execute plans already in place rather than serve as a grand visionary. Mr. McNerney had been 3M's chief since 2001 and previously held top positions at G.E., where he was a leading candidate to succeed John F. Welch Jr. He did not land that job but was picked up by 3M, where he increased profits and share price. "He brought some needed discipline over there," said Frederick M. Zimmerman, a professor of engineering and technology management at the University of St. Thomas in St. Paul, the city where 3M is based. "But some people have complained that he sacrificed the long term for the short term in ways that 3M'ers aren't used to." By leaving 3M, Mr. McNerney will soon be able to sell as many as 2.3 million stock options worth $29.7 million at 3M's closing price yesterday of $72.83. This figure assumes that the number of stock options Mr. McNerney is able to sell in the market today is the same number he held at the end of last year, based on proxy filings. A representative of 3M could not be reached late Wednesday to comment on the stock options. Eric Dash contributed reporting from New York for this article.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/30/business/30boeing.html?ref=3mcompany">Boeing Names 3M Chief as Its New Top Executive<date>Published: June 30, 2005</date><text>Correction Appended The Boeing Company, which has been on the upswing after a series of scandals, appointed the head of the 3M Company as its new chief executive today. Skip to next paragraph Jim Mone/Associated Press W. James McNerney Jr. of 3M is expected to lead Boeing. The 3M chief, W. James McNerney Jr., 55, has been a director at Boeing since 2001, and would become the third chief executive in about 18 months. Boeing's board had been actively pursuing candidates over the last few months, winnowing down a list of 20 or so names to a handful of serious contenders. At the company's annual meeting this spring, Lewis E. Platt, Boeing's chairman, said that the company had been examining a few candidates both inside and outside the company. By offering the job to Mr. McNerney, the board passed up Alan R. Mulally, its commercial airplane group leader, and James F. Albaugh, the head of its integrated military systems division. Both men were respected leaders throughout the aerospace industry. Mr. McNerney was approached early on, a person close to the board said, but it was not until about two weeks ago that he became a serious prospect. It is awkward, though not unusual, for a longtime director to be considered for the chief executive post, the person said. "Jim was asked right from the get-go if he would consider, and said, 'No, I owe my allegiance to 3M,' " an individual close to the board said last night. "But at the end of the day, they realized the best leader for their company was McNerney. The directors persuaded him to come to the plate." This person said that Mr. McNerney was persuaded to accept the job by his passion for the airline industry and a desire to leave the Minneapolis-St. Paul area, where 3M is based, for Chicago, where Boeing has its headquarters. Before coming to 3M, he was the chief executive of the jet-engine unit of General Electric, and people close to the decision said that he would bring a strong knowledge of the military and commercial business to the job. In addition, the move will allow him to sell thousands of shares of 3M stock. "If you can get your No. 1 horse, everyone else is pretty distant," the person to the board said. "McNerney was the lead horse but needed to be brought to the water to take the drink." Boeing's board also considered to varying degrees at least five candidates who came from outside the company in a list that reads like the who' s who of the airline business. Among those considered were David M. Cote, the chief executive of Honeywell; Karl J. Krapek, the former United Technologies president; and Clayton M. Jones, the Rockwell Collins chairman. The board had also flirted with two other General Electric disciples of John F. Welch Jr.: David L. Calhoun, G.E.'s airline division head, and Robert L. Nardelli, who left the company to take over at Home Depot. Calls to the home of Mr. Platt were not returned last night. Mr. McNerney takes over at Boeing at a time when its prospects had been improving under the interim chief, James A. Bell, who had been the chief financial officer. The company, which has been prohibited from competing for Air Force rocket contracts for the last two years, has recently re-entered the business. Its commercial airline business has also been looking up, and the company has said it is on track to lead the industry in orders. Its 787 Dreamliner is expected to be a hit this year. However, Boeing, the world's second-largest aerospace company and the Pentagon's No. 2 supplier, faces several challenges. Mr. McNerney must move to compete with Airbus, the largest in the industry, which has enjoyed success in emerging markets. Also, Boeing struggled for a time to recover from its role in an Air Force procurement scandal, the loss of important government contracts and the jailing of two former top executives. Mr. McNerney will take over a position left vacant on March 7 when Harry C. Stonecipher, who was brought out of retirement to restore the company's credibility, was forced to resign after admitting an affair with a female Boeing executive. His predecessor, Philip M. Condit, was forced to resign in 2003 because of ethical lapses, including affairs with employees, and the faltering business prospects that Mr. Stonecipher was hired to remedy. It was under Mr. Condit that a chief financial officer, Michael M. Sears, engaged in illegal hiring discussions with an Air Force official, Darleen A. Druyun, who later worked for Boeing; both ended up getting prison terms. Ms. Druyun said she favored Boeing in contracts in order to get jobs for herself and her family. The company was also barred from bidding on $1 billion in Air Force rocket launching contracts after Boeing employees were found to have stolen thousands of proprietary documents from a rival, the Lockheed Martin Corporation. Correction: July 1, 2005, Friday: Because of a telephone transcription error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the selection of W. James McNerney Jr. as chief executive of Boeing gave a misspelled surname in some copies for the former president of United Technologies, who was also a candidate. He is Karl J. Krapek, not Kratech. In some copies the article also misstated the company and position of another candidate, David L. Calhoun. He is the vice chairman of GE Infrastructure, not chief executive of Honeywell. More Articles in Business &gt;Correction Appended The Boeing Company, which has been on the upswing after a series of scandals, appointed the head of the 3M Company as its new chief executive today. Skip to next paragraph Jim Mone/Associated Press W. James McNerney Jr. of 3M is expected to lead Boeing. The 3M chief, W. James McNerney Jr., 55, has been a director at Boeing since 2001, and would become the third chief executive in about 18 months. Boeing's board had been actively pursuing candidates over the last few months, winnowing down a list of 20 or so names to a handful of serious contenders. At the company's annual meeting this spring, Lewis E. Platt, Boeing's chairman, said that the company had been examining a few candidates both inside and outside the company. By offering the job to Mr. McNerney, the board passed up Alan R. Mulally, its commercial airplane group leader, and James F. Albaugh, the head of its integrated military systems division. Both men were respected leaders throughout the aerospace industry. Mr. McNerney was approached early on, a person close to the board said, but it was not until about two weeks ago that he became a serious prospect. It is awkward, though not unusual, for a longtime director to be considered for the chief executive post, the person said. "Jim was asked right from the get-go if he would consider, and said, 'No, I owe my allegiance to 3M,' " an individual close to the board said last night. "But at the end of the day, they realized the best leader for their company was McNerney. The directors persuaded him to come to the plate." This person said that Mr. McNerney was persuaded to accept the job by his passion for the airline industry and a desire to leave the Minneapolis-St. Paul area, where 3M is based, for Chicago, where Boeing has its headquarters. Before coming to 3M, he was the chief executive of the jet-engine unit of General Electric, and people close to the decision said that he would bring a strong knowledge of the military and commercial business to the job. In addition, the move will allow him to sell thousands of shares of 3M stock. "If you can get your No. 1 horse, everyone else is pretty distant," the person to the board said. "McNerney was the lead horse but needed to be brought to the water to take the drink." Boeing's board also considered to varying degrees at least five candidates who came from outside the company in a list that reads like the who' s who of the airline business. Among those considered were David M. Cote, the chief executive of Honeywell; Karl J. Krapek, the former United Technologies president; and Clayton M. Jones, the Rockwell Collins chairman. The board had also flirted with two other General Electric disciples of John F. Welch Jr.: David L. Calhoun, G.E.'s airline division head, and Robert L. Nardelli, who left the company to take over at Home Depot. Calls to the home of Mr. Platt were not returned last night. Mr. McNerney takes over at Boeing at a time when its prospects had been improving under the interim chief, James A. Bell, who had been the chief financial officer. The company, which has been prohibited from competing for Air Force rocket contracts for the last two years, has recently re-entered the business. Its commercial airline business has also been looking up, and the company has said it is on track to lead the industry in orders. Its 787 Dreamliner is expected to be a hit this year. However, Boeing, the world's second-largest aerospace company and the Pentagon's No. 2 supplier, faces several challenges. Mr. McNerney must move to compete with Airbus, the largest in the industry, which has enjoyed success in emerging markets. Also, Boeing struggled for a time to recover from its role in an Air Force procurement scandal, the loss of important government contracts and the jailing of two former top executives. Mr. McNerney will take over a position left vacant on March 7 when Harry C. Stonecipher, who was brought out of retirement to restore the company's credibility, was forced to resign after admitting an affair with a female Boeing executive. His predecessor, Philip M. Condit, was forced to resign in 2003 because of ethical lapses, including affairs with employees, and the faltering business prospects that Mr. Stonecipher was hired to remedy. It was under Mr. Condit that a chief financial officer, Michael M. Sears, engaged in illegal hiring discussions with an Air Force official, Darleen A. Druyun, who later worked for Boeing; both ended up getting prison terms. Ms. Druyun said she favored Boeing in contracts in order to get jobs for herself and her family. The company was also barred from bidding on $1 billion in Air Force rocket launching contracts after Boeing employees were found to have stolen thousands of proprietary documents from a rival, the Lockheed Martin Corporation. Correction: July 1, 2005, Friday: Because of a telephone transcription error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the selection of W. James McNerney Jr. as chief executive of Boeing gave a misspelled surname in some copies for the former president of United Technologies, who was also a candidate. He is Karl J. Krapek, not Kratech. In some copies the article also misstated the company and position of another candidate, David L. Calhoun. He is the vice chairman of GE Infrastructure, not chief executive of Honeywell.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/31/technology/circuits/31filt.html?ref=3mcompany">With a Privacy Filter on Your Monitor, You Can Work and Others Can't See<date>Published: March 31, 2005</date><text>rotecting private information on your computer means more than encrypting files and running an occasional spyware sweep. A nosy neighbor can peer over your shoulder as you work on a confidential document on a flight, for instance. For times when you need to keep wandering eyes away from your screen, the 3M Company's privacy filters can make it difficult for others to see what you are doing. With a privacy filter over the display, anyone trying to snoop will see a black screen; only the person working directly in front of the machine can see what's on the screen. The filters, which can reduce glare while improving clarity, use 3M's microlouver custom technology and work somewhat the way miniblinds do. The company makes privacy filters to fit a variety of computers, including laptops with a 15.4-inch widescreen and standard screens of 12.1, 13.3, 14.1 and 15 inches. Prices start at about $50 depending on screen size; 3M has more information and a list of places to buy the filter at www.3m.com/computerfilters. Privacy filters for larger desktop monitors are also available, so people working on sensitive files like salary spreadsheets can relax as co-workers breeze past. J. D. Biersdorfer</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/17/business/yourmoney/17home.html?ref=3mcompany">Terrorbusters Inc.<date>Published: October 17, 2004</date><text>HE high-pitched whine started suddenly during breakfast in the elegant dining room of the Regency Hotel in Manhattan. Richard G. Hudak, a good-natured, talkative executive, ignored it at first, but the sound persisted. Clearly distracted, he broke off the conversation, rose from the table and walked slowly toward the lobby, tracking the source of the noise with the concentration of a hunting dog. No one else seated at the elaborately set tables in the crowded room seemed especially concerned. The whine stopped as abruptly as it began, and when Mr. Hudak returned a minute or two later, he was his relaxed self again. An elevator had malfunctioned, setting off the alarm, he explained. The whine had not signaled a terrorist attack, which is Mr. Hudak's great concern as director of corporate safety and security for the Loews Corporation, the Regency's owner. Before 9/11, retired cops did this sort of work, Mr. Hudak said, disdainfully. He, by contrast, is a specialist, a former F.B.I. agent and a Harvard graduate who is high enough in the Loews hierarchy to compete successfully for corporate funds to protect the company's many properties from terrorism. "Since 9/11, senior executives listen more closely and I have much more access to them,'' he said. The 3M Corporation brought Mr. Hudak to a reporter's attention. Thanks to him, Loews has become a good customer for a 3M product: a paper-thin, puncture-proof film that is affixed to windows so they won't shatter when a terrorist bomb explodes, sending shards of glass flying into employees and customers. Believing that the Regency, particularly the ground floor, is a potential target, Mr. Hudak had the film installed on the restaurant's huge plate glass windows, at a cost of $8 a square foot. The product's first test at the hotel came not from terrorists, but from a disgruntled employee who smashed a window with a hammer. "It broke but did not shatter,'' Mr. Hudak said. The shards stayed sandwiched between the two layers of film, as if they were part of a shatterproof auto windshield. "That demonstrated to management the value of applying window film,'' he said. Four of the 20 hotels in the company's chain now have it. So do the windows of a two-story Bulova watch factory that Loews owns in Woodside, Queens, as well as the glass doors to the Loews executive offices in Manhattan. "It has become a recommended solution for a lot of situations, including labor unrest,'' Mr. Hudak added. Corporate America is spending heavily for protection. Private-sector outlays for antiterrorism measures and to guard against other forms of violence may now be as much as $40 billion to $50 billion a year, or two or three times higher than the annual rate before 9/11, according to estimates compiled by CQ Homeland Security, a daily Internet newsletter published by Congressional Quarterly. The federal government's contribution has also passed the $40 billion mark, double what it was before 9/11. As the spending soars, domestic security seems poised to become a significant factor in the overall economy, much the way military spending was during the cold war. THE question is: What is enough security?'' said Gordon Adams, who oversaw national security spending at the Office of Management and Budget in the Clinton administration and now heads a security policy studies program at George Washington University. "The answer is, no one knows, and fear is a powerful driver here. Since we do not know who means us harm, where they are and how long they are going to continue to mean us harm, where do you stop?'' Mr. Adams contends that much of the spending on domestic security is justified. Shattered glass is certainly a legitimate concern, he said, "but I predict that five years from now there will be Congressional hearings about the illegitimate business that is also being done, through the exploitation of fear.'' For now, such second-guessing is not even on the horizon. If anything, Senator John Kerry accuses President Bush of not spending enough on domestic security. "The measurement is not are we safer, the measurement is are we as safe as we ought to be,'' Mr. Kerry said in the presidential debate on Wednesday night. And his answer was no. The marketplace for domestic security is developing apace. Mr. Hudak and his counterparts at more than 300 big corporations have banded together as members of the International Security Management Association. The group says the risk of terrorist attacks justifies more spending, and it is busy making that case to employers. Continued 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 5 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/15/science/epa-orders-companies-to-examine-effects-of-chemicals.html?ref=3mcompany">E.P.A. Orders Companies to Examine Effects of Chemicals<date>Published: April 15, 2003</date><text>Scientists and regulators are raising concerns about the potential health and environmental effects of an important family of industrial chemicals.Those concerns were highlighted yesterday when the Environment Protection Agency announced it was forcing the chemical industry to do further research on perfluorooctanoic acid, or PFOA, one member of that family.The broader group of chemicals, known as perfluorinated acids, has been discovered widely in the environment and in almost all Americans. No human health effects have been discovered, but E.P.A. officials' concerns were raised by recent toxicological data in animals.Since World War II, perfluorinated acids have become incorporated into many brand-name chemicals because they repel water and oil and are resistant to heat and chemical stress. Used in the manufacturing process of Teflon and Gore-Tex, they are released as breakdown products from Stainmaster, Teflon and the original formulation of Scotchgard. They are also used to make polymers for aircraft and electronics.Scientists say the properties that make the chemicals attractive to industry -- their chemical stability and resistance to high temperatures -- may potentially have serious effects on the environment.Perfluorinated acids do not degrade. They are widely distributed -- showing up in the Arctic, in food samples and in almost all human blood samples that have been tested. No one has found that the chemicals have a toxic effect on humans, but early research on animals shows that at least some perfluorinated acids in high doses have the potential to be toxic.This combination of traits caught the attention of the E.P.A.''Though we have concerns, there is a lot of uncertainty,'' said Stephen L. Johnson, assistant administrator of E.P.A.'s Office of Prevention, Pesticides, and Toxic Substances. ''Given the uncertainty, additional scientific information is needed to determine if regulatory actions are necessary.''Environment groups are comparing perfluorinated acids to PCB's and DDT, which appeared benign when they were first introduced. Environmental groups note that PCB's were banned by Congress in 1976, and less was known about them then than is currently known about perfluorinated acids.Chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, were also prized for their chemical stability until the 1970's, when scientists discovered that their accumulation in the atmosphere eroded the ozone layer.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/28/travel/driving-bells-whistles-cooling-film-for-windows.html?ref=3mcompany">DRIVING: BELLS &amp; WHISTLES; Cooling Film For Windows<date>Published: March 28, 2003</date><text>Sure, a bulky cardboard shade propped in the windshield will help keep a parked car from heating up like an oven in the summer sun. But 3M has come up with something way cooler, Solar Reflecting Film, an ultrathin sheet of clear plastic built into the windshield. It deflects the sun's heat and ultimately increases fuel efficiency.The invisible film, sandwiched in the windshield's layers of glass and plastic, is on the rear windshield of the BMW 7 series and the Porsche Cayenne. In the next model year, more brands and models will have the film. Its use will be expanded to front windshields and, possibly, side windows, said Doug Thompson, business director in the automotive division of 3M.The film does not just keep the car cooler in the sun, but it also works while the car is moving, reducing the burden on air-conditioners and raising fuel economy up to 0.3 miles a gallon, Mr. Thompson said. He added that concern about gasoline consumption was growing as designers seek to add glass on cars. The film helps manage the solar energy load.Previous attempts to screen out the bright sun relied on metal-based coatings that reduced visibility and interfered with electronic signals like those used for mobile telephones, garage-door openers and toll passes. Now, 3M hopes to expand the use of its film to windows for buses, trains and ships. JOYCE COHEN</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/23/business/3m-quarterly-profit-is-essentially-flat.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Quarterly Profit Is Essentially Flat<date>Published: April 23, 2002</date><text>The 3M Company said today that its first-quarter earnings were little changed as the strong dollar slowed sales overseas.3M, which recently changed its name from Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, said it earned $452 million, or $1.14 a share, compared with $453 million, or $1.13 a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue fell to $3.89 billion from $4.16 billion.Excluding one-time items, 3M earned $487 million, or $1.23 a share, in the first quarter, compared with $467 million, or $1.16 a share, in the period a year earlier. On that basis, the company exceeded the $1.19 a share expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call.Shares of 3M rose 12 cents, to $125.01.The company's health care and transportation, graphics and safety segments showed volume growth while volume in other areas slipped.Worldwide sales dropped 6.5 percent, to $3.89 billion, in the quarter from $4.16 billion a year earlier.3M, which has been working to cut costs and improve efficiency across its businesses, paid out $100 million in severance-related costs during the quarter, said Pat Campbell, the chief financial officer.W. James McNerney Jr., 3M's chairman and chief executive, said earnings for the full year were expected in the range of $4.80 to 5.10 a share, before one-time items and including the benefits from new accounting rules. Second-quarter earnings are expected at or above first-quarter levels, Mr. McNerney added.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/10/business/a-surge-in-asbestos-suits-many-by-healthy-plaintiffs.html?ref=3mcompany">A Surge in Asbestos Suits, Many by Healthy Plaintiffs<date>Published: April 10, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedDecades after American companies largely stopped using asbestos, a wave of asbestos-related lawsuits is again flooding the nation's courts.The suits, once filed mainly against shipbuilders, makers of asbestos and companies in a few other industries, now touch thousands of companies. In the last two years, they have forced at least 18 companies, with more than 100,000 employees, into bankruptcy protection.Exposure to asbestos has plunged since the 1970's, and the number of new cases of asbestos-related disease has been falling, doctors say. Very few new plaintiffs have serious injuries, even their lawyers acknowledge. But at least 90,000 new claims were filed last year. If the trend continues, as many as 2.5 million people could file asbestos-related suits before the litigation begins to fade around 2030.Many companies now facing asbestos lawsuits did not make asbestos or use it heavily in their products. They have been sued because more obvious defendants have already filed for bankruptcy protection and are protected from large verdicts.Wall Street has grown uneasy that even profitable giants like Dow Chemical, which had $27 billion in sales last year, could struggle with claims for years. The National Association of Manufacturers calls asbestos a top priority, along with taxes, trade and energy.Among the companies that have lost multimillion-dollar judgments since last fall are Dow, Halliburton and 3M. Viacom reported 106,000 claims at the end of the year related to its one-time ownership of Westinghouse, and the big automakers are so worried that they have hired the lawyer who successfully represented Dow Corning in its breast-implant litigation.''We've got a lot of people who have claims,'' said Stephen Carroll, a senior economist at the Rand Institute for Civil Justice who has studied asbestos litigation. ''It's going to take a lot of money to settle those claims, and we are beginning to run out of people who are rather clearly and distinctly culpable to charge.''New claims have steadily increased since 1997, when the Supreme Court struck down a class-action settlement between asbestos defendants and lawyers for plaintiffs. The settlement would have prevented most people exposed to asbestos from filing lawsuits unless they became sick. The court said the settlement was unfair to future claimants, who would be forced to abide by its terms even though they had not agreed to it.Correction: April 11, 2002, Thursday A front-page article yesterday about an increase in the number of asbestos lawsuits erroneously included Dow Chemical among those that have lost multimillion-dollar judgments since last fall. Dow has not lost a multimillion-dollar verdict, but it said in a filing with regulators last month that in 2001 Union Carbide, which it acquired in February 2001, had raised its estimate of the amount it could be liable for in asbestos cases by $115 million, to $233 million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/05/business/company-news-3m-is-upbeat-about-the-quarter-now-about-that-name.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M IS UPBEAT ABOUT THE QUARTER; NOW, ABOUT THAT NAME<date>Published: April 05, 2002</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing gave an optimistic outlook for the first quarter yesterday and said it would change its name to the 3M Company, as it is already commonly known. 3M, based in St. Paul, also said it expected its first quarter profit to be at the top or above earlier forecasts. The company, which makes Post-It notes and Scotch tape, said it expected to earn $1.20 a share or slightly more in its first quarter, compared with its earlier expectation of $1.05 to $1.20 a share. The company's name change will become legally effective on Monday.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/08/business/company-news-3m-cutting-500-jobs-as-it-phases-out-tape-plant.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M CUTTING 500 JOBS AS IT PHASES OUT TAPE PLANT<date>Published: February 08, 2002</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it would cut 500 jobs as it phased out most production at a tape and abrasives plant in St. Paul and developed a technology resource center. The plant has about 1,500 employees, two-thirds engineers and designers and one-third maintenance and production workers. Over the next year, about 500 manufacturing and manufacturing-related jobs will be eliminated, 3M said. Longer term, the company expects employment to climb at the site as the technology resource center is developed.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/19/business/company-news-3m-plans-to-eliminate-2500-more-jobs.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M PLANS TO ELIMINATE 2,500 MORE JOBS<date>Published: January 19, 2002</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, which cut 6,000 jobs last year, said yesterday that it would cut 2,500 more jobs in the next year. ''These are tough and unusual times, and I don't see the negative global economic situation abating any time soon,'' 3M's chief executive, W. James McNerney Jr., said. The company, which is based in Minneapolis, announced the job cuts as it reported that its profit for its fourth quarter fell to $387 million, or 98 cents a share, from $447 million, or $1.12 a share, a year earlier. The results included a $103 million pretax charge related to job cuts and accelerated depreciation and a $73 million pretax gain related to the company's successful appeal in an antitrust case.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/09/business/investing-diary-the-ge-racehorses-one-year-afterward.html?ref=3mcompany">INVESTING: DIARY; The G.E. Racehorses, One Year Afterward<date>Published: December 9, 2001</date><text>About this time last year, the horse race to succeed John F. Welch Jr. as the head of General Electric ended. Jeffrey R. Immelt got the job. In an instant, Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing snared W. James McNerney Jr., one of the two also-rans, and Home Depot grabbed Robert L. Nardelli, the other. Other companies in need of leadership could only watch with envy. So, how have these most wanted done? If stock prices are any indication, Home Depot got the best deal. On Dec. 4, 2000, the day Mr. Nardelli became chief executive, it closed at $40.75 a share. A year later, it was up 17 percent, at $47.70. Mr. McNerney has not fared as well, but he appears to have kept the damage at 3M to a minimum. On Jan. 2, his first day on the job, its shares closed at $119.20 a share. By Dec. 4, they had dropped 2.3 percent, to $116.43. It is Mr. Immelt who has fallen behind. On Nov. 27, 2000, when G.E. anointed him, its stock closed at $49.125 a share. Between then and Sept. 7, the day he officially took over, G.E.'s plan to acquire Honeywell International imploded, and the share price dropped 19.3 percent, to $39.65. And, to keep the comparison apples to apples, it closed at $37.35 on Dec. 4, down an additional 5.8 percent. But analysts, perhaps mindful that Mr. Immelt cannot be blamed for the battering of G.E.'s insurance and aircraft-related businesses in the aftermath of Sept. 11, remain in his fan club. According to Thomson Financial/First Call, analysts have buy recommendations on the stocks of all three of the companies. But their strongest buy is still on G.E. Claudia H. Deutsch</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/14/business/baxter-faces-suit-on-dialysis-deaths.html?ref=3mcompany">Baxter Faces Suit On Dialysis Deaths<date>Published: November 14, 2001</date><text>CHICAGO, Nov. 13— Baxter International Inc. was sued here today on behalf of patients who used its kidney dialysis machines, which are blamed in dozens of deaths worldwide. The lawsuit, which seeks to be declared a class action, accuses Baxter, a medical products maker based in Deerfield, Ill., of carelessness and negligence and says that at least 56 people who used the dialysis machines are reported to have died. ''We believe that the total number of deaths around the world will be much higher in light of the inquiries our firm has received,'' the lawyer, Kenneth Moll, said in a statement as the suit was filed in Cook County Circuit Court. Other defendants are the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, maker of the processing fluid that Baxter said mistakenly remained in the filters after they were manufactured at a Baxter plant in Sweden, and the Baxter Healthcare Corporation, a Baxter unit. The Food and Drug Administration said last week that health authorities were investigating 53 reported deaths in seven countries this summer and fall in connection with the Baxter kidney dialysis filters, which have since been recalled. An F.D.A. spokeswoman did not immediately return a phone call today regarding the latest total. The agency has said some of the deaths being looked at were apparently not linked to the filters. The filters have been linked to four American deaths --two in Austin, Tex., and two in Kearney, Neb. Baxter said on Nov. 5 that chemical residue in its recalled filters appeared to have played a role in ''many'' of the reported deaths. Besides discontinuing the product and idling two plants, it said it was setting aside $100 million to $150 million for litigation and related expenses.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/23/business/3m-s-profit-declines-21-in-last-period.html?ref=3mcompany">3M's Profit Declines 21% In Last Period<date>Published: October 23, 2001</date><text>ST. PAUL, Oct. 22— The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that its third-quarter earnings fell 21 percent and that its fourth-quarter profit might be less than some estimates. 3M, which makes products ranging from Post-It Notes to electronic circuitry, said its net income fell to $394 million, or 99 cents a share, from $499 million, or $1.25 a share, in the quarter a year ago. Sales fell 7.1 percent, to $3.97 billion. Excluding costs related to work force cuts and depreciation, profit in the latest quarter would have been $1.10 a share, the company said. Analysts had expected 3M to earn $1.09 a share, according to Thomson Financial/First Call. The company's chief executive, James McNerney, who was hired late last year, has been introducing the cost-cutting and efficiency programs he learned at General Electric. 3M has shed about 4,200 of the 5,000 jobs it has said it will eliminate and plans to cut more in coming months to cope with slowing sales, Robert Burgstahler, the chief financial officer, said during a conference call. ''3M has a new focus on costs and working capital,'' said Lewis Johnson, an analyst at T. Rowe Price. ''This will benefit the company when the economic conditions normalize.'' Sales of health care products, which account for about 15 percent of annual sales, rose 9.4 percent in the quarter. The business includes dental and pharmaceutical products and health-information systems, like computers that manage patient records. Sales fell at all of 3M's other businesses including transportation and consumer products. Especially hard hit was the electronic and telecommunications business, where sales fell 21 percent, and profit 60 percent. Mr. Burgstahler said the drop in the company's total profitability from last quarter to this quarter was solely attributable to the telecommunications and electronic business. Shares of the company, based in St. Paul, rose $5.22, or 5.1 percent, to $107.39. Fourth-quarter profit, before certain expenses, will fall to 95 cents to $1.05 a share from $1.12 in the period a year earlier, 3M said. The company is expected to have profit of $1.05 a share, according to First Call.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/24/business/in-a-cost-cutting-move-3m-says-it-will-eliminate-5000-jobs.html?ref=3mcompany">In a Cost-Cutting Move, 3M Says It Will Eliminate 5,000 Jobs<date>Published: April 24, 2001</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, reacting to the slowing economy with a pre-emptive strike, said yesterday that it would cut 7 percent of its work force, or about 5,000 jobs.''In this uncertain environment, we are focused on the things that we can control,'' W. James McNerney Jr., 3M's chief executive, told analysts yesterday.The cuts are not desperation moves. Although 3M's United States sales have slowed, its international sales remain strong. And its first-quarter earnings, although below its target of double-digit earnings growth, were exactly what analysts had predicted.Many analysts say the job cuts are as much a reflection of Mr. McNerney's impatience with 3M's somewhat leisurely culture as it is a reaction to slowing sales.''In a word, McNerney is bringing speed,'' said Mark R. Gulley, an analyst with Banc of America Securities.The job cuts are just the most visible change that Mr. McNerney has made since he became the first outsider to run 3M in the company's 98 years.Mr. McNerney, who spent most of his career at the General Electric Company, was one of the runners-up to succeed the G.E. chairman, John F. Welch Jr. When 3M, which is based in St. Paul, announced in December that it had hired Mr. McNerney, its shares shot up, as its investors bet that Mr. McNerney would apply G.E.'s much-vaunted productivity programs to the more leisurely paced 3M. He has not disappointed them. In February, about 100 of 3M's top executives were trained in Six Sigma, the highly complex statistical quality-control system that has saved G.E. billions of dollars. So far this year, 3M has embarked on 35 Six Sigma projects, and 100 more are already scheduled.Mr. McNerney has also promised investors that he will cut procurement costs by 2 percent this year, in good part by consolidating suppliers and moving more of 3M's procurement onto the Web. He has already saved $16 million a year by reducing the types of packages the businesses use.First-quarter results seemed to reflect some of the belt-tightening. Although high energy costs and the strong dollar took a toll of 11 cents a share on 3M's earnings last quarter, the company still earned $1.16 a share excluding extraordinary charges. That was up 3 cents a share from the first quarter of last year, which also had charges. Net income was $453 million, or $1.13 a share, compared with $487 million, or $1.21 a share, in the period of 2000. Sales were up 2.3 percent, to $4.17 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/18/business/company-news-3m-says-it-will-cut-many-jobs-through-attrition.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M SAYS IT WILL CUT MANY JOBS THROUGH ATTRITION<date>Published: January 18, 2001</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it planned to improve profits by controlling costs through ''significant'' work-force attrition, but news of disappointing fourth-quarter earnings sent its stock tumbling. 3M said it would report net income of $447 million, or $1.12 a share, for the quarter, 8 cents a share less than analysts had expected; it is scheduled to issue a full fourth-quarter earnings report next week. Its stock fell $3.50, to $110.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/10/business/private-sector-nice-bounty-for-two-big-heads.html?ref=3mcompany">PRIVATE SECTOR; Nice Bounty For Two Big Heads<date>Published: December 10, 2000</date><text>When Jack Welch finally anointed a successor on Nov. 27, people at General Electric were not the only ones to sigh in relief. ''By then I didn't have any fingernails left,'' said Gerard R. Roche, senior chairman of Heidrick &amp; Struggles International, the executive recruiters.Far more than his nails were at stake. For months, Mr. Roche had been on retainer to find new leaders for both 3M and Home Depot. His firm stood to make a flat fee of more than $1 million for each search. At least 20 percent of the take would go to Mr. Roche, and probably, considering his seniority, a lot more.W. James McNerney Jr. and Robert L. Nardelli, two of the three executives on Mr. Welch's short list, seemed perfect for the jobs. ''I'd tell the boards, 'If I was in your shoes I'd keep my powder dry, and see how things shake out'' at G.E., Mr. Roche said.So, when Mr. Welch chose Jeffrey R. Immelt as his successor, Mr. Roche pounced. ''We knew Lucent and others would be after them, and we had to move at warp speed,'' he said.Last Sunday, it all came together: Mr. McNerney met with 3M's search committee in Chicago, Mr. Nardelli with Home Depot's in Atlanta. By Tuesday, both had been offered, and had accepted, their new jobs.So, isn't it time for Mr. Roche, 69, to plan his next move, too -- like, maybe, retirement? ''Hey, I'm five years younger than Alan Greenspan,'' he said. ''Sure, I'd like to step back a little. But I still don't know what I'm going to do when I grow up.'' Claudia H. Deutsch</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/05/business/3m-to-select-ge-executive-as-next-chief.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Select G.E. Executive As Next Chief<date>Published: December 05, 2000</date><text>For the first time in its history, Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing has reached outside its ranks for a chief, hiring W. James McNerney Jr. from General Electric to be its chairman and chief executive.The appointment, which 3M is expected to announce today, held little shock value on Wall Street. Livio D. DeSimone, 3M's chairman since 1991, will be 65 in July, and 3M's board has been prospecting for a replacement for several months. Although six 3M insiders were said to be on a short list of candidates, analysts had speculated that the company would go outside.That speculation hit fever pitch last week, when G.E. ended its own much publicized succession race. The company named Jeffrey R. Immelt to succeed John F. Welch Jr. when Mr. Welch retires next year. Mr. Welch, in making that announcement, said that he expected the also-rans in that contest to be quickly spirited away to head other companies. Mr. McNerney, 51, head of GE Aircraft Engines, was one of them; the other, Robert L. Nardelli, 52, head of GE Power Systems, is expected to announce a new job this week.Analysts say 3M could use an infusion of G.E. dynamism. ''3M has good margins and a good product line that is getting better, but they need an injection of intensity,'' said Jack L. Kelly, who follows 3M for Goldman, Sachs. ''G.E. has an 'in your face, perform or you're out' culture, and anyone who flourished in that culture will know how to raise the bar for performance at 3M.''Actually, 3M has reinvigorated itself of late. Until the middle of last year, the company was floundering badly. It had missed earnings estimates in three of six quarters, it was suffering from the economic downturn in Asia, and many of its products were selling in highly cyclical industries like construction.Since mid-1999, though, the company, based in St. Paul, has cut costs and shifted its focus to high-growth markets. Products like fiber optics, abrasives used in the manufacturing of semiconductors and drugs that bolster immune systems already make up about 23 percent of its sales, and 3M has promised to raise that percentage to 35 percent by 2003. In September, Mr. DeSimone told analysts that 3M's earnings would grow at least 12 percent annually through 2003.The company's stock has held its own through the market's gyrations. Although 3M has tried mightily to position itself as a high-technology stock, it has generally traded in line with makers of specialty chemicals.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/15/business/company-news-minnesota-mining-to-buy-microtouch-for-160-million.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; MINNESOTA MINING TO BUY MICROTOUCH FOR $160 MILLION<date>Published: November 15, 2000</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company agreed to buy MicroTouch Systems Inc. for about $160 million in cash, or $21 a share, to expand its line of touch screens used in automated teller machines and kiosks. The price is a 41 percent premium on MicroTouch's closing price Monday. MicroTouch has no long-term debt, the company said. Minnesota Mining is based in St. Paul. MicroTouch is based in Methuen, Mass.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/business/minnesota-mining-quarterly-profit-up-8.html?ref=3mcompany">Minnesota Mining Quarterly Profit Up 8%<date>Published: October 24, 2000</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that its third-quarter profit rose 8 percent on increased sales of telecommunications and computer equipment in Asia.Profit from operations rose to $499 million, or $1.25 a share, compared with $462 million, or $1.14 a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales rose 6.4 percent, to $4.25 billion from $4 billion.Analysts had expected the company to earn $1.24 a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.3M had a third-quarter charge of $118 million related to a change in how it makes Scotchgard products and a $119 million gain on the sale of assets. The company said the items offset each other. In the period a year earlier, a charge for litigation, a gain related to divestitures and a gain related to a restructuring estimate change resulted in net income of $459 million, or $1.13 a share.Shares rose $2.56,to $89.81, after the company said profits in the fourth quarter and next year would meet estimates. That eased concern among investors, who have seen companies like Lucent Technologies, Motorola and others lower forecasts.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/business/company-news-minnesota-mining-will-buy-electronics-maker.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; MINNESOTA MINING WILL BUY ELECTRONICS MAKER<date>Published: October 04, 2000</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the electronic-connector maker Robinson Nugent Inc. for $115 million in stock and assumed debt to add Internet router connectors to its Interconnect business. Robinson shareholders will get $19 in 3M stock for each share, a 14 percent premium over Monday's closing price. Robinson had $93 million in sales in its fiscal year that ended in June. Shares of 3M, which is based in St. Paul, rose $2.31 to $94. Shares of Robinson, based in New Albany, Ind., rose $1.69 to $18.31.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/business/company-news-minnesota-mining-bringing-scotchgard-back-to-market.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; MINNESOTA MINING BRINGING SCOTCHGARD BACK TO MARKET<date>Published: September 23, 2000</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company expects to have some reformulated Scotchgard products on the market by December to replace products that were discontinued earlier this year because of health concerns. Consumer products to protect carpeting will be the first replacements coming to market, with others to follow, said Charles Reich, executive vice president for the company's specialty material markets business. The company announced in May that it would discontinue some Scotchgard products after it found that the compound tended to persist in the environment, had a strong tendency to accumulate in animal and human tissues, and could pose an undetermined risk to humans. The affected home-care products included Scotchgard protector for fabric, upholstery, rugs and leather. Affected commercial products included those for carpets and upholstery.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/business/company-news-3m-says-it-expects-to-meet-second-half-earnings-goals.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M SAYS IT EXPECTS TO MEET SECOND-HALF EARNINGS GOALS<date>Published: September 22, 2000</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company outlined aggressive growth targets for the next three years yesterday and said it expected to reach its earnings goals for the second half of this year, setting off a 6 percent rise in the value of its shares. The company, which makes Post-It Notes and Scotch Tape, said it expected annual sales growth of about 11 percent and per-share earnings growth of about 13 percent over the next three years. Shares of 3M were up $4.69, to $86.44. Analysts had expected earnings of $1.24 a share in the third quarter and $1.20 a share in the fourth quarter, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/24/business/company-news-3m-plans-to-make-three-acquisitions-by-october.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M PLANS TO MAKE THREE ACQUISITIONS BY OCTOBER<date>Published: August 24, 2000</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, whose 50,000 products include Post-It Notes and electronic circuitry, said yesterday that it planned to make three acquisitions by October that would add $400 million a year in sales by 2003. The unnamed companies make electronics and telecommunications products, said Harry C. Andrews, executive vice president of electro and communications markets. Minnesota Mining, which was hurt by the recession that swept Asia in late 1998, wants to add sales that will help it to post more consistent earnings growth.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/25/garden/tear-stains-on-the-easy-chair-as-scotchgard-fades-away.html?ref=3mcompany">Tear Stains on the Easy Chair, as Scotchgard Fades Away<date>Published: May 25, 2000</date><text>WHILE experts argue the efficacy of building America's space-based Strategic Defense Initiative, here on Earth one of the nation's most trusted defense systems will, by year's end, be dismantled.Scotchgard, the soil-retardant and stain-repellent spray made by the 3M Company of St. Paul, is being ''phased out,'' the company announced on May 16, because of environmental concerns about a chemical used to make it, perfluorooctanyl. The same stuff that makes it easy to lift a blob of chip dip off a carpet is, it turns out, harder to get off the planet. Scotchgard stain prevention products do not decompose.As Prof. Ned Brainard, played by Fred MacMurray in the 1961 movie ''The Absent-Minded Professor,'' said of flying rubber, or Flubber, ''It's a substance whose behavior is disturbingly nonclassical.''The company's move to discontinue Scotchgard was voluntary. (Manufacture will not stop for some months, 3M says; availability will depend on store inventories.) But the Environmental Protection Agency said on May 18 that it had been poised to remove it from the market if the company had not taken action.''We would advise consumers to adopt a precautionary approach,'' said Stephen Johnson, deputy assistant administrator for the agency's office of prevention, pesticides and toxic substances. ''Given the agency's concerns about long-term exposure, people should exercise judgment as to whether to use the materials.''The dirt of the ages appears to have won a round. Though there are other protective products, including DuPont's Stainmaster, the Scotchgard announcement left many vendors and consumers unprotected from the vision of a future without soil retardance or stain repellence in clothing, home furnishings and floor coverings: three huge textile categories (with an estimated $45 billion in annual sales, according to the Census Bureau) in which the product is ubiquitous.With an air of national emergency, Heloise, the syndicated household-hints columnist, was scrambled like a fighter pilot by the ''Today'' show for a not very reassuring appearance two days after 3M's news.''I looked around my hotel room that night,'' she said, reached on a car telephone in Texas. ''Carpeting, drapes, bedspread -- probably all fabric protected.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/19/business/epa-says-it-pressed-3m-for-action-on-scotchgard-chemical.html?ref=3mcompany">E.P.A. Says It Pressed 3M for Action on Scotchgard Chemical<date>Published: May 19, 2000</date><text>The Environmental Protection Agency said today that it had pressed Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing to come up with a solution after the company's own tests had shown that a chemical compound used in Scotchgard and an array of household products could pose a risk to human health and the environment.The E.P.A. account differs from that of 3M, which said on Monday that it had voluntarily decided to stop making the chemical used in Scotchgard and many other products by the end of the year because the tests showed that the chemical compounds failed to decompose in the environment. Officials of 3M say they have no evidence that the chemicals pose a long-term threat to human health.While the E.P.A. said it did not see an immediate safety risk for consumers using products now on the market, agency officials said that if 3M had not acted they would have taken steps to remove the product from the market. The officials said they grew concerned about potential long-term health risks to humans after a 3M study showed that the chemical, perfluorooctanyl sulfonate, lingered for years in human blood and animal tissue and that high doses were known to kill laboratory rats.''The results raised a number of concerns,'' said Stephen Johnson, who works in the office of prevention, pesticides and toxic substances at the E.P.A. ''What it suggests to us is that there are potentially long-term consequences. But we don't have evidence it is unsafe now.''Officials of 3M, however, say they are absolutely confident that their products are safe, and that there are no long-term consequences to human health.''This isn't a health issue now, and it won't be a health issue,'' said Larry Zobel, the medical director at 3M., which is based in St. Paul.''To the question of whether this builds up in humans, it would have to be a long time, like hundreds of thousands of years, to be a threat,'' he said.Many scientists have praised 3M's decision to stop production of perfluorooctanyl and related chemicals.''The real issue is this stuff accumulates, and if it accumulates in the ecosystem, you have to be worried about that because it could be trouble,'' said John Doull, a retired professor of clinical toxicology at the University of Kansas Medical Center in Kansas City. ''No chemical is totally innocuous, and it seems inconceivable that anything that accumulates would not eventually become toxic.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/17/us/3m-says-it-will-stop-making-scotchgard.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Says It Will Stop Making Scotchgard<date>Published: May 17, 2000</date><text>The 3M Company, the giant consumer products company, said today that it would stop making many of its well-known Scotchgard products after tests showed that the chemical compounds used to make the products linger in the environment and in humans for years.Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing said that Scotchgard, a spray that protects clothing, fabrics, upholstery and carpets from stains and other damage, was safe and that the chemical compounds pose no health risk to humans. But the company also said the compounds do not easily decompose and therefore are not environmentally friendly.''These products have been safely used for 40 years and they continue to be safe,'' said William E. Coyne, the head of research and development at 3M, which is based in St. Paul. ''But the best decision we can make now is to stop adding to the environment. This is a corporate responsibility issue. This product does not decompose, it's inert -- it's persistent; it's like a rock.''The company, whose products include Scotch tape and Post-it notes, said the Scotchgard line represented about $300 million a year in sales, or about 2 percent of the company's $16 billion in annual revenues. The company, which has 71,000 employees worldwide, said it did not expect to lay off any of the 1,500 workers with jobs tied to Scotchgard.The company said that most Scotchgard products, primarily fabric and upholstery protectors, would be phased out by the end of the year. Some Scotchgard fabric and rug cleaners are unaffected.The company, which is also known as the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, said that it discovered in 1998 that the chemical compound used to make many Scotchgard products, perfluorooctanyl, was pervasive; it persisted for years in the environment, and could even be found in human blood, at very low levels.The company said the presence of the chemical compound in human blood at low levels was not harmful, but Mr. Coyne said that ''with extremely high doses you are going to see effects.'' He also said the production of the compounds had very little effect on the environment.Officials of 3M said they ran exhaustive tests on animals and humans and found no adverse health effects. But because the compounds were persistent in the environment and in human blood, the company said it alerted regulators and began working to come up with alternative compounds.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/26/business/shares-of-3m-are-hammered-despite-19-gain-in-profit.html?ref=3mcompany">Shares of 3M Are Hammered Despite 19% Gain in Profit<date>Published: April 26, 2000</date><text>Shares of Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing fell 3.7 percent today after the company said that its profit in 2000 might fall short of analysts' highest estimates.Although 3M's first-quarter profit rose 19 percent, beating expectations, marketing expenses are expected to offset a one-time gain.''Now you've got management putting a damper on expectations,'' said Alex Henderson, an analyst at Prudential Securities. The extra profit ''everyone was counting on isn't any good.''The stock fell $3.5625, to $93.8125. It had risen 20 percent the last year.The company said in a conference call that full-year per-share profit would rise 12 percent to 14 percent compared with earnings in 1999, when it earned $4.21 a share from continuing operations. The company is expected to earn $4.68, the average estimate of analysts polled by First Call/Thomson Financial. Estimates ranged from $4.60 to $4.80 a share.In the first quarter, profit from operations increased to $455.4 million, or $1.13 a share, compared with $384 million, or 95 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 7.3 percent, to $4.05 billion from $3.78 billion. Wall Street estimates were $1.08 a share.3M had a first-quarter gain of $31.6 million, or 8 cents a share, from ending a marketing agreement with Hoechst of Germany, which made net income $487 million, or $1.21 a share.That gain will be offset by marketing spending expected in the rest of the year, the company said.It receives more than half its revenue outside the United States and has benefited from rebounding economies in Asia and Europe. It is also selling more industrial products in the United States.Robert J. Burgstahler, the company's chief financial officer, said the company expected to earn $3.60 a share -- ''at the very top end'' -- for the rest of the year. Added to the $1.21 a share it earned in the first quarter, per-share profit in 2000 would be $4.81 at most.''That range today reflects some of these concerns,'' Mr. Burgstahler said. ''We have been overcoming all of those and are delivering.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/27/business/3m-reports-a-28-rise-in-quarterly-earnings.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Reports a 28% Rise in Quarterly Earnings<date>Published: January 27, 2000</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, maker of Scotch tape and Post-It notes, reported a 28 percent rise in fourth-quarter profits today, driven by strong sales of new products and a rebound in Asia.For the quarter ended Dec. 31, 3M earned $444 million, or $1.10 a share, compared with $348 million, or 86 cents a share, excluding a nonrecurring revamping charge taken in the final quarter of 1998.The earnings easily beat analysts' expectations of $1.02 a share, as reported by First Call/Thomson Financial. 3M's stock rose $4.9375, to $96.3125 on the New York Stock Exchange.Quarterly revenue rose 6 percent, to $4.02 billion, from $3.79 billion.''We're pleased with our record fourth-quarter and full-year 1999 results,'' said L. D. DeSimone, chairman and chief executive. ''Our volume growth increased during each quarter of 1999, and we enter 2000 with good momentum.''This was the third consecutive quarterly earnings increase for 3M after six quarters of falling earnings.Mr. DeSimone said 3M got 34 percent of its 1999 sales from products new to the market within the last four years, including microflex electronic circuits used in printers and computers, special cleaning cloths and pharmaceutical products.3M said sales and profit growth were particularly strong in Asia.''Our people did an expert job navigating through difficult challenges in Asia during 1998, and we emerged in 1999 with even stronger customer relationships and competitive positions,'' Mr. DeSimone said.For the full year, 3M earned $1.71 billion, or $4.21 a share, compared with $1.53 billion, or $3.74 a share, excluding restructuring in 1998. Revenue in 1999 rose to $15.66 billion, from $15.02 billion.Including revamping charges, 1998 fourth-quarter net income was $211 million, or 52 cents a share, and full-year net income was $1.18 billion, or $2.88 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/30/business/company-news-3m-buys-polaroid-s-anti-glare-screen-business.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M BUYS POLAROID'S ANTI-GLARE SCREEN BUSINESS<date>Published: November 30, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it had bought the Polaroid Corporation's anti-glare computer-filter business, adding to 3M's No. 1 position in the world market for anti-glare screens. Terms were not disclosed. Polaroid, the world's biggest instant photography company, also will sell computer-filter parts to 3M and allow 3M to use the Polaroid name for marketing. The sale is part of Polaroid's effort to increase its share price by selling some businesses that are not directly related to the main business of instant photography. Polaroid shares rose 6.25 cents, to $19.375, in New York Stock Exchange trading, while 3M, based in St. Paul, fell 56.25 cents, to $94.9375.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/26/business/3m-reports-its-profits-for-the-third-quarter-were-18-higher.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Reports Its Profits for the Third Quarter Were 18% Higher<date>Published: October 26, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, the maker of Post-It notes and Scotch tape, said today that its third-quarter earnings rose 18 percent, more than expected, as sales rose and the cost of raw materials fell.Profit from operations rose to $462 million, or $1.14 a diluted share, compared with $392 million, or 97 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Sales rose 6.1 percent, to $4 billion.Analysts had expected 3M to earn $1.06 a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks company earnings.Earnings have now increased for two consecutive quarters after sliding the previous six. Sales in Asia buoyed profit by rising more than 30 percent as the region's economy recovered. In the United States, sales rose 3 percent, led by industrial and safety products and office supplies.''They're producing good results, they are taking costs out, and that's what you like to see,'' said Rich Turgeon, an analyst at Society Asset Management, which owned more than 1.5 million 3M shares in June.The company expects to meet analyst estimates of $1 a share for fourth-quarter earnings, Giulio Agostini, the chief financial officer, said in a conference call. The company also expects to reach its per-share earnings growth target of about 10 percent in 2000, he said.Shares of 3M, based in St. Paul, rose 25 cents, to $92.8125. They have gained 30 percent this year.The company took a series of gains and charges in the quarter. A $73 million pretax charge stems from a Federal jury's ruling that 3M violated antitrust laws involving its tape business. The company also had pretax gains totaling $69 million related to asset sales and to change the estimated cost of a restructuring. The company did not provide after-tax figures for the gains and charge.The actions resulted in net income of $459 million, or $1.13 a share, in the quarter. In the period a year earlier, a charge of $214 million, or 53 cents a share, for job cuts and plant closings resulted in net income of $178 million, or 44 cents a share.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/15/business/company-news-3m-to-buy-hoechst-s-stake-in-dyneon-joint-venture.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M TO BUY HOECHST'S STAKE IN DYNEON JOINT VENTURE<date>Published: October 15, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, which makes thousands of consumer products, including Scotch brand tape, said yesterday that it would buy the stake held by Hoechst A.G. in their joint venture fluoropolymer business, Dyneon. Hoechst, Germany's largest drug maker, owns a 46 percent stake in Dyneon and said it expected the sale would generate proceeds of $300 million for its Celanese A.G. unit, which is being spun off to shareholders this month. Dyneon has more than 700 employees at five sites in the United States, Germany and Belgium. In 1998, it had sales of $350 million.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/06/business/the-handwriting-on-the-post-it-note-image-and-returns-suffer-at-3m.html?ref=3mcompany">The Handwriting On the Post-It Note; Image and Returns Suffer at 3M<date>Published: July 06, 1999</date><text>Here at the technology center of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Corporation, scientists are tinkering with stickier adhesives, longer-lasting abrasives, glare-free reflective signs -- indeed, with improvements on virtually every product, from the esoteric to the mundane, that 3M makes.The road to product nirvana, the scientists say, is a hot new technology called microreplication, a way to place thousands of identical microscopic shapes on the surfaces of all kinds of materials, from sandpaper to flat-panel computer screens.''Microreplication is reinventing our core businesses,'' said Robert S. Finocchiaro, a 3M technical director, who runs the microreplication project.But the mood is a bit more somber across the street, where the corporate types are. Try as they will, they cannot shake Wall Street's perception of 3M as a boring, low-technology drone whose glory days ended with Scotch tape and Post-it notes.''You put it next to a machinery company, and the stock performance looks the same,'' said B. Alexander Henderson, who follows 3M for Prudential Securities Research.The problem is not just image, though; it is performance. For two years, 3M has consistently missed earnings estimates, and its revenues, half of them from foreign shores, have been stuck at $15 billion. Its shares, which sold near $100 in July 1997, drifted to $70 by April. The stock has rebounded some, closing at $88.875 on Friday, but many 3M watchers say the rise comes from investor disaffection with Internet stocks and hopes for an Asian economic recovery, not from confidence in 3M's management.''They just don't have the killer instinct when it comes to financial returns,'' said Jack L. Kelly, who follows 3M for Goldman, Sachs.Is 3M, once a darling of Wall Street, now just another badly managed also-ran? Or is it still a new-product machine that had a bad case of the hiccups last year?Critics of the company have accused Livio D. DeSimone, 3M's chairman since 1991, of everything from losing 3M's innovative touch to refusing to cut costs to mismanaging inventories to sticking with humdrum products too long. Some have even put pressure on the board to ask Mr. DeSimone, who turns 63 this month, to step down before the mandatory retirement age of 65.''He knows an incredible amount about product, but he just doesn't have a good enough grip on daily operations,'' one analyst said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/01/business/minnesota-mining-says-profit-declined.html?ref=3mcompany">Minnesota Mining Says Profit Declined<date>Published: May 01, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, the maker of more than 50,000 industrial and consumer products, said today that its first-quarter profit fell 4 percent despite a rebound in sales in Asia.Net income fell to $384 million, or 95 cents a share, from $400 million, or 98 cents, a year earlier. The per-share results were better than the average forecast of 91 cents of analysts polled by the First Call Corporation, which tracks corporate earnings. The company's shares rose $3.375, to $89.Minnesota Mining, whose products range from Scotch tape to Nexcare bandages to industrial abrasives, said revenue rose 2.2 percent, to $3.78 billion from $3.7 billion. The company, which gets half its sales overseas, had its best performance in five quarters in the Asia Pacific region. Sales also rose in the United States, though just 2 percent at a time when the economy surged.In Asia Pacific, sales volume rose 7 percent. Optimism for a turnaround in the region has fueled industrial stocks for the last two weeks.The company's shares, which touched a two-year low of $65.625 on Sept. 1, have weakened in the last 18 months on concerns about Asia's economies and six straight quarters of year-to-year profit declines for the company.But since the start of the year, its shares have risen 25 percent, helped by this month's gains by industrial stocks.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/16/business/company-news-terumo-says-it-will-buy-3m-s-cardiovascular-division.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; TERUMO SAYS IT WILL BUY 3M'S CARDIOVASCULAR DIVISION<date>Published: April 16, 1999</date><text>The Terumo Corporation, Japan's largest medical equipment supplier, said yesterday that it would buy the cardiovascular division of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company for more than $100 million in cash. Terumo did not disclose the acquisition terms. The acquisition of 3M's cardiovascular business, which has annual sales of $100 million, will enable Terumo to supply all the equipment needed for open heart surgery. 3M, the maker of more than 50,000 industrial and consumer products, is undergoing a reorganization. Shares of 3M rose $4, to $79.25.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/01/28/business/3m-to-close-plant.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Close Plant<date>Published: January 28, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that it was closing a plant in West Deptford, N.J., and moving the factory's operations to southern Minnesota. The West Deptford plant makes components for 3M's electrical products division and construction and home improvement division. It employs 94 people. The company said 60 to 70 jobs would be added to the 3M plant in New Ulm.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/01/26/business/3m-reports-drop-of-4.9-in-profit.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Reports Drop Of 4.9% in Profit<date>Published: January 26, 1999</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, the maker of more than 50,000 industrial and consumer products, said today that its fourth-quarter profits fell 4.9 percent.Fourth-quarter earnings before a charge fell to $348 million, or 86 cents a diluted share, from $366 million, or 89 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of 80 cents a share.Revenue rose 1.9 percent, to $3.79 billion from $3.71 billion. 3M, widely viewed as an economic bellwether because of the diversity of its products and regional markets, gets more than half its revenue overseas. United States revenue rose 1 percent, to $1.77 billion. Overseas revenue rose 3 percent, to $2.01 billion.In the fourth quarter, the company took a charge of $99 million for production improvements and $38 million to refinance the debt of its employee stock-ownership plan. The charges resulted in net income of $211 million, or 52 cents a share. There were no gains or charges in the period a year earlier.Shares of 3M rose $3.8125 today, to $75.125.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/17/business/minnesota-mining-expects-earnings-decline-of-10.html?ref=3mcompany">Minnesota Mining Expects Earnings Decline of 10%<date>Published: December 17, 1998</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, one of the nation's industrial and manufacturing giants, warned today that slumping global sales and a slowdown at home would probably cut fourth-quarter earnings 10 percent from the comparable quarter a year earlier.The announcement by 3M, which makes Post-it notes, Scotch tapes and consumer health products, sent the company's shares down $2.375 each, to $71.375, and is just the latest jolt to hit some of the nation's largest corporations.Since late November, share prices have been sliding after a sharp run-up in October, and that selloff has been intensified by unnerving news from Washington and the onset of the season when American companies traditionally warn Wall Street that they may not meet expectations in their next quarterly report.The 3M announcement, which encouraged Wall Street to lower its already bleak expectations, lengthens the list of ailing companies that constitute the widely followed Dow Jones industrial average. Of the 30 companies in that stock average, at least 8 have issued earnings warnings this month, and several others have announced reorganization plans or huge layoffs.The list, of course, is a Who's Who in corporate America: Boeing; Coca-Cola; Merck; Sears, Roebuck; Union Carbide, and Caterpillar. Boeing will cut 20,000 jobs in the next year; Citigroup -- another Dow component -- also issued bad news on Tuesday, saying it would cut 10,400 jobs, or about 6 percent of its work force. The stock of a ninth company, Procter &amp; Gamble, fell sharply last week after it said growth in the number of products sold would not meet expectations in the quarter.Those announcements have caused the Dow to fall 5 percent from its all-time high over the last few weeks and, for a broader group of investors, the parade of warnings has heightened concerns that the nation's best and brightest companies continue to suffer from global economic turmoil and even threatened to topple a seven-year-long bull market in the United States.''We're going through the same thing we've gone through in the last few quarters: management is saying things aren't as good as they used to be,'' said Marshall Acuff, the chief market strategist at Salomon Smith Barney. ''There are increasing pressures on profit margins for more and more companies, and that pressure is intensifying.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/10/23/business/3m-profit-declined-9.2-in-third-quarter.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Profit Declined 9.2% in Third Quarter<date>Published: October 23, 1998</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, better known as 3M, said yesterday that its third-quarter profit fell by 9.2 percent amid slower economic growth, both in the United States and abroad.The company, which makes products ranging from Post-It Notes and Scotch tape to flexible computer circuits and drug delivery systems, said it earned $392 million, or 97 cents a share, in the third quarter, down from $432 million, or $1.03 a share, a year earlier. The results were slightly below the expectations of Wall Street analysts, and shares of 3M tumbled $2.8125, to close at $81.4375 on the New York Stock Exchange.3M, which derives more than half its sales from outside the United States and 18 percent from Asia, said difficult economic conditions worldwide hurt its results in the quarter.Worldwide sales totaled $3.77 billion in the quarter, down 1.6 percent from $3.82 billion a year earlier.Outside of the United States, 3M said sales rose by 5 percent in local currency terms, but because of the strength of the dollar, sales in dollar terms fell by 2 percent, to $1.87 billion. To adjust to slower worldwide growth, 3M has announced a cost-cutting plan that includes closing plants, discontinuing certain product lines and eliminating 4,500 jobs by the end of 1999.''While we are facing a challenging economic environment, we expect to see increasing benefits from our cost-reduction efforts,'' said L. D. DeSimone, 3M's chairman. ''We are monitoring global economic conditions closely, and we will make further adjustments as necessary.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/28/business/company-news-3m-says-it-will-cut-500-more-jobs-by-the-end-of-1999.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M SAYS IT WILL CUT 500 MORE JOBS BY THE END OF 1999<date>Published: August 28, 1998</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it would eliminate 4,500 jobs by the end of next year, 500 more than the company announced in late July. The job cuts, which will reduce the 3M work force to about 71,000, are aimed at improving productivity. The company, based in Maplewood, Minn., also announced previously that it would consolidate some manufacturing operations worldwide. The company announced the additional 500 job cuts yesterday during a meeting with financial analysts. 3M expects to take a pretax charge of as much as $500 million for the revamping. The company's shares closed at $73.8125, down 31.25 cents, after hitting a 52-week low earlier in the day.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/24/business/3m-reports-decline-in-its-quarterly-profit.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Reports Decline in Its Quarterly Profit<date>Published: July 24, 1998</date><text>Hurt by the strong dollar and weak Asian economies, the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that quarterly profit declined 7.7 percent and that it planned to cut at least 3,500 jobs.The company, which makes consumer and industrial products, said most of the jobs, which will amount to 4.6 percent of its labor force, will be eliminated through attrition within the next two years.Net income in the second quarter fell to $386 million, or 94 cents a diluted share, from $418 million, or 99 cents a share, a year ago. Still, the profit exceeded the figure of 92 cents a share that analysts had expected.The company's stock declined $2.1875, to $78.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.Sales fell 1.2 percent, to $3.77 billion, from $3.82 billion.The Asian economic turmoil caused the 3M Company to fall below its earnings targets in the region. Foreign-currency translation cut its profit about 12 percent, making the period the 11th consecutive quarter in which currencies hurt earnings. The strong dollar cut sales about 5 percent.There is ''clearly a lot of frustration with 3M stock performance and earnings relative to expectations,'' Alex Henderson, an analyst at Prudential Securities Inc., told executives of the 3M Company during a conference call today.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/16/business/3m-to-trail-forecasts-and-its-shares-fall.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Trail Forecasts, and Its Shares Fall<date>Published: June 16, 1998</date><text>The stock of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company skidded $5.8125, or 6.7 percent, to $81 in active trading today, after the company said its second-quarter earnings would be below estimates.Earnings are likely to be between 90 cents and 94 cents a diluted share, the company said, short of both the figure of 99 cents a year earlier and an analysts' consensus of $1.05 from the First Call Corporation.Attributing the earnings pressure to weak Asian economies, modest domestic growth and the strengthening dollar, L. D. DeSimone, chairman and chief executive of 3M, said in an interview that the company might look into layoffs to cut costs. 3M will explore a ''whole series of cost cuts,'' he said.Mr. DeSimone noted that employment had gone down to about 75,000 employees from about 90,000 in the early 1990's. ''We're doing a lot more business now than then,'' he said. ''We've got 15,000 to 17,000 fewer people. It's something you keep working on.''Mark R. Gulley, an analyst with Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, said in a research note last week, in which he downgraded 3M to neutral from outperform, that growth in productivity was slipping.''Head count was essentially flat in 1Q '98 but needs to decline to meet 8 percent per annum productivity goals,'' Mr. Gulley wrote.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/04/29/business/3m-s-earnings-decrease-by-2.html?ref=3mcompany">3M's Earnings Decrease by 2%<date>Published: April 29, 1998</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that its first-quarter earnings had dropped 2 percent because of Asian economic problems and the strong dollar.The company, which makes Scotch brand tape, scouring pads and industrial and electronics products, said it earned $400 million, or 98 cents a diluted share, in the three months that ended March 31, compared with $410 million, or 97 cents a share, a year earlier. That was a penny a share below Wall Street's expectations, according to a survey of analysts by the First Call Corporation.''Earnings benefited from solid international growth and effective cost controls worldwide, while the strength of the U.S. dollar and the economic slump in Asia had substantial negative effects,'' said L. D. DeSimone, chairman and chief executive. Changes in currency exchange rates reduced earnings by an estimated 10 cents a share.First-quarter revenues slipped to $3.7 billion from $3.71 billion a year earlier.Shares of 3M rose $2.3125 a share, to $92.50, in New York Stock Exchange trading.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/28/business/the-markets-currencies.html?ref=3mcompany">THE MARKETS: CURRENCIES<date>Published: January 28, 1998</date><text>DOLLAR FALLS. The dollar fell to the lowest level against the yen in more than two months, hurt by continued anxiety about the scandal surrounding President Clinton, a sharp retreat in Treasury bond prices and rallies in Asian markets. In New York, the dollar cost 125.32 yen, down from 126.85.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/18/business/company-news-3m-predicts-flat-profit-as-asia-woes-take-toll.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS; 3M PREDICTS FLAT PROFIT AS ASIA WOES TAKE TOLL<date>Published: December 18, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it expected flat earnings for the latest quarter, which would be below Wall Street expectations. The company said the strong dollar, economic turmoil in Asia and slower domestic sales growth were responsible. Shares of 3M tumbled $9 yesterday, to $84.875, in trading of more than 3.4 million shares. In the fourth quarter last year, 3M earned $375 million, or 90 cents a share. Analysts had forecast that the company, which makes Scotch tape, Post-It notes, coatings and other products, would earn $1 a share in this year's fourth quarter.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/21/business/secrets-leaked-kodak-contends.html?ref=3mcompany">Secrets Leaked, Kodak Contends<date>Published: November 21, 1997</date><text>A week after a retired Eastman Kodak Company manager got a year in prison for stealing film-making trade secrets, the photography giant accused one of his colleagues of leaking secrets to the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company.Kodak contended in legal papers today that Melvin Sterman, 67, peddled unspecified data to what was then 3M's photographic film divisionin Ferrania, Italy, the world's largest maker of private-label film. The unit came under a new company, the Imation Corporation, in a 1996 spinoff.Kodak is seeking $100,000 in damages, plus legal costs ''or such other amount as may be established at trial,'' the papers filed in State Supreme Court said.Harold Worden, who started a consulting firm in 1992 after a 28-year career with Kodak, drew a one-year prison sentence on Nov. 13 after pleading guilty to stealing secrets.Mr. Sterman was a senior researcher when he retired in 1992 after 37 years at Kodak. While consulting for Mr. Worden's company, Kodak contends, Mr. Sterman passed on confidential data to 3M Italia, its affiliates and successors, and to at least one other company.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/23/business/3m-profit-rises-8-as-sales-are-strong.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Profit Rises 8% As Sales Are Strong<date>Published: October 23, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that earnings grew in line with estimates during the third quarter, lifted by strong sales and cost controls.The company's profit, before a gain, rose 8.5 percent, to $432 million, or $1.05 a share, from $398 million, or 95 cents a share, a year earlier.A gain in the latest quarter of $495 million, or $1.20 a share, from the sale of 3M's billboard business in August resulted in net income of $927 million, or $2.25 a share. In the period a year earlier, operating earnings and net income were the same.Analysts had expected 3M to report operating earnings of $1.04 a share. The company's shares rose $5.75, to $100.375 Revenue for 3M, whose products include Post-It notes and Scotch brand tape, increased 5.6 percent, to $3.83 billion from $3.62 billion.The company said sales growth exceeded the economic growth rates of the countries in which it operates, aided by the introduction of products. Still, the stronger dollar, which reduces foreign profits when they are converted into the American currency for reporting purposes, lowered per-share earnings by 7 cents, in line with expectations.Analysts said 3M was able to improve its margins by keeping expenses under control.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/08/05/business/lamar-advertising-to-buy-assets-from-outdoor-systems.html?ref=3mcompany">LAMAR ADVERTISING TO BUY ASSETS FROM OUTDOOR SYSTEMS<date>Published: August 05, 1997</date><text>Outdoor Systems Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to resell certain advertising assets that it was acquiring as part of its $1 billion acquisition of the National Advertising unit of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company. The buyer is the Lamar Advertising Company, which is based in Baton Rouge, La. According to Phoenix-based Outdoor Systems, the $115 million assets to be resold include about 1,800 displays in Atlanta, Denver, Detroit, Grand Rapids, Mich., Houston, New Orleans, Kansas City, Louisville, Ky. and Phoenix.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/24/business/3m-earnings-increase-9.7-but-fall-short-of-expectations.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Earnings Increase 9.7% But Fall Short of Expectations<date>Published: July 24, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that earnings rose 9.7 percent in the second quarter, slightly less than analysts expected, as the strong dollar and new-product costs cut into higher sales.The company's financial health is often considered a benchmark for the economy because of the manufacturer's large and diverse base of consumer and commercial products.Net income at 3M, whose products include Post-It brand notes and Scotch brand tape, rose to $418 million, or $1.01 a share, from $381 million, or 91 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.The per-share results fell short of the $1.03 that analysts, on average, had expected. On the New York Stock Exchange, 3M declined $1.875, to $98.4375.Sales increased 8.4 percent, to $3.82 billion from $3.52 billion.While sales in the United States and abroad were better than expected, rising 10 percent in this country and 15 percent internationally, the dollar's strength reduced earnings by 5 cents a share. As the dollar rises, sales denominated in other currencies produce less American currency.International prices dropped 1 percent, and costs increased because of investments in the Pacing Plus new-products program, 3M said.Jonathan Rosenzweig, an analyst at Salomon Brothers, said, ''Revenue beat our forecasts handily due to strong international volume growth, implying the company must have had a very strong June.'' Operating profit margins were not as strong as expected, he said, because of the dollar's strength and the cost of the new products.The manufacturer said both of its two major product sectors -- industrial and consumer products and life sciences -- did well.Research and development costs increased $20 million from a year ago as 3M stepped up production of brightness-enhancement film, which is used on laptop computer screens, as well as chemicals that replace chlorofluorocarbons. Both are part of the Pacing Plus program, which speeds development of products that 3M believes have the potential for large sales and profits.The company said it expected strong growth to continue in the second half despite the impact of currency conversions.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/22/business/raymond-herzog-81-executive.html?ref=3mcompany">Raymond Herzog, 81, Executive<date>Published: July 22, 1997</date><text>Raymond H. Herzog, former chairman of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, died July 12 at his home in Pine Tree Hills, Minn. He was 81. The cause of death was cancer, according to a statement from the company.Mr. Herzog retired from 3M in 1980 after nearly 40 years of service. He was president from 1970 until 1975, when he became chairman and chief executive. Mr. Herzog had also been a member of 3M's board of directors from 1965 until 1985.Mr. Herzog, who was a high school science teacher and coach before joining 3M, continued to think of himself as a coach. ''My job is stimulating others to do a little better than they can do themselves,'' he once said. ''It works in business just as well as it works in sports.''Mr. Herzog spent several years in quality control and production assignments. He was particularly known for helping to start its copier business. After that assignment, he became vice president of several divisions before becoming president.A native of Merricourt, N.D., he was raised in Appleton, Wis., where he received a bachelor's degree in physics from Lawrence University.Mr. Herzog had at various times during his career served as a director of several corporations, including Northwest Airlines and the General Motors Corporation, and he was a trustee of the Mayo Foundation.He is survived by his wife, Jane; a daughter, Mollie Keys of Rochester; two sons, Richard Herzog of Los Altos Hills, Calif., and Ray Herzog Jr. of Lake Quivira, Kan.; seven grandchildren, and a great-granddaughter.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/12/business/suit-accuses-3m-of-tape-monopoly.html?ref=3mcompany">Suit Accuses 3M Of Tape Monopoly<date>Published: June 12, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company was sued in United States District Court here today by LePage's Inc., which accused 3M of trying to monopolize the $275 million market for transparent tape.The lawsuit contends that 3M offered retailers like Kmart, Wal-Mart, Staples and Kinko's big incentives and rebates on Scotch brand tape, Post-It brand notes and other office products in exchange for promises not to buy transparent and invisible tape from LePage's or the only other United States competitor, Tesa Tape Inc., a subsidiary of Beiersdorf A.G.LePage's, a Pittsburgh unit of the privately held Jordan Company, said that since 1992 its market share had been cut in half, to about 6 percent, while 3M's share rose to 91 percent. It wants $25 million in damages, which could triple to $75 million if 3M was found guilty of violating Federal antitrust laws.Spokesmen for 3M, based in St. Paul, declined to comment before seeing a copy of the lawsuit.LePage's, founded 121 years ago, makes Big Chief writing tablets, Ticonderoga No. 2 pencils and Prang watercolors.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/02/business/billboard-operators-set-1-billion-merger.html?ref=3mcompany">Billboard Operators Set $1 Billion Merger<date>Published: May 02, 1997</date><text>Outdoor Systems Inc., the nation's biggest outdoor advertising company, said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the billboard unit of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company for $1 billion.The acquisition comes at a time of sweeping consolidation in outdoor advertising. Indeed, the purchase of the unit, the National Advertising Company, would be the 11th such deal for Outdoor Systems since the company went public in April 1996.The company, however, was somewhat vague on how it intended to finance the purchase.Tom Wisz, a spokesman for the company, which is based in Phoenix, said a combination of bank debt and subordinated debt would be used to raise the cash.But analysts said that during a conference call to discuss the deal Outdoor Systems officials mentioned that the transaction would include at least $300 million in equity.Still, investors did not seem to be concerned about the details. On the Nasdaq market, Outdoor Systems shares closed at $29.75, up $2.''Outdoor Systems is one of the best billboard operators, and 3M was not particularly well managed,'' said Andrew W. Marcus, an analyst at Alex. Brown &amp; Sons, the firm that was the lead underwriter for Outdoor Systems' initial public offering.Mr. Marcus said that while the $1 billion price tag ''is a good one for 3M,'' Outdoor Systems has a good chance to increase National Advertising's value. ''They will probably raise occupancy rates and profit margins,'' he said.With the National Advertising purchase, Outdoor Systems will have 96,000 billboards -- an increase of more than 50 percent. Its billboards will be in 40 states, including 20 of the top 25 American metropolitan markets and 7 of the top 10 markets in Canada.''This acquisition gives us the opportunity to offer broader national, regional and local advertising coverage as well as maintain our leadership of the outdoor advertising industry,'' Arte Moreno, the president and chief executive of Outdoor Systems, said in a statement.The transaction is subject to approval by Federal regulators. Analysts said that because the two companies overlapped in five to 10 markets, at least some divestitures were likely.''Outdoor Systems has taken on the responsibility of getting the regulatory issues resolved,'' Mary Auvin, a Minnesota Mining spokeswoman, said. ''If that means selling off some of their boards, that is what they will do.''Mr. Marcus from Alex. Brown said that ''the markets in which they overlap is a small percentage of the deal.''</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/23/business/minnesota-mining-s-earnings-up-13-on-strong-us-sales.html?ref=3mcompany">Minnesota Mining's Earnings Up 13% on Strong U.S. Sales<date>Published: April 23, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that its earnings rose 13.3 percent in the first quarter, aided by economic strength in the United States.Net income increased to $410 million, or 99 cents a share, from $362 million, or 87 cents a share, a year ago. On average, analysts had expected profit of 98 cents a share.The company said the strong dollar, which reduces profits denominated in other currencies when they are converted into dollars, reduced per-share earnings by about 5 cents.On the New York Stock Exchange, 3M shares jumped $4.125, to $87.375.Quarterly sales were up 7.1 percent, to $3.71 billion, from $3.47 billion a year earlier.''They had an extremely strong March,'' said Alex Henderson, a Prudential Securities analyst. ''That's a function of the economic backdrop in the U.S., where gross domestic product is expected to have grown about 4.2 percent in the first quarter.''The company's products include Post-It notes, Scotch brand adhesive tape, sandpaper, industrial adhesives and drugs.United States sales rose 12 percent, with all the gain coming from increased unit volume. Internationally, unit sales gained 11 percent, but lower prices and the strong dollar resulted in a gain of only 3 percent.Growth in unit sales was strongest in the United States, the Asia-Pacific region and Latin America.The company also improved its productivity. It spun off many of its less profitable businesses last summer, including its operations that made computer floppy disks, X-ray film and photographic film.''We're off to a good start for the year,'' said L. D. DeSimone, the chairman and chief executive. ''We continue to expect a solid operating performance for 1997 as a whole, despite further strengthening of the U.S. dollar and continued economic softness in much of Western Europe.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/07/business/lawyer-s-foundation-awash-in-questions.html?ref=3mcompany">Lawyer's Foundation Awash in Questions<date>Published: February 07, 1997</date><text>John M. O'Quinn is the highest of high-flying lawyers -- and a highly visible one, too, playing a central role in turning plaintiffs' lawsuits involving silicone breast implants into a flourishing cottage industry.In 1995 he was ranked by Forbes magazine as the nation's second-highest-paid lawyer, his estimated $40 million income behind only Joe Jamail, the Texas lawyer made famous in the Texaco-Pennzoil case.Now, though, Mr. O'Quinn may face a prickly set of problems over the operation of his tax-exempt private foundation. Over the last four years, public documents and interviews indicate, foundation funds were used to underwrite the college educations of two children of an expert witness who testified on the fee Mr. O'Quinn deserved for his work on a breast implant case.In recent months, Mr. O'Quinn has jumped from crisis to crisis. Late last year, Texas bar officials accused him of using associates to improperly solicit clients after a 1994 airplane crash -- a charge that, if proven, could lead to his disbarment. South Carolina officials have been investigating similar suspicions. In November, Mr. O'Quinn, who practices in Houston, was arrested by the police there for drunken driving.On the drunken-driving charge, Mr. O'Quinn, 55, has pleaded no-contest, but he has adamantly rejected any suggestion that he improperly solicited clients. And he has asserted in recent interviews that the allegations against him are the work of corporate adversaries like Dow Corning, the implant maker that plaintiffs' lawyers like Mr. O'Quinn helped drive into bankruptcy.Federal tax rules bar use of a foundation's assets for the benefit of a trustee or other insider. In such cases, the Internal Revenue Service may penalize both the foundation and the individual. A private foundation is a charitable organization financed by a family or individual endowment.Wilson Fadely, an I.R.S. spokesman, said the agency would not comment on specific cases. On hearing a description of the transaction, several experts said they were troubled by it.''This sounds like a pretty clear-cut case of self-dealing,'' said Thomas A. Troyer, a Washington lawyer who specializes in tax-exempt organizations.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/29/business/minnesota-mining-mfg-mmmn.html?ref=3mcompany">MINNESOTA MINING &amp; MFG. (MMM,N)<date>Published: January 29, 1997</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company reported a profit yesterday for the fourth quarter after a loss a year earlier that was caused in part by a charge for restructuring. Operating earnings improved, too, and the company credited the introduction of new products.The company, which makes Scotch tapes, Post-it notes and other products, earned $385 million, or 92 cents a share, for the quarter ended Dec. 31, compared with a loss of $97 million, or 24 cents a share, a year ago. But the results a year earlier reflected one-time items, including a charge of $79 million related to the spinoff of 3M's data storage and imaging systems businesses.Earnings from continuing operations rose 41 percent, to $375 million, or 90 cents a share, from $266 million, or 63 cents a share, a year earlier.Analysts had predicted earnings of 88 cents a share from continuing operations. Minnesota Mining stock rose $1.50 to close at $83.50 on the New York Stock Exchange.Fourth-quarter sales reached $3.6 billion, compared with $3.3 billion a year earlier.For the year, 3M earned $1.5 billion, or $3.65 a share, on sales of $14.2 billion. That compared with 1995 earnings of $976 million, or $2.32 a share, on sales of $13.5 billion.New products accounted for about $400 million of 1996 sales, a spokeswoman said. Among those are hydrofluoroethers that replace environmentally damaging chlorofluorocarbons in cleaners for electronic components and flexible circuits for inkjet printers.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/26/business/3m-earnings-rise-15.7-stock-surges.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Earnings Rise 15.7%; Stock Surges<date>Published: October 26, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that earnings rose 15.7 percent in the third quarter on strong international sales, especially in Japan, other parts of Asia and Latin America.The results from the maker of tapes, adhesives, coatings and films beat expectations on Wall Street, and its stock soared $3.125, to $74.375, on the New York Stock Exchange. 3M is one of the issues in the 30-share Dow Jones industrial average.3M, based in St. Paul, said profits rose to $398 million, or 95 cents a share, in the quarter, from $344 million, or 82 cents a share, in the 1995 period, which included earnings of $5 million, or 1 cent a share, from discontined operations.Sales grew 7.4 percent, to $3.62 billion from $3.37 billion.The results surpassed analysts' average forecasts of 93 cents a share, according to First Call, which tracks estimates.The company said unit sales rose 10 to 12 percent internationally and more than 7 percent in the United States.''A strong flow of innovative, high-impact new products, an intense focus on customer satisfaction and continued expansion internationally fueled our worldwide volume growth,'' 3M's chairman, Livio D. DeSimone, said in a statement.3M, which makes products ranging from Post-It notes and Scotch brand adhesive tape to medical imagers and industrial adhesives, said its prices rose just 1 percent in the quarter while unit volume increased 10 percent.The company's units in Japan, elsewhere in Asia, Latin America and Canada posted double-digit volume increases in the quarter while unit sales in Europe grew 7 percent, despite sluggish economies in many major European countries.Changes in currency exchange rates reduced earnings in the latest quarter by 5 cents a share, 3M said. That reflected a stronger dollar, which causes earnings in overseas markets to be worth less when converted to dollars.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/20/business/fda-approves-inhaler.html?ref=3mcompany">F.D.A. Approves Inhaler<date>Published: August 20, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company has won approval from the Food and Drug Administration for the first asthma drug inhaler of its type that is free of a propellant thought to harm the ozone layer. The inhaler made by 3M delivers the drug albuterol without using chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's. The Schering-Plough Corporation will market and distribute the so-called metered dose inhaler in the United States under the brand name Proventil HFA on behalf of 3M's pharmaceutical division.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/30/business/comapny-reports-3m-earnings-climbed-7.9-in-2d-quarter.html?ref=3mcompany">COMAPNY REPORTS;3M Earnings Climbed 7.9% in 2d Quarter<date>Published: July 30, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that its second-quarter earnings rose 7.9 percent, bolstered by strong sales in the United States and lower raw material costs.The company earned $381 million, or 91 cents a share, in the quarter, up from $353 million, or 84 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.But the 1995 quarter included earnings of $7 million a share on operations that have been discontinued, including the company's audio tape and videotape business, and other operations spun off as the Imation Corporation on July 1.The most recent results were slightly better than the 90-cent average estimate of 11 analysts surveyed by Zacks Investment Research.Shares of Minnesota Mining rose 50 cents today, to $63.875, on the New York Stock Exchange."The U.S. rebounded pretty sharply," said Jack Kelly, an analyst with Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company. Unit sales in the United States rose 5 percent after being unchanged during the first quarter.Sales in terms of the dollar rose 7 percent in the United States, with price increases adding two percentage points.The company credited strong demand from the domestic auto, chemical, consumer and office markets. In its life sciences unit, gains in drug-delivery systems, commercial graphics, diaper tapes, dental products and safety and security systems were offset by slower sales of medical products.Outside the United States, sales rose 8 percent, with volume up 7 percent and prices up 1 percent.A stronger dollar, however, canceled out all of that gain. Minnesota Mining estimated currency exchange rates cut second-quarter earnings by 5 percent, or 4 cents a share.Most of the international sales gains came in Japan, the rest of Asia and South America. Japanese unit sales increased 11 percent, helped by an improved economy and new products tailored for that market. Volume increased about 15 percent in Asia outside Japan and more than 20 percent in Latin America.By contrast, Europe showed a 3 percent increase because of sluggish economies there.Minnesota Mining was also helped in the quarter by lower costs. The cost of goods sold dropped to 56.3 percent of sales, from 60.3 percent in 1995 and 59.6 percent two years ago."Raw material costs, which had a substantial negative effect on gross margins in each of the past several quarters, started to show a small, positive impact this quarter," Giulio Agostini, the company's chief financial officer, told analysts at a San Francisco meeting.He said the trend should continue to help earnings over the next few quarters.Mr. Agostini also said the company expected 1996 earnings to rise by more than 10 percent."We haven't seen signs of slowing in major world economies versus what we experienced in the second quarter," he said.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/30/business/investing-it-3m-s-big-spinoff-has-high-hurdles-ahead.html?ref=3mcompany">INVESTING IT;3M's Big Spinoff Has High Hurdles Ahead<date>Published: June 30, 1996</date><text>ALL STREET analysts have not forgotten their meeting with managers of Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing two years ago.The managers spoke optimistically about reviving their ailing data storage and imaging business by introducing new products, cutting costs and improving profit margins. But today, annual revenues at the division have fallen by 2.7 percent. It is struggling to recover from $85 million in losses in 1995. And, despite 3M's optimism two years ago, the division will be spun off tomorrow to form a new company, Imation.Investors who held 3M stock on Friday will receive one share of Imation for every 10 of their 3M shares. The new company, whose chairman will be William T. Monahan, a 3M executive, will begin trading on the New York Stock Exchange on July 16. Until then, it will trade in the "when issued" market, where some stocks trade before their debut.With the recent troubles still in mind, however, Wall Street is likely to receive 3M's division with caution."A lot has to go right for this to be a good stock," said Peter Doyle, an analyst at The Spin-Off Report, a newsletter. "It is definitely not without its risks."The 3M division that is becoming Imation had $2.2 billion in sales last year. It makes more than 10,000 imaging and data-storage products, from computer disks to film to magnetic resonance imaging equipment. While the products vary widely, many share an important trait: they are in highly competitive markets. In the imaging business, for example, Imation's rivals will include Eastman Kodak, Fuji Photo Film, Sony, Agfa, Polaroid, Konica and Du Pont.In many of these competitive markets, the technology and the products are changing rapidly. That spells declining prices. In 1990, for example, a 10-pack of 3M's 1.44-megabyte, formatted disks sold for $44.50. Today, 3M recommends that retailers sell a 10-pack for $10.18.Also, the new company's stock is likely to experience some initial selling pressure. Because Imation, unlike 3M, will not be a part of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index, all the mutual funds that invest only in index companies will have to sell their Imation shares. In addition, Imation will start without a dividend. That means the managers of income-oriented funds who own 3M will also discard their Imation stock. Together, income funds and S.&amp; P. 500 funds will own about 12 percent of Imation stock, Salomon Brothers estimates.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/20/business/company-briefs-030635.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: June 20, 1996</date><text>MINNESOTA MINING AND MANUFACTURING CO., St. Paul, set June 28 as the date for the spinoff of its data storage and imaging systems businesses, Imation Corp. Investors will receive 1 Imation share for every 10 shares of 3M stock held.GENERAL NUTRITION COS., Pittsburgh, a retailer of vitamins and other nutritional supplements, said its board had authorized the buyback an additional $50 million in common stock. The company repurchased about $100 million of its stock under a previous buyback. NORDICTRACK INC., Chaska, Minn., a unit of the CML Group, said it planned to close its plant in Sioux Falls, S.D., in September and lay off 48 full- and part-time workers.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/03/business/company-reports-minnesota-mining-posts-a-drop-in-quarter-s-net-income-of-3.7.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY REPORTS;Minnesota Mining Posts a Drop In Quarter's Net Income of 3.7%<date>Published: May 03, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, which is shedding a variety of businesses, said today that net income fell 3.7 percent in the first quarter but that profit from the operations it was retaining rose about 2 percent.Sales increased in the United States and at a faster rate abroad, 3M said, but the stronger dollar reduced the size of the foreign increase. For all of 1996, 3M said it expected solid sales and earnings growth despite the strong currency.The company announced last November that it would spin off its imaging and data-storage businesses, shut down its audiotape and videotape production and take some smaller steps. It will concentrate on its industrial and consumer group and its life-sciences sector, whose products include a wide variety of medical supplies. It plans the spinoff for July 1 and expects to close the tape businesses by the end of the year.In reporting earnings today, 3M did not include the operations that are being discontinued in the results for the 1996 first quarter but did so in the results for the 1995 quarter.Net income in the latest quarter equaled profit from continuing operations and stood at $362 million, or 87 cents a share. That was down from the net income of $376 million a year earlier, or 90 cents a share, which included $21 million, or 5 cents a share, from the discontinued operations. But it was up 2 percent from the 1995 profit from continuing operations of $355 million, or 85 cents a share.The profit of 87 cents a share in the latest quarter matched the average forecast of nine analysts surveyed by Zacks Investment Research. On the New York Stock Exchange today, 3M's shares fell by 50 cents, to $65.375.Revenue rose 3.2 percent in the first quarter, to $3.47 billion from $3.36 billion."We achieved record sales and profits despite slow growth of major world economies, strengthening of the U.S. dollar and negative effects from raw material costs," Livio D. DeSimone, chairman and chief executive, said in a statement.He added, "While we saw solid growth in a number of business areas, including pharmaceuticals, consumer products, office supplies and personal-care products, demand was soft in the industrial markets." Demand was especially slow in the auto, furniture and textiles industries, the company said.International revenue increased 4 percent in the quarter, lifted by sales in Japan, elsewhere in Asia and Latin America, 3M said. Unit sales rose 6 percent and prices rose 2 percent. The stronger dollar, however, pared the results.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/03/us/major-advertising-company-to-bar-billboard-ads-for-tobacco.html?ref=3mcompany">Major Advertising Company to Bar Billboard Ads for Tobacco<date>Published: May 03, 1996</date><text>In another setback for American cigarette companies, the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that its 3M Media subsidiary, the nation's third-largest outdoor billboard advertising company, would no longer accept billboard contracts for tobacco products after this year.The news was hailed by President Clinton and by anti-tobacco groups as the first time a major billboard company had instituted such a ban.I applaud 3M Media for accepting responsibility for the impact billboards have" in influencing youth smoking, Mr. Clinton said yesterday in a prepared statement. "Smoking is a pediatric disease that shows no sign of abating, in part because young people are constantly barraged by messages that glamour and grit can be found in a pack of cigarettes."The announcement, on the same day that 3M reported slightly improved first-quarter earnings, was made less than two weeks before the company's annual meeting. It was unusual in that it was issued jointly by 3M Media and by the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, a coalition of 275 Protestant, Jewish and Roman Catholic institutional investors that seeks to influence corporations on social issues.The Rev. Michael Crosby, the tobacco-program coordinator for the center, said that the organization had threatened to raise the tobacco-advertising issue from the floor of the company's annual meeting on May 14 and that religious-affiliated hospitals had threatened to boycott 3M hospital products."This is an important breakthrough," Father Crosby said. "The country had to look at all those tobacco billboards for years with the letters 3M beneath them. But now, 3M is no longer promoting health with one hand while advertising a product that leads to death with the other hand."He was referring to 3M's health subsidiaries, which generate $2 billion of the company's $13.5 billion in annual revenue.The health-care divisions make products ranging from surgical gowns and wound dressings to heart-lung machines."We want to let the health care industry know that we are serious about good health, and advertising tobacco doesn't seem to fit with that goal," said Mary Auvin, a spokeswoman for 3M. All major tobacco companies now have contracts with 3M Media, she said.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/25/business/3m-sets-plant-closing.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Sets Plant Closing<date>Published: April 25, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that it was phasing out a medical and graphic arts imaging business here and laying off 335 employees over the next 15 months. The transfer of operations to Medford, Ore., and Ferrania, Italy, is part of a restructuring of 3M's data storage and imaging system businesses being spun off in July as an independent company called Imation.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/22/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-imation-account-to-ketchum-unit.html?ref=3mcompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA;Imation Account To Ketchum Unit<date>Published: April 22, 1996</date><text>Imation, the imaging systems and data storage company that will be spun off in July from the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, has chosen the Ketchum Advertising Pittsburgh unit of Ketchum Communications as its first agency of record. Billings were estimated at $14 million.Ketchum Advertising Pittsburgh was selected after a six-week review that also included three other finalists: Bozell Worldwide in New York, a unit of Bozell, Jacobs, Kenyon &amp; Eckhardt; Colle &amp; McVoy in Minneapolis, and Grey Advertising in New York, which handles the bulk of the 3M worldwide corporate and consumer account. Imation, which will be based in Oakdale, Minn., will be promoted in a worldwide print campaign scheduled to begin in June.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/11/business/3m-chases-the-dream-of-building-a-better-disk.html?ref=3mcompany">3M Chases the Dream of Building a Better Disk<date>Published: March 11, 1996</date><text>Correction AppendedThe 3.5-inch floppy disk is now 12 years old. For the computer industry, which reckons time in something akin to dog years, that makes it at least an octogenarian, and there is no shortage of young pups barking for a chance to take its place.The latest contender, introduced last week by the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, is the LS-120 Diskette, a new 3.5-inch diskette with a formatted capacity of 120 megabytes. That is about 80 times the capacity of the 1.44-megabyte floppy, which was introduced in the Apple Macintosh in 1984 and has since become the standard for personal computers of all types.Helping create a market for the new 3M diskette, which will become available April 2, the Compaq Computer Corporation said last week that it would include a drive for the new diskette in two models, due in late April, and make it available as an option on other machines.The LS-120 diskettes will cost about $20 each, compared with less than $1 for 1.44-megabyte floppy disks. And the necessary disk drive will add about $200 to the cost of a personal computer. The drive, which will be manufactured by Matsushita-Kotobuki Electronics Industries Ltd., is "backward-compatible," meaning it can also read the older 3.5-inch floppy disks. And, according to 3M, an LS-120 drive can read and write a 1.44- megabyte diskette up to three times as fast as current drives.The original 3.5-inch floppy, which was invented by the Sony Corporation, has followed a much slower progression than the development of the built-in hard disks that act as the main data reservoirs for computers. While typical hard disks have increased in capacity twentyfold -- to 1,000 megabytes -- over the last decade, floppy disks have only doubled in capacity, to 1.44 megabytes from 720 kilobytes.As software programs and the files they create have swelled in size, performing backup or distributing applications on floppy disks have become increasingly difficult.CD-ROM's, with their vast capacity, are one alternative for distributing new software, but they are not user-recordable, and so are unsuited for making backups. And CD-R, the recordable version, remains too expensive for general use -- around $550 for a built-in disk drive and $40 or so for each disk.So is LS-120 the answer?Correction: March 16, 1996, Saturday Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Monday about a new type of computer floppy disk misstated the data capacity of the original 3 1/2-inch floppy used with the first Apple Macintosh. That disk had a capacity of 400 kilobytes -- not 720 kilobytes. Later versions had capacities of 720 kilobytes, 1,000 kilobytes, and, ultimately, 1,400 kilobytes -- or 1.4 megabytes.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/06/business/company-reports-minnesota-mining-mfg-co-mmmn.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY REPORTS;MINNESOTA MINING &amp; MFG. CO. (MMM,N)<date>Published: February 06, 1996</date><text>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing reported a loss yesterday of $97 million for the fourth quarter as a result of charges for job cuts and write-downs.The company, which makes Post-it notes and Scotch adhesive tapes, took charges of $414 million as part of a plan to close its audiotape and videotape businesses and spin off several others. In the comparable quarter a year earlier, the company earned $332 million, or 79 cents a share.But earnings from continuing operations were higher in the latest quarter, rising to $318 million, or 75 cents a share, from $294 million, or 70 cents a share. Sales from continuing operations rose 7 percent, to $3.3 billion from $3.09 billion. The company did not disclose total sales. The results were in line with Wall Street estimates.Minnesota Mining, based in St. Paul, had said on Jan. 17 that it expected fourth-quarter earnings to fall because of weak December sales. The company said demand in the United States was weakest in the automotive, furniture and textile industries, although its consumer products, office supplies and roofing materials did well. European sales were also weak in December, the company said, in part because of a monthlong transportation strike in France.For the quarter, sales in the United States rose 4 percent and international sales gained 10 percent, the company said. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/01/18/business/company-news-lower-earnings-expected-because-of-slow-sales.html?ref=3mcompany">COMPANY NEWS;LOWER EARNINGS EXPECTED BECAUSE OF SLOW SALES<date>Published: January 18, 1996</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said yesterday that it expected earnings for the fourth quarter to be lower than a year earlier, even before a charge related to the spinoff of some operations, because of weak sales in December. The company's shares fell $3.50, to $63.75, on the New York Stock Exchange. The businesses to be spun off, including the computer floppy-disk manufacturing operation, were among those with the weakest sales, the company, known as 3M, said. The continuing operations, which include Post-It Notes, Scotch adhesive tapes and Thinsulate insulating fabric, are expected to have been about as profitable as a year earlier.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/18/business/manager-at-3m-to-head-spinoff.html?ref=3mcompany">Manager at 3M To Head Spinoff<date>Published: November 18, 1995</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company named William T. Monahan today to head the computer data storage and imaging units that it will spin off next year.Mr. Monahan, 48, is group vice president of 3M's electro and communications systems group in Austin, Tex. More than 20 of his 23 years at 3M have been spent in sales and marketing at the data storage unit.Mr. Monahan will head a company with $1 billion in sales and about 11,000 employees. It will be the world's largest maker of computer floppy disks and color-proofing systems for the graphics industry.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/15/business/3m-to-cut-jobs-and-businesses-lagging-in-profit.html?ref=3mcompany">3M to Cut Jobs And Businesses Lagging in Profit<date>Published: November 15, 1995</date><text>The Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company said today that it would lop off some of its best-known but least-profitable businesses, cut 5,000 jobs from its work force of 85,000 and take a $600 million charge against profits in the fourth quarter.The scope and timing of the moves startled Wall Street, but also pleased it. The company's shares jumped $2.625, to $61.625, on the New York Stock Exchange, for a gain on the day of 4.4 percent.Analysts have long been concerned that the company's information, imaging and electronic sector might be a permanent drag on profits because several key businesses, including videotape, floppy disks and photographic film, had become commodities subject to brutal price competition. 3M repeatedly responded with assurances that it had no intention of living indefinitely with the status quo.Still, that had not prepared Wall Street for a plan that includes spinning off imaging and data storage businesses with more than $2 billion in sales, shutting down audiotape and videotape production and a number of smaller changes. Such changes seemed radical for a company known for cautious planning and a reluctance to dismiss employees."This is more and sooner than expected," said Peter J. Enderlin, who follows 3M for Smith Barney Inc.The businesses to be spun off will top $2.3 billion in sales this year, analysts estimate. The tape operations scheduled for closing have sales of $650 million. The surviving pieces of 3M are headed toward revenues this year of $13.3 billion.Until today, 3M had maintained that it could resurrect the flagging margins of the group through a strategy of introducing new products and cutting manufacturing costs. The one kind of risk that is exalted in 3M's corporate culture is a bet on innovation. But applying that strategy in the businesses now being shed has consumed $1.24 billion since 1992, more than half of 3M's capital budget, without any clear payoff.Not only were the audiotape and videotape businesses producing little or no profit, but the other imaging and data businesses were also projected to produce skimpy margins of around 5 percent this year and next, not counting extra spending on new products. Even with growing sales from the new products, margins for 1997 were projected at no more than 10 percent. By contrast, 3M's other businesses have margins of 18 percent, with room for improvement.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/14/us/3-companies-agree-to-settle-implant-cases.html?ref=3mcompany">3 Companies Agree to Settle Implant Cases<date>Published: November 14, 1995</date><text>Correction AppendedThe boards of three companies that are being sued by women who had silicone breast implants agreed today to a new multibillion-dollar settlement.Judge Sam C. Pointer Jr. of Federal District Court in Birmingham, Ala., who is overseeing the class-action case, announced the settlement yesterday evening.The settlement, which could cost $2 billion to $3 billion if all eligible women participated, replaces a $4.25 billion agreement reached in late 1993. The previous settlement collapsed a few months ago.The companies participating in the new settlement are the Bristol-Myers Squibb Company, Baxter Healthcare, which is a subsidiary of Baxter International, and Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing. Another company, the Dow Corning Corporation, the major implant maker jointly owned by Dow Chemical and Corning Inc., is not part of the new agreement because it has filed for bankruptcy. Claims against it are now being handled by a bankruptcy court.Lawyers representing women with implants say the devices caused a wide variety of illnesses, including vague aches and pains, fatigue, autoimmune diseases and neurological disorders resembling multiple sclerosis.But the companies say that there is no evidence that the devices cause diseases and that they were forced to enter into the settlement because they were hit with an avalanche of lawsuits.Mary Thomas, a spokeswoman for Baxter Healthcare, said 6,949 lawsuits and 1,757 claims had been filed against her company. Baxter, she added, never made or sold implants. It became liable because it acquired a company in 1985, the American Hospital Supply Company, that had once owned another company, the Heyer-Schulte Company, that had sold implants.The previous settlement had included Dow Corning as the major contributor. It failed because so many women registered and the damage awards were so high that even $4.25 billion was not enough to pay them. The awards ranged from $100,000 to $2 million and 430,000 women registered.The new agreement has sharply lower awards, from about $10,000 to $250,000 depending on how old the women were, how ill and how much medical data they submitted. About half of the women who registered for the original agreement are ineligible to register for the new one because their devices were made by Dow Corning.Women who choose not to participate in the new agreement and who believe that they were injured by their implants can pursue their claims in court, suing the manufacturers as individuals.Correction: November 16, 1995, Thursday An article on Tuesday about a multibillion-dollar settlement of breast implant litigation misstated the timing in some editions. The agreement was announced on Monday, not Tuesday.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/08/business/where-repetition-is-exciting.html?ref=3mcompany">Where Repetition Is Exciting<date>Published: November 08, 1995</date><text>Not long ago, botanists discovered that mushrooms scattered over a 30-acre area in upper Michigan were actually part of one huge fungus.Something similar is happening here at the headquarters campus of the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, where new materials for products as diverse as highway signs, laptop computer screens and diapers are growing out of a single manufacturing technology called microreplication.The technology allows 3M to cover the surfaces of large sheets of plastic, rubber and other moldable materials with microscopic ridges, pyramids or other raised features. Packed thousands to the square inch, the shapes are arrayed in patterns that improve the performance of a wide range of everyday products, making highway signs reflect more light or adding durability to industrial sandpaper. The latest application, just in time for Christmas, is a computer mouse pad that gives users more pinpoint control of their cursors. Scores of other products are in the works."Thirty percent of the company's products could be tied to this in 10 years," said Roger Appeldorn, the scientist who has been 3M's most zealous proponent of microreplication. Even taking the more conservative projection of 15 to 20 percent favored by senior executives, the result would be sales of as much as $8 billion a year, greater than last year's revenues at such giants as Eli Lilly, Kellogg and Gillette."This is an example of American innovation at its best," said Ronald Mitsch, the executive vice president in charge of 3M's industrial and consumer businesses and one of Mr. Appeldorn's earliest supporters.That said, microreplication is no overnight success story. Despite its current hot status, it provides a case study of the hurdles facing innovation even in the most receptive of environments.The 3M culture lionizes the inventors of creative products like the company's Post-It note pads, and it encourages researchers to devote part of their time to blue-sky projects. Even so, microreplication had to overcome competition from other technology projects for resources. It also had to survive gaps in 3M's production and research skills and difficulties in sorting out which products would benefit most from it.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/10/12/business/in-implant-case-missteps-could-hurt-dow-corning.html?ref=3mcompany">In Implant Case, Missteps Could Hurt Dow Corning<date>Published: October 12, 1995</date><text>The tentative agreement that three major producers of silicone breast implants finally reached last week to settle thousands of lawsuits by women who used the devices will cost them billions. But the Dow Corning Corporation, which was not part of the agreement, could end up even worse, the possible victim of its own miscalculations.Dow Corning, which is jointly owned by the Dow Chemical Company and Corning Inc., sought bankruptcy protection in May, citing billions of dollars in implant-related claims. It was the largest implant producer and made most of the silicone gel used by other makers.It's the only way to bring an overall resolution to the situation," Richard A. Hazleton, the company's chairman and chief executive, said at the time.That may well have been true, but Dow Corning's transit into bankruptcy was also accompanied by a series of miscues by executives, near fist-fights among lawyers and a faulty presumption about what the judge in the case would do.While the other producers have agreed to pay huge sums to put much of the implant controversy behind them, Dow Corning faces the possibility of living with what may prove to be a slow, painful illness.Bankruptcy offers some breathing room for the company, but it also gives a judge the power to second-guess its business decisions. And Dow Corning still does not know how far its liability will extend. The situation may not be so stark for Bristol-Myers Squibb, Baxter International and Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, the other big implant makers, which are hoping to limit most of their liability to $3 billion.Dow Corning's biggest miscalculation, lawyers in the case said, involved the $4.25 billion global settlement of implant claims, one intended to buy peace that ended up producing only more war. The plan promised individual women who said silicone exposure caused health problems awards of $200,000 to $2 million. Few medical hurdles existed to qualify. And the plan contained an unusual escape clause: class action claimants could wait to see a deal's final shape before deciding whether to take part in it.As the settlement unleashed a flood of lawsuits, women saw their promised awards fall to as low as 5 percent of what they had originally expected. Thousands more then decided to pursue lawsuits on their own against Dow Corning.</text></article></page></root>
