<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="American Electric Power Co."><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/20/opinion/20wed2.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Blame Congress for Not Acting on Climate Change<date>Published: July 19, 2011</date><text>American Electric Power’s decision to shut down an ambitious experiment aimed at capturing greenhouse gases from a coal-fired power plant was a disappointing setback to efforts to control harmful global warming emissions from coal, among the world’s most abundant fuels.It was also a predictable result of Congress’s failure to enact climate change legislation that would have placed a price on emissions and given businesses compelling economic reasons to clean up their plants and develop new technologies. Without industrywide federal standards in place, state utility regulators would not have allowed A.E.P. to recoup its investment through higher prices, making the whole project untenable. Coal-fired power plants produce one-third of the nation’s emissions of carbon dioxide. Policy makers have other tools to help lower these greenhouse gas emissions, including regulations requiring more efficient plants. What they do not have is breakthrough technologies. The A.E.P. project, located at a 31-year-old coal-fired plant in West Virginia, was the country’s most advanced attempt to strip carbon dioxide from the flue gases and store it permanently underground in deep-rock formations under the plant. The company had completed a small pilot program, and the Energy Department had promised to pay for half the final $668 million bill. But A.E.P. would have been on the hook for the rest. When work began two years ago, it was assumed that Congress would adopt a cap-and-trade program — imposing a price on emissions, rewarding companies that found innovative ways to reduce them and providing upfront subsidies for advanced technologies. The House passed such a bill, but the Senate balked. Most of the other proposals and projects in the United States involve enhanced oil recovery, in which utilities capture carbon dioxide and ship it to oil fields where it is injected into wells to extract more oil. Senator Richard Lugar has introduced legislation that would provide tax breaks for utilities that participate. That’s a start. But, at best, oil recovery will be able to absorb only one-sixth of the country’s annual carbon-dioxide emissions. To address global warming, the country needs new technology and more ambitious projects. There is little chance that industry will invest in them unless Congress provides far stronger financial incentives.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/14/scattered-attempts-at-carbon-capture/?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Scattered Attempts at Carbon Capture<date>July 14, 2011, 3:54 pm</date><text>Department of EnergyThe Energy Department is aiding eight such projects. (A.E.P.’s was canceled.) As my colleague John Broder and I reported in Thursday’s paper, American Electric Power is dropping its plan to build a commercial-scale version of a carbon dioxide scrubber at Mountaineer, its coal-fired power plant in New Haven, W.Va. The company decided that since public service commissions in West Virginia and Virginia had refused to give it full reimbursement for a pilot version that it ran for two years, it could not expect to recover its investment for the full-scale version — even if the Energy Department was going to pony up $334 million, or half the cost. Senator Jay Rockefeller, the West Virginia Democrat who had helped secure the $334 million as part of the fiscal stimulus act, was quick to praise the pilot project and to say that the money would be available for other carbon-capture projects. In fact, eight other such projects are in the pipeline, although none quite like Mountaineer, a middle-aged coal-fired electric plant that had planned to bury the carbon dioxide. Plants like that will probably continue to pump carbon dioxide into the atmosphere for decades. It is possible that not all of the eight will come to fruition, but they offer interesting possibilities the Southern Company, for example, has already broken ground on a $2.67 billion power plant in Kemper County, Miss., to which the Energy Department will contribute $270 million. The plant will cook coal into a gas, separate out some of the carbon dioxide and burn the gas. The plant will emit very low levels of other pollutants and can use local coals that have low heating value per ton. Some other projects aided by the Energy Department yield carbon dioxide but are not power plants. An Archer Daniels Midland ethanol plant in Decatur, Ill., will sequester its carbon dioxide in an underground sandstone layer. Ethanol production gives off a stream of nearly pure carbon dioxide, so capture is easy. In Meredosia, Ill., the Energy Department is helping pay for the conversion of a plant that was originally built to use oil. In its new configuration, an air separation unit will pull oxygen out of the air and use it to burn coal. At a conventional power plant, the exhaust is mostly nitrogen. But if the coal is burned in oxygen, the exhaust is mostly carbon dioxide. It is by far the Energy Department’s biggest investment, $1.08 billion out of a total cost of about $1.3 billion. The W.A. Parish generating station, a coal-fired power station in Thompsons, Tex., southwest of Houston, and owned by NRG, will be equipped with a carbon scrubber. It sits in the midst of oil fields and could sell its carbon dioxide to drillers, who would pump the material underground to force oil to the surface. Depending on the oil field, a ton of carbon dioxide can produce two to four barrels. At $100 a barrel, that would be a high market value for the carbon dioxide. The Parish project is supposed to cost $339 million, with the Energy Department contributing $167 million. It is about one-quarter the size of the canceled A.E.P. project. Near Odessa, Tex., another plant will also cook coal into a gas and sequester the carbon. But that plant, Summit TX Clean Energy, is a “poly-gen” plant, making both fertilizer and electric power. It is supposed to cost $1.7 billion, with a $450 million taxpayer contribution. In Lake Charles, La., Leucadia Energy will turn petroleum coke into methanol and capture the carbon dioxide. That project is supposed to cost $436 million, with $261 million coming from the Energy Department. And in Port Arthur, Tex., Air Products will expose natural gas to steam to create methanol; the carbon dioxide will be captured and used in the oil fields. That is a $426 million project, of which $261 comes from the Energy Department. In Kern County, Calif., the Energy Department will put $408 million toward a $2.8 billion plant that will take petroleum coke, a leftover from oil refining, and cook it into hydrogen gas for use in power generation, with sequestration of the carbon dioxide. These projects use a variety of capture technologies. A crucial part of A.E.P.’s now-abandoned attempt was the use of ammonia, which is well suited to existing plants, to bind with the carbon dioxide. A.E.P.’s partner in the Mountaineer pilot, Alstom, which built the ammonia system, said it understood the decision to shelve the capture project but cautioned that commercialization of the technology was needed to reduce climate change. “If we deviate from the critical path for commercializing C.C.S. technology and do not build large-scale demonstration plants, it will take longer to drive down the technology cost curve, and significantly increase delivered electricity costs,’’ Alstom said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/14/business/energy-environment/utility-shelves-plan-to-capture-carbon-dioxide.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utility Shelves Ambitious Plan to Limit Carbon<date>Published: July 13, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — A major American utility is shelving the nation’s most prominent effort to capture carbon dioxide from an existing coal-burning power plant, dealing a severe blow to efforts to rein in emissions responsible for global warming.American Electric Power has decided to table plans to build a full-scale carbon-capture plant at Mountaineer, a 31-year-old coal-fired plant in West Virginia, where the company has successfully captured and buried carbon dioxide in a small pilot program for two years. The technology had been heralded as the quickest solution to help the coal industry weather tougher federal limits on greenhouse gas emissions. But Congressional inaction on climate change diminished the incentives that had spurred A.E.P. to take the leap. Company officials, who plan an announcement on Thursday, said they were dropping the larger, $668 million project because they did not believe state regulators would let the company recover its costs by charging customers, thus leaving it no compelling regulatory or business reason to continue the program. The federal Department of Energy had pledged to cover half the cost, but A.E.P. said it was unwilling to spend the remainder in a political climate that had changed strikingly since it began the project. “We are placing the project on hold until economic and policy conditions create a viable path forward,” said Michael G. Morris, chairman of American Electric Power, based in Columbus, Ohio, one of the largest operators of coal-fired generating plants in the United States. He said his company and other coal-burning utilities were caught in a quandary: they need to develop carbon-capture technology to meet any future greenhouse-gas emissions rules, but they cannot afford the projects without federal standards that will require them to act and will persuade the states to allow reimbursement. The decision could set back for years efforts to learn how best to capture carbon emissions that result from burning fossil fuels and then inject them deep under-ground to keep them from accumulating in the atmosphere and heating the planet. The procedure, formally known as carbon capture and sequestration or C.C.S., offers the best current technology for taming greenhouse-gas emissions from traditional fuels burned at existing plants. The abandonment of the A.E.P. plant comes in response to a string of reversals for federal climate change policy. President Obama spent his first year in office pushing a goal of an 80 percent reduction in climate-altering emissions by 2050, a target that could be met only with widespread adoption of carbon-capture and storage at coal plants around the country. The administration’s stimulus package provided billions of dollars to speed development of the technology; the climate change bill passed by the House in 2009 would have provided tens of billions of dollars in additional incentives for what industry calls “clean coal.” But all such efforts collapsed last year with the Republican takeover of the House and the continuing softness in the economy, which killed any appetite for far-reaching environmental measures. A senior Obama administration official said that the A.E.P. decision was a direct result of the political stalemate. “This is what happens when you don’t get a climate bill,” the official said, insisting on anonymity to discuss a corporate decision that had not yet been publicly announced. At the Energy Department, Charles McConnell, the acting assistant secretary of energy for fossil energy, said no carbon legislation was near and unless there was a place to sell the carbon dioxide, utilities would have great difficulties in justifying the expense. “You could have the debate all day long about whether people are enlightened about whether carbon dioxide should be sequestered,” he said. But, he added, “it’s not a situation that is going to promote investment.” His department has pledged more than $3 billion to other industrial plants to encourage the capture of carbon dioxide for sale to oil drillers, who use it to more easily get crude out of wells. The West Virginia project was one of the most advanced and successful in the world. “While the coal industry’s commitment and ability to develop this technology on a large scale was always uncertain, the continued pollution from old-style, coal-fired power plants will certainly be damaging to the environment without the installation of carbon capture and other pollution control updates,” said Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts, co-author of the House climate bill. “A.E.P., the American coal industry and the Republicans who blocked help for this technology have done our economy and energy workers a disservice by likely ceding the development of carbon-capture technology to countries like China.” A.E.P., which serves five million customers in 11 states, operated a pilot-scale capture plant at its Mountaineer generating station in New Haven, W.Va., on the Ohio River, from 2009 until May of this year. But the company plans to announce on Thursday that it will complete early engineering studies and then will suspend the project indefinitely. Public service commissions of both West Virginia and Virginia turned down the company’s request for full reimbursement for the pilot plant. West Virginia said earlier this year that the cost should have been shared among all the states where A.E.P. does business; Virginia hinted last July that it should have been paid for by all utilities around the United States, since a successful project would benefit all of them. Five years ago, when global warming ranked higher on the national political agenda, the consensus was that this decade would be one of research and demonstration in new technologies. A comprehensive 2007 study by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology concluded that global coal use was inevitable and that the ensuing few years should be used to quickly find ways to burn the cheap, abundant fuel cleanly. But with the demise of the Mountaineer project, the United States, the largest historic emitter of global warming gases, now appears to have made little progress solving the problem. Robert H. Socolow, an engineering professor at Princeton and the co-director of the Carbon Mitigation Initiative there, said he was encouraged that some chemical factories and other industries were working on carbon capture without government incentives. Mr. Socolow, the co-author of an influential 2004 paper that identified carbon capture as one of the critical technologies needed to slow global warming, said that there was a trap ahead. “Lull yourself into believing that there is no climate problem, or that there is lots of time to fix it, and the policy driver dissolves,” he said in an e-mail. He added that for companies like A.E.P., “business wants to be ahead of the curve, but not a lap ahead.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/27/opinion/lweb27coal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Coal and Electricity<date>Published: June 26, 2011</date><text>To the Editor: “A.E.P. Protests Too Much” (editorial, June 20) , calling American Electric Power cynical, was dismissive of the 600 A.E.P. workers who stand to lose their jobs years ahead of schedule because of the Environmental Protection Agency’s proposed regulations. While a few more years on the job may not seem like much to you, I am sure that the 600 workers and their families feel differently. A.E.P. and its workers are not alone in their struggle. According to a recent initial National Economic Research Associates analysis, two of E.P.A.’s proposed regulations would increase the cost of energy by up to 24 percent in parts of the country, and could destroy significant numbers of jobs. There is a reason coal generates nearly half of our nation’s electricity: because it’s affordable, abundant, reliable and increasingly clean. We need energy policies that take advantage of coal’s importance to the United States, not diminish it. STEVE MILLER President and Chief Executive American Coalition for Clean Coal Electricity Alexandria, Va., June 21, 2011</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/20/opinion/20mon1.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">A.E.P. Protests Too Much<date>Published: June 19, 2011</date><text>American Electric Power, one of the nation’s largest utilities, warned last week that new air quality rules could force it to “prematurely” shut down about two dozen big coal-fired units and fire hundreds of workers. This is a deceptive and particularly cynical claim. The utility is making a business decision that has little to do with the rules.Here is what A.E.P. is not saying: These units are, on average, 55 years old. Some are running at only 5 percent of capacity. Many had long been slated for retirement, in part to comply with a 2007 settlement with the George W. Bush administration in which the company agreed to settle violations of the Clean Air Act by spending $4.7 billion to retire or retrofit aging units. Blaming the rules is a transparent scare tactic designed to weaken the administration’s resolve while playing to industry supporters on Capitol Hill. Fortunately, Lisa Jackson, head of the Environmental Protection Agency, which proposed the rules, refuses to be bullied. Ms. Jackson called the A.E.P. charges “misleading at best” and made clear she would not retreat from her statutory duty to protect public health. She said she would stick to her timetable and make the rules final this year. We hope that the White House is equally determined. Two rules are at issue. One, proposed last year, would require utilities to sharply reduce emissions of already-regulated soot and smog-forming pollutants like sulfur dioxide. The other, for the first time, would mandate reductions in toxic pollutants like mercury. Coal-fired plants, which generate the vast bulk of A.E.P.’s power, are by far the biggest producers of all these pollutants. Companies will have to begin complying with the soot and smog rules next year and the air toxics rule by 2015. A.E.P. says this timeline is “unrealistic” and asks for a delay of up to five years; otherwise, it says, it will have to shut down one-fourth of its coal-fired capacity and lay off up to 600 workers. Yet in a June 1 meeting with investors, Michael Morris, the utility’s chairman, who last week warned about the impact of the proposed regulations on “our customers and local economies,” told investors that the closings were “the appropriate way to go” for customers and shareholders. As for the utility’s claims of undue haste, they don’t stand up to even minimal review. Both rules have been in the works since the Clinton administration, and companies that have made their plants more efficient or invested in cleaner-burning fuels or up-to-date pollution control technologies are by now well prepared to deal with them. A.E.P., by contrast, has always seemed much more interested in fighting the Clean Air Act than in finding sensible ways to meet its requirements. It fought the statute after it passed in 1970 and resisted efforts to strengthen the law under President George H. W. Bush. Even now it is shopping a bill around Capitol Hill that would block or delay the proposed new standards. The bill does not so far have a sponsor, though it will likely have plenty of sympathizers among Republicans and some Rust Belt Democrats. It does not reflect the interests or wishes of the vast majority of Americans, for whom cleaner air is rightly a higher priority than any company’s bottom line.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/03/01/choosing-a-home-for-captured-carbon-dioxide/?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">A Home for Captured Carbon Dioxide<date>March 1, 2011, 9:45 am</date><text>FutureGen, the Energy Department’s on-again, off-again pilot project for capturing and sequestering carbon dioxide from coal-fired power plants, has chosen a place to put this greenhouse gas: in Morgan County, Ill., about 32 miles from a power plant in Meredosia, Ill., that was chosen for the project. Ameren The FutureGen project would ship carbon dioxide by pipeline from this power plant in Meredosia, Ill., and inject it into a porous layer of rock. The site must still pass an environmental review and, perhaps more important, the government’s policy must be maintained long enough to get the project done. The government abandoned a previous effort as too expensive. But project leaders described the selection of a preferred site as a major step forward. They also said that they were encouraged that about 30 communities had expressed interest in hosting the project, which comes complete with a visitor center and about 1,000 construction jobs. While tremendous attention has focused on how to capture a stream of carbon dioxide, less time has been spent on the essential companion technology, sequestration. The plan is to ship the carbon dioxide by pipeline and then inject it into a porous layer of rock called the Mount Simon Sandstone, which lies under several Midwestern states. At the Morgan County site, the rock is about 850 feet thick, beneath several hundred feet of a cap rock called the Eau Claire Shale. FutureGen has moved around a bit; the power plant was originally supposed to be built from scratch in Mattoon, Ill., using a technology that cooks coal into a fuel gas made up of carbon monoxide and hydrogen; the carbon monoxide then reacts with water to form carbon dioxide and more hydrogen. The hydrogen is burned and the carbon dioxide is set aside for sequestration. But the Bush administration pulled the plug on that project because it considered the costs too high. The new version, dubbed FutureGen 2.0, is using an old and barely used oil-fired power plant in Meredosia. It will be reconfigured to rely on coal and pure oxygen so that the emissions will be nearly pure carbon dioxide. In both cases, the Mount Simon Sandstone was the likely repository. It is filled with salty water, which has no economic value, according to Kenneth K. Humphreys, chief executive of the FutureGen Alliance, a consortium of companies that will build and operate the project. Thus future human intrusion is unlikely, he said. But exactly how the carbon dioxide will behave is uncertain. The goal is to inject 1.3 million tons per year for 30 years, and at the end of that period, the gas might cover 2,500 acres, or perhaps 10,000, he said. Technicians will monitor the underground spread of the carbon dioxide, which will be under such pressure that it will become a liquid, and could vary the speed at which they inject it, the number of wells, or the depth, Mr. Humphreys said, as they learn more about the injection process. One sequestration demonstration is already under way in West Virginia, on the banks of the Ohio River, but it is far smaller: it uses carbon dioxide captured from an existing coal plant owned by American Electric Power. Carbon dioxide from a plant that turns coal into methane, a component of natural gas, is used to help force oil to the surface at a Canadian oil field. Recently local residents said that carbon dioxide was leaking, although this has not been clearly established. But among the many steps needed before injection can begin in the FutureGen project is a change in Illinois’s liability law, Mr. Humphreys said. Plans call for the FutureGen consortium to monitor the site for 50 years after closing it, taking out a commercial insurance policy and setting up a fund in case of problems. But the ultimate responsibility, if FutureGen followed all its permit requirements, would fall to the state of Illinois.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/08/keep-courts-out-of-climate-policy-g-o-p-lawmakers-say/?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Keep Courts Out of Climate Policy, G.O.P. Lawmakers Say<date>February 8, 2011, 11:13 am</date><text>Three leading Republicans in Congress filed a brief with the Supreme Court late Monday asking the justices to overturn a lower court ruling that allowed several states and environmental groups to sue electric utilities over their global warming emissions. The lawmakers – Senator James Inhofe of Oklahoma and Representatives Fred Upton of Michigan and Ed Whitfield of Kentucky – submitted a 13-page friend of the court brief in the case, American Electric Power v. Connecticut, No. 10-174. The Supreme Court will hear arguments in April in an appeal of a 2009 decision by the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in New York, allowing a suit filed against five utilities by eight states, New York City and three land trusts to proceed. Bloomberg News Senator James Inhofe A lower court had dismissed the suit, calling regulations of emissions a matter to be decided in the political, not legal, system. The suit, originally brought in 2004, argued that the utilities were creating a public nuisance by burning coal and pouring heat-trapping gases into the atmosphere, adding to the problem of global warming. The states and groups that filed the case considered it an alternative to legislative or regulatory action on climate change, which was then – as now – moving at a snail’s pace. A number of other business, labor, legal and local government groups have also filed briefs in the case, but the petition from the three Republican lawmakers is novel. The three lawmakers have all expressed skepticism about the reality of human-caused global warming, yet in their brief they say that the political system, not the courts, should deal with the problem. The three just last week circulated draft legislation that would prevent the Environmental Protection Agency from issuing any regulations on greenhouse gases beyond those already written for vehicles. At the same time, they oppose any comprehensive legislation to deal with climate-altering gases because they say they believe the science is uncertain and the costs of reining in carbon dioxide and other emissions will be too high. Yet in their brief they say there is no need for judicial intervention because Congress and the administration are already dealing aggressively with the matter. In this, they take the same position as the Obama administration, which has also argued that the appeals court decision should be overturned because the administration is hard at work on the problem and does not need the courts’ help. “E.P.A. has already begun taking actions to address carbon-dioxide emissions,” the Obama administration’s acting solicitor general, Neal Katyal, said in a brief last August. “That regulatory approach is preferable to what would result if multiple district courts — acting without the benefit of even the most basic statutory guidance — could use common-law nuisance claims to sit as arbiters of scientific and technology-related disputes and de facto regulators of power plants and other sources of pollution.” The Republicans agree, to a point. “This case involves political and public policy matters that are being resolved by the legislative and executive branches of government,” the three Republicans wrote in their brief. “These public policy determinations are necessarily within the purview of the Congress and the executive branch, not the judicial branch, because of the complexity and significance of the environmental and economic issues that they raise.” Mr. Inhofe, the senior Republican on the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, is the most outspoken climate change skeptic in Congress. Mr. Upton is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee; Mr. Whitfield is chairman of the panel’s subcommittee panel on Energy and Power. Mr. Whitfield’s committee is planning a hearing on Wednesday to grill administration officials about plans to regulate carbon dioxide emissions. Mr. Inhofe is one of the scheduled witnesses. Their brief lists several actions, from the Clean Air Act in 1963 through recent energy legislation, that show that the political branches of government are acting on the problem of emissions. They say that the government is spending billions of dollars a year in climate change research and mitigation efforts. They note that the United States ratified the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change and participates actively in global climate diplomacy. They even note that in 2009 the House passed a sweeping cap and trade bill to control greenhouse gas emissions – legislation that all three of them vigorously opposed. “No one can seriously question that the executive branch, acting through the E.P.A., the Department of State and various other departments and agencies, has aggressively employed its various statutory authorities in acting on climate change,” they write in their brief. They go on to say that some of the recent actions by the Obama administration, including its intent to regulate greenhouse gases under the Clean Air Act, “may well exceed the authorities Congress has vested in the executive, and are at a minimum extremely misguided.” Misguided or not, the brief continues, the issue should be debated and resolved by representatives and officials who are elected or otherwise accountable to the public. “Climate change issues are extraordinarily complex, both because of the climate science itself and because any proposed solutions to address climate change have enormous domestic, international and economic implications,” they said. “This case calls for determinations that are not appropriate for judicial discretion,” they add a few pages later. “As such, they raise public policy issues that necessarily should be determined by the Congress and the executive branch precisely because they are so complex and controversial.” Joseph Mendelson, director of global warming policy at the National Wildlife Federation and a lead lawyer on the last major global warming case to come before the Supreme Court, Massachusetts v. Environmental Protection Agency, No. 05-1120, said that the argument from the three Republicans was “ironic at the least.” “It’s rather amazing what they’ve done,” he said in an interview. “They’re trying to foreclose action by anybody.” The Supreme Court is scheduled to hear arguments in the Connecticut case on April 19. Justice Sonia Sotomayor recused herself because she sat on the Second Circuit panel that heard the case, although she did not take part in the ruling.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/30/business/energy-environment/30utility.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Power Industry Seeks Fresh Talent to Run the Grid of Tomorrow<date>Published: December 29, 2010</date><text>GRANVILLE, Ohio — Speaking to a classroom of seventh and eighth graders at the middle school here, Lisa Magnuson shared a popular dictum from the power industry: if Alexander Graham Bell, the inventor of the telephone, could see how his technology had evolved over the last century, how would he react?“He’d be amazed,” offered one student, mentioning that his cellphone can play music, display movies and send text messages. And if Thomas Edison, the pioneer of power distribution, were to return? “He’d probably go, ‘Wow, everything is still the same,’ ” said Ms. Magnuson, the director of marketing for Silver Spring Networks, which produces hardware and software to make the electric grid as smart as the phone network. To pull off the modernization, Ms. Magnuson and others are trying to persuade this generation of fidgety teenagers to put their creativity to work in the power industry once they graduate. “We want to help make utilities cool again,” she said. The power companies desperately need a jolt of youthful energy. The industry and the creaky distribution system it manages are on the cusp of a major technological overhaul just as about half of electric utility employees are expected to retire in the next 5 to 10 years. At the same time, the federal government and utilities are spending billions of dollars to upgrade the electric grid with intelligent digital technology so they can vary a customer’s price for power based on the time of day and more seamlessly integrate electricity from a variety of sources like wind and solar. The upgrade would give the power generation and distribution network the sort of nervous system it has lacked since Edison first conceived it in the late 19th century. By some estimates, the smart grid could help reduce electricity use by more than 4 percent a year by 2030 and save $20 billion a year for utilities and their customers. To push along the transformation, educators and government officials, often in partnership with utilities, are drawing up smart grid curriculums for elementary classrooms, vocational schools and university laboratories. In addition to educating youngsters about electricity, the goal is to lure some of the technologically inclined away from Silicon Valley and toward a profession that, in the popular mind, long ago became the province of Homer Simpson drones. Last spring, the energy secretary, Steven Chu, awarded $100 million in stimulus money to 54 training programs in the smart grid aimed at high school and college students around the country. “Building and operating smart grid infrastructure will put tens of thousands of Americans to work,” Mr. Chu said at the time. “Today’s investment will help ensure that we have the work force in place to meet this need.” The Energy Department estimated that some 30,000 workers would be trained because of the grants, which range from $87,000 for the Preparing Occupations for Lineman Education, or Pole, program at the Austin Community College District to $5 million to Florida Power &amp; Light to develop its Gateway to Power Program, which aims to bring industry and academia together to develop power system and smart grid education. And just as Reddy Kilowatt, a cartoon character created by a utility company, was used to promote the benefits of nuclear power to previous generations of students, the electric industry aims to use the new curriculums to promote its vision of the future. “How will the smart grid change your life or your future career?” students are asked in one of the six lessons that Silver Spring Networks, based in California, helped to develop, and which were part of a pilot program this month in Ohio and in Oakland, Calif. “Write a journal entry in which you imagine how life or work will change after the smart grid is ready to go.” Part of the coursework is aimed at preparing young consumers for the arrival of dynamic pricing — the ability to vary the price of electricity throughout the day, based on overall demand, rather than charge one rate all day, as is the norm now. Dynamic pricing is an oft-promoted benefit of the smart grid, although it has proved contentious in some of the early markets where it has been proposed, particularly among ratepayers at home during the day, when the electricity cost is higher. Here in central Ohio, American Electric Power, the big regional utility, was awarded $75 million in stimulus money last year for a $150 million smart-grid pilot project now in development. In addition to replacing roughly 110,000 analog electric meters at customers’ homes with digital meters that can transmit data to and from the utility in real time, A.E.P. — working with Silver Spring Networks and other companies — will deploy and test a full menu of interconnected grid technologies, like digital management, distribution networks, plug-in hybrid cars and smart appliances.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/27/nyregion/27cuomoside.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Where Andrew Cuomo Made His Mark as Attorney General<date>Published: October 26, 2010</date><text>ENVIRONMENTAL CASES Upholding a tradition that goes back to the days when Attorney General Robert Abrams made it his business to clean up the Love Canal toxic waste site, Andrew M. Cuomo has displayed sharp elbows when it comes to environmental protection. He filed lawsuits against the Bush administration’s Environmental Protection Agency over global warming and American Electric Power, the nation’s largest power producer, when emissions from its Midwestern plants were blowing into New York. Just as telling are the less glamorous cases he brought forcing operators of mobile home parks to fix conditions that were imperiling the health of residents.PUBLIC INTEGRITY CASES Eager to show he can clean up Albany, Mr. Cuomo has exposed several serious cases of public corruption. He bore down, for instance, on conflicts of interest and schemes in the public pension arena and extracted a guilty plea this month from former State Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, above, a fellow Democrat, who had steered public pension money to a firm that gave him freebies and hired an ally. At the other extreme, Mr. Cuomo’s handling of investigations into two sitting governors invited criticism, and he has yet to resolve a two-year-old investigation looking into whether the Bloomberg administration’s financing of local development corporations violated state lobbying laws. COLLEGE LOAN CASES Fast-tracking a case that had been initiated just before he took office, Mr. Cuomo quickly amassed evidence that colleges were steering students to lenders that gave the colleges kickbacks or furnished insiders with various goodies. Still unclear, three years later, is what is to become of the $13 million in settlements that Mr. Cuomo wrung from the targeted companies. His latest plan envisions taking $3 million to create a 24-hour call center and Web site that gives students unvarnished advice about loans, with the balance being spent on advertising. For now, it is all stalled because Mr. Cuomo’s advisers say they do not want to run afoul of election laws by running advertisements that indirectly help his campaign. MUNICIPAL CONSOLIDATION One of Mr. Cuomo’s proudest legislative victories was the legislation he pushed through last year that makes it easier for certain municipalities and special districts to consolidate or go dark. His staff counted more than 10,000 such entities in New York, as varied as fire protection districts and public entities that deal with duck waste. Pitched as a way for taxpayers to save money, the bill was opposed by volunteer firefighters who worried that their livelihoods might be at risk. Drafters of the bill overcame some resistance by pointing out that the bill, as written, was entirely optional — one reason there has been only a smattering of municipalities that have expressed interest in making use of the law since its March 21 effective date.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/22/science/earth/22carbon.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">States Can Sue Utilities Over Emissions<date>Published: September 21, 2009</date><text>A two-judge panel of a federal appeals court has ruled that big power companies can be sued by states and land trusts for emitting carbon dioxide. The decision, issued Monday, overturns a 2005 District Court decision that the question was political, not judicial. Skip to next paragraph Related Refitted to Bury Emissions, Plant Draws Attention (September 22, 2009) A panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in New York, ruled that eight states  California, Connecticut, Iowa, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Wisconsin  as well as New York City and three land trusts could proceed with a suit against American Electric Power, Southern Corporation, the Tennessee Valley Authority, Xcel Energy and Cinergy Corporation, all large coal-burning utilities. The case, brought in 2004, said the defendants were creating a “public nuisance” and sought reductions in emissions that scientists say are changing the climate. The states cited studies from the United Nations and the National Academy of Sciences that predicted damage and said in fact that their environments had already been damaged. The land trusts said that an increase in sea level would inundate their properties, among other problems. The power companies said that the federal courts had never recognized an argument in common law that greenhouse gas emissions contribute to global warming, and that if action were to be taken, Congress would have to do it. The lower court agreed that the issues demonstrated the “transcendently legislative nature of this litigation,” and that if they found in favor of the states and the land trusts, the courts would have to figure out how to cap emissions, set reduction goals and a schedule for achieving them, and take other steps that would seem to require legislation. The appeal was heard by a three-judge panel, but one of the judges, Sonia Sotomayor, was elevated to the Supreme Court in August. The case was decided by Joseph M. McLaughlin, who was appointed to the court in 1990 by the first President George Bush, and Peter W. Hall, nominated in 2003 by the second President Bush. Matt Pawa, the lead lawyer for the Open Space Institute and the Audubon Society of New Hampshire, both plaintiffs, said in a statement that “for hundreds of years, courts have been there to protect citizens from harm,” and could do so again now. At the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group that was not a plaintiff, David Doniger, a senior lawyer, said the best way to fight global warming was to have Congress act. But he added, “The court’s decision guarantees that if the Congress fails to do its job, or blocks the E.P.A. from doing its job, the biggest power companies will still be held accountable in the federal courts.” At American Electric Power, Pat D. Hemlepp, a spokesman, said the company’s lawyers had not decided whether to appeal. But he added: “We don’t feel that litigation is a proper avenue to address climate concerns. In our view, it’s a policy issue.” “Legislation would be the best approach, and that’s happening now,” Mr. Hemlepp said, referring to a bill that has passed the House and that the Senate may take up this year. Many participants in the global warming debate appear to prefer a decision by the Congress, because it could balance competing interests, between and among regions and industries, to cut emissions of global warming gases. But Monday’s decision means that all three branches of the federal government could have a role. In addition to the possibility that Congress will act, the Supreme Court held in April 2007, that global warming gases were a pollutant under the Clean Air Act, and thus could be regulated by the Environmental Protection Agency. More Articles in Science » A version of this article appeared in print on September 22, 2009, on page A18 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/22/science/earth/22coal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Refitted to Bury Emissions, Plant Draws Attention<date>Correction: September 23, 2009Published: September 21, 2009</date><text>NEW HAVEN, W.Va.  Poking out of the ground near the smokestacks of the Mountaineer power plant here are two wells that look much like those that draw natural gas to the surface. But these are about to do something new: inject a power plant’s carbon dioxide into the earth. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Captured, Then Buried Related Times Topics: Coal Enlarge This Image Kevin Riddell for The New York Times The inside of the plant. The New York Times The Mountaineer plant in New Haven is ready to inject carbon dioxide into the earth. A behemoth built in 1980, long before global warming stirred broad concern, Mountaineer is poised to become the world’s first coal-fired power plant to capture and bury some of the carbon dioxide it churns out. The hope is that the gas will stay deep underground for millennia rather than entering the atmosphere as a heat-trapping pollutant. The experiment, which the company says could begin in the next few days, is riveting the world’s coal-fired electricity sector, which is under growing pressure to develop technology to capture and store carbon dioxide. Visitors from as far as China and India, which are struggling with their own coal-related pollution, have been trooping through the plant. The United States still depends on coal-fired plants, many of them built decades ago, to meet half of its electricity needs. Some industry experts argue that retrofitting them could prove far more feasible than building brand new, cleaner ones. Yet the economic viability of the Mountaineer plant’s new technology, known as carbon capture and sequestration, remains uncertain. The technology is certain to devour a substantial amount of the plant’s energy output  optimists say 15 percent, and skeptics, 30 percent. Some energy experts argue that it could prove even more expensive than solar or nuclear power. And as with any new technology, even the engineers are unsure how well it will work: will all of the carbon dioxide stay put? Environmentalists who oppose coal mining and coal energy of any kind worry that sequestration could simply trade one problem, global warming, for another one, the pollution of water supplies. Should the carbon dioxide mix with water underground and form carbonic acid, they say, it could leach poisonous materials from rock deep underground that could then seep out. Given the depths to which workers have drilled, they also fret that the project could cause earthquakes, although experts at the Environmental Protection Agency discount the risk of catastrophe. More broadly, some environmentalists argue that the carbon storage effort could give corporations and consumers another excuse to drag their heels in supplanting coal dependence with an embrace of renewable energy sources like the sun and wind. “Coal is the drug of choice of a major industry with a lot of political power,” said David H. Holtz, executive director of Progress Michigan, an environmental group. Instead of adopting carbon capture, which Mr. Holtz likens to a methadone cure for addiction, he argues that the industry would do better to go cold turkey. “There’s no evidence that burying carbon dioxide in the earth is a better strategy than aggressively pursuing other alternatives that clearly are better for the environment and will in the long run be less costly,” Mr. Holtz said. But power company officials say the effort is the energy industry’s best hope of stanching carbon dioxide emissions over the next few decades. “I really believe, in my heart of hearts, that coal is going to be burned around the world for years to come,” said Michael Morris, chairman and president of American Electric Power, which owns the plant here. “Retrofitting is going to be essential.” American Electric Power is the nation’s largest electricity producer, with a coal-fired grid stretching across 11 states. If all goes smoothly, this week engineers will begin pumping carbon dioxide, converted to a fluid, into a layer of sandstone 7,800 feet below the rolling countryside here and then into a layer of dolomite 400 feet below that. The liquid will squeeze into tiny pores in the rock, displacing the salty water there, and assume a shape something like a squashed football, 30 to 40 feet high and hundreds of yards long. American Electric Power’s plan is to inject about 100,000 tons annually for two to five years, about 1.5 percent of Mountaineer’s yearly emissions of carbon dioxide. Should Congress pass a law controlling carbon dioxide emissions and the new technology proves economically feasible, the company says, it could then move to capture as much as 90 percent of the gas. For now the project consists of the two wells and a small chemical factory. In the factory, smoke diverted from the plant’s chimney is mixed with a chilled ammonia-based chemical. The chemical is then heated, releasing the carbon dioxide, which is pumped deep into the wells. American Electric Power is spending $73 million on the capture and storage effort, which includes half the cost of the factory. Alstom, the manufacturer of the new equipment, paid for the other half of the factory, hoping to develop expertise that will win it a worldwide market. Alstom would not say what it spent, but public figures indicate that the two companies are jointly spending well over $100 million. For energy planners, a crucial question is how much this technology would cost if refined and installed on a bigger scale. The answer remains elusive. Still, many scientists emphasize that Mountaineer is within a dozen miles of four other big coal plants with a combined capacity of 6,000 megawatts, a concentration so great that industry insiders have nicknamed the area Megawatt Alley. If the technology spread to all of them in a cost-effective way, many say, it could have a broad impact on the coal industry. S. Julio Friedmann, leader of the carbon management program at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California, calls this corner of the Ohio River Valley a “must win” region for carbon dioxide storage. Robert Socolow, a Princeton University engineering professor, echoed that sentiment. The nation’s fleet of coal-burning plants “completely dominates our national emissions,” Professor Socolow said. It is also far easier to corral several million tons flowing from a single chimney than a comparable amount coming from tens of millions of car tailpipes or home heating systems, experts point out. Far larger projects for capturing and storing carbon dioxide underground have been under way for several years in Europe and North Africa. In North Dakota, the Great Plains Synfuels plant, which converts coal to methane, takes the leftover carbon dioxide and pumps it through a pipeline to Canada to stimulate oil production there. But Mountaineer is the world’s first electricity plant to capture and store carbon dioxide. A state permit issued to American Electric Power limits the pressure it can use to inject carbon dioxide into the rock. This is to reduce the risk that the injection will crack rock layers above that engineers are counting on to keep the carbon dioxide in place. A nonprofit research group, Battelle Memorial Institute, has installed monitoring wells around the rock that will measure changes in pressure and temperature. Engineers can also send energy pulses through the earth between the wells and measure how fast these travel, as a guide to how the carbon dioxide is spreading. Asked whether the injections of carbon dioxide could increase the frequency or magnitude of the small earthquakes that are common in the area, an E.P.A. official said it seemed unlikely. “With proper site selection and good management, we should be able to implement this safely,” said Dina Kruger, director of the agency’s climate change division. Ms. Kruger also emphasized that the carbon dioxide would be monitored to see if it was seeping. Some local residents are skeptical. “It doesn’t matter to me if a scientist says it may or may not leak,” said Elisa Young, an anti-coal activist who lives nearby on the Ohio side of the river. “That’s not going to stop it from leaking when push comes to shove.” At the same time, many others in this coal-dependent region suggest that the notion that carbon dioxide is a menace has been overplayed. Charles A. Powell, the manager of the Mountaineer plant, who has worked there since it opened three decades ago, pointed out that the gas is given off by every human and animal. “You are breathing out?” he asked a visitor dryly. This article has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: September 23, 2009 Because of an editing error, an article on Tuesday about a coal-fired power plant in West Virginia that is capturing and burying some of the carbon dioxide it generates misstated the materials processed by a plant in North Dakota that captures carbon dioxide and sends it to Canada for storage. That plant, Great Plains Synfuels, converts coal to methane; it does not convert methane to natural gas. (Methane is the principal component of natural gas.) More Articles in Science » A version of this article appeared in print on September 22, 2009, on page A1 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/26/business/energy-environment/26coal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Two Utilities Are Leaving Clean Coal Initiative<date>Published: June 25, 2009</date><text>Two of the nation’s biggest coal-burning utilities said Thursday that they were withdrawing from a $2.4 billion project to demonstrate carbon capture and storage, and would instead pursue their own work in the field. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio American Electric Power Co Inc Go to your Portfolio » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » The announcement by the utilities, Southern Company and American Electric Power, is a blow to the multinational consortium called the FutureGen Alliance. The group is seeking to build a $2.4 billion plant in Mattoon, Ill., that would convert coal to a fuel gas, capture the carbon dioxide and then burn the gas in a turbine to make electricity. Financing for the project was uncertain even before the announcement by the two utilities. The Bush administration had tried to kill FutureGen, saying it was too expensive. But the Obama administration said last week it would restore financing. Michael J. Mudd, chief executive of the alliance, said the group had begun with seven members, and had expanded to 13. After other departures, the group now has nine members, but it is seeking a total of 20. The alliance is a 501(c)(3) voluntary organization; each member has contributed about $2 million. Executives are trying to determine whether costs have fallen because of the drop in the price of materials and construction work that has followed the recession. The federal government has agreed to contribute $1 billion, Mr. Mudd said, in addition to $100 million previously appropriated. The partners will contribute $400 million to $600 million, although that still leaves a shortfall. To cut costs, the alliance had decided that initially, the plant would capture only 60 percent of the carbon dioxide instead of 90 percent as originally planned. Much of the laborious work of picking a site and getting permits is done. But many companies are pursuing alternatives because of the delays created by government’s vacillation in financing. Steve Higginbottom, a spokesman for Southern Company, confirmed that the company had pulled out of the alliance. “The reason we did was to focus on the projects that we are currently involved in with government and industry partners that focus on the carbon capture and sequestration and clean coal technologies,” he said. Melissa McHenry, a spokeswoman for American Electric Power, cited the current economic conditions, a cut in the company’s capital budget as well as the shortfall in the FutureGen plan. She said the utility would focus on pursuing its own project at a plant in West Virginia. An environmental group supporting the project, the Natural Resources Defense Council, said it was disappointed with the news. “We really do need an engagement with the private sector in this,” Henry Henderson, the group’s Midwest director, said. “I don’t believe it’s a death knell.” Kate Galbraith contributed reporting. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on June 26, 2009, on page B6 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/17/business/energy-environment/17coal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Stimulus Money Puts Clean Coal Projects on a Faster Track<date>Published: March 16, 2009</date><text>EDWARDSPORT, Ind.  Near the middle of a dusty construction site here stands a patch of land, about the size of two football fields, notable because it is empty. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Duke Energy Corp Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image A. J. Mast for The New York Times Work on Dukes Edwardsport project is being closely watched by environmental interests. A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Duke Energy has high hopes for this two-acre plot: If all goes right, and there is a happy convergence of technology, money and federal energy policy, the construction project could become the first environment-friendly coal-fired power plant in the nation. The company is studying a method for capturing the carbon dioxide produced by using coal and storing the gas underground, preventing it from entering the atmosphere. Machines to separate carbon dioxide from other elements in the coal may someday stand on the empty land. For years, scientists have been experimenting with ways to “clean” coal, a carbon-heavy fuel that countries around the world increasingly rely on. But the technology for carbon capture and storage has been tried only on a small scale. Governments have not required companies to do what Duke is proposing here, in part because costs were so uncertain. The allocation of $3.4 billion in the federal stimulus bill for carbon capture and sequestration, as carbon storage is often called, however, has allowed Duke Energy and other companies to consider mounting full-scale projects. The federal money is the latest sign of a growing interest worldwide in clean coal technologies, which backers believe could prove one of the most significant ways to tackle global warming. The projects are being watched closely by environmentalists, engineers and energy officials. The Duke effort, said John Thompson, a coal expert at an environmental group, the Clean Air Task Force, “may be the first commercial carbon sequestration site in the United States.” If Duke is successful, the plant could be capturing about 18 percent of its carbon dioxide emissions within four or five years, and an additional 40 percent a few years after that. Carbon dioxide is the main heat-trapping gas linked to global warming. Duke already received some money under the Energy Policy Act of 2005 to build a $2.35 billion coal-burning power plant, the largest new construction project in Indiana. The site here is already crawling with workmen and heavy machinery. The new plant will differ from conventional coal plants in significant ways, cooking the coal into a fuel gas rather than burning it as a powder, and then thoroughly cleaning the gas and burning it in a jet engine, similar to that used to burn natural gas. Emissions of conventional pollutants, like sulfur, soot and smog-forming nitrogen, will be extremely low. Two other such “gasification” plants already operate, in Florida and Indiana. Duke’s first addition would be to use a machine to strip the carbon dioxide out of the fuel gas. Duke is conducting a $17 million study of that idea, and has asked permission from its regulators to study a second step, to capture an additional 40 percent or so of the carbon dioxide produced at a later stage. The carbon would then be stored in a deep well on the site or sent by pipeline to an old oil field, where it would stimulate oil production. Part of the test is meant to demonstrate that carbon dioxide can safely stay put underground. Other companies around the country also are exploring carbon capture and storage projects. According to a recent report by Emerging Energy Research, a consulting firm, Illinois has passed legislation that could require its utilities to buy electricity from plants that sequester their carbon. And six other states are considering legislation to help pay for carbon capture or ease the way for carbon storage. There are several competing technologies for approaching the problem  more than the money in the stimulus bill can pay for. And experts say that before new methods can be commercialized, projects need three to five years of planning and construction, followed by eight to 10 years of actual pumping of carbon dioxide into the ground. “We need to get off the dime with this and build some full scale projects to demonstrate this technology at scale,” said Edward S. Rubin, a professor of environmental engineering at Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, “but the price tag per project is $800 million to $1 billion.” The Edwardsport venture might prove a little cheaper. The first step, capturing the carbon dioxide created when coal is turned into a fuel gas, would add 5 percent to 15 percent to the initial $2.35 billion cost, according to W. Michael Womack, vice president of Duke Energy in charge of the project. In the second stage, one of the components of the fuel gas, carbon monoxide, is mixed with water to make hydrogen, for fuel, and carbon dioxide, for sequestration. The cost of that is “a little fuzzier,” he said, and probably higher than the cost for the first step. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on March 17, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD1230F936A15753C1A9619C8B63&amp;ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utility's Profit Surges<date>Published: October 25, 2007</date><text>American Electric Power said Wednesday that its third-quarter earnings rose 54 percent, helped by a warmer than normal summer that increased energy usage. A.E.P., one of the nation's largest power generators, said it made $407 million, or $1.02 a share, for the quarter that ended Sept. 30, compared with a profit of $265 million, or 67 cents a share, a year ago, when it recorded a charge for the sale of a plant in Louisiana. Revenue rose 6 percent to $3.8 billion, from $3.6 billion last year.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/15/opinion/15mon2.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Temporary Victory on Clean Air<date>Published: October 15, 2007</date><text>Last weeks record-breaking consent decree requiring American Electric Power, the nations largest utility, to pay $4.6 billion to clean up its act represents a satisfying, if delayed victory for the Clinton administration and other plaintiffs who brought the suit eight years ago. More than anything, though, it is a victory for millions of people downwind of the companys plants who have been forced to breathe dirty air. But before people start jumping for joy, they should know that the Bush administration, while claiming some credit for this settlement, is still actively trying to undermine the very law on which it was based. The law in question is a key provision in the Clean Air Act called new source review. It says that companies that significantly upgrade a plant in order to generate more power must also install state-of-the-art controls to deal with the increased pollution. The utilities have long resented this law, which requires costly investments, and Vice President Dick Cheney targeted it for extinction in his infamous energy report in 2001. Various courts, including the Supreme Court, have upheld the law. Even so, the administration has paid little attention and is still doing everything it can to torpedo the law by administrative means. The most recent assault is a proposed rule that would exempt plants from having to install new controls as long as their hourly rate of emissions does not increase as a result of any plant upgrade  even if total emissions skyrocket because the upgrades enable a plant to run longer and harder. The A.E.P. settlement stems from an enforcement action brought in 1999 by the Clinton administration and nine state attorneys general, including New Yorks Eliot Spitzer, against A.E.P. and six other utilities in the Midwest and South. The case was joined by 13 advocacy groups. Under the settlement, the company, which bitterly resisted the original suit, has agreed to install $4.6 billion in new pollution-control measures at 16 existing plants. The investments will sharply reduce the companys emissions of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and nitrogen oxide, which contributes to urban smog. A.E.P. can well afford the settlement, which gives the company a generous time frame in which to meet its responsibilities. Indeed, the company had already committed much of the money in anticipation of the settlement as well as investments that will be required under other clean air laws. The agreement also includes a covenant that effectively shields the company from further government action while it installs the new controls. Some environmental groups warn that this covenant, which the Clinton administration inserted in similar agreements, only creates more room for mischief-making by the company. But far more worrisome are the proposed changes to the underlying new source review provision. These changes would have made it almost impossible to bring the case against A.E.P. in the first place, much less win it. More Articles in Opinion »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/09/business/09power.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Big Utility Says It Will Settle 8-Year-Old Pollution Suit<date>Published: October 9, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, Oct. 8  American Electric Power, one of the nations largest utilities, is expected to announced that it has reached an agreement to settle a long-running lawsuit over emissions from its coal-fired power plants. The suit was filed eight years ago by the Environmental Protection Agency, 8 states and 14 environmental organizations. The company will spend more than $1 billion on improvements to its plants over the next 12 years, will pay a civil penalty of $15 million and will spend another $60 million on environmental mitigation, a spokesman, Pat D. Hemlepp, confirmed Monday night, after The Associated Press carried a report on the settlement. A.E.P. will not admit to any wrongdoing, Mr. Hemlepp said. The agreement, to be filed on Tuesday in Federal District Court in Columbus, Ohio, before Judge Edmund A. Sargus Jr., would settle a suit brought by the federal government in 1999. That suit, and similar ones filed against other companies, argued that A.E.P. had violated a provision of the Clean Air Act called new source review. Under that clause, a company undertaking major work on old power plants activates a requirement that the plants be brought up to current pollution standards. But A.E.P. argued that its work was maintenance and not covered by the provision. As part of the settlement, Mr. Hemlepp said, the government agreed to allow A.E.P. to make efficiency improvements on other old plants without coming under the new source review provisions. That work includes replacing turbine blades to allow the plants to produce more electricity on the same amount of fuel. The company has held off on such changes because of regulatory uncertainty, he said. He said the company had agreed to install devices that reduce emissions of sulfur, which causes acid rain, and of nitrogen oxides, which contribute to smog, at each of two twin coal burners in Rockport, in southern Indiana, one in 2017 and the other in 2019. It will also install antipollution equipment at a plant in Clinch River, Va., he said. The total value of the projects, in todays dollars, is $1.6 billion, he said. In addition, he said, the company had agreed to operate nitrogen oxide removal plants, in a process called selective catalytic reduction, year-round at three coal stations that already have the equipment but now use it only in summer smog season. Those are Mountaineer and Amos, both in West Virginia, and Muskingum River, in Ohio. That will begin in 2008, he said, but added that existing environmental regulations would have required us to do that by 2009 anyway. A.E.P. operates in 11 states. The Associated Press, citing unnamed sources, said the company would pay $4.6 billion to reduce pollution. Mr. Hemlepp said that figure took into account money spent on projects that were completed, under way or had already been announced. The announcement on the Rockport project, he said, was unusual for the company because it does not generally announce work that is a decade away. The lawsuit against A.E.P. was part of a large enforcement action by the E.P.A. and the Justice Department that began in 1999. The government accused A.E.P. and six other giant electric companies in the Midwest and the South of defying antipollution regulations and illegally contaminating the air breathed by millions of Americans. In the suits, the government said the companies wanted to prolong the lives of old plants without modernizing them. We were adamant at the time that we had not violated the provisions. That is still strongly our position, Mr. Hemlepp, the company spokesman, said last night. Matthew L. Wald reported from Washington and Stephanie Saul from New York. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/11/business/11battery.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utility Will Use Batteries to Store Wind Power<date>Published: September 11, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, Sept. 10  American Electric Power, a coal-burning utility company that is looking for ways to connect more wind power to its grid, plans to announce on Tuesday that it will install huge banks of high-technology batteries. The batteries are costly and their use at such a big scale has not been demonstrated, but they may be an essential complement to renewable power, experts say. Were looking at what we believe the grid of the future is going to be, said Carl L. English, president of A.E.P. Were going to need a significant amount of storage if for no other reason than to take greatest advantage of alternative energy sources like wind power. The investment would position the company well if any of the 11 states in its service territory establish a minimum quota for renewable energy, or if Congress sets a national standard, company executives said; it would also help if carbon controls were instituted and wind power were to gain a financial advantage over coal. An expert not involved in the program, Edgar DeMeo of Renewable Energy Consulting Services, said, They must think theres enough potential there so they want get a better handle on how it works. But Mr. DeMeo and others said that wind energy had substantial room to grow before storage became necessary. American Electric Powers batteries will be used to smooth the power delivery from wind turbines. They can charge at night, when the wind is strong but prices are low, and give the electricity back the next afternoon, when there is hardly any wind but power prices are many times higher, company officials said. That strategy would reduce the amount of power generated from inefficient peak-demand units. The batteries can also insert energy into the grid during brief voltage drops, reducing the chance of a blackout and stabilizing the grid for all users. They may also delay or eliminate the need for transmission upgrades in some areas, the company said. At least at this stage, saving money by storing a windmills production for peak-price hours will be difficult. The cost is very high, $27 million for six megawatts of capacity, or about $4,500 a kilowatt, including the price of substation improvements. Building a gas turbine of that size to meet peak needs would cost substantially less. But the battery system would be able to store power made from wind, a form of generation that does not produce any carbon dioxide. The batteries can each deliver one megawatt of power  enough to run a medium-size shopping center  for a little more than seven hours. Replenished nightly, they give back about 80 percent of the electricity put into them. Each is the size of a double-decker bus, and installation is not permanent; they can be moved to another site as the need arises. The batteries will be built by NGK Insulators Ltd. of Japan. They use a sodium sulfur chemistry and operate at temperatures of more than 800 degrees Fahrenheit. And while the batteries are large by the standards of previous installations, they are small relative to wind production; one battery would hold about as much energy as a single large wind machine could produce in a day, Mr. DeMeo pointed out. And they are small relative to total energy demand. But, he said, If we ever really do get cheap storage, and thats a possibility, thats a game changer. A.E.P. intends to have 1,000 megawatts of energy storage on its system in the next decade, according to the company, and at least 25 megawatts from batteries of this type. A range of options is available for the remainder of the storage, including the use of plug-in hybrid cars, Mr. English said. The idea behind plug-in hybrids is that the owner of a car would charge the batteries every night when demand and cost of electricity were low. The next day, under a contract between the utility company and the driver, the car would be left plugged when not in use, and the power company could reverse the flow of electricity and draw power out of its batteries during times of peak demand. Enough power would be left in the batteries to start the engine, so that a driver returning to a drained car could still run it on gasoline until the batteries could be charged again at night. It would take more than 1,000 such vehicles to equal one of the sodium-sulfur batteries, however. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/15/business/15carbon.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">In a Test of Capturing Carbon Dioxide, Perhaps a Way to Temper Global Warming<date>Published: March 15, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, March 14  American Electric Power, a major electric utility, is planning the largest demonstration yet of capturing carbon dioxide from a coal-fired power plant and pumping it deep underground. Skip to next paragraph Related Push to Fix Ozone Layer and Slow Global Warming (March 15, 2007) Various experts consider that approach, known as sequestration, essential to reining in climate change by preventing the gas from being added to the atmospheric blanket that promotes global warming. The project, to be announced Thursday by American Electric Power, based in Columbus, Ohio, will use a new process  so far tested only at laboratory scale  that uses chilled ammonia to absorb the gas for collection. The process was developed by Alstom, a major manufacturer of generating equipment, and aims to reduce the amount of energy required to capture the carbon dioxide. Some experts have estimated that nearly a third of a power plants energy output might be needed to pull carbon dioxide from the waste stream. Alstom hopes to hold it to 15 percent. The cost must be kept as low as possible if the technology is to be used on a wide scale. Congress is seen as unlikely to impose enormously expensive restraints on emissions. And under proposals to cap emissions nationally and let companies trade credits for extra reductions, only the cheapest methods of reducing greenhouse gases would thrive in the marketplace. A report released Wednesday by researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology called for prompt work on demonstrating the necessary sequestration technologies. The co-chairman of that study, Ernest J. Moniz, a former assistant secretary of energy, said the unusually large scale of the American Electric project made it quite relevant. Climate policy specialists said the project was a significant test of the technology and also a sign that American Electric, which relies on coal for fuel, is expecting carbon emission limits of some kind. The initial trial, at the companys Mountaineer plant in New Haven, W.Va., will take a portion of the carbon dioxide from the flue, compress it into liquid form at more than 1,000 pounds of pressure per square inch, and inject it 9,000 feet below the earths surface, a technique that experts say is not well understood but would be essential to large-scale carbon sequestration. The project will begin next year, the company said. A demonstration 6 to 12 times that size, which would be commercial scale, will be conducted soon after at a plant in Oklahoma. This basically represents jumping ahead, said Stuart M. Dalton, director of generation at the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility consortium, in Palo Alto, Calif. His organization has helped organize a test, one-sixth the size of the West Virginia test, that is supposed to begin this year at a coal-fired power plant in Wisconsin. That carbon will be re-released. Some plants use a different separation technology to capture and sell food-grade carbon dioxide, used in making carbonated beverages. Worldwide, there are several places where carbon dioxide is injected into deep wells, but none are power plants. At the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, David G. Hawkins, a climate expert, said, Under any plausible scenarios of global coal use, we are going to need carbon dioxide capture and storage. But Mr. Hawkins and other environmentalists said that Congress should not wait for the outcome of demonstrations like American Electrics to order mandatory controls on carbon emissions. Michael G. Morris, the president, chairman and chief executive of the utility, said in a telephone interview that sequestration would be necessary for society but was also enlightened self-interest on the part of his company. The Energy Department has concentrated on a different technology, converting coal to a gas and taking the carbon out before the gas is burned. American Electric is also pursuing that technology, but the chilled-ammonia method is applicable to traditional coal plants that use pulverized coal technology, and dozens of them are on the drawing boards. You, me and everyone else needs to understand that the government talks big and moves slow, Mr. Morris said. He said the demonstration would cost $800 million, including work to remove conventional pollutants like soot and sulfur dioxide before carbon separation. The company will seek federal grants and will ask state regulators to let it charge customers. Carbon from the larger trial at the Oklahoma plant will be sold for injection into old oil fields where pressure and production have fallen. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/28/business/28coal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">2 Industry Leaders Bet on Coal but Split on Cleaner Approach<date>Published: May 28, 2006</date><text>WRIGHT, Wyo. — More than a century ago a blustery Wyoming politician named Fenimore Chatterton boasted that his state alone had enough coal to "weld every tie that binds, drive every wheel, change the North Pole into a tropical region, or smelt all hell!"His words seem prophetic. The future for American energy users is playing out in coal-rich areas like northeastern Wyoming, where dump trucks and bulldozers swarm around 80-foot-thick seams at a Peabody Energy strip mine here, one of the largest in the world. Coal, the nation's favorite fuel in much of the 19th century and early 20th century, could become so again in the 21st. The United States has enough to last at least two centuries at current use rates — reserves far greater than those of oil or natural gas. And for all the public interest in alternatives like wind and solar power, or ethanol from the heartland, coal will play a far bigger role. But the conventional process for burning coal in power plants has one huge drawback: it is one of the largest manmade sources of the gases responsible for global warming. Many scientists say that sharply reducing emissions of these gases could make more difference in slowing climate change than any other move worldwide. And they point out that American companies are best positioned to set an example for other nations in adopting a new technique that could limit the environmental impact of the more than 1,000 coal-fired power projects on drawing boards around the world. It is on this issue, however, that executives of some of the most important companies in the coal business diverge. Their disagreement is crucial in the debate over how to satisfy Americans' energy appetite without accelerating climate change. One of those executives, Michael G. Morris, runs American Electric Power, the nation's largest coal consumer and biggest producer of heat-trapping carbon dioxide emissions from its existing plants. He is spearheading a small movement within the industry to embrace the new technology. His company plans to build at least two 600-megawatt plants, in Ohio and West Virginia, at an estimated cost of as much as $1.3 billion each. The company says these plants are not only better for the environment but also in the best interests of even its cost-conscious shareholders. While they would cost 15 to 20 percent more to build, Mr. Morris says they would be far less expensive to retrofit with the equipment needed to move carbon dioxide deep underground, instead of releasing it to the sky, if limits are placed on emissions of global warming gases. "Leave the science alone for a minute," Mr. Morris said in an interview at the Columbus, Ohio, headquarters of his company. "The politics around climate issues are very real. That's why we need to move on this now." But most in the industry are not making that bet. Among them is Gregory H. Boyce, chief executive of Peabody Energy, the largest private-sector coal producer in the world thanks in part to its growing operations here in Wyoming and with aspirations to operate coal-fired plants of its own. Mr. Boyce's company alone controls reserves with more energy potential than the oil and gas reserves of Exxon Mobil. "We're still not convinced that the technology or cost structure is there to justify going down a path where we're not comfortable," Mr. Boyce said. Mr. Boyce's view has prevailed. No more than a dozen of the 140 new coal-fired power plants planned in the United States expect to use the new approach. The decisions being made right now in industry and government on how quickly to adopt any new but more costly technologies will be monumental. "Coal isn't going away, so you have to think ahead," said Gavin A. Schmidt, a climate modeler at the Goddard Institute for Space Studies, part of NASA. "Many of these power stations are built to last 50 years." Promise and Perils Michael Morris and Gregory Boyce, both kingpins in their industries, have a lot in common. They do a lot of business together — Mr. Morris is one of Mr. Boyce's largest customers. They are solid Republicans. And they serve together on various industry initiatives. They agree that energy from coal — the nation's most important source of electricity — is cheaper than energy from oil and natural gas and is competitive with the uranium used in nuclear power plants. And coal could serve new uses: replacing petroleum in making chemicals, for example, or even fueling vehicles. But while sooty smokestacks are no longer a big problem in modern coal-burning power plants, the increase in global warming gases is. A typical 500-megawatt coal-fired electricity plant, supplying enough power to run roughly 500,000 homes, alone produces as much in emissions annually as about 750,000 cars, according to estimates from Royal Dutch Shell. Coal has no stronger evangelist than Mr. Boyce, who grew up on Long Island, the son of a mining executive, and studied engineering in Arizona. He argues that a way to reduce carbon dioxide emissions can be found without having to switch from the existing cheaper coal-burning technology.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/22/business/22emission.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Study Says U.S. Companies Lag on Global Warming<date>Published: March 22, 2006</date><text>European and Asian companies are paying more attention to global warming than their American counterparts. And chemical companies are more focused on the issue than oil companies. Those are two conclusions from "Corporate Governance and Climate Change: Making the Connection," a report that Ceres, a coalition of investors and environmentalists, expects will influence investment decisions. The report, released yesterday, scored 100 global corporations  74 of them based in the United States  on their strategies for curbing greenhouse gases. It covered 10 industries  oil and gas, chemicals, metals, electric power, automotive, forest products, coal, food, industrial equipment and airlines  whose activities were most likely to emit greenhouse gases. It evaluated companies on their board oversight, management performance, public disclosure, greenhouse gas emissions, accounting and strategic planning. The report gave the chemical industry the highest overall marks, with a score of 51.9 out of a possible 100; DuPont, with 85 points, was the highest-ranking American company in any of the industries. Airlines, in contrast, ranked lowest, with a score of 16.6; UAL, the parent of United Airlines, received just 3 points. The study gave General Electric, American Electric Power and Cinergy among the highest scores in their industries. But over all, it concluded, American companies "are playing catch-up" with international competitors like BP, Toyota, Alcan, Unilever and Rio Tinto. "Dozens of U.S. businesses are ignoring the issue with 'business as usual' responses that are putting their companies, and their shareholders, at risk," said Mindy S. Lubber, president of Ceres and director of the Investor Network on Climate Risk, a group whose members control a total of $3 trillion in investment capital. "When Cinergy and American Electric Power are tackling this issue, and Sempra and Dominion Resources are not, that should be a red flag to investors." Art Larson, a Sempra Energy spokesman, took exception to Sempra's score of 24. He said that Sempra, based in San Diego, had been "aggressive in promoting energy efficiency and procuring renewable energy sources," and that "in the area of environmental responsibility, Ceres seems to give more weight to words over action." Hunter Applewhite, a spokesman for Dominion, a big electric utility in Richmond, Va., that scored 27, said the company had no comment on its ranking. Members of the Investor Network said they would take the report's conclusions seriously. "We need to continue to press poor-performing companies to clean up their act," said California's state treasurer, Phil Angelides, who is on the board of two pension funds that collectively manage more than $300 billion in assets. Connecticut's state treasurer, Denise L. Nappier, who administers a $22 billion investment fund, lauded the report as an "unprecedented window into how companies most affected by climate risk are responding at the board level, through C.E.O. leadership and strategic planning." The report does show progress since 2003, when a much smaller Ceres study concluded that most American companies were ignoring the threat of climate change. Since then, Ceres notes, Chevron Texaco has invested $100 million in developing cleaner fuels, Ford Motor introduced the first American hybrid car, American Electric Power has committed itself to "clean coal" technologies and G.E. has introduced its Ecomagination program stressing "green" products. And many companies including Dow Chemical, Anadarko Petroleum and Cinergy have board committees that oversee the curbing of greenhouse gases. "More U.S. companies realize that climate change is an enormous business issue that they need to manage immediately," Ms. Lubber said. Still, the top-scoring company, with 90 points, was BP, a British company that has said it will invest $8 billion in solar, wind and other clean-energy technologies in the next decade. "BP understands that all companies must work to reduce their carbon footprint, starting with fossil fuels," Ms. Lubber said. More Articles in Business »</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/07/national/07cleanair.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Big Utility Goes to Trial Over Pollution<date>Published: July 7, 2005</date><text>COLUMBUS, Ohio, June 6 (AP) - The nation's biggest power generating company broke the Clean Air Act by failing to cut emissions at plants in four states and so fouling the air in the Northeast and harming health, the government argued Wednesday as the trial of a lawsuit against the utility began. The case against the company, American Electric Power, based here in Columbus, is the biggest among several filed in the waning days of the Clinton administration against utilities in the Midwest and the South. The government and eight states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, say the company violated the law when it made major modifications to nine coal-burning plants without installing equipment that would have drastically cut pollution. As a result, the plants, in Ohio, Indiana, Virginia and West Virginia, continue to spew sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and soot, which cause acid rain, smog and haze downwind. The government says the pollutants lead to severe respiratory problems, including asthma and bronchitis. The Bush administration has rewritten the clean-air regulations that the Clinton administration used to sue the utilities, but the new rules are under review by federal courts and consequently have yet to take effect. In any event, American Electric Power and the other sued utilities have argued that work done on the plants was nothing more than routine maintenance, which even under the earlier rules does not require the addition of the expensive pollution controls. The case is being heard without a jury by Judge Edmund A. Sargus Jr. In the first case to go to trial, Judge Sargus ruled for the government against Ohio Edison. That company, owned by the FirstEnergy Corporation, later agreed to spend $1.1 billion for equipment to control emissions at four plants and to pay $33.5 million in fines and environmental initiatives. More Articles in National &gt;</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5DD173BF934A15752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC TO PAY $81 MILLION TO SETTLE LAWSUIT<date>Published: January 27, 2005</date><text>American Electric Power said yesterday that it would pay $81 million to settle a lawsuit by regulators who accused the utility's traders of manipulating prices in the natural gas market. The Commodity Futures Trading Commission sued the company in 2003, accusing the traders of sending thousands of false or misleading reports to publications from 2000 to 2002. American Electric fired five traders in 2002 for giving false information to Platts, a publication whose index is sometimes used as a benchmark to set prices of natural gas contracts. The lawsuit, which sought up to $355 million in penalties, said that American Electric made a profit of $63.5 million from the false reports.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/18/business/18util.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Biggest Utility in New Jersey Seen as Target of Acquisition<date>Published: December 18, 2004</date><text>he Exelon Corporation, the owner of utilities in northern Illinois and eastern Pennsylvania, is in advanced talks to acquire New Jersey's largest utility, P.S.E.&amp;G., for about $12 billion, executives involved in the negotiations said yesterday. A deal would create the largest utility holding company in the country, with annual revenue of more than $26 billion and 25,000 employees. Advertisement Buying P.S.E.&amp;G. would allow John Rowe, Exelon's chief executive, to expand his business in the Northeast, the country's largest electricity market, and add both customers and nuclear power plants to his existing assets in Illinois and Pennsylvania. The Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent of P.S.E.&amp;G., also owns plants in California, Texas and Hawaii, as well as businesses abroad. The move comes a year after Exelon abandoned its offer to buy Illinois Power from Dynegy for $425 million in cash and $1.8 billion in assumed debt. Exelon is also negotiating to assume $14 billion of Public Service debt, the executives involved in the discussions said. While an announcement of a deal may come as soon as next week, the executives cautioned that the terms were not yet complete and the transaction could still fall through. The talks come a year after Exelon abandoned its offer to buy Illinois Power from Dynegy for $425 million in cash and $1.8 billion in assumed debt. Shares of Public Service spiked yesterday afternoon after chat boards talked about a possible merger and the Web site of The Wall Street Journal reported the talks. Shares of Public Service rose to a three-year high of $49.10 before retreating a bit to close up 3.6 percent, at $47.27. Exelon shares fell 1.7 percent, to $41.86. They are up 26 percent this year, compared with an 8 percent gain for Public Service. Exelon runs the largest nuclear power operation in the United States, including the Three Mile Island reactor in Middletown, Pa. The company accounts for 20 percent of the nation's nuclear power capacity, with a total of 10 power stations generating 18,000 megawatts of power. The offer comes as nuclear power advocates are pushing for the construction of new-generation power plants to offset the country's growing reliance on imported oil at a time of soaring energy costs. No nuclear plants have been built in the United States since the accident at the Three Mile Island reactor in March 1979. The acquisition fits with Exelon's pattern of buying troubled companies and turning them around by selling some assets. The companies already jointly operate some power plants. While Exelon has a reputation of being best in class, the parent of P.S.E.&amp;G. is viewed with more caution by industry analysts. The company's Salem power plant in southwestern New Jersey, for example, was cited this year for its poor management and lax maintenance. The latest deal is the largest for the industry since June 2000 when the American Electric Power Company bought the Central and South West Corporation for $12.2 billion, according to Bloomberg data. "There are a lot of economies of scale to be made in the nuclear power industry," said Paul Patterson, an analyst with Glenrock Associates. "Whether you own one plant or 10, there's a certain amount of regulatory framework and oversight to deal with. There will clearly be some synergies there." Exelon, which had revenue of over $15 billion last year, was formed in 2000 when the Philadelphia-based PECO Energy bought Unicom of Chicago. Exelon distributes electricity to 5.1 million consumers in northeastern Illinois and southeastern Pennsylvania. It also sells natural gas to 460,000 customers, according to the company's Web site. "Over time you should see more of these deals in the industry although that's not happening too rapidly because of regulatory hurdles they face," Mr. Patterson said. The offer is expected to face review from the states involved as well as the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, which has oversight over electric and gas utilities. Public Service, based in Newark, employs 10,500 people and had annual revenue of $11 billion in 2003. The company operates power plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania and serves 2 million electric customers and 1.6 million gas customers. The company's roots go back to 1903 when more than 400 electricity and transport companies in New Jersey were amalgamated to form the Public Service Corporation. Its operations abroad include plants in Brazil, Oman and Poland.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/21/us/new-york-city-and-8-states-plan-to-sue-power-plants.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">New York City and 8 States Plan to Sue Power Plants<date>Published: July 21, 2004</date><text>Eight states and New York City plan to sue utilities today that they say are the country's biggest emitters of carbon dioxide, the heat-trapping gas that scientists have linked to global warming.The states and the city will not seek financial penalties but, according to a draft news release, will demand ''substantial cuts'' in the emissions, which they say ''pose serious threats to our health, our economy and our environment.''State and city officials familiar with the effort said yesterday that they would not discuss details of the suit until today. The planned statements and other details had changed since the draft, dated July 16, the officials said, but they did not disavow the basic thrust of the release.The states are California, Connecticut, Iowa, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Wisconsin. The suit will be filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, according to the release.The document was provided to The New York Times and other news outlets by a person at an industry-financed advocacy group in Washington opposed to restrictions on carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases.The companies named as defendants in the draft were American Electric Power, Cinergy, the Southern Company, the Tennessee Valley Authority and Xcel Energy. They operate a total of 174 power plants that burn fossil fuels and that the states and city say emit 646 million tons of carbon dioxide a year, or 10 percent of the national total.''The states are collectively deciding that our economy, our public health, our environment is being damaged,'' Marc Violette, a spokesman for Attorney General Eliot Spitzer of New York, said.Many of the states in this suit as well as others have used suits to pressure out-of-state utilities to curtail nitrogen and sulfur emissions that travel long distances. Other suits have been filed by states and private organizations against the Environmental Protection Agency over carbon dioxide, saying the agency had failed to restrict the gas as a pollutant under the Clean Air Act despite growing evidence that it posed risks.But the new suit is the first state legal action taken directly against companies that discharge carbon dioxide, an unavoidable byproduct of burning coal, oil and other fossil fuels.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/15/us/ohio-groups-question-justice-s-trip-on-utility-jet.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Ohio Groups Question Justice's Trip On Utility Jet<date>Published: May 15, 2004</date><text>A power plant company based in Ohio with a dozen cases in federal courts is flying Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist to Columbus so he can deliver a speech on Saturday at the dedication of a judicial center.The cost of using the corporate jet, which belongs to American Electric Power, one of the nation's largest utilities, is being covered by money raised from a $75-a-plate lunch after the speech at the center, the new home of the Ohio Supreme Court. But environmental groups in Ohio are expressing concern over the propriety of a Supreme Court justice's being accorded favors by a company that has so many active cases, including one that goes to trial next year involving accusations that its plant operations in Ohio violated the Clean Air Act. Environmentalists say the case could reach the Supreme Court.''The idea that A.E.P. is bending over backwards to get the chief justice to Ohio for this speech is offensive,'' said Sandy Buchanan, executive director of Ohio Citizen Action, the state's largest environmental group. ''It could signal a potential conflict of interest, and it's a favor that would not be afforded to the average citizen.''Mike Eckhardt, policy director of the Ohio League of Conservation Voters, said the trip reflected ''suspect behavior'' by Chief Justice Rehnquist, adding, ''You'd have to consider that it would make him not an impartial justice'' in any case involving the power company.The trip, first reported by The Toledo Blade, is the second in recent months by a Supreme Court justice that has prompted objections by environmental groups over the appearance of a conflict of interest. Late last year, with a case before the court involving the Sierra Club and Vice President Dick Cheney, Justice Antonin Scalia invited Mr. Cheney on a duck-hunting trip to Louisiana, and Mr. Cheney reciprocated by providing the transportation, a government jet, at no cost to Justice Scalia.Melissa McHenry, a spokeswoman for the power company, which operates about 80 plants in 11 states, said the company was bearing none of the $3,800 cost for the plane to leave Columbus, pick up Chief Justice Rehnquist in Washington, take him back, then return to Columbus.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/22/magazine/l-something-in-the-air-416576.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Something in The Air<date>Published: February 22, 2004</date><text>There is an interesting paradox in the story of why American Electric Power purchased the property of Cheshire, Ohio (photographs by Mitch Epstein, text by Adam Goodheart, Feb. 8). The problem that bothered residents the most was the result of new pollution-control equipment at our Gavin power plant there. We have spent hundreds of millions of dollars to make Gavin one of the cleanest coal-burning plants in the world. However, equipment we installed to reduce nitrogen oxide emissions reacted unexpectedly with other equipment that reduces sulfur dioxide emissions. We know that is no consolation to the residents who were inconvenienced, but it's an important point for those who may think that this is a case of wanton pollution by an uncaring company. On the contrary, the situation resulted from an unforeseen consequence of doing the right thing.Nicholas J. AshoohSenior Vice PresidentCorporate CommunicationsAmerican Electric PowerColumbus, Ohio</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/22/magazine/l-something-in-the-air-416584.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Something in The Air<date>Published: February 22, 2004</date><text>If 30 years' worth of local newspaper reports are any indication, American Electric Power had a negative impact on local quality of life from its inception. The plant's offer came only after citizens retained environmental attorneys from Washington. Upon agreeing to sell their homes, residents also signed pledges never to sue American Electric Power. By the way, there are heroes in this story -- the ones who stood up to protect the health of their families.Nancy R. BainGeoffrey L. BuckleyAthens, Ohio</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/22/magazine/l-something-in-the-air-416592.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Something in The Air<date>Published: February 22, 2004</date><text>Here is a case in which people largely recognized and accepted the price of coal-burning energy, the power company did the right thing and gave them a generous buyout without a protracted legal battle and people moved on with their lives -- or stayed to live them out in the shadows of the power plant, as they chose. The outcome was bittersweet, yes, but seeing people make choices and live with the costs of progress without victimizing and demonizing themselves and one another was refreshing.Sarah ConnellCampbellGroton, Mass.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/08/magazine/something-in-the-air.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Something in the Air<date>Published: February 08, 2004</date><text>The town, in the end, proved as insubstantial as smoke. More so, really: the houses, the Methodist church and the playground seemed to drift away into the colorless Midwestern sky, while the twin columns of roiling vapor remained, sometimes gray, sometimes yellow, sometimes tinged with venomous blue.It was the blue that doomed Cheshire, Ohio. That was the signature tint of sulfur trioxide and sulfuric acid, emissions from the massive coal-burning power plant whose smokestacks and cooling towers loomed over the town. On days when the smoke was blue, locals complained of sore throats, burning eyes and strange blisters. Sometimes the smog was so thick that cars drove through the streets at noon with their headlights on.As for the rest of the story, it's easy to imagine how Hollywood would script it. One or two plucky souls stand up at a town meeting and vow to fight. The plant's owner, a ruthless multibillion-dollar corporation, strikes back with everything its high-priced attorneys can devise, or worse. Someone has to die. And finally, good (or just possibly evil) prevails.But that's not what happened. Instead, it was something quite undramatic, or at least uncinematic: in a series of town meetings in the spring of 2002, lawyers presented an offer from American Electric Power to buy all of Cheshire for $20 million. The 200-odd residents would have to move, their houses would be razed and their community would cease to exist -- and in exchange they would each receive about three times the assessed value of their property. Though a few dissenters stood up and said they would rather fight than leave, they couldn't sway their neighbors. Nothing rallied the townspeople to resist, to tap the stubborn courage of the American heartland, to show the company that their hometown couldn't be bought. They deliberated for a short while and told American Electric Power that, yes, they would accept the offer. They would waive their right to sue. They would take the money, and they would lose Cheshire.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/04/business/loss-narrows-at-utility.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Loss Narrows at Utility<date>Published: February 04, 2004</date><text>American Electric Power, the Ohio utility, reported a narrower loss in the fourth quarter on Tuesday, hurt by lowered values for some operations being sold and losses from discontinued operations.The company reported a loss of $762 million, or $1.93 a share, for the quarter that ended Dec. 31, compared with a loss of $837 million, or $2.47 a share, a year earlier.Revenue fell to $3.3 billion from $3.5 billion.The company recorded charges of $960 million for the fourth quarter that included the write-down in value of natural gas pipeline and storage operations in Louisiana and Texas and power generation operations in Britain. The operations are for sale.Discounting the charges, the company recorded a profit of $156 million, or 40 cents a share, for the quarter. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected earnings of 39 cents a share.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/17/business/company-news-american-electric-selects-new-chief-executive.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC SELECTS NEW CHIEF EXECUTIVE<date>Published: December 17, 2003</date><text>American Electric Power chose the head of a New England-based utility as its new president and chief executive, the company said yesterday. The executive, Michael G. Morris, 57, will replace E. Linn Draper Jr. on Jan. 1. He will also become chairman of the board when Draper retires on or before April 27, the date of American Electric's annual shareholders meeting. Mr. Draper, 61, had previously announced his plans to step down after leading American Electric for about 10 years. Mr. Morris has served as chairman, president and chief executive of Northeast Utilities of Berlin, Conn.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/22/business/company-news-aep-affiliates-sue-enron-and-bank-of-america.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; A.E.P. AFFILIATES SUE ENRON AND BANK OF AMERICA<date>Published: November 22, 2003</date><text>The Houston Pipe Line Company and the A.E.P. Energy Services Gas Holding Company, affiliates of American Electric Power, said they filed a lawsuit yesterday against the Enron Corporation and the Bank of America Corporation regarding natural gas storage assets. A.E.P. said the suit was filed in the Enron bankruptcy proceeding pending in United States Bankruptcy Court for the Southern District of New York. ''Our filing supports our position that we have the right to continue to operate these assets for the full period for which we contracted and paid,'' Michael Miller, A.E.P.'s deputy general counsel, said in a statement. ''To try to avoid any uncertainty about our rights we are asking the bankruptcy court to confirm those rights.'' Representatives for Enron and Bank of America were not immediately available to comment.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/01/business/energy-company-accused-of-trying-to-skew-index.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Energy Company Accused of Trying to Skew Index<date>Published: October 01, 2003</date><text>The Commodity Futures Trading Commission sued the American Electric Power Company yesterday, accusing it of falsely reporting prices in an effort to manipulate the natural gas market from at least November 2000 through October 2002.The complaint, filed in Federal District Court in Columbus, Ohio, is the latest by the commission as part of an investigation into accusations last year that natural gas traders at large power and gas companies were providing false information about prices to publishers of indexes, like Platts, to increase profits on their transactions. The indexes are used to price billions of dollars worth of short- and long-term energy contracts.From December 2002 through September, the commission entered into six settlements with what just a year ago were the major energy trading companies, including the Dynegy Corporation, the El Paso Corporation, the Williams Companies, Enserco, WD Energy Services and Duke Energy. Most have since atrophied under the glare of scandal. The commission has collected $96 million in civil penalties from the companies.In its complaint, the commission accused American Electric Power of violating the Commodity Exchange Act by knowingly providing ''false information to firms such as Platts in an attempt to skew those indexes for their financial benefit,'' according to a commission statement.Melissa McHenry, a spokeswoman for American Electric, based in Columbus, said the company's lawyers had not seen the complaint yet. But she said the company was surprised by the commission's actions, given that American Electric had undertaken its own investigation and voluntarily reported to the federal government that five traders, whom the company quickly dismissed, had given false information to Platts and other indexes.Ms. McHenry said the company has since taken steps to try to ensure that such behavior did not recur.Gregory G. Mocek, director of the commission's division of enforcement, said American Electric had been warned that the commission planned to sue it.''We recognized that the company acknowledged the inaccurate reporting,'' Mr. Mocek said, ''and we hope that the company will continue down the road for accepting responsibility for its numerous violations.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/01/business/us-trading-of-emissions-starts-slowly.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">U.S. Trading Of Emissions Starts Slowly<date>Published: October 01, 2003</date><text>The Chicago Climate Exchange, a start-up venture hoping to create a market for member companies and governments to trade rights to emit gases associated with global warming, got off to an ambiguous start yesterday with an auction that laid the groundwork for trading to begin Oct. 31.The prices paid by companies like Ford Motor, DuPont and American Electric Power for carbon dioxide emissions averaged less than $1 a metric ton. That was one-tenth the price of over-the-counter trades of carbon dioxide emissions allowances in Europe.Experts had several possible explanations for the pricing, saying that it will take many months to know if the low prices reflected the traditionally cautious view that traders take toward new financial products, or a justifiably optimistic disagreement with Europe over the cost of reducing emissions, or flaws in the concept of the exchange.Greenhouse gas trading is patterned in part on successful markets for trading other air pollutants, most notably sulfur dioxide. In such markets, polluters that have trouble meeting regulatory limits on emissions buy allowances from other companies that can reduce pollution, thus helping to find the cheapest way to reduce overall emissions.Greenhouse gas emissions are not limited by any regulations in the United States and there are doubts that a market based on voluntary caps like those adopted by the Chicago Climate Exchange can succeed.''It's going to be at best a fantasy baseball sort of exercise unless real emissions caps are in place,'' said Jon Coifman, a spokesman for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group that has supported emissions trading for other pollutants.The 21 members of the exchange are committed to cutting their greenhouse gas emissions annually by 1 percent, but there is no threat of government prosecution or fines if they fail.The auction yesterday was intended to help members estimate prices and establish trading strategies for trading, scheduled to begin Oct. 31. ''It's going to take five or six years to really mature,'' said Dr. Richard Sandor, chairman and chief executive of the exchange.The exchange's voluntary approach has attracted support from the Bush administration, which is opposing proposed legislation in Congress calling for mandatory caps.Environmental consultants said that although it was a good sign that the exchange sold all 125,000 metric tons of allowances it put up for auction, the low prices raised questions about whether the market could serve its function of encouraging efficient investment in cutting greenhouse emissions.''At a dollar a ton it's not really a price suggesting it's worth it to invest in abatement,'' Benedikt von Butler, chief greenhouse gas broker for Evolution Markets, said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/31/business/company-news-american-electric-says-its-net-income-nearly-tripled.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC SAYS ITS NET INCOME NEARLY TRIPLED<date>Published: July 31, 2003</date><text>The American Electric Power Company, owner of utilities from Ohio to Texas, said yesterday that profit almost tripled from a year earlier, when the company recorded losses on the sale of utilities in Britain and Australia. Net income rose to $175.3 million, or 44 cents a share, from $61.9 million, or 19 cents, a year earlier, the company said. Revenue rose 2.8 percent, to $3.7 billion from $3.6 billion. Shares of American Electric, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, rose 2 cents, to $27.78. The stock has fallen 17 percent in the last year.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/01/us/extraordinary-reactor-leak-gets-the-industry-s-attention.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Extraordinary Reactor Leak Gets the Industry's Attention<date>Published: May 01, 2003</date><text>Reactor experts around the country hope that there is something unique about Reactor No. 1 at the South Texas Project here. If not, the little crust of white powder that technicians found at the bottom of the reactor vessel, a discovery that has brought operations here to a halt for the indefinite future, could be the beginning of a broad problem for the nuclear power industry.The powder, which managers here repeatedly compare in volume to about half an aspirin tablet, is boric acid, which is used in reactor cooling water to soak up excess neutrons, and its presence under the vessel presumably means there is a leak.Highly corrosive when damp, boric acid has been found in the last few years on the lids of reactor vessels around the world. A plant near Toledo, Ohio, accumulated 900 pounds, some of which ate away a football-size chunk of steel in the vessel lid, leaving only a thin stainless-steel liner and bringing the plant uncomfortably close to accident.But until the discovery here, on April 12, nobody had ever seen a leak on the bottom. A leak in that location is far harder to repair, and would be harder to control if a significant hole developed in the vessel, although the chances of accident seem far smaller than they did in Ohio.''It is something different,'' said Gary Parkey, vice president of the South Texas Project Nuclear Operating Company, which runs the two reactors here.Measuring the problem and then resolving it will take new applications of technology, he said, adding with no evident pleasure, ''We are at the cutting edge of this issue.''Until the discovery, in an inspection during a routine shutdown for maintenance, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission believed that it understood the mechanism for leaks in reactor vessels. It assumed that such leaks were caused by an occurrence called stress corrosion cracking, which, after long periods of operation, develops in hard metals that are under strain and high temperature.Not long ago, the commission developed a formula combining temperature and years of operation, and used it to tell reactor operators around the country whether they needed to shut down promptly for inspection or could do the job at a more convenient time.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/court-rejects-appeal-in-aep-tax-case.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Court Rejects Appeal In A.E.P. Tax Case<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>A federal appeals court yesterday rejected a request by American Electric Power to reduce its 1996 federal income taxes by $25 million.The United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, based in Cincinnati, turned down American Electric Power's arguments that it should have been allowed to deduct interest payments on loans it took out against life insurance policies for employees.''Our lawyers are reviewing the decision now, but obviously we are disappointed with the outcome,'' a company spokesman, Pat Hemlepp, said. ''We are going to take a few days to consider what the options are before deciding our next steps.''In 1990, the company started a corporate-owned life insurance plan, buying policies for more than 20,000 employees.The Internal Revenue Service rejected the company's 1996 deduction of interest on loans against the policies and told American Electric Power it owed another $25 million.It paid the additional tax under protest and sued to challenge the I.R.S. In February 2001, Judge James Graham of the Federal District Court in Columbus, Ohio, ruled in favor of the I.R.S.The company appealed. A three-judge panel unanimously upheld the lower court's ruling.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/26/business/company-news-norwegian-buyer-acquires-american-electric-unit.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; NORWEGIAN BUYER ACQUIRES AMERICAN ELECTRIC UNIT<date>Published: April 26, 2003</date><text>The Nordic Trading House said yesterday that it had acquired the Nordic trading operations of American Electric Power Company for an undisclosed sum in a management buyout. The announcement from the new company in Oslo came as American Electric said it had completed its exit from Nordic power trading and took a $16.6 million loss in the fourth quarter on the pullout. The management team of AEP Energy Services Norway, led by Thor Lien, completed a management buyout of 100 percent of the shares and will assume American Electric's Nordic trading book, leases and other obligations, the company said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/24/business/company-news-pollution-issue-raised-at-american-electric-s-meeting.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; POLLUTION ISSUE RAISED AT AMERICAN ELECTRIC'S MEETING<date>Published: April 24, 2003</date><text>A resolution urging the country's biggest electric producer, the American Electric Power Company, to do more to disclose and reduce its emissions of global-warming gases and air pollutants won 26.9 percent of shareholder votes at the company's annual shareholders meeting yesterday. While that is far from a majority, it is one of the biggest showings so far for a global-warming-related resolution. The resolution, filed by the Connecticut pension fund and Christian Brothers Investment Services Inc., asked the company to disclose how its profitability could be hurt by the company's status as a major emitter. American Electric, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, makes about 70 percent of its electricity in the United States by burning coal.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/19/us/texas-reactor-is-leaking-cooling-water-from-its-base.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Texas Reactor Is Leaking Cooling Water From Its Base<date>Published: April 19, 2003</date><text>A nuclear reactor in Texas is leaking cooling water from the bottom of its giant reactor vessel, a development that experts view with concern because they have never seen it before, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said today.Technicians at the South Texas Nuclear Project, 90 miles southwest of Houston near Wadsworth, have found residues that indicate that cooling water leaked from the vessel through two penetrations where instruments are inserted into the core, according to the plant operator.Operators at all 103 commercial nuclear reactors have been giving closer attention to their reactor vessels since the discovery last year of extensive leaks in the vessel head at the Davis-Besse plant in Oak Harbor, Ohio, near Toledo.The Texas plant, South Texas 1, shows much smaller signs of leaking than the Ohio plant. In both cases, technicians found deposits of boron, a chemical added to the water to control the nuclear reaction, which remains after the water evaporates.At Davis-Besse, technicians cleaned out boron with shovels. In Texas, technicians found an amount about half the volume of an aspirin tablet, said Ed Halpin, the plant general manager.No corrosion is visible, but no one is sure what is underneath. At Davis-Besse, the steel of the vessel was so corroded that a metal part on the head flopped over like a mailbox post that has been loosened from the front lawn. Workers have replaced the vessel head, a part intended to last for the lifetime of the reactor. Davis-Besse has remained closed since the leak was discovered, 13 months ago.South Texas 1 is one of the youngest plants in the country. It went on line in August 1988. South Texas 2, which is adjacent, followed in June 1989. It shows no sign of leakage.The two reactors are owned by the Cities of Austin and San Antonio, a subsidiary of American Electric Power of Columbus, Ohio, and Texas Genco, a generating company that is a subsidiary of CenterPoint Energy of Houston.The South Texas leak is unexpected and, so far, unexplained.''This is the first time it's been seen, either here or abroad,'' said Victor Dricks, a spokesman for the regulatory commission.Representatives of two industry groups are at the plant to study the problem, and managers have promised to keep the reactor, which is closed for refueling, out of operation until they find the cause and repair it to the satisfaction of the nuclear agency, Mr. Dricks said.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/10/business/company-news-chairman-of-american-electric-power-to-retire.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; CHAIRMAN OF AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER TO RETIRE<date>Published: April 10, 2003</date><text>The chairman of American Electric Power, E. Linn Draper Jr., will retire next year after more than 10 years leading the company, the nation's largest generator of electricity, the company said yesterday. Mr. Draper, 61, will step down around the time of the company's shareholder meeting, which is next April.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/25/business/company-news-money-losing-american-electric-cuts-dividend.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; MONEY-LOSING AMERICAN ELECTRIC CUTS DIVIDEND<date>Published: January 25, 2003</date><text>The American Electric Power Company, which reported a fourth-quarter loss of $837 million yesterday, said it would cut its dividend to preserve cash. The company also said it had eliminated 1,300 jobs in the quarter. The 42 percent dividend reduction will save $340 million a year, American Electric said. The company will also shed assets and may sell stock to reduce debt of $13 billion. American Electric, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, said it lost $124 million from its nonutility businesses in the quarter. The $837 million loss, or $2.47 a share, was in contrast to net income of $52 million, or 16 cents, a year earlier. Revenue rose 31 percent, to $3.8 billion.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/17/us/fire-at-nuclear-plant-shuts-down-reactor.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Fire at Nuclear Plant Shuts Down Reactor<date>Published: January 17, 2003</date><text>A transformer fire at a nuclear plant injured a security officer on Wednesday night and led to the automatic shutdown of one of the plant's two reactors.The fire at the Donald C. Cook Nuclear Plant in southwest Michigan also resulted in a brief activation of the site's emergency plan, the plant's owner, the American Electric Power Company, said.The security officer was treated for smoke inhalation.When the transformer, which is adjacent to the plant, failed, the plant's operating system automatically shut down the Unit 1 reactor, which was operating at full power.All safety systems responded appropriately, and the reactor was not damaged, the company said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/17/business/utility-shareholders-demand-liability-disclosure.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utility Shareholders Demand Liability Disclosure<date>Published: January 17, 2003</date><text>A group of shareholders that includes the Connecticut treasurer's office and several religious organizations have begun a campaign to compel the largest electric utilities in the nation to publish information about liabilities they might face because of their emission of gases that contribute to global warming.Led by the State of Connecticut Plans and Trust Fund and members of the New York-based Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, the shareholder coalition has filed resolutions to be voted upon at the annual meetings later this year of American Electric Power, the Southern Company, Xcel Energy Inc., the TXU Corporation and the Cinergy Corporation.The shareholders contend that there are hidden risks at the large power companies because of their release of carbon dioxide, which is widely thought to be linked to global warming, and the pollutants sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and mercury. They contend that companies could face risks if emissions of carbon dioxide were regulated and limited, which many environmentalists and some power companies think is inevitable. They also assert that the electric utilities may have to grapple with litigation linked to the emissions.''In American Electric Power's own disclosure to the S.E.C., they acknowledge climate change as a risk factor,'' said Denise L. Nappier, the Connecticut treasurer. ''What they haven't done, and what most utility companies haven't done, so far, is present to their shareholders a comprehensive assessment of these risks and how they plan to address them.''American Electric Power, the nation's largest utility, has filed a letter seeking no action against it from the Securities and Exchange Commission if it chooses not to include the shareholder resolution in the proxy statement for its annual meeting. A company spokeswoman said that American Electric Power already provided the kind of information the shareholders seek, and accused them of seeking to stop the burning of fossil fuels for electricity generation.But the investors contend that they seek disclosure of information rather than a radical change in business practices.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/26/business/company-says-traders-gave-out-false-data.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Company Says Traders Gave Out False Data<date>Published: October 26, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies, the owner of natural gas pipelines, said today that its traders provided phony information to a journal that compiles gas price indexes used by the industry in sales contracts.The company, the third to admit lying about energy prices, has stopped providing information to publications about gas trades, a spokesman, Kelly Swan, said. Williams shared its findings with the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, which is investigating the industry's trading.The other two companies, Dynegy and American Electric Power, fired traders earlier this month for feeding bogus prices to industry publications. Regulators are investigating whether traders used false data to rig prices and manipulate energy markets, causing California's energy crisis in 2001.Mr. Swan said Williams would stop reporting trade information to industry publications immediately. The company would not say how many traders were involved or which publication received the bogus prices.''The lack of clarity in this disclosure doesn't bode well for Williams,'' said Jake Dollarhide, an asset manager at Fredric Russell Investment Management. ''It makes a bleak situation even more so.''American Electric and Dynegy fired a total of 11 traders for making bogus reports.American Electric's false reports went to Platts, a division of McGraw-Hill. The federal commodities commission subpoenaed Platts for lists of subscribers and employees who gathered prices as part of a broader investigation of trading practices.A second agency, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, concluded in August that prices published by Platts and rivals ''may be subject to manipulation.'' Platts disagrees.Neither Dynegy nor American Electric has responded to requests that they specify which reports were false.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/15/business/accuracy-of-energy-prices-is-under-review.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Accuracy of Energy Prices Is Under Review<date>Published: October 15, 2002</date><text>The Mirant Corporation and rival energy traders are reviewing the accuracy of prices used to set energy contracts after Dynegy and the American Electric Power Company disclosed that they provided false data to trade journals.Mirant, the largest trader of natural gas in North America, said it was verifying both gas and electricity prices that it provided trade publications. The Duke Energy Corporation, the No. 2 gas trader, and Reliant Resources said they were checking gas price reports.Regulators are investigating whether companies fed trade journals false data to manipulate energy prices. Last week, the government subpoenaed Platts, an energy news service and a division of the McGraw-Hill Companies, as part of the inquiry. Journals typically compile the information from surveys of anonymous traders to calculate price indexes. The lists are a basis for some contracts in the energy industry, where companies rarely make prices public.''Most contracts, directly or indirectly, are tied to one of these indexes,'' said Arthur Corbin, president of the Municipal Gas Authority of Georgia, which buys natural gas for 580 cities and towns. ''Even federally approved pipeline tariffs use price indexes.''American fired five energy traders last week, contending that they had given false prices on Gulf Coast gas to Platts. Dynegy reported late last month that its traders had also given trade publications bogus prices.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/11/business/company-news-american-electric-plans-to-reduce-its-energy-trading.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC PLANS TO REDUCE ITS ENERGY TRADING<date>Published: October 11, 2002</date><text>American Electric Power, the nation's largest power generator, said yesterday that it would reduce its trading and wholesale marketing operation. The news set off a gain of 20 percent in the company's share price. E. Linn Draper Jr., American Electric's chief executive, told analysts in a conference call that the company was reducing its exposure to speculative energy trading markets. He did not offer a number or range on job cuts. American Electric will focus its wholesale energy efforts on areas where it has assets, said Eric J. van der Walde, the company's executive vice president, including the Midwest, Texas, the Gulf Coast and Britain. Stock in the company rose $3.51, to $21.20 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/10/business/company-news-utility-company-fires-5-employees-over-pricing-data.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; UTILITY COMPANY FIRES 5 EMPLOYEES OVER PRICING DATA<date>Published: October 10, 2002</date><text>Five employees at the American Electric Power Company were fired for providing inaccurate price information for use in indexes compiled and published by trade publications, the company said yesterday. American Electric, the utility company based in Columbus, Ohio, said that it had found the inaccuracies during its own review of trading activities. The company said it did not know whether the inaccurate information had any effect on published indexes, which are compiled using trade data provided by industry sources. American Electric's stock fell $5.22, or 23 percent, to $17.69 a share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/31/business/company-news-sec-seeks-documents-from-american-electric-power.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; S.E.C. SEEKS DOCUMENTS FROM AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER<date>Published: August 31, 2002</date><text>American Electric Power said yesterday that the Securities and Exchange Commission made an informal request on Wednesday for documents about questionable energy trades. American Electric, the nation's largest power generator, said it would comply with the request regarding ''round trip'' transactions, in which one company sells power to another and then simultaneously buys back an equal amount at the same price. Such trades typically do not affect profits but can make market demand appear greater and thereby drive up prices. By inflating revenue, the trades could also mislead investors, a violation of securities laws. The company, based in Columbus, Ohio, said previously that a review of its trading activities from Jan. 1, 1999, through March 31 found a small number of trades that involved the same terms and parties.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/26/business/company-news-american-electric-reduces-2002-earnings-forecast.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC REDUCES 2002 EARNINGS FORECAST<date>Published: July 26, 2002</date><text>American Electric Power reduced its 2002 earnings forecast for the second time in a week, after second-quarter earnings fell 91 percent on costs from selling assets. Net income fell to $21.9 million, or 7 cents a share, from $231.8 million, or 72 cents a share, a year earlier, the company said yesterday. Revenue rose 7.8 percent, to $15.2 billion. American Electric, based in Columbus, Ohio, cut its 2002 earnings forecast to $3.20 to $3.35 a share, citing declines in power prices. The company, a utility owner, had reduced the forecast by 10 percent, to $3.24 to $3.38 a share, on July 18. Excluding charges from the sale of Seeboard in Britain and CitiPower in Australia, quarterly profit was $181.6 million, or 56 cents a share, better than Wall Street's forecast of 52 cents. Shares of American Electric rose $3.19, or 12 percent, to $29.50.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/20/business/world-business-briefing-europe-australia-power-unit-sold.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">World Business Briefing | Europe: Australia: Power Unit Sold<date>Published: July 20, 2002</date><text>American Electric Power has agreed to sell a gas and electricity company in Australia to two Hong Kong-based companies for $181 million. American Electric said it was selling CitiPower of Melbourne to Cheung Kong Infrastructure Ltd. and Hong Kong Electric as part of its strategy to focus on the wholesale energy business in the United States and select international markets and its utility business in the United States. The buyers will assume $674 million in Citpower debt.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/19/business/company-news-american-electric-power-reduces-profit-outlook.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER REDUCES PROFIT OUTLOOK<date>Published: July 19, 2002</date><text>The American Electric Power Company reduced its 2002 profit outlook by 10 percent as the company, the biggest utility owner in the nation, warned that its second-quarter profit would fall short of analysts' estimates. Second-quarter profit was 52 cents to 57 cents a share, excluding one-time items, the company said. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected 75 cents. The company said a slump in trading and cool weather held down its income. Shares of American Electric fell $3.14, or 9 percent, to $31.31 a share.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/19/business/electricite-de-france-buying-seeboard-a-british-utility.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Électricité de France Buying Seeboard, a British Utility<date>Published: June 19, 2002</date><text>The American Electric Power Company said today that it would sell its Seeboard regional power utility in Britain to the state-owned French power monopoly ÃlectricitÃ© de France for $975 million in cash and the assumption of $1.05 billion in Seeboard debt.The move raises the possibility of European regulatory difficulties because the French market remains closed to similar deals.ÃlectricitÃ© de France, Europe's biggest power company, already owns London Electricity and Western Electricity.The acquisition of Seeboard's two million retail customers will give ÃlectricitÃ© de France ''a large share of the competitive market'' that is developing, said Mark Robinson, a utilities analyst with Commerzbank here.Earlier this year, RWE of Germany bought Innogy, Britain's biggest electricity retailer, while E.ON of Germany is close to acquiring Powergen, another utility in the fragmented British market that has emerged from the privatization of electricity and gas businesses since 1990.Seeboard was the last remaining independent energy supplier in Britain.With the acquisition of Seeboard, ÃlectricitÃ© de France will have about five million customers -- regarded by analysts as sufficient to establish a critical mass.''Once you get north of four million customers you are most of the way there,'' Mr. Robinson said. The deal puts ÃlectricitÃ© de France in a position to catch up with rivals like RWE and Centrica of Britain, each of which supply power to around five million customers.Like its rivals in the United States, American Electric Power of Columbus, Ohio, the biggest domestic electricity generator, is selling overseas assets to cut its debt as credit rating companies scrutinize energy companies more closely after the bankruptcy of Enron.In a statement, American Electric said it would use the proceeds of the Seeboard sale to cut its debt.''The risks inherent to the competitive retail energy business are best undertaken by consolidators like London Electricity Group,'' said E. Linn Draper Jr., the chief executive of American Electric. He has said that he wants to cut the company's $15.8 billion debt through asset and securities sales.American Electric said London Electricity would also assume obligations valued at $146 million related to a power purchase agreement with Medway Power of Britain. Seeboard has a 37.5 percent stake in Medway.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/13/us/utility-buys-town-it-choked-lock-stock-and-blue-plume.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utility Buys Town It Choked, Lock, Stock and Blue Plume<date>Published: May 13, 2002</date><text>This would have been an ordinary little town except for the bizarre blue plume that periodically emerged from the gigantic power plant and stalked through the streets, leaving townspeople complaining of raspy throats, burning eyes, sore lips, mouth blisters and grime everywhere.The village clerk read a list of cloud incidents at a recent public meeting.''Sightings of blue cloud.''''Touchdown of blue haze.''''Complaints of spots on vehicle.''''Citizen complains of fly ash release.''The words could have come from a science-fiction movie, except that in this story, the blue plume was no mystery and everyone already knows the ending.Two years after the Environmental Protection Agency accused the plant's owner, American Electric Power, of violating the Clean Air Act in this southeast Ohio hamlet, the company, which is contesting that accusation, is solving at least some of its problems by buying the town, for $20 million.Over the next few months, all 221 residents of Cheshire will pack up and leave. The 90 homeowners here will get checks for about three times the value of houses they probably could not have sold anyway. In return, they have signed pledges never to sue the power company for property damage or health problems.The deal, announced April 16, is believed to be the first by a company to dissolve an entire town. It will help the company avoid the considerable expense and public-relations mess of individual lawsuits, legal and environmental experts said.The sale of an entire town is extremely rare in corporate and environmental history. Since 1973, about two dozen neighborhoods -- Love Canal and Times Beach are famous examples -- have been bought out because of environmental problems. Then it was the government, not the polluting company, that bought the houses, and only after years of legal challenges. In cases where companies did the buying, the numbers of houses were much smaller.In this case, while threats were made, no one has sued American Electric Power. Despite residents' complaints, no one has documented an abnormal rate of long-term health problems, and the village is not a toxic Superfund site. At this point, the company is not even in violation of E.P.A. rules, having spent $7 million to fix the blue plume problem, which the company says resulted from two antipollution devices that did not work properly together.Still, most residents appear happy to go, no questions asked.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/08/business/a-rush-to-hire-enron-employees.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">A Rush to Hire Enron Employees<date>Published: March 08, 2002</date><text>While the auctioneer's hammer was going down on furniture and bric-a-brac from Enron's European headquarters here last week, another auction was quietly taking place.The bidders in this auction -- mainly rival energy companies and investment banks -- were not after the 10-foot maple veneer table with walnut trim (Lot No. 5536) that graced Enron's boardroom in a marble and granite edifice overlooking Buckingham Palace. What they wanted were the cream of the 1,600 former Enron employees in Europe, the people who made it the dominant force in energy trading before its collapse last year.The investment bank Barclays Capital hired 25 former Enron traders and is using the group to establish a beachhead in electricity and natural gas trading. American Electric Power hired Enron's European coal and freight teams en masse, along with its entire trading operation in Norway. Others bidding for Enron employees included two energy rivals, Dynegy and Entergy-Koch.As these companies try to seize the opportunity created by Enron's demise, they must weigh the potential effect of the collapse on the pace and direction of market deregulation. Britain, one of the first European countries to deregulate its energy markets as part of a privatization program under Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, has no intention of backtracking, although it has recently created several oversight bodies to protect consumers and investors. But countries like France, Italy and Switzerland have yet to deregulate fully, and government officials may take the collapse of Enron as a reason to delay the move, analysts said.''When you go from regulated prices to market prices, you create a lot of risk,'' said Michelle Michot Foss, director of the Institute for Energy, Law and Enterprise at the University of Houston. ''You need companies that everyone trusts to manage that risk.''Enron created distrust,'' Ms. Foss said, ''and that has had a hugely negative impact in Europe. It gives decision makers in countries still struggling with state-owned enterprises an excuse to slow down the process of opening those markets to competition.''Rival energy companies and investment banks apparently ignored those concerns as they rushed to divide the Enron spoils, executive recruiters said, although many have chosen not to match Enron's pay packages.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/01/business/company-news-american-electric-power-buys-an-enron-wind-project.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER BUYS AN ENRON WIND PROJECT<date>Published: January 01, 2002</date><text>American Electric Power said yesterday that it had acquired a 160-megawatt wind-power project in West Texas from a subsidiary of the bankrupt Enron Corporation for $175 million. Under the deal, American Electric agreed to honor long-term contracts to sell power from the Indian Mesa project to San Antonio's municipal electric utility. The Enron Wind Corporation will operate and maintain the project near Iraan, Tex. Enron Wind was not included in the Chapter 11 bankruptcy filing Enron made on Dec. 2. American Electric, based in Columbus, Ohio, recently completed another wind farm, the 150-megawatt Trent Mesa Wind Project, which also uses Enron wind turbines.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/09/business/company-news-american-electric-power-to-buy-2-plants-in-england.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER TO BUY 2 PLANTS IN ENGLAND<date>Published: October 9, 2001</date><text>American Electric Power, one of the largest generators of electricity in the United States, said yesterday that it would acquire two coal-burning power plants in England. The company, based in Columbus, Ohio, said it would buy the plants from Edison Mission Energy, a subsidiary of Edison International, as part of a $960 million deal. The acquisition, to be completed by the end of the year, is expected to add 6 cents a share to American Electric's earnings in 2002. Edison Mission said it expected to take a onetime, aftertax write-off of $1.18 billion as a result of the deal. The two plants are the 2,000-megawatt Fiddlers Ferry and the 2,000-megawatt Ferrybridge power stations.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/15/business/pre-emptive-strike-global-warming-many-companies-cut-gas-emissions-head-off.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">A Pre-emptive Strike On Global Warming; Many Companies Cut Gas Emissions To Head Off Tougher Regulations<date>Published: May 15, 2001</date><text>Despite the Bush administration's decision to back away from regulating emissions of global- warming gases, many multinational companies plan to continue reducing such emissions because they face strong pressure to do so in Europe and Japan, fear rising energy costs or want to promote their products as being friendly to the environment.Some of the executives with plans to reduce emissions say they are trying to be good corporate citizens. But companies also cite a wide range of business reasons that have little to do either with the environment or with what happens in Washington.And even as they move ahead on their own, some top officials at these companies say that while voluntary action is the right approach in the short run, at some point they expect the United States and others to adopt binding restrictions on the gases.''Eventually, you're going to have to have a hard cap of some kind,'' said E. Linn Draper Jr., chairman and chief executive of American Electric Power, which owns coal-fired power plants across the Midwest and builds power projects overseas.Because of the many steps being taken, emissions of global-warming gases by American industry are in fact falling, and at a surprising rate. The big increases these days come more from decisions made by consumers than corporations, as emissions from autos and homes continue to rise with people driving farther each year, buying less-fuel-efficient vehicles and building ever-larger houses with more appliances.The shift in thinking at big companies is so marked that some executives who once led the fight against restrictions on the heat-trapping gases are now advocating action. Peter J. Pestillo, chairman and chief executive of the Visteon Corporation, one of the world's largest auto parts makers, said many companies had discovered that efforts to address climate and other environmental matters not only had marketing value but could often be addressed at a modest cost, provided the problems were identified early in the planning of each new project.''People aren't debating global warming any more,'' Mr. Pestillo said. ''It is more to take a high ground where you will be one day, rather than be driven to it.''Mr. Pestillo's views are significant because as a top executive at Ford in the 1990's, he used to coordinate the auto industry's opposition to many environmental rules.In industry after industry, steps like these are being taken that have the effect of reducing global-warming emissions:</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/28/business/world-business-briefing-europe-yorkshire-power-group-bought.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; YORKSHIRE POWER GROUP BOUGHT<date>Published: February 28, 2001</date><text>Innogy Holdings P.L.C. said it agreed to pay two United States utility companies Â£508.6 million ($735 million) for 94.75 percent of the Yorkshire Power Group to expand its position as a gas and electric supplier in Britain. Innogy, which was created when National Power P.L.C. was split into two companies last year, also will assume Â£1.37 billion in debt. One of the United States businesses, the American Electric Power Company, said it was selling its stake to concentrate on wholesale energy in Britain and Europe. The other, Xcel Energy Inc., said it would sell all but a 5.25 percent stake in Yorkshire, as it turns its attention to its European subsidiary NRG Energy Inc. Suzanne Kapner</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/21/business/tax-shelter-is-disallowed.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Tax Shelter Is Disallowed<date>Published: February 21, 2001</date><text>A federal judge has ended a tax shelter that American Electric Power, an electric utility based in Columbus, Ohio, created using life insurance sold by the Hartford Group. American Electric said it would take a $317 million tax charge against 2000 earnings as a result of the decision yesterday by Judge James L. Graham of United States District Court in Columbus, Ohio. The charge covers taxes avoided, plus interest, from 1991 to 1999, said Pat D. Hemlepp, a spokesman for the company, which plans to appeal. The case is significant because American Electric obtained state approval for the shelter, only to be rejected by Judge Graham.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/09/business/company-news-american-electric-power-selling-plant-in-texas.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER SELLING PLANT IN TEXAS<date>Published: February 09, 2001</date><text>The American Electric Power Company, which owns utilities in 11 states and Europe, agreed to sell a 500-megawatt power plant in Texas to Teco Energy Inc. for $265 million. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission required A.E.P., which is based in Columbus, Ohio, to sell the plant as part of its $12.2 billion purchase of the Central and South West Corporation, the Dallas-based utility company. Teco owns or has interests in 21 plants in eight states and Guatemala, Costa Rica and the Czech Republic. The natural-gas-powered plant being sold is outside Mission, Tex., near the border with Mexico.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/13/business/company-news-american-electric-power-laying-off-370-workers.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER LAYING OFF 370 WORKERS<date>Published: January 13, 2001</date><text>American Electric Power said it would lay off 370 workers at two coal mines it is shutting down, the Windsor Coal Company underground mine in West Liberty, W. Va., and the Central Ohio Coal Company surface mine in Cumberland, Ohio, on or about March 15. The company will then begin environmental reclamation efforts at the mines; the closings were first announced more than 18 months ago. The company said last August that it would seek to sell all its mining interests in Ohio and West Virginia.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/business/company-news-company-to-split-regulated-from-unregulated-utilities.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; COMPANY TO SPLIT REGULATED FROM UNREGULATED UTILITIES<date>Published: October 31, 2000</date><text>The American Electric Power Company, which owns utilities in 11 states and in Europe, said it would split its regulated utilities from its less-regulated businesses, creating two wholly owned companies. The separation resembles plans the company has already filed for units in Ohio and Texas as part of efforts to open the power market in those states to competition, the company said. It also said it had ruled out merging Seeboard, a natural gas and power distributor it owns in England, with Yorkshire Electricity, a British utility it partly owns. American Electric is based in Columbus, Ohio.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/business/judge-rules-that-tax-shelter-worth-6-billion-is-a-sham.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Judge Rules That Tax Shelter Worth $6 Billion Is a Sham<date>Published: October 18, 2000</date><text>A federal judge in Delaware, in a decision made public yesterday, held that one company's corporate tax shelter was a sham and noted that 85 other large corporations used the same deduction to avoid paying $6 billion in corporate income taxes.Judge Murray Schwartz of United States District Court in Wilmington, Del., ruled that Camelot Music could not deduct interest on loans it took out against life insurance on its 1,430 employees in 1990 through 1993.The decision could affect many of the other 85 companies, which the judge did not identify by name, because his ruling applies to every company organized in Delaware, whose corporate-governance laws have made it a leading center for the nominal headquarters of large companies.American Electric Power, an electric utility in Columbus, Ohio, has a case involving almost identical issues scheduled to go to trial in two weeks. Pat D. Hemlepp, a spokesman for the company, said that $240 million in taxes were at issue.The case in which the ruling was issued Monday, and made public yesterday, involved Camelot Music, which was bought by the Trans World Entertainment Corporation of Albany last year for $451.9 million.Camelot took out life insurance from the Hartford Group beginning in 1990 on its 1,430 workers. The company paid for the insurance, taking a deduction for this expense, and then borrowed back the premium through a loan against the insurance policy. On its corporate income tax returns the company took $13.8 million of deductions in 1990 through 1993 tax returns for interest it paid on the loans.Judge Schwartz said that there was no buildup in the cash value of the insurance policies and because of the way the loans were structured there was no reasonable prospect that the company would profit from buying the insurance.He called the arrangement ''a factual sham'' that ''lacked objective economic substance and a subjective business purpose other than the tax benefits flowing from the interest deductions.''The judge said the deal ''crossed the line'' on permissible deductions by such a wide margin that the Internal Revenue Service was right to impose penalties for filing an inaccurate tax return.John Sullivan, Trans World Entertainment's chief financial officer, said that if the decision stood it would cost the company about $8 million plus interest. ''I'm surprised by the ruling,'' Mr. Sullivan said, adding that he expected the company would appeal the decision.The Camelot Music and American Electric Power cases are similar to the corporate-owned life insurance policy tax shelter of Winn-Dixie Stores, a big supermarket chain, that a tax court judge demolished last year in an 81-page opinion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/27/business/utilities-take-stake-in-power-trade-site.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Utilities Take Stake In Power-Trade Site<date>Published: July 27, 2000</date><text>Abandoning plans to create their own Internet energy-trading exchange, the Duke Energy Corporation, the El Paso Energy Corporation, the Southern Company and three other power-trading companies acquired a stake in IntercontinentalExchange, an online power and metals trading site.The six companies, which did not disclose the financial terms of the transaction, handle about 37 percent of the electricity and 27 percent of the gas traded in the United States. Partners' stakes in the exchange are based on the size of their trading business.The Atlanta-based exchange was founded in March by seven energy and investment companies.In addition to Duke, El Paso Energy and Southern, the other three utilities joining in the exchange are American Electric Power, Reliant Energy and UtiliCorp United.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/26/us/old-plants-with-new-parts-present-a-problem-to-epa.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Old Plants With New Parts Present a Problem to E.P.A.<date>Published: December 26, 1999</date><text>In the roaring hot interior of the Philip Sporn electric plant here, giant pulverizers work around the clock to reduce coal to the consistency of talcum powder. Howling fans then blow it into giant boilers.Every second that the plant operates, it grinds and burns 200 pounds of coal. Every second, it produces enough energy to run a medium-sized city.To its owner, the American Electric Power Corporation, Sporn is an engineering marvel, the first coal plant in the world to produce a kilowatt-hour of power with less than 10,000 B.T.U.'s, which is well under a pound of the coal it uses. This level of efficiency is far better than the industry average.To the Environmental Protection Agency, the problem is that Sporn set that standard 50 years ago. The plant, environmental regulators say, is a relic of the era when the symbol of prosperity was a smokestack spewing a fat black plume; now, they say, it is time to clean up or shut down.But Sporn and plants like it are, for now at least, doing neither. Entering what might have been their twilight years, they are producing more electricity than ever by running for more hours every year, as utility deregulation promotes shipment of their cheap electricity over increasingly long distances, from the banks of the Ohio River here to the big load centers of the East Coast.And if their owners have their way, plants like this may be nearly eternal. Rather than being replaced by new generating stations with younger technology, Sporn may be an example of the past replacing the future.''The lifetime is 35, 40 or 45 years on many components, but not all components,'' said Mark A. Gray, manager of American Electric Power's environmental services division, during a recent tour of the plant. ''Some may have an expected design life of 10 years or 15 years,'' he said, but some major parts, with proper painting and cleaning, will endure ''for centuries.''And the end of a component's life does not mean the end of a plant's, he said; it just means time for replacement, and then a plant can run like new for years.The E.P.A. emphatically disagrees. ''If you want to treat it as a newish unit, you should have newish controls,'' Sylvia Lowrance, the agency's principal deputy assistant administrator, said in an interview in Washington.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/04/us/7-utilities-sued-by-us-on-charges-of-polluting-air.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">7 UTILITIES SUED BY U.S. ON CHARGES OF POLLUTING AIR<date>Published: November 04, 1999</date><text>In what federal officials called one of the biggest enforcement actions in the nation's history, the government sued seven giant electric companies in the Midwest and the South today, accusing the utilities of defying anti-pollution regulations and illegally contaminating the air breathed by millions of Americans.The government took legal or administrative action against 32 coal-fired plants in 10 states, saying that if the plants reduced pollution as required it would have the same effect as taking 26 million cars off the road.In the suits, filed by the Justice Department on behalf of the Environmental Protection Agency, the government accused the companies of modernizing their generating plants without modernizing their pollution controls as required by the Clean Air Act. The government contends that 17 of the companies' plants have fouled the air for years and contributed ''to some of the most severe environmental problems facing the United States today.''''When children have trouble breathing because of pollution from a utility plant hundreds of miles away, something must be done,'' Attorney General Janet Reno said.The civil suits, which seek to fine the companies and force them to install modern anti-pollution equipment, were filed in Federal District Court in five Midwestern and Southern cities.The E.P.A. administrator, Carol Browner, said the seven defendants had committed ''very, very significant violations of the Clean Air Act,'' an accusation that the utilities immediately denounced.Ms. Browner said the companies had illegally retooled old, pollution-spewing coal plants without notifying regulators, getting the necessary permits and installing expensive new equipment to reduce emissions and meet pollution standards that apply to new plants.''They chose not to,'' Ms. Browner said, ''because they knew that if they did they'd have to reduce their pollution, and they didn't want to do it.''The utilities' motive, she added, was to prolong the lives of the old plants and to avoid the cost of building new plants with tough, modern standards.The defendants denounced the government's action. ''We regret that the agency has again demonstrated that it prefers headlines and confrontation over consensus-building,'' said Dale Heydlauff, a vice president of American Electric Power of Columbus, Ohio. ''We are fully prepared to vigorously defend against these allegations, and we believe we will prevail.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/24/business/international-business-entergy-is-selling-australian-unit.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Entergy Is Selling Australian Unit<date>Published: November 24, 1998</date><text>The American Electric Power Company agreed today to buy the Entergy Corporation's electric distribution unit in Australia for $1.1 billion, continuing its push to expand in that nation.Entergy, which is based in New Orleans, will record a gain of about $30 million, or 12 cents a share, from the sale of the unit, Citipower, which supplies electricity to 233,000 customers in central Melbourne.Australia is opening power and gas sales to competition, and American Electric, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, has said it wants to take advantage of the shift.American Electric made three unsuccessful bids for Australian electricity generators in the last two years and is considering bidding for $3.2 billion worth of natural gas units also being sold by the state of Victoria.Entergy is the fourth-largest electricity generator in the United States. It said it was selling Citipower to reduce debt and focus on more profitable businesses like nuclear plants, international power generation and trading electricity.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/09/15/business/company-news-equitable-resources-to-sell-some-natural-gas-units.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; EQUITABLE RESOURCES TO SELL SOME NATURAL GAS UNITS<date>Published: September 15, 1998</date><text>Equitable Resources Inc. said yesterday that it would sell its natural gas midstream operations in Louisiana and Texas for $320 million in cash to the American Electric Power Company, an electric utility holding company based in Columbus, Ohio. Equitable said the operations included Louisiana Intrastate Gas, a 2,000-mile pipeline system; five natural gas processing plants; Jefferson Island Storage facilities, and an energy trading business. Equitable, an energy company based in Pittsburgh, had 1997 revenues of $2.15 billion.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/23/business/two-big-utilities-in-6.6-billion-merger-accord.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Two Big Utilities In $6.6 Billion Merger Accord<date>Published: December 23, 1997</date><text>Two big utilities, the American Electric Power Company and the Central and Southwest Corporation, announced yesterday that they had agreed to combine in a stock deal worth $6.6 billion.The combination would create a huge system serving about 4.6 million customers in 11 states from Ohio through Texas.The deal, under which American Electric would acquire Central and Southwest, is one of the most ambitious plans so far to create a major low-cost producer of electricity that would be in a strong position to sell power as states open their utilities to competition.But some analysts said yesterday that they foresaw a long and complicated road ahead for the merger, which must be approved by regulators in a number of states, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and other Federal agencies at a time of increased scrutiny of such deals.Just how precarious the merger road has become was highlighted yesterday, when the Baltimore Gas and Electric Company and the Potomac Electric Power Company announced that after a two-year effort, spending $100 million and obtaining most of the regulatory approvals, they had decided to cancel their agreement to merge.The cancellation of that deal illustrates the growing potential for conflicts between cost-cutting utility executives bracing for deregulation and state regulators under pressure to pass on savings from deregulation to consumers.Christian M. Poindexter, the chairman and chief executive of Baltimore Gas and Electric, said that orders issued by the Maryland and District of Columbia Public Service Commissions contained ''financial conditions that make it impossible for the two companies' investors to share in the benefits of the proposed merger.''The regulators approved the merger on the condition that Baltimore Gas and Potomac pass on the savings to customers in the form of rate cuts. Mr. Poindexter said that the utilities had tried to get the regulators to reconsider ''but now conclude that a favorable outcome cannot be expected within a reasonable period, if at all.''Morton Pierce, a partner with the Manhattan law firm of Dewey Ballantine who specializes in utility mergers, said that ''states are getting more concerned on what this means for the rates of their citizens.''But if regulators want most of the savings from a merger to be passed on in terms of rate cuts, he said, management must then ask: Why do the deal?</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/24/business/trading-pollution-exchange-global-warming-plan-would-make-emissions-commodity.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Trading on the Pollution Exchange; Global Warming Plan Would Make Emissions a Commodity<date>Published: October 24, 1997</date><text>If President Clinton has his way, rights to spew carbon dioxide into the atmosphere will eventually be traded by energy producers, utilities and even investors on exchanges the way pork bellies, German marks and interest rate futures change hands today.While the Administration's plan for curtailing greenhouse gases -- announced Wednesday in preparation for the world climate change talks in Kyoto, Japan, in December -- demands no immediate action by businesses, it confirms that a system of tradable emissions permits will figure prominently in any long-term effort to control pollutants. Such a system, already being used under the Clean Air Act of 1990 to cut sulfur emissions, would allow companies that voluntarily reduce emissions below a certain level to sell the difference to others as unused ''rights'' to pollute.The reliance on free markets in reducing carbon emissions to 1990 levels has been greeted with enthusiasm by specialists who have long argued that managing the task with traditional regulation would be hugely wasteful.''An approach that promises to reduce the cost of containment by 90 percent is certainly worth a try,'' said Richard Richels of the Electric Power Research Institute in California.But many economists caution that emissions trading is no panacea. They emphasize the desirability of bringing developing countries into the trading systems as soon as possible and the need for care in designing the control mechanisms that will redirect billions or even trillions of dollars in pollution-control investments worldwide.''At this point, the learning is more important than the doing,'' suggested Robert Hahn of the American Enterprise Institute, a research group in Washington.The Administration's plan has been criticized by many foreign governments that will also attend the Kyoto conference, where the participants will try to work out a global climate treaty. The critics say the American plan is not aggressive enough because it would not roll back emissions to 1990 levels until sometime between 2008 and 2012. Whatever happens in Kyoto, Mr. Clinton seems committed to emissions trading.It is no secret why: It costs less and keeps Big Brother in the background.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/03/business/company-news-american-electric-and-conoco-plan-2-joint-ventures.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC AND CONOCO PLAN 2 JOINT VENTURES<date>Published: October 03, 1997</date><text>The American Electric Power Company and Conoco Inc. said yesterday that they had agreed to form two joint venture companies to provide energy management and capital. Conoco is the energy subsidiary of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company. DuPont and American Electric are to each invest about $125 million in stock, with the remainder of the joint ventures to be financed through debt. AEP Conoco Energy Capital is to acquire and lease back energy assets at industrial and large commercial plants. AEP Conoco Energy Management Services is to provide energy management services, like maintenance, energy reduction services, technical support and energy and fuel procurement.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/25/business/2-us-utilities-to-buy-british-company-for-2.4-billion.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">2 U.S. Utilities to Buy British Company for $2.4 Billion<date>Published: February 25, 1997</date><text>Two United States utilities, the American Electric Power Company and the Public Service Company of Colorado, announced yesterday that they had agreed to acquire Yorkshire Electricity Group P.L.C. for $2.43 billion.The deal, which was expected, would leave only one of Britain's 12 power distributors independent. American utilities have led the buying scramble, acquiring seven British utilities -- including Yorkshire Electricity -- in the last two years.The British market is attractive to American utility companies because it is undergoing deregulation at a faster pace than the United States market. The British Government spun off its utility industry in 1990 to the private sector, creating 12 regional electricity companies. On April 1, 1998, most customers in Britain will be able to choose their own suppliers of power.E. Linn Draper Jr., the chairman of American Electric, said yesterday that the deal was being made because British utilities had been profitable and had been growing rapidly.Yorkshire Electricity, based in Leeds, distributes electricity to 2.1 milion customers in northeast England and has some generating capacity. The company agreed to the offer of $:9.27 a share, or $14.83, up 13.5 percent from Yorkshire's closing price of $:8.165 on Friday. In London yesterday, the shares rose 7.8 percent, to $:8.82.Shares of the remaining independent distributor, Southern Electric P.L.C. rose 3.2 percent yesterday, to $:7.70.Unlike other American executives who have stressed Britain's advanced stage of deregulation as a major reason for acquisitions, Mr. Draper, American Electric's chairman, said that this was not the case in the Yorkshire deal.''Our motive was not the learning experience,'' he said in a news conference in London. ''That's quite an expensive tuition to buy a company just for the learning experience.''In the United States, deregulation will come to a small group of states, including California, by 1998. Most states, however, are not yet ready to open their utilities to competitors.American Electric Power, based in Columbus, Ohio, is one of the giants in the industry, serving about seven million customers in Indiana, Kentucky, Michigan, Ohio, Tennessee, Virginia and West Virginia.It has a series of low-cost plants, which is expected to put it in a good position to sell cheap power to other regions as the industry deregulates. Shares of American Electric rose 25 cents yesterday, to $42.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.Public Service, based in Denver, serves about three million customers in Colorado and Cheyenne, Wyo. Its shares rose $1, to $39.875.In addition to its power operations, Yorkshire Electricity offers telecommunications services and has built and operated some wind farms. For the fiscal year ended March 31, 1996, Yorkshire had a profit of $310.8 million on revenues of $2.2 billion.American Electric and Public Service will each invest about $360 million in the deal while the rest will be provided through a loan to Yorkshire.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/24/business/us-utility-is-said-to-be-near-to-british-deal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">U.S. Utility Is Said to Be Near to British Deal<date>Published: February 24, 1997</date><text>The American Electric Power Company is expected to announce as early as today that it plans to acquire Yorkshire Electricity P.L.C. of Britain.American Electric, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, has scheduled a news conference today to make ''a major announcement.'' It did not disclose the details, but people in the industry said that the company would announce that it had reached a deal with Yorkshire.Few details of the expected deal were available last night. In London, The Financial Times reported today that American Electric would bid as much as $2.4 billion for Yorkshire; The Daily Telegraph reported that Yorkshire had accepted a bid for that amount from American Electric and another United States power company that was not identified.Yesterday, Yorkshire described as speculative a report in The Sunday Telegraph that a deal had been reached. American Electric declined to comment.If a deal is completed, Yorkshire would be the seventh British electric utility to be taken over by an American company in recent years.Yorkshire, which provides electricity in parts of northern England, and Southern Electric P.L.C. are the last two independent regional electricity companies in Britain, of the 12 that had been privatized by the British Government in 1995. In December, Calenergy Inc. claimed victory in its $1.5 billion hostile takeover bid for Northern Electric P.L.C.Faced with the coming deregulation of its markets in the United States, American utilities have been acquiring British electricity companies because they are growing fast and have learned how to cope with deregulation. Britain already allows many customers to choose their electric suppliers, as American customers will be able to do in the next few years in some states.American Electric is one of the largest power companies in the United States, serving nearly three million customers in Ohio, Indiana, Michigan, Virginia and Kentucky.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/01/business/company-news-american-electric-to-cut-more-than-1200-jobs.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC TO CUT MORE THAN 1,200 JOBS<date>Published: August 01, 1995</date><text>The American Electric Power Company said yesterday that it would cut more than 1,200 jobs at power plants in five states as part of a corporate reorganization plan. The company, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, said the job reductions were expected to begin in October and continue into 1996 at 16 fossil-fuel plants, in West Virginia, Virginia, Ohio, Kentucky and Indiana. The plan is part of a reorganization announced earlier this summer that will separate the company's power generation unit from its energy delivery unit.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/12/17/business/company-news-top-officer-set-to-retire-at-american-electric-power.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; Top Officer Set to Retire At American Electric Power<date>Published: December 17, 1992</date><text>Richard E. Disbrow, chairman and chief executive of the American Electric Power Company, one of the nation's largest utilities, intends to retire in April, after the company's 1993 annual meeting, it was announced yesterday.E. Linn Draper Jr., American Electric's president, will succeed Mr. Disbrow. Mr. Draper, who is 50, joined the company last March after a 13-year career at Gulf States Utilities, the last five as chairman, chief executive and president.Mr. Disbrow, who is 62, was named chairman earlier this year and president and chief executive in 1991. He has been with the utility, which is based in Columbus, Ohio, since 1954.News of the changes came as no surprise to securities analysts, and in a prepared statement Mr. Disbrow emphasized he had agreed to take on the chairman's job only to help position the company for the next management transition."The company faces a number of new challenges and opportunities, and in my view it would be preferable to step aside now and let those who will manage through the 1990's and beyond have free rein in establishing the needed policies and programs," Mr. Disbrow said in the statement.Mr. Disbrow elaborated on the challenges facing his successor in a telephone interview."We have many problems remaining in the environmental area," he said. "There will be some new initiatives from the Clinton Administration, but our position is that there has to be a balance between energy, the economy and the environment. I am concerned that we not desecrate the environment, but neither should we leap to Draconian solutions that would jeopardize the economy."The profitability of American Electric, the parent company of seven electric utilities that provide service to seven million people in parts of seven states, has declined so far this year.For the nine months ended Sept. 30, the company reported net income of $302 million on revenues of $3.75 billion. In the corresponding period a year ago, American Electric earned $382 million."This is a slow-growth company in a slow-growth part of the country," said Sanford M. Cohen, an analyst at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company.American Electric operates in Ohio, Indiana, Michigan, Kentucky, Virginia, West Virginia and Tennessee.A graduate of Rice University, where he received bachelor's and master's degrees, and from Cornell University, where he earned a doctorate in nuclear science and engineering, Mr. Draper was an associate professor and director of the nuclear engineering program at the University of Texas before joining Gulf States.His expertise in nuclear energy did not make life much easier at Gulf States. The company has been in financial trouble since 1986, when it completed a nuclear plant at St. Francisville, La., in the midst of a regional recession.Mr. Draper spearheaded efforts to raise rates to cover the costs of the plant. Those efforts met with stern resistance from regulators.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/11/06/business/company-news-american-electric-power-to-eliminate-500-ohio-jobs.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER TO ELIMINATE 500 OHIO JOBS<date>Published: November 06, 1992</date><text>The American Electric Power Company said yesterday that it would eliminate 500 jobs in Ohio over as long as 14 months through attrition and dismissals. The company will combine work at Columbus Southern Power's Columbus office, which employs 600 headquarters staff members, and Ohio Power's Canton office, with about 700 such employees. Richard Disbrow, the parent's chairman and chief executive, said limited growth, strict environmental regulations and a more competitive market had led to the cuts.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/23/business/l-american-electric-power-a-help-or-a-hindrance-767892.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">American Electric Power: A Help . . . Or a Hindrance?<date>Published: August 23, 1992</date><text>To the Editor:American Electric Power paint itself green? The problem is identified in the article's subhead: "But a wildlife preserve and new light bulb may not be enough." It's not.A.E.P. seems to expect kudos for spending $1 billion to meet acid rain requirements of the Clean Air Act. That would be noble except for two key points. First, it's spending $1 billion of rate-payers' money, not its own. Second, it can meet the act's requirements at less than one-third that cost.As noted in the article, a key component lacking in all A.E.P. planning is commitment to any energy conservation programs. In fact, A.E.P. doesn't plan to distribute the e-lamp to its own customers. Central to A.E.P.'s compliance plan is building a scrubber at its Gavin plant. But there is an alternative plan -- including a combined strategy of energy conservation programs linked to reduced utilization of its high-emitting plants, fuel-switching at several other units and a small number of emission allowance purchases -- that would save consumers $820 million by 1999.The A.E.P. plan doesn't only hit consumers in their household budgets, it could also end up costing them their jobs. It is estimated that repercussions from the 3.9 percent rate increase (to pay for the $1 billion scrubber) include the loss of almost 7,000 jobs in the A.E.P. service territory. Our plan would save more than 5,500 jobs and raise rates only 1 percent.With all the negative economic impacts of the A.E.P. plan, one would think that it was a model of environmental planning. Not so. The scrubber plan, while reducing SO2 emissions, will create a 383-acre landfill of scrubber sludge, destroying 14 acres of wetlands.A.E.P. also expressed concern about present legislative trends toward reductions in CO2 emissions. It is ignoring a potential first step: Reducing utilization at high-emitting plants would cut all emissions -- SO2, NOx, CO2 and air toxics. This would be of much greater environmental benefit than over-controlling one pollutant -- SO2 -- while maintaining or actually increasing other pollutants.While a wildlife preserve is exciting, and the e-lamp shows promise, A.E.P. is missing the boat. Consumers and the environment are the big losers. NED HELME Washington, Aug. 10 The writer is executive director, Center for Clean Air Policy.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/23/business/l-american-electric-power-a-help-768692.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">American Electric Power: A Help . . .<date>Published: August 23, 1992</date><text>To the Editor:"A Coal-Burning Utility That's Trying to Paint Itself Green," (July 26) leaves the impression that the American Electric Power Corporation's donation of reclaimed land to the International Center for the Preservation of Wild Animals (now known as the Wilds) was a thinly disguised public relations exercise. On the contrary. The loss of jobs in southeastern Ohio resulting from coal-mining cutbacks is a major concern and A.E.P.'s gift ultimately will result in the creation of employment opportunities for the region.Most significantly, it was A.E.P.'s expensive reclamation and careful attention to positive environmental standards over the years that made this area ideal for endangered species breeding and preservation. The mission of the Wilds is to serve as a unique resource for zoological parks and for university and field scientists involved in restoration ecology, species reintroduction and myriad other investigations. Ultimately, the Wilds will attract thousands of visitors who wish to see, experience and learn more about the natural world. These visitors, in turn, will require services and those services mean more jobs for the people of the region.By providing the land, A.E.P. has contributed to an enormously significant conservation project, and provided a sustainable benefit to the area economy. ROBERT W. REECE Columbus, Ohio, Aug. 11 The writer is executive director of the Wilds.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/07/26/business/a-coal-burning-utility-that-s-trying-to-paint-itself-green.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">A Coal-Burning Utility That's Trying to Paint Itself Green<date>Published: July 26, 1992</date><text>Scimitar-horned oryxes browse amid the grass and wildflowers of the valley, as their ancestors have for millennia on the African savannah. But this is not Africa, it is eastern Ohio. And the oryxes are here not in their natural niche in the food chain -- eating foliage and falling prey to predators -- but in another role. They are helping to make coal look green.The oryxes, a type of antelope, along with Hartmann's mountain zebras and other rare species graze on a reclaimed strip mine donated by the American Electric Power Company. They will soon be joined by elephants, rhinos and snow leopards, and the company proudly notes that at 9,200 acres the wild-animal preserve is the largest in North America.More than perhaps any other North American utility, A.E.P. needs to show an environmental conscience. Of the one billion tons of coal that will be used in the United States this year, A.E.P. will use 45 million, more than anyone else, to serve seven million people in seven states from Virginia to Michigan. In this age of concern over acid rain and global warming, a coal-burning utility is a bit like a butcher shop in a village where the new religion is vegetarianism.True, A.E.P. is refining a generation and transmission system that is already very modern and efficient, and plans to spend well over $1 billion to comply with the Clean Air Act amendments of 1990, primarily for control of emissions believed to cause acid rain. But it is looking ahead with dread to the debate over the greenhouse effect. Many scientists say carbon dioxide emissions, which are larger from coal than from other fuels, could bring catastrophic changes in weather.Bruised by the Clean Air Act amendments, which imposed strict limits on sulfur dioxide emissions, and horrified at the idea of a tax on carbon dioxide emissions, like that proposed at the recent Earth Summit, A.E.P. is trying to demonstrate that it is an environmental good guy even if it does rely on coal for 89 percent of its fuel.Not only is the Columbus-based company emphasizing to shareholders and customers a 40-year program of land reclamation and tree planting at old mines like the one here; it is also on the cutting edge of cleaner ways to burn coal, as evidenced by an experimental plant in Brilliant, Ohio, and better ways to use electricity, like an energy-efficient bulb.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/06/01/business/bulb-lighted-by-radio-waves-may-last-for-up-to-14-years.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">Bulb Lighted by Radio Waves May Last for Up to 14 Years<date>Published: June 01, 1992</date><text>In what appears to be a significant advance in the technology of efficient lighting, a bulb will be introduced today that uses a high-frequency radio signal instead of a filament to produce light.The new bulb is more cost effective than existing types and will last 14 years if lighted 4 hours a day, which is typical household use, electrical engineers say.Compared with a 100-watt incandescent bulb, which would cost about 30 cents a week to buy and operate for 4 hours daily, a 25-watt version of the new bulb would provide as much light but cost only 9 cents a week.The bulb is expected to have a life of at least 20,000 hours, in contrast to most incandescent bulbs, which burn out after 750 to 1,000 hours. The compact fluorescent bulbs introduced a few years ago last about 7,000 to 10,000 hours, but are bulkier than the new bulbs, limiting the places they fit. Expected Early Next YearThe developers of the bulb, which is to be available early next year, say they expect it to be used first in spotlights and in other commercial applications where the cost of bulb replacement is a major expense. A version for standard household use will follow soon after.An independent expert, Howard S. Geller, the executive director of the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy, said he had not seen the bulb itself but had seen the makers' description of it. If it works as described, he said, "then it would be a real breakthrough."The new bulb, which the makers have called the E-Lamp, for electronic lamp, will sell for about the same price as existing compact fluorescent bulbs, or $12 to $15 each, said Richard E. Disbrow, the chairman and chief executive of the American Electric Power Company, of Columbus, Ohio, the nation's second-largest electric utility company after the Atlanta-based Southern Company.Compact fluorescent bulbs, which are priced at about 15 times the cost of an incandescent bulb, have had limited appeal to consumers. But the new bulbs will last much longer and the price is expected to drop as they are produced in larger quantities, said Pierre G. Villere, the president of Intersource Technologies, a small Silicon Valley company that developed the bulb with backing from American Electric Power and will make and market it.Mr. Villere said that as a bulb that would last for years, the E-Lamp was "not a disposable good, but a durable good, like an appliance."</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/15/business/company-news-american-electric.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; American Electric<date>Published: November 15, 1991</date><text>The Thomas &amp; Betts Corporation, which makes electrical systems, agreed to buy American Electric for $432.5 million. American Electric's parent, Forstmann Little &amp; Company, accepted $342.5 million in cash and $82.5 million in Thomas &amp; Betts common stock. Thomas &amp; Betts also agreed to assume $7.5 million in American Electric's debt. American Electric, based in Memphis, makes products under such names as Steel City, Blackburn and Hazlux.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/08/18/business/largest-coal-user-criticizes-bush-s-acid-rain-proposal.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">LARGEST COAL USER CRITICIZES BUSH'S ACID RAIN PROPOSAL<date>Published: August 18, 1989</date><text>The nation's largest user of coal said yesterday that President Bush's acid rain proposal could wreck the American economy, and contended that it was ''one of the harshest, least flexible and most costly bills ever introduced in the Congress.''The statement, by the American Electric Power Company, which serves seven million people in seven states, was the first by a major company on the President's acid rain plan. It may signal rough going for the proposal in Congress, where the utilities have a track record of successful lobbying.The Bush proposal would effectively make building new electric plants impossible, and even operating old ones at full power would be barred, the company said. ''Our nation would find the anomalous situation of energy shortages coexisting with substantial unused generating capacity at existing power plants,'' said W.S. White Jr., chairman of the company.A spokesman for the Environmental Protection Agency, Christian Rice, replied, ''We don't accept their claim that doomsday is near.'' Mr. Rice said that he had not seen the American Electric statement but that technology was available for pollution control. Utilities have sufficient flexibility to operate under the proposed law, he said.The President's bill calls for utilities that want to build new power plants to obtain ''emissions offsets'' by reducing the pollution output of existing plants by an amount equal to what the new one would produce. But Mr. White said that emissions offsets would gradually be used up, and ''it may become impossible to find additional offsets at any price.''Several utilities and the Edison Electric Institute responded critically to a White House position statement on acid rain in June, and American Electric said that the bill itself was tougher than the position statement.The company said it had sent letters to its largest customers - some industrial customers could see rate increases of 39 percent - seeking to enlist them in the battle against the bill. The company said that residential customers would also suffer, with an average rate rise of 12 percent.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/07/28/business/business-people-no-2-us-electric-ulitiy-names-heads-for-5-units.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">BUSINESS PEOPLE; No. 2 U.S. Electric Ulitiy Names Heads for 5 Units<date>Published: July 28, 1989</date><text>The American Electric Power Company, the nation's second-largest electric utility, named presidents yesterday for five operating companies in a major change of management.''As it happened, we had three people coming up on retirement pretty quickly,'' said the company's chairman, W. S. White Jr. ''We decided to announce the changes all at the same time.''American Electric Power, based in Columbus, Ohio, operates eight power subsidiaries in seven states. It used to be the nation's biggest electric utility, but its region's growth has slowed and it has been knocked into second place by the Southern Company, based in Atlanta.Those named yesterday are all from within the utility's ranks:Joseph H. Vipperman, 48, was named president and chief executive of the Appalachian Power Company, Roanoke, Va., effective Jan. 1. Appalachian is the utility's largest electric operating company. Mr. Vipperman will become executive vice president of the utility Oct. 1.Thomas R. McCaffrey, 50, was named president and chief operating officer of the Columbus Southern Power Company, Columbus, effective Oct. 1.James M. Allison, 36, was named president and chief operating officer of the Wheeling Power Company, Wheeling, W. Va., effective Oct. 1.Richard C. Menge, 54, will be president and chief operating officer of the Indiana Michigan Power Company, Fort Wayne, Ind., effective Oct. 1.Coulter R. Boyle 3d, 41, was named president and chief operating officer of the Kentucky Power Company, Ashland, Ky., effective next May 1.In addition, William J. Lhota, 49, will be executive vice president for operations of the AEP Service Corporation, Columbus, effective Oct. 1.The three presidents who are retiring are John W. Vaughan, 63, of Appalachian; William A. Black, 64, of Indiana Michigan Power, and Robert E. Matthews, 64, of Kentucky Power.Mr. Lhota is moving to the service company from his post as president and chief operating officer of Columbus Southern Power, opening the position for Mr. McCaffrey. Mr. McCaffrey, in turn, is leaving as president of Wheeling Power, opening the post to Mr. Allison.Until 1980, American Electric was a utility holding company based in New York. Mr. White, 62, the chairman, has led the company since 1976.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/05/20/business/company-news-utility-seeks-grant-to-burn-coal-cleanly.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">COMPANY NEWS; Utility Seeks Grant to Burn Coal Cleanly<date>Published: May 20, 1988</date><text>An application to build the world's first full-size electric plant with a new system for burning coal cleanly is among the proposals that the Energy Department will begin evaluating next week.Between 50 and 100 applications are expected to compete for $575 million in funds intended to stimulate coal technologies.Utility companies have high hopes for the clean-coal technology, known as pressurized fluidized bed combustion, because it extracts more usable energy, with sharply reduced emissions of two components of acid rain, nitrogen oxide and sulfur oxide. Burns at Lower TemperatureFluidized bed combustion is a system for burning coal in which pulverized coal is supported on a bed of air, instead of being blown across a surface in a boiler. The coal spends longer in the boiler and burns at a lower temperature, which reduces nitrogen emissions. In addition, the coal in the boiler is mixed with limestone, allowing a chemical reaction in which the sulfur attaches to the ash, instead of flying up the stack.In the pressurized version of this technology, the boiler is kept under pressure, so that the hot gases it emits can be used to drive two turbines, one directly and one with the steam produced. That allows 4 percent more electricity to be produced from the same amount of coal. 7 Million Customers The application for the bed-combustion system will be made by the American Electric Power Company, one of the nation's largest utilities. The company, based in Columbus, Ohio, provides power to seven million people in seven states. American Electric said yesterday that it would apply for a subsidy to put the new coal technology to work at its Philip Sporn Plant, on the Ohio River near New Haven, W.Va.The plant would have a capacity of 330 megawatts, more than 15 times as large as the biggest existing plant using that technology.''This new clean-coal technology has the potential for making our nation's coal supply usable in an environmentally acceptable manner,'' W. S. White Jr., American Electric's chairman, said.The Energy Department program subsidizes projects in which the private-sector participants pay more than half the cost. Applications are due on Monday, and the department is concentrating on technologies that can be added to existing coal plants. Replacing Two BoilersThe department also accepted applications in early 1986, in a $400 million program that covered any technology for using coal cleanly.According to American Electric, replacing two of the Sporn plant's four boilers with a single pressurized fluidized bed boiler would raise the power output to 330 megawatts from 300 megawatts and cut the nitrogen oxide emissions to 1,600 tons a year from 6,900 tons. The sulfur emissions would fall from 8,100 tons a year to between 900 tons and 3,800 tons, depending on the coal used. The project would cost $579 million, of which American Electric is seeking $185 million from the Federal Government.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/09/11/us/michigan-atom-plant-charged-with-lying-to-us.html?ref=americanelectricpowercompany">MICHIGAN ATOM PLANT CHARGED WITH LYING TO U.S.<date>September 11, 1986</date><text>The corporate owners and a former safety engineer of a Michigan nuclear power plant were indicted today on charges of lying to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission in 1981 about compliance with Federal fire safety regulations. At issue is the 10-year-old Donald C. Cook nuclear plant at Bridgman, Mich. A grand jury in Grand Rapids, Mich., charged the plant operator, the Indiana and Michigan Electric Company of Fort Wayne, Ind., and the utility's corporate parent, the American Electric Power Company of Columbus, Ohio, with eight fire safety violations, according to the Justice Department.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The corporate owners and a former safety engineer of a Michigan nuclear power plant were indicted today on charges of lying to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission in 1981 about compliance with Federal fire safety regulations. At issue is the 10-year-old Donald C. Cook nuclear plant at Bridgman, Mich. A grand jury in Grand Rapids, Mich., charged the plant operator, the Indiana and Michigan Electric Company of Fort Wayne, Ind., and the utility's corporate parent, the American Electric Power Company of Columbus, Ohio, with eight fire safety violations, according to the Justice Department.</text></article></page><page index="10" /></root>
