<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Avon Products Inc"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/31/business/calling-for-avon-to-make-a-change.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Calling for Avon to Make a Change<date>Published: October 30, 2011</date><text>A good look in the mirror might help Avon’s management. Andrea Jung, the chief executive of the $8 billion cosmetics company, has twice failed to turn it around. Never mind the federal investigation into possible wrongdoing that was disclosed last week; Avon’s performance even before then had been dismal.The company’s stock is down more than 20 percent since the beginning of the year, substantially underperforming peers like L’Oréal and Revlon. A big part of the decline came after its quarterly report on Thursday. But Ms. Jung can’t blame the current tough economy, even if it has not helped matters. She presided over several years of strong performance after becoming the chief in 1999. The company’s shares have significantly underperformed the broader market and major rivals at least since 2005, when Avon announced plans to flatten the management structure, streamline the supply chain and outsource certain services. Ms. Jung took the restructuring scalpel out again four years later, but failed to produce lasting results. Sales growth ran in double digits early during her tenure, but won’t even reach mid-single digits this year. Moreover, she seems to accept that her strategy in one big market, Brazil, needs to be rethought, and the company’s performance in America has been disappointing, too. Some investors may have been reluctant to rock the boat given Avon’s lucrative 5 percent dividend yield. But a squeeze on the company’s free cash flow has put that in doubt. The $37 million of free cash generated in the first nine months of this year is well short of the dividend outflow of $302 million in the same period. Dipping into cash holdings to maintain the payout may not be a sustainable approach. Avon’s new chief financial officer, Kimberly Ross, will have that to grapple with when she starts on the job next month. In addition, she and her colleagues will have to handle a Securities and Exchange Commission inquiry into whether the company broke bribery and disclosure laws. Ms. Jung said the buck stops with her. After 12 years in charge and two ineffectual efforts to revamp the company, the Avon board should hold her to the statement and give someone else a chance. Fixing Housing There’s a growing chorus among legislators to get the government out of the housing business. That’s understandable given the possible $311 billion bill that Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac may hand over to taxpayers, according to an estimate last week from the Federal Housing Finance Agency, the firms’ regulator. But the recent failure of PMI Group’s mortgage insurance business is a reminder that swaths of housing’s private sector need fixing, too. PMI, like rivals Radian and MGIC, was once a high flier during the mortgage boom. It even had a $4 billion market capitalization. This month, PMI was effectively seized by the Arizona Department of Insurance. The state regulator took over its mortgage-writing unit after prohibiting it from issuing new policies. That’s a death knell in an industry that needs new premiums to counterbalance claims delivered by the housing bust. And PMI is not the only one in trouble. Only one of the six major home loan insurers has an investment-grade credit rating. A few are dangerously close to breaching their risk-to-capital limit of 25 to 1, the minimum required to ensure they have enough to pay claims. It took just one quarter for PMI to race through this threshold, moving from 24.4-to-1 to 58.1-to-1 by the end of June, according to the brokerage CRT Capital. The duration of the housing crisis has made life hard for mortgage insurers. They earn their money by insuring lenders against future losses on mortgages that don’t come with a 20 percent down payment from the borrower. As home sales have slumped and banks become loath to lend to borrowers who don’t deliver large down payments, the business has suffered. But bad practices prevalent in the good years bear a good part of the blame. For instance, as lenders loosened their credit standards during the boom, many mortgage insurers felt compelled to give banks a share of their premium income. That left the insurers with a smaller cushion to weather losses from claims during the housing collapse. If the government ever hopes to extricate itself from the business of housing finance, it needs to ensure private sector backstops are well-fortified and well-regulated. For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com.A good look in the mirror might help Avon’s management. Andrea Jung, the chief executive of the $8 billion cosmetics company, has twice failed to turn it around. Never mind the federal investigation into possible wrongdoing that was disclosed last week; Avon’s performance even before then had been dismal.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/04/business/04avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Latin American Market Lifts Profit at Avon<date>Published: May 3, 2011</date><text>Raising prices and selling more products in Latin America, its largest market, helped the cosmetics seller Avon Products more than triple its first-quarter profit, the company said on Tuesday. Avon’s net income and revenue beat expectations, and the company’s stock rose more than 4 percent. Investors were reassured that two large markets for Avon showed signs of recovery after struggling, although Avon said work remained. “We are squarely focused on restoring growth in Brazil and Russia in the second half,” the chief executive, Andrea Jung, said. Revenue also rose fast in other areas, particularly Turkey and South Africa, and Citi Investment Research analyst Wendy Nicholson said the year was off to a strong start. More than 80 percent of Avon’s quarterly revenue came from outside the United States and Canada. But its North America revenue, excluding Mexico, fell 2 percent for the quarter. The company said it would have fallen 10 percent if Avon hadn’t bought a direct seller of jewelry, Silpada. Avon, based in New York, makes more than 40 percent of its revenue in Latin America, where a 16 percent sales increase helped the company’s total revenue rise 7 percent to $2.63 billion, beating analysts’ average expectation for $2.59 billion. Mexico and Venezuela were particularly strong in Latin America, helped by growth in independent sellers. Excluding the effect of a weaker dollar, Avon’s total revenue rose 4 percent. Its net income was $143.6 million, or 33 cents a share, up from $42.5 million, or 10 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding discontinued operations and one-time items, Avon said it earned 37 cents a share. Analysts expected earnings of 32 cents a share, according to FactSet. Avon’s shares rose $1.34, or 4.5 percent, to close at $30.91 Tuesday.Raising prices and selling more products in Latin America, its largest market, helped the cosmetics seller Avon Products more than triple its first-quarter profit, the company said on Tuesday. Avon’s net income and revenue beat expectations, and the company’s stock rose more than 4 percent. Investors were reassured that two large markets for Avon showed signs of recovery after struggling, although Avon said work remained. “We are squarely focused on restoring growth in Brazil and Russia in the second half,” the chief executive, Andrea Jung, said. Revenue also rose fast in other areas, particularly Turkey and South Africa, and Citi Investment Research analyst Wendy Nicholson said the year was off to a strong start. More than 80 percent of Avon’s quarterly revenue came from outside the United States and Canada. But its North America revenue, excluding Mexico, fell 2 percent for the quarter. The company said it would have fallen 10 percent if Avon hadn’t bought a direct seller of jewelry, Silpada. Avon, based in New York, makes more than 40 percent of its revenue in Latin America, where a 16 percent sales increase helped the company’s total revenue rise 7 percent to $2.63 billion, beating analysts’ average expectation for $2.59 billion. Mexico and Venezuela were particularly strong in Latin America, helped by growth in independent sellers. Excluding the effect of a weaker dollar, Avon’s total revenue rose 4 percent. Its net income was $143.6 million, or 33 cents a share, up from $42.5 million, or 10 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding discontinued operations and one-time items, Avon said it earned 37 cents a share. Analysts expected earnings of 32 cents a share, according to FactSet. Avon’s shares rose $1.34, or 4.5 percent, to close at $30.91 Tuesday.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/14/fashion/14skinside.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Direct Approach Works for Avon<date>Published: January 13, 2010</date><text>IN the 1880s, David McConnell, a door-to-door book salesman in upstate New York, thought that he might have better luck if he presented potential customers with a gift of perfume. By 1886, McConnell had formed the California Perfume Company, and within 20 years, 10,000 representatives were selling 117 products in 600 styles. In 1939, the company changed its name to Avon Products.Today, direct sales make up 1 percent, or $29.6 billion, of consumer sales in the United States, according to Amy Robinson, a spokeswoman for the Direct Selling Association. In the cosmetics and personal care market, Avon dominates with more than 5.8 million representatives worldwide. Even in a sluggish economy, Avon is calling. Its sales last year were estimated to be $10.4 billion, nearly double what they were in 2000. Although Avon is recognized for its mass-market products — in the United States, a basic face cream sells for $3.49 — the company also offers a more premium brand, Anew, with prices as high as $68 for an anti-aging serum. And because high-end beauty sales have been outperforming low-end products, Avon will likely continue to focus on developing more premium products, said Mark Astrachan, an analyst at Stifel Nicolaus, an investment bank. Face-to-face sales still account for over 76 percent of all direct sales. “The personal connection of this kind of sale cannot be underestimated,” Ms. Robinson said. Just because someone’s on a tight budget, she said, “doesn’t mean she’s stopped buying her foundation.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/14/fashion/14SKIN.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon’s Little Sister Is Calling<date>Published: January 13, 2010</date><text>KRISTIAUNA MANGUM, 22, a senior at Ohio State University in Columbus, said she always had a flair for makeup, but never considered it a professional calling. Then she heard about a pilot college program offered by Avon’s little sister brand, Mark, two years ago. “My mother was an Avon Lady, so I thought, huh, maybe becoming a Mark Girl could really be the way to go,” she said.Now Ms. Mangum is the sales manager for Mark at Ohio State, and manages 155 other Mark Girls who roam the dormitories and sorority houses, selling Mark beauty products and fashion accessories for a commission in the range of 20 to 50 percent. “It’s really a grass-roots kind of thing, hitting the dorms, sororities, Facebook,” said Ms. Mangum, who uses her share of the profit, about $800 a month, to help settle her student loans. “I even rented space at local high school fairs — with 16- and 17-year-olds, you can move a lot of lip gloss,” said Ms. Mangum, whose major is marketing. She is one of more than 40,000 Mark Girls in North America, mainly 18- to 24-year-old women who are changing the nature of direct sales by using the brand’s personalized e-boutiques, iPhone app and new Facebook e-shop, one of the beauty industry’s first forays into Facebook e-commerce. “We’ve taken the same DNA of direct selling that has always been a part of Avon’s history and applied it to the digital world for our Mark reps to reach their customers,” said Claudia Poccia, president of Mark at Avon, which introduced the brand in 2003. “Now, we’re offering our Mark reps the opportunity to sell products not just door to door, but on Facebook, wall to wall.” The Mark brand is evolving. It has its own spokeswoman, Lauren Conrad, the former reality TV star of “The Hills,” now a fashion designer and best-selling author of “L.A. Candy.” Its Facebook fan page has over 84,000 fans. According to estimates from Stifel Nicolaus, an investment bank, Mark’s revenue last year was about $70 million. Unlike other companies involved in direct sales — including Amway, which may dedicate a product line or two to a more youth-oriented market, or Mary Kay and Avon, whose products are geared toward middle-aged women — Mark focuses almost exclusively on teenagers and women under 30. The younger demographic, at least concerning sales representatives, has its drawbacks. “The fact that the reps are younger can mean different rules apply as to how a direct-selling company is going to have to manage them,” said Linda Bolton Weiser, a managing director of consumer equity research at Caris &amp; Company, an investment bank. “There could be questions about volume limits and credit — a younger rep may be cut off earlier. And, if a rep is under 18, obviously you would need parental permission.” Still, Mark’s motto — “Make your mark” — seems to resonate with its zealous representatives. But can Tweets and news feeds from Mark Girls compete with over a century of Avon Ladies’ experience? Because of the difference in how the products are branded and the separation between Avon and Mark representatives (those selling Avon can also sell Mark products, but not the other way around), there is some internal competition among representatives. On the mark.girl discussion board on Facebook, the Mark-versus-Avon topic sparked a lively debate when one Mark representative wrote: “Has anybody else noticed Avon reps not taking the Mark product seriously?” An Avon representative replied: “A lot of Avon women I know don’t push Mark because it has a lower profit as compared to the Avon core product line.” Some experts in the beauty business are fans of Mark. “It really helps that Mark has such low price points,” said Elaine D’Farley, beauty director of Self magazine. “Visually, it’s fun. The products hit the trend.” Indeed, products such as the magnetic refillable color palette compact ($4) and Hook Ups (about $10) — two-ended cosmetic dispensers that can be customized to connect, for example, lip gloss and lip pencil, eyeliner and mascara — are so popular, as one Mark representative said, that “they’re impossible to keep in my purse.” But some products have been criticized online, where a bad review may resonate more negatively than an item quietly returned to a store. On the Mark Web site, one reviewer said that a cheek tint left “zero shimmer on my cheek but plenty on my hands.” And on Makeupalley, a forum for comments on beauty products, a reviewer complained about Mark’s Good Riddance: “I have under eye circles and it didn’t even come close to covering them.” But when it comes to using social media tools to sell services or products, Annemarie Frank, director of digital media and strategic alliance of Mark at Avon, said the viral nature of Mark’s brand presence is what company executives are after. “Mark Girls can advertise their ability to sell products right on their Facebook profiles, and the widget functionality of Mark’s e-shop enables us to drop the shop into other places to give the brand a presence wherever people hang out online,” she said. Of course, Mark is not the only beauty company to use digital marketing. Direct-sales firms like Mary Kay and Avon are also using social media and online tools. Both companies have a presence on Facebook as well as apps for cellphones and hand-held devices that their representatives can use to make sales. Other skin care companies like Jafra, which also sells cosmetics, and Arbonne do less with social media. But this might be changing. The Direct Selling Association dedicated its annual communications seminar last month to new media strategies. “Attendance was double our usual number,” said Amy Robinson, an association spokeswoman. “If you’re a direct-selling company and you’re not on the Internet or making use of some of these new technologies, you’re already behind.” For college-age sales representatives, Mark’s digital and mobile offerings can inspire any number of approaches. One Mark representative, Hannah Parish, 20, a senior at Coastal Carolina University in Conway, S.C., has been selling Mark products since last January, when she ordered a Speedway Do Everything cover stick ($8) and signed up for her Mark Girl starter kit two weeks later. “I fell in love with it,” Ms. Parish said. This fall, when the Mark Rewards Program advertised a contest for all-expense-paid trips to this year’s Sundance Film Festival (a guest included) for the two highest-selling Mark Girls, Ms. Parish said, “That forced me to be really creative.” She created a Facebook event, “Send Hannah to Sundance,” and invited 600 people in her network to join. She made numerous special offers, including one to bring her best client along with her to the festival in Park City, Utah. Ms. Parish sold $6,000 worth of products; she and a friend will be traveling to the festival in two weeks. “I’m a film buff and I’ve never seen snow," she said. “When I answered the phone and heard, ‘Congratulations,’ I started screaming. My friend who bought $617 worth of merchandise and gets to come with me is still screaming.”</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/01/business/01interview.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Selling Beauty on a Global Scale<date>Published: October 31, 2008</date><text>THE cosmetic company Avon Products traces its roots to the horse and buggy days of the late 19th century, when sales representatives sold perfume door-to-door, often to women who lived far from big department stores. This American frontier model has translated well to countries like Brazil and China, where large populations are dispersed across a vast countryside. Today, more than two-thirds of Avon’s sales are outside the United States. Skip to next paragraph Andrea Jung Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » The direct-selling model  where independent sales representatives do not work directly for Avon  makes it easier to break into new markets, says Avon’s chairwoman and chief executive, Andrea Jung. About 5.5 million sales representatives now sell Avon products, be it lip gloss in Shanghai or face powder in Rio de Janeiro. The company, reporting its third-quarter earnings Thursday, said the only region where sales fell was North America, which it defines as the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. By contrast, revenue rose 25 percent in both Latin America and China and 8 percent in Western Europe, the Middle East and Africa. Ms. Jung, who was born the daughter of Chinese immigrants in Toronto and moved to a suburb of Boston when she was 10, recently discussed how she thinks the company’s direct-selling model can improve the lives of women in developing countries and where the next big growth opportunities are for Avon. Q. Since you became the chief of Avon in 1999, the company has expanded into emerging markets. Why do you think your direct-selling model works so well in developing countries? A. It is part of a movement around the world for women to have more economic independence. From her very first order, a representative does not have to pull the money out of her pocket. We send her the products, and she pays us after she sells them. The direct-selling model does not have to be centered around where there is heavy retail infrastructure, either. For example, China is going to be one of Avon’s largest market opportunities. It has a large geographic expanse, with hundreds of thousands of women in small villages really striving to make an earnings opportunity for themselves. Q. And the majority of your independent sales representatives are women? A. Well over 95 percent are women and the men are often in Avon couples. I love those conversations, where the husbands tell me that they quit their jobs because their wife’s business was doing so well, so they’ve joined forces to run the business as a couple. Q. Given the fact that your sales representatives are not employed by Avon, how do you establish new markets? A. We hire recruiting managers, who are Avon employees. They start canvassing for representatives in work places, in religious gatherings, in school fund-raisers. We also run recruiting advertisements in a dozen markets today. And we train our representatives how to manage their businesses online. For example, in Turkey, where there is not much Internet penetration, we have close to 100 percent of our sales representatives entering their orders online. They go to Internet cafes or libraries. Q. How do you deal with economic uncertainty in emerging markets? A. With what’s going on the last couple of weeks, it reminds me of the very difficult time we had in Russia. I recall in the late ’90s, with the massive devaluation of the ruble, our Russian business really became quite challenged. Some companies were retrenching, but we looked across Russia and saw 11 time zones, with women in every small town and village who wanted the opportunity to be economically independent. So we were committed to staying. Q. Do you feel that your experience growing up as the daughter of Chinese immigrants has influenced your career? A. It has given me a global vantage point, being the daughter of immigrants from China, who had nothing when they came here. And now I am leading a company. It speaks to something deep in me, the concept that you don’t have to start with anything. The direct-sales opportunity allows people to change their lives. Q. Many of your customers are familiar with the work of the Avon Foundation, but they might not know that you have similar programs in countries like Mexico and Malaysia. How global is your philanthropy now? A. We’ve got programs in around 50 different countries. Together, we have raised $580 million, mostly for breast cancer research, diagnosis and treatment. A couple of years ago, we added a second issue: violence against women. We have made educational pamphlets about breast self-exams and about domestic violence, which our representatives can give to their customers. We have donated mammography units to underserved hospitals in Spain and created mobile mammography units in China. Recently, I had one of those amazing experiences where life and work intersect. My maternal grandmother, who was from mainland China, died of breast cancer in Singapore in the 1970s. It was diagnosed at a late stage and she just passed away. It was something that wasn’t talked about back then. It was the “c” word. About a year ago, my mother discovered that she had breast cancer. She was diagnosed at an Avon breast cancer center, which our people worked so hard to donate to Mass. General. It was detected at a very early stage, with digital mammography, and one year later she is cancer-free. When I look at the two generations in my own family, it shows the progress that has been made on this issue over the last 30 years. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on November 1, 2008, on page B2 of the New York edition.THE cosmetic company Avon Products traces its roots to the horse and buggy days of the late 19th century, when sales representatives sold perfume door-to-door, often to women who lived far from big department stores. This American frontier model has translated well to countries like Brazil and China, where large populations are dispersed across a vast countryside. Today, more than two-thirds of Avon’s sales are outside the United States. Skip to next paragraph Andrea Jung Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » The direct-selling model  where independent sales representatives do not work directly for Avon  makes it easier to break into new markets, says Avon’s chairwoman and chief executive, Andrea Jung. About 5.5 million sales representatives now sell Avon products, be it lip gloss in Shanghai or face powder in Rio de Janeiro. The company, reporting its third-quarter earnings Thursday, said the only region where sales fell was North America, which it defines as the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. By contrast, revenue rose 25 percent in both Latin America and China and 8 percent in Western Europe, the Middle East and Africa. Ms. Jung, who was born the daughter of Chinese immigrants in Toronto and moved to a suburb of Boston when she was 10, recently discussed how she thinks the company’s direct-selling model can improve the lives of women in developing countries and where the next big growth opportunities are for Avon. Q. Since you became the chief of Avon in 1999, the company has expanded into emerging markets. Why do you think your direct-selling model works so well in developing countries? A. It is part of a movement around the world for women to have more economic independence. From her very first order, a representative does not have to pull the money out of her pocket. We send her the products, and she pays us after she sells them. The direct-selling model does not have to be centered around where there is heavy retail infrastructure, either. For example, China is going to be one of Avon’s largest market opportunities. It has a large geographic expanse, with hundreds of thousands of women in small villages really striving to make an earnings opportunity for themselves. Q. And the majority of your independent sales representatives are women? A. Well over 95 percent are women and the men are often in Avon couples. I love those conversations, where the husbands tell me that they quit their jobs because their wife’s business was doing so well, so they’ve joined forces to run the business as a couple. Q. Given the fact that your sales representatives are not employed by Avon, how do you establish new markets? A. We hire recruiting managers, who are Avon employees. They start canvassing for representatives in work places, in religious gatherings, in school fund-raisers. We also run recruiting advertisements in a dozen markets today. And we train our representatives how to manage their businesses online. For example, in Turkey, where there is not much Internet penetration, we have close to 100 percent of our sales representatives entering their orders online. They go to Internet cafes or libraries. Q. How do you deal with economic uncertainty in emerging markets? A. With what’s going on the last couple of weeks, it reminds me of the very difficult time we had in Russia. I recall in the late ’90s, with the massive devaluation of the ruble, our Russian business really became quite challenged. Some companies were retrenching, but we looked across Russia and saw 11 time zones, with women in every small town and village who wanted the opportunity to be economically independent. So we were committed to staying. Q. Do you feel that your experience growing up as the daughter of Chinese immigrants has influenced your career? A. It has given me a global vantage point, being the daughter of immigrants from China, who had nothing when they came here. And now I am leading a company. It speaks to something deep in me, the concept that you don’t have to start with anything. The direct-sales opportunity allows people to change their lives. Q. Many of your customers are familiar with the work of the Avon Foundation, but they might not know that you have similar programs in countries like Mexico and Malaysia. How global is your philanthropy now? A. We’ve got programs in around 50 different countries. Together, we have raised $580 million, mostly for breast cancer research, diagnosis and treatment. A couple of years ago, we added a second issue: violence against women. We have made educational pamphlets about breast self-exams and about domestic violence, which our representatives can give to their customers. We have donated mammography units to underserved hospitals in Spain and created mobile mammography units in China. Recently, I had one of those amazing experiences where life and work intersect. My maternal grandmother, who was from mainland China, died of breast cancer in Singapore in the 1970s. It was diagnosed at a late stage and she just passed away. It was something that wasn’t talked about back then. It was the “c” word. About a year ago, my mother discovered that she had breast cancer. She was diagnosed at an Avon breast cancer center, which our people worked so hard to donate to Mass. General. It was detected at a very early stage, with digital mammography, and one year later she is cancer-free. When I look at the two generations in my own family, it shows the progress that has been made on this issue over the last 30 years.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/31/business/31avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Sales Abroad Lift Profit for Avon<date>Published: October 30, 2008</date><text>Strong foreign sales helped Avon Products post a 60 percent increase in third-quarter profit, but adjusted earnings missed expectations and the company’s shares fell to a seven-year low on Thursday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » Avon, which sells beauty products, jewelry and apparel, has been overhauling its business by cutting jobs, closing unprofitable operations and moving work to countries with lower labor costs. The company has also raised prices to help offset rising costs for commodities, like oil, which has increased the cost of manufacturing, packaging and distribution. Profit rose 60 percent to $222.6 million, or 52 cents a share, compared with $139.1 million, or 32 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 13 percent, to $2.64 billion, compared with $2.35 billion a year ago, partly because of higher prices and 15 percent growth in sales of beauty products. Shares of Avon, which is based in New York, fell $4.10, or 15 percent, to $22.57 a share. During the quarter, advertising costs rose 11 percent, to $106 million, as Avon increased marketing efforts to introduce products, including its Anew Rejuvenate skin care line. The company benefited from a weaker dollar and recorded strong sales growth abroad, especially in Latin America, where revenue rose 25 percent. Sales also rose 25 percent in China and climbed 17 percent in Central and Eastern Europe. Sales in North America grew just 3 percent. Sales of beauty products were flat, as the economy remained weak. More Articles in Business »Strong foreign sales helped Avon Products post a 60 percent increase in third-quarter profit, but adjusted earnings missed expectations and the company’s shares fell to a seven-year low on Thursday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » Avon, which sells beauty products, jewelry and apparel, has been overhauling its business by cutting jobs, closing unprofitable operations and moving work to countries with lower labor costs. The company has also raised prices to help offset rising costs for commodities, like oil, which has increased the cost of manufacturing, packaging and distribution. Profit rose 60 percent to $222.6 million, or 52 cents a share, compared with $139.1 million, or 32 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 13 percent, to $2.64 billion, compared with $2.35 billion a year ago, partly because of higher prices and 15 percent growth in sales of beauty products. Shares of Avon, which is based in New York, fell $4.10, or 15 percent, to $22.57 a share. During the quarter, advertising costs rose 11 percent, to $106 million, as Avon increased marketing efforts to introduce products, including its Anew Rejuvenate skin care line. The company benefited from a weaker dollar and recorded strong sales growth abroad, especially in Latin America, where revenue rose 25 percent. Sales also rose 25 percent in China and climbed 17 percent in Central and Eastern Europe. Sales in North America grew just 3 percent. Sales of beauty products were flat, as the economy remained weak.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/31/business/31avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Profit Jumps on Strong Global Sales<date>Published: July 31, 2008</date><text>Avon Products said on Wednesday that quarterly profit more than doubled, beating estimates and sending its shares to a three-year high, as increased demand for its products in Europe and Latin America offset slower sales growth in the United States. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » Price increases and the weak dollar lifted revenue for the company, the world’s largest direct seller of cosmetics, and cost savings from a three-year-old reorganization helped counter rising commodity costs. Second-quarter profit rose to $235.6 million, or 55 cents a share, from $112.7 million, or 26 cents a share, a year earlier. The 2008 quarter included $13 million of reorganization charges, versus $82 million of one-time charges a year earlier for revamping and an overhaul of the company’s product line. Excluding one-time items, Avon earned 57 cents a share, beating the average analyst estimate of 49 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Avon is cutting jobs and weeding out less profitable products. More Articles in Business »Avon Products said on Wednesday that quarterly profit more than doubled, beating estimates and sending its shares to a three-year high, as increased demand for its products in Europe and Latin America offset slower sales growth in the United States. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Avon Products Inc Go to your Portfolio » Price increases and the weak dollar lifted revenue for the company, the world’s largest direct seller of cosmetics, and cost savings from a three-year-old reorganization helped counter rising commodity costs. Second-quarter profit rose to $235.6 million, or 55 cents a share, from $112.7 million, or 26 cents a share, a year earlier. The 2008 quarter included $13 million of reorganization charges, versus $82 million of one-time charges a year earlier for revamping and an overhaul of the company’s product line. Excluding one-time items, Avon earned 57 cents a share, beating the average analyst estimate of 49 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Avon is cutting jobs and weeding out less profitable products.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DD1630F937A15756C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING; Madison Avenue Says Hello to 'Hello,' Again<date>Published: May 24, 2007</date><text>IT seems as if Madison Avenue is on some kind of a ''Hi.'' At least half a dozen advertising campaigns are using the greeting ''Hello'' as a way to attract consumer attention. Some of the salutations are logical, like the ''Hello'' offered in a commercial for the iPhone from Apple. Some are meant to be upbeat, like ''Hello tomorrow'' and ''Hello future'' in ads for, respectively, Avon Products and the Lincoln Financial Group. Some ''Hellos'' are more intriguing, like the enticing ''Hello delicious'' in print ads for Level vodka. The fact that several campaigns for disparate brands are based on the same word reinforces the notion that similarity is often the sincerest form of advertising. Centering a campaign on ''Hello'' represents ''a friendly, more engaging way to connect with consumers, but it's pretty overused,'' said Allen P. Adamson, managing director at Landor Associates in New York, a brand and corporate identity consulting company owned by the WPP Group. ''The first few might have been effective as a 'pay attention to me' thing,'' he added, because ''we're hard-wired to look up when someone says 'hello.' '' This is not the first time that ''hello'' and its variants have been used as marketing devices. The comedian Jack Benny, for instance, opened his radio show by proclaiming ''Jell-O again,'' accenting his sponsor's brand name the way ''Hello'' would be. Colgate-Palmolive once sold a shampoo named Halo, which was the subject of a popular jingle that began ''Halo everybody, Halo.'' And in 1984, Apple introduced the Macintosh with print ads that showed the computer with just one word -- ''Hello'' -- displayed on its screen. ''Advertising being an annoying, interruptive medium, 'Hello' is kind of a nice salutation, a friendly way of introducing yourself,'' said Lee Clow, chairman and chief creative officer at the TBWA Worldwide unit of the Omnicom Group who has long worked for Apple. That is particularly true for technology products, he added, which can use the greeting ''to let people feel comfortable, to humanize something that they might look at and say, 'I don't know if I can use it.' '' The ''Hello'' in the iPhone commercial, which started running in February, was intended to accomplish the same task, Mr. Clow said, as well as echo the ''Hello'' from the Macintosh campaign 23 years earlier. ''We felt like it was a little part of our Apple vocabulary,'' he added, ''so it seemed like a natural to use it to introduce the iPhone.'' The iPhone commercial features excerpts of scenes from movies and television shows in which stars both human (Marlon Brando, Jerry Lewis) and animated (Betty Rubble, Mr. Incredible) are answering the telephone. The spot ends with an appearance by the iPhone, scheduled to make its debut next month. Just as a ''Hello'' can help make a technology pitch seem less intimidating, it can make ads for financial products less daunting, executives at the Lincoln Financial Group say. ''We don't want people approaching their retirement with fear or apprehension,'' said David Wozniak, assistant vice president for corporate branding and advertising at the Lincoln National Corporation in Philadelphia, which is using ''Hello future'' in ads as well as on the cover of its annual report. The idea to say ''Hello future'' is also tailored to the target audience for the campaign, he added, which is the baby boom generation. ''Looking at retirement and what it means to the boomers,'' Mr. Wozniak said, ''we realized an opportunity we had to zone in on optimism for the future, enabling people to achieve their dreams and beyond.'' The Lincoln campaign, by Martin/Williams in Minneapolis, an agency also owned by Omnicom, appears to have started the most recent ''Hello'' trend; the ads began appearing in spring 2005. The campaign was followed a year later by the ''Hello delicious'' campaign for Level vodka, sold by the V&amp;S Group. ''We were cognizant of 'Hello' being used before in advertising, commercials, songs,'' said Rob Smiley, creative director on Level at TBWA/Chiat/Day in New York, part of TBWA Worldwide, ''but here it's not 'Hello' in isolation.'' ''The campaign is very much an introduction or reintroduction of the Level brand to the consumer,'' he added, ''and just as 'Hello' is a way to greet someone you don't know, this is a way to greet the vodka you don't know.'' Among other ''Hello'' ads are commercials for Target discount stores that change the Beatles song ''Hello, Goodbye'' into ''Hello Goodbuy,'' a campaign for the National Marine Manufacturers Association that urges consumers to ''Discover boating'' with a song featuring lyrics like ''Hello, hello, how are you?'' and the ''Hello tomorrow'' campaign for Avon, created by Soho Square in New York, an agency owned by WPP. The theme speaks to ''the sense of pride and optimism as we go forward with our business strategies,'' said Elizabeth A. Smith, executive vice president at Avon in New York and president for Avon North America and global marketing. She referred to changes at Avon that include a significant increase in the ad budget. As repetitious as all the ''Hellos'' might be, think of what was avoided as a result of Americans shunning the greeting preferred by the inventor of the telephone. According to legend, Alexander Graham Bell advocated answering calls with a hearty ''Ahoy.'' Photos: The ''Hello delicious'' campaign for Level, sold by the V&amp;S Group, aims to introduce the vodka to consumers.; Apple introduced the Macintosh computer in 1984 with ads that showed the computer with the word ''Hello'' displayed on its screen.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/15/business/media/15adco.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Comes Calling With a New Campaign<date>Published: March 15, 2007</date><text>REMEMBER the perky commercials that began with the ringing of a doorbell followed by the words Avon calling? Now, years later, Avon wants to ring billions of doorbells at the same time with the largest campaign in its 121-year history. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image The Hello tomorrow ads for Avon are the first work from a new creative agency, Soho Square in New York, part of the WPP Group, which has been developing the campaign since September 2005. Multimedia Video Avon Ad Video 2nd Avon Ad The campaign, now getting under way, carries the upbeat theme Hello tomorrow. The ads are the first work from a new Avon creative agency, Soho Square in New York, part of the WPP Group, which has been developing the campaign since September 2005. It was a journey in getting there, said Elizabeth Smith, executive vice president at Avon Products in New York, who is president for Avon North American and global marketing. It was not a matter of, Gee, I love that brand,  she added, explaining what the campaign is meant to accomplish, but rather an effort to express that Avon is the company that best understands and empowers women. The campaign seeks to recruit sales representatives to join the more than five million who already work for Avon, as well as to build morale among employees of the company, which recently went through layoffs. The campaign also has a worldwide scope, in keeping with a recent reorganization of Avon by Andrea Jung, its chief executive, to make more decisions along global lines in areas like marketing. To reflect the ambitious nature of the campaign, Avon plans to increase ad spending this year to $340 million, compared with $250 million in 2006 and $135 million in 2005. We feel wonderful about the message, Ms. Smith said, and were backing it up with the dollars. A marketing expert said that the campaign might still fall short. The issue remains as to whether Ms. Jung can use this effort to enthuse and energize her five million sales representatives, said Peter Sealey, a former marketing executive for companies like Coca-Cola. Maybe she can rally the troops, said Mr. Sealey, who is adjunct professor of marketing at the Drucker School of Management at Claremont Graduate University, but he said the real issue was what he called a conflict between relying on a sales force and embracing the opportunity to sell in a more pervasive and personal way, through the Internet.  The campaign has an online component, at avon.com, where Avon has been selling products for the last decade, along with television commercials, print advertisements and brochures. There is also a cause-marketing element. Avon is founding a Hello Tomorrow Fund and pledges to donate money through it to organizations in 18 countries that help women in areas like business development and community service. The campaign has a broader reach than the sales force and company employees, Ms. Smith said. It is also intended to burnish the Avon brand image among consumers as well as help sell Avon products like lipsticks, skin lotions, fragrances and moisturizers. Avon is one of those classic brands that everyone knows, said Nicola Bell, client services director at Soho Square, but theyve come to a point in time when they needed to re-energize the brand across all audiences. After research by the agency determined that Avon had to look for a more fresh, contemporary expression of its values in terms of empowering and supporting women, Ms. Bell said, a decision was made to speak in an optimistic tone as epitomized by the Hello tomorrow theme. The category is full of advertising that can sometimes make women feel a little guilty about the way they look and be a bit judgmental, Ms. Bell said. Were saying, Look to the future with optimism, look at aging with confidence.  The idea that a womens beauty and skin care brand can take a positive approach, in contrast to the typical pitch for the category, is gaining popularity. For example, a sibling agency of Soho Square, Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide, has been lauded for ads for the Dove brand sold by Unilever, which can be seen online at Web sites that include dove.com and campaignforrealbeauty.com. The initial two commercials in the Avon campaign, looking to recruit sales representatives, feature actual saleswomen, the company says. In one spot, the women are extremely enthusiastic, making statements like I love my job, I love the fact that Avon sells itself and Anyone can do this. In the other spot, the tone is more measured. The saleswomen make statements like We do business online now. One praises Avon for introducing new products that fit into your life, not the other way around. Another describes how the money she makes helps put her children through college. Ms. Smith said the two points of view were deliberate, to appeal to different types of prospective sales representatives. Some people have more pragmatic reasons, she added, and some have more entrepreneurial vision. The commercials, as well as the rest of the campaign, were tested in Avon markets, including Brazil, China and Poland, Ms. Smith said, and to a country it worked on the same emotional level.  The campaign is at least the third recent effort for a marketer that uses Hello as a welcoming word. The minitrend may have started with ads last summer for Level vodka, sold by V&amp;S Vin &amp; Sprit, which carry the headline Hello delicious. Next came a commercial for the Apple iPhone, which began appearing during the Academy Awards show on Feb. 25. The spot features snippets from movies and TV shows in which stars like Marilyn Monroe, Jackie Gleason and Robert Redford answer the telephone. The commercial, which can also be watched on apple.com, ends with the words Hello and Coming in June onscreen. Typically, such convergence is coincidental, according to a leading Madison Avenue creative executive, who said it could be difficult to trace sources of inspiration. Maybe its the planets, said Sal DeVito, creative director at DeVito/Verdi, known for campaigns for advertisers like Daffys, Legal Sea Foods and New York magazine. Its happened to us a few times. More Articles in Business »REMEMBER the perky commercials that began with the ringing of a doorbell followed by the words Avon calling? Now, years later, Avon wants to ring billions of doorbells at the same time with the largest campaign in its 121-year history. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image The Hello tomorrow ads for Avon are the first work from a new creative agency, Soho Square in New York, part of the WPP Group, which has been developing the campaign since September 2005. Multimedia Video Avon Ad Video 2nd Avon Ad The campaign, now getting under way, carries the upbeat theme Hello tomorrow. The ads are the first work from a new Avon creative agency, Soho Square in New York, part of the WPP Group, which has been developing the campaign since September 2005. It was a journey in getting there, said Elizabeth Smith, executive vice president at Avon Products in New York, who is president for Avon North American and global marketing. It was not a matter of, Gee, I love that brand,  she added, explaining what the campaign is meant to accomplish, but rather an effort to express that Avon is the company that best understands and empowers women. The campaign seeks to recruit sales representatives to join the more than five million who already work for Avon, as well as to build morale among employees of the company, which recently went through layoffs. The campaign also has a worldwide scope, in keeping with a recent reorganization of Avon by Andrea Jung, its chief executive, to make more decisions along global lines in areas like marketing. To reflect the ambitious nature of the campaign, Avon plans to increase ad spending this year to $340 million, compared with $250 million in 2006 and $135 million in 2005. We feel wonderful about the message, Ms. Smith said, and were backing it up with the dollars. A marketing expert said that the campaign might still fall short. The issue remains as to whether Ms. Jung can use this effort to enthuse and energize her five million sales representatives, said Peter Sealey, a former marketing executive for companies like Coca-Cola. Maybe she can rally the troops, said Mr. Sealey, who is adjunct professor of marketing at the Drucker School of Management at Claremont Graduate University, but he said the real issue was what he called a conflict between relying on a sales force and embracing the opportunity to sell in a more pervasive and personal way, through the Internet.  The campaign has an online component, at avon.com, where Avon has been selling products for the last decade, along with television commercials, print advertisements and brochures. There is also a cause-marketing element. Avon is founding a Hello Tomorrow Fund and pledges to donate money through it to organizations in 18 countries that help women in areas like business development and community service. The campaign has a broader reach than the sales force and company employees, Ms. Smith said. It is also intended to burnish the Avon brand image among consumers as well as help sell Avon products like lipsticks, skin lotions, fragrances and moisturizers. Avon is one of those classic brands that everyone knows, said Nicola Bell, client services director at Soho Square, but theyve come to a point in time when they needed to re-energize the brand across all audiences. After research by the agency determined that Avon had to look for a more fresh, contemporary expression of its values in terms of empowering and supporting women, Ms. Bell said, a decision was made to speak in an optimistic tone as epitomized by the Hello tomorrow theme. The category is full of advertising that can sometimes make women feel a little guilty about the way they look and be a bit judgmental, Ms. Bell said. Were saying, Look to the future with optimism, look at aging with confidence.  The idea that a womens beauty and skin care brand can take a positive approach, in contrast to the typical pitch for the category, is gaining popularity. For example, a sibling agency of Soho Square, Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide, has been lauded for ads for the Dove brand sold by Unilever, which can be seen online at Web sites that include dove.com and campaignforrealbeauty.com. The initial two commercials in the Avon campaign, looking to recruit sales representatives, feature actual saleswomen, the company says. In one spot, the women are extremely enthusiastic, making statements like I love my job, I love the fact that Avon sells itself and Anyone can do this. In the other spot, the tone is more measured. The saleswomen make statements like We do business online now. One praises Avon for introducing new products that fit into your life, not the other way around. Another describes how the money she makes helps put her children through college. Ms. Smith said the two points of view were deliberate, to appeal to different types of prospective sales representatives. Some people have more pragmatic reasons, she added, and some have more entrepreneurial vision. The commercials, as well as the rest of the campaign, were tested in Avon markets, including Brazil, China and Poland, Ms. Smith said, and to a country it worked on the same emotional level.  The campaign is at least the third recent effort for a marketer that uses Hello as a welcoming word. The minitrend may have started with ads last summer for Level vodka, sold by V&amp;S Vin &amp; Sprit, which carry the headline Hello delicious. Next came a commercial for the Apple iPhone, which began appearing during the Academy Awards show on Feb. 25. The spot features snippets from movies and TV shows in which stars like Marilyn Monroe, Jackie Gleason and Robert Redford answer the telephone. The commercial, which can also be watched on apple.com, ends with the words Hello and Coming in June onscreen. Typically, such convergence is coincidental, according to a leading Madison Avenue creative executive, who said it could be difficult to trace sources of inspiration. Maybe its the planets, said Sal DeVito, creative director at DeVito/Verdi, known for campaigns for advertisers like Daffys, Legal Sea Foods and New York magazine. Its happened to us a few times.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/13/business/13short.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Why Short Sellers Want to Crash the Tupperware Party<date>Published: November 13, 2006</date><text>When the Federal Trade Commission proposed new rules this spring for multilevel marketers  businesses best known for commercials that promise riches selling herbal supplements and beauty supplies  it drew howls of protest. Tupperware party-givers, diet pill vendors and knife salesmen sent the agency more than 15,000 letters complaining that the proposed rules would undo a $30-billion-a-year industry. Skip to next paragraph Tony Cenicola/The New York Times Now the regulator has gained an unusual ally: short sellers. These investors are betting that the stocks of multilevel marketing companies will decline when the new rules, which have received little public attention, go into effect. For years, companies like Avon Products, Herbalife and Amway have prospered by building armies of part-time sales representatives promoting insurance plans and anti-aging creams. Those representatives, in turn, are encouraged to recruit others and are promised that they will receive a portion of new enlistees profits. The companies profit, at least in part, by collecting increased revenue and fees paid by new sales representatives. In April, citing hundreds of fraud investigations, the F.T.C. proposed new rules for multilevel marketing companies and related businesses. They would require companies to tell potential recruits how many sales representatives have failed to earn more than their start-up costs and how many customers have filed lawsuits for deceptive practices. The proposal, which may be modified and could take as long as two years before approval, also requires a weeklong waiting period between approaching new sales representatives and sealing the deal. These companies provide part-time employment for hundreds of thousands of stay-home moms and people who need to feed their families, said Doris Wood, an official with the Multi-Level Marketing International Association. Its unfair to treat them like criminals. Analysts say the companies real concern is that the new rules will undermine their ability to attract new sales representatives. If companies have to tell recruits that the average income is only $1,400 instead of the $50,000 advertised on their Web site, or that the average salesman only lasts two months, a lot fewer people are going to sign up, said Mimi Sokolowski, an analyst with Sidoti &amp; Company who follows Tupperware Brands, Nu Skin Enterprises and other publicly traded multilevel marketing companies. She said that if the proposed rules pass without modification, recruitment in the United States could fall by as much as 40 percent. Which is why short selling investors, who sell borrowed shares of a stock and bet that the price will decline before they must repay the loans, are encouraging the F.T.C. to adopt the new rules. Since the commissions proposal, short sales of many publicly traded multilevel marketing companies have increased. Short positions in Avon, Tupperware, Nu Skin, Herbalife, Pre-Paid Legal Service, Mannatech, USANA Health Sciences and Medifast have grown. For instance, the number of Avon shares shorted has increased 44 percent, to 11.3 million, since April. Shorted shares of Tupperware are up 77 percent, to 3.9 million, or roughly 1 in every 15 publicly traded shares. To understand short sellers enthusiasm, consider Pre-Paid Legal, a public company that sells legal insurance through multilevel partnerships. For about $26 a month, Pre-Paid Legal lets customers consult an affiliate lawyer on legal matters like speeding tickets or writing a will. In 2005, the companys nearly 500,000 sales representatives brought in revenue exceeding $423 million. But like many multilevel marketing companies, Pre-Paid Legal suffers from high turnover. In 2005, the company replaced at least 50 percent of its active sales force, according to filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission. Industrywide, multilevel marketing companies typically replace almost all of their sales representatives every year. Short sellers are betting that the F.T.C.s proposed rules will make it harder for Pre-Paid Legal to replenish its ranks. Under the rules, Pre-Paid Legal would have to tell prospects that fewer than a quarter of its sales representatives sold more than one insurance plan in 2005, something it disclosed to investors in a filing with the S.E.C. While Pre-Paids Web site tells prospects that if they market just five memberships per week, youll receive $500 per week! very few representatives have consistently sold five memberships a week. Pre-Paid Legals promotional materials also make little mention of current litigation. But the proposed rules would probably force the company to disclose that in 1997, Pre-Paid Legal acknowledged misleading customers and consented to suspend sales of living trusts after an F.T.C. investigation. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »When the Federal Trade Commission proposed new rules this spring for multilevel marketers  businesses best known for commercials that promise riches selling herbal supplements and beauty supplies  it drew howls of protest. Tupperware party-givers, diet pill vendors and knife salesmen sent the agency more than 15,000 letters complaining that the proposed rules would undo a $30-billion-a-year industry. Skip to next paragraph Tony Cenicola/The New York Times Now the regulator has gained an unusual ally: short sellers. These investors are betting that the stocks of multilevel marketing companies will decline when the new rules, which have received little public attention, go into effect. For years, companies like Avon Products, Herbalife and Amway have prospered by building armies of part-time sales representatives promoting insurance plans and anti-aging creams. Those representatives, in turn, are encouraged to recruit others and are promised that they will receive a portion of new enlistees profits. The companies profit, at least in part, by collecting increased revenue and fees paid by new sales representatives. In April, citing hundreds of fraud investigations, the F.T.C. proposed new rules for multilevel marketing companies and related businesses. They would require companies to tell potential recruits how many sales representatives have failed to earn more than their start-up costs and how many customers have filed lawsuits for deceptive practices. The proposal, which may be modified and could take as long as two years before approval, also requires a weeklong waiting period between approaching new sales representatives and sealing the deal. These companies provide part-time employment for hundreds of thousands of stay-home moms and people who need to feed their families, said Doris Wood, an official with the Multi-Level Marketing International Association. Its unfair to treat them like criminals. Analysts say the companies real concern is that the new rules will undermine their ability to attract new sales representatives. If companies have to tell recruits that the average income is only $1,400 instead of the $50,000 advertised on their Web site, or that the average salesman only lasts two months, a lot fewer people are going to sign up, said Mimi Sokolowski, an analyst with Sidoti &amp; Company who follows Tupperware Brands, Nu Skin Enterprises and other publicly traded multilevel marketing companies. She said that if the proposed rules pass without modification, recruitment in the United States could fall by as much as 40 percent. Which is why short selling investors, who sell borrowed shares of a stock and bet that the price will decline before they must repay the loans, are encouraging the F.T.C. to adopt the new rules. Since the commissions proposal, short sales of many publicly traded multilevel marketing companies have increased. Short positions in Avon, Tupperware, Nu Skin, Herbalife, Pre-Paid Legal Service, Mannatech, USANA Health Sciences and Medifast have grown. For instance, the number of Avon shares shorted has increased 44 percent, to 11.3 million, since April. Shorted shares of Tupperware are up 77 percent, to 3.9 million, or roughly 1 in every 15 publicly traded shares. To understand short sellers enthusiasm, consider Pre-Paid Legal, a public company that sells legal insurance through multilevel partnerships. For about $26 a month, Pre-Paid Legal lets customers consult an affiliate lawyer on legal matters like speeding tickets or writing a will. In 2005, the companys nearly 500,000 sales representatives brought in revenue exceeding $423 million. But like many multilevel marketing companies, Pre-Paid Legal suffers from high turnover. In 2005, the company replaced at least 50 percent of its active sales force, according to filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission. Industrywide, multilevel marketing companies typically replace almost all of their sales representatives every year. Short sellers are betting that the F.T.C.s proposed rules will make it harder for Pre-Paid Legal to replenish its ranks. Under the rules, Pre-Paid Legal would have to tell prospects that fewer than a quarter of its sales representatives sold more than one insurance plan in 2005, something it disclosed to investors in a filing with the S.E.C. While Pre-Paids Web site tells prospects that if they market just five memberships per week, youll receive $500 per week! very few representatives have consistently sold five memberships a week. Pre-Paid Legals promotional materials also make little mention of current litigation. But the proposed rules would probably force the company to disclose that in 1997, Pre-Paid Legal acknowledged misleading customers and consented to suspend sales of living trusts after an F.T.C. investigation. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/01/business/01avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Revamping Plan Drives Down Avon Profit<date>Published: August 1, 2006</date><text>Avon Products, the worlds biggest direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that its second-quarter profit fell 54 percent, mostly as a result of a revamping program. The company, which is based in New York, said that it earned $150.9 million, or 33 cents a share, compared with $328.6 million, or 69 cents a share, a year earlier. The latest results were reduced by 7 cents a share after taxes for revamping costs. The result fell short of the 35 cents expected by analysts polled by Thomson Financial, and Avons stock fell $3.82, or 12 percent, to $28.99 a share. Revenue in the period rose to $2.1 billion, from $1.98 billion a year earlier, and exceeded the $2.06 billion expected by analysts. Revenue in the North America region was unchanged in the latest quarter from the previous year. In Latin America, revenue increased 17 percent as the region benefited from an acquisition in Colombia and continued strength in Brazil. Revenue in Western Europe, Middle East and Africa rose 2 percent, largely driven by growth in Turkey. Asia Pacific revenue was 10 percent lower in the quarter, while active representatives decreased 14 percent and the number of products sold fell 11 percent. More Articles in Business »Avon Products, the worlds biggest direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that its second-quarter profit fell 54 percent, mostly as a result of a revamping program. The company, which is based in New York, said that it earned $150.9 million, or 33 cents a share, compared with $328.6 million, or 69 cents a share, a year earlier. The latest results were reduced by 7 cents a share after taxes for revamping costs. The result fell short of the 35 cents expected by analysts polled by Thomson Financial, and Avons stock fell $3.82, or 12 percent, to $28.99 a share. Revenue in the period rose to $2.1 billion, from $1.98 billion a year earlier, and exceeded the $2.06 billion expected by analysts. Revenue in the North America region was unchanged in the latest quarter from the previous year. In Latin America, revenue increased 17 percent as the region benefited from an acquisition in Colombia and continued strength in Brazil. Revenue in Western Europe, Middle East and Africa rose 2 percent, largely driven by growth in Turkey. Asia Pacific revenue was 10 percent lower in the quarter, while active representatives decreased 14 percent and the number of products sold fell 11 percent.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/29/fashion/thursdaystyles/29skin.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Knock, Knock. Who's There? Avon Man.<date>Published: June 29, 2006</date><text>THIS might sound weird," Salvatore D'Amico will say when he approaches a man in the locker room at his gym. In other settings around suburban Philadelphia, he skips the introductory throat-clearing and just blurts out the bad news. "You look terrible," he will say, or "You look like you haven't slept in a week." Then Mr. D'Amico, 32, will slip the potential customer a $10 tube of Avon ProExtreme Advanced Eye Cream for Men and reassuringly tell him, "This will help." Skip to next paragraph Lars Klove for The New York Times Salvatore D'Amico with his products at a flea market in New Hope, Pa. "With men, eye cream is an easy sell," Mr. D'Amico said. Mr. D'Amico doesn't look much like an Avon lady, with his high-and-tight haircut and treadmill-perfected physique. Then again, the Avon lady isn't what she used to be. For starters, she isn't always a lady. Today up to 12,000 men stand ready to sell you a tube of Avon ProExtreme Energizing Face Moisturizer for Men an enormous number for a corporation whose identity is so thoroughly feminine that it still bills itself as "the company for women." Mr. D'Amico joined Avon when he got tired of having to wear a guest name tag at company events with his wife, Katrina, who is also a sales representative. He works as security guard at a local hospital, too, but that doesn't stop him from selling Avon when he's on duty. "I say, 'Doc, are you living at the office now,' " he said. "Then I get serious and sell him the eye cream." Mr. D'Amico trumpets his association with Avon the way some men broadcast their fervor for their favorite football team. Outside his house in Levittown, Pa., a three-foot-wide sign spells out AVON in white light bulbs. At the gym, he wears a sleeveless shirt that reads AVON on the back and LET'S TALK on the front. In the summer his sons Caleb, 5, and Gavin, 3, sell Avon products in front of the house instead of lemonade. But the life of the Avon man can be lonely. It's not just the occasional wisecrack ("Did you get a new dress to wear to your makeup sale," Mr. D'Amico's buddies joke) or the double take from new customers. Women still make up close to 98 percent of the sales force of 500,000 representatives  Avon could not provide figures on whether this percentage has changed in recent years  and Avon's corporate culture remains stubbornly ladylike. The company rewards each rep who sells $10,000 in merchandise with a porcelain figurine of Mrs. P. F. E. Albee, the first Avon lady, dressed in full Victorian regalia, holding an umbrella or a birdcage. Last year, Mr. D'Amico moved about $40,000 in Avon products to men and women (he kept half the money) to reach the Rose Circle, the third of six levels recognizing top earners. He earned not just a figurine but a cruise to British Columbia. His fellow sales representatives left their husbands at home, making Mr. D'Amico, one of the few men on board, as rare a sight as the gray whales spotted off the side of the ship. A fellow sales champion asked him in disbelief, "Why would you want to go on a cruise with 800 women who are running around talking about hair and makeup?" The heckling from his friends and fellow sales representatives doesn't bother Mr. D'Amico; he laughs off comments that real men don't sell moisturizer. "A man has to be secure in himself to sell Avon," he said. "The little teasing I get I have fun with." At a recent craft sale in Levittown, Mr. D'Amico accessorized with a gold Avon pin that was almost as bright as his bleached teeth. He talked to everyone who walked by, offering free hand massages with Avon Moisture Therapy intensive hand cream and enthusing about the products. He praised the men's abdominal firming cream, which he said feels like Ben-Gay when he smears it on. "It burns off something in your stomach," he said. Most of the people who stopped by for his hand rubs were women, who make up the bulk of his customers despite his best attempts to round up clients in the men's locker room. To them, he sells Avon perennials like Skin So Soft original bath oil. He doesn't ring up much makeup because he hasn't been willing to take Avon's beauty adviser course, an intense study of such things as which lipsticks and eye shadows should be worn together. 1 2Next Page » More Articles in Fashion &amp; Style »THIS might sound weird," Salvatore D'Amico will say when he approaches a man in the locker room at his gym. In other settings around suburban Philadelphia, he skips the introductory throat-clearing and just blurts out the bad news. "You look terrible," he will say, or "You look like you haven't slept in a week." Then Mr. D'Amico, 32, will slip the potential customer a $10 tube of Avon ProExtreme Advanced Eye Cream for Men and reassuringly tell him, "This will help." Skip to next paragraph Lars Klove for The New York Times Salvatore D'Amico with his products at a flea market in New Hope, Pa. "With men, eye cream is an easy sell," Mr. D'Amico said. Mr. D'Amico doesn't look much like an Avon lady, with his high-and-tight haircut and treadmill-perfected physique. Then again, the Avon lady isn't what she used to be. For starters, she isn't always a lady. Today up to 12,000 men stand ready to sell you a tube of Avon ProExtreme Energizing Face Moisturizer for Men an enormous number for a corporation whose identity is so thoroughly feminine that it still bills itself as "the company for women." Mr. D'Amico joined Avon when he got tired of having to wear a guest name tag at company events with his wife, Katrina, who is also a sales representative. He works as security guard at a local hospital, too, but that doesn't stop him from selling Avon when he's on duty. "I say, 'Doc, are you living at the office now,' " he said. "Then I get serious and sell him the eye cream." Mr. D'Amico trumpets his association with Avon the way some men broadcast their fervor for their favorite football team. Outside his house in Levittown, Pa., a three-foot-wide sign spells out AVON in white light bulbs. At the gym, he wears a sleeveless shirt that reads AVON on the back and LET'S TALK on the front. In the summer his sons Caleb, 5, and Gavin, 3, sell Avon products in front of the house instead of lemonade. But the life of the Avon man can be lonely. It's not just the occasional wisecrack ("Did you get a new dress to wear to your makeup sale," Mr. D'Amico's buddies joke) or the double take from new customers. Women still make up close to 98 percent of the sales force of 500,000 representatives  Avon could not provide figures on whether this percentage has changed in recent years  and Avon's corporate culture remains stubbornly ladylike. The company rewards each rep who sells $10,000 in merchandise with a porcelain figurine of Mrs. P. F. E. Albee, the first Avon lady, dressed in full Victorian regalia, holding an umbrella or a birdcage. Last year, Mr. D'Amico moved about $40,000 in Avon products to men and women (he kept half the money) to reach the Rose Circle, the third of six levels recognizing top earners. He earned not just a figurine but a cruise to British Columbia. His fellow sales representatives left their husbands at home, making Mr. D'Amico, one of the few men on board, as rare a sight as the gray whales spotted off the side of the ship. A fellow sales champion asked him in disbelief, "Why would you want to go on a cruise with 800 women who are running around talking about hair and makeup?" The heckling from his friends and fellow sales representatives doesn't bother Mr. D'Amico; he laughs off comments that real men don't sell moisturizer. "A man has to be secure in himself to sell Avon," he said. "The little teasing I get I have fun with." At a recent craft sale in Levittown, Mr. D'Amico accessorized with a gold Avon pin that was almost as bright as his bleached teeth. He talked to everyone who walked by, offering free hand massages with Avon Moisture Therapy intensive hand cream and enthusing about the products. He praised the men's abdominal firming cream, which he said feels like Ben-Gay when he smears it on. "It burns off something in your stomach," he said. Most of the people who stopped by for his hand rubs were women, who make up the bulk of his customers despite his best attempts to round up clients in the men's locker room. To them, he sells Avon perennials like Skin So Soft original bath oil. He doesn't ring up much makeup because he hasn't been willing to take Avon's beauty adviser course, an intense study of such things as which lipsticks and eye shadows should be worn together. 1 2Next Page »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDF113FF932A35756C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">For the Avon Lady, a World Beyond Ringing Doorbells<date>Published: May 1, 2006</date><text>LUZ STELLA BONGIOVI has a job that many people would envy. After 12 years in the same business, she supervises more than 100 employees and logs about 50 hours a week, coming into work at 10 a.m. and often working at home. She has been sent on junkets to Hawaii, Las Vegas and Puerto Rico. Her earnings total nearly $170,000 a year. Her job title: Avon lady. The folks at Avon, however, would call her a sales representative, the updated term for the 468,000 people in the company's work force generating more than 95 percent of sales revenue. But to the public, ''Avon lady'' has stuck, ever since the company's sales representatives began ringing doorbells in 1886. Ms. Bongiovi is an example of how to succeed the old-fashioned way: she started small, worked hard and took advantage of her natural business sense to build a living slowly by selling Avon to her extended network of family, friends and acquaintances. But now, Avon is trying to force itself to step into the future -- and bring the sales reps with it, turning its distinctly mid-20th-century sales model into a 21st-century version. In fact, Avon will announce a new initiative this month to encourage more business to move to the Internet, said Thomas Kelly, Avon's senior vice president for direct selling in the United States. ''We really are guns blazing with our excitement about the Internet,'' he said. ''We're moving from just ordering online to supporting their efforts to sell online.'' The company is teaching its sales reps to file customer orders online; before, reps would phone in their orders. Now, more than 80 percent use the Internet to do business. Avon is also encouraging its sales reps to set up individual pages on the company's Web site for customers to make online purchases. For instance, by typing in their ZIP code, customers will be directed to their sales rep's page. But Avon is still holding on to the fundamental part of its business model -- a sales force that is paid only by commissions, without salaries, health care or benefits. Signing up is simple: a potential rep pays a $10 fee, fills out a form and receives a starter kit. Then it's up to the newly minted representative to go out and garner sales. That person is also responsible for day-to-day operating expenses and promotions. Ms. Bongiovi pays for print advertising from her own budget. For example, if a rep wants business cards printed with her name, she pays for them herself. Asked to define the employment status of sales reps, an Avon spokeswoman responded, ''Self-employed.'' On a recent morning, Ms. Bongiovi was sitting behind a desk in her office in Bushwick, which doubles as a retail space with a storefront on Myrtle Avenue, where she sells Avon products and performs occasional walk-in makeovers. Avon began for her as it had for many women -- a side job for stay-at-home mothers who want to earn a little extra money. (The reps are predominantly female.) Ms. Bongiovi grew up in Colombia. Her father owned a supermarket, and she often watched him working in the store and fantasized about her own future. ''I used to dream, 'Oh, I want to have a business when I grow up,' '' she said. Marriage and three children intervened, but one day she signed up for Avon on a whim, getting her first order mostly from family and friends in her neighborhood. ''My first order was $500, and I thought, 'Hmm, this is good,' '' said Ms. Bongiovi, who wore a neatly cut blazer, violet-framed eyeglasses and gleaming red nail polish. Soon, she began recruiting other people to become sales representatives in her ''downline,'' Avon's term for sales reps' own staff members whom they personally recruit and supervise. Ms. Bongiovi's sales pitch to potential reps reflects her own life story. When she first started selling Avon, she had children at home and no income of her own. Now she owns a six-unit apartment building in Brooklyn and is going through a divorce, dividing up assets and income. When talking to potential reps, she said, ''I tell them: 'What about if your husband leaves you? What if you don't have a husband anymore?' I like to help them, I like to give them support. I teach them how to earn money with Avon.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/04/business/04health.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Program Offers Health Care for Some Part-Time Workers<date>Published: October 4, 2005</date><text>Dozens of part-time workers at six large companies have begun to sign up for low-cost, limited health benefits in a new national program for uninsured employees. The HR Policy Association, a nonprofit organization of senior personnel executives, said enrollment was under way at units of General Electric, I.B.M., Sears, Avon Products, the computer-storage company EMC and the auto supplier Federal-Mogul. Six more large employers plan to start enrolling uninsured workers in the next few weeks, and five additional companies will join early next year, said Jeff McGuiness, the president of the association, whose members are personnel executives at 250 of the nation's largest employers. Those eligible include independent contractors like Avon sales representatives, as well as temporary and seasonal employees, and their spouses and dependents. The companies are taking a small first step toward slowing the spiraling growth of the uninsured, who now number more than 45 million. They acknowledge that the program is far from an overall solution, but they are addressing a challenge that government officials have largely ignored, said Steven M. Coppock, a senior actuary at the Hewitt Associates benefits consulting firm, which is helping the association with the program. "Because our health system is primarily employment-based, it makes sense for large employers to take collective action to try to come up with innovative, collaborative solutions to this pressing problem," said J. Randall MacDonald, a senior vice president for human resources at I.B.M. The coverage will be financed from the premiums paid by participants, with no subsidy from employers. But by pooling large numbers of their people, the employers say they hope to lower individuals' insurance costs by spreading the risks and attracting relatively healthy participants who will outnumber those in need of care. As members of an employee group, people with medical problems typically escape the higher premiums that insurers require from individuals with "preconditions." Options include a discount card for drugs and medical and dental checkups, which will also provide access to a 24-hour advice center run by nurses. The nurse line was added and the monthly cost of the card was raised to $6.99 from $4.41, after focus-group discussions with potential enrollees, Mr. Coppock said. In a revealing example of purchaser psychology, some potential enrollees expressed skepticism that any card that cost less than $5 would be worth having, he noted. The UnitedHealth Group is offering the discount card and four levels of limited coverage in all 50 states at monthly premiums ranging from $59 to $149. In 15 states, United will also offer high-deductible policies that cover major medical costs, under the same group rules with no add-on charges for people with preconditions. The major medical premiums vary based on an enrollee's age, sex and location. Humana will offer the high-deductible policies to individuals in 17 states and Cigna will offer them in Arizona only. Under these individual contracts, premiums may also be higher for those with preconditions. More Articles in Business &gt;Dozens of part-time workers at six large companies have begun to sign up for low-cost, limited health benefits in a new national program for uninsured employees. The HR Policy Association, a nonprofit organization of senior personnel executives, said enrollment was under way at units of General Electric, I.B.M., Sears, Avon Products, the computer-storage company EMC and the auto supplier Federal-Mogul. Six more large employers plan to start enrolling uninsured workers in the next few weeks, and five additional companies will join early next year, said Jeff McGuiness, the president of the association, whose members are personnel executives at 250 of the nation's largest employers. Those eligible include independent contractors like Avon sales representatives, as well as temporary and seasonal employees, and their spouses and dependents. The companies are taking a small first step toward slowing the spiraling growth of the uninsured, who now number more than 45 million. They acknowledge that the program is far from an overall solution, but they are addressing a challenge that government officials have largely ignored, said Steven M. Coppock, a senior actuary at the Hewitt Associates benefits consulting firm, which is helping the association with the program. "Because our health system is primarily employment-based, it makes sense for large employers to take collective action to try to come up with innovative, collaborative solutions to this pressing problem," said J. Randall MacDonald, a senior vice president for human resources at I.B.M. The coverage will be financed from the premiums paid by participants, with no subsidy from employers. But by pooling large numbers of their people, the employers say they hope to lower individuals' insurance costs by spreading the risks and attracting relatively healthy participants who will outnumber those in need of care. As members of an employee group, people with medical problems typically escape the higher premiums that insurers require from individuals with "preconditions." Options include a discount card for drugs and medical and dental checkups, which will also provide access to a 24-hour advice center run by nurses. The nurse line was added and the monthly cost of the card was raised to $6.99 from $4.41, after focus-group discussions with potential enrollees, Mr. Coppock said. In a revealing example of purchaser psychology, some potential enrollees expressed skepticism that any card that cost less than $5 would be worth having, he noted. The UnitedHealth Group is offering the discount card and four levels of limited coverage in all 50 states at monthly premiums ranging from $59 to $149. In 15 states, United will also offer high-deductible policies that cover major medical costs, under the same group rules with no add-on charges for people with preconditions. The major medical premiums vary based on an enrollee's age, sex and location. Humana will offer the high-deductible policies to individuals in 17 states and Cigna will offer them in Arizona only. Under these individual contracts, premiums may also be higher for those with preconditions.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DF1630F930A35756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON OFFSETS WEAKNESS IN U.S. WITH GROWTH OVERSEAS<date>Published: May 3, 2005</date><text>Avon Products, the cosmetics company, reported a 16 percent increase in first-quarter profit yesterday as international business offset weakness in the United States. It also raised its full-year profit outlook, but its shares fell $1.28, to $38.80, more than 3 percent, on a disappointing second-quarter outlook. Net income was $172 million, or 36 cents a share, up from $148.1 million, or 31 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 7 percent to $1.88 billion from $1.76 billion. Revenue in the United States fell 6 percent and operating profit fell 15 percent. In Europe, first-quarter revenue increased 17 percent and operating profit rose 26 percent. In Latin America, first-quarter revenue was up 10 percent in dollars and operating profit rose 12 percent. Revenue in the Asia-Pacific region was up 10 percent. Avon is based in New York.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDE1031F93AA35751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON FORECASTS SALES DECLINES THROUGH 2005<date>Published: December 9, 2004</date><text>Avon Products, the cosmetics company, said yesterday that fourth-quarter sales in the United States would decline more than it had previously forecast, setting off a 4 percent decline in its share price. Avon said that sales would fall 5 percent in the fourth quarter, more than the 3 percent the company had forecast in October. Avon, which is based in New York, said that it expected sales to decline again next year but that it expected to be profitable in 2006. Avon said that demand for cosmetics like lipstick was weak in the United States, and that it planned to eliminate some products, like toys.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFD8123DF93BA15753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; KRAFT EXECUTIVE TAKING POSITION AT AVON PRODUCTS<date>Published: October 28, 2004</date><text>Avon Products, the direct seller of cosmetics, said yesterday that Elizabeth Smith will join the company as executive vice president and brand president. Ms. Smith, who will start on Jan. 1, will report to Andrea Jung, the company's chief executive. In the newly created position, Ms. Smith, 41, will be responsible for management of Avon's worldwide brand and product categories, and will lead all global brand and marketing functions. Ms. Smith comes to Avon from Kraft Foods, which she joined in 1990 and where she had been president of the United States beverages and grocery sectors since January.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EED71730F93AA3575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON REDUCES ITS OUTLOOK FOR UNITED STATES SALES<date>Published: September 9, 2004</date><text>Avon Products Inc. cut its forecast for sales in the United States in the third quarter as demand weakened for the company's color cosmetics. Avon, based in New York, said sales in the United States would be flat in the quarter, a reduction from its previous forecast for an increase of as much as 4 percent from a year earlier. Avon will begin a new marketing campaign this month in the United States, where it gets more than a third of its revenue. The company expects worldwide sales in the third quarter to increase 11 percent. Sales in Europe, Latin America and the Asia/Pacific region have been higher than it expected. Avon also reaffirmed its third-quarter profit forecast of 34 cents a share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/15/style/pulse-skin-so-soft-and-so-bite-free.html?ref=avonproductsinc">PULSE; Skin So Soft and So Bite-Free<date>Published: August 15, 2004</date><text>About 40 years -- after consumers first noticed that Avon's Skin-So-Soft bath oil repelled mosquitoes, the company introduced Skin-So-Soft bug sprays and lotions. The latest, called Bug Guard Plus Expedition, is said to turn away not only mosquitoes but also deer ticks, black flies and gnats. While experts say that only products containing DEET have been scientifically proved effective, an unscientific test suggests that the Expedition spray works. Twenty-one guests at an outdoor party near mosquito-thick marshes in upstate New York were well spritzed one humid evening in late July. Seven hours later, they found no bites.One advantage of Skin-So-Soft products is the absence of toxic ingredients. This means there is no need to wash them off before turning in. And there is also no need to wait until an Avon representative rings the doorbell: the repellents, $10 to $12, are available at www.avon.com.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/09/business/company-news-avon-says-quarterly-earnings-will-beat-forecast.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS QUARTERLY EARNINGS WILL BEAT FORECAST<date>Published: June 09, 2004</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that its second-quarter profit would rise about 3 cents a share more than its earlier forecast because of lower tax expenses and higher sales in the United States and Europe. Profit will increase to 46 cents a share, Avon said. The average estimate of nine analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial was 43 cents. Avon earned 36 cents a year earlier. The company's effective tax rate may fall to 31 percent from 35 percent when tax strategies are put in place next year, Avon said. Sales are expected to rise 12 percent this quarter, as the company increases door-to-door sales staff and adds cosmetics lines.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/26/business/company-news-avon-raises-its-earnings-forecasts.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON RAISES ITS EARNINGS FORECASTS<date>Published: March 26, 2004</date><text>Avon Products Inc. raised its forecast yesterday for first-quarter and full-year earnings on strength in Europe and Latin America. Avon said it expected earnings of 59 cents a share in the first quarter, up from 42 cents in the year-earlier period and exceeding its previous outlook of 50 cents a share. Analysts expect a profit of 51 cents a share, according to Reuters. Avon said sales were up about 19 percent so far in the quarter, helped by the weak dollar.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/21/nyregion/by-the-way-ask-the-boss.html?ref=avonproductsinc">BY THE WAY; Ask the Boss<date>Published: December 21, 2003</date><text>A focused business plan, a clear link between performance and rewards, a cohesive team and a charismatic guy in the No. 1 spot. That sounds like a sound formula for success in anyone's book -- that and the occassional decapitated head in a bowling ball bag.That's ''Leadership Sopranos Style,'' a new book by Deborrah Himsel, vice president for organizational effectiveness at Avon Products Inc. The book, subtitled ''How to Become a More Effective Boss,'' was just released by Dearborn Trade Publishing (www.dearborntrade.com). It costs $20.When Tony Soprano first showed up on the HBO series, Ms. Himsel was intrigued by how he handled problems in his organization, and soon found herself translating his style into her own workplace (minus the rubouts, of course). She thinks others could benefit by doing the same''If you were facing a tough negotiation with a valued partner,'' she asks, ''wouldn't you want Tony on your team hammering out a win-win agreement?''''Wouldn't Tony ensure that meetings were conducted with great speed and efficiency; wouldn't he guarantee that core issues were addressed without preamble and pontification?''From Satriale's Pork Store to by-invitation-only poker games, Ms. Himsel draws parallels between the Soprano organization and the place you get your paycheck. Want to see how your boss stacks up next to Tony? Take the quiz on page 38. Is there an employee who reports to you who never meets the team goals? See how Tony might handle the situation in the chapter titled ''Coaching the Poubahs and Goombahs.''If nothing else, the book will give you a chance to spend some time with the Soprano family while waiting for the new season to open. And who knows? It might turn out to have advice that you can't refuse.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/09/business/company-news-avon-says-profits-in-quarter-will-not-meet-expectations.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS PROFITS IN QUARTER WILL NOT MEET EXPECTATIONS<date>Published: December 09, 2003</date><text>The cosmetics maker Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it expected profit in the fourth quarter to fall below analysts' estimates because sales in the United States had not been as high as expected. The company said United States sales would increase less than 5 percent, down from its previous estimate, as a result of the cost of promotions on fragrance brands and its inability to keep up with demand for gift items and home decorations. Operating profit in the United States is expected to be down slightly. Stock in Avon, which is based in New York, fell $5.40, or 7.9 percent, to $62.67.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/26/business/world-business-briefing-europe-russia-avon-to-build-plant.html?ref=avonproductsinc">World Business Briefing | Europe: Russia: Avon To Build Plant<date>Published: September 26, 2003</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said it would spend $40 million to build a factory near Moscow to supply its Russian business. The plant, in Narofominsk, will employ more than 800 people and manufacture makeup, skin-care products, fragrances and deodorants, Avon said. It is Avon, which isbased in New York, said it forecast sales in Russia would more than triple to $500 million in 2007 from $142 million in 2002.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/17/realestate/commercial-property-suffern-ny-100-million-research-hub-for-site-of-avon-factory.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Commercial Property/Suffern, N.Y.; $100 Million Research Hub for Site of Avon Factory<date>Published: August 17, 2003</date><text>ON the same 11-acre site in Suffern, N.Y., where Avon Products built its first factory -- a wood-frame structure for 12 employees in 1897 -- the women's beauty company has begun construction of a $100 million glass and granite research and development center for 350 workers.When the new three-story 225,000-square-foot center is completed in early 2005, an existing 360,000-square-foot building that has housed both research and manufacturing will be demolished and the land used for employee parking.Avon plans to consolidate its research laboratories and support staff, which are now in locations throughout the world, in the new building. The facility will become the center for development of all cosmetic, fragrance and toiletries products, said Janice Teal, a group vice president and the chief scientific officer.The first 30-by-50-foot factory was built 106 years ago by David H. McConnell, who founded the business, then called the California Perfume Company. Shortly after, it was expanded, and by the late 1920's, the building was more than 20 times its initial size. In 1971, a new wing was completed, with further alternations and additions -- including deconstruction of the original structure -- taking place in later years.All that is now left of the company's first factory is a small stack of bricks, one of which is incorporated into each new Avon building, Ms. Teal said. One of the bricks will become part of the company's new Suffern building.Avon first considered building a new research and development center in the early 1980's but abandoned those plans several years later because of financial difficulties and takeover threats, Ms. Teal said, explaining that ''research and development was not a profit maker.''After deciding two years ago to reactivate the plans, Avon weighed the idea of renovating the existing structure, which Ms. Teal described as ''a four-floor hodgepodge of beige and stucco older buildings that looks like a manufacturing facility.''It also considered moving away from Suffern, a village of 11,000 people in Rockland County at the foot of the Ramapo Mountains. Last year, Avon started moving 260 employees along with its manufacturing operations in Suffern to Springdale, Ohio. For the research and development functions, the company looked at locations outside Suffern in New York and in other states, Ms. Teal said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/26/business/avon-profit-aided-by-strong-overseas-sales.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Profit Aided by Strong Overseas Sales<date>Published: April 26, 2003</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that its profit edged higher in the first quarter, helped by new products and strong growth in international sales.But the company said earnings in the current quarter would fall short of analysts' consensus estimate and said the outbreak of a respiratory illness is affecting business in China.Avon, which is based in New York, posted net earnings in the quarter of $98.9 million, or 42 cents a share, which compared with $96.3 million, or 40 cents a share, a year earlier.Avon said it had started to notice an impact from severe acute respiratory syndrome, the flulike virus known as SARS, in China in the current quarter and scaled back its targets for about 25 percent of the region. China accounts for 2 percent of Avon's total sales, and less in terms of profit.Sales in the quarter advanced 7 percent, to $1.47 billion from $1.37 billion, Avon's strongest increase since the third quarter of 2000. In local currencies, sales were up 12 percent.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/24/business/sec-is-advised-to-take-action-against-couple.html?ref=avonproductsinc">S.E.C. Is Advised to Take Action Against Couple<date>Published: April 24, 2003</date><text>Officials in the enforcement division of the Securities and Exchange Commission have recommended that it file an insider trading suit against a former Wall Street analyst, Holly B. Becker, and her husband, Michael J. Zimmerman, a professional stock trader who has worked at several large hedge funds, according to a person involved in the investigation.The full commission is expected to decide Tuesday whether to file suit against Ms. Becker and Mr. Zimmerman, the person said.Regulators have been investigating stock trades made by Mr. Zimmerman from 1999 to 2001 that appear to have been based on information he received from Ms. Becker while she was a prominent analyst at Salomon Smith Barney and later at Lehman Brothers. The S.E.C. notified Ms. Becker and Mr. Zimmerman last summer that it had gathered enough evidence to bring an enforcement action against them. As is customary, they then told the regulators why they did not believe an enforcement action was merited.The commission's investigation into Mr. Zimmerman and Ms. Becker, according to the person involved in it, has identified a series of trades he made in three stocks in 1999, when he was employed by Omega Advisors Inc., a hedge fund in New York. According to the person, Ms. Becker provided Mr. Zimmerman with advance information about the contents of research reports that were soon to be published on Avon Products, eBay and Drugstore.com. Mr. Zimmerman then made bets on the shares based on whether those reports were positive or negative, the person said, adding that Mr. Zimmerman's trades were quickly closed out and produced several million dollars in profits to the fund.Omega Advisors is not a subject of the investigation. Mr. Zimmerman worked there for one year; he left in January 2000 to join SAC Capital Advisors, a hedge fund with offices in Connecticut and New York. The commission has also scrutinized trades made by Mr. Zimmerman when he worked at SAC, but those trades are not part of the case now before regulators.Mr. Zimmerman did not return a phone call seeking comment. Ms. Becker's lawyer, David E. Brodsky, of Cleary, Gottlieb, Steen &amp; Hamilton in New York, also did not return a phone call. Mr. Brodsky represented both Ms. Becker and Mr. Zimmerman last year, but Mr. Zimmerman has since retained separate counsel.The S.E.C. does not comment on the status of its investigations.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/29/business/company-news-avon-raises-annual-sales-target-and-earnings-forecast.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON RAISES ANNUAL SALES TARGET AND EARNINGS FORECAST<date>Published: March 29, 2003</date><text>The beauty products maker Avon Products Inc. raised its long-term annual sales target yesterday on expectations that it will be helped by new products, and raised its quarterly earnings forecast. Avon, the largest direct seller of cosmetics, said it expected annual sales growth of 12 percent to 13 percent in local currencies, up from a target of 10 percent growth it set in 2001. The company said it planned to introduce its Mark product line, using sales representatives aged 16 to 24, in August, to try to attract younger consumers. Avon expects Mark to reach $100 million in sales in 2004.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/01/business/company-news-jc-penney-and-avon-end-cosmetics-partnership.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; J.C. PENNEY AND AVON END COSMETICS PARTNERSHIP<date>Published: February 01, 2003</date><text>J. C. Penney and Avon Products are terminating their partnership to sell a cosmetics line, ending Avon's first attempt at selling at retail. Penney said yesterday that the move to stop selling the beComing line of cosmetics was part of a strategy to exit from most of its cosmetics lines and concentrate on women's accessories. An expanded accessories assortment will be in stores by Aug. 1. Penney began selling beComing in 90 of its stores in August 2001. Avon said the beComing line would be available through its direct selling channel in the United States. The company said its first-quarter income would be reduced by about $20 million as a result of the termination.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/23/business/company-news-avon-to-close-plant-in-montreal-cutting-150-jobs.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO CLOSE PLANT IN MONTREAL, CUTTING 150 JOBS<date>Published: January 23, 2003</date><text>The cosmetics company Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it would close its plant in Montreal, eliminating about 150 jobs, as part of a restructuring program. The company said it would phase out its Montreal-based manufacturing operation by the first quarter of 2004, and transfer the production to Avon's larger plants in Springdale, Ohio, and Morton Grove, Ill. The majority of the job cuts will take place by the end of the year, Avon said. Avon, which is based in New York, said that its direct-selling operations in Canada, which employ 950 associates to support the country's 71,000 independent sales dealers, would not be affected by the closing.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/11/business/company-news-avon-raises-its-forecast-on-fourth-quarter-earnings.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON RAISES ITS FORECAST ON FOURTH-QUARTER EARNINGS<date>Published: December 11, 2002</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it expected to report fourth-quarter earnings slightly above its previous forecast. Avon said that profit was driven by a focus on core beauty products, while it had 10 percent more sales representatives. Avon expects to earn 79 cents a share in the fourth quarter, a penny ahead of its previous forecast, but matching analysts' consensus forecast, according to the research firm Thomson First Call. The company also said it expected 2003 profits to be $2.54 a share, near the low end of analysts' estimates.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/04/business/company-news-avon-holds-firm-to-its-third-quarter-outlook.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON HOLDS FIRM TO ITS THIRD-QUARTER OUTLOOK<date>Published: September 04, 2002</date><text>Avon Products Inc., a direct seller of cosmetics, yesterday stood by its profit outlook for the third quarter and full year, with strength in the United States and Europe offsetting weakness in Argentina. The company also said its planned revamping charge for the quarter would be substantially lower than it had forecast earlier this year as it gained a clearer picture of how 2002 is shaping up. Avon backed the analysts' average earnings estimate of 47 cents a share, excluding the charge, for the third quarter. For the year, it said it was on track to earn $2.30 a share, up 10 percent from $2.09 in 2001. Avon, with some of the largest Latin American exposure of any American consumer products maker, suffered from the effects of a currency devaluation in Argentina earlier this year.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/25/nyregion/in-business-another-home-shopping-network.html?ref=avonproductsinc">IN BUSINESS; Another Home-Shopping Network<date>Published: August 25, 2002</date><text>FUELED by new hobbies and a new generation, selling products at home remains a bright spot in the economy. While longstanding companies like Avon and Tupperware now sell in retail outlets as well as through individual consultants, other companies are finding profits in events that can resemble old-style coffee klatches.One of the most successful party-plan companies, as they are called, is Pampered Chef, an Illinois-based cookware company. And one of its more successful consultants is Penney Parkes, a Fairfield, Conn., resident who also covers Westchester. She came upon the business by happenstance, when a friend invited her to a show.It turns out that Mrs. Parkes had a natural affinity for her new business. Part comedian, part chef, she easily sold $1,000 in products at a recent gathering in the West Harrison home of Anna Gallo.Michele Costa of New Rochelle, a consultant for Creative Memories, products, not only sells its products like specialized scrapbooks, adhesives and marking pens, but also organizes gatherings so others can work on their books together.She started keeping scrapbooks five years ago and says her involvement was highly personal. ''I lost my mother before my daughter was born, and I didn't have anyone to ask the questions of what it was like to be pregnant, when did I take my first steps?'' said Ms. Costa, who has been a consultant for more than a year.Cathy Parlitsis of Somers got hooked on a new hobby three years ago when she and an aunt attended a party sponsored by Stampin' Up!, one of the newer direct sales companies. ''Once the host handed me the stamp, I was a goner,'' she said.Her income last year, excluding trips and bonuses, was close to $30,000.In contrast to other party-plan products, the three best-known clothing lines sold through the home -- Carlisle, Doncaster and Worth -- are not offered at large gatherings. Rather, representatives transform their homes with display fixtures and invite clients by appointment.Kathryn Parter of Larchmont, for example, who has represented Doncaster for the last 10 years, keeps her quarterly shows low-key and personal, an approach that keeps her clients coming back. While shopping in someone's home is not for everyone, ''it is by no means Loehmann's,'' said one longtime client, Betsy Cherkasky of Larchmont.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/05/business/mediatalk-words-and-mascara-in-a-marketing-deal.html?ref=avonproductsinc">MediaTalk; Words and Mascara In a Marketing Deal<date>Published: August 05, 2002</date><text>Putting a new magazine into the hands of the consumer has become so difficult that publishers almost need to go door to door to get some attention. So it is not surprising that Latina magazine, a 230,000-circulation monthly magazine for bilingual Hispanic women, has joined with Avon Products to sell subscriptions. This fall, up to 80,000 Avon sales representatives catering to a Hispanic customers will begin selling subscriptions to Latina for $10.99 a year.''We all know the kind of challenges that magazines face in the area of subscription acquisition,'' said David L. Kahn, a former publisher at The New Yorker who was named publisher of Latina on Friday. The collapse of sweepstakes subscription marketers and a flood of direct-mail solicitations have made it harder to find subscribers. ''This kind of innovative partnership is essential to moving us forward.''First published in May of 1996, the magazine now owned by Latina Media Ventures covers the usual array of health, beauty and fashion issues found in most women's magazine, but with a twist. The magazine uses headlines that mix languages -- like August's ''Work it, Chica!'' -- and runs some articles in both English and Spanish.This unorthodox publishing method is driven by compelling demographics. According to the Census bureau, there are 13.8 million Hispanic women who are proficient English speakers, a number that is expected to grow significantly the next decade.Latina has been growing as well, grabbing a spot on AdWeek's Hot List in each of the last two years, but the magazine is currently confronting a very difficult ad market. Latina's ad pages for the first half of the year were down 20.4 percent compared with the period in 2001. DAVID CARR</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/20/business/company-news-avon-reports-12.5-gain-in-second-quarter-profit.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON REPORTS 12.5% GAIN IN SECOND-QUARTER PROFIT<date>Published: July 20, 2002</date><text>Avon Products, helped by strong performances in the United States and Europe, reported a 12.5 percent rise in earnings for the second quarter yesterday, narrowly beating Wall Street expectations. Avon, the world's largest direct seller of beauty products, said it earned $155 million, or 64 cents a share, for the three months ended June 30 compared with $137.7 million, or 57 cents a share, in the period last year. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected earnings of 63 cents a share. Sales in the quarter increased 4 percent, to $1.51 billion from $1.46 billion. In the United States, Avon's largest market, sales in the second quarter rose 6 percent and operating profit rose 11 percent.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/18/business/pricewaterhousecoopers-to-pay-5-million-to-end-sec-case.html?ref=avonproductsinc">PricewaterhouseCoopers to Pay $5 Million to End S.E.C. Case<date>Published: July 18, 2002</date><text>The accounting firm PricewaterhouseCoopers will pay $5 million to settle charges that it violated rules requiring auditors to remain independent of their clients, the Securities and Exchange Commission announced yesterday.The settlement, the largest fine paid by an accounting firm for a violation of the independence rules, resolves three S.E.C. enforcement actions. One involved the firm's approval of improper accounting of expenses by Avon Products; the second involved a similar problem in its audit of Pinnacle Holdings; and the third concerned the type of fees charged by the firm's broker-dealer subsidiary.In an e-mail message sent to Pricewaterhouse partners on Tuesday, the firm's chairman, Dennis M. Nally, wrote, ''We felt it important to resolve these former matters once and for all and direct our energy and focus on the future.''Wayne M. Carlin, director of the S.E.C.'s office for the Northeast region, called the settlement ''very significant.''''It's of crucial importance,'' he said yesterday, ''because the independence and objectivity of an auditor is really the linchpin'' of a reliable audit.The actions against Pricewaterhouse for its audits of Pinnacle and Avon are particularly significant because they suggest that the accounting firm may have been swayed in its audit by fees it was paid for nonaudit services.According to the S.E.C., Avon hired Pricewaterhouse to help put together a complex software system in the late 1990's and then terminated the project before it was completed in April 1999. Instead of writing off the full cost of the project, about $42 million, Avon wrote down only $15 million, according to the S.E.C., and recorded the rest of the money spent, which consisted largely of fees to Pricewaterhouse, as a capital expense. Pricewaterhouse, which is also the company's auditor, approved the flawed accounting. This accounting treatment delayed the effect of the failed project on Avon's earnings. The company took an additional charge of $24 million in the third quarter of 2001.Under a separate settlement, Avon will issue revised financial statements for the first three months of 1999 and the full year and for 2001. The restatement will reduce Avon's 1999 earnings by 6 cents a share and will increase earnings for the third quarter of 2001 by 6 cents a share, according to Avon.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/27/business/company-news-avon-says-it-will-meet-or-beat-analysts-estimates.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS IT WILL MEET OR BEAT ANALYSTS' ESTIMATES<date>Published: June 27, 2002</date><text>Avon Products, the direct seller of cosmetics, said yesterday that it expected second-quarter earnings to meet or beat most analysts' expectations. The company said it expected significant gains from currency trading strategies it has used to hedge against the devaluation of currencies in Latin America. Avon does a significant amount of business in Latin America, where economic turmoil has hurt the Mexican and Argentine pesos and the Brazilian real. Wall Street analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expect the company to earn 63 cents a share, a figure that Avon said three weeks ago it expected to meet. Avon's stock rose $3.17, or 7 percent, to $51.26 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/24/business/company-news-avon-to-close-plant-in-new-york-state-and-cut-260-jobs.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO CLOSE PLANT IN NEW YORK STATE AND CUT 260 JOBS<date>Published: May 24, 2002</date><text>Avon Products said yesterday that it would phase out its plant in Suffern, N.Y., over the next 12 months as part of a realignment of manufacturing operations in the United States. The majority of the production will be transferred to a larger and more efficient plant in Springdale, Ohio, the company said. Avon said that about 260 jobs would be eliminated at Suffern, about 35 miles northwest of Midtown Manhattan, but that it expected to add about 200 jobs at Springdale. Avon also said it planned to build a research and development center to replace the Suffern plant.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/13/business/company-news-avon-to-close-british-factory-eliminating-465-jobs.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO CLOSE BRITISH FACTORY, ELIMINATING 465 JOBS<date>Published: April 13, 2002</date><text>Avon Products said yesterday that it planned to close a factory in Britain, laying off 465 employees. The company plans to cease manufacturing in Northampton, Britain, over the next 12 months. Most of that production will be carried out instead at Avon's recently expanded plant in Poland. In the fourth quarter ended Dec. 31, Avon, a direct seller of beauty products, recorded a special charge of $68.3 million for the closing and the layoffs. Avon, which had 2001 revenue of about $6 billion, said the closing would save it $10 million to $12 million a year.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/19/business/company-news-avon-to-lay-off-3500-workers-8-of-work-force.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO LAY OFF 3,500 WORKERS, 8% OF WORK FORCE<date>Published: March 19, 2002</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the largest direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that it would lay off 3,500 employees, or about 8 percent of its work force, as it scales back manufacturing to cut costs. Avon said last month that it would close a jewelry plant in Puerto Rico with 320 workers. Avon employs 43,800 people, including 9,600 in the United States. The chief executive, Andrea Jung, said last month that the company would save $400 million a year by 2004 because of expense reductions, including lowered supply costs and elimination of more than a fifth of its products.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/08/business/company-news-avon-to-take-90-million-in-charges-for-job-cuts.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO TAKE $90 MILLION IN CHARGES FOR JOB CUTS<date>Published: December 8, 2001</date><text>Avon Products , the large direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that it would post up to $90 million in charges in the fourth quarter and might take more next year as it speeds up cost-cutting. But the company said it still expected to meet fourth-quarter earnings and sales targets, helped by strong sales in the United States. Most of the charges will be related to severance payments. The company declined to specify how many jobs would be cut. The market in Latin America, which accounts for about a third of Avon's business, has been worse than expected. Avon shares were down 21 cents, to $48.61.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/12/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-accounts-154830.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Accounts<date>Published: November 12, 2001</date><text>* Equiva Services, Houston, the marketing services arm for the Shell and Texaco brands in the United States, to the Houston office of J. Walter Thompson, part of the WPP Group, to handle Texaco, which had been at the Houston office of BBDO Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group. Billings were estimated at $20 million. Thompson is the worldwide agency of record for Shell, part of Royal Dutch/Shell; the American Texaco stations are to eventually be rebranded as Shell. * Avon Products, New York, to Modernista, Boston, to work with an in-house creative team on the next phase of a print campaign with the theme ''Let's Talk,'' scheduled to begin in March. Billings were not disclosed. Avon has worked with other agencies to create the ''Let's Talk'' print ads. * Time magazine, New York, to Prime Access, New York, to create a television campaign carrying the theme ''T.I.M.E., Today information means everything.'' The primary agency for Time, which is published by the Time Inc. unit of AOL Time Warner, is the New York office of Fallon Worldwide, part of the Publicis Groupe. Prime Access has created campaigns for Time since February aimed at multicultural audiences and was asked to create the television campaign, which is aimed at general audiences.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/11/nyregion/c-corrections-131415.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Corrections<date>Published: September 11, 2001</date><text>A credit was omitted in Business Day on Friday for a brief report about the appointment of Andrea Jung, chief executive of Avon, to the additional post of chairwoman. It was by Bloomberg News.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/07/business/avon-chief-adds-post.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Chief Adds Post<date>Published: September 7, 2001</date><text>Correction Appended Avon Products Inc., the largest direct seller of cosmetics, gave Andrea Jung the additional title of chairman, after profit climbed during her nearly two years as chief executive. Ms. Jung, 42, is one of five female chief executives of Fortune 500 companies, according to the research group Catalyst, and is one of three holding the titles of chairman and chief executive. She replaces Stanley Gault, former chairman of Rubbermaid Inc. and the Goodyear Tire &amp; Rubber Company. Her appointment is effective immediately, Avon said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/17/business/a-campaign-by-avon-on-breast-cancer.html?ref=avonproductsinc">A Campaign By Avon on Breast Cancer<date>Published: August 17, 2001</date><text>''Strength'' and ''Courageous Spirit'' probably do not conjure up images of bright red or raisin-colored lipstick. But they are, indeed, the names of two of six new lipstick shades being introduced in mid-September by Avon Products.The lipstick choices are part of Kiss Goodbye to Breast Cancer, the largest cause-related marketing effort in Avon's history, with a worldwide goal of raising $100 million for breast cancer research and prevention by the end of 2002.''This is something that goes beyond just marketing,'' said Carolyn Aishton, vice president for corporate programs in New York. ''This is something that everybody in the company feels strongly committed to, and it's become personal. Every single person out there has in one way or another been touched by breast cancer, so it penetrates to the grass-roots level. I doubt there's a company in the world that's as grass-roots as Avon is.''One dollar of every $4 lipstick sale will be contributed to the research effort. Avon has raised nearly $150 million since 1993, when it started the Avon Breast Cancer Crusade, through three-day walks and products like pens and candles.To sell the new lipstick and increase awareness, Avon has planned a variety of marketing efforts. Celebrity support has been arranged in the form of kisses; stars like Cuba Gooding Jr., Lisa Ling and Camryn Manheim donated lip prints with the new colors, meant for promotions and publicity.The lip prints of the tennis players Venus and Serena Williams are being featured in a public service print campaign that will appear in magazines like Elle, Essence and Health. Advertising also includes public service TV spots, as well as paid outdoor and radio ads.Avon representatives will have fliers and catalogs featuring the new shades; miniature versions of the catalogs will be inserted into October issues of Cosmopolitan, In Style, Parents and Redbook.Events include a ''day of commitment'' on Sept. 25, with the objective of selling two million lipsticks; 550,000 Avon representatives will be joined by executives like Ms. Aishton and Andrea Jung, the chief executive, whose grandmother lost a battle with breast cancer.Avon's interest goes beyond health concerns. ''It's incredibly beneficial to the overall business,'' Ms. Jung said. ''When the associates, reps and consumers have an enhanced experience, as a result, the shareholder obviously wins, as well.''</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/11/business/avon-creates-a-new-business-to-draw-teenagers-into-fold.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Creates a New Business To Draw Teenagers Into Fold<date>Published: August 11, 2001</date><text>Avon Products, the world's largest direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that it would start a new beauty business aimed at teenage girls around the world.Avon, which has been updating its image for a younger market, said it named a former magazine publishing executive, Deborah Fine, as president of its new Teen Business. Ms. Fine has held various senior executive positions at CondÃ© Nast Publications since 1994, most recently as vice president and publisher of Glamour magazine. She will join Avon Sept. 4.Most of the details of Teen Business, which will not be started until early 2003, are yet to be determined by Ms. Fine, but the company expects that teenagers will sell Avon products to other teenagers through direct selling, catalogs, and the Internet.In recent quarters, the company has ventured into retailing, health and wellness products and Internet commerce, and has started a national ad campaign featuring the tennis stars Venus and Serena Williams. Analysts have lauded those initiatives as ways of altering the company's image, which for more than a century has been epitomized by its door-to-door sales representatives, or ''Avon ladies.''''Marketing to teens is a continuation of our stated strategy to extend Avon's brand equity into new customer segments, new distribution channels and new product categories,'' the chief executive, Andrea Jung, said in a statement, noting the rapid growth of the teenage market all over the world.Recently, the company has had some success in drawing younger customers and sales representatives. In the United States, the company's largest market, 43 percent of Avon customers are between the ages of 15 and 34. In China, a much newer market, that age group is 75 percent of the clientele.The average age of representatives who joined Avon in the last two years is 35.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/11/business/company-news-sears-to-take-53-million-charge-to-drop-skin-care-line.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; SEARS TO TAKE $53 MILLION CHARGE TO DROP SKIN CARE LINE<date>Published: July 11, 2001</date><text>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company will give up its skin care and color cosmetics business next year, resulting in a $53 million charge in the second quarter, the company said yesterday. Sears also reached an agreement with Avon Products that its department stores will not introduce Avon's new retail brand, beComing, this fall. ''As work on improving the performance of full-line stores progresses, it has become clear that a broad cosmetics business no longer fits with our financial and strategic objectives for Sears full-line stores,'' said Alan J. Lacy, chairman and chief executive.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/10/nyregion/public-lives-spearheading-a-marketing-makeover-at-avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">PUBLIC LIVES; Spearheading a Marketing Makeover at Avon<date>Published: May 10, 2001</date><text>TRADITION has it that the Avon Lady rings your doorbell with a smiling face, comes to visit on your turf and terms. But that's not quite the way it works with the head Avon Lady, Andrea Jung. Here we are on her turf, the hushed 27th floor of the Avenue of the Americas skyscraper that serves as global headquarters of Avon Products Inc., the 115-year-old cosmetics heirloom she's hustled ever deeper into makeover mode since her installation 18 months ago as chief executive.Just 42, she is one of only two women at the helm of a Fortune 500 company. (She prefers to place Avon in Fortune 300 territory -- it is 310th.) And here are her terms, as defined by the two concerned sentries outside her spacious but not ostentatious corner office: She'll chat about being a corporate leader, about Avon and its $250 million commitment to breast cancer research (the disease killed her maternal grandmother), but she will not waste time talking about her personal life and silly stuff like how she spends her Saturdays.Uh, oh. She sounds a shade standoffish, as if the only thing she allows under her skin is that $24 Anew Retroactive, her company's contestant in the frenzied miracle-in-a-jar, anti-aging sweepstakes. Does Ms. Jung actually use Avon cosmetics? Of course. You don't make it into the Advertising Hall of Fame (she got there in 1998 as Avon's president and chief operating officer) unless you sincerely plug your products.Ms. Jung materializes a half-hour late (she's been huddling with her second-in-command), a corporately correct vision in an Armani pantsuit topped by three sensible strands of Avon pearls, a big coral smile on her lips, her slim right arm outstretched and, wow, offering up what has to be one of Midtown's most powerful handshakes. (Must be those piano lessons her parents, immigrants from Shanghai and Hong Kong, insisted she begin at 5 in her birthplace, Toronto, when she would way rather have been playing with her Barbie. But the lessons stuck; guess how she spends her Saturdays?)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/13/business/company-news-avon-says-it-expects-to-exceed-profit-forecast.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS IT EXPECTS TO EXCEED PROFIT FORECAST<date>Published: April 13, 2001</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the largest direct seller of cosmetics, said yesterday that it expected first-quarter earnings to slightly exceed forecasts as it increased sales of more-profitable cosmetics and reined in costs. Avon is expected to earn 33 cents a share, the average estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call. Sales growth was in line with analysts' forecasts of about 3 percent, the company said, the slowest pace in more than a year. The company's chief executive, Andrea Jung, said Avon's operating profit margin widened for the 13th consecutive quarter as it cut the cost of supplies and increased United States sales of its more profitable makeup and fragrances by 5 percent. Shares of Avon rose $1.90, or 5.2 percent, to $38.67.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/06/business/company-news-avon-names-new-head-of-retail-operations.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON NAMES NEW HEAD OF RETAIL OPERATIONS<date>Published: January 06, 2001</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the world's largest direct seller of beauty products, said yesterday that it had named Steve Bock to the new position of president of retail operations, effective on Feb. 1. Avon said in a statement that Mr. Bock would be responsible for company relationships with Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company and the J. C. Penney Company, as well as the company's ''Becoming'' brand, scheduled to be introduced this fall. Mr. Bock has been executive vice president for merchandising at the Sephora unit of LVMH Moet-Hennessey Louis Vuitton since 1997.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/business/avon-profit-up-5-despite-slump-in-europe.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Profit Up 5% Despite Slump in Europe<date>Published: October 19, 2000</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the direct seller of beauty products, reported a 5 percent rise in third-quarter earnings yesterday, narrowly beating Wall Street's projections despite weakness in Europe.Avon also said it expected its earnings to increase from 10 to 15 percent during the rest of the year.The company reported earnings of $93 million, or 39 cents a share, in the three months ended Sept. 30, up from $88.2 million, or 34 cents a share, in 1999. Revenue increased 7 percent, to $1.34 billion, from $1.25 billion in the 1999 period.The results beat Wall Street's forecast of 38 cents. Shares of Avon fell 6 cents, to $43.94, on the New York Stock Exchange.Avon said that sales and profit gains in the United States, Latin America and in the Asia-Pacific region more than offset a 3 percent sales decline in Europe from currency weakness.The United States operations posted a 5 percent sales increase, but spending on advertising, its e-commerce site and other brand-building efforts was higher. Total beauty sales were up 9 percent, fueled by the successful introduction of Retroactive, a skin-care product under the Anew brand. Avon expects Anew to be the best-selling skin-care product in the company's history.Avon's Latin American sales were up 15 percent, while the Pacific region posted a 9 percent increase in revenue.Excluding the effects of foreign currency exchange, the company's overall sales rose 10 percent in the quarter.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-thompson-to-handle-new-beauty-line.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Thompson to Handle New Beauty Line<date>Published: October 03, 2000</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it had named J. Walter Thompson in New York, part of the WPP Group, as agency of record to help introduce Becoming, a line of beauty products to be sold at J. C. Penney and Sears, Roebuck stores.Debora Coffey, a spokeswoman for Avon in New York, said the decision came after a review involving Thompson and agencies she declined to identify. Advertising for the cosmetics sold through the company's direct sales force -- the so-called Avon ladies -- is created in-house.Avon plans to begin selling Becoming in the second half of 2001, at 150 to 200 Avon Center ''stores within a store'' at Penney and Sears. Though billings were not disclosed, Andrea Jung, Avon's chief executive, said the company would spend $10 million to $15 million to start and market Becoming.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/company-news-avon-to-cosmetic-products-in-department-stores.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON TO COSMETIC PRODUCTS IN DEPARTMENT STORES<date>Published: September 19, 2000</date><text>Avon Products, the world's largest direct seller of cosmetics, will begin selling its products in department stores next year for the first time in the company's 115-year history. Avon, which sells mainly through door-to-door sales representatives, will sell a new line of cosmetics at Sears, Roebuck and at J. C. Penney in 2001, said Victor Beaudet, a spokesman. The stores will not sell Avon's current products.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/business/company-news-avon-says-sec-is-investigating-15-million-charge.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS S.E.C. IS INVESTIGATING $15 MILLION CHARGE<date>Published: September 15, 2000</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that the Securities and Exchange Commission was investigating a charge of $15 million it recorded during the first quarter of 1999. The company said in a filing that it was cooperating fully with the commission. Avon said the charge involved an order management software system for sales representatives, for which $15 million in costs where written off as part of the special charge. The remainder of the project's development costs, about $26 million, continued to be carried as an asset on Avon's books, the company said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/08/business/company-news-avon-says-it-will-buy-back-up-to-1-billion-of-stock.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS IT WILL BUY BACK UP TO $1 BILLION OF STOCK<date>Published: September 08, 2000</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the world's largest direct seller of cosmetics, plans to buy back up to $1 billion of its common shares, which have fallen 13 percent in the last year. Avon, the maker of Anew and Skin-So-Soft beauty products, said the repurchase, equal to about 11 percent of the company's shares, would be financed by cash generated from operations over the next five years. The company plans to buy back up to 25.3 million shares, based on yesterday's closing price. Avon, which sells in 137 countries, had 1999 sales of $5.3 billion. Its products include fragrances, jewelry, apparel, gifts and collectibles. The shares of Avon, based in New York, rose 94 cents, to $40.50.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/23/business/the-maniac-markets-diary-avon-answers-a-knock-on-its-door.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MANIAC MARKETS: DIARY; Avon Answers A Knock on Its Door<date>Published: April 23, 2000</date><text>Springtime is proxy season, and if history is any guide, a fair number of the shareholder proposals are raising the issue of the paucity of women in management ranks and in boardrooms.You might think that Avon Products wouldn't need to worry about such things. After all, the New York-based marketer of lipstick and other cosmetics has 5 women on its 11-member board. Moreover, its chief executive, Andrea Jung, 41, is a woman.But you would not have taken into account Evelyn Y. Davis, the shareholder activist. According to Corporate Governance Highlights, a newsletter published by the Investor Responsibility Research Center in Washington, Ms. Davis notified Avon last November that she planned to submit a proposal requesting that the company disclose in its annual report the percentage of men in certain categories of jobs that are traditionally held by women.In particular, she wants the company to disclose the percentage of men among Avon's sales representatives, telephone operators, receptionists and secretaries. Ms. Davis said she was concerned that Avon, which has called itself ''the company for women,'' may be discriminating against men. ''They are not a private company,'' she said. ''They are a public company.''Avon, for its part, saw no reason to do battle with Ms. Davis on the proxy issue. It has agreed to disclose such information beginning with the 2000 annual report, due early next year.''We're proud of the fact that women are well represented at all levels of the company,'' said Brian Martin -- himself the senior vice president for corporate communications -- who estimated that more than 95 percent of sales representatives were women. But he added, ''we have some very good men here, too.''RICHARD TEITELBAUM</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/05/business/opportunity-re-knocks-avon-passed-over-before-woman-named-chief-executive.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Opportunity Re-Knocks at Avon; Passed Over Before, a Woman Is Named Chief Executive<date>Published: November 05, 1999</date><text>Slightly more than a month after warning investors to expect disappointing financial results soon, Avon Products said yesterday it was replacing its chief executive with the ultimate Avon lady.The promotion of Andrea Jung, Avon's president and chief operating officer, comes less than two years after a high-profile executive search in which she and three other women at the company were passed over in favor of Charles R. Perrin, an outsider with no experience in direct selling or cosmetics.Ms. Jung becomes the fourth chief executive of a Fortune 500 company who is a woman, and the second to be named this year. She joins Carleton S. Fiorina at Hewlett-Packard, Jill Barad at Mattel and Marion Sandler at Golden West Financial.The company also said yesterday that Stanley C. Gault, a 14-year Avon director who has been chairman and chief executive of the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company and Rubbermaid, would replace Mr. Perrin as chairman, a position he had held since May.Less than 18 months after Mr. Perrin arrived at Avon, two women considered for the top job back then have left the company and Avon's North American business is in a slump. Mr. Perrin, who is 53, abruptly announced yesterday that he was retiring with more than a year left on his contract.Now, the Avon board is counting on Ms. Jung -- who is 41 and had been the company's second in command -- to revive a business that is facing tougher competition, slowing sales in the United States and a credibility issue with disappointed investors and analysts.Given the weakness in Avon's core business, analysts said, the change was not entirely unexpected. But the timing was surprising.Indeed, when Mr. Perrin became chief executive in July 1998, his predecessor, James Preston, said that the inside candidates, which included at least two men in addition to the four women, were ''just a few years away'' from being ready to take over.At the time of Mr. Perrin's selection, Ms. Jung was also promoted to president from executive vice president, signaling her status as heir apparent to Mr. Perrin.Ms. Jung ''has a thorough knowledge of the company and the global beauty industry, as well as the passion to mobilize the organization during this period of significant change,'' Mr. Gault, who is 70, said in a statement yesterday. ''It has been the board's intention that Andrea would become Avon's next C.E.O., and given Charlie's decision to retire, we firmly believe this is the right time.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/19/business/avon-steps-up-buyback.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Steps Up Buyback<date>Published: October 19, 1999</date><text>Avon Products Inc., the world's largest direct seller of cosmetics and fragrances, said yesterday that it was speeding up its $1.1 billion stock-buyback program to finish in the fourth quarter because its shares are cheap. Avon will repurchase $500 million of common stock in the quarter. Avon's shares rose $1.0625 yesterday, to $27.4375, less than half the 52-week high of $56.1875.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/09/30/business/avon-s-stock-declines-27-after-warning-about-profit.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon's Stock Declines 27% After Warning About Profit<date>Published: September 30, 1999</date><text>Avon Products Inc. yesterday became the latest multinational consumer products company to be pummeled by investors after management announced a surprise warning that it expected to report disappointing financial results.Avon shares fell $9.875, or 27.6 percent, to close at $25.8125 after the company said it was suffering from weak economies abroad, currency volatility and stiff domestic competition. The announcement came a day after the Gillette Company made a similar announcement.Avon, the door-to-door cosmetics seller, said it would meet expectations of earning 34 cents a share in the third quarter, which ends today, but would probably be short of analysts' estimates for the fourth quarter. Analysts had expected profit of 63 cents a share in the fourth quarter, but Avon said yesterday that it expected profits to be even with or only slightly higher than the 56 cents earned in the period a year ago.Avon, which is based in New York, gets two-thirds of its profits from outside the United States but is being hit by domestic woes as well.Largely because of a currency devaluation in Brazil and increased competition and heavy sales discounts in Mexico, ''results are not expected to reach the level previously anticipated'' in Latin America, said Charles R. Perrin, chairman and chief executive.''In addition, in the U.S., trends in beauty sales in the fourth quarter are expected to improve significantly over third quarter, but we are seeing weakness in early sales of holiday gifts, causing us to revise the sales outlook in the U.S.,'' Mr. Perrin said. Avon had expected domestic revenue to increase by 5 percent but now says it will not meet that target.For the year, Avon expects to report a double-digit increase in profit over last year's $1.48 a share. Analysts polled by First Call had expected the company to earn $1.71 but revised the number yesterday to $1.64. Some also downgraded the stock, despite Avon's assurances that it was adopting a growth strategy and expected sales growth to pick up next year.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/09/08/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-avon-creative-goes-in-house.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Avon Creative Goes In-House<date>Published: September 08, 1999</date><text>Avon Products Inc. in New York is moving its worldwide creative account in-house after working with D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Communications in New York, part of MacManus Group.Tricia Kenney, a spokeswoman for MacManus, confirmed a report of the shift this week in Advertising Age, adding that Mediavest Worldwide, the MacManus media services agency, was expected to continue to handle media duties for Avon.A D'Arcy sibling, N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners in New York, had been the Avon domestic creative agency from 1994 until 1998, when Avon named D'Arcy to handle international creative duties and the two agencies shared the account. In June, MacManus consolidated the creative assignments at D'Arcy.Telephone calls to Avon seeking comment were not returned. Advertising Age reported that Avon was planning to cut ad spending significantly in an effort to bolster earnings. Avon said yesterday that third-quarter sales would increase less than analysts had forecast.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/22/business/l-shatter-the-ceiling-but-not-the-dream-093238.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Shatter the Ceiling, But Not the Dream<date>Published: August 22, 1999</date><text>To the Editor:Like millions of other young girls around the world, my 10-year-old daughter reveled at the World Cup victory of the United States women's soccer team. It was a crowning celebration of women's skill and achievement in sports, and I loved watching her proud reaction to the ''girls can do anything boys can do'' euphoria.Reading the newspaper not long after that event, she was delighted to see her mother's photograph accompanying a brief report entitled ''Women as Chief Executives: O.K., Who Could Be Next?'' (Private Sector, July 25). Excitedly, she scrolled down the list of names in the article, which included her mom along with several other highly accomplished and admired female executives.But I was dismayed when, together, we read the closing paragraph. ''Don't expect these women to be juggling work and children,'' it said. ''Women may be shattering the glass ceiling, but most of those next in line are doing it without young children in tow.''The speculation about whether or not her mother becomes one of the next chief executives was irrelevant. I shuddered, however, at the slightest suggestion, now planted in the mind of a young girl, that she and her toddler brother could be the very reasons that her own role model might not become all that she hopes to be.I also winced at the phrase ''in tow,'' praying that its negative connotation of anything like ''baggage'' would be lost in a child's translation and not taint a pure and healthy idealism.In a time when women, including mothers of young children, are breaking through in every aspect of American life, I hope that you will take more care to inspire this nation's young girls to dream of a country where everything is possible -- and, in fact, probable in the near term.I hope that you do not fill them with unfortunate judgments that add, not subtract, inches to a ceiling that some of us have taken great measures to chip away.ANDREA JUNGManhattan, July 26The writer is the president and chief operating officer of Avon Products Inc.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/15/business/private-sector-avon-joins-the-fight-against-cancer.html?ref=avonproductsinc">PRIVATE SECTOR; Avon Joins the Fight Against Cancer<date>Published: August 15, 1999</date><text>Avon is doing more than calling these days. Charles Perrin, the company's chairman and chief executive, plans to lead hundreds of Avon employees, from senior management to sales people, who are walking, marching or jogging 55 miles in three days to raise money to fight breast cancer.Mr. Perrin, 54, and his wife Sheila will be among the expected 2,400 walkers who will leave Bear Mountain on Friday, Aug. 27, and walk through Rockland County and New Jersey to the closing ceremonies for the Avon Breast Cancer 3-Day in Central Park on Sunday, Aug. 29. Mr. Perrin and his company are seeing to it that en route, the walkers will have catered meals, hot showers and medical services, plus shelter in tents.''I think this is a very important program,'' Mr. Perrin said, ''and I think it's important for the C.E.O. to walk the talk.'' He's a jogger and his wife takes aerobics classes. Even so, the Perrins and their friends have been training for the event all summer.With similar events, backed by Avon, in Chicago, Los Angeles and Atlanta this year, Mr. Perrin predicts that about $20 million will be raised to help women with the early detection of breast cancer. JAN M. ROSEN</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/28/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-a-consolidation-by-macmanus.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; A Consolidation By MacManus<date>Published: June 28, 1999</date><text>MacManus Group in New York is consolidating its large accounts with Avon Products Inc. in New York by shifting duties from a smaller agency, N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners, to a larger one, D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Communications.The consolidation involves billings estimated at $33 million out of Ayer's estimated total of $475 million. The 10 employees at Ayer working on Avon accounts out of the total of 396 will join D.M.B.&amp; B.Ayer and D.M.B.&amp; B. had worked jointly on the global Avon account since October, when Avon expanded its relationship with MacManus by giving assignments to D.M.B.&amp; B.; before that, Ayer had been Avon's American agency of record since 1994.Roy Bostock, chairman and chief executive at MacManus, said that the move completes a worldwide realignment to create distinct agency brands; in March, MacManus consolidated its Procter &amp; Gamble brands by shifting assignments handled by Ayer to D.M.B.&amp; B.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/09/14/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-six-to-enter-hall-of-achievement.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Six to Enter Hall of Achievement<date>Published: September 14, 1998</date><text>The American Advertising Federation will induct six men and women into its Hall of Achievement, which honors executives 40 and younger.They are: David Angelo, executive vice president and executive creative director at Cliff Freeman &amp; Partners in New York, a unit of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi P.L.C.; Keith T. Clinkscales, president and chief executive at Vibe Ventures in New York; John Farrell, president at D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles North America in New York, a unit of MacManus Group; Eleo Hensleigh, senior vice president for marketing at Disney/ABC Cable Networks in Burbank, Calif., part of the Walt Disney Company; Andrea Jung, president and chief operating officer at Avon Products in New York, and David H. Steward, president and chief executive at TV Guide magazine in New York, which the News Corporation is selling to United Video Satellite Group.The executives will be honored at a luncheon in New York on Nov. 10.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/03/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-avon-expands-ties-with-macmanus-units.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Avon Expands Ties With MacManus Units<date>Published: August 03, 1998</date><text>Avon Products Inc. in New York has expanded its relationship with two agencies owned by MacManus Group in New York -- N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners and D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Communications -- by consolidating its worldwide advertising there.Billings, estimated at $65 million in the past, are expected to increase.Ayer, which has handled Avon's estimated $30 million American account since 1995, will continue in that role.Its sibling, D.M.B.&amp; B., which has handled the Avon account in the Philippines since 1993, was named to handle the account in 25 additional markets overseas; those duties had been handled by various local agencies.Other agencies owned by MacManus -- including Bromley, Aguilar &amp; Associates; Mediavest, and Televest -- will work with Avon to coordinate local, regional and global advertising strategies.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/06/business/international-briefs-avon-plans-to-resume-its-operations-in-china.html?ref=avonproductsinc">INTERNATIONAL BRIEFS; Avon Plans to Resume Its Operations in China<date>Published: June 06, 1998</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it planned to resume its operations in China by June 15 after receiving approval from the Chinese Government. Since April 21, all direct selling companies in China, including Avon, have been prohibited from selling products or recruiting sales representatives.Under the new business license granted by Chinese authorities, Avon said, it intends to operate as a wholesaler to Chinese retail stores and to convert its 75 branches into retail outlets.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/27/world/wuhan-journal-selling-in-china-a-smile-a-shoeshine-and-a-scam.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Wuhan Journal; Selling in China: A Smile, a Shoeshine and a Scam<date>Published: May 27, 1998</date><text>Door-to-door sales networks can seem dangerously intriguing to people still gullible about tales of easy money, so when a craze for selling ankle massage machines hit this city early this year, it spelled trouble.Many thousands of wide-eyed men and women clamored for a chance to sell, convinced that it was the road to riches. They were willing to pay up to $500, almost a year's salary for most urban workers, just for the right to cart an ankle massager door-to-door.But the frenzy for selling was limited, it turned out, to selling. Few people wanted to buy. And no wonder: anyone who looked closely could see that the ankle massager does not really massage the ankle at all. It simply shakes it back and forth.''I lost my own money, my wife's money, my parents' money, my brother's money, my friends' money,'' said Fu Yanbing, who borrowed from so many to buy a small truckload of ankle massagers. ''My wife says I have a year to pay it all back or she wants a divorce.''Door-to-door sales captured, and destroyed, the hopes and dreams of millions of people across China, sketching a painful episode in this nation's elaborate move from a planned to a market economy.In April, citing a rash of fly-by-night operations like the one that tricked Mr. Fu, the Chinese Government banned all door-to-door selling, or direct sales. When the announcement was made, managers at many of those companies closed shop and fled, provoking riots in Wuhan and other cities where salespeople were unable to return unsold goods.The ban has been a disaster for American companies like Amway, Avon Products and Mary Kay, which have spent heavily trying to apply a direct sales formula for soap, cosmetics and other products in China's vast market. Suddenly their prospects look very dim.The ban was intended to clamp down on illegitimate sales operations, many of them run by local Chinese and Taiwanese businessmen, which played shamelessly on the naive aspirations of a people still emerging from poverty and not yet wise to the dark side of capitalism.''Do you want to get rich? To afford a mistress? To own a villa?'' cried one local newspaper advertisement in Guangdong Province, trying to attract sales personnel.Yet the ban has also deprived millions of legitimate work. Tens of millions of urban workers in China are already unemployed, and many of those who went into direct sales had lost a job in a state-run enterprise.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/29/realestate/commercial-property-companies-seek-high-profile-street-level-presence.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Commercial Property; Companies Seek High-Profile Street-Level Presence<date>Published: March 29, 1998</date><text>IN late 1995, when the Intertech Corporation of Washington bought the 33-story building at 1500 Broadway, on the east side of Times Square between 43d and 44th Streets, its executive vice president, Orna Shulman, decided there had to be a better use for the ground-floor space than the chain restaurant, two-screen cinema and small shops that were there.Although the transformation of the Times Square area was just under way, Ms. Shulman decided to consolidate the space so it could be offered to a tenant who wanted the visibility of being in an increasingly popular and tourist-thronged area. ''We thought there was a higher and better use than what was there, although we were not sure whether it would be retail or entertainment,'' she said. ''We were not interested in a dry-goods or a big-box store.''She said the plan was to capitalize on the growing excitement of the area, which has already attracted media companies such as Walt Disney, Viacom, Conde Nast and Warner Brothers. Early this year she announced that Disney, on behalf of its subsidiary ABC network, would take 75,000 square feet on four floors.In a clear effort to match NBC's morning ''Today'' show, which celebrates its location in Rockefeller Center and uses the crowds that gather there as part of the entertainment, ABC's counterpart program, ''Good Morning America,'' will be broadcast from 1500 Broadway with Times Square as a background. ''Companies like Disney find a location like Times Square compelling as we move into the next century,'' Ms. Shulman said.Another big media company, Reuters, has reached agreement with Rudin Management Company to build a headquarters at the intersection of 42d Street and Seventh Avenue, a location that is diagonally across from 1500 Broadway and likely to be in the backdrop of the television broadcast. ''They want to be sure their sign is visible,'' Ms. Shulman said.Ms. Shulman is keenly aware of the value of signs, and has moved to end 1500 Broadway's status as the only major building in the area without them. Some temporary signs now adorn the building, while the framework for a larger, illuminated sign is being erected on the lowest setback. The marquee that used to announce the movies being shown within is now covered with a banner proclaiming ABC's impending move, which is expected next year.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/23/business/staying-with-pitch-stalwarts-face-face-sales-reluctant-peddle-line.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Staying With the Pitch; Stalwarts of Face-to-Face Sales Reluctant to Peddle on Line<date>Published: February 23, 1998</date><text>At a virtual Tupperware party, no coffee is served and there are no demonstrations of the product's notorious ''burp'' when properly sealed or how the cheese plane doubles as an eggplant peeler. But Regina Baker thinks her modern interpretation of the fabled American sales gathering is an effective substitute.''Not everybody has time to go to a party,'' Ms. Baker said. Which is why she built a site on the World Wide Web two years ago to sell her plastic products. She said that the site now accounted for 60 percent of her revenue and 80 percent of her customer base, which has grown to include Tupperware buyers in Japan, Singapore, the Netherlands and Germany -- markets far beyond the reach of a living-room gathering near her home in Houston.But by selling over the Internet, Ms. Baker is violating the policies of the Tupperware Corporation. The company, based in Orlando, Fla., forbids its self-employed sales consultants -- about one million of them worldwide -- from building Web sites to sell its products, and a year ago, it amended the contracts of its new consultants to reflect the prohibition. Since then, warning letters have been sent to site operators, and the number of Tupperware sites has reportedly dropped from 100 to a renegade handful.''The Internet is an information source, not a sales source,'' said Lawrie Hall, a spokeswoman for Tupperware. ''We see it as a wonderful way to educate people. The Internet doesn't provide the kind of service we see as beneficial to the consumer.''The traditional Tupperware party, Ms. Hall says, connects the customer to the product in an essential way: ''At a party, you see more, feel it, understand it.''Though electronic commerce is widely promoted as the Holy Grail of the Internet and the next wave of retailing, Tupperware is not alone in swimming against the tide. Other direct-sales businesses, including Amway, Mary Kay, the cosmetics company, and Electrolux, the vacuum cleaner company, have all shunned the notion of selling directly to consumers on line, though each company has built a Web presence for educating customers, enhancing brands and recruiting salespeople.Several others, including Avon Products and Fuller Brush, a unit of CPAC Inc., are offering their products for sale on line but say that is a sign they wish to appeal to the wired generation -- not that they are dropping the notion of face-to-face selling.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/13/nyregion/metro-business-avon-s-first-store-coming-to-fifth-ave.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Metro Business; Avon's First Store Coming to Fifth Ave.<date>Published: February 13, 1998</date><text>Avon Products and Donald J. Trump announced yesterday that the beauty products company would open its first retail outlet in the United States at Trump Tower.The new store and spa will occupy four floors of the tower, a bronze and glass building on Fifth Avenue between 56th and 57th Streets. The terms of the 15-year lease were not disclosed.Avon had been looking for a site that would dispel any outdated notions about the company's image and proclaim that it no longer sells makeup and skin-care items only to stay-at-home suburban moms.And Mr. Trump wanted to replace the hodgepodge of boutiques on the two upper floors of his luxury mall at Trump Tower with one tenant.Avon products will be sold on the first two floors, in space adjacent to Tiffany that once housed a Salvatore Ferragamo shop. The spa will take up the entire fifth and sixth floors. The dark, reflective glass on the windows of those floors will be replaced by clear glass so that the spa, which will offer fitness classes, can be visible from the street, Mr. Trump said.''These are the crossroads of the world,'' said Kathleen Walas, a spokeswoman for Avon. ''This is an opportunity for us to further establish our global, corporate identity.'' She said the company was going after younger and more urban customers as well as foreign tourists.A separate elevator will also connect the shop and spa.About 100 people will work at the new shop and spa, Ms. Walas said. The company, which has its headquarters at 1251 Avenue of the Americas, employs about 1,000 people in New York, she said. TERRY PRISTIN</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/12/business/avon-calls-man-lead-it-female-cosmetics-executives-passed-over-for-top-post.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Calls On a Man to Lead It; Female Cosmetics Executives Passed Over for Top Post<date>Published: December 12, 1997</date><text>Correction AppendedAvon Products Inc. may be filled with women who sell its products to women all over the world. But it has decided not to be run by one.From the 2.3 million ''Avon ladies'' who peddle its cosmetics door-to-door to the huge female presence in its executive suite, Avon has long enjoyed a reputation of wide-open career opportunities for women. Not only are its millions of customers women, but Avon has more women in powerful positions than most other Fortune 500 companies.And, until yesterday, it looked as if a woman might just be in line to become Avon's next chief executive. But those chances evaporated with the announcement that Charles Perrin, 52, former chief executive of Duracell International Inc., the maker of batteries, will become Avon's next vice chairman and chief operating officer.Mr. Perrin is expected to replace James E. Preston, 64, as Avon's chief executive sometime next year. At the same time, Mr. Preston also announced that Andrea Jung, 39, an executive vice president, was being elevated to become president of Avon's worldwide operations, putting her in line to be Mr. Perrin's successor some day.In gaining this position, Mr. Perrin was selected over Ms. Jung, three other female inside candidates, and two men, as well as any number of female executives in the cosmetics and retailing industries. Mr. Preston said, ''They are just a few years away.''''We wanted someone who had been there and done it,'' Mr. Preston said. ''We wanted someone who had experience as a chief executive of a global company. A lot has been made of the gender issue. But the first responsiblity of the Avon board is to place Avon in the hands of someone who can lead it.''Mr. Preston's announcement was greeted with disappointment by some female executives, who saw it as a missed opportunity. And it was viewed with puzzlement by several analysts, who questioned whether Mr. Perrin's background -- which is neither in the direct selling that is the hallmark of Avon, nor in the cosmetics business -- made him a good fit.''Avon's direct selling is a bit different than any other business,'' said Diane K. Temple, a cosmetics analyst with her own firm. ''I find it surprising that someone with so little experience with a direct selling company is potentially put at the helm of Avon. I would have much preferred an insider or someone with more familiarity with the direct selling business.''Correction: December 13, 1997, Saturday A chart in Business Day yesterday listing top women executives of Fortune 500 companies misspelled the name of the company headed by Jill Barad. It is Mattel, not Mattell.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/18/business/company-news-avon-says-earnings-will-fall-short-of-expectations.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SAYS EARNINGS WILL FALL SHORT OF EXPECTATIONS<date>Published: November 18, 1997</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that its fourth-quarter earnings would not meet analysts' estimates because of worse-than-expected sales in a number of countries, including Brazil, the United States, China and Japan. The company, a direct marketer of cosmetics, said it expected to earn $1 to $1.05 a share in the quarter. The company had been expected to earn $1.13 a share. Last year, the New York-based Avon earned $132 million, or 99 cents a share, in the fourth quarter. Its shares closed unchanged at $62.50. It had been up almost $3 a share before the announcement.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/25/business/company-news-avon-shares-surge-on-cost-cutting-news.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SHARES SURGE ON COST-CUTTING NEWS<date>Published: October 25, 1997</date><text>The stock of Avon Products Inc. surged yesterday after the company announced measures intended to cut costs by up to $400 million a year by 2000. Late on Thursday, Avon said re-engineering costs, including the elimination of 30 percent of its beauty-products line, would reduce earnings in the next two years by $150 million to $200 million. Avon, based in New York, is also studying whether to open new Avon stores and next year it will open an Avon spa in New York. About half of the charges related to the reorganization will be recorded in the first quarter of 1998. Shares of Avon were up $6.875, at $73.75, on the Big Board</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/09/19/arts/photography-review-beauty-in-a-variety-of-guises.html?ref=avonproductsinc">PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW; Beauty, in a Variety of Guises<date>Published: September 19, 1997</date><text>What if McDonald's sponsored a medical conference and invited cardiologists from around the world to talk about the importance of a healthy diet? What would you think?You might scorn the doctors. You might suspect that McDonald's is more insidious than you had ever thought. And you might have a hard time deciding which was worse: health food or Big Macs.These are the kinds of reactions you can expect when looking at ''Eye of the Beholder: Photographs From the Avon Collection,'' an exhibition about the social construction of beauty, created by a company that sells beauty products. Yes, it's Avon calling.For some reason, the International Center of Photography has taken almost all of Avon's brand-new collection of photographs (92 out of 125) and moved it a few blocks south to the photography center's midtown location. The show was put together by Avon's two curators and one from the center.There is nothing wrong with a company collecting art. There is nothing wrong with Avon's curators collecting pictures that reflect on the idea of beauty. And there is nothing wrong with the company thinking that there is a connection between its art and its corporate goals.Avon, for example, sees its photography collection as a reminder of its aim ''to be the company that best understands and satisfies the needs of women around the world.'' Naturally, from Avon's perspective, those needs have more to do with wearing makeup than, say, overturning sexual stereotypes. (One of Avon's latest plans is to team up with Mattel to sell Barbie perfume, shampoo and lip balm to 6- to 12-year-old girls.) So be it. Avon is a company. As long as it's on company grounds, all is fair.But when a museum takes that same collection and passes it off as a meditation on beauty as seen through the eyes of women with cameras, everything turns sour.The implication is that all the living photographers in the show, including Jan Groover, Mary Ellen Mark, Laurie Simmons and Carrie Mae Weems, have knowingly entered the pageant.The exhibition further muddies the already murky issue of who is endorsing what by loading the walls with a lot of text about the cultural construction of beauty and the relationship between the observer and the observed.Indeed, these texts have even been spiked with photographers' quotations (taken from various sources), which makes it look as if the ones quoted actually helped with the show.Thus, any dissent seems to have been pre-empted. Wink, wink, we're all in this together.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/09/04/sports/planned-women-s-series-could-aid-us-runners.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Planned Women's Series Could Aid U.S. Runners<date>Published: September 04, 1997</date><text>In the 1980's and 1990's, American women have enjoyed limited success in distance running.In 1983, in the first women's world track and field championships, Marianne Dickerson won the silver medal in the marathon and returned to obscurity. In 1984, Joan Benoit Samuelson won the first Olympic marathon for women. From 1990 through 1992, Lynn Jennings won three consecutive world cross-country championships.Otherwise, American women have been overshadowed by Europeans and Africans. But a move to change that will be made today with the announcement of a 16-nation road-race circuit for women, with the heaviest action in the United States.The program of 10-kilometer races will be sponsored by Avon, which conducted a women's running series from 1978 though 1985. It will be directed by Kathrine Switzer, who in 1967 became the first woman to run officially in the Boston Marathon. The races have attracted, among others, Samuelson; Jennings; Valentina Yegorova of Russia, the Olympic gold medalist in 1992 and silver medalist in 1996, and Lorraine Moller of New Zealand, the Olympic bronze medalist in 1992.From April to October, there will be nine American races -- in Atlanta; Denver; Dallas; Portland, Ore.; Sacramento, Calif.; Baltimore; Hartford; Kansas City, Mo., and Cincinnati. The American final will be run Nov. 8 in Chicago. Each site will also stage a masters race and a 5-kilometer fitness walk.There will also be one race each in Argentina, Brazil, Canada, Chile, China, Germany, Hungary, Mexico, Italy, Japan, Panama, Philippines, Thailand, the United Kingdom and Venezuela. Those winners will join the American champion in the international final, with a $50,000 purse, at a time and site to be determined.''I think the whole thing is great,'' Samuelson said. ''It's going to give women more opportunities to step into competitive races without feeling intimidated and fearful.''Jennings said the series would provide more opportunities for the elite and potential elite American runners. But she said the problem was greater than that.''Is it commitment, ability, desire, discipline, training hard enough, a willingness to give up short-term things for long-term things?'' Jennings said. ''I don't know. But when I made the commitment to win the world cross-country championship, everything I did was predicated on whether it would help me win. I was willing to forgo indoor track money, road-race money and vacations.'' The new series, Jennings said, might help women make that commitment.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/04/business/with-makeover-a-big-success-avon-turns-a-lot-of-heads.html?ref=avonproductsinc">With Makeover A Big Success, Avon Turns A Lot of Heads<date>Published: July 04, 1997</date><text>Until recently, Avon Products Inc. had become as outdated as the frosty blue eyeshadow it sold to a dwindling number of stay-at-home mothers. But the company is in the middle of a turnaround, brought about largely by the six executives who are now in line to become its next leader.Today, the company's army of 2.3 million Avon Ladies is selling a wide range of products -- from lacy black panties to skin bronzers -- to working women from New York to Hong Kong. Avon, built on a strategy of making house calls, now even sells cosmetics on the Internet. And it introduced a line of apparel in 1994 that became a $128 million unit in nine months and is now a $600 million business.Avon has also expanded into 15 foreign markets since 1990 -- 65 percent of its sales and profits now come from markets abroad. It has shed the $1 billion in debt that weighed down the company during the 1980's, when it was the target of three unsuccessful takeover attempts. And new product introductions are paying off: Avon sold $43 million worth of Avon Barbies last year, for example.The result of the initiatives is that since 1989 Avon's sales have grown at a compounded annual rate of 7 percent, and earnings from continued operations have increased at a rate of 16 percent. And the company has been a hit with investors. Its stock is up 31 percent so far this year, compared with a 24 percent gain for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index. Avon's shares rose 6.25 cents yesterday, to $75.The turnaround effort had been led by the company's 64-year-old chairman, James E. Preston, and president, Edward J. Robinson. But Mr. Robinson stepped down in late May after what the company called a disagreement over who would succeed Mr. Preston, who has been asked by Avon's board to remain as chairman for two more years.As result, there has been much speculation recently about who will move into Mr. Robinson's old office and who will ultimately succeed Mr. Preston.Among the six contenders are Andrea Jung, the 38-year-old head of global marketing and new business who is the brains behind the company's product and marketing overhaul, and Christina A. Gold, 49, who is in charge of global direct selling and development and the executive who motivated the Avon Ladies to ring more doorbells after her predecessor angered them by skimping on incentives.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/30/nyregion/editor-s-note.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Editor's Note<date>Published: May 30, 1997</date><text>An article in Business Day on Wednesday described management and cost-control problems at Donna Karan International, noting that the board had been relatively inactive in the face of the company's problems.The article identified one board member, Andrea Jung, as the wife of Michael Gould, the chief executive of Bloomingdale's, which is a major Donna Karan customer.Ms. Jung should have been further identified by her own professional credentials. She is an executive vice president of Avon Products Inc.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/23/style/chronicle-255297.html?ref=avonproductsinc">CHRONICLE<date>Published: May 23, 1997</date><text>Despite the fact that once again SUSAN LUCCI has been bypassed for a Daytime Emmy Award, she will not be bereft of honors this year. On June 12 she is to receive the Spirit of Enterprise Award at the Women of Enterprise luncheon given by Avon Products at the Waldorf-Astoria. More than 1,400 guests are expected for the ceremony, at which Ms. Lucci will speak.Sizable though that number may be, it is minuscule compared with the number of television viewers who watched Ms. Lucci, who plays the vixen Erica Kane on ''All My Children,'' lose the Emmy for best actress for the 17th consecutive year, this time to Jess Walton of ''The Young and the Restless.''Yesterday, Ms. Lucci, who had shared master of ceremonies duties at the Emmy ceremony with REGIS PHILBIN, was stoic. ''I had a wonderful time appearing on the stage at Radio City Music Hall,'' she said. ''It was a dream come true, and the audience was incredibly warm. I had to rein in my tears a lot when I got a standing ovation during my entrance. There was a great deal of warmth coming at me on that stage.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/02/business/avon-and-mattel-to-sell-barbie-products.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon and Mattel to Sell Barbie Products<date>Published: May 02, 1997</date><text>Avon Products Inc. and Mattel Inc. said yesterday that they would start a line of Barbie lip balms, perfumes, shampoos, conditioners, bubble bath and hand creams aimed at girls ages 6 to 12.The products will range in price from $1 to $7.50 and will be available in the last three months of this year in the United States, Canada and certain Latin American markets, with markets in Europe and Asia under consideration.Avon also said it would again market Barbie dolls designed for Avon by Mattel. Last year, the dolls were Avon's best-selling gift product ever, generating $40 million in sales, the company said.Avon said the alliance with Mattel was expected to increase Avon's net sales by $100 million annually.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/07/business/avon-authorizes-buyback-of-up-to-500-million.html?ref=avonproductsinc">AVON AUTHORIZES BUYBACK OF UP TO $500 MILLION<date>Published: February 07, 1997</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that its board had authorized the repurchase of up to $500 million of Avon stock in the next three to five years. The direct seller of beauty and related products said occasional purchases would be made in the open market. Avon recently completed the repurchase of about 12.6 million Avon shares for $423 million. At the end of 1996, the company had about 132.8 million shares outstanding. In New York Stock Exchange trading yesterday, Avon shares closed at $60.375, down 50 cents. The company also raised its quarterly dividend 7.75 percent, to 31.25 cents a share, from 29 cents. The dividend will be paid on March 3, to stock of record on Feb. 18.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/06/business/somber-news-for-women-on-corporate-ladder.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Somber News for Women on Corporate Ladder<date>Published: November 06, 1996</date><text>If only corporate America would make it easier for women to take care of their duties at home, they could at last compete on an equal footing with men in the workplace -- and rise to the top.That, at least, was the much heralded theory of the 1980's. A comparison of two recent reports suggests, however, that it is not working out that way in the 1990's.One, a census of women at the top of corporate America, delivers the somber news that women hold just about 2 percent of the power positions no matter how they are defined -- by title, by paycheck or by responsibility for the bottom line. Of the nation's 500 largest companies, only 61 can count a woman among their five top earners or can say that a quarter or more of their officers are women. Just 13 of the 61 can do both.When a roster of those 61 companies is placed side-by-side with a list of companies that have won plaudits for their enlightened work-and-family policies, there is very little overlap: few companies that did well on the census conducted by Catalyst, a nonprofit women's research group, also shined on Working Mother magazine's list of the ''100 Best Companies for Working Mothers,'' released in September. And vice versa.Only a handful of companies -- Avon Products; the Federal National Mortgage Association, or Fannie Mae, and Merck among them -- proved to be exceptions, showing up on both lists.''The lack of association'' between the two lists, said Heidi Hartman, director of the Institute for Women's Policy Research in Washington, D.C., ''suggests that this could be a problem,''Jean Lipman-Blumen, a professor at Claremont Graduate School in Claremont, Calif., and author of ''Gender Roles and Power,'' also finds the contrast worrisome. ''I think it means that the women who are making it are making it in the old-fashioned way, accepting the traditional organizational structure and culture,'' she said. ''And it looks like the organizations that have made it easier for women to work in are substituting that for hard-nosed rewards at the top.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/14/business/avon-and-mary-kay-create-opportunities-for-women.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon and Mary Kay Create Opportunities for Women<date>Published: August 14, 1996</date><text>There are more than 15,000 Avon ladies in Russia, and not one of them rings the doorbell.Bowing both to security fears and old-time Soviet etiquette, Russian representatives of the world's largest direct-sales cosmetics company do not go door to door. They do not even make house calls to established customers. Instead, they sell lipsticks, wrinkle creams and facial toners in factories, airports, beauty parlors, laboratories and, sometimes, from a park bench.''Russians are afraid to open their door to strangers,'' explained Mariya Gerasyova, 31, the company's national sales director. ''And even if they know you, they don't want you to see how their apartments look, the lack of repair, the dirt.''But Russian women have swept aside almost every other cultural inhibition to embrace the latest capitalist profit notion sweeping the Russian economy -- direct-sales marketing. Avon Products Inc. of New York and its main rival, Mary Kay Cosmetics, a unit of the Mary Kay Corporation of Dallas, have invaded the Russian market the last two years and recruited an all-female army to sell tens of millions of dollars worth of beauty products each year.And Russia -- with its swelling rolls of unemployed or underemployed professionals -- is a recruiter's dream. Thousands of women trained as engineers, physicists and teachers are grabbing an entrepreneurial opportunity that even five years ago was both illegal and socially taboo.''The professional qualifications of these women are unbelievable,'' declared Susan Kropf, president for new and emerging markets at Avon, on her first visit to Russia last month. ''When the first Russian coordinator I met told me she was a surgeon, I fell out of my chair.'' Mrs. Gerasyova, similarly, is a trained linguist and a reserve lieutenant in the Russian Army.As a result of their new-found wealth and independence, the lives of many of these newly minted entrepreneurs have undergone a more radical make-over than had taken place during the collapse of the Soviet Union five years ago. ''When I started, my husband was always furious,'' said Svetlana Morosova, 29, an area manager for Avon. She sat at a table in the Avon sales office in Moscow with a dozen other managers and sales coordinators. All of them were elegantly turned out in muted pastel business suits. And all of them nodded knowingly.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/04/business/company-news-avon-stock-jumps-on-earnings-and-product-plans.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS;AVON STOCK JUMPS ON EARNINGS AND PRODUCT PLANS<date>Published: April 04, 1996</date><text>Executives at Avon Products Inc. announced ambitious new product plans yesterday and said the worst appeared to be over for Avon in economically troubled Mexico. Meeting with analysts at Avon's headquarters in Manhattan, the executives also said first-quarter earnings would be in line with analysts' estimates, on modestly higher revenue. The company's stock gained $4.50 a share, to $93, an all-time high. Among the new products announced by Avon is its first hair-care line, Avon Techniques. Late this year, the company will come out with a newly formulated skin-care product and a new fragrance, the company said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/06/business/an-acquisition-for-avon.html?ref=avonproductsinc">An Acquisition for Avon<date>Published: February 06, 1996</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire Justine Ltd., marking the beauty-care company's entrance into South Africa. Terms were not disclosed. Justine, of South Africa, is a privately held direct seller of skin care, color cosmetics, fragrances and other beauty products there.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/09/business/avon-products-plans-29.6-million-charge.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Products Plans $29.6 Million Charge<date>Published: December 09, 1995</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it would take a fourth-quarter charge of $29.6 million, or 43 cents a share, to settle a lawsuit with its former Mallinckrodt Inc. unit.The company said that the settlement would result in a charge to discontinued operations. Profit from continuing operations is expected to exceed last year's $110.1 million, or $1.59 a share, Avon said.Avon, a beauty products retailer that is based in New York, said that the settlement would cover all obligations related to its 1986 sale of Mallinckrodt, including environmental cleanup claims and litigation concerning the unit's 1988 settlement of a Du Pont patent claim.Mallinckrodt, a medical products and chemicals company that is based in St. Louis, filed the lawsuit in 1988.Avon acquired Mallinckrodt in 1982 as part of a diversification strategy. In recent years, Avon has sold noncore business to focus on its direct-selling cosmetics and apparel business.Avon ultimately sold Mallinckrodt to the International Minerals and Chemicals Corporation, which changed its name to Mallinckrodt Group Inc.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/29/business/readers-digest-in-avon-venture.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Readers Digest In Avon Venture<date>Published: September 29, 1995</date><text>Reader's Digest Association Inc. and Avon Products Inc. said today that they would test an alliance under which each company would help the other market its products in five countries.The terms of the deal were not disclosed.Under the agreement, Avon's direct-selling representatives will sell Reader's Digest magazine subscriptions and books to its customers in Canada, France, Brazil, Australia and New Zealand. Avon's direct mail brochure will be offered to Reader's Digest customers through product shipments and mailings.The companies said they would also test various joint promotions and incentive programs, as well as direct mail marketing of each other's product lines.The joint marketing effort began recently in Canada and will begin in the other countries in the coming months.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/08/nyregion/avon-office-is-expected-to-remain-in-midtown.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Avon Office Is Expected To Remain In Midtown<date>Published: August 08, 1995</date><text>Avon Products Inc., which has threatened to move its headquarters and 950 employees from West 57th Street in Manhattan to Westchester County or Connecticut, is now expected to move to the Avenue of the Americas instead, real estate executives said yesterday.If Avon remains in Manhattan, it will probably join a long list of corporations that have received city tax breaks as an incentive not to leave. City officials declined to comment yesterday.Brian Martin, a spokesman for Avon, also declined to comment, other than to say that Avon's 25-year lease expires at 9 West 57th Street on July 31, 1997. The company has been considering sites in Westchester, Connecticut and Manhattan, he said.Mary Ann Tighe, executive managing director of Edward S. Gordon &amp; Company, a commercial real estate firm, said, "The negotiations are at a level of specificity that we believe they are very far along." Because city tax breaks have become a standard bargaining chip for large employers that threaten to leave, "we presume there is some commitment from the city," she added. Her firm has been involved in several major midtown deals but not this one.Real estate executives speculated that Avon, the nation's largest cosmetics marketing company, would move to several low floors at 1251 Avenue of the Americas, the former Exxon Corporation headquarters, at 51st Street. A group of executives is expected to move to 1345 Avenue of the Americas, a block north.One real estate executive, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said the deal was "imminent" and would save the company money, even without city tax breaks, because Avon's current building, off Fifth Avenue, is one of Manhattan's most expensive. He estimated that the company's rental costs in that building, if it were to renew its lease, would be close to $50 a square foot, compared with $40 in the Avenue of the Americas buildings.Aides to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani are known to have been been courting Avon heavily since at least early June, when the company said it would move 160 employees in its finance department to a building it owns in Rye, in Westchester County. If Avon gets tax breaks similar to those given to other employers who have announced intentions to leave New York City, it could save more than $1 million over 15 to 20 years.Some recent examples of tax incentives approved by the Giuliani administration include a 16-year package worth $2.2 million for Tullett &amp; Tokyo Forex, a foreign exchange trading company, which agreed in June to keep 555 jobs in the city, and a $1.4 million, 15-year package granted in April to Cantor Fitzgerald &amp; Company, a stock brokerage, which said it would keep 958 jobs in the city.In all, the Giuliani administration has agreed to extend more than $350 million in long-term tax breaks. Most of the tax reductions affect sales taxes.In almost all cases, companies that have received the benefits have promised to increase the number of jobs they have in New York City.The tax breaks have been criticized by some City Council members as excessive assistance to big businesses at a time when city and state support is being reduced for social services and education.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/07/us/in-the-amazon-guess-who-s-calling.html?ref=avonproductsinc">In the Amazon, Guess Who's Calling?<date>Published: July 07, 1995</date><text>This item appeared in the paper as a stand alone photograph. Caption information is provided below.Photo: With nary a doorbell in sight, Eliana Maria Machado da Silva, who oversees 1,000 Avon ladies in Brazil, balanced a box of cosmetics as she stepped to shore on the job with Iraci Macedo da Costa Queiroz. Page A4. (John Maier Jr. for The New York Times)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/07/world/careiro-da-varzea-journal-who-braves-piranha-waters-your-avon-lady.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Careiro da Varzea Journal; Who Braves Piranha Waters? Your Avon Lady!<date>Published: July 07, 1995</date><text>Padding down cow paths in flip-flop sandals or paddling a canoe through piranha-infested creeks, Iraci Macedo da Costa Queiroz lugs from door to door what rain forest dreams are made of: Mesmerize cologne, Forever Fragrance perfume and Cool Confidence deodorant.With no doorbells to ring at the riverside shanties on stilts, this Avon lady of the Amazon claps her hands and calls out cheerily: "Hi, honey! I'm here!""Women want to give me chickens, manioc flour -- but what am I going to do with a chicken?" this veteran, 52-year-old saleswoman exclaimed on the job one recent morning as her son piloted a motor launch across a quiet Amazon tributary where baby pink dolphins played in the sunlight.Far from being a lone missionary for smelling nice in the tropics, Mrs. Queiroz works at the end of a computerized, 2,500-mile long supply chain, part of a national web that last year boosted Brazil over Mexico to become Avon's largest market outside the United States. Offering food for sociological thought, Avon's sales army in Brazil -- 478,000 "beauty consultants" -- is more than double the size of Brazil's Army: 200,000 soldiers.The power of Latin cosmetics has not been lost on Avon, the world's largest cosmetics company. With sales increasingly stagnant in the United States and Europe, Avon now enjoys its fastest growth in the developing world. The beauty star is Brazil, where Avon's sales are expected to hit $1 billion this year, more than double the 1993 level.Argentina ranks as the fourth-largest market for the New York City-based cosmetics company. While Argentina ranks as the biggest per capita consumer of cosmetics in the world, Brazil beats all Latin markets in volume. Every year, Brazilian women use seven tons of skin cream. Last year, Avon sold 1.5 million jars of Renew, an anti-wrinkle cream.Avon's success has drawn attention from other United States direct-sales companies. Amway, which started its Brazil operations here less than four years ago, now has 200,000 distributors.To blanket Brazil, Avon recognizes that there are many Brazils.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/11/realestate/postings-rye-lures-160-employees-when-avon-calls-manhattan-listens.html?ref=avonproductsinc">POSTINGS: Rye Lures 160 Employees; When Avon Calls Manhattan Listens<date>Published: June 11, 1995</date><text>When Avon Products announced last week that it would move 160 of its Manhattan employees to a building it owns in Rye, N.Y., it was a clear defeat for New York City in its battle to retain the cosmetics giant. But the city will not concede the war."Avon still has more than 900 people here, and we want to make sure it continues to find the city a good place to do business," said Forrest R. Taylor, chief of staff for Deputy Mayor John Dyson. Mr. Taylor would not elaborate, but the city traditionally offers tax incentives to retain large companies.Avon, meanwhile, says that it is talking to New York City, Westchester and Connecticut (New Jersey has dropped out because it is inconvenient to many Avon employees), and that it is weighing finances and commuting convenience in deciding where to go. "We know New York is a hub, and we will factor this into our equation," said James E. Preston, Avon's chief executive, who says Avon will announce its decision by July.The only sure loser so far seems to be 9 West 57th Street, where Avon currently occupies 20 very expensive floors on a lease that expires on July 31, 1997. Avon will neither disclose its rent nor publicly rule out the possibility that it will renew. But brokers note that West 57th Street, in the so-called Plaza District, is a high-cost area, and that if Avon planned to renew it would probably have started renewal talks by now.The Rye building is certainly cost-efficient for Avon. A decade ago Avon sold half of its building for $18 million; last year it repurchased it for far less. But the building already houses about 300 Avon data-processing people, and when the Manhattan contingent moves up next year, it will be full.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/02/02/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-an-avon-account-is-awarded-to-ayer.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; An Avon Account Is Awarded to Ayer<date>Published: February 02, 1995</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it had selected N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners in New York to handle the creative portion of its account, which had been handled by FCB/Leber Katz Partners in New York since 1990. Billings were estimated at $15 million to $20 million.Delia deLisser, advertising director at Avon in New York, said Ayer was awarded the account after a four-month review that began with 33 agencies, was narrowed to 7 and then to 3 New York-based shops: Ayer, Altschiller &amp; Company and Kirshenbaum &amp; Bond.Avon was "looking for an agency that can demonstrate how women think today," she added, "and how to market to women today." Ms. deLisser praised Mary Lou Quinlan, a managing partner at Ayer who is also president at Ayer's New York office; Ms. Quinlan was also a predecessor of Ms. deLisser's at Avon.FCB/Leber Katz resigned the account in September because of a conflict caused by the work that a sibling agency, Foote, Cone &amp; Belding in Chicago, created for S. C. Johnson &amp; Son. Avon had previously awarded the media services portion of the account for 1995 to Creative Media in New York. The Nantucket Group in New York served as the consultant for the creative review.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/12/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-three-finalists-in-avon-review.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Three Finalists In Avon Review<date>Published: December 12, 1994</date><text>Avon Products Inc. of New York has narrowed the review on the creative portion of its account to three finalists from seven semifinalists. The account, with billings estimated at $15 million to $20 million, was previously handled by FCB/Leber Katz Partners in New York.Delia deLisser, advertising director at Avon, identified the finalists Friday as three agencies based in New York: Altschiller &amp; Company, the new name for Altschiller Reitzfeld; N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners, and Kirshenbaum &amp; Bond. The four agencies eliminated were Goldsmith/Jeffrey in New York, Leonard Monahan in Providence, R.I., the Martin Agency in Richmond and a shop that Avon declined to identify. A decision is expected by the end of January. Creative Media in New York was named last week to handle the media portion of the account for 1995.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/17/business/company-news-avon-joining-betterware-of-britain-in-venture.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON JOINING BETTERWARE OF BRITAIN IN VENTURE<date>Published: September 17, 1994</date><text>Avon Products Inc. said yesterday that it would form joint ventures with Betterware P.L.C. of Britain in North and South America to sell Betterware's housewares directly to consumers through local independent distributors. Betterware, based in Birmingham, England, contracts third parties to make its houseware products, more than half of which are exclusive designs. It has recently expanded into European markets, including France, Spain and Germany. Avon, the world's leading direct seller of beauty products, said the companies would form their first venture in a major Latin American market by the third quarter of 1995. Avon stock was off 87.5 cents yesterday, to $59.875, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/14/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-fcb-leber-katz-and-avon-part-ways.html?ref=avonproductsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; FCB/Leber Katz And Avon Part Ways<date>Published: September 14, 1994</date><text>Avon Products Inc. and FCB/Leber Katz Partners in New York are parting ways on the company's account, with billings estimated at $10 million to $20 million, because of a conflict with a client of FCB/Leber Katz's parent, Foote, Cone &amp; Belding.Vonda LePage, a spokeswoman for FCB/Leber Katz, confirmed a report of the account's departure yesterday in the Advertising Age Daily Fax edition. "We mutually agreed earlier in the month that we would end our relationship because of the conflict," she said. FCB/Leber Katz has handled Avon's account since 1990.The conflict arose when the Chicago office of Foote, Cone created advertising for Off! Skintastic insect repellent, a brand marketed by an important Foote, Cone client, S. C. Johnson &amp; Son. Those ads disparaged an Avon product, Skin-So-Soft, which has found a second use among consumers as an insect repellent. Avon has filed a lawsuit against Johnson over the ads.Victor Beaudet, a spokesman for Avon in New York, said the company was "just starting to evaluate what our next steps will be," adding that FCB/Leber Katz would handle the account through the end of the year.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/08/business/company-news-avon-shares-rise-on-takeover-talk.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; AVON SHARES RISE ON TAKEOVER TALK<date>Published: September 08, 1994</date><text>Shares of Avon Products Inc. rose $2 yesterday, to $61.50, on the New York Stock Exchange amid takeover speculation. The CNBC commentator Dan Dorfman said there was speculation that Goldman, Sachs was putting together a transaction that would pay $80 a share for Avon's stock. Avon declined to comment. Without a takeover, Avon is a "solid buy" on strong fundamentals, said Robert Rank of R. L. Rank &amp; Company, who manages $50 million in assets.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/27/business/company-reports-avon-to-sell-its-giorgio-unit-for-150-million-to-p-g.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY REPORTS; Avon to Sell Its Giorgio Unit For $150 Million to P.&amp; G.<date>Published: July 27, 1994</date><text>Avon Products Inc. is selling its Giorgio Beverly Hills Inc. perfume unit to the Procter &amp; Gamble Company for $150 million in cash, the companies said yesterday. The deal will complete the sale by Avon of its noncore businesses.For P.&amp; G., the household and personal-care conglomerate, the acquisition will bring its worldwide fragrance business to about $500 million, including $330 million in prestige fragrances.Avon, the world's largest direct seller of beauty products, with $4 billion in annual revenues, has been trying to sell Giorgio since 1989 -- two years after acquiring it -- to streamline operations around cosmetics. Profit Reported by AvonSeparately, Avon reported a profit of $50.1 million in the second quarter ended June 30, down 23.6 percent from $65.6 million a year ago. Revenue rose 8.7 percent, to $1.0 billion from $920.2 million. The results exclude Giorgio.P.&amp; G. has been seeking to build a prestige fragrance empire since it entered the business in 1991 with the purchase of Max Factor. Its latest acquisition follows a pact earlier this month with Salvatore Ferragamo Firenze of Florence, Italy, to create a perfume in the luxury market segment. Rumors of P. &amp; G.'s interest in Giorgio had circulated in June."Our objective is to be a worldwide leader in fragrances," said Edwin Artzt, the chairman and chief executive of P.&amp; G.. "Giorgio has a strong prestige fragrance business in the U.S. and a developing one in Europe, which nicely complements P.&amp; G.'s growing U.S. and well-established European businesses."James E. Preston, the chairman and chief executive of Avon, said the sale "will complete our efforts to divest nonstrategic operations and focus Avon's resources on direct selling."Proceeds from the sale will be used to reduce debt and support Avon's share repurchase program, the company said.Giorgio, based in Santa Monica, Calif., makes Red for men and women, one of the top five-selling fragrances in the United States, and Giorgio, one of the top 15 brands. It also makes Wings fragrance for women and will introduce a version for men later this year.Since Avon acquired Giorgio, annual sales of the unit have grown to about $165 million in 1993, or about 4 percent of Avon's total sales.P. &amp; G.'s key prestige brands include Laura Biagiotti Venezia, a women's fragrance, Hugo Boss and Boss Elements, a men's fragrance. Earlier this year, it introduced Biagiotti's Roma Uomo -- Roma for Men.Avon first expressed interest in divesting itself of Giorgio shortly after selling Parfums Stern to Safrep, an affiliate of Elf Sanofi S.A. of France, for $210 million in 1989. Analysts said Avon had hoped to get that amount for Giorgio.Avon markets its products in more than 100 countries through 1.7 million independent representatives. P.&amp; G. had worldwide sales of $30.4 billion in the 1993 fiscal year.Shares of Avon were off 75 cents yesterday, to $57.625, on the New York Stock Exchange. P.&amp; G.'s stock was down 12.5 cents yesterday, to $54.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/06/16/business/company-news-procter-gamble-said-to-be-interested-in-avon-unit.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE SAID TO BE INTERESTED IN AVON UNIT<date>Published: June 16, 1994</date><text>Avon Products Inc., which has been willing to take an offer for its perfume unit since 1989, may have found a bidder in the Procter &amp; Gamble Company, analysts said yesterday. Avon, based in New York, has long wanted to sell the fragrance unit, which includes the Giorgio Beverly Hills brand, to concentrate on its core direct-marketing business. Neither company would comment on a report in The Wall Street Journal yesterday that they were in talks. The cosmetics company has wanted to dispose of the unit since it sold its Parfums Stern to Safrep, an affiliate of Elf Sanofi S.A. of France, for $210 million in 1989. Avon acquired Giorgio Beverly Hills for $165 million in 1987.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/03/business/profile-relighting-the-fires-at-avon-products.html?ref=avonproductsinc">Profile; Relighting the Fires at Avon Products<date>Published: April 03, 1994</date><text>THERE'S a flowering plant on Christina A. Gold's desk. She's not sure if it is an azalea or a hibiscus or what. But she loves that plant every bit as much as the more familiar blooms she tends at home."A sales rep sent it to me," Ms. Gold said with visible pride. "The note said, 'Thanks for bringing springtime back to Avon.' "Avon Products Inc. has gone through a series of emotional seasons every bit as harsh as the actual winter that just passed. In November, after 24 years with Avon's Canadian division, Ms. Gold was called to New York to become the first woman to head the United States, Canadian and Puerto Rican operations of the direct-sales beauty company. She replaced Walker Lewis, who resigned after only 19 months.Avon insiders say that Mr. Lewis, a former management consultant, ran Avon entirely with his head. Now Ms. Gold is trying to put heart back into the place."Walker was a brilliant strategist," said James E. Preston, Avon's chief executive. "But now we need someone whose first priority is to re-energize the sales force."Mr. Lewis, reached in Greenwich, Conn., refused to comment. But Avon insiders say it is no coincidence that Mr. Preston says re-energize, not simply energize. For the last five months, Ms. Gold, who is 46, has been reconstructing some of the motivational institutions that Mr. Lewis so carefully took apart."Over the last few years, the whole program for incentives was skinnied down," recalled Brian C. Connolly, whom Ms. Gold plucked from the Southeast sales region to become director of national incentives and motivation -- a position that Mr. Lewis had abolished. "The push was toward advertising and chasing fringe customers."Actually, many of Mr. Lewis's strategies worked. Avon's new "800" number, which allows customers to bypass the Avon Lady to buy direct, has added incremental sales. Anew, Avon's high-tech skin care product, has been successful, as has a new line of skin care products for men. And most analysts have high hopes for lingerie, a new product for which Mr. Lewis laid the groundwork.Avon's stock, which bottomed at about $19 five years ago, closed at $56.25 on Thursday, the final day of trading last week. The company has stayed independent, despite Chartwell Inc.'s takeover run in 1990.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/19/business/company-news-lingerie-business-is-planned-by-avon-in-us.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; LINGERIE BUSINESS IS PLANNED BY AVON IN U.S.<date>Published: October 19, 1993</date><text>Avon Products Inc. plans to begin a United States lingerie sales business through its direct selling channels. James E. Preston, the company's chief executive, said yesterday that Avon hoped to reduce its reliance on its $300 million gift business and emphasize lingerie instead. Test marketing of lingerie sales in the United States with the Warnaco Group Inc. and an existing lingerie sales business in Canada have both been successful. Avon's gift sales declined in the third quarter and executives expected that full-year gift sales would be 15 percent below 1992 levels. The United States lingerie business will begin by the second quarter of 1994.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/09/03/business/company-news-shares-of-avon-drop-by-7-on-third-quarter-forecast.html?ref=avonproductsinc">COMPANY NEWS; Shares of Avon Drop by 7% On Third-Quarter Forecast<date>Published: September 03, 1993</date><text>Avon Products Inc. stock lost more than 7 percent of its value yesterday after the company announced that third-quarter earnings would not match 1992 levels.The shares lost $4.625 to close at $54.875. Nearly two million shares were traded on the New York Stock Exchange.In a statement issued before trading opened, James E. Preston, Avon's chairman and chief executive, said the combination of a sluggish economy and changes in Avon's business operations would result in earnings for the quarter below the $53.9 million, or 75 cents a share, reached in the corresponding quarter last year.The company, which markets beauty products, jewelry and gifts, plans to announce third-quarter results on Oct. 18.Mr. Preston predicted the decline was temporary and said he expected an improvement for the fourth quarter and full year over 1992 levels, based on several new advertising initiatives and sales programs. Neither his statement nor a company spokesman provided any details on the nature of the changes."These programs should position us to perform satisfactorily in the current difficult economic environment and to take full advantage of any upturn in consumer confidence," Mr. Preston said in the statement. But he hedged his bet, adding, "The degree of improvement will obviously depend on consumers' willingness to spend."His optimistic view was shared by several stock analysts, who said investors expecting a better quarter might have overreacted, reflecting larger concerns over consumer-product companies in general."Everybody is very jittery about consumer stocks," said Diana K. Temple, an analyst who follows them for Salomon Brothers.She agreed that Avon's year-end results would be better and said that the third-quarter decline could be attributable, in part, to a change in the qualifying period for the President's Club, an incentive award program for Avon's leading salespeople. The time was extended from this month to March, creating more time -- but less urgency -- to meet various award levels.Joseph H. Kozloff, an analyst for Smith Barney Shearson, said September sales would be improved over the "squishy" months of July and August although not enough to save the quarter. But he was more heartened by the company's willingness to exude any degree of confidence in public."This is not a company that over-promises," he said. "But as I read it, they are convinced they are doing the right thing, that their programs are working and they have the right mix of product and price."</text></article></page></root>