<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Baker Hughes"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/17/business/energy-environment/17oil.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">As Iraq Oil Industry Rebuilds, American Subcontractors Dominate the Work<date>Published: June 16, 2011</date><text>MOSCOW — When Iraq auctioned rights to rebuild and expand its oil industry two years ago, the Russian company Lukoil won a hefty portion — a field holding about 10 percent of Iraq’s known oil reserves.It seemed a geopolitical victory for Lukoil. And because only one of the 11 fields that the Iraqis auctioned off  went to an American oil company — Exxon Mobil — it also seemed as if few petroleum benefits would flow to the country that took the lead role in the war, the United States. The auction’s outcome helped defuse criticism in the Arab world that the United States had invaded Iraq for its oil. “No one, even the United States, can steal the oil,” the Iraqi government spokesman, Ali al-Dabbagh, said at the time. But American companies can, apparently, drill for the oil. In fact, American drilling companies stand to make tens of billions of dollars from the new petroleum activity in Iraq long before any of the oil producers start seeing any returns on their investments. Lukoil and many of the other international oil companies that won fields in the auction are now subcontracting mostly with the four largely American oil services companies that are global leaders in their field: Halliburton, Baker Hughes, Weatherford International and Schlumberger. Those four have won the largest portion of the subcontracts to drill for oil, build wells and refurbish old equipment. “Iraq is a huge opportunity for contractors,” Alex Munton, a Middle East analyst for Wood Mackenzie, a research and consulting firm based in Edinburgh, said by telephone. Mr. Munton estimated that about half of the $150 billion the international majors are expected to invest at Iraqi oil fields over the next decade would go to drilling subcontractors — most of it to the big four operators, which all have ties to the Texas oil industry. Halliburton and Baker Hughes are based in Houston, as is the drilling unit of Schlumberger, which is based in Paris. Weatherford, though now incorporated in Switzerland, was founded in Texas and still has big operations there. Michael Klare, professor of peace and world security studies at Hampshire College and an authority on oil and conflict, said that American oil services companies were generally dominant both in the Middle East and globally because of their advanced drilling technology. So it is no surprise, he said, they came out on top in Iraq, too — whatever the initial diplomatic appearances. United States officials have said that American experts who advised the Iraqi oil ministry about ways to restore and increase petroleum production did so without seeking any preferences for American companies. And immediately after the 2009 auction round won by Lukoil, the United States Embassy spokesman in Baghdad, Philip Frayne, told Reuters that “the results of the bid round should lay to rest the old canard that the U.S. intervened in Iraq to secure Iraqi oil for American companies.” But Professor Klare said that the American officials who had advised the Iraqi government on its contracting decisions almost certainly expected American oil services companies to win a good portion of the business there, regardless who won the primary contracts. “There’s no question that they would assume as much,” he said. The American oil services companies, which have been in Iraq for years on contract with the United States occupation authorities and military, are expanding their presence even as the American military prepares to pull out. For example, Halliburton, once led by former Vice President Dick Cheney, has 600 employees in Iraq today and said in a statement that it intended to hire several hundred more before the end of the year. “We continue to win significant contracts in Iraq, and are investing heavily in our infrastructure,” Halliburton said. The 11 contracts Iraq signed with oil majors, including the six for the largest fields, are intended to raise Iraqi output from about 2.5 million barrels of oil a day now to 12 million barrels daily in 2017. Some of the oil services contracts are for repairing currently productive fields, others to tap mostly unused sites. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/10/business/10markets.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Commodity Prices Rise, Lifting Energy and Materials<date>Published: May 9, 2011</date><text>Commodity prices recovered some of last week’s losses Monday, helping to lift the stocks of energy and materials companies. The broader market also rose despite new worries about Greece’s debt problems.Oil prices again exceeded $100 a barrel and pushed energy stocks higher. Marathon Oil rose 5.3 percent. Baker Hughes, which helps companies drill for oil and gas, gained 3.4 percent. Energy companies within the Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index rose nearly 2 percent, the most among the 10 industries in the index. The index added 6.09 points, or 0.45 percent, to close at 1,346.29. The Dow Jones industrial average gained 45.94 points, or 0.36 percent, to 12,684.68. The Nasdaq composite index rose 15.69 points, or 0.55 percent, to 2,843.25. The increase in commodity prices helped other industries as well. Producers of metals and other materials rose 1.5 percent, second best among the S.&amp; P. 500 groups, aided by a 5 percent increase in silver prices and a 3 percent increase in corn. Metals and other commodities had steep losses last week, when silver tumbled 27 percent and oil sank 15 percent because of fears of weaker global demand and higher margin requirements. Financial stocks were the only industry group to decline Monday. Citigroup fell 2.7 percent on its first day of trading after completing a one-for-10 reverse split that substantially increased its share price by lowering the number of available shares. It is now trading in the $40 range for the first time since 2007. Companies often turn to reverse splits to raise their share prices as a way to attract institutional investors who may be prohibited from buying into companies with share prices in the single digits. Better sales pushed other companies higher. The nation’s largest food distributor, Sysco, rose 10.7 percent after reporting a 4 percent rise in income. Analysts had expected a drop. McDonald’s rose 0.8 percent after reporting that its global sales rose last month. The strongest growth came from its restaurants abroad. Tyson Foods lost 6 percent after reporting that its earnings were flat from a year ago. The Dollar Thrifty Automotive Group rose 13.8 percent after Hertz Global Holdings raised its buyout offer for the car rental company to more than $2.2 billion. Avis Budget Group is also trying to buy Dollar Thrifty. Most companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 have reported earnings for the first quarter, and the trends have been strong. Through Friday, nearly three out of four companies released earnings that beat analysts’ expectations. Economic figures, by contrast, have been mixed. Growth for the manufacturing industry slowed last month, and the economy grew at a lower-than-expected 1.8 percent in the first quarter. European stock markets fell on worries that Greece will need more time or aid from other European Union countries to make payments on its debt, or worse, the country could partly default on the debt it owes to bond investors. Standard &amp; Poor’s downgraded Greece’s debt rating even further into junk status. The Euro Stoxx 50, an index of large companies in countries that use the euro, fell 1.7 percent. Interest rates were steady. The Treasury’s benchmark 10-year note fell 3/32, to 103 29/32, and the yield was unchanged at 3.15 percent.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/01/business/01oilfield.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes To Buy Rival In Services To Oil Fields<date>Published: August 31, 2009</date><text>HOUSTON (AP)  The oil field services company Baker Hughes said on Monday that it would buy a rival, BJ Services Company, in a cash-and-stock deal valued at $5.5 billion. The company said the purchase would allow it to expand internationally and compete for projects with companies engaged in all phases of the oil business. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Baker Hughes Inc BJ Services Company Go to your Portfolio » The acquisition is expected to produce $75 million in cost savings for Baker Hughes in 2010 and $150 million in 2011, and add to earnings per share in 2011, the company said. The chief executive of Baker Hughes, Chad C. Deaton, said in a statement that the transaction would particularly help customers with unconventional gas and deepwater fields. “It will better position us to drive international growth and to compete for the growing large integrated projects by incorporating pressure pumping into our product offering,” Mr. Deaton added. Integrated oil companies are active in all phases of the business including production, refining, transportation and marketing. Pressure pumping made up less than 1 percent of Baker Hughes’s 2008 revenue, but is expected to account for about 20 percent of the company’s revenue after the deal is complete. BJ stockholders will receive about 0.4 shares of Baker Hughes and $2.69 in cash for each share they own. The deal represents a 16.3 percent premium to BJ’s $15.43 closing stock price on Friday, the companies said. BJ’s shareholders will own about 27.5 percent of Baker Hughes once the acquisition closes, and two BJ Services board members will join Baker’s board. The acquisition, which has approval from both companies’ boards, may close by year’s end. It still needs the approval of both companies’ shareholders. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 1, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/27/business/worldbusiness/27settle.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes Admits to Overseas Bribery<date>Published: April 27, 2007</date><text>Baker Hughes, a large oil services company, pleaded guilty yesterday to violating the foreign corrupt practices act by bribing foreign officials, an action that continued even after the company promised in 2001 to stop making such payments. The criminal charges covered payments to win oil field contracts in Kazakhstan, but the company also settled civil charges filed by the Securities and Exchange Commission accusing it of making illegal payments in five other countries  Angola, Indonesia, Nigeria, Russia and Uzbekistan. The company agreed to pay $44.1 million in penalties and forfeitures, which the government said was the largest penalty ever for violations of the Foreign Corrupt Practices Act. It also agreed to appoint a monitor to assure that it complied with the law in the future. The acts which resulted in these enforcement actions are contrary to our core values, our policies and our expectations for ethical behavior, Chad C. Deaton, the chief executive of Baker Hughes, said in a statement. He said that the employees involved had left the company. Linda Chatman Thomsen, the S.E.C.s enforcement director, said, Baker Hughes committed widespread and egregious violations of the F.C.P.A. while subject to a prior commission cease-and-desist order. She added that the suit demonstrates that companies must adhere to commission orders and that recidivists will be punished. Alice S. Fisher, an assistant attorney general, said, The record penalties leveled in this case leave no doubt that foreign bribery is bad for business. By enforcing the F.C.P.A., we are maintaining the integrity of U.S. markets and leveling the playing field for those companies that want to play by the rules. In an action that was filed on Sept. 12, 2001, and received little attention at the time, Baker Hughes agreed to a cease-and-desist order issued by the S.E.C., which said that it had violated the corrupt practices act by bribing an official in Indonesia. That cease-and-desist order appeared to have had little impact on the companys behavior, the S.E.C. action filed Wednesday indicated. It said the payments in Kazakhstan and Angola went on from 1998 to 2003, while those to an agent involved in securing business in Russia and Uzbekistan went on from 1998 to 2004, and payments in Indonesia went on from 2000 to 2003. Payments in Nigeria were made from 2001 to 2005, the S.E.C. said. In 2003, the company initiated an investigation, but, the S.E.C. said, it did not uncover some of the violations, which allowed them to continue. In yesterdays settlement, the company agreed to pay a fine of $11 million in connection with the criminal case, and it entered into a deferred prosecution agreement that would bar further prosecution if it did not commit more violations in the next two years. It also agreed to pay more than $23 million in disgorgement and interest and a civil penalty of $10 million for violating the cease-and-desist order. No criminal charges were filed against company executives, and the S.E.C. filed a civil complaint against one person, Roy Fearnley, a former business development manager for Baker Hughes in Kazakhstan. Mr. Fearnley has not settled the suit, and the commission said it knew of no lawyer representing him. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/04/business/04baker.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes Subpoenaed in Iraq Sales<date>Published: November 4, 2004</date><text>OUSTON, Nov. 3 (AP) - A federal grand jury in Manhattan has asked the oil services company Baker Hughes for information about goods and services it delivered to Iraq from 1995 to 2003, the company said on Wednesday. The company, based in Houston, said in a regulatory filing that it was subpoenaed by the grand jury in the Southern District of New York. The grand jury and several Congressional committees are investigating possible corruption in the United Nations' oil-for-food program, which ran from 1996 to 2003. Advertisement The Houston Chronicle reported that Baker Atlas, a unit of Baker Hughes, sold $8.2 million in equipment to Iraq in the late 1990's, according to a list compiled by a committee led by the former Federal Reserve chairman, Paul A. Volcker. "We are in the process of responding to the subpoena," the company said, adding that other companies in the industry apparently had received subpoenas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/12/business/company-news-baker-hughes-lowers-first-quarter-profit-forecast.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES LOWERS FIRST-QUARTER PROFIT FORECAST<date>Published: April 12, 2003</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., the world's third-largest provider of oil field services, said first-quarter profit probably fell because production was disrupted at wells in Nigeria, Venezuela and the Middle East. The company, based in Houston, now expects a profit of 13 cents to 14 cents a share, excluding discontinued businesses and the effect of changes in accounting. Net income a share was 22 cents for the first quarter of 2002. Sales from the company's oil field segment fell 4 to 6 percent from the fourth quarter of 2002. The company expects to report first-quarter earnings before trading starts on April 22. It previously forecast earnings of 17 cents to 20 cents.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/11/business/baker-hughes-in-buyback.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes in Buyback<date>Published: September 11, 2002</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., a leading oil services company, said today that it would repurchase as much as $275 million of its common stock, its first buyback since the early 1970's.Based on Monday's closing price of $27.90, the company could repurchase about 9.9 million shares, or 2.9 percent of those outstanding. Baker Hughes, which is based in Houston, will repurchase shares at times depending on market price and available cash, the company said.Shares in Baker Hughes rose 74 cents, or almost 3 percent, to $28.64 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/30/business/baker-hughes-is-target-of-us-investigation.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes Is Target of U.S. Investigation<date>Published: March 30, 2002</date><text>Baker Hughes, the oil field services company, said today that the Securities and Exchange Commission and the Justice Department were investigating accusations of a kickback scheme involving a contract in Nigeria.A former employee, Alan Ferguson, sued Baker Hughes this week in a Texas state court, asserting that the company had paid kickbacks to win a contract with a unit of the Royal Dutch/Shell Group in Nigeria and that he had been fired for refusing to go along with the arrangement.Baker Hughes said in a statement that it had already started an investigation into the incident before the lawsuit was filed. It also said it was cooperating with investigators and ''will not tolerate improper payments or other improprieties.'' Company representatives did not return telephone calls.The lawsuit and news of the investigations come six months after Baker Hughes signed a consent decree with the S.E.C. promising not to bribe foreign officials. The S.E.C. accord, signed in September, was the result of claims that the company's former controller and chief financial officer approved a bribe to an Indonesian government official in 1999.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/26/business/ex-executive-sues-baker-hughes-kickbacks-cited.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Ex-Executive Sues Baker Hughes; Kickbacks Cited<date>Published: March 26, 2002</date><text>A former executive of Baker Hughes, the oil field services company, contends in a lawsuit that the company paid kickbacks to win a major contract with a unit of Royal Dutch/Shell and that he was dismissed for refusing to go along with the arrangement.The lawsuit, filed yesterday in a Texas state court, comes at an awkward time for Baker Hughes and Shell, which have struggled to rid themselves of suspicions of corruption overseas. After accusations that the company's former controller and chief financial officer approved a bribe to an Indonesian government official in 1999, Baker Hughes entered into a consent agreement with the Securities and Exchange Commission on Sept. 12, 2001, promising not to violate rules regarding payments to foreign officials in the future. Shell, for its part, has published an audit of its anticorruption practices since 1997, documenting actions it has taken against corruption in its ranks, after it came under harsh criticism for its business practices in Nigeria.Baker Hughes, which is among the biggest oil field services companies, declined yesterday to comment on the lawsuit. Shell, the second-largest oil company in the world, pointed out that it was not involved in the complaint and defended its efforts against corruption. ''Shell's business principles are very clear: that we will not tolerate corruption or the taking or giving of bribes,'' said Michael McGarry, a spokesman for the company. ''Our record in Nigeria and elsewhere shows that we are committed to having the highest standards of integrity in all of our business dealings.''The lawsuit, which was filed in Harris County District Court in Houston, where Baker Hughes is based, was brought by Alan Ferguson, formerly the region operations manager in Nigeria for the Baker Hughes Inteq drilling systems group, one of the company's six business units.Mr. Ferguson, who said he had been with the company for 24 years until he was dismissed last October, contends that in 1999, a ''senior Shell employee'' with the oil company's Nigeria unit offered to award Baker Hughes a lucrative contract with a project in Nigeria if a so-called agency he had created received a percentage of Baker Hughes's revenue. Shell Nigeria is controlled by the Nigerian National Petroleum Corporation, and Shell has a 30 percent stake in the unit.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/23/business/company-news-baker-hughes-reduces-earnings-forecast-for-quarter.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES REDUCES EARNINGS FORECAST FOR QUARTER<date>Published: March 23, 2002</date><text>Baker Hughes, the world's third-largest oil field services company, sharply reduced its forecast for first-quarter earnings yesterday, saying lower energy prices caused by the recession had led to weaker demand for its drilling rigs. The company, which is based in Houston, forecast first-quarter profit of 20 cents to 22 cents a share, down from a mid-February forecast of 24 cents to 27 cents. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call had predicted a profit of 26 cents a share.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/01/business/company-news-schlumberger-and-baker-hughes-form-seismic-venture.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER AND BAKER HUGHES FORM SEISMIC VENTURE<date>Published: June 01, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's No. 2 oil field services company, agreed yesterday to pay $500 million to a rival, Baker Hughes Inc., for a 70 percent stake in a new joint venture to provide seismic services used to locate oil and gas. Seismic technology is used to study the physical properties of land or water in an effort to save on the expense of drilling into dry areas. Schlumberger and Baker Hughes will combine their seismic divisions to form a venture called Western GECO. The shares of Schlumberger rose $2.3125 each, to $73.3125. Baker Hughes rose $2.125, at $36.25.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/19/business/oil-exploration-up-in-us.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Oil Exploration Up in U.S.<date>Published: February 19, 2000</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States rose this week by 11, to 773. Of the rigs running nationwide, 153 were exploring for oil and 620 were looking for gas, Houston-based Baker Hughes Inc. reported today. During the same week last year, 531 rigs were operating in the United States. Of the major oil- and gas-producing states, Texas and Louisiana each gained six rigs, and New Mexico gained two. California and Wyoming each lost two, and Oklahoma dropped by one. Alaska remained unchanged.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/18/business/company-news-baker-hughes-to-restate-earnings-by-31-million.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES TO RESTATE EARNINGS BY $31 MILLION<date>Published: February 18, 2000</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., which provides services to the oil industry, said yesterday that it would restate earnings for several years, reducing past profit by $31 million, because of accounting errors at its Inteq drilling unit. Baker Hughes said it also planned to sell its Baker Process division, which makes water-filtering equipment, and use the proceeds to reduce debt and focus on oil field operations. The business had 1999 sales of $389.8 million. The earnings restatement will cut profit in the years before 1995 by about $24 million, the company said. Baker Hughes, which is based in Houston, created Inteq in 1993.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/01/business/ouster-at-the-top-of-baker-hughes.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Ouster at the Top Of Baker Hughes<date>Published: February 01, 2000</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., the world's third biggest oil field services company, said today that Max Lukens had been ousted as its chairman, chief executive and president because of the board's dissatisfaction over the company's recent stock market performance.''We have not been satisfied with our performance in the stock market,'' the interim chairman, Joe Foster, said in a statement. ''We want to improve value for the shareholders of Baker Hughes.''Baker Hughes stock jumped $3.875 a share today, to $24.6875, on the New York Stock Exchange.Mr. Foster, a member of the Baker Hughes board since 1990, will assume all three of Mr. Lukens's positions until a new chief executive is appointed.Shares of Baker Hughes fell sharply in December when the company said accounting problems at one unit would lead to a pretax charge of $40 million to $50 million and that it would also take a pretax charge of $130 million at its seismic business.The fall in the Baker Hughes stock price led to several lawsuits by law firms representing investors who contended that they had been misled by the company.Mr. Foster said that at current oil and natural gas prices, Baker Hughes's markets should improve.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/10/business/company-news-baker-hughes-says-accounting-errors-will-be-costly.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES SAYS ACCOUNTING ERRORS WILL BE COSTLY<date>Published: December 10, 1999</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. shares fell 15 percent yesterday after the company said accounting discrepancies at its Inteq drilling technology unit could cost it $40 million to $50 million before taxes. Baker Hughes, the No. 3 oil-field services company, said the accounting errors led it to postpone a $200 million bond sale. The company had planned to use the proceeds to refinance debt and pay for a ship used for undersea oil exploration. Earnings from earlier quarters may have to be restated, Baker Hughes said. The company, which is based in Houston, did not say which quarters would be affected. Baker Hughes shares fell $3.25, to $19.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/03/business/company-news-shares-of-baker-hughes-fall-7.5-after-profit-warning.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; SHARES OF BAKER HUGHES FALL 7.5% AFTER PROFIT WARNING<date>Published: December 03, 1999</date><text>The shares of Baker Hughes Inc., the No. 3 United States oil field company, fell 7.5 percent yesterday, a day after it warned it might have a small fourth-quarter loss because of lagging demand for some services. The company also said it had taken a $130 million pretax charge related to its seismic business, which uses sound waves to map geological formations. Its shares fell $2, to $24.50. Analysts surveyed by the First Call Corporation had expected Baker to earn 4 cents a share. The company earned 3 cents in the third quarter. Baker did not specify how big a loss it could report.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/30/business/company-news-unitrin-continuing-to-cut-its-stake-in-baker-hughes.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; UNITRIN CONTINUING TO CUT ITS STAKE IN BAKER HUGHES<date>Published: October 30, 1999</date><text>Unitrin Inc., an insurance and consumer finance company, sold shares of Baker Hughes Inc. for about $85 million, further cutting its stake in the third-largest United States oilfield service company to just under 5 percent. Chicago-based Unitrin said it sold 2.8 million shares at an average price of $30.22 between Sept. 10 and this Wednesday, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. In September, Unitrin reported it had trimmed its stake to 5.8 percent and intended to sell more. The recent move cut Unitrin and two unidentified Unitrin subsidiaries' total stake in Houston-based Baker by to 16.4 million, or a 4.98 percent holding. Shares of Baker have risen about 57 percent this year but have fallen in recent weeks. Shares of Baker gained 31.25 cents yesterday, to $27.9375.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/02/business/more-layoffs-at-baker-hughes.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">More Layoffs At Baker Hughes<date>Published: February 02, 1999</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., which slashed more than 4,000 jobs last year, says it will lay off another 2,450 employees by the end of the first quarter to cut costs in response to depressed energy prices.Baker Hughes, an oil services company based in Houston, also announced today that its fourth-quarter earnings had plunged to $6.1 million, from $114 million in the fourth quarter of 1997.Baker Hughes had reduced its work force to 32,250 people by the end of 1998, from a peak of 36,500 employees in the second quarter of last year. The number of employees will be further reduced to 29,800 by March 31.With oil prices at their lowest point in more than a decade, oil service and oilfield equipment companies have been forced to cut back as drilling activity slows. The United States rig count, announced weekly by Baker Hughes, fell to an all-time low of 562 last week.Baker Hughes's businesses include seismic imaging of fields, evaluation of underground formations, steerable drilling, oilfield and refining chemicals, drill bits and other tools and services.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/01/26/business/number-of-oil-rigs-down.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Number of Oil Rigs Down<date>Published: January 26, 1999</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., the third-largest United States oilfield services company, said the number of rigs drilling for oil and natural gas in the United States had fallen to the lowest level since 1947. The count has fallen for months as companies cut exploration spending because of dropping oil and gas prices. There were 588 rigs operating in the United States last week, down from 996 last year, the Houston-based Baker Hughes said. The previous low was 596, on June 12, 1992. Baker Hughes's weekly report counts inland and offshore rigs actively drilling to find or develop oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/11/business/baker-hughes-likely-to-buy-western-atlas.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Baker Hughes Likely to Buy Western Atlas<date>Published: May 11, 1998</date><text>Baker Hughes is close to reaching agreement to buy Western Atlas Inc. for about $5 billion in stock, according to people close to the transaction, giving it services to compete better with bigger oilfield companies.A deal could be announced as early as today that would value Western at more than $90 a share, based on the company's closing stock price Friday. That would be 10 percent or more above the current share price; Western gained $1.625 on Friday, to close at $81.375, while Baker Hughes shares slipped 12.5 cents, to $41.125.As part of the deal, Baker Hughes would also assume almost $700 million in Western Atlas debt.Western specializes in finding oil by mapping geological formations with sound waves, and using wires to manipulate tools and gauges in the thin confines of oil and natural gas wells. Baker needs those businesses to win customers from the industry leaders, Schlumberger and Halliburton.''Baker Hughes doesn't have divisions that provide those services,'' said John Lovoi, an analyst with Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''It is the major difference separating them from Schlumberger and Halliburton.''Companies that can do everything from providing the seismic data used to map potential exploration sites to drilling the well and pumping out the oil and natural gas are winning more contracts than smaller oil-services providers.While Baker was one of the first companies to establish a division offering integrated services to its drilling customers, it needs partners to compete for the biggest contracts. Western's operations would allow it to seek that business alone.Baker now sells customers the drill bits, oilfield chemicals and well pumps they need after choosing a site to drill. With a seismic business, Baker could get contracts to help start the search for oil, as well.The boards of Western Atlas and Baker Hughes are expected to name Baker's chairman, Max Lukens, to run the new company, the people close to the talks said.Top executives at Western Atlas were in meetings yesterday and did not return telephone calls for comment. Baker executives also could not be reached yesterday.The purchase of Western would follow several recent transactions in the oilfield-services industry.Halliburton said in February that it would buy Dresser Industries for $8.9 billion, which will make it the largest oil-services company in the world based on annual revenue. Schlumberger is now the largest, with annual revenue of more than $10.6 billion.Buying Western would give Houston-based Baker, third largest in the industry, more than $4.7 billion in annual revenue.On March 4, EVI Inc. agreed to buy Weatherford Enterra Inc. for $2.6 billion in stock and assumed debt, marrying the biggest maker of oil-drilling pipe with the largest pipe distributor.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/04/business/company-news-baker-hughes-agrees-to-acquire-assets-of-bit-company.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES AGREES TO ACQUIRE ASSETS OF BIT COMPANY<date>Published: March 04, 1998</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. agreed yesterday to acquire the assets of the Western Rock Bit Company, a privately held Canadian bit distributor, for $30.8 million. Baker Hughes, based in Houston, provides products and services for the oil, gas and process industries. Western Rock, based in Calgary, Alberta, has been the exclusive licensee and Canadian bit distributor for Baker Hughes's Hughes Christensen unit. Western Rock will be operated as a separate division of the Hughes Christensen Company, which supplies roller cone and drill bits, Baker Hughes said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/18/business/drilling-rig-count-up-13.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rig Count Up 13<date>Published: October 18, 1997</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide jumped by 13, to 987, this week, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 845 rigs operating in the United States in the week last year. A total of 579 were exploring for natural gas and 404 for oil. Four were listed as miscellaneous. The count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/08/16/business/the-rig-count-rises-by-12.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">The Rig Count Rises by 12<date>Published: August 16, 1997</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States rose to 999 this week, up 12 from the previous week, Baker Hughes Inc. said yesterday. There were 805 rigs at work a year earlier. A total of 417 rigs were exploring for crude oil this week, down 12 from the previous week; rigs searching for gas rose 25, to 580, while the number of miscellaneous projects now stands at 2, down one. The weekly count reflects rigs exploring for, but not producing, oil and gas.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/28/business/rig-count-is-unchanged.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Is Unchanged<date>Published: June 28, 1997</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States was 966 this week, unchanged from the previous week, Baker Hughes Inc. said yesterday. This week's figure is 189 more than the count a year earlier, Baker Hughes said. The number of rigs drilling on land fell 4, to 820, while rigs working offshore rose 5, to 122. The number of rigs active in inland waters dipped 1, to 24. The count reflects rigs exploring for, not producing, oil and gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/31/business/rig-count-climbs-by-13.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Climbs by 13<date>Published: May 31, 1997</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide jumped by 13 this week, to 961, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 765 rigs operating in the United States a year ago. Of the rigs running this week, 562 were exploring for natural gas, 395 for oil and 4 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count is the number of rigs actively exploring for, not producing, oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/24/business/rig-count-jumps-by-31.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Jumps by 31<date>Published: May 24, 1997</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States stood at 948 yesterday, up 31 from the previous week and 173 above the total of 775 a year earlier, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. A total of 387 rigs were exploring for crude oil, up 19 from last week. The number of rigs searching for gas rose by 12, to 557, while the number of miscellaneous drilling projects remained at 4. The rig count reflects the number exploring for oil and gas.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/10/business/rig-count-rises-by-32.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises by 32<date>Published: May 10, 1997</date><text>The number of drilling rigs searching for oil and gas nationwide jumped by 32 this week, to 913, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 772 rigs operating a year earlier. Of the rigs that were in operation this week, 535 were exploring for natural gas, 374 for oil and 4 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/18/business/baker-hughes-to-acquire-drilex-international.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">BAKER HUGHES TO ACQUIRE DRILEX INTERNATIONAL<date>Published: April 18, 1997</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Drilex International Inc., a provider of drilling products and services, for as much as $109 million in stock. Baker Hughes said that it would pay either $15 or $16 for each outstanding share of Drilex, based in Houston, depending on Drilex's financial performance in the coming months. Drilex stock gained 75 cents, to $14.125 a share in Nasdaq trading. Baker Hughes shares slipped 50 cents, to $35.375, on the New York Stock Exchange. In 1996, Drilex International earned $3 million, or 53 cents a share, on revenue of $76 million. Baker Hughes is also an oil services company based in Houston.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/15/business/rig-count-is-up-by-3.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Is Up by 3<date>Published: March 15, 1997</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide increased by 3 this week, to 885, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 693 rigs operating in the United States in the corresponding week last year. Of the rigs running this week, 517 were exploring for natural gas, 366 for oil and 2 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count is the number of rigs actively exploring for, not producing, oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/27/business/baker-hughes-to-buy-petrolite-for-693-million-in-stock.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">BAKER HUGHES TO BUY PETROLITE FOR $693 MILLION IN STOCK<date>Published: February 27, 1997</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the Petrolite Corporation, a specialty chemicals company, for $693 million in stock. The offer values Petrolite's stock at $61 a share. Baker Hughes provides services to the petroleum industry and also makes specialty chemicals for water treatment. Petrolite, which is based in St. Louis, makes chemicals used in the petroleum industry. It has 11.36 million shares outstanding. In the fiscal year ended Oct. 31, Petrolite had sales of $361 million, down from $364.8 million a year earlier. Petrolite shares rose $10.375, or 21.6 percent, to $58.375. Shares of Baker Hughes were unchanged at $35.50.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/22/business/drilling-rig-count-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rig Count Up<date>Published: February 22, 1997</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States stood at 863 yesterday, up three from the prior week and 158 above the total a year ago of 705, according to Baker Hughes Inc. The number of rigs drilling on land fell by one, to 731, while rigs working offshore remained at 106. The number of rigs active in inland waters was up five at 26. The weekly rig count reflects the number of rigs exploring for oil and gas, not those producing oil and gas.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/30/business/rig-count-down-by-7.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Down by 7<date>Published: December 30, 1996</date><text>A total of 353 rigs were exploring for crude oil last week, down 7 from the previous week, according to the latest report from Baker Hughes Inc. The number of rigs that were searching for gas last week remained unchanged at 496, while the number of miscellaneous drilling projects remained at 2.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/26/business/rig-count-increases-by-8.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Increases by 8<date>Published: October 26, 1996</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States stood at 853 yesterday, up 8 from the prior week and 92 above the total a year earlier, according to Baker Hughes Inc.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/07/business/rig-count-drops-slightly.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Drops Slightly<date>Published: October 07, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by three last week, to 819, Baker Hughes Inc. said. There were 754 rigs operating in the United States a year earlier. Of the rigs running last week, 503 were exploring for natural gas and 311 for oil. Five rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/31/business/rig-count-drops-by-16.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Drops by 16<date>Published: August 31, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 16 this week, to 812, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 772 rigs operating in the United States in the corresponding week last year. Of the rigs running this week, 493 were exploring for natural gas and 288 for oil; 31 rigs were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/19/business/rig-count-is-down-by-4.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Is Down by 4<date>Published: August 19, 1996</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas fell to 805 last week, from 809 the previous week, the oilfield services company Baker Hughes Inc. said yesterday. A year ago, 744 rigs were exploring. The number of rigs drilling on land fell to 677 from 680, while rigs working offshore rose to 110 from 105. The number of rigs active in inland waters fell to 18 from 24. The weekly rig count reflects the number of rigs exploring for, but not those producing, oil and gas.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/10/business/rig-count-up-by-8-to-809.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 8, to 809<date>Published: August 10, 1996</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said today that the rig count, a measure of drilling activity, rose by 8 this week, to 809. Rigs drilling for oil rose by 8, to 305; those seeking natural gas were unchanged at 483 and those seeking either oil or gas were unchanged at 21.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/08/business/more-rigs-explore-in-us.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">More Rigs Explore in U.S.<date>Published: July 08, 1996</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States stood at 782 last week, up by 5 from the previous week and by 68 from a year ago, according to Baker Hughes Inc. The number of rigs drilling on land rose by 10, to 656, while the number of rigs working offshore fell by 5, to 107. The number of rigs active in inland waters remained at 19.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/15/business/drilling-rig-count-is-down.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rig Count Is Down<date>Published: June 15, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 8 this week, to 773, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.There were 670 rigs operating in the United States during the corresponding week last year. Of the rigs in operation this week, 464 were exploring for natural gas and 304 for oil; 5 rigs were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/01/business/rig-count-drops-by-10.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Drops by 10<date>Published: June 01, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 10 this week, to 765, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 677 rigs operating in the United States a year ago. Of the rigs running this week, 472 were exploring for natural gas and 288 for oil; 5 rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/28/business/rig-count-rises-by-18.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises by 18<date>Published: May 28, 1996</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States stood at 775 on Friday, up 18 from the previous week and 85 above the total a year ago of 690, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. The number of rigs drilling on land rose by 25, to 645, while rigs working offshore fell by 4, to 114. The number of rigs active in inland waters fell by 3, to 16.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/18/business/rig-count-down-by-15.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Down by 15<date>Published: May 18, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 15 this week, to 757, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 673 rigs operating in the United States during the corresponding week last year. Of the rigs running this week, 463 were exploring for natural gas and 285 for oil. Nine rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/11/business/rig-count-jumps-by-23.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Jumps by 23<date>Published: May 11, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide rose by 23 this week, to 772, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 689 rigs operating in the United States a year ago. Of the rigs running this week, 474 were exploring for natural gas and 290 for oil.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/02/business/rig-count-rises-by-2.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises by 2<date>Published: March 02, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States jumped by 2 this week, to 707, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 684 rigs operating nationwide during the comparable week a year earlier. Of the rigs running this week, 436 were exploring for natural gas and 265 for oil. Six rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/17/business/rig-count-up-to-707.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up to 707<date>Published: February 17, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States jumped by 12 this week, to 707, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 724 rigs operating nationwide a year ago. Of the rigs running this week, 417 were exploring for natural gas and 285 for oil. Five rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil or natural gas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/12/business/rig-count-up-by-2.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 2<date>Published: February 12, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States increased by two last week, to 695, Baker Hughes Inc. said. There were 706 rigs operating nationwide a year ago. Of the rigs running last week, 407 were exploring for natural gas and 281 for oil. Seven rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/01/29/business/rig-count-down-by-13.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Down by 13<date>Published: January 29, 1996</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States dropped by 13 last week to 703, Baker Hughes Inc. said. During the corresponding week a year ago, there were 731 rigs operating nationwide. Of the rigs running last week, 404 were exploring for natural gas and 291 for oil.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/25/business/rig-count-drops-by-5.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Drops by 5<date>Published: November 25, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States dropped by five this week, to 774, Baker Hughes Inc. said. In the corresponding week a year ago, there were 842 rigs operating nationwide. Because of Thanksgiving, this week's count was through Wednesday instead of Friday. Of the rigs running this week, 436 were exploring for natural gas and 327 for oil. Eleven rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rigs in the count are those actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/20/business/rig-count-up-by-10.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 10<date>Published: November 20, 1995</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas rose to 779 last week, up 10 from the previous week but below the total of 839 a year earlier, according to Baker Hughes Inc. The number of rigs drilling on land fell by 1, to 649, while rigs working offshore rose by 7, to 107, the oilfield services company reported. The number of rigs active in inland waters rose by 4, to 23. The weekly count reflects the number of rigs exploring for, not those producing, oil and gas.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/10/28/business/rig-count-is-down.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Is Down<date>Published: October 28, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States dropped by 4 this week, to 761, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, there were 813 rigs operating nationwide. Of the rigs running this week, 417 were exploring for natural gas and 331 for oil.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/16/business/executive-changes-237895.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Executive Changes<date>Published: September 16, 1995</date><text>BAKER HUGHES INC., Houston, named Max L. Lukens president and to the newly created position of chief operating officer. Mr. Lukens succeeds James D. Woods as president; he will continue as chairman and chief executive.KAMAN CORP., Bloomfield, Conn., said Harvey S. Levenson, the president and chief operating officer, will retire at the end of the year.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/02/business/rig-count-rises-by-9.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises by 9<date>Published: September 02, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States increased by 9 this week, to 772, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, there were 784 rigs operating nationwide. Of the rigs running this week, 421 were exploring for natural gas and 330 for oil. Twenty-one rigs were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/26/business/rig-count-is-up-19.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Is Up 19<date>Published: August 26, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the United States increased by 19 this week, to 763, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. In the corresponding week a year ago, there were 768 rigs operating nationwide. Of the rigs running this week, 410 were exploring for natural gas and 333 for oil. Twenty rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/12/business/rig-count-rises-to-739.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises to 739<date>Published: August 12, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide rose by 7 this week to 739, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 753 rigs operating during the corresponding week a year ago. Of the rigs running this week, 394 were exploring for natural gas and 327 for oil. Eighteen rigs were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/31/business/rig-count-climbs-by-20.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Climbs by 20<date>Published: July 31, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide increased by 20 last week, to 739, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. Of the total, 417 rigs were exploring for natural gas, 301 were exploring for oil and 21 were listed as miscellaneous. There were 771 rigs operating in the corresponding week a year earlier.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/08/business/48-more-oil-and-gas-rigs.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">48 More Oil and Gas Rigs<date>Published: July 08, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide increased by 48 this week, to 714, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. There were 768 rigs operating in the corresponding week last year. Of the rigs running this week, 390 were exploring for natural gas and 299 for oil.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/19/business/rig-count-falls-by-4.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Falls by 4<date>Published: June 19, 1995</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said last week that the United States rig count fell 4 for the week, to 670. Rigs drilling for oil rose 4, to 307, while those drilling for natural gas fell 10, to 340. The number drilling for either commodity was up 2, to 23. This week's active rig total was about 13 percent lower than a year ago, when 769 rigs were drilling. In 1994, the count hit a high of 842 in November and a low of 697 in May.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/03/business/rig-count-drops-by-13.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Drops by 13<date>Published: June 03, 1995</date><text>The weekly count of rigs drilling for oil and natural gas fell 13, to 677, in the week that ended today, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. The number of rigs drilling for natural gas fell 5, to 343. Rigs drilling for oil dropped 8, to 325, and the number of rigs drilling for either commodity was unchanged at 17.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/26/business/company-news-sonat-to-sell-baker-hughes-shares-at-a-loss.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; SONAT TO SELL BAKER HUGHES SHARES AT A LOSS<date>Published: May 26, 1995</date><text>Sonat Inc. said yesterday that it would sell preferred stock back to Baker Hughes Inc. for $167 million, taking a loss of $8 million on the sale. Sonat, a gas pipeline and exploration company based in Birmingham, Ala., said it would sell back to Baker Hughes four million shares of preferred stock it received as part of the April 1992 sale of Sonat's Teleco Oilfield Services Unit. Sonat will report an after-tax loss of $8 million, or around 9 cents a share, on the sale of the stock, which has a face value of $200 million and was carried on Sonat's books for $180 million. The preferred stock pays a 6 percent dividend and is convertible into common shares of Baker Hughes for $32.50 a share. Sonat said it was selling the stock to help pay off $700 million in debt and to raise money for exploration and drilling.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/08/business/drilling-rigs-up-by-21.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rigs Up by 21<date>Published: April 08, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide jumped by 21 this week to 669, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago 709 rigs were running. Of the rigs running this week, 347 were exploring for natural gas, 310 for oil and 12 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/03/25/business/rig-count-down-by-15.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Down by 15<date>Published: March 25, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 15 this week, to 652, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, the number of rigs running was 725. Of the rigs running this week, 327 were exploring for natural gas, 313 for oil and 12 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/02/21/business/drilling-rigs-increase.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rigs Increase<date>Published: February 21, 1995</date><text>The number of rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States rose by 18 last week, to 724, Baker Hughes Inc. said. A year ago the total was 752. A total of 336 rigs were exploring for crude oil, up 15 from the previous week. The number of rigs searching for gas rose by one, to 376.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/02/04/business/drilling-rigs-drop.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rigs Drop<date>Published: February 04, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 7 this week to 724, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, the number of rigs running was 752.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/01/07/business/fewer-rigs-drilling.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Fewer Rigs Drilling<date>Published: January 07, 1995</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide dropped by 25 this week, to 766, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago at this time the count was 807. Of the rigs running this week, 425 were exploring for natural gas, 328 for oil and 13 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/27/business/rigs-rise-by-6-to-813.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rigs Rise by 6, to 813<date>Published: December 27, 1994</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide last week rose by 6, to 813, Baker Hughes Inc. said. Despite the gain, the total still lagged behind last year's tally at this time of 843. Of the rigs running last week, 448 were exploring for natural gas, 351 for oil and 14 were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/20/business/rig-count-falls.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Falls<date>Published: December 20, 1994</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide fell by 34 last week, to 807, according to Baker Hughes Inc. Of the rigs running for the week that ended last Friday, 442 were exploring for natural gas, 350 for oil and 15 were listed as miscellaneous, Baker Hughes said. The rig tally was 833 at this time last year.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/12/business/rig-count-up-by-14.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 14<date>Published: December 12, 1994</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating nationwide last week was up by 14, to 841, Baker Hughes Inc. said. The count was 868 at the corresponding time last year. Of the rigs running, 465 were exploring for natural gas, 361 for oil and 15 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/10/03/business/drilling-activity-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Activity Up<date>Published: October 03, 1994</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said last week that its rig count, a measure of oil and natural gas activity in the United States, rose by 2 last week, to 838. A year ago, 856 rigs were drilling. The number of rigs drilling for oil last week rose 9, to 348, while the number for gas drilling was down 8, to 476. Rigs not designated in either category rose 1, to 14.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/22/business/rig-count-rises-to-772.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises to 772<date>Published: August 22, 1994</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the nation last week rose by 19, to 772, Baker Hughes Inc. said on Friday. Last year at this time the rig count was 805. The rig count is the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/15/business/fewer-oil-and-gas-rigs.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Fewer Oil and Gas Rigs<date>Published: August 15, 1994</date><text>The number of oil and gas rigs operating in the nation dropped by 18 this week to 753, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. A year ago, the rig count was 786. Of the rigs running this week, 428 were exploring for natural gas, 311 for oil and 14 were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/16/business/drilling-activity-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Activity Up<date>Published: July 16, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide rose slightly, by 5, this week, to 773, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The total a year ago was 720. Of the rigs running this week, 421 were exploring for natural gas, 337 for oil and 15 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/11/business/rig-count-up-by-2.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 2<date>Published: July 11, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide rose by two last week, to 768, according to Baker Hughes Inc. The total a year earlier was 713. Of the rigs running last week, 412 were exploring for natural gas, 340 for oil and 16 were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/02/business/rig-count-up-5-to-766.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up 5, to 766<date>Published: July 02, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide rose by five this week, to 766, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago this time the count was 732. Of the rigs running this week, 415 were exploring for natural gas and 333 for oil and 18 were listed as miscellaneous. Since 1940 the Houston-based Baker Hughes has kept track of the rig count, which represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/05/14/business/rig-count-up-3-to-722.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up 3, to 722<date>Published: May 14, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide rose by three this week, to 722, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, the total was 619. Of the rigs running this week, 388 were exploring for natural gas, 319 for oil and 15 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/05/02/business/rig-count-down-by-2.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Down by 2<date>Published: May 02, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide slipped by 2 last week, to 730, according to Baker Hughes Inc.. A year ago, the count stood at 609. Of the rigs running last week, 393 were exploring for natural gas, 326 for oil and 11 were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/12/business/weekly-rig-count-off-23.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Weekly Rig Count Off 23<date>Published: April 12, 1994</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs across the nation was down 23 last week, to 709, according to Baker Hughes Inc. In the corresponding week last year, 615 rigs were working. Of the rigs now running, 390 were exploring for natural gas, 309 for oil and 10 were listed as miscellaneous.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/25/business/company-news-baker-hughes-says-it-will-sell-a-subsidiary.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAKER HUGHES SAYS IT WILL SELL A SUBSIDIARY<date>Published: March 25, 1994</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc., based in Houston, said yesterday that it intended to sell its Envirotech Pumpsystems subsidiary as part of a plan to divest itself of noncore assets. The subsidiary, which had revenue of about $220 million in its 1993 fiscal year, provides specialized pumps to the mining and petrochemical industries and to local governments. Earlier this month, Baker Hughes completed the sale of its Envirotech Measurements and Controls group to the Thermo Electron Corporation of Waltham, Mass., for $134 million.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/19/business/company-news-rig-count-up-by-10.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; Rig Count Up by 10<date>Published: March 19, 1994</date><text>The nation's working oil and gas rig count rose by 10 this week, to 743, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. This week's count surpassed the total of 614 working rigs posted a year ago this week. Of the rigs running this week, 404 were exploring for natural gas, 330 for oil and 9 were listed as miscellaneous. The rig count represents the number of rigs actively exploring for oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/02/04/business/company-news-thermo-electron-units-buying-baker-hughes-businesses.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; THERMO ELECTRON UNITS BUYING BAKER HUGHES BUSINESSES<date>Published: February 04, 1994</date><text>The Thermo Electron Corporation of Waltham, Mass., said yesterday that two of its publicly traded subsidiaries would buy six businesses from Baker Hughes Inc. of Houston for about $134 million. Thermo Instrument Systems Inc., which makes environmental monitoring instruments, will buy Environtech Controls, Noran Instruments, TN Technologies and Tremetrics for about $93 million. The businesses have combined annual sales of $129 million. Thermedics Inc., a maker of medical products and electronic detection equipment, will buy Ramsey Technologies and Epsilon Industrial for about $41 million. Ramsey makes equipment for inspecting bulk materials and packaged goods, and Epsilon designs products for measuring the moisture content in materials. The two companies had combined sales of $59 million in the year ended in September.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/02/01/business/company-news-thermo-electron-units-to-buy-6-businesses.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; THERMO ELECTRON UNITS TO BUY 6 BUSINESSES<date>Published: February 01, 1994</date><text>The Thermo Electron Corporation of Waltham, Mass., said yesterday that two of its publicly traded subsidiaries would buy six businesses from the Houston-based Baker Hughes Inc. for about $134 million. All six are part of Baker's Envirotech Measurements and Controls group. Under the agreements, Thermo Instrument Systems Inc., which is 81 percent-owned by Thermo Electron, will buy Environtech Controls, Noran Instruments, TN Technologies and Tremetrics for about $93 million. In addition, Thermedics Inc., which is 52 percent owned by Thermo Electron, will buy Ramsey Technologies and Epsilon Industrial for about $41 million.Shares of Thermo Electron were up 37.5 cents, at $43.875, on the New York Stock Exchange; Baker was up 50 cents, at $20.125.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/02/business/drilling-rig-count-dips.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rig Count Dips<date>Published: October 02, 1993</date><text>The nation's oil and gas count dropped by 10 this week, to 856, Baker Hughes Inc. said today.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/09/13/business/rig-count-edges-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Edges Up<date>Published: September 13, 1993</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. says its count of rigs drilling for petroleum in the United States rose by one, to 835, last week. The oil service company's widely watched measure of oil and natural gas exploration is 21.5 percent above the count a year ago, when 687 rigs were drilling.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/09/04/business/oil-rig-count-rise.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Oil Rig Count Rise<date>Published: September 04, 1993</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc.'s count of active rigs drilling petroleum wells in the United States rose 12 this week, to 834. The oil service company's widely watched measure of oil and natural gas exploration is 18 percent above the count a year earlier of 706 rigs. Higher natural gas prices have promoted more gas drilling, Baker Hughes said. Drilling rig counts reflect exploration and production companies' expectations of how petroleum prices will perform.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/08/21/business/rig-count-rises-to-805.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises to 805<date>Published: August 21, 1993</date><text>The nation's rig count, led by gains in natural gas exploration, rose by 19 this week, to 805, Baker Hughes Inc. said today.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/08/17/business/drilling-rig-count-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Rig Count Up<date>Published: August 17, 1993</date><text>The number of rigs drilling for oil and natural gas in the United States rose by 10 last week, to 786, according to Baker Hughes Inc. A year earlier, there were 678 rigs exploring for oil and gas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/07/13/business/dip-in-oil-drilling.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Dip in Oil Drilling<date>Published: July 13, 1993</date><text>After nearly three months of growth, the nation's oil and gas rig count decreased by 19 last week, to 713, Baker Hughes Inc. has reported. A year ago, the number of working rigs stood at 667. The rig count measures domestic drilling activity. The total is the number of rigs actively exploring for -- not producing -- oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/05/31/business/more-rigs-are-drilling.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">More Rigs Are Drilling<date>Published: May 31, 1993</date><text>The number of drilling rigs exploring for oil and natural gas in the United States rose 30, to 671, last week, the strongest weekly gain since November, Baker Hughes Inc. reported. The company said Friday that the count was also above that of the corresponding period a year earlier, when 629 rigs were drilling for oil and gas.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/05/15/business/rig-count-up-2-to-619.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up 2, to 619<date>Published: May 15, 1993</date><text>The nation's rig count increased by two this week, to a total of 619, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. A year ago, the tally stood at 652. The count is the widely watched index of domestic drilling activity. The total represents the number of rigs actively exploring for -- not producing -- oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/04/03/business/oil-drilling-is-up-again.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Oil Drilling Is Up Again<date>Published: April 03, 1993</date><text>The nation's rig count rose for a third straight week, climbing by 17, to 627, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The count climbed by 14 rigs in each of the two previous weeks. A year ago, the tally stood at 658. The rig count is the number of rigs actively exploring for -- not producing -- oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/03/30/business/number-of-rigs-falls.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Number of Rigs Falls<date>Published: March 30, 1993</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs in the United States fell by four last week, to 610, according to Baker Hughes Inc. A year earlier, the count stood at 639. The rig count is a widely watched index of domestic drilling activity.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/03/20/business/rig-count-rises.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Rises<date>Published: March 20, 1993</date><text>The number of active oil and gas drilling rigs in the United States rose by 14 in the week ended today, to 614, from the previous week, but it was below the level of 643 in the comparable week a year ago, according to Baker Hughes Inc.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/02/15/business/oil-and-gas-rigs-drop.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Oil and Gas Rigs Drop<date>Published: February 15, 1993</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs nationwide has dropped for the fifth straight week, falling by 22 rigs, to 698. Baker Hughes Inc., which keeps track of oil and gas rigs, said Friday that the count remained ahead of the 661 posted a year ago.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/01/business/drilling-activity-slips.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling Activity Slips<date>Published: January 01, 1993</date><text>The number of active drilling rigs in the United States slipped by 6 during the latest week, dropping to 922, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. Despite the decline, the weekly count continued a more than two-month trend of exceeding the total for the corresponding week a year earlier. Last year at this time the count stood at 764, Baker Hughes said. The count peaked at 4,500 in December 1981 during the oil boom.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/12/25/business/company-news-drilling-rigs-show-decline.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; Drilling Rigs Show Decline<date>Published: December 25, 1992</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said today that there were 928 active United States oil and gas drilling rigs during the week ended Wednesday, down seven from the week earlier.The number of rigs fell for the first time in 12 weeks, starting the seasonal decline in oil and gas exploration, analysts said. A year ago, 770 rigs were drilling. Rig counts usually dip starting in mid-December, when winter weather deters drilling in North America.Gas rigs, however, have outnumbered oil rigs every week but one since Aug. 24. Companies trying to take advantage of the Section 29 tax incentive to drill for natural gas raised the gas rig count by 118 percent.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/12/19/business/rig-count-up-by-5.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Up by 5<date>Published: December 19, 1992</date><text>The nation's rig count continued a seasonal surge, increasing by 5 this week to 935, Baker Hughes Inc. officials said today. Last year at this time the count stood at 797. The tally represents the number of rigs actively exploring for -- not producing -- oil and natural gas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/09/05/business/more-oil-and-gas-rigs.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">More Oil and Gas Rigs<date>Published: September 05, 1992</date><text>Led by an increase in Oklahoma because of improved weather there, the number of working oil and gas rigs in the United States rose 38 this week to 706, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The count, which fell by 21 last week, in part because Hurricane Andrew halted most activity in the Gulf of Mexico, still lagged behind the total of 798 a year earlier, according to the Houston-based maker of drilling tools.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/29/business/rig-count-declines.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Rig Count Declines<date>Published: August 29, 1992</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs in the United States dropped by 21 this week, to 668, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The count lagged behind last year's total of 799 rigs, the Houston toolmaker said. Earlier this summer, the rig count dropped to a record low of 596. Last week, the tally climbed by 11, to 689.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/08/business/drilling-rig-count-up.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Drilling-Rig Count Up<date>Published: August 08, 1992</date><text>Helped by modest gains in several states, the number of working oil and gas rigs in the nation rose by 19 this week to total 709, Baker Hughes Inc. said today. The count continued a slow recovery after dropping to a record low of 596 rigs earlier this summer, but the tally still trailed last year's total of 796, the Houston toolmaker said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/07/18/business/company-news-drilling-rigs-up-by-22.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">COMPANY NEWS; Drilling Rigs Up by 22<date>Published: July 18, 1992</date><text>Baker Hughes Inc. said today that the number of active rigs in the United States rose by 22, to 689. The latest gain follows an increase of 19 rigs in the week ending July 10. After four consecutive declines this spring, the rig count hit 596 on June 15, its lowest point since the drilling-services company began tracking the number of active rigs in 1940.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/06/13/business/oil-drilling-at-a-low.html?ref=bakerhughesinc">Oil Drilling at a Low<date>Published: June 13, 1992</date><text>The number of working oil and gas rigs in the nation fell to another record low in the latest week, Baker Hughes Inc. reported today. The count was 596 rigs, a loss of 14 from the figure a week ago.</text></article></page></root>
