<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Bank of New York"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DB1539F932A25753C1A9679D8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">DealBook Online<date>Published: October 11, 2011</date><text>PAINFUL LOSS Tired of incessant leaks to the media about its poor performance, Paulson &amp; Company, the hedge fund started by the billionaire John A. Paulson, below, decided a few weeks ago to amend its reporting policies to make it harder to obtain performance data. But the changes failed to obscure this painful fact: One of his largest funds is down 47 percent through September, a loss that would require returns of almost 100 percent to surmount, according to investors in the fund. AZAM AHMED NEW INTERPRETATION Groupon has made it clear that it doesn't want to act like the usual boring business. On Monday, the online coupon giant proved that yet again, putting a new spin on transparency. The company wrote in a blog post that it had begun deliberately undercounting the number of times a deal had been purchased by consumers, by anywhere from half a percentage point to about 19.5 percent. As the company cheekily wrote in its post: ''We're blogging about it to be transparent about our lack of transparency.'' MICHAEL J. de la MERCED 'BEST' CLAIMS The Justice Department and the New York attorney general, Eric T. Schneiderman, filed separate civil charges last week against Bank of New York Mellon, accusing it of defrauding customers of its foreign exchange services. According to White Collar Watch, the cases raise sticky questions about when marketing claims cross the imperceptible line from puffery to fraud. PETER J. HENNING BUYING A RIVAL Superior Energy Services, an oil field services company based in New Orleans, agreed to buy a competitor, Complete Production Services, for about $2.7 billion. Under the terms of the agreement, investors in Complete, based in Houston, will receive 0.945 of Superior common stock and $7 in cash. That is about 29 percent above Complete's two-month average stock price. MARK SCOTT nytimes.com/dealbook PHOTO GRAPHIC</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/10/10/the-difference-between-puffery-and-fraud/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">The Difference Between Puffery and Fraud<date>October 10, 2011, 2:43 pm</date><text>Richard Drew/Associated PressThe Bank of New York Mellon building in Manhattan. The Justice Department and the New York attorney general, Eric T. Schneiderman, filed separate civil charges last week against Bank of New York Mellon, accusing it of defrauding customers of its foreign exchange services. The cases raise sticky questions about when marketing claims cross the imperceptible line from puffery to fraud. The bank used phrases like “best execution” and “most competitive rates” in promoting its services, while the complaints assert it overcharged a number of pension funds and governments by secretly taking advantage of spreads in the prices for foreign currencies to reap profits. Bank of New York Mellon has responded aggressively, taking out a full-page advertisement in The New York Times on Thursday, asserting that the “claims are flat out wrong and we will fight them in court.” Foreign exchange trading has been a consistent profit center for the bank, so it has a powerful incentive to litigate the case to protect an important part of its business. White Collar Watch View all posts Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links U.S. and New York Sue Bank of New York Mellon Over Foreign Exchange Fees The charges relate to Bank of New York Mellon’s “standing instruction” service, through which customers give an order to the bank to execute foreign exchange transactions related to trading in securities denominated in foreign currencies. Unlike a privately negotiated trade that would be much more cumbersome, the standing instruction service is an easy way for customers to have foreign exchange transactions completed because Bank of New York Mellon simply puts through the trade without needing any further authorization from the customer. The Justice Department’s complaint contends that the bank “consistently gives standing instruction clients virtually the worst rates of the day,” and the New York attorney general argues that it “flagrantly misrepresented” its practices by stating that it was using the “best rate of the day.” The federal suit asserts that Bank of New York Mellon violated the mail and wire fraud statutes, while the New York action alleges breaches of the Martin Act, the state’s broad securities fraud statute. Some of the allegedly false statements could be found on the bank’s Web site and in marketing brochures provided when an account was opened. In addition, the complaints assert that Bank of New York Mellon sought to obscure its pricing practices by not providing time-stamped trade confirmations to customers and gave misleading information when it received inquiries about the pricing of foreign exchange transactions. When words like “best” and “lowest” are used to promote a product or service, the law is unclear about how much a customer should take those with a grain of salt, or whether they can provide a basis for finding a fraud. Should a potential used-car buyer believe the signs at a dealership touting its prices as the “lowest” around and that the cars on its lot are the “best” available? To violate the mail or wire fraud statutes, a false statement must be “material,” which means it was capable of deceiving someone into acting in reliance on it. What has been described as “sales talk” or “mere puffery” in a commercial transaction is not considered to be material because the average listener would not be misled by the hype put forth by a seller. It is no defense that the victim was gullible, but the sophistication of the target audience can play into the determination whether Bank of New York Mellon’s statements promoting its foreign exchange service really were intended to mislead. Bank of New York Mellon is also accused of having claimed that the standing instruction service was “free,” but an argument can be made that customers understand that a financial firm does not really provide anything for free, even if there is no specific cost attached to it. And “best execution” does not necessarily mean the lowest possible spread in foreign exchange rates. There have been cases brought against brokers and investment advisers for not giving clients the best price available and taking advantage of spreads in prices to profit at their expense. But those cases involve a different relationship because a broker is required to protect the customer’s financial interests. Bank of New York Mellon did not have that kind of relationship with those who used its standing instruction service, instead dealing with them in more of an arms-length transaction typical of a seller and buyer, which does not entail any fiduciary obligation. The standing instruction service was offered as a convenient way for institutional investors to get foreign exchange transactions without having to deal with currency dealers directly, but it did not involve the bank in giving investment advice to clients. The Justice Department and New York attorney general cite internal Bank of New York Mellon e-mails that indicate the bank’s officers were aware that it was not giving the best possible deal to the standing instruction customers, and that the program depended on taking advantage of the spread in transactions by assigning less favorable transactions to its customers. Those e-mails could go a long way toward proving the claim that the bank misled customers to maintain a profitable line of business. The question whether Bank of New York Mellon crossed the line into fraud may explain why civil complaints were filed against it and not criminal charges, even though both cases allege the type of conduct more often seen in criminal prosecutions. The Justice Department need only establish its claims by the more favorable preponderance of the evidence standard, rather than proof beyond a reasonable doubt required in criminal cases. For Mr. Schneiderman, the Martin Act only requires that a defendant acted negligently in defrauding another, rather than intentionally, a fairly low threshold for a violation. The Justice Department bases its claim against Bank of New York Mellon on violations of the mail and wire fraud statutes, but filed its case under a law enacted in 1988, 12 U.S.C. § 1833a, which allows it to pursue a civil penalty for a violation. Congress passed the statute during the savings and loan crisis to provide another tool for pursuing bank fraud, and it authorizes a penalty of up to $1 million a day or the total amount of the improper gain realized from the fraud. The federal complaint asserts that Bank of New York Mellon’s alleged scheme dates back to 2000, so the potential civil penalty could total billions of dollars if the bank is found to have defrauded its customers. A corporate defendant in a criminal case can only be fined and not imprisoned, so the net effect of the civil penalty would be similar to the punishment in a criminal prosecution if the Justice Department wins its case. And the collateral consequences of a civil case would not be as severe because a criminal conviction might jeopardize Bank of New York Mellon’s ability to continue to do business with a number of clients who could be prohibited from dealing with a company convicted of fraud. I suspect the Justice Department is unwilling to risk the loss of jobs from another collapse like the one the accounting firm Arthur Andersen suffered a decade ago as a result of its participation in the Enron fraud. Bank of New York Mellon stated it plans “to fight these unwarranted allegations,” so the case could be a chance to clarify the line between fraud and puffery. The charges against the bank also should give other foreign exchange providers some concern about whether their own marketing claims could have crossed that line, wherever it might be. Peter J. Henning, who writes White Collar Watch for DealBook, is a professor at Wayne State University Law School.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/05/business/new-york-state-says-bank-of-new-york-mellon-cheated-pension-funds.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">U.S. and New York Sue Bank of New York Mellon Over Exchange Fees<date>Published: October 4, 2011</date><text>The New York attorney general and the United States attorney in Manhattan filed separate lawsuits on Tuesday against the Bank of New York Mellon, accusing it of cheating state and other pension funds nationwide out of foreign exchange fees over the last decade.In a civil lawsuit filed in state court, the attorney general, Eric T. Schneiderman, said that the Bank of New York Mellon had consistently overcharged customers for processing foreign currency transactions. He is seeking about $2 billion, which is the ostensible ill-gotten profits that the bank generated over the last decade. Preet S. Bharara, the United States attorney in Manhattan, filed a civil complaint in Federal District Court in Manhattan that also charges the Bank of New York Mellon with defrauding its customers in the foreign exchange markets. Whereas Mr. Schneiderman is seeking redress on behalf of state pension funds, Mr. Bharara is seeking hundreds of millions of dollars in penalties on behalf of the United States. “This suit seeks to impose not only appropriate civil penalties, but also comprehensive injunctive relief to ensure that Bank of New York’s alleged fraud stops now,” Mr. Bharara said. Among those affected by the bank’s actions were pension funds operated by the State University of New York and New York City retirees, as well as thousands of investment funds, including some run by Duke University and Walt Disney. In separate statements, Bank of New York Mellon vigorously denied any wrongdoing. It claimed that the United States attorney's accusations were based on "flawed analysis" of its role as a principal in the foreign exchange market, and said the attorney generals' lawsuit was an example of "prosecutorial overreach." The bank said it was confident that it had provided competitive and attractive foreign exchange rates to its customers. Still, bank officials recognize the impact that the drumbeat of bad publicity has on their brand. The bank's newly installed chairman and chief executive, Gerald L. Hassell, has said he will be pragmatic about resolving any suits. Mr. Schneiderman’s lawsuit charges that the bank guaranteed that customers would receive the most competitive or attractive rates available on any given trading day. In reality, the lawsuit says, the Bank of New York Mellon provided the opposite: the worst or nearly the worst of the rates available to the bank. Then it earned nearly $2 billion — or as much as 75 percent of its foreign exchange revenue — by pocketing the difference, the suit contends. The New York attorney general’s action comes after similar moves by authorities in California, Florida, Massachusetts and three other states that are looking into the foreign exchange practices of the Bank of New York Mellon and one of its main competitors, the State Street Corporation. The Securities and Exchange Commission and Justice Department are also in the middle of investigations, according to corporate filings from the banks. The inquiries began almost two years ago when a group of whistle-blowers made up of plaintiffs’ lawyers and Harry M. Markopolos, the financial investigator who first sounded the alarm about Bernard L. Madoff’s Ponzi scheme, sought out the New York state attorney general’s office to bring lawsuits against the bank. But by taking advantage of the powerful New York state securities law known as the Martin Act, Mr. Schneiderman has turned it into a national case. The lawsuit seeks to recover damages incurred not only by the New York pension funds, but also by dozens of government and private investors across the country. It is not the first time Mr. Schneiderman has squared off against the Bank of New York Mellon. He recently moved to block a proposed $8.5 million settlement involving the bank and the Bank of America over troubled loan pools issued by Countrywide Financial. The suit accuses the Bank of New York Mellon of fraud in its role as trustee overseeing the investment pools, a claim the bank has denied. Mr. Schneiderman has not shied away from fights with other big banks. In the continuing settlement talks with the nation’s largest mortgage servicers, Mr. Schneiderman stepped down from the lead committee of attorneys general after making it clear that he would not sign a broad release that would allow the banks to avoid liability for an array of issues. His office is now conducting its own investigation. Mr. Bharara brought his lawsuit against Bank of New York Mellon under the Financial Institutional Reform, Recovery and Enforcement Act, a law that gives federal prosecutors the right to seek civil penalties for banking-related violations. Congress passed the law in 1989 in the wake of the savings-and-loan crisis, giving the government a civil prosecutorial tool with a lower burden of proof than federal criminal statutes. This year, Mr. Bharara’s office used another law, the False Claims Act, to file a complaint against Deutsche Bank, claiming that one of its units had lied about the quality of government-backed mortgage loans it underwrote. Deutsche Bank has denied the claims.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/30/business/outsize-severance-continues-for-executives-even-after-failed-tenures.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Outsize Severance Continues for Executives, Even After Failed Tenures<date>Published: September 29, 2011</date><text>The golden goodbye has not gone away.Just last week, Léo Apotheker was shown the door after a tumultuous 11-month run atop Hewlett-Packard. His reward? $13.2 million in cash and stock severance, in addition to a sign-on package worth about $10 million, according to a corporate filing on Thursday. At the end of August, Robert P. Kelly was handed severance worth $17.2 million in cash and stock when he was ousted as chief executive of Bank of New York Mellon after clashing with board members and senior managers. A few days later, Carol A. Bartz took home nearly $10 million from Yahoo after being fired from the troubled search giant. A hallmark of the gilded era of just a few short years ago, the eye-popping severance package continues to thrive in spite of the measures put in place in the wake of the financial crisis to crack down on excessive pay. Critics have long complained about outsize compensation packages that dwarf ordinary workers’ paychecks, but they voice particular ire over pay-for-failure. Much of Wall Street and corporate America has shifted a bigger portion of pay into longer-term stock awards and established policies to claw back bonuses. And while fuller disclosure of exit packages several years ago has helped ratchet down the size of the biggest severance deals, efforts by shareholders and regulators to further restrict payouts have had less success. “We repeatedly see companies’ assets go out the door to reward failure,” said Scott Zdrazil, the director of corporate governance for Amalgamated Bank’s $11 billion Longview Fund, a labor-affiliated investment fund that sought to tighten the restrictions on severance plans at three oil companies last year. “Investors are frustrated that boards haven’t prevented such windfalls.” Several years ago, the Securities and Exchange Commission turned a brighter spotlight on severance deals by requiring companies to disclose the values of the contracts in regulatory filings. More recently, the Dodd-Frank financial reforms required that public companies include “say on pay” votes for shareholders to express opinions about compensation — including a separate vote for golden parachutes initiated by a merger or sale. Yet so far, few investors have gone to battle. Only 38 of the largest 3,000 companies had their executive pay plans voted down, according to Institutional Shareholder Services. Even then, the votes are nonbinding. Severance policies typically call for a lump-sum cash payment, the ability to cash out stock awards and options immediately instead of having to potentially wait for years, and sometimes even bonuses. And that’s not counting the retirement benefits and additional company stock that executives accumulate, which can increase the total value of their exit package by millions of dollars. Some critics believe investors have become inured to the hefty payouts. In addition, the continuing financial crises in Europe and the United States have pushed compensation into the backseat on the shareholder agenda. “People are preoccupied with the bigger issues,” said Frederick Rowe Jr., a hedge fund manager and president of Investors for Director Accountability which has sought to curb excessive pay. The Obama administration, meanwhile, seemed to lose its bully pulpit for compensation reform after most of the nation’s biggest financial companies repaid their government loans — and Kenneth R. Feinberg, its tough-talking pay overseer, moved on to tackle other issues. Federal Reserve officials flagged golden parachutes as a concern when they began a compensation review almost two years ago, but their inquiry was limited to large banks — not all large companies. The findings of the review are expected to be made public in the next few weeks. Over the last year, regulators have been pressing corporate boards to draft policies denying huge severance payouts to senior executives if the firm teeters on collapse. That still leaves wiggle room for managers to score big if they merely perform poorly. Practices such as large cash payouts and having shareholders pay the tax bill for departing executives are on the decline, especially after the uproar over the $200 million-plus exit packages of Hank McKinnell of Pfizer and Robert Nardelli of Home Depot in the last decade. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/09/02/the-expensive-goodbye-for-bank-of-new-york-mellons-kelly/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">The Expensive Goodbye For Bank of New York Mellon's Kelly<date>September 2, 2011, 5:03 pm</date><text>Parting is such costly sorrow. In the case of Robert P. Kelly at Bank of New York Mellon, the company will end up paying $22 million in the third quarter, and potentially more down the road. In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, the bank announced that its former chief executive, who resigned on Wednesday, would receive an immediate severance of $2 million. In addition, Mr. Kelly could receive another $4 million, based on the bank’s performance this year, and some $11.2 million from vested equity awards. He is also entitled to a pension annuity currently valued at $16.6 million. Given the payout, the bank said it would take a charge of roughly $22 million in the current quarter, adding “a substantial portion of which is an acceleration of future expenses.” Mr. Kelly stepped down late Wednesday because of “differences in approaches to managing the company,” the bank said. While the decision was mutual, several people close to the bank said Mr. Kelly was surprised by the board’s decision to replace him. Mr. Kelly declined to comment on Friday on both his severance package and his departure from the bank. Bank of New York Mellon has been under pressure for months. While it has avoided the mortgage woes that have bedeviled the nation’s biggest financial institutions, it has come under scrutiny because of accusations that it and other custody banks shortchanged clients when executing currency trades for foreign transactions. In addition, the bank’s performance has lagged behind that of its chief rival, State Street. A spokesman for the bank has said Mr. Kelly’s departure had nothing to do with the foreign-exchange lawsuits, which it says are “completely without merit.”</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/09/01/lucrative-package-for-outgoing-bank-of-new-york-mellon-chief/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Lucrative Package for Outgoing Bank of New York Mellon Chief<date>September 1, 2011, 2:12 pm</date><text>Chris Ratcliffe/Bloomberg NewsBank of New York Mellon said Wednesday that Robert K. Kelly was stepping down as chief executive and chairman. Robert P. Kelly stands to collect tens of millions of dollars on his way out as chief of Bank of New York Mellon, a figure unlikely to be dented by a successful shareholder initiative last year that sought to limit executive severance at the company. The bank said Wednesday that Mr. Kelly was stepping down because of “differences in approaches to managing the company.” The company isn’t expected to disclose how much Mr. Kelly will receive in severance for at least a day or two, but the sum is likely to hinge on how his departure is characterized for contractual purposes. That determination typically reflects negotiations between lawyers for each side as much as any underlying reality. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Bank of New York Mellon Chief Resigns in a Shake-Up Video: Executive Shuffle at BNY Mellon Company regulatory filings suggest that Mr. Kelly could be eligible for as much as $36.6 million in cash, stock and continued benefits if his departure is considered a termination by the company without cause. The terms of Mr. Kelly’s employment, as with most executive contracts, largely limits cause to serious infractions like dereliction of duty or conviction of a crime. By contrast, if Mr. Kelly is considered to have quit for “good reason” — a category that generally includes involuntary demotion or pay cuts — he could receive as much as $20 million. A simple resignation, rarely seen when executives are forced out over company performance, would bring Mr. Kelly about $5.5 million from faster vesting for some equity awards. Separately, Mr. Kelly is eligible to collect a pension that was valued at more than $15.1 million as of Dec. 31. A Bank of New York Mellon spokesman declined to comment on the terms of Mr. Kelly’s severance. Last year, the company’s shareholders approved by a wide margin a proposal intended to rein in executive severance payouts. Soon after, the company’s board adopted a policy reflecting the proposal. And in March, Bank of New York Mellon executives signed on to a severance plan incorporating the new restrictions, which limits severance to 2.99 times annual salary and bonus. Based on Mr. Kelly’s 2010 compensation, that would appear to limit his payout to about $19.7 million. But it is unlikely to make much difference. That’s because the policy applies the limit only to cash severance payments, consulting fees and some perks and pension sweeteners. It ignores payouts from improved terms for stock or option awards, post-employment medical benefits and payments made to settle potential legal or other claims, among other payments. Based on disclosures in the company’s March proxy filing, much of Mr. Kelly’s payout is likely to come from accelerated vesting for stock and option awards: $5.5 million to $14.2 million, depending on how his departure is classified. Another $14.8 million would come from pension sweeteners, and at most $7.6 million would be in cash. He is also eligible for two years of company-sponsored health care, which doesn’t count against the limit, and a year of job-hunting services. Theo Francis is a senior reporter for the Web site Footnoted, a division of the financial information company Morningstar that scrutinizes corporate disclosures.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/31/kelly-steps-down-at-bank-of-new-york-mellon/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Mellon Chief Resigns in a Shake-Up<date>August 31, 2011, 5:31 pm</date><text>Jin Lee/Bloomberg NewsRobert P. Kelly, who stepped down as chairman and chief executive of Bank of New York Mellon. Gerald L. Hassell, below, is his successor. Amanda Gordon/Bloomberg News 9:27 p.m. | Updated Bank of New York Mellon’s chief executive and chairman, Robert P. Kelly, stepped down late Wednesday because of “differences in approaches to managing the company,” the bank said. Pressure on the bank has been growing for months. While it has avoided the mortgage woes that have bedeviled the nation’s biggest financial institutions, it has come under scrutiny because of accusations that it and other custody banks shortchanged clients when executing currency trades for foreign transactions. In addition, Bank of New York’s performance has lagged that of its chief rival, State Street. A spokesman for the bank said Mr. Kelly’s departure had nothing to do with the foreign-exchange lawsuits. A person close to the board, who was not authorized to speak on the record, said that the decision was not rooted in the litigation or in any one particular issue. Rather, this person said, Mr. Kelly’s departure was the result of differences “in terms of management style.” Another person involved in the management shake-up, who was also not authorized to speak on the record, said the directors felt that Mr. Kelly was not as engaged in the day-to-day operations as they would have liked. Both people said that the rift between the board and Mr. Kelly had been brewing for some time. Gerald L. Hassell, 59, the bank’s president and a board member since 1998, was appointed chairman and chief executive. Bank of New York Mellon is not as well known as institutions like Bank of America or JPMorgan Chase, in part because it has no retail branches. But it is one of the world’s largest custodial banks and asset managers, with $26.3 trillion in assets under custody and administration and $1.3 trillion in assets under management. It was created in 2007 by the $16.5 billion merger of Bank of New York and Mellon Financial of Pittsburgh. Revolving Door View all posts Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The press release Mr. Kelly, 57, had been a candidate to succeed Ken Lewis as chief executive of Bank of America. But his talks with the bank became public in 2009 and apparently broke down over compensation. At the time, some Wall Street insiders were surprised that Bank of New York’s board did not dismiss him once it became known that he was negotiating to leave. In December 2009, Mr. Kelly sent a note to employees saying that while he had been approached by another bank, “I firmly concluded that my place is here at BNY Mellon.” A native of Nova Scotia, Mr. Kelly worked at Toronto-Dominion Bank for years. He was considered a candidate to one day run the bank. In 2000, however, he took a job at First Union Corporation. It acquired Wachovia in 2001, and he became chief financial officer of the combined company, named Wachovia. He left before Wachovia made what turned out to be the disastrous decision to buy Golden West Financial, a California lender that eventually dragged down the bank with mortgages that soured. He had moved to become chief executive of Mellon Financial in 2006 and when Mellon merged with Bank of New York in 2007, he got the top job. As an executive, he tends to fly under the radar on Wall Street. But the bank, like its peers, has had some recent setbacks. While Bank of New York did not have the same mortgage problems as other banks, it did accept $3 billion in taxpayer money during the financial crisis. Still, it was among the first banks to pay back the money. More recently, the bank has come under scrutiny over how it priced currency trades for some clients, including many pension funds. Several state attorneys general have filed lawsuits against the bank, contending that it cheated pension funds by selecting improper prices when processing currency trades. Jeep Bryant, a Bank of New York spokesman, said on Wednesday that the lawsuits were “completely without merit and we are defending against them vigorously.” Mr. Kelly did not return a call seeking comment. Shares of Bank of New York, like other financial stocks, have struggled in the last year. Yet since the beginning of the year, its shares have fallen 31 percent compared with a 23 percent decline in shares of State Street. Alexander Blostein, a research analyst who covers Bank of New York Mellon for Goldman Sachs, said, “The announcement of Mr. Kelly’s resignation and its timing were unexpected, which introduces new uncertainty to the stock, in our view.” “While the exact reasons behind Mr. Kelly’s departure are unclear,” Mr. Blostein said, “we believe the firm’s focus under the new leadership could shift to more aggressive cost management and business rationalization and away from acquisitions.” Analysts say Bank of New York has underperformed State Street in part because its business is more sensitive to interest rates, and the current prolonged low interest rate environment has eaten into profits.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/25/buffett-adds-another-bank-to-his-investment-portfolio/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Buffett Adds Another Bank to His Portfolio<date>August 25, 2011, 12:15 pm</date><text>Pankaj Nangia/Bloomberg NewsWarren E. Buffett, chairman of Berkshire Hathaway. With his $5 billion investment in Bank of America, Warren E. Buffett is adding yet another American financial giant to his stock portfolio. His investment vehicle, Berkshire Hathaway, has long been an investor in the nation’s banks, and counts five firms in which it has a major stake. Here were Berkshire’s top holdings in financial companies as of June 30, according to a regulatory filing: FIRM MARKET VALUE OF STAKE AMOUNT OF SHARES CHANGE FROM 1ST QUARTER American Express $7.84 billion 151,610,700 No change Wells Fargo $9.89 billion 352,327,608 + 9,703,683 shares US Bancorp $1.76 billion 69,039,426 No change Source: Bloomberg News/S.E.C. filing Berkshire also owns smaller stakes in the Bank of New York Mellon and the M&amp;T Bank Corporation. Of course, Mr. Buffett’s most notable bets on the finance sector of late came from his big capital injections into Goldman Sachs and General Electric during the financial crisis. Those two deals closely resemble his new investment in Bank of America; he bought $5 billion worth of perpetual preferred shares in Goldman and $3 billion in G.E. Those purchases were highly profitable for Mr. Buffett, with the preferred shares carrying a 10 percent annual dividend, as well as requirement that Goldman and G.E. pay a 10 percent premium to buy Berkshire out. Goldman has since bought back Mr. Buffett’s holdings, while G.E. has said that it intends to do so. Still, not all of Mr. Buffett’s Wall Street moves have turned out well. While Berkshire earned a profit from its Goldman and G.E. investments, warrants that it received along with the preferred shares remain underwater. (The 700 million warrants that Berkshire received from Bank of America, on the other hand, are currently in the money: They carry a strike price of $7.142857, while the firm’s stock price is at $7.89 as of late Thursday morning.) Going further back, just before the market crash of 1987, Berkshire bought $700 million of Salomon Brothers preferred shares. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Buffett Invests $5 Billion in Bank of America To protect his holdings, Mr. Buffett undertook a highly unusual move. He stepped in as Salomon’s chairman in 1991 after John Gutfreund was forced to resign following a Treasury securities bidding scandal. Mr. Buffett was widely credited with saving the firm from collapsing by quickly cleaning house and winning over angry clients, politicians and investors. (He famously delivered the following lines in his testimony before Congress on the scandal: “Lose money for the firm, and I will be understanding; lose a shred of reputation for the firm, and I will be ruthless.”) Mr. Buffett stepped down as Salomon’s chairman after roughly 10 months. Berkshire sold its shares in the firm in 1997, after Salomon was sold to what is now Citigroup. Outside of banks, Mr. Buffett declined to invest in the hedge fund Long-Term Capital Management in 1993. After LTCM faced collapse in 1998 amid a global financial crisis, its officials approached Mr. Buffett — and he again passed. This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: August 25, 2011 A previous version of this article misstated the size and value of Berkshire Hathaway's holdings in Wells Fargo.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/10/bank-of-new-york-mellon-to-cut-1500-jobs/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Mellon to Cut 1,500 Jobs<date>August 10, 2011, 9:36 am</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon said on Wednesday that it was planning to cut 1,500 jobs, or about 3 percent of its global work force of 48,900. The bank said that much of the reduction will take place through a company-wide hiring freeze and by cutting the use of temporary workers, consultants and contractors. The cuts are coming amid a widespread belt-tightening by the big banks this summer. Uncertain markets, an increased regulatory burden and weak consumer demand has prompted banks like Goldman Sachs and Barclays to retrench. Earlier this month, HSBC said that it was cutting 25,000 more jobs, on top of 5,000 it had already eliminated. “Over recent quarters, BNY Mellon has succeeded in building positive revenue momentum,” said Robert P. Kelly, BNY Mellon’s chief executive. “However, expenses have been growing unsustainably faster.”</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/05/business/new-york-moves-to-block-mortgage-settlement.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">New York Attorney General Moves to Block Mortgage Settlement<date>Published: August 4, 2011</date><text>The New York attorney general is moving to block a proposed $8.5 billion settlement struck in June by Bank of New York Mellon and Bank of America over troubled loan pools issued by Countrywide. A lawsuit filed late Thursday accuses Bank of New York of fraud in its role as trustee overseeing the pools for investors. In papers filed in New York State Supreme Court, lawyers for Eric T. Schneiderman, the attorney general, contended that Bank of New York misled investors about its conduct as overseer of the securities. The bank also breached its duties to investors by agreeing to the deal with Bank of America, according to the complaint, because the trustee is conflicted and “stands to receive direct financial benefits” as a result of the agreement. Questioning the fairness of the deal, the attorney general’s lawsuit said that it could “compromise investors’ claims in exchange for a payment representing a fraction of the losses” that have been suffered by investors. When the terms of the deal emerged, they appeared to be quite favorable to Bank of America. On June 29, when the deal was announced, Bank of America’s shares closed with a gain of almost 3 percent. A spokesman for Mr. Schneiderman declined to comment. Jeep Bryant, a spokesman for Bank of New York Mellon, disputed the attorney general’s allegations, calling them “outrageous, baseless, unsupported by fact and law” and saying that the bank would fight them in court. “We are confident that we have fulfilled in all respects our responsibilities as trustee,” he said, adding that Mr. Schneiderman’s action fails to understand the “benefit the settlement would provide to investors.”  Bank of America purchased Countrywide in a distress sale in early 2008. A judge overseeing the settlement will ultimately decide whether it should be approved. A court hearing on the proposed settlement was scheduled to take place Friday. Mr. Schneiderman’s lawsuit is likely to change the nature of those discussions.   As announced by Bank of New York, which is overseeing 530 mortgage pools issued by Countrywide, the deal would require Bank of America to pay $8.5 billion to investors holding the securities. The unpaid principal amount of the mortgages remaining in the pools totaled $174 billion. Lawyers representing 22 institutional investors, including the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, BlackRock and Pimco, contended the deal was favorable. But other investors in the Countrywide pools who were not part of the settlement negotiations between Bank of New York and Bank of America complained that the terms were inadequate. Among the criticisms made by a group of investors known as Walnut Place were that the negotiations were conducted in secret and that Bank of New York was conflicted as a negotiator because Bank of America agreed to cover all its costs and liabilities relating to the deal. Mr. Schneiderman’s contention that Bank of New York breached its duties to investors is significant because a trustee that agrees to oversee loan pools like those issued by Countrywide must abide by the rules governing the securities. Such rules require that lenders deliver to the trust complete and original mortgage documents for each loan in a pool, for example, and require that the trustee notify investors when such loan documents are missing. Bank of New York led investors in the Countrywide pools to believe that the lender had in fact delivered complete and adequate mortgage files for each loan as was required, the lawsuit said. The bank also misled investors by confirming that loan files relating to hundreds of thousands of mortgages were complete. But the bank failed in these duties, the attorney general’s complaint said. After conducting a review of court records in the Bronx and Westchester County, Mr. Schneiderman’s investigators have determined that Bank of New York did not ensure that notes underlying properties were delivered properly to some trusts, according to the lawsuit. If loan documents were not delivered as required to the trustee, investors could recover the money they invested in the mortgages. “Investors in the trusts were misled by Bank of New York Mellon into believing that Bank of New York Mellon would review the loan files for the mortgages securing their investment, and that any deficiencies would be cured,” the lawsuit said.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/13/business/13mortgage.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">2 States Probe Paperwork in Mortgage Bundling<date>Published: June 12, 2011</date><text>Opening a new line of inquiry into the problems that have beset the mortgage loan process, two state attorneys general are investigating Wall Street’s bundling of these loans into securities to determine whether they were properly documented and valid.The investigation is being led by Eric T. Schneiderman, the attorney general of New York, who has teamed with Joseph R. Biden III, his counterpart from Delaware. Their effort centers on the back end of the mortgage assembly lines — where big banks serve as trustees overseeing the securities for investors — according to two people briefed on the inquiry but who were not authorized to speak publicly about it. The attorneys general have requested information from Bank of New York Mellon and Deutsche Bank, the two largest firms acting as trustees. Trustee banks have not been a focus of other investigations because they are administrators of the securities and did not originate the loans or service them. But as administrators they were required to ensure that the documentation was proper and complete. Both attorneys general are investigating other practices that fueled the mortgage boom and subsequent bust. The latest inquiry represents another avenue of scrutiny of the inner workings of Wall Street’s mortgage securitization machine, which transformed individual home loans into bundles of loans that were then sold to investors. It follows months of sharp criticism of the mortgage foreclosure process, which produced an uproar last year over shoddy paperwork and possible forgeries of legal documents by banks, other lenders or their representatives. The slipshod practices in foreclosures led to further questions about whether all the necessary documents were delivered to the trusts and properly administered by them. Some of the nation’s biggest mortgage servicers are currently in negotiations with a group of state attorneys general to settle an investigation into foreclosure abuses. The new inquiry by New York and Delaware indicates the big banks’ troubles may not end even if a settlement is reached in the foreclosure matter. The stakes are potentially high. If the trustees did not follow the rules set out in the prospectus, they may be liable for breaching their duties to investors who bought the securities. That could expose the banks to costly civil litigation. Spokesmen from Bank of New York and Deutsche Bank declined to comment about the investigation, as did representatives from the offices of both attorneys general. A complex process that produced hundreds of billions of dollars in securities during the lending boom, the issuance of mortgage securities began with home loans, which were then bundled into investments and sold to pension funds, mutual funds, big banks and other investors. The bundles were created as trusts overseen by institutions such as Bank of New York and Deutsche Bank; they were supposed to make sure the complete mortgage files for each loan were delivered within a specified time and with the proper documentation. After the securities were sold, the trustees disbursed interest and principal payments to investors over the life of the trusts. The trusts were governed by the laws of the states in which they were set up. Roughly 80 percent of the trusts are governed by New York law with the rest by Delaware law. The rules governing the securitization process are labyrinthine, and there are steps required if the investment is to comply with tax laws and promises made by the issuer in its offering document. If the trusts did not comply with tax laws, for example, the beneficial treatment given to investors could be rescinded, causing taxes to be levied on the transactions. The terms of these mortgage deals varied, but many of them required that the trustee examine each of the loan files as soon as they came in from the Wall Street firm or bank issuing the security. For a file to be complete, it would typically have to include all of the information necessary to establish a chain of ownership through the various steps of the bundling process, as when the originator transferred it to the issuer of the security who then moved it to the trustee. Complete loan files were supposed to be delivered to the trusts within 90 days in most cases. If the trustee found any missing or defective documents, it was supposed to notify the loan originator so that it could either cure the deficiency or replace the loan. Such substitutions are typically allowed only in the early years of the trust. By asking for documents relating to this process, investigators are trying to determine if the trustees fulfilled their obligations to the investors who bought the mortgage deals, according to the people briefed on the inquiry.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/02/business/02loan.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Salvation Army Sues Bank of New York Over Securities Losses<date>Published: April 1, 2011</date><text>The southern division of the Salvation Army filed suit against the Bank of New York Mellon on Friday for almost $22 million, contending that the bank had “grossly mismanaged” assets belonging to the charity by investing them in mortgage-backed securities and other risky investments.“As a result of BNY Mellon’s misconduct, the Salvation Army has incurred losses and is left holding unproductive, toxic assets with extended maturity dates, the values of which have substantially declined,” the organization said in a lawsuit filed on Friday. “The Salvation Army cannot now devote those assets to its many charitable projects.” The organization, with its four divisions, is one of the largest charities in the country, with assets of $8.8 billion in 2009, the latest year for which financial data is available. In 1997, the Salvation Army hired BNY Mellon to maintain custody of securities it owned, and shortly thereafter, agreed to participate in a securities lending program. Under that program, the organization’s securities were lent to short-sellers in exchange for cash collateral, which the bank then invested. “We believe our actions were appropriate, and we will defend ourselves vigorously against these claims, which are without merit,” said Ron Gruendl, a spokesman for BNY Mellon. “We have a very rigorous process, and our clients understand both the benefits and risks of securities lending.” The Salvation Army said in its lawsuit that it had no previous experience with securities lending and thus “emphasized to BNY Mellon that it wanted little or no risk as a result of participating in the program.” When the securities in such programs are returned, the collateral that was posted is returned to the borrower and the lender keeps any returns made on it — or makes up any losses. In its lawsuit, the organization said that the list of approved investments offered to it by the bank included low-yielding but highly liquid products like government bonds, certificates of deposit and high-grade commercial paper. Instead, it said, the bank invested the collateral in securities backed by subprime and other risky mortgages as well as floating-rate notes of highly leveraged companies like Lehman Brothers, the CIT Group and the insurer American International Group. “These investments were inconsistent with the conservative risk profile of the Salvation Army,” the organization said in the lawsuit. “Moreover, BNY Mellon’s decision to overweight the Salvation Army’s portfolio heavily in favor of asset-backed securities tied to the housing market and financial services companies violated basic principles of prudent investing.” The lawsuit noted that in a meeting last July, the bank’s chief executive, Robert P. Kelly, stated that the Salvation Army had pushed for higher yields on the securities-lending account, but it denied that such a request was ever made by the charity.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/12/business/12advantage.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Post-Meltdown, Banks Still Rule Derivatives Trade<date>Published: December 11, 2010</date><text>On the third Wednesday of every month, the nine members of an elite Wall Street society gather in Midtown Manhattan.The men share a common goal: to protect the interests of big banks in the vast market for derivatives, one of the most profitable — and controversial — fields in finance. They also share a common secret: The details of their meetings, even their identities, have been strictly confidential. Drawn from giants like JPMorgan Chase, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, the bankers form a powerful committee that helps oversee trading in derivatives, instruments which, like insurance, are used to hedge risk. In theory, this group exists to safeguard the integrity of the multitrillion-dollar market. In practice, it also defends the dominance of the big banks. The banks in this group, which is affiliated with a new derivatives clearinghouse, have fought to block other banks from entering the market, and they are also trying to thwart efforts to make full information on prices and fees freely available. Banks’ influence over this market, and over clearinghouses like the one this select group advises, has costly implications for businesses large and small, like Dan Singer’s home heating-oil company in Westchester County, north of New York City. This fall, many of Mr. Singer’s customers purchased fixed-rate plans to lock in winter heating oil at around $3 a gallon. While that price was above the prevailing $2.80 a gallon then, the contracts will protect homeowners if bitterly cold weather pushes the price higher. But Mr. Singer wonders if his company, Robison Oil, should be getting a better deal. He uses derivatives like swaps and options to create his fixed plans. But he has no idea how much lower his prices — and his customers’ prices — could be, he says, because banks don’t disclose fees associated with the derivatives. “At the end of the day, I don’t know if I got a fair price, or what they’re charging me,” Mr. Singer said. Derivatives shift risk from one party to another, and they offer many benefits, like enabling Mr. Singer to sell his fixed plans without having to bear all the risk that oil prices could suddenly rise. Derivatives are also big business on Wall Street. Banks collect many billions of dollars annually in undisclosed fees associated with these instruments — an amount that almost certainly would be lower if there were more competition and transparent prices. Just how much derivatives trading costs ordinary Americans is uncertain. The size and reach of this market has grown rapidly over the past two decades. Pension funds today use derivatives to hedge investments. States and cities use them to try to hold down borrowing costs. Airlines use them to secure steady fuel prices. Food companies use them to lock in prices of commodities like wheat or beef. The marketplace as it functions now “adds up to higher costs to all Americans,” said Gary Gensler, the chairman of the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, which regulates most derivatives. More oversight of the banks in this market is needed, he said. But big banks influence the rules governing derivatives through a variety of industry groups. The banks’ latest point of influence are clearinghouses like ICE Trust, which holds the monthly meetings with the nine bankers in New York. Under the Dodd-Frank financial overhaul, many derivatives will be traded via such clearinghouses. Mr. Gensler wants to lessen banks’ control over these new institutions. But Republican lawmakers, many of whom received large campaign contributions from bankers who want to influence how the derivatives rules are written, say they plan to push back against much of the coming reform. On Thursday, the commission canceled a vote over a proposal to make prices more transparent, raising speculation that Mr. Gensler did not have enough support from his fellow commissioners. The Department of Justice is looking into derivatives, too. The department’s antitrust unit is actively investigating “the possibility of anticompetitive practices in the credit derivatives clearing, trading and information services industries,” according to a department spokeswoman. Indeed, the derivatives market today reminds some experts of the Nasdaq stock market in the 1990s. Back then, the Justice Department discovered that Nasdaq market makers were secretly colluding to protect their own profits. Following that scandal, reforms and electronic trading systems cut Nasdaq stock trading costs to 1/20th of their former level — an enormous savings for investors. “When you limit participation in the governance of an entity to a few like-minded institutions or individuals who have an interest in keeping competitors out, you have the potential for bad things to happen. It’s antitrust 101,” said Robert E. Litan, who helped oversee the Justice Department’s Nasdaq investigation as deputy assistant attorney general and is now a fellow at the Kauffman Foundation. “The history of derivatives trading is it has grown up as a very concentrated industry, and old habits are hard to break.” Representatives from the nine banks that dominate the market declined to comment on the Department of Justice investigation.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/10/19/new-york-fed-urges-bofa-to-buy-back-loans/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">New York Fed Urges BofA to Buy Back Loans<date>October 19, 2010, 4:09 pm</date><text>A group of financial institutions demanding that Bank of America repurchase $47 billion worth of loans packaged by Countrywide Financial has an unusual new member: the Federal Reserve Bank of New York. The New York Fed, along with BlackRock, the Pacific Investment Management Company and others, argued in a letter to Bank of America and the Bank of New York Mellon that Countrywide failed to properly service the loans. (Read it at the end of the post.) The mortgages were packaged into bonds, some of which are now owned by the New York Fed through its Maiden Lane portfolios of loans acquired from its rescues of Bear Stearns and the American International Group. Countrywide was acquired by Bank of America in 2008. Bondholders’ Letter to Bank of America Over Countrywide Loans (inc. NY Fed)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/20/business/20mellon.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Mellon Returns to Profitability<date>Published: October 19, 2010</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon reported Tuesday that it returned to profitability in the third quarter, which it attributed to acquisitions and an improvement in its investments.The bank said it had net income of $622 million, or 51 cents a share, in the three months ended Sept. 30. That contrasts with a net loss of $2.44 billion, or $2.05 a share, a year earlier, which was related to a charge for restructuring the company’s investment securities portfolio. Thomson Reuters analysts, who usually do not consider one-time items in their estimates, had predicted earnings of 54 cents a share. The bank’s revenue rose 3 percent, to $3.43 billion, from $3.33 billion, which beat Wall Street’s $3.39 billion forecast. Total adjusted fee revenue rose to $2.71 billion, from $2.61 billion last year. Net interest revenue, or earnings from deposits and loans, rose to $718 million, from $716 million. The bank has recently been on a buying spree, purchasing BHF Asset Servicing in a $343 million European deal. It also completed its $2.31 billion acquisition of PNC’s Global Investment Servicing in July. Assets under management rose 18 percent, to $1.14 trillion, mostly from the takeover of Insight Investment Management. Assets under custody and administration climbed 10 percent, to $24.4 trillion, reflecting higher market values and new business. The bank’s provision for credit losses was a credit of $22 million compared with a charge of $147 million in the 2009 quarter, because of the current quarter’s 26 percent decline in criticized assets, which are loans that are classified just above nonperforming loans. The unrealized gain on the investment securities portfolio was $319 million, up sharply from $114 million in the second quarter on declining interest rates and the tightening of credit spreads. In midday trading Tuesday, Bank of New York Mellon shares were down 8 cents, to $26.54.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/07/27/former-mellon-chiefs-said-to-launch-fund-business/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Ex-Mellon Chiefs Said to Begin Fund Firm<date>July 27, 2010, 6:24 am</date><text>Two former heads of one of Bank of New York Mellon‘s fund-of-hedge-funds units are planning to hang their own shingle, Financial News reported. Derek Stewart and Scott MacDonald, who previously ran BNY Mellon’s Mellon Global Alternative Investments, have formed Carduus Capital and plan to raise money for a fund of funds later this year, the publication said, citing a person familiar with the situation. The two men left the firm in May, following BNY Mellon’s move to rejigger its fund of hedge funds business. Go to Article from Financial News »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/06/21/bank-of-new-york-mellon-buys-toronto-firm/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Mellon Buys Toronto Firm<date>June 21, 2010, 4:46 am</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon is expanding its wealth management arm into Canada with the acquisition of I3 Advisors, a firm in Toronto with $3.43 billion in assets, Reuters reported. The purchase, for undisclosed terms, is expected to close in the third quarter. June Ntazinda will continue to be chief executive of I3 which has doubled its client assets since she founded it in 2005. Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times » Go to Press Release from Bank of New York Mellon via PR Newswire »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/12/business/12madoff.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Cuomo Sues Hedge Fund Over Madoff<date>Published: May 11, 2010</date><text>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York on Tuesday charged a unit of Bank of New York Mellon and two former executives with fraud, saying they failed to disclose information that pointed to problems at Bernard L. Madoff Investments.Mr. Cuomo’s civil lawsuit against Ivy Asset Management says memos and e-mail messages show the business had discovered that Mr. Madoff was not investing in the manner he had described. Yet Ivy and its executives refrained from telling investors for fear of losing out on lucrative fees, the suit says. Ivy made about $40 million over 10 years for advising several large Madoff investors. According to Mr. Cuomo, Ivy’s clients lost more than $227 million. The lawsuit also names as defendants Ivy’s former chief executive, Lawrence Simon, and its former chief investment officer, Howard Wohl. “Ivy and its former co-principals saw the trouble with Madoff coming around the bend, but instead of guiding their clients through the financial waters, they sold them down the river,” Mr. Cuomo said in a statement. “They shamelessly profited off of their own clients’ impending misfortune.” Mr. Cuomo is seeking damages and penalties from the three defendants. It also seeks to bar Mr. Simon and Mr. Wohl from working as investment advisers. Representatives for Ivy, Mr. Simon and Mr. Wohl said they would contest the charges. The lawsuit is the latest to emerge after the dissolution of Mr. Madoff’s multibillion-dollar Ponzi scheme, the largest in American history. Mr. Cuomo has also sued a hedge fund manager, J. Ezra Merkin, who lost more than $1 billion in investor money in Mr. Madoff’s scheme. Bank of New York acquired Ivy, a fund of funds, in 2000. Ivy said that Mr. Cuomo’s charges were tied to a “legacy nondiscretionary” side business whose clients were investment advisers in charge of their own clients’ money. Ivy is winding down its main fund-of-funds business. As far back as 1997, Ivy had discovered apparent holes in Mr. Madoff’s stated investment strategy, according to the lawsuit. Among them were analyses that show the volume of outstanding options tied to the Standard &amp; Poor’s 100-stock index supported only half of the assets Mr. Madoff had under management. “This is a clear example of our inability to make sense of Madoff’s strategy, and one where his trades for our accounts are inconsistent with the independent information that is available to us,” one Ivy internal memo read. Yet Mr. Simon and Mr. Wohl chose not to disclose to clients their suspicions. In 1999, Ivy sent a letter to clients saying it had “no reason to believe there is anything improper in the Madoff operation.” And from 1998 to 2004, the firm said its only concern about Mr. Madoff was an “ability to manage what must be an enormous pool of capital with such consistently outstanding results,” the complaint said. Representatives for Mr. Simon and Mr. Wohl said the two had repeatedly warned clients to reduce their exposure to Mr. Madoff, only to be ignored. In a letter to one client sent in 2000 and provided by a lawyer for Mr. Simon, the executive wrote, “Despite Madoff’s stellar record, we continue to be concerned by his unwillingness to be fully forthcoming about capital under management and other aspects of his business, and we reiterate our strong recommendation that the outsized allocations to this strategy be reduced.” A spokeswoman for Mr. Wohl added that at no time did he know or conclude that Mr. Madoff was running a Ponzi scheme.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/05/11/fidelity-reshuffle-boosts-abigail-johnson/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Fidelity Reshuffle Boosts Abigail Johnson<date>May 11, 2010, 6:17 am</date><text>Fidelity Investments, the giant mutual fund firm, has shuffled top management, expanding the duties of Abigail Johnson, the daughter of its chief executive, and hiring a top Bank of New York Mellon executive to run its asset-management business, Reuters reported. The changes, announced on Monday, are the latest at the firm as Fidelity’s chief executive, Edward C. Johnson III, approaches his 80th birthday in June with no public succession plan in place at the family-controlled business. The shifts suggest that Ms. Johnson, 48, could be closer to taking the top spot at the Boston-based firm. She will continue to oversee the company’s big retirement and personal investing business, and is vice chairwoman of the parent company’s board. Ms. Johnson will also oversee distribution arms including its Institutional Services wing, whose clients include broker-dealer firms, investment advisers and banks, the company said. Ronald O’Hanley, 53, who heads BNY Asset Management, will run Fidelity’s Asset Management and Corporate Services unit, taking over at midsummer after he leaves his current post. Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times » Go to Article from The Boston Globe »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/03/business/03views.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">A Winning Deal for PNC Investors<date>Published: February 3, 2010</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon, the giant trust bank, is growing but at a price. The bank agreed Tuesday to buy the back-office operations of PNC Financial Services for $2.3 billion. That works out to 23 times annualized fourth-quarter 2009 earnings of the unit. That is a heady multiple for only a marginal increase in market share. Skip to next paragraph Larry Downing/Reuters Robert Kelly of BNY Mellon, which bought a unit of PNC Financial. PNC’s shareholders seem to be getting the better end of the transaction. The sale of the unit, PNC Global Investment Servicing, raises PNC’s capital and is helping it repay $7.6 billion in bailout money. As a result of the deal, PNC’s Tier 1 capital ratio rises to 6.7 percent, from 6 percent. PNC said Tuesday that it would also sell $3 billion in new stock and pay back its bailout funds, but it would have had to raise more without the BNY Mellon deal. The advantages for BNY Mellon shareholders look less certain. The bank says the acquisition complements multiple business lines. But Robert P. Kelly, the chief executive, seems to be spending too much cash for just a 4 percent gain in assets. PNC’s back-office business results have been uneven. And even using last quarter’s earnings as the basis for analysis  the unit’s strongest quarter in 2009  BNY Mellon is paying a big multiple. The purchaser believes that it can squeeze out $120 million a year in costs. Taxed and capitalized, those savings are worth about $720 million today. Take that off the purchase price, and BNY Mellon is still paying $1.6 billion for the PNC unit  a price-to-earnings ratio of 16 times, which still looks like a full price. It’s the same multiple that Northern Trust, a leading rival, trades on; BNY Mellon’s own shares trade at just 12 times this year’s estimated earnings. To sell the deal to shareholders, management is talking about $200 million to $300 million of extra revenue based on integrating the unit into BNY Mellon. The company delivered on revenue promises in its acquisition of Mellon. But such cross-selling opportunities can be elusive, and BNY Mellon acknowledges that they could take three to four years to transpire. If Mr. Kelly and his crew can produce such revenue benefits, both sides may be able to call the deal a success. But for now, PNC holders have more to cheer. New Russian I.P.O.’s Russian initial public offerings are set for a comeback. Some $20 billion of Russian share sales are forecast this year, including dozens of I.P.O.’s. With plenty of options, investors should be able to drive a hard bargain. After a two-year lull in activity, bankers are excited at the prospect of a return to the heady days of 2006 and 2007, when Russian companies raised some $37 billion in 42 international stock offerings. The media group Profmedia plans to raise $500 million in April with a London listing. Metalloinvest, an iron ore mining concern, and SUEK, a coal mining company, are considering I.P.O.’s in 2010. Russian new issues have been understandably popular with investors. They tend to be sizable and offer exposure to high-growth sectors. The Russian stock market also appears less expensive than other emerging markets on some measures. But the managers of issuing companies often have inflated estimates of what they are worth. Around two-thirds of all Russian I.P.O.’s have underperformed the local stock market since issue date, in some cases losing 80 percent of their value, according to data compiled by Renaissance Capital. That suggests the prices of previous Russian I.P.O.’s were too high. This time, it should be different. Many Russian companies are under pressure to raise money quickly. They borrowed heavily before the crisis and need cash fast. Uralsib Capital estimates that Russian companies will issue $55.5 billion of equity in 2010 and 2011, of which $17.5 billion is required to repair balance sheets. The Profmedia I.P.O., for instance, would help repay some of its parent company’s $2 billion in debt. With local financing still scarce and expensive, smaller and less indebted Russian companies also need to raise equity to restart stalled expansion plans. Investors in the last wave of Russian I.P.O.’s were too willing to overpay. This time, it should be more of a buyer’s market. For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 3, 2010, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/02/02/bank-of-new-york-to-buy-pnc-unit-for-23-billion/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York to Buy PNC Unit for $2.3 Billion<date>February 2, 2010, 7:37 am</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon said Tuesday that it would buy the global investment servicing unit of the PNC Financial Services Group for $2.31 billion in cash, bolstering its back-end offerings for fund managers and financial advisers. The deal is likely to help PNC pay back some of the billions in government bailout money it still holds. It will also bolster Bank of New York’s services for big institutional clients and brokers, adding $855 billion in assets under administration and giving it a bigger presence in alternative fund assets and in Europe. “This acquisition significantly strengthens our service offering and market share with asset managers and financial advisers, while delivering attractive returns to our shareholders,” Robert P. Kelly, Bank of New York’s chief executive, said in a statement. “We expect the transaction to accelerate our growth, deliver economies of scale and strengthen our leadership position for asset servicing and Pershing.” One of the stronger firms to emerge from the financial crisis, Bank of New York serves mostly corporations as a custodian of assets. Bank of New York said the acquisition price includes the purchase of about $1.57 billion of stock and the repayment of PNC intercompany debt. Bank of New York also plans to sell about $800 million in new shares to help pay for the deal. The global investment servicing unit, based in Wilmington, Del., has about 4,500 employees. Its chief executive, Stephen M. Wynne, will remain with the business, reporting to Bank of New York’s co-heads of asset servicing, Tim Kearney and Jim Palermo. Go to Bank of New York Press Release »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/new-york-mellon-said-to-eye-pncs-global-unit/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">New York Mellon Said to Eye PNC's Global Unit<date>January 29, 2010, 1:32 am</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon is in talks to buy PNC Financial Services Group‘s global investment-servicing unit for as much as $2.5 billion to add hedge-fund and mutual-fund clients, a person familiar with the matter told Bloomberg News. The purchase would add about $2 trillion in assets administered for mutual funds and hedge funds to the $22.3 trillion that New York-based BNY oversees. Asset custodians are buying units from banks and other financial firms that are reassessing their holdings after the financial crisis triggered $1.7 trillion in write-downs worldwide, the news service reports. Go to Article from Bloomberg News »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/21/business/21regionals.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Wealth Management Unit Lifts Bank of New York<date>Published: January 20, 2010</date><text>The Bank of New York Mellon said Wednesday that it fourth-quarter profit surged as asset and wealth management revenue offset lower interest income. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Bank of New York Mellon Corp Go to your Portfolio » Profit rose to $593 million, or 49 cents a share, from $28 million, or 2 cents a share. Excluding discontinued operations, a tax benefit, a restructuring charge and other items, adjusted profit totaled $728 million, or 60 cents a share. Analysts expected earnings a share of 51 cents, according to Thomson Reuters. Asset and wealth management fees rose 5 percent to $736 million, in part because of the acquisition of Insight Investment Management, which closed during the quarter. Meanwhile, low interest rates hurt the bank’s net interest income, which slid 31 percent to $724 million. “The persistent low interest rate environment globally increasingly challenged our net interest revenue and fee revenue,” the chief executive, Robert P. Kelly, said in a statement. U.S. BANCORP The Minneapolis-based regional bank, U.S. Bancorp said on Wednesday that its fourth-quarter profit more than doubled from a year ago, as mortgage banking revenue grew. The bank also benefited from growth in traditional deposits, giving it a cheap source of money for loans. It still wrote off more bad loans in the quarter, and expected those write-offs will increase in this quarter as well, because of economic conditions and weak home prices. Net loan charge-offs were $1.11 billion, up 6.6 percent from the third quarter. It said the upward trends in charge-offs and bad loans "continue to moderate and credit costs overall remain very manageable." In a hopeful sign, the bank said the percentage of loans in the early stages of delinquency (running 30 to 89 days late) fell compared to the third quarter. The bank said it earned $580 million, or 30 cents a share, for the last three months of 2009, up from $259 million, or 15 cents a share, a year ago. The profit and its $4.38 billion in revenue were better than analysts expected. US Bancorp has been under pressure to raise its quarterly dividend from the current 5 cents per share. It’s taking a wait-and-see approach, though. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/01/15/ivy-assets-chief-resigns-amid-restructuring/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Ivy Asset's Chief Resigns Amid Restructuring<date>January 15, 2010, 2:27 pm</date><text>Sean Simon, head of the fund of hedge funds Ivy Asset Management, has left the firm amid a broad restructuring of the fund of funds unit within its corporate parent, the Bank of New York Mellon Corporation. Mr. Simon, who is the son of Ivy’s founder, Lawrence Simon, is leaving to “pursue other interests,” according to a statement by BNY Mellon Asset Management. He will be replaced by Larry Morgenthal, Ivy’s chief operating officer. BNY Mellon said Ivy would join Mellon Global Alternative Investments, MGAI, and EACM Advisors in reporting directly to Phil Maisano, head of alternative investments. BNY Mellon said the move would create a hedge fund of funds group with more than $8 billion in assets under management BNY Mellon said Ivy would undergo a “strategic review” of its business. EACM is also undergoing changes as BNY Mellon consolidates its funds of hedge funds business. The firm’s chief executive, Bill Crerend, will take on the additional title of chairman, continuing to report to Mr. Maisano. The assets of Mellon Global Alternative Investments will be transferred to EACM’s control. Ivy has seen a substantial fall in assets under management in the last few years as investors pulled their money out of funds of hedge funds during the financial crisis. Ivy’s assets under management dropped to about $5 billion at the end of last year from a high of $14 billion in 2007. The younger Mr. Simon took sole control of the firm a year ago, after several years as co-president alongside Michael Singer. His father, Lawrence, sold the company to BNY Mellon in 2000. In the statement, Mr. Maisano said: “By aligning the group under one leadership team, we will be able to enhance our ability to innovate and at the same time further strengthen our businesses.” – Zachery Kouwe</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/10/business/10pay.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Banks Prepare for Big Bonuses, and Public Wrath<date>Published: January 9, 2010</date><text>Everyone on Wall Street is fixated on The Number. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Goldman Sachs Group Bank of New York Mellon Corp Citigroup Inc Bank of America Corp Morgan Stanley Go to your Portfolio » The bank bonus season, that annual rite of big money and bigger egos, begins in earnest this week, and it looks as if it will be one of the largest and most controversial blowouts the industry has ever seen. Bank executives are grappling with a question that exasperates, even infuriates, many recession-weary Americans: Just how big should their paydays be? Despite calls for restraint from Washington and a chafed public, resurgent banks are preparing to pay out bonuses that rival those of the boom years. The haul, in cash and stock, will run into many billions of dollars. Industry executives acknowledge that the numbers being tossed around  six-, seven- and even eight-figure sums for some chief executives and top producers  will probably stun the many Americans still hurting from the financial collapse and ensuing Great Recession. Goldman Sachs is expected to pay its employees an average of about $595,000 apiece for 2009, one of the most profitable years in its 141-year history. Workers in the investment bank of JPMorgan Chase stand to collect about $463,000 on average. Many executives are bracing for more scrutiny of pay from Washington, as well as from officials like Andrew M. Cuomo, the attorney general of New York, who last year demanded that banks disclose details about their bonus payments. Some bankers worry that the United States, like Britain, might create an extra tax on bank bonuses, and Representative Dennis J. Kucinich, Democrat of Ohio, is proposing legislation to do so. Those worries aside, few banks are taking immediate steps to reduce bonuses substantially. Instead, Wall Street is confronting a dilemma of riches: How to wrap its eye-popping paychecks in a mantle of moderation. Because of the potential blowback, some major banks are adjusting their pay practices, paring or even eliminating some cash bonuses in favor of stock awards and reducing the portion of their revenue earmarked for pay. Some bank executives contend that financial institutions are beginning to recognize that they must recalibrate pay for a post-bailout world. “The debate has shifted in the last nine months or so from just ‘less cash, more stock’ to ‘what’s the overall number?’ ” said Robert P. Kelly, the chairman and chief executive of the Bank of New York Mellon. Like many other bank chiefs, Mr. Kelly favors rewarding employees with more long-term stock and less cash to tether their fortunes to the success of their companies. Though Wall Street bankers and traders earn six-figure base salaries, they generally receive most of their pay as a bonus based on the previous year’s performance. While average bonuses are expected to hover around half a million dollars, they will not be evenly distributed. Senior banking executives and top Wall Street producers expect to reap millions. Last year, the big winners were bond and currency traders, as well as investment bankers specializing in health care. Even some industry veterans warn that such paydays could further tarnish the financial industry’s sullied reputation. John S. Reed, a founder of Citigroup, said Wall Street would not fully regain the public’s trust until banks scaled back bonuses for good  something that, to many, seems a distant prospect. “There is nothing I’ve seen that gives me the slightest feeling that these people have learned anything from the crisis,” Mr. Reed said. “They just don’t get it. They are off in a different world.” The power that the federal government once had over banker pay has waned in recent months as most big banks have started repaying the billions of dollars in federal aid that propped them up during the crisis. All have benefited from an array of federal programs and low interest rate policies that enabled the industry to roar back in profitability in 2009. This year, compensation will again eat up much of Wall Street’s revenue. During the first nine months of 2009, five of the largest banks that received federal aid  Citigroup, Bank of America, Goldman Sachs, JPMorgan Chase and Morgan Stanley  together set aside about $90 billion for compensation. That figure includes salaries, benefits and bonuses, but at several companies, bonuses make up more than half of compensation. Goldman broke with its peers in December and announced that its top 30 executives would be paid only in stock. Nearly everyone on Wall Street is waiting to see how much stock is awarded to Lloyd C. Blankfein, Goldman’s chairman and chief executive, who is a lightning rod for criticism over executive pay. In 2007, Mr. Blankfein was paid $68 million, a Wall Street record. He did not receive a bonus in 2008. Goldman put aside $16.7 billion for compensation during the first nine months of 2009. Responding to criticism over its pay practices, Goldman has already begun decreasing the percentage of revenue that it pays to employees. The bank set aside 50 percent in the first quarter, but that figure fell to 48 percent and then to 43 percent in the next two quarters. JPMorgan executives and board members have also been wrestling with how much pay is appropriate. “There are legitimate conflicts between the firm feeling like it is performing well and the public’s prevailing view that the Street was bailed out,” said one senior JPMorgan executive who was not authorized to speak for the company. JPMorgan’s investment bank, which employs about 25,000 people, has already reduced the share of revenue going to the compensation pool, from 40 percent in the first quarter to 37 percent in the third quarter. At Bank of America, traders and bankers are wondering how much Brian T. Moynihan, the bank’s new chief, will be awarded for 2010. Bank of America, which is still absorbing Merrill Lynch, is expected to pay large bonuses, given the bank’s sizable trading profits. Bank of America has also introduced provisions that would enable it to reclaim employees’ pay in the event that the bank’s business sours, and it is increasing the percentage of bonuses paid in the form of stock. “We’re paying for results, and there were some areas of the company that had terrific results, and they will be compensated for that,” said Bob Stickler, a Bank of America spokesman. At Morgan Stanley, which has had weaker trading revenue than the other banks, managers are focusing on how to pay stars in line with the industry. The bank created a pay program this year for its top 25 workers, tying a fifth of their deferred pay to metrics based on the company’s later performance. A company spokesman, Mark Lake, said: “Morgan Stanley’s board and management clearly understands the extraordinary environment in which we operate and, as a result, have made a series of changes to the firm’s compensation practices.” The top 25 executives will be paid mostly in stock and deferred cash payments. John J. Mack, the chairman, is forgoing a bonus. He retired as chief executive at the end of 2009. At Citigroup, whose sprawling consumer banking business is still ailing, some managers were disappointed in recent weeks by the preliminary estimates of their bonus pools, according to people familiar with the matter. Citigroup’s overall 2009 bonus pool is expected to be about $5.3 billion, about the same as it was for 2008, although the bank has far fewer employees. The highest bonus awarded to a Citigroup executive is already known: The bank said in a regulatory filing last week that the head of its investment bank, John Havens, would receive $9 million in stock. But the bank’s chief executive, Vikram S. Pandit, is forgoing a bonus and taking a salary of just $1. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 10, 2010, on page A1 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/22/nyregion/22dawnay.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Tenants Struggle as a British Landlord Goes Bust<date>Published: December 21, 2009</date><text>Foreign investors were a major force in New York’s real estate boom of the last decade, with families and companies from Dubai to Australia swallowing weekend apartments and Midtown office towers. In 2007, the roster of international investors came to include a British firm, Dawnay Day, whose executives had a splashy reputation for spending millions on fine art and yachts. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Guy Naggar, left, and Peter Klimt, the principal executives of the Dawnay Day real estate firm. It was then, after a meeting with a New York landlord at an art show in Miami, that the British firm plunked down $225 million for 47 rental buildings, most of them in East Harlem. The plan, in a gentrifying neighborhood, was to repeat the success its executives once found in the transformation of the south London neighborhood of Brixton. Dawnay Day would ease out its mainly lower-income residents, rehabilitate the apartments and charge a new generation of younger, more affluent tenants substantially steeper rents. The efforts, though, didn’t get far before the recession spread across the globe and Dawnay Day went bust. Now, as part of one of the United Kingdom’s largest real estate insolvencies of the recession, the firm’s yachts are up for auction, and their expensive art has been stripped from the walls of its former London headquarters. And in the 47 buildings, anger, uncertainty and a degree of misery have set in. At tenant meetings, renters complain of gaping holes in their ceilings and walls that allow rats to freely roam. The properties face foreclosure, and it is very possible that the buildings may fall back into the hands of the landlord some tenants say neglected them long before they attracted a foreign buyer. “They were a multinational corporation guided by greed,” Juan Haro, director of the housing rights group Movement for Justice in El Barrio, who has worked with tenants in the buildings, said of Dawnay Day. “They failed miserably. They crumbled financially and they were a victim of their own devices.” Saying the federal government has not adequately responded to the broader real estate crisis, a group of tenants are planning a demonstration for Tuesday at the Bank of New York Mellon, which holds the mortgage on the Dawnay Day properties. For the moment, the thousands of residents of the 1,100 apartments in East Harlem have been left partly to fend for themselves. Many of them have lived in the buildings for generations, and they are hardly unfamiliar with hardship and discord. Still, their current state of limbo  days trying to get apartments repaired and night meetings with a court-appointed receiver  has taken its toll. For Joaquin Rufiles, a barrel-chested butcher who shares a one-bedroom apartment in one of the East Harlem buildings with his wife, Josefina Toiralua, their two children and his wife’s uncle, Dawnay Day’s collapse means living with rats in their kitchen. On Nov. 4, his family presented their complaints to the receiver handling the bankruptcy. They said the problems were not fixed. “We pay rent. It’s not like we live for free,” said Ms. Toiralua through a translator. The tale of this portfolio of Harlem buildings began in the 1980s, when Steven Kessner, the son of a Bronx taxi driver who studied economics at Dartmouth based on the encouragement of one of his father’s passengers, passed up Harvard Business School to return to the city and work in real estate. Mr. Kessner said he started buying and repairing East Harlem walk-ups when most banks would not lend in the neighborhood. In what he described as 100-hour workweeks that required “blood, sweat and tears,” he repaired boilers, eliminated thousands of violations and kicked out drug dealers running the buildings. At the same time, he expanded his empire by buying properties in the East Village. While Mr. Kessner said that he worked hard to manage the buildings, and repaired many of their problems, The Village Voice identified him as one of the 10 worst landlords in New York City in 2006. By the time Mr. Kessner sold the buildings in March 2007, the 1,111 apartments still had 2,419 violations, according to the Department of Housing Preservation and Development. Mr. Kessner decided to sell the bulk of his portfolio in the fall of 2006. The real estate market in New York was peaking. All corners of Harlem were being transformed  integrated and gentrified and alive with new commercial investments and enterprises. A world away, the real estate firm Dawnay Day had become something of an insatiable Goliath, buying up mainly commercial real estate in a half-dozen countries. Its purchases included well-known trophies like the Michelin-starred London restaurant the Wolseley and a hotel in the Cotswolds where Oliver Cromwell once stayed. British newspapers varied widely on their estimates of the company’s value, though they roughly put it at several billion dollars. With company money, Dawnay Day executives also indulged their personal hobbies. Yachts were bought to entertain friends and relatives. Local British papers say they decorated their office with multimillion-dollar works of art including a Damien Hirst, and a Lucian Freud called “Benefits Supervisor Sleeping,” which was auctioned by Christies in May 2008 for $34 million. They then set their sights on what for them was an unconventional purchase, the buildings in East Harlem. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in New York Region » A version of this article appeared in print on December 22, 2009, on page A31 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/12/18/payout-politics-behind-bofas-ceo-search/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Payout Politics Behind BofA's C.E.O. Search<date>December 18, 2009, 6:39 am</date><text>Pay czar Kenneth Feinberg’s reaction to the compensation proposed by Robert Kelly caused Bank of America‘s search committee to think again about trying to hire the Bank of New York Mellon chief executive as its next C.E.O., The Wall Street Journal reported, citing people close to the talks. During discussions with the board’s search committee, Mr. Kelly proposed a payout totaling between $35 million and $40 million, the newspaper said. That sum included roughly $20 million to buy out unvested Bank of New York Mellon shares and options, plus $15 million to $20 million in annual compensation as chief executive, with all but $1 million of that amount to be paid in stock, according to The Journal. However, when the committee approached Mr. Feinberg to sound out the political viability of the payout, he said the figure might cause alarm and be seen as excessive, The Journal said, citing people familiar with the exchange. Mr. Feinberg doesn’t have any say on the pay package, given that BofA has repaid $45 billion of TARP financing, but his response contributed to a dramatic shift in the deliberations, the newspaper said. Go to Article from The Wall Street Journal »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/12/14/ny-mellon-chief-said-to-be-in-lead-for-bofa-post/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">N.Y. Mellon Chief Said to Be in Lead for BofA Post<date>December 14, 2009, 5:45 am</date><text>Bank of New York Mellon‘s chief executive, Robert Kelly, is the front-runner to succeed the retiring Bank of America chief Kenneth D. Lewis, but compensation issues could get in the way of a deal, The Wall Street Journal reported, citing people familiar with the situation. The Journal said that the talks were fluid as of Sunday night, and that a person close to Mr. Kelly warned that it might not be possible for him to reach an agreement with Bank of America’s directors. According to the report, Mr. Kelly has not yet received an official offer. One person familiar with the situation told The Journal that if Mr. Kelly and the board “can reach some level of comfort around compensation, he will take it.” BofA, the largest United States bank, last week said it had finished repaying the $45 billion it had borrowed under the Troubled Assets Relief Program. Go to Article from The Wall Street Journal » Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/12/10/looking-to-bail-wealth-advisers-hunt-for-deals/?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Looking to Bail, Wealth Advisers Hunt for Deals<date>December 10, 2009, 5:33 am</date><text>Once driven by their desire for an up-front profit, wealth advisers have been selling their firms out of fear they may not survive the economic downturn, an industry study released Wednesday said. Reuters reported that the study — commissioned by Bank of New York Mellon‘s Pershing Advisor Solutions unit — found that registered investment advisory firm deals were down by one-third from their peak of 67 deals in 2007, and roughly matching the pace of 2008, when 45 wealth firms merged or were acquired. The recent deals — 35 through the first three quarters of 2009 — are about self-preservation, Reuters said, citing the study. “Many small RIA firms are looking for a lifeline through an association with a larger firm,” the study said. Boutique investment firms, typically created when wealth advisers leave the largest American brokerages, are at the center of a long-predicted shift of business and billions of dollars in client assets away to more local and regional players. Deals were driven by long-term growth prospects and sustainability of the firm, rather than short-term profit, the study found. Cost savings and economies of scale were often the main drivers, rather than a jolt to earnings. The study found that, on average, the deals done so far this year were fewer in number, but larger in relative size. The typical advisory firm sold this year had $600 million in assets under management, $4 million in annual revenue and $700,000 in net earnings, the study found. And while deals were down from their peak in 2007, wealth advisory mergers and acquisitions this year were still ahead of the pace seen early in the decade. Investment advisers were involved in 45 deals in 2008, a pace 2009 will likely match, the study said. From 2000 to 2004, no more than 36 deals were done by wealth firms in a single year, a figure 2009 is expected to exceed. “The critical drivers for transactions have not gone away,” the Pershing study said. Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/07/nyregion/07pensions.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Pension Checks of Retired New York City Teachers Canceled<date>Published: November 6, 2009</date><text>The pension checks of tens of thousands of retired New York City teachers and school staff members were electronically canceled as of Friday morning, just days after they had been deposited, according to city and union officials. City and union officials laid blame on the Bank of New York Mellon, which oversees electronic transfers for the Teachers Retirement System of the City of New York, which serves 178,000 current and former city educators. The checks, totaling $185 million, were part of the monthly pension payments made by New York City through the city comptroller’s office. “BNY Mellon is taking a number of actions today to remedy a processing incident that occurred regarding the bank accounts of the participants in the New York City Teachers Retirement Fund,” said Ron Gruendl, a spokesman for the bank. “Our issue is that we want it corrected today, Friday,” said Ernest Logan, the president of the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators, a union that represents principals and other administrators. He said many retirees depended on the money and had already written checks or withdrawn the money. “We are outraged, and this is unacceptable,” said Michael Mulgrew, president of the United Federation of Teachers, the city’s teachers’ union. The pension system is one of the largest in the United States and serves not only school teachers, but educational support staff and City University of New York employees as well. Mr. Logan said it appeared that everyone who was involved in electronic fund transfer was affected by the cancellation. The error happened sometime Thursday night or early Friday morning, and calls started flooding union officials’ cellphones in the morning. “We have been working on this all day,” Mr. Mulgrew said. Howard Geschwind, 70, a retired social studies teacher who lives in Lakewood, N.J., said that several thousand dollars was deposited in Sovereign Bank on Oct. 31 for both him and his wife, Lois, a retired school secretary. However, he checked his balances Friday morning and found that both electronic transfers had been reverted back to the pension system, causing an overdraft. When he called the bank, he learned that it happened to hundreds of bank customers. “Right now I am very annoyed because I was told by the bank not to make any checks today or use my debit card,” Mr. Geschwind said. “We will be returning the funds, and we will compensate participants for any overdraft fees they incur,” said Mr. Gruendl, the Bank of New York Mellon spokesman. The bank has set up a toll-free number, 1-800-627-8000, for questions. Information will also be available on the bank’s Web site, bnymellon.com. “We regret any inconvenience that results from this incident, and we are taking steps to make sure it does not recur,” Mr. Gruendl said. More Articles in New York Region » A version of this article appeared in print on November 7, 2009, on page A19 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFD61F39F93AA15753C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">CITY ROOM BLOGGING AT NYTIMES.COM/CITYROOM.<date>Published: October 29, 2009</date><text>BANK TECHNICIAN Charged in Fraud A Brooklyn man used his job as a computer technician to appropriate the identities of more than 150 employees of the Bank of New York Mellon and steal more than $1.1 million from an array of nonprofit groups and other institutions, the authorities said on Wednesday. In a 149-count indictment, the technician, Adeniyi Adeyemi, 27, of Crown Heights, was charged with grand larceny, identity theft, money laundering, scheming to defraud, computer tampering and unlawful possession of personal identification information. The fraud started in November 2001 and continued through last April, according to the office of the Manhattan district attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau, which is prosecuting the case. Using his position as a contract employee in the information technology department of the bank, the district attorney said, Mr. Adeyemi stole personal identifying information from dozens of employees, using the information for more than 30 bank and brokerage accounts in their names at E*Trade, Fidelity, Citi, Wachovia and Washington Mutual. Mr. Adeyemi then diverted money from the bank accounts of charities, transferred the funds to the dummy accounts, and later withdrew the money or funneled it into a second layer of ''dummy accounts,'' Mr. Morgenthau said. SEWELL CHAN TAKING QUESTIONS This week on the blog, Sam Roberts, a Times reporter and the author of ''Only in New York: An Exploration of the World's Most Fascinating, Frustrating and Irrepressible City,'' is answering readers' questions about the city's uniqueness. Here's an excerpt: Q. Up until the mid-to-late-1800s, New York City was world renowned for the quality and abundance of the seafood in our surrounding waters, oysters especially. Sadly, pollution has poisoned the waters for over a century. The various recent environmental cleanups seem promising, especially the G.E. Hudson project. Is there any chance this once-famous resource will return to edibility in our lifetimes? Matthew from Manhattan A. Depends how old you are! Health restrictions remain in place on eating most seafood harvested from the New York estuary, but efforts are proceeding to remove decades of accumulated pollutants. Species that have not been seen in years abound. Oyster beds are being seeded in Jamaica Bay, and the Army Corps of Engineers hopes to do the same in other parts of the harbor -- they not only offer the potential for seafood, but also filter the water -- once state concerns are overcome that poachers will prematurely harvest unhealthy ones and contaminate the market. ALSO ON THE BLOG Construction Deaths Spike: More than 30 construction workers died last year in falls and other events on job sites in the city, the Labor Department reported Wednesday. The overall number of workers who died on the job in New York in 2008 was 90, up 11 percent from 81 in 2007. PHOTO: Adeniyi Adeyemi, 27, was indicted on 149 counts. (PHOTOGRAPH BY JOHN MARSHALL MANTEL FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES)</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/17/business/global/17bony.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Settles a Protracted Russian Lawsuit<date>Published: September 16, 2009</date><text>MOSCOW  The Bank of New York Mellon and the Russian government have agreed to settle a $22.5 billion lawsuit relating to a 1990s money laundering scandal, with the bank paying the government’s legal fees of about $14 million, Russia’s finance minister said Wednesday. Skip to next paragraph Pool photo by Simon Dawson Aleksei L. Kudrin, Russias finance minister, said the Bank of New York would give a line of credit to Russias state banks. Add to Portfolio Bank of New York Mellon Corp Go to your Portfolio » That was far less than the $1 billion that lawyers for the Russian government had sought and seemed to bring to a close the bank’s strange odyssey through the Russian legal system. Separately, the Bank of New York agreed to offer a line of credit to Russian state banks to finance import and export business, the finance minister, Aleksei L. Kudrin, said in testimony to Parliament. The $400 million loan on favorable terms, though, would be an “act of good will” not formally linked to the settlement, he said. “It has nothing to do with costs of the court case, and is not an admission of guilt.” His statement seemed to confirm the Russian government’s approval of the settlement that was leaked to journalists this week, even though the government backed away from most of its claim. Bank of New York had always maintained that even if the government won in a Russian court, the award would never be collected in the United States. The case spun out of the bank’s huge money laundering scandal of the late 1990s. A group of trial lawyers in Miami took the case on a contingency fee for the Russian government after the Bank of New York reached a $14 million settlement with the American government in 2005. The bank conceded a rogue employee had laundered $7.5 billion from Russia through the bank in the 1990s, but said it had admitted no criminal wrongdoing. But incorrect wording in a news release from the Justice Department announcing the settlement said that the bank had admitted guilt, which lawyers for the Russian government seized upon as the basis for a lawsuit. (The Justice Department recently acknowledged that Bank of New York had not admitted guilt in the matter.) Jonathan D. Schiller, a managing partner of Boies, Schiller &amp; Flexner who is representing the bank, also drew attention to Mr. Kudrin’s remarks Wednesday before the Russian Parliament that the bank had committed no crime. The bank negotiated the deal directly with the Russian government, rather than the Miami law firm, Podhurst Orseck, that had been representing it, Mr. Schiller said. Russia’s customs agency had asserted that it had lost tax revenue because of the money transfer scheme, which was used in part to import goods at below market rates. The Miami lawyers from Podhurst Orseck, led by Steven C. Marks, sought to apply American antiracketeering laws in the Moscow commercial court. The laws allow a civil damage claim based on a criminal act and was first conceived as a tool against organized crime groups. According to court documents, those lawyers would be eligible for about 29 percent of any settlement. It was unclear Wednesday what, if anything, they would receive from the value of the discounted loan that Mr. Kudrin had presented as distinct from the settlement but which Mr. Marks said was worth tens of millions of dollars. Unless the fees are disclosed publicly, it will be impossible to determine whether the government used the loan to renege on the contingency fees, which are not binding in some cases in Russia. “Any objective person looking at this situation would realize it’s a quid pro quo,” Mr. Marks said in a telephone interview of the loan and settlement. “For them to provide this kind of lending is a significant benefit. It defies logic that the two are unrelated.” He said it was his “hope and expectation” that the government would pay in full, and that the $14 million figure cited by Mr. Kudrin would not cover his firm’s outlays on behalf of the Russian government. Both sides drew upon prominent lawyers and experts: Russia’s lawyers tapped Alan M. Dershowitz, the Harvard law professor, as part of its team, while the bank’s defense included Richard Thornburgh, the former United States attorney general. Though courts in the United States and elsewhere apply foreign law in rare circumstances, outside legal specialists criticized the proceedings here as a lapse of the rule of law in Russia, owing to the thinness of the claim that the bank itself had committed a criminal act. The Russian government had been backing away from the litigation for some time. Michael J. de la Merced contributed reporting from New York. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 17, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/15/business/15bony.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Settlement May Be Near in Bank of New York Case<date>Published: September 14, 2009</date><text>The Bank of New York Mellon is near an agreement to settle a $22.5 billion lawsuit by the Russian government for up to $14 million, after the two sides also agreed to hold talks about a trade-financing pact, according to people briefed on the matter. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Bank of New York Mellon Corp Go to your Portfolio » Lawyers for Bank of New York and for the Russian Federal Customs Service resumed negotiations in Moscow in July after months of on-again, off-again talks, these people said. The judge overseeing the case in Moscow Arbitration Court had been encouraging the two sides to settle. Bank of New York, one of the largest banks in the United States, was sued by Miami trial lawyers on behalf of the Russian government, seeking to collect damages related to a Justice Department investigation into a late 1990s scandal in which a bank executive was accused of secretly moving $7.5 billion out of the country. Lawyers for Russia brought the case, based on United States antiracketeering laws, not in an American courtroom but in a Moscow commercial court. Bank of New York argued that even if Russia were to have won the case, any decision rendered by the court would have no effect elsewhere. The lawsuit has attracted criticism from legal observers who argue that Russia was flouting the rule of law. A settlement payment by Bank of New York would probably cover court costs, and would be well below the hundreds of millions of dollars that the Russian customs service’s American lawyers had sought. According to court documents, those lawyers would be eligible for about 29 percent of any settlement. Closely linked to a settlement would be the restarting of a five-year, $400 million trade-finance agreement with Russian state banks, which would help pay for imports and exports, one of these people said. While not explicitly tied to the settlement of the case, it would resume soon after an agreement is reached. While the settlement proposal still needs the final blessing of the Russian government, an agreement could be reached before the next hearing in October, this person said. A spokesman for Bank of New York declined to comment. A spokesman for the Russian customs service could not be reached. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 15, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/21/business/21mellon.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Profit Drops 95% at Bank of New York Mellon<date>Published: January 20, 2009</date><text>In an effort to ease investors’ mounting concerns about the stability of the financial sector, Bank of New York Mellon issued its fourth-quarter earnings report on Tuesday two days ahead of schedule. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Bank of New York Mellon Corp Go to your Portfolio » But the results seemed to offer investors little comfort; shares lost another 3 percent in after-hours trading. Shares fell 17 percent, or $3.96, to finish regular trading at $19. Bank of New York Mellon said its profit tumbled nearly 95 percent in the final quarter of last year because of sizable losses on investments and a severance-related charge. The report came just hours after a competitor the State Street Corporation rattled investors with its own bleak fourth-quarter report and a forecast for a difficult 2009. The commercial banks, which largely cater to institutions, corporations and wealthy individuals, have so far held up reasonably well amid the ballooning financial crisis. BNY Mellon reported net income after paying preferred dividends of $28 million, or 2 cents a share, for the fourth quarter. This compares with earnings of $520 million, or 62 cents a share, in the year-ago period. Excluding certain one-time charges and expenses, the bank earned $53 million, or 5 cents a share, down from $700 million, or 61 cents per share, in the fourth quarter of 2007. Analysts were expecting earnings of 69 cents per share, according to a poll by Thomson Reuters. Analyst estimates typically exclude one-time items. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/02/nyregion/02rooms.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Where History Intersects With the Bailout<date>Published: December 1, 2008</date><text>The Bank of New York  America’s first financial firm  was founded in a rich man’s house on Pearl Street in 1784. While it is no surprise that the august institution has a long history of business in the country, it is less well known that it has also made a business of the country’s history  writing, for example, the first loan to the federal government (for $20,000) that helped retire debts from the Revolutionary War. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Interactive Feature Where It All Began Related More Articles in This Series Times Topics: Bank of New York Mellon Corporation The original copy of that note hangs today in a small alcove just outside the office of Robert P. Kelly, the chairman and chief executive of the bank, who, much like those before him, is elaborately entangled in the nation’s financial fate. Just six weeks ago, in fact, the Treasury Department named his bank  now called the Bank of New York Mellon  the master custodian of the Troubled Assets Relief Program (known in the vernacular as the Massive Wall Street Bailout). Given Mr. Kelly’s centrality to the economy, one wonders what is  literally  on his desk. Beyond a clock, a cloisonné pen jar and a surprisingly empty outbox, there are hastily scribbled notes on a monogrammed pad from a meeting with a certain “Tim G.” (Timothy F. Geithner, the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York and Barack Obama’s pick to run the Treasury?). The notes make reference to “ad com updates” and “FVA’s,” and contain the jotted notion that the current situation may not be a “pushback issue” after all. “I can’t tell you how many people have come to me recently and said, ‘I hope you’re keeping notes,’ ” Mr. Kelly, a self-described history buff, confessed. “But it’s not like this is stuff that you forget. I always have a sense of gravitas and of history in the making.” History, like a powerful smell, is everywhere in Mr. Kelly’s office: in its address (1 Wall Street); in its artwork (antique paintings); in its century-old grandfather clock, which stands there like a footman at the wall. But the office’s most historic piece is the view from out the window: It is of Alexander Hamilton’s grave  resting place of the bank’s founder  10 stories down in the Trinity Church cemetery directly across the street. History, of course, can be a guidepost, but it can also be a burden, and a metaphorist could surely make much of the fact that Mr. Kelly’s office is wedged between a graveyard and the Stock Exchange. There are those who have complained his bank is too ensconced in the establishment to oversee the bailout, but as Hamilton, the elitist, might have said: Experience sometimes counts. As for Mr. Kelly, he is tangibly aware that a page torn from his notepad might easily hang one day beside that bank note in the alcove. Such thoughts tend to give a man the long view of the rush of daily events. In fact, he told a story of Moshe Dayan, the great Israeli general, who was scouting out a battlefield near Syria one day. He took his fellow generals to the border and showed them with a finger where he planned to place his infantry and tanks. “And the generals were amazed,” Mr. Kelly said. “They said: ‘We’ve never done this before. How do you know where they should go?’ Dayan explained that actually, this battle had been fought a dozen times in the last 2,000 years. “ ‘We’re just doing it again,’ he said. ‘Right now.’ ” More Articles in New York Region » A version of this article appeared in print on December 2, 2008, on page A28 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DB1F30F936A3575BC0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING | EUROPE; RUSSIA: SUIT AGAINST BANK DELAYED<date>Published: August 5, 2008</date><text>Hearings in a closely watched, $22 billion lawsuit against the Bank of New York in a Russian court were postponed until October after one of the witnesses, Robert Blakey, an expert on United States antiracketeering law, fell ill. Russian authorities are suing the bank, claiming it made improper wire transfers out of Russia in the late 1990s, at a time when capital flight helped deflate the Russian economy. The bank maintains that even if it loses, the court's judgment will not be enforceable outside Russia and that it now has few assets in the country. The next hearing is Oct. 6.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/27/business/economy/27gret.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">How One Borrower Beat the Foreclosure Machine<date>Published: July 27, 2008</date><text>MAMIE RUTH PALMER isn’t a celebrity. People magazine doesn’t chronicle her every move. The paparazzi don’t wait for a photo op outside of the modest Atlanta home where she has lived since 1987. Skip to next paragraph Related Columnist Page: Gretchen Morgenson Times Topics: Mortgages and the Markets Add to Portfolio Bank of New York Company Go to your Portfolio » But in some mortgage circles, Ms. Palmer, a 74-year-old former housekeeper, has earned her moment of fame. After enduring six years in foreclosure hell, almost losing her home twice, Ms. Palmer has escaped intact. Last month she received a settlement from the Bank of New York, the trustee for a vast pool of mortgages that included hers. Under the terms of the deal, the bank reduced Ms. Palmer’s loan balance to $59,000 from about $100,000 and has agreed to accept the proceeds of a reverse mortgage in full satisfaction of her obligation. The settlement also eliminated about $12,000 in foreclosure fees added to her debt and called for the installation of central air-conditioning in Ms. Palmer’s home. Roughly $10,000 in legal fees billed over five years by Ms. Palmer’s lawyer, Howard D. Rothbloom, will be covered by payments she has made toward her mortgage while she was battling foreclosure. “I feel good,” Ms. Palmer said last week. “It’s been a long time coming.” To celebrate, she said, she is going to Florida to fish with her nephew. Ms. Palmer’s case is hardly unique. It’s just one of a swelling number that revolve around the thorny issue of who owns the note on a home when it’s forced into foreclosure proceedings. In the seemingly long-ago era when banks held on to the mortgage loans they made, this was a straightforward matter. But today, amid the freewheeling packaging of mortgage loans into securities that are sold off to investors, it’s much less clear who controls the note  all of which promises to cause banks enormous legal and financial headaches as foreclosures mount. The added twist is that some judges are taking the borrowers’ side in foreclosure disputes, precisely because of murkiness surrounding notes. In 2002, Ms. Palmer filed for bankruptcy protection to protect her home from a quick sale on the courthouse steps. She continued to make mortgage payments, to the bankruptcy court. Mr. Rothbloom took her case in 2003, suing the Bank of New York for levying fees on Ms. Palmer that had not been authorized by the bankruptcy court. The note securing the property was assigned to Bank of New York in September 2002, two months after it had begun foreclosure proceedings against Ms. Palmer. As a result, Mr. Rothbloom maintained, the bank had no standing to foreclose. The two sides battled for five years, until last month. “The Ms. Palmers of the world can’t afford to resolve these types of disputes,” Mr. Rothbloom said. “So they usually wind up losing their homes.” Bank of New York declined to comment on the settlement. The problems associated with banks that begin foreclosure proceedings when they do not have proper legal standing are now looming larger in the mortgage meltdown. Loans were heaped into trusts with little documentation of ownership or proper loan assignments  it was all about volume and the fees that came with it  and now that sloppiness is hurting both lenders and borrowers. Mr. Rothbloom said he had another case in which the lender’s representative has been unable to prove ownership for two and a half years. Meanwhile, consumer lawyers fear that borrowers are being pushed out of their homes by companies that have no right to do so. Such a prospect is particularly worrisome for residents in states that allow lenders to foreclose without court supervision, known as nonjudicial foreclosure states. Georgia is one; its borrowers can lose their homes on the courthouse steps less than a month after foreclosure notices have been posted. To try to protect its borrowers, Georgia just instituted a law requiring that lenders moving to foreclose on a borrower must file proof in county records that they own the underlying property before the home goes to foreclosure sale. “We believe that many of these companies can’t find the assignments,” said William J. Brennan Jr., director of the Home Defense Program of the Atlanta Legal Aid Society. “If they can never prove ownership, then they can never foreclose.” 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5DC153DF936A25754C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Appointments With Red Ink<date>Published: July 15, 2008</date><text>Vikram S. Pandit summoned 60 executives to Armonk, N.Y., last Tuesday to present his plan to buck up Citigroup, the beleaguered bank he runs. But his seven-point proposal, called ''Rules of the Road,'' will do nothing to cushion the blows that are likely to come in the days and weeks ahead, when Citigroup and other big banks are expected to report yet another round of grim quarterly results. As fears spread about the health of the financial sector Monday, when shares of many regional banks plunged, investors were bracing for even more bad news from some of the nation's largest financial companies, among them Citigroup. On Thursday, Merrill Lynch, the nation's largest brokerage, is expected to disclose billions of dollars of new write-downs and a big quarterly loss. That same day, JPMorgan Chase is likely to report its profit fell by half. And on Friday, Citigroup is expected to report its third straight quarter in the red. Citigroup, the financial conglomerate formed a decade ago, reflects many of the ills plaguing the industry. As home prices continue to decline and the economy struggles, Americans are falling behind on their mortgages and home equity loans in growing numbers. Delinquencies on auto loans and credit cards are on the rise. Concern is growing about souring loans made to builders and commercial real estate developers. Citigroup is exposed to all of this. It has recorded more than $45 billion in credit losses and write-downs since mid-2007 and lost nearly $15 billion in the last two quarters. Its shareholders have paid a steep price: The stock has lost nearly 70 percent of its value in the last year. On Monday, Citigroup shares fell 6 percent lower, closing at $15.22, the lowest share price since the company was formed in 1998. ''There is no place to hide for them,'' said Meredith A. Whitney, an Oppenheimer banking analyst. ''They are the biggest bank, which means they had big exposures to every asset class.'' Mr. Pandit, who has been chief executive for eight months, is trying to turn around Citigroup as the banking industry struggles through one of its most challenging periods since the Depression. His task is particularly difficult because many Citigroup bankers, paid with stock and options for years, have seen their fortunes vanish. Morale is low. Last week, at the company's rustic meeting center in Armonk, about 30 miles north of Midtown Manhattan, Mr. Pandit tried to lift spirits and brainstorm for ideas about how to reshape his company's culture. He pushed 60 top managers to build on his seven rules, which he unveiled in the last few weeks. Those rules include items like ''client connectivity,'' ''transparency'' and ''product excellence.'' But some Citigroup insiders roll their eyes at what they see as dull platitudes. Instead of embarking on a bold new course, as some investors had hoped, Mr. Pandit seems to be turning to the playbook of his predecessor, Charles O. Prince III, who was forced out last year. Like Mr. Prince, Mr. Pandit is pursuing plans to promote international and internal growth, and to streamline the company and eliminate thousands of jobs. Mr. Pandit is also trying to reshape Citigroup's culture, just as Mr. Prince did in his first year as chief executive. Mr. Pandit's executives say they are confident the strategy will pay off, but they have no illusions about how long it may take. ''This isn't like a sprint. This really is a marathon,'' said Gary L. Crittenden, Citigroup's finance chief. It could be two to three years before the bank's returns improve significantly, he said. Wall Street is growing impatient. ''Some of the objectives set forth have been in motion for many years,'' said William Tanona, who follows Citigroup for Goldman Sachs. ''With each passing quarter, there will be increased urgency for people to see results.'' Since becoming chief executive, Mr. Pandit has raised about $40 billion in capital, and announced plans to eliminate more than 19,000 jobs. Amid a scathing risk management review by the Federal Reserve, Mr. Pandit installed Brian R. Leach, a trusted hand, as the bank's chief risk officer and overhauled the organizational chart. Mr. Pandit's senior executives say he has led thoughtful, probing business reviews. revamped reporting lines so that regional executives can make decisions faster. ''If you want to be in the emerging markets and be successful, you have to be locally empowered,'' said Ajay Banga, who oversees Citigroup's operations in Asia. A bonus plan to reward managers for working together is next. Even so, Mr. Pandit had mixed success firing up his troops. And privately, some senior Citigroup managers say they are sometimes frustrated that he does not always include them in making decisions that affect their businesses. Part of this is the need to move quickly, they say. Mr. Pandit keeps close counsel with a handful of trusted lieutenants that many say is the real power base within Citigroup. Internally, it is known as the Gang of Five. Citigroup board members have also warned Mr. Pandit about being more forthcoming with them. Alain J. P. Belda, Citigroup's lead director, and several other board members were upset when they learned about major moves in the press; Mr. Prince, a smoother politician, took pains to alert them to big changes. It would not be surprising if Richard D. Parsons, Time Warner's chairman, takes over for Mr. Belda as lead director when board seats are rotated this summer, according to a person briefed on the situation. The hope is that Mr. Parsons's easy-going style might improve relations. In a statement, Mr. Belda did not address the past but said Citigroup's board is ''well apprised of all significant changes'' and was not aware of any director, including himself, feeling out of the information loop. PHOTO: Vikram S. Pandit, Citigroup's chief executive, is trying to raise spirits at the bank.(PHOTOGRAPH BY JIN LEE/BLOOMBERG NEWS)(pg. C4) DRAWING(C1)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5D7113DF932A35754C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING | EUROPE; Russia: Bank of New York Fights $22.5. Billion Claim<date>Published: July 1, 2008</date><text>Lawyers for the Bank of New York Mellon were in a Russian court to defend the bank against a $22.5 billion claim filed by the Russian customs service relating to a money laundering scandal in the late 1990s. Under a novel legal theory, a group of Miami lawyers working on a contingency basis has taken the case for the customs service and argued that the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act should be applied in Russia. The bank said the United States law cannot be applied by a Russian court, that the money transfers did not amount to a crime covered by the act and that the damage claim is not supported by evidence. The bank flew a former attorney general, Richard Thornburgh, above, to Moscow to make the arguments as an expert witness. The judge, however, Lyudmila Pulova, postponed the hearing before he could testify. The next hearing is Thursday; Mr. Thornburgh was scheduled to leave Moscow on Wednesday. The bank has not set aside reserves against an adverse judgment, saying the Russian court ruling will in any case not be enforceable in the United States. PHOTO</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/22/business/22swap.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Not Your Ordinary Swap Meet<date>Published: February 22, 2008</date><text>An obscure pressure point in the credit squeeze popped up this week when a boutique investment bank in Houston held a “public auction” for dozens of the most arcane products in the financial world. The auctioneer was the Sanders Morris Harris Group, whose chairman is George L. Ball, a former governor of the American Stock Exchange who served high-profile stints at the helms of Smith Barney Shearson and Prudential nearly two decades ago. The auction was announced last week in legal notices in the back pages of The Wall Street Journal. The notices looked like the kind that advertise a sheriff’s sale of repossessed cars, but actually invited bids on 55 “synthetic securities,” put up for sale on Wednesday along with dozens of more conventional “securities”  mostly pools of mortgages with ratings ranging from so-so to awful  that were auctioned over two days. The notices warned that all the goods, like fine art at Sotheby’s, “may be subject to a reserve level,” allowing the seller to refuse all bids if none met its minimum price. So, given the jitters in the market, how did it go? Hard to say. Mr. Ball’s firm declined to comment on the auction at all, citing the wishes of its client, the Bank of New York Mellon Corporation’s trust company, which arranged the auction for an unnamed investor. The Bank of New York, in turn, declined to disclose either who was selling the swaps and securities or how the auction went. “In our role as trustee, we can’t comment on the results of this or any other auction,” said Kevin Heine, a spokesman for the bank. So about all that can be said is that the seller is not related to Mr. Ball’s firm  Mr. Heine was authorized to say that the bank picked the firm because it is a neutral party  and had pretty sophisticated tastes. The 55 “synthetic securities” up for bid were described as “pay-as-you-go credit default swaps.” They are a mutation of products originally meant to provide protection to investors if a corporate borrower defaulted on its bonds or other debts. In recent years, however, default swaps have become a popular way to place bets on corporate credit trends among traders with no vested interest in the underlying debt. That has prompted enormous growth both in swaps volume  the market is now estimated at more than $45 trillion  and in the potential risks in what remains an opaque, largely unregulated market. For example, the American International Group recently reported that it had miscalculated the value of swaps contracts on its books, an error that added $3.6 billion to its loss estimates for last year. But unlike plain vanilla credit default swaps  if such a thing can be said to exist  the pay-as-you-go swaps do not involve a one-time payment to cover a default on a corporate bond, a pool of mortgages or some other debt instrument. Instead, they involve the payment of ongoing obligations on debt instruments that, because of their terms, may not be subject to a clear default trigger. These 55 swaps, in particular, involved promises to pay shortfalls on various collections of mortgage loans, most of which have been sharply downgraded by ratings agencies in recent weeks. If these had been more conventional credit default swaps, there would have been a much more visible way to sell them. Indeed, last Tuesday, just such an auction was held for credit default swaps affected by the bankruptcy of Québecor World, a Canadian printing company that filed for protection under Canada’s bankruptcy laws on Jan. 21. There is no mystery about the outcome of that event. Unlike the Houston auction, it was conducted pretty much in plain sight. Bids and offers were submitted through an electronic auction platform created by Creditex, an interdealer execution platform for credit derivatives, and Markit Group, a price information service. The results  which allowed participants to calculate the value of their swap obligations by fixing the price of the underlying debt at 41.25 cents on the dollar  were verified by Markit and jointly announced by the two firms on Tuesday afternoon. In fact, the bids submitted by each of the 13 participating dealers, by name, is posted on the Internet at www.creditfixings.com. “You can go check our math,” joked Mazy Dar, chief strategic officer for Creditex. The firm has now conducted 11 credit default swap auctions, beginning with one for swaps involving Collins &amp; Aikman debt in 2005. Other auctions involved the debt of Market Gallery, Delta Air Lines, Northwest Airlines, Corporation"&gt;Delphi Corporation, Corporation"&gt;Calpine Corporation, Corporation"&gt;Dana Corporation and Dura. The process is sufficiently trusted that 589 market participants agreed in advance, through the International Swaps and Derivatives Association, to abide by whatever settlement price the auction established for the Quebecor-related swaps. But unlike widely traded credit default swaps, which have become fairly standardized, pay-as-you-go swaps remain highly individualized. Underscoring how distinctive each of the 55 swap contracts are, Sanders Morris Harris offered to supply “the complete terms of any synthetic security” to interested bidders. And, obviously, since these highly differentiated swaps are rarely traded, there’s no market price to guide bidders  or owners. Hence, the public announcement of the unpublic auction. Bankers said that, while this was not a first, “synthetic securities” auctions like the one in Houston are still pretty rare  so far. But as more holders of these oddball swaps look for ways to value them, or unload them, it might be a good idea to check the legal notices a little more often. More Articles in Business »</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/18/business/18bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Write-Down Contributes to Profit Fall at Trust Bank<date>Published: January 18, 2008</date><text>Washington Mutual, the savings and loan, said on Thursday that it had swung to a $1.87 billion loss in the fourth quarter, hurt badly by the sinking value of its mortgage portfolio. The quarterly loss was $2.19 a share, compared with a profit of $1.06 billion, or $1.10 a share in the period a year ago. The earnings included a write down of $1.6 billion that the firm had previously disclosed. It also set aside $1.53 billion to cover loan losses, within the range of $1.5 billion to $1.6 billion it forecast in December. Revenue, including net interest income, or what the bank made on loans minus what was paid out on deposits, and non-interest income, or the cash WaMu made from mortgage loan service fees and other fees and charges, totaled $3.41 billion, lower than analyst’s expectation of $3.51 billion. At the Bank of New York Mellon, fourth-quarter profit declined 68 percent because of its exposure to assets backed by mortgages and a strong quarter a year ago, when the bank gained $1.4 billion after unloading its retail operations. Its core businesses  managing assets and providing middleman services between investors and other financial institutions  performed well, though. Its shares fell 32 cents, to $44.77. Because it is a trust bank that runs funds for companies and wealthy individuals rather than a retail bank for the mass market, Bank of New York Mellon has avoided exposure to the consumer problems afflicting other banks. Still, it was vulnerable to mortgage defaults through collateralized debt obligations, or C.D.O.’s. The bank’s exposure to those pools of mortgage-backed debt resulted in a $118 million write-down in the latest quarter, or $200 million pretax. Also, the bank brought a debt vehicle it had managed onto its balance sheet, as many banks have done. That led to a $180 million charge. Quarterly net income was $520 million, or 45 cents a share, down sharply from $1.63 billion, or $2.27 a share, in the period a year ago. Income from continuing operations was 67 cents a share, excluding a one-time merger-and-integration expense and a charge for restructuring and consolidating the assets of the Three Rivers Funding Corporation. In the same period a year earlier, earnings from continuing operations were 61 cents a share. Revenue in the quarter totaled $3.81 billion, more than double the $1.89 billion a year ago. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial, on average, predicted higher fourth-quarter earnings, 69 cents a share, and lower revenue, $3.75 billion. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/21/business/21siv.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">BlackRock Is Likely to Lead Banks’ Safety Net Fund<date>Published: November 21, 2007</date><text>BlackRock, the big investment firm, is expected to be the main asset manager for a $75 billion fund being created by three large banks to help shore up the market for asset-backed securities, a person briefed on the situation said late yesterday. A custodian for the fund could also be named shortly, according to people with knowledge of the matter, and one leading contender is Bank of New York Mellon. No official announcements have been made on either position. But with plans under way to begin raising more than $60 billion for the fund as early as next week, there is a heightened sense of urgency to fill both roles. The countrys three biggest banks  Bank of America, Citigroup and JPMorgan Chase  settled on the structure of the proposed fund about a week ago, after two months of complicated negotiations against the backdrop of deteriorating economic conditions. Banks and government officials are hoping that the backup fund will allow the financial instruments known as structured investment vehicles, or SIVs, to sell in an orderly fashion the more than $250 billion in assets they hold and avoid severe disruption to the already jittery credit markets. If BlackRock is appointed manager, as expected, it will be responsible for managing the securities sold into the funds portfolio, deciding whether to sell an asset at a particular price or hold it to maturity. It is not clear whether BlackRock will determine the prices or if they will be set by an outside party. The firm, which is known for its keen attention to risk, would lend both credibility and capital markets expertise to a proposal that has been shaky from the start. Recently, the firms profile has been raised with the ascension of Laurence D. Fink, its founder and chief executive, who was on the short list for the top job at Merrill Lynch and is still considered a potential candidate to run Citigroup. But BlackRock has kept its head down amid the turbulent markets. The firm recently indicated it had less than 1 percent of its cash assets invested in SIV-related debt. And it has largely steered clear of the subprime mortgage investments that have gone bad, spreading distress throughout the financial industry. BlackRock was chosen over at least two other investment management firms for the right to handle the assets of the backup fund, according to people briefed on the matter, even though Mr. Fink had previously been reserved about BlackRocks participation in the fund. A lot of the people who need to participate have needy issues and as a competitor you would like to shine a little better relative to your needy competitors, Mr. Fink said when he was questioned about selling assets into the fund while on a recent conference call announcing third-quarter earnings. He added, however, that on the other hand, youve got to have the bigger picture, making sure, if this works, it helps stabilize our markets, it helps stabilize issues surrounding our clients. Brian Beades, a BlackRock spokesman, declined to comment. The bank chosen for the custodian assignment would oversee the financial record-keeping and other back-office operations for the new fund. It would be a prominent and potentially lucrative task for Bank of New York Mellon, which has largely shunned the spotlight despite its legacy as Americas oldest bank, founded 223 years ago by Alexander Hamilton. Kevin Heine, a spokesman for the bank, declined to comment. It typically takes six months to a year for a bank to set up an ordinary structured investment vehicle, but the so-called super-SIV, though far larger and more complex, was put together by the three banks in a matter of weeks with the encouragement of the Treasury Department. How much effect it will have is unclear; many investors and analysts are skeptical that it will do much to help. Debt market conditions have rapidly deteriorated in the last few weeks as investor appetites for pools of assets  from mortgages to auto and, more recently, credit card loans  have all but dried up. And virtually all SIVs are trying to sell the securities they hold, doubting that the proposed backup fund will work. The funds organizers hope that it will buy enough time for asset prices to recover, although most market analysts say that is improbable. It may, however, discourage SIVs from dumping their holdings all at once, a move that could cause securities prices to collapse. That would force banks to take even bigger write-offs and could also put pressure on money market funds, whose exposure to SIV-issued commercial paper could put them in jeopardy. Bank of America, Citigroup and JPMorgan Chase are each expected to put up $5 billion to $10 billion for the fund. The remaining $60 billion or so is expected to be raised from dozens of financial institutions, including several outside the United States. Bank of America and JPMorgan will lead the fund-raising effort, while Citigroup takes a back seat. People involved with the plan said that Citigroup lacked credibility to sell the plan to investors, because it could disproportionately benefit if the plan provided relief to the seven troubled SIVs it operates. Officials at Bank of America, JPMorgan and Citigroup either did not return calls seeking comment or could not be reached. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF163EF930A2575AC0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">3 Banks Join System for Trading Unregistered Securities<date>Published: September 13, 2007</date><text>Bank of America, the Credit Suisse Group and UBS announced yesterday that they would join five other banks as members of a private system that lets institutional investors trade unregistered securities. The three firms will collaborate with Lehman Brothers Holdings, Citigroup, Merrill Lynch, Morgan Stanley and Bank of New York Mellon. The system, called the Open Platform for Unregistered Securities, or OPUS-5, tracks the number of shareholders who invest in the offerings to ensure they comply with United States regulations, according to a joint statement yesterday. Publicly traded American companies have raised $45.4 billion this year selling securities that are not registered with regulators, according to data compiled by Sagient Research Systems in San Diego. A Securities and Exchange Commission rule allows such ''private placements'' when securities are sold to no more than 499 institutional buyers, each with at least $100 million in discretionary assets. Such sales do not require the more extensive disclosures required when selling stocks or bonds to the public. Goldman, FBR Capital Markets, JPMorgan Chase and Bear Stearns operate systems similar to OPUS-5.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D9133CF936A2575BC0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Banks to Offer Private-Stock Trading<date>Published: August 15, 2007</date><text>Five of Wall Street's biggest banks, including Citigroup, Lehman Brothers and Merrill Lynch, said yesterday that they were setting up a system to trade privately placed stocks. The group, which also includes the underwriter Morgan Stanley and Bank of New York Mellon, said the system would start operating in September. It will serve companies looking to raise capital without the scrutiny given to publicly listed companies. The platform, the Open Platform for Unregistered Securities, or Opus-5, would be an alternative to those introduced by Goldman Sachs and JPMorgan Chase. Bear Stearns announced yesterday that it had started a similar platform, Best Markets. These platforms are open only to big money managers already dealing in private stock and debt transactions. Today, Nasdaq Stock Market is to introduce its own platform for private securities, Portal, which could supersede the bank-run systems.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/18/business/worldbusiness/18bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Russia Sues U.S. Bank; Laundering Case Cited<date>Published: May 18, 2007</date><text>The Federal Customs Service of Russia is seeking $22.5 billion in damages from the Bank of New York Company over accusations of money laundering in the 1990s. The bank committed violations of Russian law that resulted in damages of $22.5 billion to the state from 1996 to 1999, Maxim Smal, a lawyer for the service, said by phone after filing the lawsuit in the Moscow Arbitration Court yesterday. Andrei Stukov, head of the Customs Services legal department, confirmed the amount of damages sought, via a spokeswoman. Mr. Smal said the suit was almost entirely based on an investigation in the United States that ended in 2005 with the bank agreeing to pay $38 million to settle two criminal investigations and admitting it failed to report $7 billion in suspicious Russian transactions. The American investigation uncovered very serious violations, Mr. Smal said, but he declined to elaborate, saying more details will be revealed today at a news conference in Moscow. The Bank of New York, which said it had not received official notification of the suit, called it totally without merit. Lawyers representing the agency had approached it and offered to settle out of court for a tiny fraction of the amount now claimed, the bank said. A former Bank of New York vice president based in London, Lucy Edwards, and her husband, Peter Berlin, who ran companies with accounts at the bank, admitted in 2000 to conspiring to use the bank to launder more than $7 billion from Russia. The couple, both Russian émigrés, were sentenced last year to five years of probation after cooperating with New York federal prosecutors investigating international money laundering. Bank of New York sold its retail branches in October and two months later agreed to merge with the Mellon Financial Corporation to create a bank that acts as a custodian for investor assets. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/10/business/10banks.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Banks Settle Claims in Auction Inquiry<date>Published: January 10, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, Jan. 9 (Dow Jones/AP)  A subsidiary of Deutsche Bank, the Bank of New York Company and the Wilmington Trust Company have agreed to pay a combined $1.6 million to settle claims in an investigation of the $200 billion auction-rate securities market. The Securities and Exchange Commission announced the settlements on Tuesday, the second set of settlements to grow out of an inquiry into the auction-rate bond market. In May, 15 brokerage firms agreed to settle accusations of violations in the same market. In the case of the three banks, the S.E.C. found that from at least January 2003 through June 30, 2004, the banks accepted initial or revised bids after submission deadlines and allowed brokerage firms to intervene in auctions. In some cases, this conduct affected the rate paid on the securities, the S.E.C. said. Deutsche Bank Trust Americas, a subsidiary of Deutsche Bank, and Bank of New York each agreed to pay $750,000. Wilmington Trust agreed to pay $100,000. Rick Pepperman, a lawyer for the Bank of New York, referred calls to the company. Michael DiGregorio, the general counsel at Wilmington, referred calls to the company’s press office. A lawyer for Deutsche Bank Trust was not available to comment. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/09/business/09five.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Wall St. Gets Gifts From Deal Makers and Court<date>Published: December 9, 2006</date><text>SEVERAL large gifts arrived for investors and for Wall Street. Merger fever and cooling concern about inflation lifted stocks, while a federal appeals court appeared to save big investment firms from having to defend against a huge class-action lawsuit. Skip to next paragraph MOST POPULAR Following are the most-popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Dec. 2 through Dec. 8: 1. Spam Doubles, Finding New Ways to Deliver Itself 2. Vista Is Ready. Are You? 3. What Statistics on Home Sales Aren't Saying 4. Blowing the Whistle on Big Oil 5. Wal-Mart Says Thank You to Workers There were disappointments, too, notably for the worlds biggest pharmaceutical company, which lost its most promising new drug. BIG NICHE PLAYER Bank of New York agreed to buy Mellon Financial of Pittsburgh for $16.5 billion in stock, a deal that would cement the banks role as the worlds largest securities servicing firm. Such firms provide behind-the-scenes services like administering hedge funds directed by others and keeping records on who owns corporate bonds. The combined company will have $16.6 trillion in assets under custody and act as corporate trustee for an additional $8 trillion in assets. Bank of New York, which was founded by Alexander Hamilton in 1784, and Mellon, founded more than a century ago by Judge Thomas Mellon, said the merger would let them cut costs by $700 million a year, in part by shedding about one-tenth of their 40,000 employees over three years. While the combined company, to be called Bank of New York Mellon, would be based in New York, Mellons chairman and chief executive, Robert Kelly, said the cash management and stock transfer operations would stay in Pittsburgh. A DRUGS SUDDEN DEMISE Pfizer, the worlds biggest pharmaceutical company, pulled the plug on its most important experimental drug, a treatment for heart disease, just two days after its chief executive predicted it would be one of the most important drugs in a generation. The decision, which came after clinical tests showed the drug was associated with increased risk of heart attack, was a stunning development that will probably seriously damage the companys prospects through the next decades. Pfizer had $51 billion in sales last year. Cardiologists had raised concerns about the drug, called torcetrapib, noting that it raised blood pressure in many patients, a serious side effect for a heart medicine. It is unclear whether torcetrapibs failure suggests that other drugs aimed at raising the so-called good cholesterol will also face unexpected problems in trials. Pfizer, which recently said it would cut 2,200 jobs in the United States, may lay off as many 10,000 more people in the near future, analysts said. DODGING A BULLET Wall Street banks will not have to face a huge securities class-action lawsuit accusing them of cheating small investors out of hundreds of millions of dollars by manipulating the prices of initial public offerings of technology companies during the market boom of the 1990s, a federal appeals court ruled. A three-judge panel of the Federal Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in Manhattan, said a federal judge overseeing the lawsuit had erred in granting class-action status to 310 investors who had separately contended the banks had awarded shares of hot initial offerings to favored clients to attract investment banking business, conspired with clients to inflate prices by bidding up shares in the market, and created misleading research to lure investors into buying. Investors will probably have to pursue their claims individually, in some cases perhaps through arbitration, lawyers involved in the case said. Earlier settlements in the case, in particular a $425 million agreement with J. P. Morgan Chase, could be nullified by this decision. The Supreme Court will hear a related case, in which investment banks seek to insulate themselves from antitrust lawsuits filed by investors because, the banks contend, they are so heavily regulated by the Securities and Exchange Commission. FRONT-RUNNER STUMBLES Acknowledging it has become too bureaucratic to compete effectively against nimbler rivals, Yahoo, the leading Internet destination, said it was restructuring its operations and shuffling its management ranks. Daniel L. Rosensweig, the chief operating officer since April 2002, and Lloyd Braun, the former ABC executive who has run Yahoos media group, will leave, and the chief financial officer, Susan L. Decker, will take on additional responsibilities. At the same time, Yahoo is reorganizing itself into three operating units: one focused on its audience, one on its advertisers and publishers, and a third focused on developing technology for the rest of the company. The goal is to regain momentum against rivals like Google, which is extending its lead as the top search engine, and MySpace, the social networking site that threatens to take over Yahoo in total audience. Farzad Nazem, Yahoos chief technical officer, will run the technology group, and the company said it would seek outside executives to lead its audience group and to serve as finance chief. LESS IS MORE BETTER The Labor Department said that unit labor costs, a measure of what workers earn that takes into account their productivity, rose more slowly than expected in the third quarter, easing pressure on the Federal Reserve to resume raising interest rates and risk derailing the economy. Labor costs rose 2.3 percent in the third quarter, less than a preliminary estimate of 3.8 percent issued last month. The government also said that labor costs actually fell in the second quarter by 2.4 percent, reversing an earlier estimate suggesting they had risen 5.4 percent. The Feds policy-making Open Market Committee will meet on Tuesday to decide whether to raise short-term interest rates, cut them or leave them steady. HONOR SYSTEM In a scathing report to Congress, the Interior Departments inspector generals office says it found pervasive problems in a program intended to make sure companies pay the royalties they owe on billions of dollars of oil and gas extracted from federal lands. While investigators did not estimate the amount of money that the government might be losing, they did say the government was vulnerable to being short-changed because the agencys data were often inaccurate, its officials relied on oil company promises rather than actual records and it reviewed only about 9 percent of all oil and gas leases. The report undermines claims by top Interior officials that the department is aggressively pursuing underpayments and outright cheating by companies that drill on property owned by the American public. The departments Minerals Management Service, which collects royalties, said it would deliver the plan to act on many of the recommendations within 30 days. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/05/business/05bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York and Mellon Will Merge<date>Published: December 5, 2006</date><text>Bank of New York and Mellon Financial of Pittsburgh have agreed to merge in a $16.5 billion deal that will create a securities-processing powerhouse in a little-noticed corner of the financial world. Skip to next paragraph Related More From DealBook The deal, which was announced yesterday, would create the largest custodian in the financial services industry, keeping track of more than $16.6 trillion worth of assets for huge endowments, mutual funds and pension plans for whom it acts as a corporate trustee. The merged bank will also have an expanded international presence, as Mellons $1 trillion global asset management business will vault it into the industrys top 10. The combined company will be called the Bank of New York Mellon Corporation  a mouthful that links a New York bank founded by Alexander Hamilton in 1784 with a family that helped finance Pittsburghs transformation into a steel-making center. The bank will be based in New York. The deal may usher in a new wave of consolidation in a fragmented securities-processing industry. A relatively mundane business, the back-office recordkeeping of the securities positions of large institutional investors can be enormously profitable, but it is increasingly a commodity business dependent on scale. While it is unlikely that other leading institutions, like J. P. Morgan, State Street and Northern Trust, will merge with each other, they or some European banks could snap up smaller custody businesses. We viewed this strategically, said Robert P. Kelly, chief executive of Mellon, who will head the successor bank. We need to grow faster and generate the excess capital to win the arms race over the next decade. The deal helped buoy stocks yesterday, with both companies rising sharply and a rally in financial stocks. Bank of New York shares soared 12 percent, to $39.75. Mellon Financial rose 6.8 percent, to $42.78. For both institutions, the deal also represents a sort of reversal of fortune. Eight years ago, the Bank of New York tried to take over Mellon with an unsolicited offer that was quickly rebuffed. Yesterday, Mellon was in the drivers seat, providing the chief executive for the new bank. The board, though, will be controlled by Bank of New York. Under the deal, Bank of New York shareholders are receiving a 6.7 percent premium, while Mellon shareholders are essentially getting none. Mellon shareholders will receive one share in the combined company for each of their current shares; Bank of New York owners will get 0.943 share for each of theirs. Although the deal is being represented as a merger of equals, Bank of New Yorks current holders will control roughly 63 percent of the new company; Mellon holders will own about 37 percent. For Bank of New York, the deal is the latest step along a strategic path to bolster its position as leader in securities services industry and spur its growth. Earlier this year, Bank of New York shed most of its struggling retail banking business by swapping many branches for J. P. Morgan Chases corporate trust unit, a move that doubled the size of its debt-issuance recordkeeping business. With Mellon, the bank will now leap-frog Morgan as the biggest player in the custody business. It will also get Mellons asset management, a faster-growing business that may increase its stock multiple. And with at least $700 million projected annually in cost savings over the next three years, executives hope that money can be plowed back into their existing businesses to propel growth. About 3,900 workers, or a little less than 10 percent of the combined companys 40,000 employees, are expected to lose their jobs over the next three years. While the companies said they had not yet determined specific businesses or locations, the areas with the biggest overlap include asset servicing, technology and corporate staff members. The deal also engineers a smooth succession for Thomas A. Renyi, Bank of New Yorks 60-year-old chairman and chief executive, who will oversee the transition but will step aside 18 months after the Mellon transaction is complete. Mr. Kelly, 52, who took over as Mellons chairman and chief less than a year ago, will become the new companys chief executive and is expected to take over Mr. Renyis chairman role. Neither top executive will benefit from a change-in-control payout, the companies said. Compensation details for other senior managers will be worked out later, according to a person close to the deal. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/27/business/worldbusiness/27bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Probation in Money-Laundering Case<date>Published: July 27, 2006</date><text>A former officer at the Bank of New York and her husband were sentenced to five years probation yesterday, almost six years after they admitted conspiring to use the bank to launder more than $7 billion from Russia. The executive, Lucy Edwards, 48, who was a vice president of the bank and based in London, and her husband, Peter Berlin, 51, who ran companies with accounts at the bank, pleaded guilty in February 2000 and agreed to cooperate with prosecutors investigating money laundering. We had no right to bring the wild habits of the Russian business environment onto American soil, Mr. Berlin told Judge Shirley Wohl Kram in federal court in Manhattan. Ms. Edwards and Mr. Berlin will spend six months in home detention in New Jersey. They must make restitution of $685,000 to the Internal Revenue Service and pay fines of $20,000 each. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/21/business/21bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Business Loans Help Banks to Higher Profit<date>Published: April 21, 2006</date><text>By Reuters The Bank of America Corporation led several large banks in posting higher first-quarter profits yesterday, as strength in business borrowing and capital markets offset mixed results from consumer operations. Earnings rose 13.5 percent at Bank of America, 9 percent at the BB&amp;T Corporation and 12 percent at the Bank of New York Company. The PNC Financial Services Group posted a 15 percent jump excluding a one-time item. Net income at Bank of America, which is based in Charlotte, N.C., rose to $4.99 billion, from a restated $4.39 billion in the period a year earlier. Profit per share was unchanged at $1.07, or $1.08 excluding merger and revamping costs. Revenue increased 31 percent, to $17.94 billion. Results benefited from a 40 percent surge in investment banking fees and a record $1.07 billion of trading profits. The Jan. 1 purchase of the MBNA Corporation nearly tripled credit card fees. Cards now account for more than a fourth of Bank of America's earnings. The bank added a net 483,000 savings accounts and 603,000 checking accounts in the quarter. Net income at BB&amp;T, which is based in Winston-Salem, N.C., and is one of the 10 largest banks in the nation, rose to $431.5 million, or 79 cents a per share, from $395.4 million, or 71 cents a share. Net income for PNC, based in Pittsburgh, was unchanged at $354 million. Net income for Bank of New York rose to $422 million, or 55 cents a share, from $379 million, or 49 cents a share. Revenue increased 22 percent, to $2.33 billion, from $1.9 billion. More Articles in Business »</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/09/business/09bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">2 Banks Agree To Swap Units In Deal Worth $3.1 Billion<date>Published: April 9, 2006</date><text>J.P. Morgan Chase said yesterday that it had agreed to swap its corporate trust business for virtually all of Bank of New York's branches in the metropolitan area. The $3.1 billion deal highlights the appeal and the challenges of the country's wealthiest banking market. The deal will give J.P. Morgan 338 additional branches, solidifying its dominance in the area at a time when rivals like Citigroup and Bank of America are aggressively trying to expand their market share. The branches will be turned into Chase branches starting next spring. Bank of New York, meanwhile, will nearly double the size of its corporate trust business, which handles record-keeping for corporate debt issues. The unit has become a major part of the bank's strategy as its retail operations have struggled. The transaction, which was widely expected and will be completed in the third or fourth quarter, underscores how big a battleground for deposits the region has become. Banks are increasingly focused on their branches because they offer a face-to-face opportunity pitch other products to customers, like home equity loans. But rising interest rates, slowing deposit growth and competitive price pressure have made it tough for smaller banks to compete. Bank of America, Wachovia and Commerce Bank have all moved aggressively into the area. And when it announced its $14.6 billion purchase of North Fork Bancorp last month, Capital One Financial said the New York market would be its focus as it moved away from credit cards to become a retail and commercial bank. Bank of New York, which has not invested heavily in its branches, said that it wanted out. "When you look at the national banks competing in this marketplace and those who look to enter this marketplace," said Gerald L. Hassell, Bank of New York's president, "we thought it was strategically important for us to focus" on the trust and private banking businesses. He added: "We were going to be at a competitive disadvantage long-term." J. P. Morgan, which already has 836 Chase branches in the region, wanted to add more. "Retail is a very important part of the business, and it just doesn't stand on its own," said Charles W. Scharf, the head of retail banking. "This is a business where market share does help you grow." About 50 of the banks' branches are too close together, so many of those will likely shut down, but J. P. Morgan executives said they expected minimal job cuts. The move comes as James Dimon, J. P. Morgan's chairman and chief executive, is still trying to integrate systems and overhaul its branches after a 2004 merger with Bank One. "It's a little bit early," Mr. Scharf conceded. "A couple of months later would have been preferable, but we think we can get it done." The deal gives Bank of New York a bigger overseas presence, with 15 offices abroad. "We get very good value for our retail franchise, and we pick up a very good business that replaces the earnings that we give up," said Bruce W. Van Saun, Bank of New York's chief financial officer. Bank of New York expects a gain of $1.3 billion from the sale, with transaction costs of about $120 million; the deal will hurt earnings until 2009. J.P. Morgan anticipates an after-tax gain of between $600 and $700 million. To orchestrate the swap, the banks assigned values of $2.3 billion to the Bank of New York unit and $2.15 billion to the J.P. Morgan unit. J.P. Morgan will pay another $150 million in cash to make up the difference, and potentially $50 million more based on customer retention levels. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDA1230F931A35757C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">OPENERS: SUITS; UNUSUAL WRITE-OFF<date>Published: April 2, 2006</date><text>Executives at the Bank of New York know that lending is a risky business, even when the borrower has ties to John C. Malone, the billionaire cable guy who has been a member of the bank's board for 20 years. In the last two years, the bank has written off $9.7 million that was owed to it by three unidentified affiliates of Liberty Media, according to company filings. Mr. Malone, the chairman of Liberty Media, was not involved in the decisions to repay less than the amounts owed to the bank, said John Orr, a spokesman for Liberty Media. PATRICK McGEEHAN</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/28/business/28bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Coming Soon, a Backup Bank for the Treasury Market<date>Published: February 28, 2006</date><text>A bank created to provide emergency backup for the Treasury market will be ready to operate in the next 18 months, a bond industry group is set to announce today. The so-called NewBank exists largely on paper, but like a superhero on standby, it can spring into action to stabilize the government securities market if a legal or financial disaster strikes. The bank is a result of a five-year effort by government and banking officials to draw up plans in the unlikely event that either J. P. Morgan Chase or the Bank of New York, the only existing clearing banks in the Treasury market, are suddenly unable to operate. The two clearing banks play an obscure but crucial role in the government securities market, processing more than $1.9 trillion of very short-term trades each day between investors who want small but safe returns and dealers who want to finance securities positions. The industry's dependence on just two big institutions has long concerned the Federal Reserve, which fears the fallout of a potential trading disruption. "All of a sudden half of the securities would not be able to clear their overnight positions," said Donald H. Layton, the former vice chairman of J. P. Morgan Chase who will lead the NewBank effort. "This is a very low likelihood event but it is highly disruptive if it occurs." The terrorist attacks on Sept. 11, 2001, underscored just how vulnerable the clearing system was: Bank of New York's trade-processing operations were troubled for days, causing problems across the banking system that took months to correct. Shortly after, the Federal Reserve and the Securities and Exchange Commission began raising concerns about what would happen if a clearing bank's activities were severely disrupted again. Both J. P. Morgan and Bank of New York built backup facilities outside the New York metropolitan area to stay ahead of federal regulators and make sure their clearing operations could never be physically shut down. J. P. Morgan has upgraded an existing operation in Dallas; Bank of New York now has a clearing center in Florida. But in a May 2002 report, the regulators also expressed fear that sudden and unforeseen legal problems or a credit downgrade would cause either bank to abandon the clearing business. Their proposal called for a quasi-public entity that could perform emergency clearing functions for the entire Treasury market. The government-led idea drew a cool reception from the banks. In response, a working group of banking executives and government officials was formed by the Federal Reserve to examine other ways to address the problem. Their solution, a privately organized "standby bank," emerged in 2004. This dormant bank would leap into action only if a credit or legal crisis caused investors and dealers to withdraw their business from either of the two existing banks and if no other qualified buyer, like Bank of America or Citigroup, stepped forward to buy the clearing operations. Regulators released formal plans for the NewBank in December. The Bond Market Association, an industry group, is expected to announce today that it will take responsibility for enacting them over the next 12 to 18 months. The NewBank will have no physical location and no full-time employees. It will be funded with roughly $500 million from 24 banking industry shareholders so that, if needed, it could immediately have money available to begin clearing trades. It will be set up as a limited-purpose trust company under the New York state banking laws and will also be regulated by the Federal Reserve. In a crisis, however, the NewBank would take over the legal position of the existing clearing bank and replace its top officers with a small group of designated executives from other institutions. The NewBank would then take over the troubled bank's existing operations to process the trades. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/09/business/09bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank Settles U.S. Inquiry Into Money Laundering<date>Published: November 9, 2005</date><text>Federal prosecutors said yesterday that the Bank of New York agreed to pay $38 million in penalties and victim compensation in a deal stemming from a six-year investigation of fraud and money laundering involving suspect Russian and American bank accounts and other fraudulent transactions. Prosecutors said the bank, one of the nation's oldest, did not adequately monitor and report suspect accounts at the bank. The bank agreed to make what prosecutors described as "sweeping internal reforms to ensure compliance with its antifraud and money laundering obligations." Authorities said that the bank has "accepted responsibility for its criminal conduct" and that it will not be prosecuted as long as it complies with the terms of the deal for three years. Bank of New York also agreed to allow an independent examiner to monitor its operations. The investigation, which began in 1998 and ended last year, first became publicly known in the summer of 1999 when Russia's pell-mell rush to privatize formerly state-owned assets resulted in widespread criticism of insider deals and possible corruption among Russia's business elite and officials of the Kremlin. The fine, which is among the largest ever assessed against an American bank for money laundering violations, consisted of $14 million for failing to supervise suspect Russian accounts and $24 million for a separate series of fraudulent activities involving a branch on Long Island. Riggs Bank, a subsidiary of the Riggs National Corporation, paid $41 million in federal penalties this year and last to settle a high-profile investigation of money laundering problems at that institution. Prosecutors with the United States attorneys' offices in Manhattan and Brooklyn noted that the money laundering scheme at the Bank of New York involved unlicensed transmissions of about $7 billion that originated in Russia, passed through American accounts, and then moved into other accounts worldwide. Authorities said that at least nine individuals, including a former Bank of New York vice president, had been convicted for their roles in the two cases. The Bank of New York acknowledged in the settlement that it had failed to adequately police and intentionally failed to report suspect accounts at the bank. Moreover, according to the settlement, the bank's general counsel, managing counsel, and other senior executives repeatedly ignored requirements to report illicit transactions until authorities began arresting suspects in its investigations. The agreement also said that the Bank of New York subsequently provided incomplete reports about suspect activities and failed to report separate transactions that resulted in the defrauding of other banks - even though the Bank of New York had already reached an agreement with regulators to overhaul its troubled monitoring operations. "We are satisfied that reaching this agreement is in the best interest of our company and all of our constituents," the bank's chief executive, Thomas A. Renyi, wrote in a statement. "We are taking the right steps in today's environment to ensure sound business practices." Two Russian émigrés - Lucy Edwards, a former vice president at the bank, and her husband, Peter Berlin - originally opened the suspect accounts at the bank in 1996. The couple pleaded guilty to fraud charges in early 2000, conceding that they helped two Moscow banks conduct illegal operations through Bank of New York accounts. Prosecutors declined to describe the plea agreement but a person briefed on the investigation said that Ms. Edwards and her husband were among those convicted in the scheme. The couple could not be reached for comment and T. Barry Kingham, a New York lawyer representing them when they first pleaded guilty to fraud charges, did not return repeated telephone calls seeking comment. In 1999, the Bank of New York suspended Natasha Gurfinkel Kagalovsky, a senior executive who oversaw Ms. Edwards. Federal investigators were exploring Ms. Kagalovsky's possible role in the money laundering scheme at the time and she subsequently resigned from the bank and moved to London. She has never been charged with wrongdoing in connection with the investigation. Her New York lawyer, Stanley S. Arkin, said yesterday that his client never violated any laws. Ms. Kagalovsky's husband, Konstantin Kagalovsky, served in senior government and corporate posts in Russia. He once worked for two large companies, Menatep and Yukos, which the Russian billionaire Mikhail Khodorkovsky formerly controlled. Mr. Khodorkovsky, once one of Russia's most prominent and powerful figures, was convicted in Moscow in May on fraud and tax evasion charges in a highly disputed case pitting him against the Kremlin. J. Michael Shepherd, who was general counsel at the Bank of New York during the money laundering investigation, left the bank last year to become general counsel of the BancWest Corporation. He did not return a telephone call seeking comment. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D81F38F936A15752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK WILL BUY STANDARD &amp; POOR'S UNIT<date>Published: January 25, 2005</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the institutional brokerage unit of Standard &amp; Poor's, expanding its independent research offerings and adding about 300 institutional investor clients to the 700 it already has. Bank of New York said its BNY Brokerage would assume the client relationships of the S.&amp;P. unit, Standard &amp; Poor's Securities Inc. Terms were not disclosed.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4D6113CF933A25752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; FEDERAL REGULATORS EXAMINING BANK OF NEW YORK UNIT<date>Published: November 10, 2004</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that federal regulators were examining whether the company's Pershing equity clearing unit violated stock market trading restrictions. The government was investigating how Pershing cleared trades for Mutuals.com and other so-called introducing brokers, the bank said in a filing yesterday with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The bank did not identify the regulatory agency investigating it.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/10/business/10wall.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">A Farsighted New Fortress Mentality on Wall St.<date>Published: September 10, 2004</date><text>n May, senior executives from Wall Street's top investment banks gathered at a conference center with a cadre of federal and local law enforcement authorities. Their task for the day was to simulate, down to the last detail, the aftermath of an explosion of a bomb in Midtown followed by others in Lower Manhattan. Advertisement Their scripts, distributed to them that day, read like a Hollywood screenplay: electricity was out, telephone lines had been severed, employees were evacuating buildings and the markets were down - what do you do? The searing events of Sept. 11, 2001, when 1,400 employees of securities firms were killed, prompted some changes in and around Wall Street that are easy to see. Morgan Stanley, for instance, which lost 1.2 million square feet in the south tower of the World Trade Center, is now moving employees to a new corporate installation in Westchester with the capacity to house 3,000 people. Lehman Brothers, whose headquarters in the World Financial Center was destroyed during the attacks, is comfortably ensconced in a new office building in Midtown. But the more profound effects are less evident - like war games played by managing directors of Wall Street firms. In the wake of the loss of 32,000 financial jobs in New York State of the 211,000 before the attacks and the billions of dollars spent since on security, business continuity and disaster-recovery planning, there is a prevailing sense of wariness, both with regard to the uncertain security environment and the future direction of the markets. "People are cautious and 9/11 did not pass unnoticed," said Roy Smith, a former Goldman, Sachs partner and a professor of finance at New York University. "We have had a bubble, and there is political uncertainty. Yes, firms have let a lot of people go, but firms are adaptive and have made money other ways, such as by trading." To be sure, many of the lost jobs have resulted from trends that predate Sept. 11, 2001, like industry consolidation, more automated trading, weak equity markets and, most significantly, the migration of jobs to other places. But economists note that the attacks have hastened these trends, especially with regard to firms moving their operations. "9/11 has accelerated and expanded the need for geographic dispersion for Wall Street firms," said Frank Fernandez, chief economist for the Securities Industry Association. "The result is job losses for New York City." Not all firms have moved away. Merrill Lynch, which was forced to evacuate one of its buildings at the World Financial Center, has moved back into the building. And Goldman, Sachs, long an anchor in Lower Manhattan, is expected to start construction this year on a global headquarters in Battery Park, with its completion planned in 2008. Wall Street firms are still making billions in profits, thanks mainly to the bull market in bonds that was further spurred by the Federal Reserve's reduction of interest rates right after the attacks. But as the third anniversary of Sept. 11 approaches, an air of extreme caution pervades Wall Street - symbolized best, perhaps, by the phalanx of machine-gun toting police officers that stand guard at the New York Stock Exchange. Indeed, of all the institutions on Wall Street, the exchange - which was forced to close for four business days after the attacks and was said in August by the Bush administration to be a target of a terrorist threat - has enacted the most significant and far-reaching security and contingency plans. Since the attacks in 2001, it has spent more than $100 million to prevent or recover from a market interruption, with a contingency trading floor, capable of trading all exchange-listed stocks immediately, as the centerpiece. The exchange has also put in place a new communications system linking its data centers to its member firms through a secure network that skirts traditional phone lines. Nasdaq, the stock exchange's electronic competitor, was affected less by the attacks - it says it could have started trading on Sept. 11 - because its main trading facilities are in Connecticut, with a backup installation in Maryland. Still, it now has a contingency program that would enable it to trade all New York Stock Exchange stocks in the event of a major disruption. Wall Street firms have also upgraded their backup trading facilities, making sure they are a significant distance from their headquarters. Lehman Brothers and Merrill Lynch have backup operations in New Jersey, while Morgan Stanley has its new building in Westchester, which will house the retail brokerage division, to use in an emergency. The increase in spending on security, business continuity and disaster recovery has been striking. This year, analysts at the Tower Group, a consulting firm, estimate that Wall Street firms will spend $3.8 billion - up from $1.8 billion in 2001 - for contingency planning and security measures, with more than 60 percent of that dedicated to information technology and the rest going toward new building and the hiring of personnel. Spending is expected to level off in the coming years, analysts say. As for the exercises in May, they were successful, allowing the 13 broker-dealers that took part to test employee evacuation strategies and the activation of their backup sites as well as their ability to prepare for a market opening the next day. "It was intended to be as real as it could be," said Howard Sprow, the Securities Industry Association's director of business continuity planning. While Wall Street's cautious mood can, in some ways, be attributed to security concerns that linger three years later, it is also true that the wave of accounting scandals and the explosion of regulatory investigations into research and mutual fund trading abuses since the attacks have left deep marks. And while 4,000 jobs were added this summer, economists do not expect job growth on the Street to continue, especially in light of the wan markets and the strides that firms are taking to automate their trading desks, making them less dependent on labor. "Yes, you had a geopolitical event," said David Trone, a securities analyst at Fox-Pitt, Kelton, "but you also have a weak economy, automated trading in equities, regulatory issues and accounting fraud. They all hit at the same time and have changed the business in a permanent way."</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/27/business/investors-sue-citigroup.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Investors Sue Citigroup<date>Published: August 27, 2004</date><text>Citigroup was sued this week by a group of institutional investors that contend the bank defrauded them in selling $2.4 billion of notes linked to the creditworthiness of the Enron Corporation.The suit was filed in State Supreme Court in New York by the Bank of New York Company, acting on behalf of investor groups that include Angelo, Gordon &amp; Company. The investors contend that the Citibank unit of Citigroup aided Enron in artificially maintaining the company's creditworthiness from 1999 until it sought bankruptcy protection in December 2001.The suit comes after others filed against Citigroup and rival investment banks over their dealings with Enron and WorldCom Inc., which filed the two biggest bankruptcies in United States history.Citigroup set aside $6.7 billion to pay for legal costs, and in May paid $2.65 billion to settle a WorldCom investor suit.The investor lawsuit filed this week contended that Enron used phony ''prepay'' transactions for the sale of commodities like natural gas and oil to hide debt.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/22/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-reports-higher-quarterly-profits.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; Bank of New York Reports Higher Quarterly Profits<date>Published: July 22, 2004</date><text>The Bank of New York Company, the big New York-based bank, said yesterday that second-quarter profit rose 26 percent because of fees from activities like currency trading and serving as a stock transfer agent. Net income increased to $371 million, or 48 cents a share, from $295 million, or 39 cents, a year earlier, the company said. The chief executive, Thomas A. Renyi, has transformed the 220-year-old bank into a company that gets most of its business from securities processing, instead of from fees at its more than 300 New York-area banks. Fees from securities processing rose to $717 million, from $598 million a year earlier.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/14/business/commercial-real-estate-regional-market-westchester-some-old-bank-buildings-take.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE: REGIONAL MARKET -- Westchester; Some Old Bank Buildings Take On New Life<date>Published: July 14, 2004</date><text>Where others saw little future for an empty bank building that was once an architectural centerpiece in this changing city, a businessman here envisioned an upscale restaurant.Zane Tankel, the chief executive of Apple-Metro, a company that franchises Applebee's and Chevys Fresh Mex restaurants, is transforming the former 78-year-old Home Savings Bank into a 250-seat restaurant. The original vault with its colossal steel door will be functional once again as a dining area for private parties.''It's a shame to let beautiful old structures like these just go to waste,'' Mr. Tankel said. His company has spent $3 million to renovate the structure and is opening Zanaro's Italian Restaurant this month. The property is owned by Cappelli Enterprises and leased to Apple-Metro under a 20-year deal.The building, which is listed on the National Register of Historic Places, is one of a number of vacant bank structures in Westchester, and the process of reviving such structures is also being played out in other cities and towns.Anchoring a nearby corner location in White Plains, for instance, another landmark bank, the former People's National Bank and Trust Company, was purchased by the Westchester Arts Council in 1998 and has been converted to art studios, offices and galleries. The village of Ossining, N.Y., where the downtown has four bank buildings built before the middle of the 20th century, recently received one as a gift from an individual donor and is planning to convert it to a municipal cultural center. In Port Chester, N.Y., one old bank has been turned into a restaurant, another has become a food market and a third, a Bank of New York, is still open, seemingly defying the odds.In the last 15 years, as Bank of New York was involved in a series of mergers, more than 25 branches have been closed, said Christopher Taylor, senior vice president and chief executive for the company's retail division. While costs are often lower in smaller more modern branches, some larger older offices have been kept open because they are in good locations and heavily used.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/20/business/merrill-picks-2-firms-for-outside-research.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Merrill Picks 2 Firms for Outside Research<date>Published: May 20, 2004</date><text>Merrill Lynch &amp; Company has selected BNY Jaywalk, a unit of the Bank of New York, and Morningstar to provide independent stock research under an industrywide regulatory settlement signed last year, Merrill said yesterday.Merrill Lynch is one of 10 investment banks forced to offer outside research to its clients. It must spend $75 million on independent research over five years.Bridget Macaskill, a former chief executive of Oppenheimer Funds, who was hired as an independent consultant and oversaw the selection process, said Bob McGann, vice chairman of Merrill's Wealth Management Group.Thus far, BNY has been the front runner in the competition for such contracts. It has made deals with the Bear Stearns Companies, Lehman Brothers Holdings and UBS, although the Merrill contract has the potential to be the largest so far.This is the first such victory for Morningstar, a mutual fund research firm.The settlement grew out of nearly two years of investigations led by the state attorney general of New York, Eliot Spitzer, who showed that Wall Street analysts had issued biased research in efforts to bring in investment banking business to their firms.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/27/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-says-profits-will-not-meet-forecasts.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK SAYS PROFITS WILL NOT MEET FORECASTS<date>Published: January 27, 2004</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that it expected 2004 operating profit to rise less than analysts' forecasts, hurt by a sluggish recovery in capital markets and expensing of stock options. The bank forecast operating profit of $1.84 to $1.89 a share, or $1.86 to $1.91 excluding the cost of the options. Analysts polled by Reuters forecast operating profit of $1.95 a share. The bank reported operating profit of $1.67 a share in 2003, as overall profit rose 28 percent, to $1.16 billion. The bank made its forecast in a presentation to analysts.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/22/business/profits-rose-at-3-big-banks-in-4th-quarter.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Profits Rose At 3 Big Banks In 4th Quarter<date>Published: January 22, 2004</date><text>J.P. Morgan Chase &amp; Company, the Bank of New York Company and the PNC Financial Services Group all reported higher fourth-quarter earnings yesterday.J.P. Morgan Chase, which last week agreed to buy the Bank One Corporation for about $58 billion in stock, had a profit of $1.86 billion in the fourth quarter, in contrast to a loss in the year-earlier quarter, amid gains in securities underwriting and a decline in bad loans.Net income was 89 cents a share, contrasted with a net loss of $387 million, or 20 cents, in the year-earlier period. Analysts expected earnings of 77 cents a share.Fourth-quarter revenue rose 21 percent, to $7.93 billion.Shares of J.P. Morgan rose $1.01, or 2.6 percent, to $40.10, in New York Stock Exchange trading.Investment banking profit more than doubled, to $860 million, as underwriting and merger fees increased 28 percent, to $834 million. Bad loans to companies declined 42 percent, to $2.37 billion.The Bank of New York said fourth-quarter profit tripled as the stock market rally increased trading fees and as loan losses declined.Net income rose to $307 million, or 40 cents a share, from $100 million, or 14 cents, the bank said. Revenue rose 15 percent , to $1.69 billion. Return on average common shareholder equity, a measure of profitability, rose to 15.1 percent from 14 percent.The chief executive, Thomas A. Renyi, is focusing on fee-based businesses rather than lending to bolster profit.The company spent $2.5 billion in 2003 to buy the Pershing stock trade processing business from Credit Suisse First Boston.Fees from servicing securities transactions increased to $760 million from $560 million, rising to 44 percent of net revenue from 38 percent.The Bank of New York's provision for bad loan losses fell to $35 million from $390 million in the year-earlier period, when it faced losses in aircraft leases with airlines like the UAL Corporation's United Airlines. The bank said losses in loans to the telecommunications industry declined to $875 million as of Dec. 31 from $1.5 billion at the end of 2002.Shares of the Bank of New York lost 30 cents, or 0.9 percent, to close at $33.81 on the Big Board.PNC Financial Services, Pennsylvania's biggest bank, said fourth-quarter profit rose 5 percent as it earned more from customer fees and made fewer bad loans.Net income climbed to $274 million, or 98 cents a share, from $262 million, or 92 cents, in the year-earlier period, the bank said.Excluding an accounting charge, the bank earned $1.08 a share, exceeding the average 99-cent estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call. Revenue rose 4.3 percent, to $1.35 billion.Earnings from consumer checking accounts, mortgages and credit cards increased 4.6 percent, to $159 million, bolstered by a decline in noninterest expenses. Earnings from corporate banking, which includes loans to business customers, rose 12 percent, to $94 million. PNC set aside $34 million for bad loans in the quarter, down from $65 million a year earlier.Shares of PNC gained 54 cents, or 1 percent, to close at $55.03 on the New York exchange.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/15/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-to-oversee-city-pension-funds.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK TO OVERSEE CITY PENSION FUNDS<date>Published: January 15, 2004</date><text>The City of New York has hired the Bank of New York Company as the custodian of its five pension funds, which hold $78 billion in assets. The retirement systems involved cover city employees, the schools, the Board of Education and the Police and Fire Departments. The Bank of New York will be responsible for accounting for and reporting of all their assets, starting on April 1, according to the city comptroller, William C. Thompson. The bank will also provide services to the pension funds' growing private equity and real estate programs.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/17/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-to-acquire-trust-business-in-hawaii.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK TO ACQUIRE TRUST BUSINESS IN HAWAII<date>Published: December 17, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company, a leading provider of corporate trust services for company and municipal debt, agreed to buy the Bank of Hawaii Corporation's corporate trust business. The sale involves the transfer of about 80 bond trust and agency agreements, worth about $3 billion, to the B.N.Y. Western Trust Company, the Bank of New York said. Terms were not disclosed, a spokesman, Kevin Heine, said. The purchase, expected to close early next year, adds to the bank's portfolio of more than 85,000 trustee and agency agreements, representing more than $1 trillion in securities, for 30,000 clients. Bank of New York has been using acquisitions to expand its corporate trust business, which manages paperwork for bond issuers.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/25/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-to-buy-trust-unit-from-fifth-third.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK TO BUY TRUST UNIT FROM FIFTH THIRD<date>Published: November 25, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Fifth Third Bancorp's corporate trust business to expand in the Midwest. Terms were not disclosed. The purchase would solidify Bank of New York's position in the consolidating, low-margin business of corporate trust services. These include managing bond payments, acting as a trustee after a sale of new bonds and acting as a custodian for retirement plans and other corporate accounts. Bank of New York said the purchase included about 5,000 bond trustee and agency appointments, representing $45 billion of debt for nearly 4,000 clients. Fifth Third is based in Cincinnati.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/13/business/company-news-investigators-ask-bank-about-mutual-fund-industry.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; INVESTIGATORS ASK BANK ABOUT MUTUAL FUND INDUSTRY<date>Published: November 13, 2003</date><text>Regulators have asked the Bank of New York to provide information about other participants in the $7 trillion mutual fund industry as part of a continuing investigation into improper trading, the bank said yesterday. ''The inquiries relate to the Bank of New York's role as a large administrator of mutual fund assets,'' a bank spokesman, R. Jeep Bryant, said. ''We are seen as having an ability to provide information about others.'' Mr. Bryant said the bank was cooperating with the requests. He declined to say who made the requests, or whether the bank had received any subpoenas.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/23/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-says-net-income-triples.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK SAYS NET INCOME TRIPLES<date>Published: October 23, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said quarterly net income tripled as it set aside less money for bad loans. Net income in the third quarter rose to $260 million, or 34 cents a share, from $79 million, or 11 cents, a year earlier, the company said. The bank set aside $40 million for bad loans compared with $225 million a year earlier. Profit from continuing operations was 42 cents a share, matching the estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call. The company reduced corporate loans on its balance sheet by 23 percent to $26.2 billion as of Sept. 30. Lending revenue before bad loan provisions fell to $284 million from $359 million.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/08/business/us-auditing-oversight-board-begins-policing-role-by-settling-on-procedure.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">U.S. Auditing Oversight Board Begins Policing Role by Settling on Procedure<date>Published: October 08, 2003</date><text>After a rocky start, the government's accounting oversight board is getting down to the business of policing the nation's most important accounting firms.In a flurry of major personnel announcements and votes on new rules on Tuesday, the board indicated that it would be ready early next year to begin intensively inspecting many of the auditors of publicly traded companies -- the first time accountants will face systematic examination by a government entity. The largest firms will have annual inspections, while smaller firms will be inspected every three years.Under its new chairman, William J. McDonough, the board has also waded into a continuing controversy. In a closely watched proceeding that will soon require larger publicly traded companies to begin extensive disclosures and audits of their internal financial controls, the board proposed the rules for conducting those activities.Many companies have complained that the new audits will be too expensive, while accounting firms have supported the changes because they would bring in new business and could expose financial problems early. The requirement, in general terms, was set by Congress, but the board's specific proposal cannot go into effect without the approval of the Securities and Exchange Commission, which reviews its major rules and enforcement actions.The requirement followed failures of internal controls at companies including WorldCom, Xerox, Rite Aid and Cendant.The accounting board also announced that Esslie W. Hughes, a former executive at the Bank of New York, would head its New York office and that Paul E. Bijou, a former partner at PricewaterhouseCoopers, would lead the office's inspection team. The New York office is expected to play an important role in enforcement and oversight because the big accounting firms have their largest operations there.Known officially as the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board, the agency's creation was a cornerstone of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, the Congressional response last year to the wave of corporate scandals and accounting meltdowns. Despite the announcements on Tuesday, however, the young agency has yet to confront many of the most significant issues.It must set standards and conflict-of-interest rules, inspect firms in the United States, fill several crucial offices and make sure overseas companies that sell securities in the United States are adequately audited.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/22/business/company-news-enron-settles-dispute-over-water-partnership-notes.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; ENRON SETTLES DISPUTE OVER WATER PARTNERSHIP NOTES<date>Published: July 22, 2003</date><text>The Enron Corporation said yesterday that it had settled a legal dispute with noteholders of an off-the-books partnership created to finance a water-treatment unit. Holders of notes in Marlin Water Trust would get about $127.5 million, including collateral held by the Bank of New York as trustee for the noteholders. In exchange, the Bank of New York will reduce its claim against Enron to $507.5 million from $1.1 billion. Enron, which owes creditors about $67 billion, said 69 percent of the Marlin noteholders and a panel of Enron's unsecured creditors support the accord. Judge Arthur J. Gonzalez of United States Bankruptcy Court in Manhattan is scheduled to consider approval of the settlement on Aug. 7, court papers show.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/18/business/company-news-profit-at-bank-of-new-york-decreases-18.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; PROFIT AT BANK OF NEW YORK DECREASES 18%<date>Published: July 18, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that its second-quarter net profit fell 18 percent, as falling interest rates cut lending gains while salaries and other costs rose. The bank reported income of $295 million, or 39 cents a share, down from $361 million, or 50 cents a share, a year earlier. It said that its $2 billion purchase in May of the Pershing L.L.C. securities clearinghouse cost it 3 cents a share in the quarter. Excluding 2 cents a share for the costs of integrating Pershing, the bank posted 41 cents a share of operating profit.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/25/nyregion/robberies-of-banks-rising.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Robberies Of Banks Rising<date>Published: May 25, 2003</date><text>THE series of bank robberies continued last week in Westchester.Last Wednesday at 11:15 a.m., a woman demanded money at the Bank of New York branch in the Shrub Oak Shopping Center in Yorktown, indicating she had a gun, according to the Yorktown police. She walked away with some cash, but the bank has not released the amount stolen.A little more than three hours later at 2:40 p.m., a woman fitting the same description robbed the HSBC branch at Overhill and Popham Roads in Scarsdale, using the same tactics, according to the Scarsdale police. She escaped with $3,100.Detectives from both towns said the suspect is white, in her mid-30's and has long blond hair. But she could be wearing a wig, Yorktown and Scarsdale police officers said.Meanwhile, on Thursday, the Federal Bureau of Investigation arrested a suspect in at least four other bank robberies in Yonkers, Newburgh and Spring Valley in the last two months.The suspect, Jerome D. Brown, was arrested in Roanoke, Va., as he was trying to rob a bank there, said David Velazquez, the senior superviser for the White Plains branch of the F.B.I.''All criminals make mistakes,'' Mr. Velazquez said. ''He got a little sloppy, and he got caught.''Mr. Brown is believed to be the man who gave a teller at the Fleet Bank in Getty Square in Yonkers a note demanding cash, according to the Yonkers Police Department. He said he had a gun and also threatened to blow the bank up if the bank teller didn't comply.Similar tactics were used in robberies weeks before at another bank in Yonkers, one in Spring Valley and one in Newburgh, by a man fitting the same description: black, six feet tall and 225 pounds.But in yet another recent bank robbery, this one in New Rochelle, no suspect has been identified, said the New Rochelle police.Two weeks ago, a man wearing a ski mask held at gunpoint the employees and a customer at the Bank of New York in New Rochelle while his partner, also wearing a ski mask, emptied the cash drawers, said a detective of the New Rochelle Police Department. The police would not reveal the amount stolen.There have been two more recent bank robberies in the area. One occurred last Monday at a First Union Bank branch in North White Plains, another on May 9 at a J.P. Morgan Chase Bank branch in Mount Kisco. The robber stole $13,282 from Chase; the Mount Kisco police have recovered that money but the robber got away.''These banks have become targets because of the ease with which the robbers could deal with the security barriers,'' said Mr. Valezquez, explaining the recent proliferation of bank robberies.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/23/nyregion/one-woman-tied-to-spree-of-robberies-in-two-states.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">One Woman Tied to Spree Of Robberies In Two States<date>Published: May 23, 2003</date><text>In her jaunty baseball cap and yellow rain slicker, the middle-aged woman with the glasses and the long blonde hair might be taken for a soccer mom. Her runabout is a red compact, maybe a Mitsubishi, and she zips from town to town, and bank to bank, like a harried suburbanite juggling too many tasks.Yesterday, she made the rounds of Fairfield County in western Connecticut, stopping at a First Union Bank and a Fleet branch in Danbury, a Peoples Bank in Newtown and a Union Savings in Brookfield. On Wednesday, she was in Westchester County, at an HSBC branch in Scarsdale and the Bank of New York in Yorktown.At each bank, witnesses said, she stood in line, waiting her turn. A witness got a peek at a gun, but mostly she just wiggled a hand in a pocket menacingly, as if she had one. She demanded money and the understandably frightened tellers gave her some. Nobody was hurt, and the losses were being added up last night.By late afternoon, the state and local police in two states and in a half-dozen jurisdictions were still trying to piece together the details of what appeared to be a one-woman interstate robbery spree in the rolling green hills of Westchester and Fairfield Counties.''It's very unusual,'' said Sgt. Paul Vance, a spokesman for the Connecticut State Police. ''It's particularly unusual because of the information given out after the first one. Police were in the area, and were kind of looking around for anything after that.''It may not have been Dragnet, but William O'Shaughnessy, the chairman of Whitney Radio, said he saw a lot of patrol activity yesterday afternoon as he drove on Interstate 84 to his home in Litchfield, Conn., especially in the triangle of Danbury, Newtown and Brookfield.''I saw a trooper go blasting off at the Brookfield exit,'' he said. ''Wow! This isn't supposed to happen in the Litchfield Hills. But there are a lot of weekenders up here, and it's a little unsettling in this bucolic setting.'' Yesterday's crime wave began at 11:32 a.m. at the People's Bank branch in the Newtown Shopping Center. The woman approached a teller, indicated that she had a weapon and demanded cash, according to the police. She got it and walked out. Witnesses said she was 30 to 40 years old and wore a baseball cap, a yellow slicker and glasses.Three hours later, a woman of the same general description went into the Union Savings branch in Brookfield, seven miles northwest. The hood of her rain slicker was up. No weapon was displayed, but she said she had a gun and would use it. She drove away with an unknown amount of cash.In Danbury, a few miles to the southwest, she hit two banks -- First Union and Fleet -- in swift succession, just before and after 3 p.m., the police said. At the Fleet, one witness glimpsed a gun. The robber's description was similar: a woman in her 40's, slender, light brown or blonde hair, a baseball cap, a light jacket.On Wednesday, the police in Yorktown said a woman with long blonde hair robbed the Bank of New York at the Shrub Oak shopping center at 11:15 a.m., escaping with $3,100. A few hours later, at 2:40 p.m., a woman with long blonde hair robbed the HSBC branch in Scarsdale, according to the police. She was slender and wore a yellow rain slicker, witnesses said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/21/business/company-news-court-dismisses-suit-against-bank-of-new-york.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; COURT DISMISSES SUIT AGAINST BANK OF NEW YORK<date>Published: May 21, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company won dismissal of a lawsuit that accused it of defrauding three offshore trusts of $40 million they invested in Inkombank, a leading Russian bank that lost its license in 1999. The trusts claimed that Bank of New York, which was a correspondent for Inkombank, knew the Russian bank laundered money and had ties to organized crime when they tried to withdraw their money in 1996. They accused Bank of New York of hiding the wrongdoing and of persuading them not to withdraw funds. In dismissing the suit, a state appeals court said the case was undermined by a similar suit litigated in federal court from 1995 to 1999. In that case, an agent for the offshore trusts said Inkombank admitted as early as 1994 that it had no intention of paying the investors, the appeals panel said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/15/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-reports-federal-fraud-inquiry.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK REPORTS FEDERAL FRAUD INQUIRY<date>Published: May 15, 2003</date><text>Bank of New York, the third-largest New York-based bank, and several of its employees are the subject of a federal inquiry into leasing fraud, the bank said yesterday in a regulatory filing. ''The bank is cooperating fully in that investigation,'' a spokesman, Robert Grieves, said. Last June, the F.B.I. arrested four officials of RW Professional Leasing, a former customer of the bank, on charges they defrauded banks by obtaining loans to lease medical equipment without passing the money to doctors. Bank of New York is also a defendant in two lawsuits related to the case seeking $46 million.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/23/business/bank-of-new-york-s-profit-falls-70.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York's Profit Falls 70%<date>Published: January 23, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York posted a 70 percent drop in fourth-quarter profit yesterday, after it wrote off loans and leases to United Airlines and other ailing carriers.The bank reported net income of $100 million, or 14 cents a share, in the fourth quarter, compared with $331 million, or 45 cents a share, in the period in 2001. That missed the consensus estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call by a penny a share.The bank said the fourth-quarter figures included a $390 million pretax loan loss provision and a $240 million charge-off ''primarily for aircraft leasing exposure to United Airlines as well as the potential for losses on leases to other domestic carriers.'' Its shares fell 36 cents, to $25.76.The chief executive, Thomas A. Renyi, said he thought the bank had dealt with its loan problems.''With respect to the additional provisioning we took in the fourth quarter,'' Mr. Renyi said, ''this action addressed our exposure to the U.S. airline industry and significantly increased our loan reserves, which created flexibility for our credit-risk-reduction efforts.''Mr. Renyi added that despite the loan problems at the company, ''each of our major business areas showed growth, with securities-servicing revenues increasing for the fifth consecutive quarter.''For the year, net income totaled $902 million, or $1.24 a share, down more than 30 percent from $1.34 billion, or $1.81 a share, in 2001.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/22/business/credit-suisse-expects-to-post-loss-for-2002.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Credit Suisse Expects to Post Loss for 2002<date>Published: January 22, 2003</date><text>The Credit Suisse Group said today that it expected to report a loss of 3.4 billion Swiss francs ($2.5 billion) for 2002.About a fourth of the loss is attributable to the cost of paying fines and settling lawsuits connected with its activities of the investment banking unit, Credit Suisse First Boston, including its involvement with Enron, its allocation of shares in initial public stock offerings that it underwrote, conflicts of interest in its research analysts' recommendations and other problems.At the same time, Credit Suisse has said it will take a charge related to the sale of its Pershing unit to the Bank of New York for $2 billion, and others related to revamping and cost-cutting measures. Complete results for the year will be published next month, the company said.Credit Suisse said that despite the loss it had enough capital on its balance sheet and that its troubled Winterthur insurance arm had returned to profitability in the fourth quarter.By taking the litigation and restructuring charges in 2002, ''our intention was to put the structures in place to return to profitability in 2003,'' chief financial officer, Philip K. Ryan, said today. ''Our strategy is to turn our core businesses back to profitability.''The company does not expect a strong improvement in financial markets this year, Mr. Ryan said, so Credit Suisse will have to continue tightening its belt. ''We want to get costs down in line with revenues and return back to profitability,'' he said. ''I think some of the leaders in the industry have shown very clearly that if you manage costs right you can have a very respectable return in very, very difficult markets.''Analysts had mixed views of Credit Suisse's situation, with some criticizing the strategy of loading the 2002 results with huge charges once it was clear that the year would be a bad one anyway.Christoph Ritschard of ZÃ¼rcher Kantonalbank said of the hopes for being profitable this year, ''I'm very optimistic that they can do it.'' Still he warned that the company's troubles were not yet all behind it.First, he said, the sweeping cuts of 2002 had left deep dents in staff morale. Second, he said, the two co-chief executives, John J. Mack and Oswald J. GrÃ¼bel, need to position the group to move quickly when the financial markets change.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/09/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-to-buy-clearing-unit-of-first-boston.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK TO BUY CLEARING UNIT OF FIRST BOSTON<date>Published: January 09, 2003</date><text>The Bank of New York Company confirmed yesterday that it had agreed to buy Credit Suisse First Boston's United States stock clearing unit, Pershing, for $2 billion. Bank of New York has been expanding its capacity to provide back-office services to financial institutions. Investors, however, are concerned, because of the price tag, which is $1.4 billion more than Pershing's book value, and Bank of New York's plan to issue millions of shares to finance the acquisition, analysts said. The bank's shares fell 4 percent. For Credit Suisse, the sale is part of an effort to focus on its securities underwriting and trading business. In November, the firm posted a third-quarter loss of $425 million as its parent company, the Credit Suisse Group, reported a record loss of $1.44 billion.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/08/business/credit-suisse-deal-is-seen.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Credit Suisse Deal Is Seen<date>Published: January 08, 2003</date><text>Credit Suisse First Boston is close to a deal to sell its stock clearing unit to Bank of New York for about $2 billion, executives close to the discussions said last night.A deal could be announced as early as today, though the executives stressed that the negotiations could drag on and both sides could still abandon the transaction.The sale of the stock clearing unit, called Pershing, is an important part of an effort by First Boston's parent company, Credit Suisse Group, to raise cash after reporting a record quarterly loss in November.First Boston inherited Pershing when it acquired Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Inc. two years ago.Pershing has been for sale for months and has drawn preliminary interest from several suitors.The deal would make the Bank of New York the nation's largest clearing firm for stock trades, an essential back-office processing business that executes trades and manages all the related record keeping.Pershing executes about 10 percent of all trades on the New York Stock Exchange and is considered one of the most consistent, stable cash generators on Wall Street, even though trade-clearing is considered a low-margin business.Credit Suisse does not disclose Pershing's earnings, though Bear Stearns, which executes about 12 percent of all trades on the Big Board, made $265 million last year from clearing trades.Victoria Harmon, a spokeswoman for Credit Suisse First Boston, declined to comment as did Robert Grieves, a spokesman for Bank of New York.The Bank of New York's bid appears to have beat out competing offers from Bear Stearns, Automatic Data Processing Inc. and Fidelity Investments, the Boston-based mutual fund company.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/19/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-warns-of-harm-from-united.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK WARNS OF HARM FROM UNITED<date>Published: December 19, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company warned yesterday that a charge to cover its exposure to United Airlines' bankruptcy and other items would cut fourth-quarter earnings. Its share price fell 16 percent. The bank's executives made the forecast at a meeting with analysts, a day after announcing that it would take a $390 million provision and a $240 million charge in the fourth quarter, mostly to cover losses on aircraft leases, including its exposure to United Airlines, whose parent is UAL. The bank said it expected to earn 14 cents to 15 cents a share in the fourth quarter and $1.78 to $1.92 in 2003. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had expected earnings of 49 cents in the fourth quarter and $1.80 to $2.14 next year. Bank of New York's stock fell $4.11, to $22.39 a share.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/24/business/guilty-plea-is-expected-from-trader.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Guilty Plea Is Expected From Trader<date>Published: October 24, 2002</date><text>John M. Rusnak, the Baltimore currency trader who is accused of hiding losses of $691 million at Allfirst Financial for five years, will plead guilty today to bank fraud charges.The office of the United States attorney for Maryland said yesterday that it would announce a guilty plea today ''in a significant financial fraud case involving Allfirst Bank.'' The statement did not name Mr. Rusnak but no one else has been indicted in the case.Mr. Rusnak was indicted in June on seven counts involving bank fraud and making false financial entries. The indictment charged that Mr. Rusnak used fictitious trades and false trade confirmations to hide losses at Allfirst Financial and to make it appear that he was actually making a profit as a currency trader.Allfirst's parent bank, Allied Irish Banks of Dublin, announced at the end of September that it would sell Allfirst to the M&amp;T Bank Corporation of Buffalo for $3.1 billion in cash and stock. Allied Irish officials said at the time that the sale was a result of the fallout from the revelations of Mr. Rusnak's hidden losses. The scandal rocked the Irish markets when it was revealed in February and cut Allied Irish Bank's 2001 profits in half.Mr. Rusnak's lawyer, David B. Irwin, had no comment.The statement did not say what the guilty plea involved but white-collar criminal lawyers suggested that Mr. Rusnak would probably plead to one of the seven charges and that his sentence would be less than the maximum 30 years that he faced.According to the indictment, Mr. Rusnak used fictitious trades and false trade confirmations to hide his losses and to make it appear that he was actually making a profit as a currency trader.Mr. Rusnak was paid more than $850,000 in salary and bonuses over five years, based on this fictitious performance, the indictment said. A $220,000 bonus scheduled for 2001 was not paid after the losses were uncovered in February.The indictment also said that Mr. Rusnak had special trading agreements, know as prime brokerage agreements, with Citibank, Bank of America and Merrill Lynch. The indictment said that the agreements helped Mr. Rusnak conceal much of his daily trading and enter fictitious trades on Allfirst's books.Citibank and Bank of America have said that they have found no evidence of collusion with Mr. Rusnak. Merrill said at the time of the indictment that it had ''no knowledge of impropriety on the part of this individual.''The three companies, along with Deutsche Bank and Bank of New York, also did option trades with Mr. Rusnak that were, in effect, so-called synthetic loans that helped him cover his losses in 2001.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/17/business/fleet-net-falls-24-but-wachovia-gains.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Fleet Net Falls 24%, but Wachovia Gains<date>Published: October 17, 2002</date><text>The FleetBoston Financial Corporation posted lower third-quarter profits yesterday on loan and investment losses, but consumer operations like taking deposits and selling mortgages lifted results at the Wachovia Corporation and other regional banks.Slack results in Argentina and investment losses led FleetBoston to post a 24 percent drop in net income, to $579 million, or 55 cents a share, including discontinued operations like its Robertson Stephens investment bank in San Francisco.The Bank of New York and Comerica reported profit declines on loan losses. But sturdy results in consumer banking operations like collecting deposits, making mortgage loans and credit card fees lifted results at Wachovia and the SouthTrust Corporation.At FleetBoston, a big player in Latin America that is trying to shift its focus to more stable operations like consumer lending in the United States, third-quarter income from continuing operations was $597 million, or 57 cents a share, compared with $771 million, or 70 cents a share.Wall Street had expected FleetBoston to earn 53 cents to 60 cents a share.Wachovia, based in Charlotte, N.C., reported third-quarter earnings of $913 million, or 66 cents a share, in contrast to a loss of $334 million, or 31 cents a share, a year earlier. Growth in deposit fees, consumer loans and retail investment sales through its branches and a lower tax provision helped Wachovia.Excluding certain one-time items, Wachovia reported operating profit of $983 million, or 71 cents a share, compared with a profit of $298 million, or 27 cents, last year.The Bank of New York earned $79 million, or 11 cents a share, in the quarter, compared with $243 million, or 33 cents a share.The Bank of New York took charges to cover bad loans to telecommunications companies and losses in a portfolio of bank shares. Excluding the charge, it said it earned 47 cents a share.At SouthTrust of Birmingham, Ala., earnings rose to $164.2 million, or 47 cents a share, in the third quarter, compared with $142 million, or 41 cents a share.Comerica said that third-quarter profit fell 89 percent, to $24 million, or 14 cents a share, from $209 million, or $1.14, a year earlier. The bank, based in Detroit, cited bad loans and a drop in the value of a mutual fund firm.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/09/business/survey-finds-loan-losses-rose-sharply.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Survey Finds Loan Losses Rose Sharply<date>Published: October 09, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedLoan losses continue to rise at banks and other institutions, mostly because of faltering telecommunications and cable companies, according to a survey by bank regulators released yesterday.The total amount of sour loans rose by more than a third from a year earlier, the survey found, but only 11 percent were at United States banks. There were much greater increases at foreign banks and other lenders. Loans to telecommunications and cable companies accounted for about three-quarters of the total increase.Regulators said they did not see an end in sight to the increase in problem loans. But analysts and investors said that severe losses would probably occur at just a handful of banks because most lenders had already sold the loans or added to their reserves if they expected losses.Bank stocks have fallen sharply the last three weeks, after several companies announced that third-quarter results would be worse than expected partly because of problem loans.J. P. Morgan Chase, the nation's largest corporate lender, set off the decline last month when it said that write-offs and additions to its reserve against potential losses on loans to companies would rise to $1.4 billion in the third quarter, up from $302 million in the second quarter. Other banks that have warned of rising loan losses include the Bank of New York, Comerica and Northern Trust .Bank stocks have tumbled more than 12 percent since J. P. Morgan's announcement, according to the Philadelphia Stock Exchange/KBW Banks index. Bank stocks rose 4.3 percent yesterday after the regulators released the report.''We've had a little bit of hysteria here,'' said Judah Kraushaar, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, referring to the decline in bank shares. In fact, he said, ''most banks will have very modest increases in credit costs.''Shares of Bank of America, for example, have fallen 16 percent since J. P. Morgan's announcement. But analysts said they did not expect the bank to report a large increase in loan losses for the quarter. The bank had $3.7 billion in loans outstanding to telecommunications companies at the end of the second quarter, making it one of the larger lenders to the industry, although it has probably sold or hedged some of these loans in recent months.The bank's chief executive, Kenneth D. Lewis, told investors last month at a conference sponsored by Merrill Lynch that write-offs would be about the same in the third quarter as they were in the second quarter.Correction: October 10, 2002, Thursday An article in Business Day yesterday about a survey by regulators that showed an increase in problem loans at banks and other institutions worldwide referred incorrectly to an 11 percent figure. That was the amount of the increase in such loans at United States banks -- not the share of soured loans held by American banks.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/03/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-issues-warning-on-earnings.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK ISSUES WARNING ON EARNINGS<date>Published: October 03, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company warned of a third-quarter earnings shortfall yesterday because of $395 million in pretax charges for bad loans to telecommunications companies and investment losses. The bank expects the charges, amounting to $260 million after taxes, to reduce earnings by 36 cents a share. Excluding charges, Bank of New York expects to earn 47 cents a share in the third quarter, below analysts' average estimate of 50 cents a share for the quarter, according to Thomson First Call, the market data firm. ''The third quarter was a very challenging period, worsening substantially after a reasonably good July,'' the chief executive, Thomas Renyi, said in a statement. Bank of New York said it would increase its loan loss provision by $185 million, to a total of $225 million, and take a $210 million charge to reflect a drop in the value of its stock investment portfolio.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/10/nyregion/liberty-bonds-to-finance-new-brooklyn-offices.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Liberty Bonds to Finance New Brooklyn Offices<date>Published: September 10, 2002</date><text>A new Brooklyn office tower to be built by Forest City Ratner Companies and occupied by the Bank of New York will be the first commercial construction project to be financed by Liberty Bonds, which were approved by Congress in response to the Sept. 11 attacks, city and state officials said yesterday.The board of the city's Industrial Development Agency is expected today to approve the issuance of $113.9 million in Liberty Bonds for the development of the 10-story building above Atlantic Terminal, the borough's largest transit hub, according to officials of the Empire State Development Corporation and the city's Economic Development Corporation.The new tower, with 396,000 square feet of office space, will be built atop a five-story retail complex under construction on a site bounded by Flatbush Avenue, Atlantic Avenue, Fort Greene Place and Hanson Place.The Bank of New York, whose offices near Wall Street were severely damaged in the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center, is expected to move 1,400 of 7,700 employees to the site and will occupy 80 percent of the office space beginning in mid-2004.Keeping the bank in New York City has been a project of major importance to city and state officials over the last year. The bank was one of the few major financial institutions with executive offices, support staff and computer operations all in Lower Manhattan. As a result, it was unable to restore service to its network of automated teller machines for more than a week after the attack. The bank estimated the attack cost it $140 million.The Bank of New York is one of the largest providers of securities settlement for Wall Street. It eases the movement of money and securities from stock and bond trades executed by brokerage firms. In that process, the bank holds large sums of cash for a day or two, and much of its income comes from investing that cash, an activity that was disrupted in the days after the attack.The savings from the use of Liberty Bonds, which are tax exempt and therefore cost the issuer less in annual interest payments than similar, taxable financing, will flow to Forest City Ratner and do not have to be passed on to the Bank of New York.But the bank itself was previously awarded a $37.5 million grant for keeping 7,700 jobs in New York City for at least 12 years. In addition, last month the Industrial Development Agency approved the bank for up to $2 million in sales tax exemptions for tenant improvements and the purchase of equipment and machinery.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/12/nyregion/in-the-big-city-smaller-banks-find-a-sizable-niche.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">In the Big City, Smaller Banks Find a Sizable Niche<date>Published: August 12, 2002</date><text>One side effect of the Chase Manhattan Corporation's acquisition of J. P. Morgan almost two years ago was supposed to be that consumers in New York City would have little room for choice, industry experts and commentators said.After all, consolidation over several decades had transformed New York from a city with several dozen big banks to a place with only three major choices: Chase, Citibank and the Bank of New York.But, in fact, choice for banking customers has expanded, with nearly a dozen smaller banks seizing on perceived public discontent with the existing options and services.Some banks from outside New York, like Commerce Bank, have moved in. Others, like HSBC, which took over Republic New York, have increased their presence through mergers. And several smaller banks, like Independence Community Bank, have opened shop where Chase, Citibank and the Bank of New York have closed branches.The upstarts and newcomers are making a play for customers like Irving Singer, a Brooklyn Heights lawyer who transferred his business and personal accounts recently to Signature Bank, which Israel's largest bank, Bank Hapoalim, started 14 months ago. Signature, based in Manhattan, now has nine branches.''I have left a whole surge of banks,'' Mr. Singer said. ''The banks are too big, their service is poor, and I want to come in and get a place with personal service, where the bank manager knows my name.''Industry experts like Bruce Harting, a banking analyst at Lehman Brothers, say that consolidation -- which saves money by closing branches and sharing costs on personnel and information technology -- has had an unintended negative impact on customer service.''New Yorkers are among the most critical people in the country and at the same time this is also one of the most lucrative markets in the country,'' Mr. Harting said. ''As big as the city is, people remember their hometown banks, whether they are in Flatbush or Astoria or Greenpoint or Flushing.''Washington Mutual, which bought Dime Savings Bank in 2001, has added a store selling piggy banks, concierges, baby changing stations and roaming tellers in order to lure customers from the big banks. Based in Seattle, Washington Mutual now has 123 branches in the New York region.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/18/business/profit-drops-6-at-bank-of-new-york.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Profit Drops 6% at Bank of New York<date>Published: July 18, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that its quarterly profit fell 6 percent, held down by severance costs, lower securities gains and a decline in profits from foreign exchange and trading.The bank, based in New York City, earned $361 million, or 50 cents a share, in the second quarter, including a severance expense of $16 million, or 1 cent a share, for cutting 400 jobs. That contrasted with $385 million, or 52 cents a share, in the 2001 quarter.Wall Street analysts expected profit of 51 cents a share, according to Thomson First Call.Lower volatility and narrow spreads caused foreign exchange and trading revenues to drop to $72 million from $98 million a year earlier. Stable interest rates also hurt results in the hedging and risk management operations.The provision for credit losses remained stable at $35 million.Fees from securities servicing increased 9 percent from a year earlier, to $473 million, helped by new business and acquisitions.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/13/world/50-held-in-european-offshoot-of-bank-of-new-york-investigation.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">50 Held in European Offshoot of Bank of New York Investigation<date>Published: June 13, 2002</date><text>As a tangential part of a money laundering investigation of the Bank of New York, police officials in several European countries this week detained more than 50 people suspected of involvement in a network that funneled millions of dollars from Russia through Western banks and companies.Orders were issued to freeze roughly 300 bank accounts in Europe and North America.The raids appeared to confirm concerns in several West European countries that large-scale laundering of money obtained illegally in Russia continues through seemingly legitimate businesses.Italian investigators said tonight that the arrests grew out of a little-noticed investigation into Russian organized-crime activity in an area of northeastern Italy near the seaside resort at Rimini.Russian business people became particularly active there after the Soviet collapse, buying consumer goods like clothing and shoes for the Russian market.Officials said some of the money had been funneled through accounts of the Benex Corporation and related accounts at the Bank of New York. Benex and the bank were at the center of a federal money laundering investigation in the United States in the 1990's.The investigators said that by examining bank and commercial records they were able to uncover a criminal network of mainly Russian and Italian business people. Of those detained, about 20 are being held in Italy, 12 in France and Monte Carlo, and the remainder in several other European countries and Canada. About half are Russian.They said the authorities had confiscated commercial records that could cast further light on the network and lead to more arrests.The investigators said much of the activity appeared to focus on a Rimini marketing company called Prima, controlled by Oleg Berezovsky, a 36-year-old Ã©migrÃ©. It was unclear, they said, whether Mr. Berezovsky was related to Boris Berezovsky, a high-profile Russian businessman often suspected of organized crime links. Oleg Berezovsky's brother Igor, owner of a Paris-based trading company, Kama Trade, was detained by the French police in the western French city of Rennes. The arrests were made Monday and Tuesday.The investigators said another Russian detained in France, Andreas Marissov, 38, an associate of the Berezovskys, is suspected of supplying funds and other support to rebel groups in Chechnya.The investigators also cited telephone intercepts and commercial records as evidence linking suspect West European businesses with money from criminal activity in Russia. The operation, the investigators said, may have laundered billions of dollars, but they did not specify exact amounts. Prostitution, drug sales, tax evasion and protection rackets were some of the sources of the funds in Russia, they said.Vladimir Vassarenko, a 34-year-old Russian, was a significant figure in the early stages of the investigation, they said. Mr. Vassarenko had established himself in the early 1990's in Rimini, where he organized shopping tours for Russian businessmen intent on buying Italian-made consumer goods for resale in Russia.With a business associate, Simon Bakhchinyan, Mr. Vassarenko is suspected of having broadened his activities to include smuggling artworks and illegal immigrants, including young East European women going to work in the West as prostitutes.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/11/business/regulators-end-scrutiny-of-bank.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Regulators End Scrutiny of Bank<date>Published: June 11, 2002</date><text>Federal banking regulators said today that they had ended a program of enhanced scrutiny of the Bank of New York that rose out of allegations that Russian mobsters used the bank to launder money.The bank agreed in February 2000 to make periodic reports on its money transfers to regulators to end an investigation of charges the bank played a role in illegally laundering $7 billion in funds from Russia. In the agreement, the bank acknowledged that deficiencies had been identified in its funds transfer and other divisions by regulators.The Federal Reserve, in a statement, said the Feb. 8, 2000, agreement between the Bank of New York and state and federal regulators was terminated.The bank agreed at the time of the agreement to identify customers who might pose a heightened risk of illegal activity. The bank did not have to pay any fines as a result of the deal.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/21/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-planning-to-acquire-trading-firm.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK PLANNING TO ACQUIRE TRADING FIRM<date>Published: May 21, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedThe Bank of New York Company, one of the largest custodians of investor assets, said yesterday that its agency brokerage unit plans to acquire a New York trading firm, Francis P. Maglio &amp; Company, to increase its securities services. Terms were not disclosed. The Bank of New York's BNY ESI &amp; Company subsidiary will add the institutional firm's trading services to its electronic brokerage operation, it said.Correction: May 24, 2002, Friday A brief report in the Company News column of Business Day on Tuesday about an agreement by the Bank of New York to acquire a New York trading firm, Francis P. Maglio, carried an erroneous credit. It was by Bloomberg News, not The Associated Press.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/18/business/company-news-slowdown-in-trading-hurts-bank-of-new-york-profit.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; SLOWDOWN IN TRADING HURTS BANK OF NEW YORK PROFIT<date>Published: April 18, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said that first-quarter profit fell 5.7 percent as a slowdown in trading cut into its securities processing business. Net income for the bank was $362 million, or 50 cents a share, compared with $384 million, or 52 cents a share, a year earlier. Non-interest income, which includes fees from the bank's securities servicing business, fell 5.6 percent, to $810 million from $858 million. ''Global equity trading levels were disappointing,'' said the chairman, Thomas A. Renyi. The bank said net interest income after taxes fell to $425 million from $441 million.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/12/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-buys-asset-management-firm.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK BUYS ASSET MANAGEMENT FIRM<date>Published: March 12, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company has agreed to acquire Gannett Welsh &amp; Kotler Inc., an asset manager based in Boston, to add more midsize institutions and clients with high net worths. Terms were not disclosed. Gannett Welsh &amp; Kotler, which is closely held, manages about $5 billion in assets and offers fixed-income and equity-portfolio management services. Its clients will have access to the products and services of the Bank of New York. The purchase will increase the bank's assets under management to about $72 billion, the company said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/05/business/how-trail-of-big-currency-losses-remained-uncovered-for-5-years.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">How Trail of Big Currency Losses Remained Uncovered for 5 Years<date>Published: March 05, 2002</date><text>Things were getting hot last year for John M. Rusnak, a currency trader at a Baltimore bank, which now says that he hid $691 million in losses over five years.He was not sleeping well, according to someone who knows him, and he needed cash to conceal his growing losses. He had managed to sweep $211 million of losses under the rug in 2000, according to the bank, on top of $90 million in losses the three previous years.So Mr. Rusnak dug deep into his bag of tricks and struck separate deals with four banks that generated a total of more than $200 million in cash, according to a person involved in the investigation and an executive at one of the banks.These deals were technically options trades, but they were effectively loans to Mr. Rusnak and his bank, Allfirst Financial, from Citibank, Bank of America,, Deutsche Bank and Bank of New York, say foreign exchange executives, including someone from a bank that made one of the deals. The trades enabled Mr. Rusnak to avoid attracting too much attention at Allfirst for one more year -- the last.Mr. Rusnak had already taken steps to cover his tracks with fictitious trades that the counterparties were unaware of. The prices on these fake trades were far out of the trading ranges at the time, and the firms on the other side of the apparent trades faced big losses. The terms might have raised eyebrows at some banks but apparently did not set off alarms at Allfirst, a unit of Allied Irish Banks of Dublin. In addition, the Singapore telephone number provided for confirming one trade was false. Though it was supposed to be the back office of Bank of America, the number was for a Singapore law office, according to a foreign exchange executive who has seen the fake confirmation.The four big option trades and the fake trades do not mean that there was outside collusion, though the four option trades might have been spotted by those outside the bank dealing with Mr. Rusnak. But in the dwindling world of currency trading, Mr. Rusnak was an important customer who was courted by the banks for his business. Although employed by a regional bank, he was a mover and shaker in the foreign exchange market, making deals of up to $150 million, traders said.While outsiders may have had reasons not to look too hard at a profitable client, inside Allfirst, internal controls apparently failed, as Mr. Rusnak's cover-up was so successful that under him the bank's foreign exchange revenue quintupled over five years.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/15/business/bank-of-new-york-suit-revived.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank of New York Suit Revived<date>Published: January 15, 2002</date><text>A federal appeals court revived a lawsuit accusing executives of the Bank of New York Company of looting assets from Inkombank, a Russian bank that is now defunct.The suit by Inkombank depositors claims that bank executives, Russian mobsters and a few Bank of New York employees systematically transferred money through the New York-based bank and caused the Russian bank to fail.Reversing a lower court decision, the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit ruled yesterday that the depositors had made sufficient factual claims to support a civil racketeering case.Allegations ''that senior B.N.Y. officials associated with certain senior Inkombank officials, forming an enterprise to loot Inkombank,'' were adequate to support the suit, the court said.Judge Lewis Kaplan of United States District Court dismissed the case last year, saying it should be heard in Russia. The appeals court did not address that point, but it did order Judge Kaplan to rule on another legal issue raised by the bank.The lawsuit stemmed from revelations in 1999 that a former Bank of New York executive, Lucy Edwards, and her husband, Peter Berlin, used an illegal wire-transfer operation to move billions of dollars through three accounts at the bank. Both have pleaded guilty.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/04/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-agrees-to-buy-a-unit-of-weiss-peck.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK AGREES TO BUY A UNIT OF WEISS, PECK<date>Published: January 04, 2002</date><text>Bank of New York said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the stock-and-bond clearing unit of the money manager Weiss, Peck &amp; Greer for an undisclosed amount. The Weiss, Peck unit, which serves about 70 clients, will become part of Bank of New York's BNY Clearing Services subsidiary. The unit provides securities clearing, trade execution and settlement to broker-dealers, banks and other financial intermediaries. Weiss, Peck is a unit of the Rabobank Group of the Netherlands.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/03/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-buys-credit-suisse-first-boston-unit.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK BUYS CREDIT SUISSE FIRST BOSTON UNIT<date>Published: January 03, 2002</date><text>The Bank of New York Company said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Credit Suisse First Boston's trading and research services unit, Autranet. The price was not disclosed. The deal, which helps Credit Suisse's effort to cut costs, will strengthen the Bank of New York's brokerage and clearing services business. Autranet's 75 employees will join the Bank of New York. Autranet has more than 500 institutional investment managers as customers. Credit Suisse First Boston, based in New York, is the investment banking arm of the Credit Suisse Group of Switzerland.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/21/business/company-news-bank-of-new-york-to-write-off-235-million-in-bad-loans.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; BANK OF NEW YORK TO WRITE OFF $235 MILLION IN BAD LOANS<date>Published: December 21, 2001</date><text>The Bank of New York said yesterday that it would write off $235 million in bad loans in the fourth quarter but still meet analysts' earnings estimates. The bank said the move was part of a program to speed up the disposal of loans or loan commitments to 24 telecommunications companies and one energy trading company. The company said these 25 ''credit relationships'' involved $758 million in loan commitments and $488 million in outstanding loans. Officials would not identify any of the companies, but the bank is known to have up to $100 million in exposure to Enron, which is in bankruptcy proceedings, and to be heavily committed to telecommunications ventures like Winstar Communications, which has also filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/29/business/company-news-lawsuit-against-bank-of-new-york-is-dismissed.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">COMPANY NEWS; LAWSUIT AGAINST BANK OF NEW YORK IS DISMISSED<date>Published: November 29, 2001</date><text>A federal judge has dismissed a shareholder lawsuit against the Bank of New York Company that accused 19 senior officials of permitting the bank to launder money when it expanded in Russia in the 1990s. Judge Denny Chin of United States District Court in New York dismissed the lawsuit, which also named the company's chairman, Thomas Renyi, as a defendant. Judge Chin said plaintiffs bought shares in the company in 1998, after the reported wrongdoing. A spokesman for the bank declined to comment. The plaintiffs contended that officers and directors had acted recklessly. Melvyn I. Weiss, a lawyer for the shareholders, characterized the ruling as a ''technical decision.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/21/business/investing-with-john-c-lui-bny-hamilton-small-cap-growth-fund.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">INVESTING WITH/John C. Lui; BNY Hamilton Small Cap Growth Fund<date>Published: October 21, 2001</date><text>WHILE the stock market remains unsettled in the aftermath of Sept. 11, John C. Lui, who runs the $325 million BNY Hamilton Small Cap Growth fund, sees slow but steady growth ahead. ''With the Federal Reserve and the government using monetary and fiscal policy to stimulate the economy, you have to look past the negative profit projections for 2001,'' Mr. Lui said from his office in Lower Manhattan, next to the New York Stock Exchange. He expects that declines in consumer confidence will hurt the economy in the short term, he said, but that shoppers will eventually resume spending. ''Their largest asset is their home, which hasn't dropped as much as stock prices, and they have a high propensity to spend,'' he said of consumers. Over a three- to five-year corporate profit cycle, Mr. Lui said he expects a 7 percent earnings growth rate, on average, for the companies in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index. The fund returned 25 percent a year, on average, for the three years through Thursday, compared with 9.6 percent for its midcap growth group and 1.5 percent for the S.&amp; P. 500, according to Morningstar Inc. It lost 25.5 percent in the last 12 months, versus a 36.1 percent loss for its group and a 19.4 drop in the S.&amp; P. The fund, like some others with a small-cap focus, has been classified as a midcap fund by Morningstar because the average capitalization of the portfolio companies over three years exceeds Morningstar's cutoff. Mr. Lui, 44, is vice president for institutional equity management at the Bank of New York, the fund's adviser. Institutional shares require a $100,000 investment minimum, while the minimum for individuals is $2,000. To pick the fund's stocks, he screens approximately 7,000 United States companies with market capitalizations of $100 million to $2 billion. He looks for businesses in which earnings growth over the next two to three years may be underestimated by Wall Street and will exceed that of the S.&amp; P. 500. About 150 companies meet his tests. To whittle the list -- the fund now has about 100 stocks -- he further reviews the earnings projections. ''You kick the tires,'' Mr. Lui said. ''You say: 'These are crystal-ball projections. Do these estimates make sense?' '' He receives help from two analysts of small-cap stocks but also works with seven industry analysts who focus on bigger stocks. ''Our companies sell to their companies,'' he explained, ''so we get a lot of useful information from them.'' To find growth companies, he says he looks for businesses with dominant market positions and proprietary products or services. ''We ask ourselves: 'What is the advantage of the widget that this company makes? What kind of growth rate can we expect? How long can the growth rate be sustained?' '' He also wants companies to have experienced management, preferably compensated with stock and able to communicate well with analysts, to prevent unrealistically high earnings estimates. ''With many small companies, the founders work from their garage and employ family members,'' he said. ''They think the initial offering is the end of the story. But you need Wall Street money to plan for widget No. 2.'' IN financial services, Mr. Lui said, ''we've seen niche companies that have developed a growth model.'' One of them, he said, is UCBH Holdings of San Francisco, owner of United Commercial Bank. The company focuses on serving Chinese-American customers by hiring bilingual employees and offering bilingual cash machines and Internet sites. ''This community is growing explosively,'' he said, ''but the rest of the major money center banks don't know how to cater to them.'' He originally bought shares in January 2000 at $10.31; the stock now trades at $28.80. He also likes Too Inc., a retailer based in Columbus, Ohio, that focuses on girls in the 7-to-14 age group in its Limited Too stores. The company was spun off from the Limited in 1999. ''These are customers that are in between Gap Kids and Abercrombie &amp; Fitch,'' he said. ''There's plenty of opportunity to grow and expand. It's growing faster than the average company but sells at a discount to the S.&amp; P. 500 companies.'' Shares sell for 16 times 2002 earnings estimates, versus a multiple of 21 for the S.&amp; P. 500, he said, because ''people think that no one will go shopping again because of the recent events.'' He bought shares in August at $24.95; they now trade at $26.12. Mr. Lui also likes Province Healthcare, a company in Brentwood, Tenn., that owns and operates acute-care hospitals, mostly outside of urban areas. Wall Street analysts say Province's earnings are likely to grow at 25 percent a year for two or three years. He bought the stock at $28.61 in August 2000; it now trades at $32.25. Photo: The fund manager John C. Lui, seeing ''a high propensity to spend'' among consumers, predicts steady growth for stocks next year. (Don Hogan Charles/The New York Times) Chart: ''BNY Hamilton Small Cap Growth'' Category: Midcap growth Net assets: $337 million Inception: April 1997 Manager: John C. Lui since inception Minimum purchase: $100,000 (institutional shares); $2,000 (individual shares) Portfolio turnover: 47% 3-year annualized return through Thursday (institutional shares): 25.0% Category average: 9.6% Sector breakdown Bank holding companies: 11% Other: 56% Electronics: 10% Retail apparel and shoes: 8% Health/medical facilities: 8% Specialty retail: 7% Fees (institutional shares) Front-end load: None 12b-1 fee: None Deferred load: None Expense ratio: 1.04% (Sources: Morningstar Inc.; company reports)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/19/business/bank-s-net-falls-attacks-cited.html?ref=bankofnewyorkcompany">Bank's Net Falls; Attacks Cited<date>Published: October 19, 2001</date><text>Bank of New York said yesterday that its third-quarter profit fell 33 percent, partly because the Sept. 11 attacks knocked out some of the its computer systems and forced it to shut down branches. The bank, based in New York, had to evacuate about 8,300 workers after two hijacked planes destroyed the World Trade Center on Sept. 11. The bank said it was hurt by the cost of contingency plans and restoring its settlement and automated teller machine networks. It earned $243 million, or 33 cents a share, in the third quarter, including the impact of the attacks, compared with $363 million, or 49 cents a share, a year earlier. The attacks pushed third-quarter profit down $140 million, more than its original estimate of $125 million. Excluding a one-time charge of 19 cents a share because of the attack, Bank of New York earned $383 million, or 52 cents a share, in the quarter. Analysts had expected 51 cents a share, according to Thomson Financial/First Call.</text></article></page></root>
