<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Baxter International Inc"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/16/health/research/16flu.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Flu Vaccine Made by New, Faster Method Is Successful, Researchers Say<date>Published: February 15, 2011</date><text>A flu vaccine made by a new, faster method works just as well as existing products, researchers reported Tuesday.The finding clears a hurdle in the government’s effort to move toward a manufacturing process that could allow for a more reliable supply of seasonal flu shots and quicker responses to pandemics. The new vaccine, which could become available in the United States in the next few years, is made by growing the influenza virus in cultures of animal cells rather than in the chicken eggs that have been used for more than half a century. Using animal cells could shave weeks off the six months or so that is now required to produce a vaccine for a pandemic. In the 2009 swine flu pandemic, large quantities of vaccine were not ready until after the wave of disease appeared to have crested. Using animal cells, which are grown in enclosed steel tanks, also reduces the risk of bacterial contamination, which has led to shortages of seasonal vaccines in some years. “I just think it’s an improvement in vaccine production that has been warranted for a long time,” said Dr. W. Paul Glezen, an influenza expert at the Baylor College of Medicine who wrote a commentary to accompany the report, which was published online Tuesday by The Lancet. “I just feel we’ve been sort of slow in implementing it.” Dr. Glezen said shorter production times would allow health officials to wait longer before deciding which strains to include in the next winter’s flu vaccine, a decision that now has to be made around February. That would increase the chance that the strains in the vaccine match the strains in circulation. In addition, Dr. Glezen said, when the virus grows in chicken eggs, it undergoes some changes. “It may not match the circulating virus as much as a vaccine made in mammalian cells,” he said. In a large clinical trial involving 7,250 healthy adults, the new vaccine was more than 70 percent effective in preventing the seasonal flu, according to researchers from Baxter International, the developer of the new vaccine. That rate is similar to what egg-based vaccines have demonstrated in past studies, the researchers wrote. The clinical trial was paid for by the Department of Health and Human Services, which awarded $1.3 billion to six companies in 2006 to develop cell-culture flu vaccines, including $242 million to Baxter and its partner, the DynPort Vaccine Company. The trial is the second to show a cell-culture influenza vaccine to be as effective as conventional ones. In November, a study involving a Novartis vaccine was published in Clinical Infectious Diseases. Experts say it is no surprise that the vaccines work. Still, proof is needed for them to win regulatory approval. Baxter began selling the vaccine in parts of Europe last October. The company, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., would not say when it would apply for approval in the United States. P. Noel Barrett, vice president for research and development in Baxter’s bioscience division, said the company was in discussions with the Food and Drug Administration about what kind of data would be needed for approval. The main issue, Dr. Barrett said, was that the clinical trial involved healthy volunteers ages 18 to 49 and compared the vaccine with a placebo. Yet children and the elderly are more vulnerable to severe problems from the flu, so for those populations it might be unethical to conduct trials using a placebo. Baxter therefore wants to show that the vaccine produces antibodies in children and the elderly at levels that correlate with those in the adults. “We are certainly committed to moving this forward into the U.S. as fast as possible,” Dr. Barrett said. Novartis won approval for its cell-culture vaccine in Europe in 2007 and plans to start the process leading to F.D.A. approval this year. With help from a nearly $500 million federal contract, the company has built a cell-culture vaccine factory in Holly Springs, N.C. Robin Robinson, the director of the Biomedical Advanced Research and Development Authority in the Department of Health and Human Services, said cell cultures would never completely supplant egg-based production. Two of the six companies that received the federal cell-culture awards in 2006 have dropped their efforts and given back the money, he said. Dr. Robinson said cell culture was an “interim solution” until even faster techniques come along that do not require growing the virus at all. Baxter’s flu vaccine is made in so-called Vero cells, derived from the kidneys of African green monkeys. The cells are already used to make other vaccines, including those for polio and rabies. The clinical trial was conducted in the United States during the flu season of 2008-9. Only 13 people, or 0.4 percent, of those getting the vaccine became infected with a flu virus matching one of the three strains in the vaccine, compared with 60 people, or 1.7 percent, of those getting the placebo. That translates to an effectiveness of 78.5 percent. Counting all strains of flu, even those not in the vaccine, the infection rates were 0.6 percent with the vaccine and 2.2 percent with the placebo, making the vaccine 71.5 percent effective. Side effects were similar to those of conventional vaccines, the researchers said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/14/business/14device.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">F.D.A. Orders Baxter to Recall Infusion Pumps<date>Published: July 13, 2010</date><text>The Food and Drug Administration ordered Baxter International to recall all of its Colleague infusion pumps in use and provide a refund or no-cost replacement to United States customers.Electronic infusion pumps that deliver intravenous fluids like medication or nutrients have come under scrutiny by the F.D.A., which in April said it would establish additional requirements for manufacturers. “Baxter has failed to adequately correct, within a reasonable timeframe, the deficiencies in the Colleague infusion pumps still in use,” the F.D.A. said in a letter on Tuesday to the company. The F.D.A. said it gave the final order to Baxter after finding “unacceptable” the company’s planned timeline to fix the pump’s problems. Baxter told the F.D.A. in April that it planned to begin its next round of corrections to the pumps in May 2012 and expected to complete them by 2013. The recall affects about 200,000 pumps, mostly used in hospitals, said Erin Gardiner, a Baxter spokeswoman. The F.D.A. ordered a transition plan for the recall that includes the option of replacing Colleague pumps covered by a June 2006 consent decree with a replacement pump other than the Colleague model. Baxter stopped selling the Colleague pumps in 2005. It sold $170 million worth of the pumps in 2004, the last full year of sales for the product, Ms. Gardiner said. Baxter said customers could replace Colleague pumps with the company’s Sigma Spectrum pumps, or they could receive the lesser of the pump’s depreciated value — a minimum of $1,500 for a single-channel pump or $3,000 for a triple-channel pump — or the purchase price. The company said it would execute the recall over the next two years and provide service and support for customers still using a Colleague pump during the transition period. Ben Andrew, an analyst at William Blair &amp; Company, said the two-year window gave Baxter more time than had been expected to arrange the manufacture of replacement Sigma Spectrum pumps. But a Goldman Sachs analyst, David Roman, said he did not think Sigma International had enough capacity to replace the full Colleague installed base. The pump recall, he said, also could have repercussions for other segments of Baxter. Baxter said it believed that a charge to earnings for the recall of $588 million, recorded in the first quarter, was adequate. Hospira, a competitor that also sells infusion pumps and accessories, could stand to benefit from the recall, Mr. Roman said. Authorities in 2005 seized more than 6,000 of the Colleague pumps thought to have a defect that could cause them to shut down or deliver the wrong amount of medication. The F.D.A. has said it has been working with Baxter since 1999 to correct numerous device flaws.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DA113FF937A35756C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=baxterinternationalinc">F.D.A. Deal Leads to Recall of Infusion Pumps<date>Published: May 4, 2010</date><text>Baxter International is recalling its Colleague infusion pumps from the American market under an agreement with federal regulators that sought to fix problems like battery failures and software errors. The Food and Drug Administration said on April 23 that infusion pumps used to administer drugs and liquids were linked to more than 56,000 complaints of injuries, deaths and malfunctions from 2005 to 2009. The Baxter Healthcare Corporation, the company's principal American subsidiary, has been under a consent decree with the F.D.A. since June 2006 that allowed the agency to require a recall of the pumps, the company said. ''There are just under 200,000 of these pumps in use'' at hospitals and other medical facilities, Erin Gardiner, a Baxter spokeswoman, said on Monday. The Colleague pumps, which have not been sold to new customers since 2005, will be phased out, she said. Baxter expects to record a pretax charge of $400 million to $600 million in the first quarter related to the recall, the company said Monday in a statement. The company isn't otherwise revising its 2010 forecast. The F.D.A. on April 30 rejected as ''unacceptable'' a plan by Baxter to keep the Colleague pumps in use until 2013 and ordered the recall, the agency said via e-mail. Baxter expects to offer to exchange its Sigma Spectrum infusion pumps for the Colleague pumps. The pumps are used in hospitals to deliver nutrients to patients in comas, blood-thinning drugs to heart patients and chemotherapy to cancer patients.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/03/business/03medschool.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Harvard Medical School in Ethics Quandary<date>Published: March 2, 2009</date><text>BOSTON  In a first-year pharmacology class at Harvard Medical School, Matt Zerden grew wary as the professor promoted the benefits of cholesterol drugs and seemed to belittle a student who asked about side effects. Skip to next paragraph Related Pfizer Worker Photographed Protesters at Harvard (March 3, 2009) Senator Asks Pfizer About Harvard Payments Add to Portfolio Pfizer Inc Bristol-Myers Squibb Co Baxter International Inc Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Jodi Hilton for The New York Times Some students, like Vijay Yanamadala, right, and Brian Fuchs, favor continued links between Harvard and drug companies. Mr. Zerden later discovered something by searching online that he began sharing with his classmates. The professor was not only a full-time member of the Harvard Medical faculty, but a paid consultant to 10 drug companies, including five makers of cholesterol treatments. “I felt really violated,” Mr. Zerden, now a fourth-year student, recently recalled. “Here we have 160 open minds trying to learn the basics in a protected space, and the information he was giving wasn’t as pure as I think it should be.” Mr. Zerden’s minor stir four years ago has lately grown into a full-blown movement by more than 200 Harvard Medical School students and sympathetic faculty, intent on exposing and curtailing the industry influence in their classrooms and laboratories, as well as in Harvard’s 17 affiliated teaching hospitals and institutes. They say they are concerned that the same money that helped build the school’s world-class status may in fact be hurting its reputation and affecting its teaching. The students argue, for example, that Harvard should be embarrassed by the F grade it recently received from the American Medical Student Association, a national group that rates how well medical schools monitor and control drug industry money. Harvard Medical School’s peers received much higher grades, ranging from the A for the University of Pennsylvania, to B’s received by Stanford, Columbia and New York University, to the C for Yale. Harvard has fallen behind, some faculty and administrators say, because its teaching hospitals are not owned by the university, complicating reform; because the dean is fairly new and his predecessor was such an industry booster that he served on a pharmaceutical company board; and because a crackdown, simply put, could cost it money or faculty. Further, the potential embarrassments  a Senate investigation of several medical professors, the F grade, a new state law effective July 1 requiring Massachusetts doctors to disclose corporate gifts over $50  are only now adding to pressure for change. The dean, Dr. Jeffrey S. Flier, who says he wants Harvard to catch up with the best practices at other leading medical schools, recently announced a 19-member committee to re-examine his school’s conflict-of-interest policies. The group, which includes three students, is to meet in private on Thursday. Advising the group will be Dr. David Korn, a former dean of the Stanford Medical School who started work at Harvard about four months ago as vice provost for research. Last year he helped the Association of American Medical Colleges draft a model conflict-of-interest policy for medical schools. The Harvard students have already secured a requirement that all professors and lecturers disclose their industry ties in class  a blanket policy that has been adopted by no other leading medical school. (One Harvard professor’s disclosure in class listed 47 company affiliations.) “Harvard needs to live up to its name,” said Kirsten Austad, 24, a first-year Harvard Medical student who is one of the movement’s leaders. “We are really being indoctrinated into a field of medicine that is becoming more and more commercialized.” David Tian, 24, a first-year Harvard Medical student, said: “Before coming here, I had no idea how much influence companies had on medical education. And it’s something that’s purposely meant to be under the table, providing information under the guise of education when that information is also presented for marketing purposes.” The students say they worry that pharmaceutical industry scandals in recent years  including some criminal convictions, billions of dollars in fines, proof of bias in research and publishing and false marketing claims  have cast a bad light on the medical profession. And they criticize Harvard as being less vigilant than other leading medical schools in monitoring potential financial conflicts by faculty members. Dr. Flier says that the Harvard Medical faculty may lead the nation in receiving money from industry, as well as government and charities, and he does not want to tighten the spigot. “One entirely appropriate source, if done properly, is industrial funds,” Dr. Flier said in an interview. And school officials see corporate support for their faculty as all the more crucial, as the university endowment has lost 22 percent of its value since last July and the recession has caused philanthropic contributors to retrench. The school said it was unable to provide annual measures of the money flow to its faculty, beyond the $8.6 million that pharmaceutical companies contributed last year for basic science research and the $3 million for continuing education classes on campus. Most of the money goes to professors at the Harvard-affiliated teaching hospitals, and the dean’s office does not keep track of the total. But no one disputes that many individual Harvard Medical faculty members receive tens or even hundreds of thousands of dollars a year through industry consulting and speaking fees. Under the school’s disclosure rules, about 1,600 of 8,900 professors and lecturers have reported to the dean that they or a family member had a financial interest in a business related to their teaching, research or clinical care. The reports show 149 with financial ties to Pfizer and 130 with Merck. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on March 3, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/23/business/23drug.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Financier Stands by a Firm Tainted by Heparin<date>Published: May 23, 2008</date><text>Two years ago, a financier named Malon Wilkus spied what seemed like a good buy: Scientific Protein Laboratories, of Waunakee, Wis. He never dreamed that events on the other side of the world would cost him millions on his investment. Mr. Wilkus, the founder of American Capital, an investment firm in Maryland, now finds himself swept into the story of deadly, contaminated heparin imported from China. Scientific Protein sells an ingredient for heparin, and it says suppliers in China provided it with tainted goods. The company sold its products to Baxter International, which makes heparin. Baxter recalled the drug, which has been linked to 81 deaths in the United States. “It’s a sad situation, of course, but it’s a company that for about 30 years has been producing a drug that has saved millions of people’s lives,” Mr. Wilkus said of Scientific Protein. “We think this is a very good company.” Even so, American Capital, which owns stakes in some 170 companies, booked $29.6 million in unrealized depreciation related to its investment in Scientific Protein in the first quarter. American Capital’s stock is down about $4 since February, but that appears more related to the company’s write-downs on some of its assets, including mortgage bonds. Jefferies, the investment bank, downgraded American Capital’s stock to underperform in April, but did not mention the tainted blood thinner in its report. The Jefferies analyst said he was aware of the risk the scandal might pose to the company but that he did not have enough information to estimate the potential legal fallout. It is also unclear whether lawsuits will hit American Capital at all, since Baxter, the distributor of heparin in the United States, is more well known. Mr. Wilkus said this week that he had no plans to sell Scientific Protein, whose troubles underscore the dangers that loosely regulated, global supply chains can pose to companies, their investors and the public. Scientific Protein set up a subsidiary in China in the 1990s, but the company’s roots are in Wisconsin, where it was founded by Oscar Mayer, of hot dog fame, to use the animal byproducts of its food products. Pig intestines are used to make heparin. When American Capital purchased its stake in Scientific Protein, executives cited the company’s production of heparin as a motivating factor. Scientific Protein has been owned by four companies in the last 30 years, including Wyeth, the big drug company. American Capital’s connection with Scientific Protein has remained largely under the radar. The buyout company was not the focus of a Congressional panel on the problem in April, where David Strunce, the chief executive of Scientific Protein, testified. Regulators at the hearing said the contamination appeared to have been intentional. The blood thinner is the latest example of breakdowns of the supply chain traced to Chinese factories. The Food and Drug Administration halted exports from Scientific Protein’s Chinese lab in February, after discovering the problem during an inspection. This week, Mr. Wilkus blamed Scientific Protein’s supplier, echoing the public comments of Scientific Protein’s chief executive. He said he did not regret his investment in the company, adding that there was still a huge market for heparin. But, he said, “without China it will be hard for the producers to really fulfill the need.” Speaking about his entire investment portfolio this week, Mr. Wilkus said there were always companies that he regretted purchasing. But Scientific Protein, he said, was not one of them. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/22/health/policy/22fda.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">U.S. Identifies Tainted Heparin in 11 Countries<date>Published: April 22, 2008</date><text>WASHINGTON  A contaminated blood thinner from China has been found in drug supplies in 11 countries, and federal officials said Monday they had discovered a clear link between the contaminant and severe reactions now associated with 81 deaths in the United States. Skip to next paragraph RSS Feed Get Health News From The New York Times » But a Chinese official disputed the assertion that the contaminant found in the drug, heparin, caused any deaths and insisted that his country’s inspectors be allowed to inspect the American plant where the finished heparin vials were made. He said any future agreement to allow American inspections of Chinese firms should be reciprocal. “We don’t have a strong evidence to show that it is heparin or its contaminant that caused the problem,” said the official, Ning Chen, second secretary at the Chinese Embassy. Mr. Chen said that illnesses associated with contaminated heparin had occurred only in the United States, which he said suggested that the problem arose in this country. Dr. Janet Woodcock, director of the Food and Drug Administration’s drug center, said that German regulators uncovered a cluster of illnesses among dialysis patients who took contaminated heparin. She said Chinese officials had conceded that heparin produced in their country contained a contaminant, though they say it was not connected to the illnesses. “Heparin should not be contaminated, regardless of whether or not that contamination caused acute adverse events,” Dr. Woodcock said. “We are fairly confident based on the biological information that we have had that this contaminant is capable of triggering these adverse reactions.” The dispute is a sign of growing tensions between China and the United States over the safety of Chinese imports. China has in recent years exported poisonous toothpaste, lead-painted toys, toxic pet food, tainted fish and now, contaminated medicine. Bills to require far more aggressive inspections of Chinese products and companies are being proposed by members of Congress. Hearings are scheduled for Tuesday in the House and Thursday in the Senate. China has lurched between defensiveness and cooperation on issues of product safety. Last year, it initially blocked the F.D.A. from investigating tainted pet food and accused foreign forces of exaggerating the issue. Then in July, China said that it had executed its former top food and drug regulator for taking bribes and promised reforms. The F.D.A. sent a warning letter on Monday to Changzhou SPL, the Chinese plant identified as the source of contaminated heparin made by Baxter International in the United States. It warned that the plant used unclean tanks to make heparin, that it accepted raw materials from an unacceptable vendor and that it had no adequate way to remove impurities. Heparin is made from the mucous membranes of the intestines of slaughtered pigs that, in China, are often cooked in unregulated family workshops. The contaminant, identified as oversulfated chondroitin sulfate, a cheaper substance, slipped through the usual testing and was recognized only after more sophisticated tests were used. The F.D.A. has identified 12 Chinese companies that have supplied contaminated heparin to 11 countries  Australia, Canada, China, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the Netherlands, New Zealand and the United States. Deborah Autor, director of compliance at the F.D.A.’s drug center, said the agency did not know the original source of all the contamination or the points in the supply chain at which it was added. Officials have discovered heparin lots that included the cheap fake additive manufactured as early as early as 2006, although a spike in illnesses associated with contaminated heparin began in November and persisted through February, officials said. Separately, the Government Accountability Office will release a report on Tuesday showing that the F.D.A. would need to spend at least $56 million more next year to begin full inspections of foreign plants. It would need to spend at least $15 million annually to inspect China’s drug plants every two years, which is the domestic standard. Bush administration officials have acknowledged problems associated with poor inspection of overseas plants and have plans to improve the situation. But President Bush’s budget does not provide the F.D.A. with funds to hire more inspectors. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/10/health/policy/10heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Heparin Is Now Suspected in 62 Fatalities Across U.S.<date>Published: April 10, 2008</date><text>The number of suspicious deaths in the United States linked to the blood thinner heparin has risen to 62 from 19, with most of them reported this past December, January and February, according to the first detailed analyses of heparin fatalities by the Food and Drug Administration. Skip to next paragraph RSS Feed Get Health News From The New York Times » The F.D.A. is still investigating whether those deaths and hundreds of allergic reactions were caused by a heparinlike contaminant made in China that was added to the drug somewhere during the manufacturing process. The drug agency defined suspicious deaths as those involving one or more allergic reactions or a drop in blood pressure. There have been no reports of deaths since the end of February, after Baxter International recalled heparin made with ingredients from a Chinese supplier. The agency’s Web site reported Tuesday that the 62 deaths covered a 14-month period that began in January 2007. In comparison, the agency said, there were three suspicious deaths involving heparin in all of 2006. The F.D.A. had earlier identified the contaminant as a chemically altered substance that slipped through standard testing screens because it mimicked heparin. The agency was able to spot the additive only by using a more sophisticated test. Investigators have not yet established how or why the additive, called oversulfated chondroitin sulfate, ended up in heparin, though the fact that it is cheaper to make than the actual drug points to the possible involvement of counterfeiters. In addition to Baxter, companies that have recalled heparin products made with Chinese ingredients include Covidien, formerly Tyco Healthcare, and B. Braun. Both Covidien and Braun said that they had received no reports of adverse reactions from the heparin and that the recalls had been undertaken merely as a precaution. Similar recalls of the drug have occurred in Germany, Denmark, France, Italy and Japan. Heparin is made from the mucous membranes in pig intestines. It is commonly used in dialysis and in many types of surgery. Drug regulators in China, the world’s biggest supplier of heparin ingredients, have said they are tightening supervision over production of the drug, which involves thousands of small family workshops that gather and treat the raw material from pig intestines. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/01/business/01pigdrugs.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Seeking Alternatives to Animal-Derived Drugs<date>Published: April 1, 2008</date><text>Chopped pig pancreas may not sound appetizing. But most cystic fibrosis patients eat a refined version of it each breakfast, lunch and dinner  five large capsules a meal  to supply enzymes their bodies do not produce. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Rick Friedman for The New York Times Hiren Patel at Altus Pharmaceuticals, which is working to develop a synthetic version of pancreatic enzymes. The pills are life-sustaining for most of the nearly 30,000 people in the United States with cystic fibrosis, a hereditary disease that attacks the lungs and digestive tract. But partly because of the drug’s source there have been longstanding concerns about those capsules, according to Leslie Hendeles, a University of Florida professor of pharmacy and pediatrics who has studied them. “What would happen if there were a virus, a pig virus, something analogous to mad cow disease?” Dr. Hendeles asked. The recent recall of the Baxter International blood thinner heparin, which has been linked to 19 deaths and whose main ingredient comes from pig intestines, has raised public awareness that even in the age of sophisticated bioengineering, certain crucial medicines are still derived from animal parts. The concerns remain, even though, as it turned out, the heparin problem had nothing to do with the pigs. A company called Scientific Protein Laboratories, which supplies the active ingredient in heparin to Baxter International, is also the supplier of much of the pig-derived pancreatic enzymes used by cystic fibrosis patients. Medical and drug scientists have long worried about animal-derived drugs, but they also know that the search for synthetic alternatives has often ended in frustration. “A number of pharmaceutical firms are trying to eliminate all animal-sourced products from their raw material streams,” said Dr. Robert G. Rohwer, the director of a Department of Veterans Affairs neurovirology laboratory. “It’s a very demanding task.” In the case of cystic fibrosis, though, continued as well as a history of unusual variations and impurities in the pig-derived pills, have led the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation to pursue an alternative. The foundation is working with Altus Pharmaceuticals of Cambridge, Mass., to develop a synthetic version of the enzyme capsules. Altus has entered the final stages of clinical studies on the drug and is planning to seek Food and Drug Administration approval next year to market its synthetic product. The company’s chief financial officer, Jonathan I. Lieber, said that to make the drug, the company uses enzymes derived from microbes that come not from animals but from bacteria and fungus. The enzymes are crystallized, then reproduced in large vats similar to those used to brew beer. Synthetic replacements are also being sought for other medical products, including the lung fluids called surfactants that are used in neonatal wards and for raw materials used in pharmaceutical production. There are also various efforts to find synthetic versions of heparin. History has shown that the risk of transmitting disease from animal-based drugs, while small, is not merely theoretical, according to Paul W. Brown, a retired National Institutes of Health senior investigator. “Any time you take a tissue or an extract process from a tissue from one species and put it into a another species or even another animal, you run the risk of unwanted pathogens that you didn’t know were there; that’s been responsible for repeated problems over the course of time,” Dr. Brown said. “If you can do something without taking tissue or a product from another being, you’re ahead of the game.” Even before the heparin recall, efforts were under way to find synthetic alternatives to that drug. Millions of vials of heparin are used each year in this country to prevent the formation of blood clots during major surgery and kidney dialysis. So far, no ideal synthetic version has been found. Arixtra, a synthetic drug that is marketed by GlaxoSmithKline and copies the most active portion of heparin, has been successfully used for some types of surgery. But besides being about 10 times as expensive as heparin  the company said Arixtra sells for about $42 for a low dose and twice that for a higher dose  it has at least one major medical drawback. Unlike heparin, Arixtra has no specific antidote to enable doctors to reverse its anti-clotting properties if a patient develops bleeding problems. Robert J. Linhardt, a heparin expert at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., who has been working to develop another synthetic alternative, said the use of pigs for heparin was of less concern to him than the issue of where the heparin pigs came from. The recent recall in the United States involved heparin material from Chinese pigs that Scientific Protein Laboratories supplied to Baxter International, a leading heparin marketer. “There are 700 million pigs slaughtered each year, and 400 million are slaughtered in China,” Dr. Linhardt said. “It makes us dependent. Basically 70 percent of the supply of heparin is coming from China. There’s very little regulatory control in China. So the reason why synthetic heparins are appealing is that they could be made in places where there is stronger regulatory control.” In some cases, companies are managing risks of animal-derived products by using animals from specially controlled herds. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED81639F935A15750C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=baxterinternationalinc">WORLD BRIEFING | EUROPE; Heparin Is Recalled In 3 Countries<date>Published: March 26, 2008</date><text>Health officials in Denmark, France and Italy began recalling stores of the blood-thinning drug heparin and any ingredients used in it that had originated in China, as a precautionary measure. In the United States, certain batches of the drug have been linked to 19 deaths and hundreds of allergic reactions. The lots were manufactured by Baxter International and used ingredients from China; investigators discovered that the faulty batches contained a contaminant. Baxter has recalled virtually all its heparin products. In Germany, heparin made by Rotexmedica from Chinese raw materials is believed to be the cause of more than 80 cases of allergic reactions. There have been no reactions reported in Denmark, France or Italy, according to the European Medicines Agency.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/22/world/asia/22heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">China Orders New Oversight of Heparin, With Tainted Batches Tied to U.S. Deaths<date>Published: March 22, 2008</date><text>SHANGHAI  China’s top drug safety agency has ordered its local bureaus to increase supervision over the production of heparin, a blood-thinning drug that has been linked to at least 19 deaths and hundreds of allergic reactions in the United States, China’s state-run news agency reported Friday. Skip to next paragraph Related Scientists Near Source of Altered Heparin (March 19, 2008) The drug agency, the State Food and Drug Administration, said producers of the active ingredient in heparin must now obtain their raw material from registered suppliers, and it ordered the suppliers to strengthen their checks on the quality and safety of those raw ingredients. The announcement, just hours after American officials said they had identified a contaminant in heparin from China, represents a turnabout for Chinese drug regulators. Previously, they had said they did not have oversight of large parts of the industry, and they had called on importing countries to take responsibility for ensuring heparin’s safety. China is the world’s largest supplier of the active ingredient in heparin. With the drug agency’s announcement, and a related order from the Ministry of Commerce, the government is seeking to bring closer regulation to the heparin industry. Yet officials did not say precisely how they planned to do that, given that so much of the complex supply chain is now unregulated, from thousands of small workshops that gather the raw material from pig intestines up to chemical companies that produce the pure active ingredient in heparin. The American company that manufactured the finished drug associated with the problems in the United States, Baxter International, has recalled virtually all its heparin products. This week, the United States Food and Drug Administration reported that active ingredients from Baxter’s Chinese supplier, Changzhou SPL, were contaminated with a cheap, unapproved ingredient modified to mimic heparin. Investigators are still trying to determine whether the contamination was the result of counterfeiting, and whether the fake material  oversulfated chondroitin sulfate  was the cause of the allergic reactions. In a statement on Friday, the American company that controls Changzhou SPL, Scientific Protein Laboratories, said tests had indicated that the contaminant was already in the crude heparin when it reached the Changzhou SPL factory. “We believe that the contamination identified by the F.D.A. occurred earlier in the supply chain,” the company said. Changzhou SPL, in turn, buys its crude heparin from two wholesalers, called consolidators, that gather it from smaller producers. Last month, The New York Times reported that at least one of Changzhou SPL’s consolidators had received supplies from small unregulated family workshops. The heparin recall in the United States expanded Friday when B. Braun Medical recalled 23 lots of infusion bags made with an active ingredient that came from Changzhou SPL. The recall came after the heparin-like contaminant was found in one lot of heparin sold to B. Braun. The infusion bags are used by hospitalized patients who need heparin over an extended period, said Karen Riley, a spokeswoman for the F.D.A. B. Braun said no adverse effects had been reported. Ms. Riley said that because other companies made the infusion bags there should be no shortage of the product. In recent weeks, the F.D.A. has ordered all American imports of heparin to be inspected for contaminants. Germany has also ordered a recall of some heparin from a different supplier in China after reports of about 80 allergic reactions. That heparin has been found to be tainted as well, but whether the contaminant is the same is not yet known. The Chinese agency’s order, issued Thursday, was accompanied by a separate announcement from the Commerce Ministry. The ministry said it had issued an urgent notice to government offices and trade organizations involved in health and drug exports to step up supervision and inspection of heparin production and to create a system that would allow the industry to trace the path of heparin supplies back to the raw ingredient suppliers. Much of China’s production of raw heparin begins in homes and tiny factories, where teams of three to five people transform pig intestines into a dry substance that is eventually sold to major pharmaceutical companies. Most of the small factories are unlicensed and unregulated. They sell to traders and consolidators, who sell the raw heparin to companies like SPL that purify it to produce the active ingredients. Many of them are not regulated by the Chinese drug agency, since they are considered chemical companies, not drug makers. The active ingredients, in turn, are sold to pharmaceutical companies like Baxter that produce the finished drug. Walt Bogdanich contributed reporting from New York. More Articles in World »</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/19/world/asia/19heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Scientists Near Source of Altered Heparin<date>Published: March 19, 2008</date><text>Scientists investigating a mystery contaminant in the blood thinner heparin are closing in on what they believe is a counterfeit substance, most likely made in China from animal cartilage, that was chemically altered to act like the real drug. The United States Food and Drug Administration declined to confirm that statement and a spokeswoman said the agency would have no comment. But in interviews, heparin experts in China and the United States  including one researcher involved in the inquiry  said that a chemically altered substance called over-sulfated chondroitin sulfate is probably the contaminant that the F.D.A. says is linked to hundreds of allergic reactions and 19 deaths. Even so, researchers said they were not certain that the contaminant, constituting between 5 percent and 20 percent of the drug, is what is causing the allergic reactions, nor do they know precisely how or when it was mixed into the active ingredient. Chondroitin sulfate is a widely used supplement to treat joint pain. In its unaltered state, it does not have the blood-thinning properties found in the contaminant. But scientists and researchers say the act of changing the molecule gives the substance anti-coagulating properties. Scientists who have examined batches of the contaminated heparin distributed by Baxter International in the United States said in interviews that they suspected that the heparin-like molecule was intentionally mixed into the drug. “A child could tell you it’s counterfeiting,” said Dr. Jawed Fareed, a professor of pathology and pharmacology at Loyola University Chicago, who has been studying batches of heparin since the problems with the drug were discovered. Dr. Fareed said he was conducting his own investigation because he was concerned that the quality problems with heparin were far more widespread than acknowledged. “Of seven or eight batches I have, six are contaminated,” said Dr. Fareed. “And these were used by doctors at Loyola University Medical Center.” One American chemist, who asked not to be identified because he had signed a confidentiality agreement, said he and the F.D.A. had looked at chondroitin sulfate, a substance derived from animal cartilage, as a possible contaminant because of its structural similarities with heparin. “It is something that is a little bit different,” said the chemist, “like a distant family relative you don’t recognize.” He added, “Once we have the exact fingerprint, we will try to figure out how it got into the product.” Zhang Tianmin, 80, a retired professor at the Shandong University School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, said counterfeiters would likely choose chondroitin sulfate, from animal cartilage, or chitosan, from shellfish, as a base substance to create a heparin-like molecule, because both substances are cheap. But since neither has natural blood-thinning activity, counterfeiters would have to add something that does. “Sulfate groups appear naturally in the heparin molecule,” Mr. Zhang said, “but they can also be produced by chemical synthesis.” On March 5, the Food and Drug Administration announced that its scientists had found a “heparin-like compound that is not heparin” in batches of the drug sold by Baxter. The molecule bore such a close resemblance to heparin that it had fooled standard quality tests and made it into the United States drug supply. Earlier this month, German health authorities notified the F.D.A. of 80 adverse reactions to heparin that had been sourced from China. The F.D.A. has said it has the world’s top heparin chemists working on the contaminant at two F.D.A. laboratories, three American universities and several European academic institutions. There are more than a dozen scientists working to identify the contaminant, or contaminants, an F.D.A. spokeswoman said. Chinese investigators are “working with the F.D.A. to do our best to find the root cause of these adverse reactions,” said a spokeswoman for China’s drug agency, Yan Jiangying. “China has not had reports of adverse reactions that resemble those in the United States.” Tang Haitao, president of Guanglong Biochemical Factory in eastern Shandong Province, said Chinese drug regulators made a surprise visit to his factory on Sunday, suggesting that a broader sweep is under way. Mr. Tang said he told regulators his company did not produce heparin anymore. Cui Huifei, a heparin expert at Shandong University School of Medicine, said, “It appears that a foreign substance has been added.” Baxter has recalled virtually all of its heparin products in the United States and since that recall there have been no new deaths, the F.D.A. said last week. As of last week, F.D.A. and Baxter said they had not visited any workshops that make crude heparin from pig intestines. Many of them are family owned and are largely unregulated. Dr. Fareed said it was too early to say whether the contaminant is causing the adverse reactions. A variety of reactions have been observed, including abdominal pain, hypotension, burning sensation, vomiting, diarrhea, rising temperature and anaphylaxis, he said, “but one cannot link all of these to one substance.” “This is a deliberate act of chemically manipulating a heparin-like substance and mixing it with heparin to increase the yield,” he added. But some batches of heparin containing the contaminant did not elicit adverse reactions, casting uncertainty on their root cause, Dr. Fareed said. Scientists interviewed by The New York Times had different views about whether such an over sulfated molecule could occur naturally. The F.D.A., Baxter International, and Scientific Protein Laboratories, the company whose Chinese plant produced the active ingredient in the tainted batches, are all conducting independent inquiries, according to a scientist participating in the investigation. External experts hired by each share their findings with the F.D.A., though they do not talk with one another because of non-disclosure agreements. More Articles in World »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/15/health/policy/15fda.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Tainted Blood Drug to Face Import Tests<date>Published: March 15, 2008</date><text>The Food and Drug Administration said Friday that all heparin products being imported into the United States would be stopped and tested for a possibly dangerous contaminant. The action comes after the agency’s inspectors in China found the contaminant in 20 of the 28 lots of the drug’s active ingredient inside a plant that supplied it to much of the American market. Skip to next paragraph Related Germans Seek China Tie to Blood Thinner Heparin (March 8, 2008) The still-unidentified contaminant, which the F.D.A. described as a heparin-like substance that mimics the real drug, was discovered last week in heparin manufactured in the United States by Baxter International. Heparin has been linked to 19 deaths and hundreds of severe allergic reactions in the United States. Germany has reported allergic reactions in 80 patients using heparin there, and investigators were testing all heparin made with Chinese ingredients to determine if it contained the same contaminant found in American supplies. Other countries have begun or are about to begin similar testing. “There is now a worldwide testing effort going on,” said Dr. Janet Woodcock, director of the F.D.A.’s Center for Drug Evaluation and Research. “We are going to have a lot of information and get a much better understanding of what the global heparin situation is like within a week or so.” Heparin, a blood thinner, is most commonly used in dialysis and cardiac surgery. F.D.A. officials said they could not yet prove that the contaminant had caused the allergic reactions, though it is the prime suspect. “We are very close to knowing exactly what these molecules are,” Dr. Woodcock said. “What we don’t know is how they are causing these adverse reactions.” Federal investigators also said they did not know yet whether the contaminant had been added intentionally as a cheap counterfeit substitute for real heparin. F.D.A. officials said Friday that they had not inspected the Chinese workshops where the raw heparin ingredient originated. The workshops used pig intestines to make raw heparin, a product that eventually ended up at the Chinese plant, Changzhou SPL, which supplied the active ingredient in heparin to Baxter. Some heparin experts had expressed concern over the safety of using pig intestines in medicine, particularly after “blue ear” pig disease swept through 25 of China’s 31 provinces and regions last year. Agency officials, who have praised the cooperation they are getting from China’s State Food and Drug Administration, declined to say why they had not tried to visit the workshops. The agency had earlier admitted that it violated its own policy by failing to inspect the Changzhou plant before allowing it, in 2004, to make and export heparin’s active ingredient to Baxter in the United States, where the finished product was made. When the F.D.A. did inspect the Changzhou plant last month, it found that at least some heparin was made from “material from an unacceptable workshop vendor.” Baxter has recalled virtually all of its heparin products in the United States. Erin Gardiner, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said the drug company had intended “to follow the supply chain as close as we could to the original source  the workshops.” But she added, “We have not been able to do so.” Ms. Gardiner said Baxter did not have the authority to demand access to the workshops. If such access is granted, she said, Baxter stands “ready to return to China as part of our investigation.” Richard L. Friedman, the F.D.A.’s director of manufacturing and product quality, said the agency generally inspected only manufacturers of active pharmaceutical ingredients and finished products, and did not go further back in the supply chain. In this case, that part of the chain, Mr. Friedman said, is the responsibility of China’s equivalent of the United States Department of Agriculture. The F.D.A. did inspect the two Chinese “consolidators” that collected crude heparin from the workshops, which then supplied it directly to Changzhou SPL. In a statement, a spokesman for Changzhou SPL said much of the active ingredient produced from Chinese material did not show any abnormalities. “It is important to note that similar clusters of adverse events have been observed not only in the U.S. but also in Germany from heparin not originating from Changzhou SPL,” the statement said. The Food and Drug Administration, in announcing that all heparin products entering the country had to first be tested, said it had secured a commitment from five manufacturers to test the products. The agency declined to name the five companies, nor would it say how many companies did not agree to test heparin imports. In such cases, it said, the drug agency would test the products itself. Dr. Woodcock said Friday that the F.D.A had received no new reports of deaths associated with heparin. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/08/world/europe/08heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Germans Seek China Tie to Blood Thinner Heparin<date>Published: March 8, 2008</date><text>FRANKFURT  The German authorities said Friday that they had asked all German producers of the blood thinner heparin to check whether their ingredients came from China, after allergic reactions to the drug there were linked to two Chinese suppliers. Skip to next paragraph Patrick Lux/Associated Press Rotexmedica, in Trittau, Germany, manufactures heparin. In cases where China did supply the raw ingredient, manufacturers were asked to test for any irregularities. The German authorities recalled the suspect heparin on Wednesday after receiving reports of allergic reactions in about 80 patients. Heparin manufactured with Chinese ingredients has been linked to 19 deaths in the United States. Federal drug regulators there said sophisticated tests had found what might be a counterfeit ingredient in the heparin associated with the deaths and serious allergic reactions in more than 700 patients. That unknown substance mimics real heparin and was found in concentrations of up to 20 percent in some of the suspect drug, according to the United States Food and Drug Administration. But the agency said it had not yet established whether the contaminant was responsible for the allergic reactions. The suspect heparin in the United States was made by Baxter International, with ingredients from a Chinese company called Changzhou SPL. The discovery that the ingredients for the German-made heparin came from two different Chinese plants has led investigators to suspect that the problem may lie farther back in the supply chain. The German authorities identified the two plants as Changzhou Quianhong Bio Pharma Company, and the Yantai Dongcheng Biochemicals Company. Both are among the top 10 Chinese exporters of heparin, according to a report last September by the China Chamber of Commerce for the Import and Export of Medicines and Health Products. Officials in the sales departments of both Chinese companies said Friday that they were unaware of the problems in Germany. The suspect heparin was manufactured by Rotexmedica, a subsidiary of the French company Groupe Panpharma. Rotexmedica, based in Trittau in northern Germany, said Friday that it would not comment on the recall because its executives were busy consulting with regulators. Rotexmedica has issued a worldwide recall for its heparin-containing products, which are mostly exported from Germany, said Ulrich Hagemann, an official in the pharmaceutical safety department of the Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices. The European Medicines Agency, which is based in Britain, has looked through databases in Europe and concluded that there had been no allergic reactions to heparin in any European countries except Germany. He said the reactions in Germany were far less severe than those in the United States, and had been traced to three specific batches of heparin produced by Rotexmedica. Those batches as well as other batches containing raw materials from the same sources were recalled March 5, and there have been no other patient reactions since. Heparin is an injectable blood thinner given to prevent and treat blood clots. It is also used in kidney dialysis and open heart surgery. Adverse reactions have included lowered blood pressure, shortness of breath and an elevated heart rate. The German authorities first got word of a possible problem on Feb. 14, Mr. Hagemann said, when three hospitals reported that three patients had “severe allergic reactions” to a heparin-containing product. Since allergic responses to these medicines are known to happen from time to time, this information alone was not enough to trigger a recall. But toward the end of last week a group that provides home kidney dialysis told regulators that 80 people had suffered reactions to the products. Subsequent analysis of the reports suggested that not every patient was having a reaction to heparin-linked products, Mr. Hagemann said, but the initial information was enough to start the recall. “At that point, we had to look at all heparin-containing products of Rotexmedica,” he said. A separate heparin-containing product produced by Rotexmedica, which is more finely processed, appears not to be affected, he added. Although the German firm has no link to Baxter, those German batches are now being analyzed to see if they have the same chemical impurity as the contaminated Baxter heparin in the United States, Mr. Hagemann said. The German federal agency is still waiting for reports from state health authorities on whether any companies in their jurisdictions purchased active ingredients from China. Much of the world’s heparin originates in China, where the raw material for the drug is gathered from pigs. In the first half of last year, China exported heparin to 42 countries and regions, according to Chinese officials. China exported the most heparin, about 13 tons, to Germany. Carter Dougherty reported from Frankfurt, and Elisabeth Rosenthal from Rome. Walt Bogdanich contributed reporting from New York, and Jake Hooker from Beijing. More Articles in World »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/07/health/policy/07heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">German Authorities Report Problems With Blood Thinner<date>Published: March 7, 2008</date><text>WASHINGTON  Concerns about the safety of the blood thinner heparin spread to Germany on Thursday after drug authorities there received reports of patients being sickened after taking the drug. Skip to next paragraph Related Drug Tied to China Had Contaminant, F.D.A. Says (March 6, 2008) 4 Executives Are Charged Over Tainted Toothpaste (March 7, 2008) Meanwhile, Food and Drug Administration officials announced that they were asking all companies in the United States that produce heparin to test it with two new procedures. The complex tests, nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy and capillary electrophoresis, are the only ones that can uncover whether the drug contains a possibly counterfeit ingredient. Dr. Janet Woodcock, deputy F.D.A. commissioner, said that the agency would post instructions online for the tests. Food and Drug officials said Wednesday that a possibly counterfeit ingredient had been found in certain batches of heparin linked to at least 19 deaths in the United States and more than 700 severe allergic reactions. Federal officials said they could not yet say that the contaminant, which mimics real heparin, caused the reactions. Until Thursday, federal investigators had been focusing on heparin manufactured by Baxter International. But Dr. Woodcock said that German health authorities told the F.D.A. that Baxter did not make the heparin linked to two separate outbreaks of allergic reactions in that country. Germany has reported fewer than 100 cases of patients suffering severe allergic reactions and shock, and no deaths. F.D.A. officials declined to say whether the raw ingredients for the suspect German heparin came from China, the source of the starting materials used to make the contaminated heparin in the United States. Most of the world’s heparin supply is from China. In the last six months, more than 30 Chinese companies could be found selling heparin products on major business-to-business Web sites. “We are working as quickly as possible to analyze any potential impact on the U.S. market and worldwide,” said Deborah Autor, the director of compliance for the agency’s Center for Drug Evaluation and Research. In the first half of last year, China exported heparin products to 42 countries and regions, according to a September 2007 report by the China Chamber of Commerce for Import and Export of Medicines and Health Products. China exported the most heparin products, about 13 tons, to Germany. It also sent 11 tons to France and about 10 tons to the United States, the report said. Erin Gardiner, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said reports that her company was not responsible for making the suspect heparin in Germany would most likely point to a problem with the suppliers of crude heparin. “The news today indicates that the issue could be further back in the supply chain,” Ms. Gardiner said. Last week, Baxter withdrew from the market nearly all of its heparin products. Baxter bought the active pharmaceutical ingredient for its heparin products from Scientific Protein Laboratories, based in Waunakee, Wis., which has plants in Wisconsin and Changzhou, China. All of the suspect heparin was made from raw heparin produced in China. In some cases, those supplies were produced in small, unregulated family workshops, according to heparin traders and producers in China. On Wednesday, Scientific Protein Laboratories announced a recall of some of its product, the active ingredient in heparin. Most supplies of heparin in the United States are now from APP Pharmaceuticals, of Schaumburg, Ill. APP’s supplies have undergone the new tests. German authorities have identified Rotexmedica as a manufacturer of at least some of the suspect heparin there, F.D.A. officials said. German drug authorities could not be reached. F.D.A. officials said they were told that the German authorities had recalled an unspecified amount of heparin. In a statement released Thursday, Scientific Protein Laboratories said, “We believe this demonstrates that the heparin problem is not within Changzhou SPL’s or Baxter’s manufacturing facilities but our investigation into the root cause of the problem will continue.” Representative John D. Dingell, the Michigan Democrat who is the chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, charged in a statement released Thursday that the F.D.A. “is drowning in drug imports that it is not able to properly regulate.” In Europe, such foreign inspections may be even rarer. A 2006 report by a European chemical association said that even when European inspectors found serious safety issues, European regulators did not suspend the producers from supplying the European market because of a lack of government coordination. Andrew W. Lehren and Jake Hooker contributed reporting. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/06/health/06heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Drug Tied to China Had Contaminant, F.D.A. Says<date>Published: March 6, 2008</date><text>WASHINGTON  Federal drug regulators said Wednesday that a critical blood thinner that had been linked to at least 19 deaths and whose raw components were produced in China contained a possibly counterfeit ingredient that mimicked the real drug. Skip to next paragraph Related Twists in Chain of Supplies for Blood Drug (February 28, 2008) Routine tests failed to distinguish the contaminant from the drug, heparin. Only sophisticated magnetic resonance imaging tests uncovered that as much as 20 percent of the product’s active ingredient was a heparin mimic blended in with the real thing. Federal officials said they did not know what the contaminant was. “At this point, we do not know whether the introduction was accidental or whether it was deliberate,” said the Food and Drug Administration’s deputy commissioner, Dr. Janet Woodcock. Heparin is made from pig intestines. Scientific Protein Laboratories, based in Waunakee, Wis., bought raw heparin produced in some cases in small, unregulated family workshops in China and processed it in plants in Wisconsin and China, according to heparin traders and producers in China. Baxter International purchased the active ingredient from Scientific Protein and sold the finished drug. Wayne Pines, a spokesman for Scientific Protein Laboratories, said that nothing sinister about the contamination had been proved. “There is no evidence of counterfeiting or tampering or anything of that nature,” Mr. Pines said. “No one really knows what happened here.” Beginning in November, public health officials received reports of patients experiencing severe allergic reactions after being given Baxter’s product. Baxter initiated a series of recalls that culminated last week in a withdrawal of nearly all of Baxter’s heparin production. The F.D.A. has now received 785 reports of serious injuries associated with the drug’s use. Forty-six deaths have also been reported to the agency, but Dr. Woodcock said that just 19 of these appeared related to the suspect heparin. Baxter executives said that the total death toll was actually four. APP Pharmaceuticals, which previously split the heparin market with Baxter, has been ramping up production to meet demand. So far, APP’s products show no signs of similar contamination, Dr. Woodcock said, although some of APP’s production is also based in China. Most of the world’s heparin supply originates in China, according to Baxter. The F.D.A. will soon make public the test used to distinguish between real heparin and its mimic in hopes that regulatory bodies around the world will adopt the test. “We don’t know if any of the heparin products worldwide might contain this contaminant, and that is something we are going to be looking into,” Dr. Woodcock said. The F.D.A. has yet to prove that the heparin contaminant is the cause of the deaths and illnesses now associated with the use of Baxter’s product. But heparin batches associated with illnesses, all of which were produced with ingredients made in China, were found to contain the contaminant while batches not linked to illnesses proved to be untainted. In a written statement, Scientific Protein said that “it is premature to conclude that the heparin active pharmaceutical ingredient sourced from China and provided by S.P.L. to Baxter is responsible for these adverse events.” Since tainted batches were produced by Scientific Protein’s plants in both Wisconsin and China, “either both plants have problems with processing or there’s something wrong further up the stream,” said Peter Arduini, president of Baxter’s medication delivery business. The F.D.A. admitted last month that it had violated its own policies by failing to inspect Scientific Protein’s China plant before approving the drug for sale. The agency sent inspectors to the plant last month who found that at least some heparin was made from “material from an unacceptable workshop vendor.” Baxter undertook its own inspection of the China plant last fall. “A few of our observations touched on the same areas as F.D.A.’s inspectional findings,” said Ray Godlewski, vice president for quality at Baxter’s medication delivery business. Mr. Godlewski refused to be more specific because, he said, of a confidentiality agreement with Scientific Protein. Mr. Pines of Scientific Protein said he did not know what problems Baxter uncovered last fall or why those problems were not corrected by the time federal inspectors arrived last month. 1 2 Next Page » Gardiner Harris reported from Washington, and Walt Bogdanich from New York. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/29/us/29heparin.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Blood Thinner Might Be Tied to More Deaths<date>Published: February 29, 2008</date><text>Amid indications that more people may have died or been harmed after being given a brand of the blood thinner heparin, federal drug regulators said Thursday that they had found “potential deficiencies” at a Chinese plant that supplied much of the active ingredient for the drug. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Du Bin for The New York Times The Changzhou SPL plant, which is west of Shanghai, supplied much of the active ingredient for the blood thinner heparin. Related Twists in Chain of Supplies for Blood Drug (February 28, 2008) Baxter International, which makes the brand of heparin associated with the problems, and buys supplies from the Chinese plant, announced that it was expanding a recall to include virtually all its heparin products. Though Baxter produces much of the heparin used in the United States, regulators said the other major supplier would be able to meet the demand. The Food and Drug Administration said the number of deaths possibly associated with the drug, made from pig intestines, had risen to 21 from 4. But it cautioned that many of those patients were already seriously ill and that the drug might not have caused their deaths. The F.D.A. emphasized that it had yet to identify the root cause of the problem, and that it had not concluded that the Chinese plant was responsible. The agency also said it was investigating two Chinese wholesalers  also called consolidators  that supplied crude heparin to the Chinese plant, Changzhou SPL, as well as those that sold raw ingredients to the consolidators. The New York Times reported Thursday that at least one of the consolidators received supplies from small, unregulated family workshops that scraped mucous membrane from pig intestines and cooked it, eventually producing a dry substance known as crude heparin. The F.D.A. admitted this month that it had violated its own policy by failing to inspect SPL, located west of Shanghai, before the factory began shipping the heparin ingredient to Baxter in 2004. China’s drug agency also did not inspect the plant. Last week, the F.D.A. sent inspectors to the plant. Among the potential problems they found was a failure to properly follow the steps for identifying impurities and deficiencies related to manufacturing equipment. According to a redacted inspection report released by the agency, the SPL plant appeared to have made at least some heparin with “material from an unacceptable workshop vendor.” The vendor was not identified. Scientific Protein Laboratories, a Wisconsin company that is the majority owner of the Chinese plant, issued a statement Thursday saying the F.D.A.’s finding did not represent its final determination as to whether the plant complied with federal regulatory rules. S.P.L., the statement said, is committed to finding the root cause of the adverse reactions. Erin Gardiner, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said the company was reviewing the F.D.A.’s report. “We expect S.P.L. to respond to those observations thoroughly and promptly,” Ms. Gardiner said. “The observations are important and need to be addressed promptly but they are not necessarily indicative of the root cause.” The F.D.A.’s concern about heparin had previously centered on Baxter’s multidose vials, but on Thursday Baxter agreed to voluntarily recall not only the multi-dose vials but also single-dose vials and a diluted solution of heparin used to keep blood clots from forming in intravenous lines. There have been no adverse reaction reports involving the latter product, called Hep-Lock heparin flush products. “We have assurance from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration that there is an adequate supply in the market to meet the demand for these critical and lifesaving drugs,” Peter J. Arduini, president of Baxter’s Medication Delivery business, said in a statement released by the company. The only heparin products made by Baxter that are still on the market are premixed bags of intravenous solutions, the Food and Drug Administration said. “We at the F.D.A. understand how unsettling this whole situation with heparin is,” said Dr. Sandra Kweder, the agency’s deputy director, Office of New Drugs, Center for Drug Evaluation and Research. “We are determined to get to the root cause.” The F.D.A. estimates that more than one million multidose vials of heparin are sold per month in the United States, about half of which are manufactured and distributed by Baxter. The problems with heparin, which is used to prevent blood clotting during dialysis and after some surgery, were first reported last month at a hospital in Missouri. Since then, the number of reported adverse reactions has risen to 448, the F.D.A. said. “Yes, we have gotten more and we are continuing to evaluate those reports,” Dr. Kweder said. At first, the agency said it believed that four people had died after allergic reactions to the drug. On Thursday, officials said as many as 17 more people may have died, but they described the links to heparin as more tenuous. The adverse reactions have included decreased or low blood pressure and fast heart rate. Not all of them are known to involve Baxter products, but the drug agency did not issue warnings involving any other products. The Chinese heparin market has been in turmoil over the last year, as pig disease has swept through the country, depleting stocks, leading some farmers to sell sick pigs into the market and forcing heparin producers to scramble for new sources of raw material. As a result, even big companies have been turning increasingly to small village workshops, which are often unsanitary. In interviews this week at some of these workshops, employees told The Times that they had not been inspected by the government. Scientific Protein Laboratories said it responded to the disease outbreak by buying less raw material in China. Its president, David Strunce, said in an interview this week that the Chinese plant bought supplies only from two reputable consolidators, and that its suppliers were audited. The F.D.A has already finished inspecting one of the consolidators and is still looking at the second one, an agency spokeswoman said. The agency also plans, if necessary, to look at some of the small workshops that supply the consolidators. “We will go where the investigation takes us,” an agency official said. More Articles in US »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/28/world/asia/28drug.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Twists in Chain of Supplies for Blood Drug<date>Published: February 28, 2008</date><text>RUGAO, China  With reports of more than 400 patients in the United States suffering serious complications after receiving the blood-thinner heparin, American investigators are trying to determine whether the raw material for the drug, made from pig intestines, became contaminated on the journey that begins in the slaughterhouses of China. Skip to next paragraph Related China Didnt Check Drug Supplier, Files Show (February 16, 2008) Enlarge This Image Du Bin for The New York Times Changzhou SPL, a factory in Jiangsu Province, refines heparin. The investigators are examining the records of a factory an hour from here that supplies much of the active ingredient in heparin for Baxter International, which earlier this month halted sales of multidose vials of heparin after reports of injuries and four deaths. The owner of the factory, which is known as Changzhou SPL, says its supply chain is safe. It buys raw material from only two reputable wholesalers, it says, and audits their 10 to 12 suppliers. “We have a collection chain in place, and we stick with that,” said David Strunce, the president of Scientific Protein Laboratories, an American company that owns a majority of Changzhou SPL. He declined repeated requests from The New York Times to identify those smaller suppliers, saying it was proprietary information. But interviews with dozens of heparin producers and traders in several Chinese provinces, as well as a visit to a village near here dominated by tiny family workshops that process crude heparin from pig intestines, show the difficulties confronting investigators as they seek to trace the supply chain. The picture that emerges is of a chain more complex, and less orderly, than the one Mr. Strunce laid out. The Chinese heparin market has become increasingly unsettled over the last year, as pig disease has swept through the country, depleting stocks, leading some farmers to sell sick pigs into the market and forcing heparin producers to scramble for new sources of raw material. Traders and industry experts say even big companies have been turning more often to the small village workshops, which are unregulated and often unsanitary. One of the wholesalers named by Scientific Protein Laboratories, Ruihua Biochemical in Hangzhou, said it provided a mix of crude heparin that it manufactured and some that it bought “from small factories nearby in several villages.” The owner, Hua Ruihua, said he never inspected the small factories. “We are not the government,” he said in a telephone interview. “We have no right to inspect their pigs or intestines or facilities.” The owner of one of those workshops, Fan Yinan, said, “I sold to Ruihua several times before, but since last September I have had no intestines.” He confirmed that “no one from Ruihua inspected my pigs or intestines.” Asked about Ruihua Biochemical, the S.P.L. chief, Mr. Strunce, said, “We have no information to suggest that your information is true.” This week, a spokeswoman for Baxter said the number of reports of adverse reactions to heparin had surpassed 400. A spokeswoman for the Food and Drug Administration in the United States said the agency was reviewing the new reports and did not yet have a revised count. The authorities have not determined that problems with the heparin supply chain led to the deaths and adverse reactions, first reported last month in Missouri. Nor have investigators determined that heparin from China was the culprit. Baxter also gets some of its ingredients from a plant in Wisconsin. Neither S.P.L. nor Baxter has been accused of doing anything wrong. Even so, the problems involving heparin have again focused attention on the quality of products from China and the gaps in regulation by both the Chinese and United States governments. S.P.L.’s plant in Changzhou was certified by American officials to export to the United States even though neither government had inspected it. The plant has been exporting heparin to Baxter since 2004. Like many chemical companies in China that make pharmaceutical ingredients for export, S.P.L. fell into a regulatory void. A spokesman for China’s State Food and Drug Administration, Shen Chen, said his agency had not inspected the S.P.L. factory because “as far as we know, it is not a drug manufacturer; it is a producer of chemical ingredients.” Mr. Shen said his agency was helping American investigators as part of a recent agreement with American regulators. 1 2 Next Page » David Barboza reported from Shanghai and Rugao, and Walt Bogdanich from New York. Jake Hooker contributed reporting from Beijing, and Chen Yang contributed research from Shanghai. More Articles in World »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D7143AF933A15751C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=baxterinternationalinc">Correction: For the Record<date>Published: February 20, 2008</date><text>An article on Friday about the Food and Drug Administration breaking its own rules by not inspecting a plant in China that made the active ingredient of a blood-thinning drug misspelled part of the name of the company that founded American Capital Strategies Ltd., the majority owner of Scientific Protein Laboratories, which owns the plant. It is Oscar Mayer, not Meyer.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/16/us/16baxter.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">China Didn’t Check Drug Supplier, Files Show<date>Published: February 16, 2008</date><text>A Chinese factory that supplies much of the active ingredient for a brand of a blood thinner that has been linked to four deaths in the United States is not certified by China’s drug regulators to make pharmaceutical products, according to records and interviews. Skip to next paragraph Related Panama Releases Report on 06 Poisoning (February 14, 2008) Because the plant, Changzhou SPL, has no drug certification, China’s drug agency did not inspect it. The United States Food and Drug Administration said this week that it had not inspected the plant either  a violation of its own policy  before allowing the company to become a major supplier of the blood thinner, heparin, to Baxter International in the United States. Baxter announced Monday that it was suspending sales of its multidose vials of heparin after 4 patients died and 350 suffered complications. Why the heparin caused these problems  and whether the active ingredient in the drug, derived from pig intestines, was responsible  has not been determined. The plant in Changzhou, west of Shanghai, appears to fall into the type of regulatory void that American and Chinese health officials are trying to close  in which chemical companies export pharmaceutical ingredients without a Chinese drug license. China provides a growing proportion of the active pharmaceutical ingredients used in drugs sold in the United States. And Chinese drug regulators have said that all producers of those ingredients are required to obtain certification by the State Food and Drug Administration. However, some of the active ingredients that China exports are made by chemical companies, which do not fall under the Chinese drug agency’s jurisdiction. In December, American and Chinese regulators signed an agreement under which China promised to begin registering at least some of the thousands of chemical companies that sell drug ingredients. Some of these companies are the source of counterfeit or diluted drugs, including those used to treat malaria. Discussions that led to the accord began after an unlicensed chemical plant in China made a tainted drug ingredient that poisoned more than 170 people in Panama, killing at least 115. The heparin plant in China has not been accused of providing a harmful product. The American majority owner of that plant, Scientific Protein Laboratories, also owns a plant in Wisconsin that produces the active ingredient in heparin for Baxter. In response to questions, Scientific Protein issued a statement confirming that its Chinese plant had no license from the Chinese agency, but said that its raw ingredients come from a licensed supplier. The statement added that an “independent private U.S. validation company” had found the plant to be in compliance with good manufacturing practices. And a spokeswoman for Baxter, which buys heparin’s active ingredient from Scientific Protein, said it had inspected the China plant less than six months ago. A spokesman for China’s State Food and Drug Administration, Shen Chen, said Friday that “as far as we know, it is not a drug manufacturer  it is a producer of chemical ingredients.” Eric S. Langer, managing partner of BioPlan Associates, which prepares and publishes reports on the biopharmaceutical and biotechnology industry, said he found it hard to believe that a company exporting the heparin ingredient would not be licensed by Chinese drug regulators. “Being able to produce a pharmaceutical or a biologic in the U.S. or anywhere without having regulatory oversight really doesn’t happen,” Mr. Langer said, adding, “I find it surprising from a regulatory perspective, and I find it surprising from a business perspective.” Karen Riley, a spokeswoman for the United States Food and Drug Administration, said inspectors from that agency would be visiting the Changzhou plant soon. Ms. Riley said she could not be more specific. Earlier in the week she described her agency’s failure to inspect the plant as a “glitch.” Congress has criticized the oversight by the Food and Drug Administration of bulk pharmaceutical ingredients made by foreign manufacturers and sold in the United States. A growing number of those ingredients now come from China. Of the 700 approved Chinese drug plants, the United States agency has inspected only 10 to 20 each year. Baxter makes roughly half of the United States supply of heparin, which is used widely for surgical and dialysis patients. Problems with Baxter’s heparin were first noticed late last year when four children undergoing dialysis in Missouri had severe allergic reactions minutes after being injected with the drug. The F.D.A. then allowed Baxter to deliver heparin that it was in the midst of shipping, for fear that a total recall would lead to a shortage of the drug, but cautioned doctors to use as little of it as possible and to administer it very slowly. The agency also suggested that doctors give steroids or antihistamines with the Baxter heparin to help prevent allergic reactions. Erin Gardiner, a spokeswoman for Baxter, defended Scientific Protein, saying it had been making the heparin ingredient for more than 30 years. “They have been a good supplier,” she said. Although the cause of the adverse reactions has yet to be determined, she said tests performed by her company had detected unspecified differences between some lots of the ingredient. She did not say whether the lots had come from China or from the Wisconsin plant, which Scientific Protein also owns. Those differences had not turned up in routine testing that the company does on active ingredients, Ms. Gardiner said, but she said Baxter had used “advanced testing techniques” to find the differences. She added that it was unclear whether the finding was significant. Two Congressional committees have asked the Food and Drug Administration for more information about inspections of plants making the active ingredient of heparin. Andrew W. Lehren contributed reporting. More Articles in US »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/15/washington/15fda.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">F.D.A. Broke Its Rules by Not Inspecting Chinese Plant With Problem Drug<date>Correction: February 20, 2008Published: February 15, 2008</date><text>Correction Appended WASHINGTON, Feb. 14  The Food and Drug Administration violated its own policies when it approved for sale a crucial blood-thinning drug without first inspecting a Chinese plant which, along with a plant in Wisconsin, made the drug’s active pharmaceutical ingredient. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Food and Drug Administration “It was obviously a glitch” that the drug, heparin, produced and sold by Baxter International, was approved for sale without a plant inspection, said Karen Riley, an F.D.A. spokeswoman. The agency does not know who was at fault, and it is still “preparing to send inspectors over there,” Ms. Riley said. Peter Barton Hutt, a former top lawyer for the agency, said that since 1980 it has had a policy requiring that plants be inspected before drugs are approved for sale. Representative Bart Stupak, Democrat of Michigan and chairman of a House investigative subcommittee, said that no matter what happened with the heparin inquiry, the F.D.A.’s inability to provide basic information about the Chinese manufacturing plant weeks after concerns were first raised was deeply troubling. “They can’t tell us if they’ve inspected this plant, what other problems might have been identified at this plant, or what other U.S. firms might be getting supplies from this plant,” he said. Mr. Stupak’s committee and Senator Charles E. Grassley, Republican of Iowa, both sent letters to the agency on Thursday, asking for more information about inspections of plants making heparin. Baxter International announced on Monday that it was suspending sales of its multidose vials of heparin after four patients died and 350 suffered complications, many of them serious. Baxter bought the active ingredient for this product from Scientific Protein Laboratories, which has plants in Waunakee, Wis., and Changzhou City, China. In a news release Thursday, Scientific Protein said that its Chinese plant followed the same testing and quality control procedures as those used in domestic heparin plants. Erin Gardiner, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said the company conducted an inspection of Scientific Protein’s China plant less than six months ago and inspected its Wisconsin plant within the past year. She said Scientific Protein “is a company we have a long track record with and they have been a good supplier.” Ms. Gardiner said that recent tests by Baxter had found subtle chemical differences among the lots that Scientific Protein shipped to Baxter “but it is unclear what impact the differences would have” on Baxter’s heparin product. Dr. Ajay Singh, director of dialysis at the Brigham and Women’s Hospital in Boston, said he was astonished by what he called the many failures to ensure a safe supply of heparin. There are 450,000 people in the United States on dialysis, and nearly all of them need copious doses of heparin, he said. Heparin is also used in cardiac surgery and among chronic care patients. “We need to ensure that this country has access to the crucial medicines it needs,” Dr. Singh said. “This is a national security issue.” The heparin scare comes at a particularly delicate time for the F.D.A. Over the past year, a wave of tainted goods from China, including deadly pet food ingredients and tainted fish, has prompted concern about whether regulators are adequately monitoring imports’ safety. The Government Accountability Office released three reports in recent months that found that the drug agency provided little oversight of the increasing number of foreign plants that export food, drugs and devices to the United States. Although the agency must inspect domestic drug plants once every two years, the investigators found that it inspected foreign drug plants at best once every 13 years. The agency’s record in China, now one of the biggest drug suppliers in the world, is even worse. Of the 700 approved Chinese drug plants, the agency has been able to inspect only 10 to 20 each year and would need 40 to 50 years to inspect them all. “This heparin situation shows that F.D.A. has no people to prevent contaminated products from coming into this country,” Mr. Hutt said. American Capital Strategies Ltd., a publicly traded investment company, is the majority owner of Scientific Protein. American Capital is the latest in a series of owners. It was founded by the meat-processing giant Oscar Mayer Foods in 1976 to make products from animal byproducts, including heparin, derived from animal organs. Andrew W. Lehren contributed reporting. This article has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: February 20, 2008 An article on Friday about the Food and Drug Administration breaking its own rules by not inspecting a plant in China that made the active ingredient of a blood-thinning drug misspelled part of the name of the company that founded American Capital Strategies Ltd., the majority owner of Scientific Protein Laboratories, which owns the plant. It is Oscar Mayer, not Meyer. More Articles in Washington »</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/12/health/12drug.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Problems in Blood Drug Lead to Halt by Factory<date>Published: February 12, 2008</date><text>A major maker of heparin, a blood thinner used widely in surgery and dialysis, has stopped making it after hundreds of patients reported severe allergic reactions to the drug, which is made from pig intestines. At least four people died. Shortages of the drug are all but certain, federal regulators said. Although alternatives exist, doctors warned of serious consequences if heparin became truly scarce. “Inadequate heparin would cause a health care crisis in this country,” said Dr. Daniel Coyne, a professor of medicine at Washington University in St. Louis. Public health officials first noticed a problem late last year in four children undergoing dialysis at a hospital in Missouri. Within minutes of being injected with heparin, the children experienced serious allergic reactions. As officials investigated, they found a total of 350 reports of patients’ experiencing problems after being injected with large doses of heparin made by Baxter Healthcare. Baxter supplies about half the nation’s heparin. Most of the cases were reported in late December or January; 40 percent were deemed serious. The reactions included difficulty breathing, nausea, vomiting, excessive sweating and rapidly falling blood pressure that in some cases led to life-threatening shock. A spokeswoman for Baxter, Erin M. Gardiner, said the company had not changed its heparin manufacturing for several years. The company initially recalled nine lots of the drug, but problems continued. Baxter suspended manufacturing multidose vials that have been associated with most of the problems. Baxter continues to make single-dose vials. Dr. John Jenkins, director of the Food and Drug Administration’s office of new drugs, said the agency decided to allow the company to continue distributing the multidose vials that it had made because a full recall “would result in an immediate and severe shortage of this medically necessary drug.” APP Pharmaceuticals in Schaumburg, Ill., manufactures much of the rest of the heparin supply. Its president, Tom Silberg, said APP was rapidly increasing production. “Can we ramp up to meet all of the demands?” Mr. Silberg said. “That’s yet to be said.” Dr. Jenkins said doctors who had to continue to use Baxter heparin should use the lowest possible dose, infuse it slowly, monitor patients closely and consider administering steroids or antihistamines before heparin. “There is going to be a shortage problem in the immediate and long-term future with the suspension of Baxter’s manufacturing,” Dr. Jenkins said. “Facilities and physicians will have to decide immediately what they do with the heparin on hand, and they’ll have to start looking for heparin for the long term.” Doctors said they would face difficult choices if heparin supplies ran low. “It’s an essential part of dialysis treatment,” said Dr. Jay Wish, professor of medicine at Case Western Reserve. Heparin is used in dialysis to prevent clotting while blood circulates in a dialysis machine. Without heparin, many more patients would be likely to experience significant blood loss during dialysis, Dr. Wish said, worsening their chronic anemia. Heparin is also used to prevent clotting in catheters, which 25 percent of dialysis patients have to use for treatment. The drug is commonly used in heart-bypass surgery and for the bedridden. Other drugs thin blood, but their effects are rarely as rapid or as easily reversed. Heparin has been manufactured since 1930. “Trying to operate without heparin would be a scary proposition for the dialysis industry,” Dr. Wish said. Dr. Christina Beckwith, a drug information specialist at University of Utah Hospital, said newer versions of heparin, all far more expensive, could be used. “It’s not going to be an easy thing, but there’s still going to be options to treat these patients,” Dr. Beckwith said. Heparin is made from pig intestines that must pass through multiple purification steps to extract microbes and problem proteins, Dr. Jenkins said. The drug agency is inspecting whether something amiss occurred in the purification process. Even a factor as mundane as the rubber stoppers on the vials has to be considered a possible source of the problem, Dr. Jenkins said. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/04/world/middleeast/04aids.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Iraqis Infected by H.I.V.-Tainted Blood Try New Tool: A Lawsuit<date>Published: September 4, 2006</date><text>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Sept. 3  One day in 1986, a car from Saddam Husseins Health Ministry pulled up in front of young Hussein Fadhil Abbass farmhouse in Hib Hib, about 40 miles northeast of the capital. Mr. Abbas, 17 at the time and suffering from hemophilia, a hereditary bleeding disorder, answered the door. Skip to next paragraph Max Becherer/Polaris, for The New York Times Dr. Hanan Mehdi Abdul Karim said her brother, who contracted H.I.V., was removed from his school by government agents in 1984. Hostilities in the Mideast Go to Complete Coverage » They need you in Baghdad, the government man told him, although Mr. Abbas had just been to the city a week earlier for his monthly injection of clotting agents to reduce bleeding in his gums, nose and knees. Mr. Abbas, a thin man with watery eyes and an uncertain gait, said he spent the next six months imprisoned in a run-down sanitarium normally used for tuberculosis patients, where bars covered the windows and guards watched the exits. More hemophiliacs arrived each day, equally perplexed. Eventually, Mr. Abbas said, a Health Ministry doctor arrived with an explanation. The clotting agents they received, he said, had infected them with H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS. Officials here say that at least 115 Iraqis contracted the virus from clotting agents imported from France and Austria. I had never heard of this disease before, Mr. Abbas, now 37, recalled in an interview here. This doctor then threatened us. He said, Dont make any trouble, or youll never see your families again.  The hemophiliacs stormed the sanitariums front gate and easily escaped, because guards feared touching them. We decided that if we get killed, so be it, Mr. Abbas said. Their persecution, though, was just beginning. Twenty years later, Mr. Abbas is part of a rapidly shrinking group of H.I.V.-infected survivors seeking justice in the new Iraq, using a novel legal tool here: the civil lawsuit. In one of the first cases of its kind since the American invasion in 2003, the 35 or so infected hemophiliacs still alive, the families of the others, who have died, and the Iraqi Red Crescent Society have sued the Health Ministry and the two corporations that acquired or succeeded the companies that the plaintiffs say sold tainted blood products to Iraq  Institut Mérieux of France and Immuno AG of Austria. The suit accuses the two companies of selling products that they suspected were contaminated, and accuses the ministry of negligence in giving them to patients here. Institut Mérieux eventually became part of what is now Sanofi-Aventis, based in Paris; Immuno AG was acquired by Baxter International, of Deerfield, Ill., in 1996. A hearing in the case, which was filed in August 2005, is scheduled for Tuesday. Representatives of the two corporations declined to answer specific questions about the alleged sale of tainted blood products in Iraq and other countries in the 1980s. A Sanofi-Aventis spokesman said the company would not discuss the matter because it was under litigation. Deborah Spak, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said it had not discussed a settlement with any Iraqis, but added that those who have evidence of infection from Immuno blood products should contact Baxter AG, a German subsidiary that is responsible for those claims. In 1996, Baxter and three other companies, including a French company that acquired Institut Mérieux, agreed to pay $660 million to more than 6,000 hemophiliacs in the United States to settle claims that they contracted H.I.V. from tainted blood products. Dr. Said I. Hakki, the director of the Iraqi Red Crescent Society, said that 189 hemophiliacs, from 6 months to 18 years old, contracted H.I.V. from blood products that Mérieux and Immuno sold to Iraq from 1982 to 1986. The virus, undetected, later spread to at least another 50 Iraqis, he said, through sexual intercourse, childbirth or breast-feeding. Dr. Hakki said the companies have ignored efforts by the societys lawyers and the French ambassador here, Bernard Bajolet, to arrange a settlement or to provide antiretroviral medicines to the surviving hemophiliacs. Those people who suffered, and suffered immensely for no good reason, should be compensated, Dr. Hakki, a urologist and a naturalized American citizen, said in an interview in the societys offices in downtown Baghdad. These companies have a selfish disdain for these people. They decided theyre not going to do anything. 1 2Next Page » Khalid W. Hassan and Sahar Nageeb contributed reporting for this article. More Articles in International »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/22/national/22fda.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">F.D.A. Orders Recall of Intravenous Pumps<date>Published: July 22, 2005</date><text>WASHINGTON, July 21 - The Food and Drug Administration on Thursday announced the recall of 206,000 pumps that deliver medicines intravenously to patients. The announcement was made after three people died and six became seriously ill when the infusion pumps unexpectedly shut down. The machines, made by Baxter International and known as Colleague volumetric infusion pumps, shut down for a variety of software, wiring and design reasons. One of the most basic problems is that the "On/Off" key is so close to the "Start" key that nurses may inadvertently turn the machines off when they actually intend to begin drug therapy, the agency said. "We've received hundreds of complaints from hospitals about these pumps," said Timothy Ulatowski, director of the office of compliance in the F.D.A.'s device center. "That's extraordinary." Because some hospitals depend entirely on the pumps, the agency is not ordering that they all be sidelined. Instead, the agency is asking hospitals and other users to employ other machines in critical care cases if possible, and to monitor the machines closely, Mr. Ulatowski said. If the machines shut down in particular ways, they must be taken out of service, he said. The agency termed the recall Class 1, its most serious classification and one that involves "a reasonable probability that using the affected product will cause serious injury or death." About two dozen such recalls occur each year, Mr. Ulatowski said. The Baxter recall was unique, however, because the F.D.A. issued a press release and set up interviews with the news media to explain its actions. "We've never issued a press release in the past on something like this," Mr. Ulatowski said. "In the past, the companies were given the opportunity to be the one to issue press releases, and they always did." Lester M. Crawford, the new F.D.A. commissioner who was confirmed Monday by the Senate, has promised that the agency will become more transparent and begin speaking more directly to patients and doctors about the known and suspected risks of medicines and devices, often by using the news media, instead of allowing companies to speak for the agency. The greater public attention may also encourage other companies to be more careful in their operations for fear of negative publicity. "We want other companies to perk up and take note," Mr. Ulatowski said. Deborah Spak, a Baxter International spokeswoman, said that the company sent a letter in March to its customers warning of problems with the infusion pumps. Mr. Ulatowski said that the delay since March resulted because the agency had to inspect Baxter's plant and conduct its own tests to determine the seriousness of the problems. The agency also decided to order a recall to force Baxter to account for each suspect machine and report its findings to the agency. Such a recall also initiates a broad review of Baxter's manufacturing operations, Mr. Ulatowski said. "Whenever you have a recall, that puts into motion a lot of activities at F.D.A.," Mr. Ulatowski said. "We look at trying to identify this problem and fixing the root cause of the problem, and taking a look at how the company operates, their manufacturing and their decision process when they get complaints." Ms. Spak said that Baxter was changing the design of its pump. The company has stopped shipping new pumps, she said. Baxter is a specialty pharmaceutical and device company based in Deerfield, Ill. More Articles in National &gt;</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF1638F932A25752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER EXPECTS $245 MILLION CHARGE FOR QUARTER<date>Published: January 11, 2005</date><text>The health products maker Baxter International said yesterday that it expected charges of $245 million in the fourth quarter, mostly for the suspension of a trial of an experimental flu vaccine. Baxter suspended a late-stage European trial of the vaccine last month because of a higher-than-expected rate of mild fever and associated symptoms. Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., said it would record a noncash, after-tax charge of about $170 million for the write-down of certain assets related to its flu vaccine program. It also said it would record a charge of about $45 million for the write-down of assets related to the development of a drug, Epomax, for the treatment of anemia. It will record a charge of about $30 million for excess manufacturing capacity related to the Epomax program.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/business/company-news-chief-quits-and-successor-is-named-at-neopharm.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; CHIEF QUITS AND SUCCESSOR IS NAMED AT NEOPHARM<date>Published: June 18, 2004</date><text>NeoPharm's chief executive, James M. Hussey, resigned and will be succeeded by Gregory P. Young, who was an executive at Baxter International. Mr. Young will take over as chief executive July 13 and became a director effective yesterday, NeoPharm said. Mr. Hussey is leaving to pursue other opportunities, NeoPharm said. Neopharm's most advanced experimental product is a treatment for a form of brain cancer. An arbitration panel dismissed claims last month in a dispute between NeoPharm and Pfizer's Pharmacia unit stemming from delays in developing two cancer drugs. The joint venture ended in 2002. Neopharm is based in Lake Forest, Ill.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/28/business/company-news-literature-for-blood-clotting-drug-is-withdrawn.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; LITERATURE FOR BLOOD-CLOTTING DRUG IS WITHDRAWN<date>Published: May 28, 2004</date><text>Baxter International Inc. has stopped using some promotional literature for its new blood-clotting hemophilia drug, Advate, after receiving a warning from the Food and Drug Administration, the company said yesterday. The F.D.A. was concerned that it had not provided appropriate descriptions of side effects or sufficient supporting data for its statements, according to the Baxter Healthcare Corporation, the medical products company's main operating subsidiary in the United States. Advate was introduced in the United States last August.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/23/business/company-news-baxter-international-s-revenue-declines-13.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL'S REVENUE DECLINES 13%<date>Published: April 23, 2004</date><text>The health care products maker Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that its earnings fell 13 percent in the first quarter and that it would lay off 3,500 to 4000 employees. The company, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., also said it planned to cut production of its plasma products in a bid to improve earnings. Baxter said the layoffs would cut its work force by 8 percent.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/27/business/company-news-baxter-says-chief-executive-will-resign.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER SAYS CHIEF EXECUTIVE WILL RESIGN<date>Published: January 27, 2004</date><text>Baxter International Inc., a medical products maker, said yesterday that Harry M. Jansen Kraemer Jr. would resign as chairman and chief executive. Mr. Kraemer, 49, cited the challenges Baxter has faced during the last year as the reason for his departure. At the annual meeting last May, Mr. Kraemer admitted that Baxter's 2002 performance ''was terrible.'' Baxter said Mr. Kraemer would remain in his positions until a successor was chosen. Baxter lowered its earnings forecasts in January, March, July and December, as slowing sales and weak prices in important product lines plagued results. Mr. Kraemer has been chief executive since 1999 and chairman since 2000.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/24/business/company-news-baxter-international-lowers-2003-profit-forecast.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL LOWERS 2003 PROFIT FORECAST<date>Published: December 24, 2003</date><text>Baxter International, the world's biggest maker of blood-disease therapies, reduced its 2003 profit forecast a third time. Baxter said it now expected net income to be $1.52 to $1.55 a share, down from an October estimate of $1.65 to $1.75. Baxter cut its fourth-quarter earnings forecast because of lower-than-expected income from selling assets, including a stake in Acambis, a British vaccine maker. Fourth-quarter profit from continuing operations will be 62 cents to 65 cents a share, Baxter said. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected 68 cents. Sales for the year will still increase 8 percent to 10 percent, Baxter said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/17/business/us-may-seek-funds-for-implant-claims.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">U.S. May Seek Funds for Implant Claims<date>Published: September 17, 2003</date><text>The federal government can seek reimbursement for the cost of treating women with silicone breast implants under a $4.2 billion settlement of implant claims, a federal appeals court has ruled.The United States Court of Appeals for the 11th Circuit, in a decision made public today, ordered a lower court to reinstate the government's lawsuit seeking money for the cost of covering Medicare beneficiaries. The ruling stemmed from a 1995 settlement of thousands of lawsuits by women who said implants endangered their health or made them sick. A judge in Birmingham presided over the case.The government sought money for caring for women who blamed implants for their health problems, but a federal judge dismissed the case.The settlement initially involved eight companies, but it now involves only Baxter International; Bristol-Myers Squibb; 3M; and Union Carbide and Union Carbide Chemical and Plastics, which are now part of Dow Chemical.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/05/business/technology-briefing-biotechnology-baxter-and-cerus-halt-blood-trial.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Technology Briefing | Biotechnology: Baxter And Cerus Halt Blood Trial<date>Published: September 05, 2003</date><text>Baxter International Inc. and the Cerus Corporation said yesterday that they had halted clinical trials of a system to make blood transfusions safer after two patients developed antibodies to red blood cells treated with the compound. Shares of Cerus fell 31 percent on the Nasdaq. The patients in the late-stage trial of the pathogen-inactivated red-blood-cell program showed an antibody response, Cerus and Baxter said in a statement. An antibody response means that patients risk developing an immune response to their own red blood cells, causing the destruction of the cells, although no such effect was seen, a spokeswoman for Baxter said. Baxter and Cerus said halting the trial did not affect the development or commercialization of the pathogen inactivation programs for platelets and plasma, which use a different technology and mechanism of action. They said the antibody response was discovered using a standard blood test that was used as part of the clinical protocol. Antibodies are known to arise in transfused patients and may not be physiologically active. Cerus shares fell $2.42, to $5.29; Baxter was unchanged at $28.49.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/26/business/company-news-regulators-permit-sale-of-baxter-hemophilia-medicine.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; REGULATORS PERMIT SALE OF BAXTER HEMOPHILIA MEDICINE<date>Published: July 26, 2003</date><text>Baxter International said yesterday that the Food and Drug Administration had approved its Advate medicine for treating hemophilia. The medicine is the first genetically engineered treatment for hemophilia that is made without blood components from humans or animals. The drug is safer than other treatments because it eliminates the risk of transmission of viruses, like H.I.V. or hepatitis, Baxter said. The treatment replaces a missing or deficient amount of a protein that allows the blood to clot when a person is injured.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/18/business/company-news-sec-is-investigating-baxter-s-profit-forecasts.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; S.E.C. IS INVESTIGATING BAXTER'S PROFIT FORECASTS<date>Published: July 18, 2003</date><text>Baxter International, a maker of blood-disease treatments, said federal regulators were seeking information on a series of reductions in its revenue and profit forecasts. Baxter is struggling with lower prices for some products and has cut its 2003 sales estimates three times in nine months. Baxter said that the Securities and Exchange Commission told the company that its request ''should not be construed as an indication by the commission or its staff that any violations of law have occurred.'' The company also reported second-quarter results and said severance costs and write-downs caused net income at the company to drop 76 percent to $49 million, or 8 cents a share, from $204 million, or 33 cents, a year earlier. Revenue climbed 11 percent to $2.16 billion from $1.95 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/08/business/court-revives-suit-over-a-drug-patent.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Court Revives Suit Over a Drug Patent<date>Published: July 08, 2003</date><text>A federal appeals court has revived a patent-infringement lawsuit that Abbott Laboratories filed against Baxter International over a generic version of Abbott's inhaled anesthetic, Ultane.Ultane, also sold as Sevorane, generated $221 million in United States sales last year. Abbott sued Baxter to block Food and Drug Administration approval of the proposed generic drug, claiming it would infringe on an Abbott patent for a method to improve the shelf life of sevoflurane, the active ingredient in Ultane.Baxter received approval to sell the generic version, although it had delayed selling the drug while awaiting the ruling by the Federal Court of Appeals in Washington, a Baxter spokeswoman, Deborah Spak, said. The release of the generic version, she said, ''was not something built into any timeline.''A federal judge in Chicago had thrown out the suit, saying the Baxter generic version had a water content different from what was covered by the patent. But the appeals court said late on Thursday that the ruling had been incorrect and returned the case to the judge for reconsideration.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/03/business/company-news-baxter-to-close-26-plasma-centers-and-lay-off-2500.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER TO CLOSE 26 PLASMA CENTERS AND LAY OFF 2,500<date>Published: July 03, 2003</date><text>Baxter International Inc., a medical products maker, said yesterday that it would close 26 plasma collection centers and cut about 2,500 jobs to improve profitability. The job cuts account for 5 percent of Baxter's global work force. Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., said it would take a $200 million charge in the second quarter to write down facilities and pay employee severance costs. The company projects annual earnings a share of $1.65 to $1.75.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/14/business/company-news-warning-from-baxter-medical-products-maker.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; WARNING FROM BAXTER, MEDICAL PRODUCTS MAKER<date>Published: March 14, 2003</date><text>Baxter International, the medical products maker, yesterday scaled back its sales and profit estimates for the first quarter and the year, prompting a stock sell-off. Baxter cited increased competition in the plasma-protein business, some temporary inventory reductions and economic instability in Latin America and Turkey. The profit warning came a day after the company said it had been subpoenaed by the Justice Department under an investigation into the deaths of as many as 53 kidney dialysis patients in Texas, Nebraska and six countries. Baxter's shares fell $5.67, to $21.60. Baxter said it now expected sales growth of 5 percent to 7 percent in the first quarter. The company expects a profit of 36 cents to 38 cents a share for the quarter and $2.10 to $2.20 for the year. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected the company to earn 43 cents a share in the quarter and $2.23 for the year.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/24/business/company-news-fda-approves-kidney-dialysis-solution-from-baxter.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; F.D.A. APPROVES KIDNEY DIALYSIS SOLUTION FROM BAXTER<date>Published: December 24, 2002</date><text>Baxter International, one of the world's biggest makers of blood disease treatments, said yesterday that federal regulators had approved its new kidney dialysis solution used to cleanse the blood of patients. The Food and Drug Administration cleared Extraneal, which is designed to filter blood effectively for longer periods than older solutions. Extraneal is used in a form of dialysis that patients can perform at home; traditional hemodialysis is conducted at hospitals and clinics. Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., already sells Extraneal in 30 countries, a spokeswoman, Lisa Keltner, said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/12/business/company-news-company-that-treats-blood-disease-to-make-purchase.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; COMPANY THAT TREATS BLOOD DISEASE TO MAKE PURCHASE<date>Published: November 12, 2002</date><text>Baxter International, a leading maker of treatments for blood diseases, agreed to buy Epic Therapeutics to gain a time-release technology for medicines. Baxter will pay $50 million to $100 million for the closely held Epic. The final price will not be determined until the transaction is complete, a Baxter spokeswoman, Deborah Spak, said. Epic's Promaxx system permits drugs to be released over time, from hours to weeks, Baxter said. The companies expect to complete the transaction this month. Baxter is based in Deerfield, Ill. Epic is based in Norwood, Mass.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/19/business/company-news-baxter-shares-fall-on-poor-2nd-quarter-and-charges.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER SHARES FALL ON POOR 2ND QUARTER AND CHARGES<date>Published: July 19, 2002</date><text>The health products maker Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that its second-quarter profit declined 21 percent on disappointing sales and a large charge, driving the stock down as much as 31 percent. Shares of Baxter, which makes treatments for hemophilia and kidney disease as well as drug delivery systems, fell $11.41, or 26 percent, to $32 a share. Excluding charges, its profit met Wall Street expectations. The chief executive, Harry Jansen Kraemer, said margins improved and the company was still on track to meet its annual growth goals. Baxter, which also provides vaccines and hospital supplies, reported net earnings of $200 million, or 32 cents a share, down from $253 million, or 42 cents, a year earlier.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/05/business/company-news-cerus-and-baxter-work-on-blood-purification-process.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; CERUS AND BAXTER WORK ON BLOOD PURIFICATION PROCESS<date>Published: June 05, 2002</date><text>The Cerus Corporation and Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that they had moved a step closer to marketing in Europe a process that cleanses donated blood of harmful germs and viruses. Cerus and Baxter won European regulatory approval for a component of the Intercept Blood System, which will be on the European market later this year, the companies said.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/28/business/company-news-baxter-international-to-buy-fusion-medical.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL TO BUY FUSION MEDICAL<date>Published: February 28, 2002</date><text>Baxter International said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Fusion Medical Technologies Inc., which develops products used to control bleeding during surgery, for $157 million in stock. Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., said it would pay $10 a share in Baxter common stock for Fusion, pending approval by Fusion's shareholders and regulatory authorities. Thomas Glanzmann, president of Baxter BioScience, said the acquisition would strengthen Baxter's portfolio of products for surgery and tissue repair.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/26/us/national-briefing-rockies-montana-suit-against-drug-companies.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">National Briefing | Rockies: Montana: Suit Against Drug Companies<date>Published: February 26, 2002</date><text>The state attorney general sued 18 drug makers and marketers, accusing them of illegally inflating prices and costing the state and consumers tens of millions of dollars. The scheme hurt taxpayers because they finance the Medicaid and Medicare programs that were forced to pay the exaggerated drug prices, Attorney General Mike McGrath, left, said. The lawsuit names Abbott Laboratories; American Home Products; Amgen; AstraZeneca; Aventis Pharma and Hoechst Marion Roussel, both owned by Aventis; Baxter Pharmaceutical Products; Bristol-Myers Squibb; Eli Lilly; Chiron; Dey; GlaxoSmithKline and SmithKline Beecham, which have merged; Immunex; Pharmacia and Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn, which have merged; Schering-Plough; and Warrick Pharmaceuticals.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/01/business/company-briefs-461032.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: December 1, 2001</date><text>BAXTER INTERNATIONAL INC., Deerfield, Ill., the biggest maker of treatments for blood diseases, said it would buy the closely held Autros Healthcare Solutions Inc., Toronto, which operates a system that links doctors, pharmacists and nurses electronically, to add products that can help reduce medication errors. Terms were not disclosed. GERBER SCIENTIFIC INC., South Windsor, Conn., a supplier of automated-manufacturing systems for clothing and sign-making companies, said it planned to cut about 150 jobs in the fiscal third quarter in response to a decline in sales.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/30/business/shares-of-tiny-smallpox-vaccine-maker-soar.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Shares of Tiny Smallpox Vaccine Maker Soar<date>Published: November 30, 2001</date><text>Bad news for humankind can be very good news for a small biotechnology company making vaccines to combat some of the world's worst diseases. To make that point with investors, Acambis, a small British vaccine company, sprinkled its most recent annual report with some of the year's most unsettling headlines: ''Virus closes Central Park,'' ''Travel raises the threat of world plague'' and ''The rise of the superbug.'' Yesterday, the stock of Acambis trading in New York soared as investors digested the news that the tiny company with its much larger American partner, Baxter International, had muscled out two of the world's biggest vaccine makers, Merck &amp; Company and Glaxo SmithKline, to win a United States federal contract to make vaccine for a health threat that until Sept. 11 seemed little more than theoretical. Under a new $428 million contract, Acambis will help make enough smallpox vaccine so that the government has a dose stockpiled for every American in the unlikely event that terrorists unleash a virus that last infected a person in 1978. ''For all the wrong reasons, we are quite excited,'' said Gordon Cameron, the company's chief financial officer. ''This is a transforming event for the company.'' The contract greatly expands an original federal contract Acambis attained last year to make 40 million doses of the smallpox vaccine. That first contract had been one of the company's few sources of revenue. Acambis, with only 180 employees in Britain and Massachusetts, does not even have a product on the market and it has never made a profit. Instead, the company has pinned hopes on projects that scientists are working on in its labs, including vaccines for West Nile virus, yellow fever, dengue fever and typhoid. While the company has not succeeded yet in getting a vaccine approved for sale, some experts on bioterrorism say that they are comfortable with the government's giving it a project so important to national security. Dr. Tara O'Toole, the director of the Center of Civilian Biodefense Studies at Johns Hopkins University, said last month that the size of a company did not matter as much as the talent of its scientists. So far, Acambis has done ''high-quality research,'' Dr. O'Toole said, and appears to be making good progress on the smallpox vaccine. Over the last decade, many drug companies have left the vaccine business, in part, because they see more profit in prescription drugs. But Acambis believes -- and this week seemed to prove -- that vaccines can bring fortunes. The company estimates that it will make 30 percent to 40 percent profit on the new government smallpox contract, Mr. Cameron said. The two federal smallpox contracts combined will pay Acambis more than $800 million over the next 20 years. Mr. Cameron said the company could not disclose how much of the money would go to Baxter. Baxter has invested heavily in Acambis and now owns 13 percent of its shares. Already, dozens of people have called Acambis, Mr. Cameron said, offering to volunteer for clinical trials of the vaccine, which are expected to start early next year. Also, foreign governments have inquired about buying the vaccine, he said. Vaccine companies say it normally takes many years to develop and manufacture a new vaccine. But Acambis has agreed to deliver the smallpox vaccine to the government by the end of next year. Acambis's American depository receipts rose $7.30 yesterday, to $45, on the Nasdaq stock market.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/29/us/a-nation-challenged-bioterrorism-us-orders-vast-supply-of-vaccine-for-smallpox.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">A NATION CHALLENGED: BIOTERRORISM; U.S. Orders Vast Supply Of Vaccine For Smallpox<date>Published: November 29, 2001</date><text>WASHINGTON, Nov. 28— The Bush administration said today that it had awarded a $428 million contract for 155 million doses of smallpox vaccine. That amount, when coupled with supplies that already exist or have been ordered, should be enough to protect every American against the deadly virus. The vaccine, which will be manufactured by a joint venture of Acambis, a small Massachusetts biotechnology company, and Baxter International, a large medical products company, will be delivered to the government next fall, said Tommy G. Thompson, the secretary of health and human services. ''By signing this contract, we have created a stockpile of security against the smallpox virus,'' Mr. Thompson said in announcing the step at an afternoon teleconference with reporters. He said there would be enough vaccine ''to protect every man, woman and child in America.'' But the vaccine will not be used to immunize Americans immediately against smallpox, a disease that was declared eradicated worldwide in 1980. Rather, it will be kept in a government stockpile for use in the event of a terrorist attack with the smallpox virus. Officially, the virus exists only in two repositories sanctioned by the World Health Organization -- one in Russia, the other at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, in Atlanta. But many terrorism experts believe that other nations, including Iraq and North Korea, have clandestine stocks. The probability of a smallpox attack is low, officials say. But the disease is highly contagious, and kills 30 percent of its victims. Because the United States stopped routine vaccination against smallpox in 1972, and because immunity among those vaccinated earlier has probably worn off, the nation is especially vulnerable to the virus. Experts estimate that an intentional release of it could create an epidemic that would affect millions. Mr. Thompson said more than a month ago that the government intended to stockpile the vaccine. But the plan he announced today is slightly different from the one he spoke of then. Instead of buying 300 million doses, as he initially said, the government will buy 209 million doses -- the 155 million being made by Acambis/ Baxter, plus 54 million that have already been ordered from Acambis. The government also has 15.4 million doses, left over from the 1970's, in storage. The National Institutes of Health is running an experiment to determine if the vaccine can be diluted to stretch that supply to 77 million doses, which would bring the stockpile to 286 million doses -- roughly one dose for every American. The dilution tests will not be complete until February, but the early results ''have been very gratifying,'' said Dr. Anthony S. Fauci, director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases. ''I would be very surprised,'' Dr. Fauci said, ''if we were not able to have the 1-to-5 dilution available to us.'' In choosing Acambis and Baxter, the government bypassed two of the nation's largest vaccine manufacturers, Merck and GlaxoSmithKline, which had also bid for the contract. Mr. Thompson said that the Acambis/Baxter price, $2.76 a dose, was lower, and that Acambis and Baxter had also agreed to provide the vaccine sooner than their competitors. Mr. Thompson said Acambis had done considerable research on smallpox vaccine as a result of the government contract it already held. ''Their research and development,'' he said, ''was such that we felt very comfortable with them.'' The contract is a significant boost to Acambis, which is developing vaccines against several diseases but does not yet have a product on the market. The new smallpox vaccine to be produced by Acambis and the one to come from the joint venture will be made, like the old vaccine, from a live pox virus called vaccinia. But the new vaccines will be manufactured using more modern methods, and there will be slight differences between them. Both will require clinical trials and the Food and Drug Administration's approval, but testing will start as soon as production of doses begins, and, in an emergency, the vaccines could be administered even before formal approval by the F.D.A. There is no way to know whether the new vaccines will be any safer than the old, experts say. Studies of people who received smallpox vaccinations in the 1960's have shown that one in one million died, mostly of encephalitis. Other complications were more common. So experts say it would be dangerous to do widespread vaccination in the absence of evidence of a bioterrror attack.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/29/business/company-news-baxter-settles-suit-over-dialysis-deaths-in-spain.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER SETTLES SUIT OVER DIALYSIS DEATHS IN SPAIN<date>Published: November 29, 2001</date><text>Baxter International is to pay 55 million pesetas ($292,000) in compensation to each of the families of 10 kidney dialysis patients in Spain who died last summer after treatment with Baxter dialysis filters. Manuel Mata, a lawyer for several of the families, said his clients would withdraw a lawsuit against Baxter as part of the agreement. ''Our goal is to do the right thing,'' said Harry Jansen Kraemer Jr., chairman of Baxter. ''Our hope is that this settlement helps to minimize the distress to the families involved.'' Emma Daly (NYT)</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/27/business/baxter-international-closes-two-plants.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter International Closes Two Plants<date>Published: November 27, 2001</date><text>DEERFIELD, Ill., Nov. 26— Baxter International Inc., a leading maker of treatments for blood diseases, said today that it had shut two plants that made a blood filter possibly linked to the deaths of more than 50 kidney patients worldwide. The company, which is based in Deerfield, closed plants in Ronneby, Sweden, and Miami Lakes, Fla. The closings cost 158 people in Sweden and 98 in Florida their jobs, a spokeswoman, Lisa Scheff, said. A small team of employees will remain at both plants to assist with the investigation. Baxter employs about 42,000. Baxter said this month that the filters, which are used to cleanse the blood of toxins in patients whose kidneys do not function properly, might have caused some of the deaths. The company stopped making the filter models used for those patients. Baxter said a chemical used to test the devices for leaks was not properly removed before the filters were used on patients, and the solution entered patients' bloodstreams.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/23/business/world-business-briefing-europe-spain-legal-action-planned-against-baxter.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">World Business Briefing | Europe: Spain: Legal Action Planned Against Baxter<date>Published: November 23, 2001</date><text>Spain plans to seek legal action against Baxter International in the United States in connection with the deaths of 11 patients who used its products, the health minister said yesterday. Celia Villalobos said the suit would seek to show that Baxter had breached the terms of its contract. Baxter has acknowledged that a fluid used in its filters, or dialyzers, to treat kidney dialysis patients might have played a role in the deaths of 51 people worldwide.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/15/business/criminal-investigation-of-dialysis-deaths.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Criminal Investigation of Dialysis Deaths<date>Published: November 15, 2001</date><text>STOCKHOLM, Nov. 14— Sweden has begun a criminal investigation of the plant owned by Baxter International that made the filters suspected in the deaths of more than 50 kidney dialysis patients in the United States and six other countries, a prosecutor said today. Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., has recalled the kidney dialysis filters, which were made at its plant in southern Sweden, and has discontinued their production. Baxter has acknowledged that a chemical residue in the filters appeared to have played a role in many of the deaths. Swedish investigators plan to question employees next week at the plant in Ronneby, 230 miles south of Stockholm. The Swedish prosecutor, Tommy Clevenhult, said the investigation could lead to charges of involuntary manslaughter and violations of labor and quality standards.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/14/business/baxter-faces-suit-on-dialysis-deaths.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Faces Suit On Dialysis Deaths<date>Published: November 14, 2001</date><text>CHICAGO, Nov. 13— Baxter International Inc. was sued here today on behalf of patients who used its kidney dialysis machines, which are blamed in dozens of deaths worldwide. The lawsuit, which seeks to be declared a class action, accuses Baxter, a medical products maker based in Deerfield, Ill., of carelessness and negligence and says that at least 56 people who used the dialysis machines are reported to have died. ''We believe that the total number of deaths around the world will be much higher in light of the inquiries our firm has received,'' the lawyer, Kenneth Moll, said in a statement as the suit was filed in Cook County Circuit Court. Other defendants are the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, maker of the processing fluid that Baxter said mistakenly remained in the filters after they were manufactured at a Baxter plant in Sweden, and the Baxter Healthcare Corporation, a Baxter unit. The Food and Drug Administration said last week that health authorities were investigating 53 reported deaths in seven countries this summer and fall in connection with the Baxter kidney dialysis filters, which have since been recalled. An F.D.A. spokeswoman did not immediately return a phone call today regarding the latest total. The agency has said some of the deaths being looked at were apparently not linked to the filters. The filters have been linked to four American deaths --two in Austin, Tex., and two in Kearney, Neb. Baxter said on Nov. 5 that chemical residue in its recalled filters appeared to have played a role in ''many'' of the reported deaths. Besides discontinuing the product and idling two plants, it said it was setting aside $100 million to $150 million for litigation and related expenses.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/07/business/spain-considering-suing-baxter-on-kidney-filters-official-says.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Spain Considering Suing Baxter On Kidney Filters, Official Says<date>Published: November 7, 2001</date><text>MADRID, Nov. 6— The Spanish health minister, Celia Villalobos, said today that her government was weighing legal action against Baxter International in connection with the deaths in Spain of 11 kidney dialysis patients who had been treated with filters, known as dialyzers, made by a Baxter unit. Ms. Villalobos told reporters in Madrid that the ministry would publish a report this week holding the dialyzers responsible for the deaths. On Monday, Baxter acknowledged that a chemical used in making the dialyzers might have been responsible for the deaths of 53 patients worldwide. ''There is a clear responsibility here, if it is scientifically shown'' that the chemical caused the deaths, ''and there is only one culprit,'' Ms. Villalobos said. Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., said on Monday that it had stopped making and selling the dialyzers and had recalled those already shipped. Ms. Villalobos said Baxter needed to explain why it had not told her ministry about its suspicions in several meetings after 11 patients died in quick succession in Spain in late August, and why her staff learned of Baxter's conclusions about the toxic chemical only from news reports. ''We believe at the very least there was negligence,'' Ms Villalobos said, adding that a few weeks ago Baxter had said its dialyzers ''were perfect.'' A judge in Valencia, where 6 of the 11 Spanish patients died, has opened a criminal investigation into the matter.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/06/business/dialysis-study-cites-chemical-in-53-deaths.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Dialysis Study Cites Chemical In 53 Deaths<date>Published: November 6, 2001</date><text>Baxter International said yesterday that a chemical that it used to manufacture filters for dialysis patients might have played a role in dozens of deaths around the world. The Food and Drug Administration is investigating the deaths of 53 patients who used the Baxter devices, called dialyzers, which filter toxins out of the blood of patients whose kidneys have failed. Baxter became aware of possible problems with the filters in August, after several patients died in Spain, but a company investigation had failed to find anything wrong with the devices. The company, which recalled the filters worldwide in mid-October and continued to study them, said it uncovered the probable cause of the deaths over the weekend. Four of the deaths occurred in the United States, two in Austin, Tex., and two in Kearney, Neb. Federal regulators said yesterday that a doctor at the Nebraska dialysis center was questioning whether the company's filters were to blame. Twenty-one of the deaths being reviewed by the F.D.A. occurred in Croatia. At least 10 deaths occurred in Spain, 7 in Taiwan, 5 in Germany, 4 in Italy and 2 in Colombia, according to the F.D.A. The company voluntarily recalled all of its dialyzers in the series A, AF and AX on Oct. 18, sending letters to doctors and asking them to return any unused filters of that type. Yesterday, Baxter said it had decided to permanently cease manufacturing the dialyzers. They were made by Althin Medical, a company Baxter acquired last year, at a factory in Ronneby, Sweden. Baxter said it planned to compensate the families of patients who died. ''We are greatly saddened by the patient deaths, and I would like to extend my personal sympathies to family members,'' Harry M. Jansen Kraemer Jr., Baxter's chairman and chief executive, said in a statement. ''We have a responsibility to make public our findings immediately and take swift action, even though confirmatory studies remain under way.'' Dr. David W. Feigal, director of the F.D.A.'s center for devices and radiological health, said yesterday that the problem appeared to be that the chemical, a fluid called perfluorohydrocarbon that Baxter uses to manufacture some of the filters, is liquefied at room temperature but becomes a gas if it is warmed to body temperature. That means the liquid could have created gas bubbles in the bloodstream, Dr. Feigal said. Regulators are investigating whether the chemical fluid, which Baxter began using in December, is used by other filter manufacturers and whether other patients might have been affected. ''We want to make sure this is not a hidden problem in some other products,'' Dr. Feigal said. Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., said yesterday that it began an internal investigation of the filters after Spain reported that 10 people using its filters had died. The company said that an early series of tests on the filters had found no problems. Perfluorohydrocarbon is a nontoxic substance, the company said, but it is not labeled for human use. Sally Benjamin Young, a spokeswoman for Baxter, said the fluid was used in fewer than 10 percent of the filters, those that had been set aside after they failed a quality control test. The fluid was used to retest the filters, she said. To cover the cost of recalling the filters and compensating families, Baxter said yesterday that it was setting aside $100 million to $150 million. The cost could exceed the $130 million that Baxter paid for Althin in March 2000. In Spain, a report by the Ministry of Health that is expected to be released this week will tie the deaths of more than 10 people to Baxter's filters, according to Fernando García López, an author of the report. Autopsies on five of those who died found evidence of multiple organ failure ''which is not among the usual causes of sudden death'' in kidney patients, Mr. García López said. Manuel Mata, a lawyer who represents the families of eight people who died in Spain, said his clients were considering filing lawsuits against Baxter in the United States. Families of people who died after Aug. 18 are especially angry, Mr. Mata said, because hospitals in the city of Valencia continued to use Baxter's dialyzers, despite four deaths in Madrid between Aug. 15 and Aug. 18 and after hospitals in that city stopped using the filters. ''There is something very important that must be investigated,'' Mr. Mata said. ''What happened after Aug. 18 when the dialyzers were removed in Madrid for fear they were connected to the deaths?'' ''Baxter did not withdraw the dialyzers from Valencia,'' Mr. Mata said. ''They could have pulled the products in that time. Those deaths were avoidable.'' Ms. Young, the Baxter spokeswoman, said the company had been told that the deaths in Madrid were not related to the filters. When it learned of the deaths in Valencia, she said, Baxter immediately recalled the filters in Spain and stopped selling them worldwide. Photo: Baxter executives at a news conference in mid-October in Zagreb, Croatia, after the company said it was holding back its series A kidney dialyzers in Europe, pending an investigation into the deaths of patients. (Reuters)(pg. C7)</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/23/technology/news-watch-equipment-just-relax-surf-the-net-and-give-us-your-blood.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">NEWS WATCH: EQUIPMENT; Just Relax, Surf the Net And Give Us Your Blood<date>Published: August 23, 2001</date><text>How about a movie to go with those cookies and juice? A medical equipment manufacturer has designed a chair to help donors while away the time electronically as they sit with tubes in their arms.The reclining vinyl chairs, designed by Baxter International of Deerfield, Ill., come with a computer with Internet access, DVD player and headphones. They are being tested by the New York Blood Center and the Gulf Coast Regional Blood Center in Houston. Other centers will be testing the chairs this fall, said Margaret Stanford Stubny, a company spokeswoman.The chairs are intended for donors undergoing apheresis, a one- to two-hour process in which components like platelets and plasma are extracted from the blood and then the blood is returned to the donor's body.Catherine Greenman</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/08/business/company-news-medical-products-maker-to-acquire-oncology-unit.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; MEDICAL PRODUCTS MAKER TO ACQUIRE ONCOLOGY UNIT<date>Published: August 08, 2001</date><text>The medical products maker Baxter International has agreed to buy the oncology subsidiary of Germany's Degussa for $470 million, Baxter said yesterday. The unit, Asta Medica Oncology, employs about 900 people. The companies expect to close the transaction this year, pending regulatory approval. Baxter is based in Deerfield, Ill. Degussa is a chemicals and precious metals processor.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/13/business/nexell-baxter-transaction.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Nexell-Baxter Transaction<date>Published: June 13, 2001</date><text>Nexell Therapeutics Inc. agreed to transfer rights to the company's cell therapeutic development products to the health care unit of Baxter International Inc. unit and, as a result, will lay off about 60 workers. Terms were not disclosed. The company, a leading maker of medical supplies, will get sales, marketing and distribution rights for Nexell's cell processing products. If the agreement is completed, Nexell will dismiss about 66 percent of its work force of 90 and will shut a sales office in Brussels, a spokesman, Tad Heitmann, said. Nexell, which is based in Irvine, will get royalties on Baxter's sales of its products and will reduce expenses.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/18/us/national-briefing-science-and-health-hemophilia-drug-shortage.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">National Briefing | Science And Health: Hemophilia Drug Shortage<date>Published: May 18, 2001</date><text>Hemophiliacs are facing a severe shortage of blood-clotting drugs because of contamination at one plant and a maintenance shutdown at another. In March, the Bayer Corporation discovered bacteria in machinery at a plant in Berkeley, Calif., that makes one drug, Kogenate FS, and severely curtailed production. Earlier this year, Baxter International Inc. of Deerfield, Ill., which makes a product called Recombinate, shut down production at one of its plants for routine maintenance.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/16/business/company-news-baxter-says-it-will-double-capacity-at-swiss-plant.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER SAYS IT WILL DOUBLE CAPACITY AT SWISS PLANT<date>Published: March 16, 2001</date><text>Baxter International, a leading maker of medical supplies, said yesterday that it would double manufacturing capacity at a plant in NeuchÃ¢tel, Switzerland, that makes its hemophilia drug. The company also said it might try to meet demand for the drug, a bleeding-disorder treatment, by adding capacity at its plant in Thousand Oaks, Calif. Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., told investors in New York that the company would spend $2 billion from 1995 to 2005 to increase sales in its BioScience unit. The company seeks unit sales growth of at least 20 percent a year, to $12 billion in 2010, from $2.5 billion in 2000.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/14/business/technology-testing-of-blood-substitute-to-resume.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">TECHNOLOGY; Testing of Blood Substitute to Resume<date>Published: March 14, 2001</date><text>Alliance Pharmaceutical said yesterday that researchers investigating why patients receiving Oxygent, its blood substitute, had more strokes and other adverse reactions during heart surgery than those in a control group who did not get Oxygent have concluded that flawed surgery preparation procedures were to blame, not the product itself.As a result, Alliance, which is based in San Diego, plans to resume clinical testing of Oxygent and will receive a $15 million investment in May from Baxter International under an agreement between the companies last year.The Baxter investment had been put on hold when Alliance suspended the clinical trial in January. Under the agreement, Baxter has the right to manufacture Oxygent if it gains regulatory approval and to sell it in the United States, Canada and Europe.Alliance's shares jumped $1.44, or 58 percent, to $$3.91 on the news. Baxter's shares rose $1.65, to $91.90.Oxygent takes the place of the red cells in blood in delivering oxygen to the body. It is based on a synthetic chemical, known as a perfluorocarbon. Like other proposed blood substitutes, it is intended to free doctors from concerns about blood shortages, infections in donated blood, and the need to ensure that blood types match when transfusing blood.Baxter is working separately on a genetically engineered bacteria to produce a blood substitute, but that technology is in a much earlier stage of development.Alliance has not yet decided whether to start a new general surgery trial or resume the cardiac trials it suspended in January when control patients mysteriously seemed to be faring better than those receiving Oxygent. The changes in surgery preparation necessary to eliminate the problem in the cardiac test might make it hard for the Food and Drug Administration to accept data from the pre-suspension and postsuspension patients as part of a single study.''If we have to start all over, we will do general surgery,'' said Gwen Rosenberg, an Alliance spokeswoman. Either way, the testing is unlikely to begin before the fall. But the company may not wait for the results before applying for clearance in Europe to market Oxygent there, based on earlier tests.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/08/business/5-drug-makers-use-material-with-possible-mad-cow-link.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">5 Drug Makers Use Material With Possible Mad Cow Link<date>Published: February 08, 2001</date><text>For the last eight years, the Food and Drug Administration has repeatedly asked pharmaceutical companies not to use materials from cattle raised in countries where there is a risk of mad cow disease.But regulators discovered last year that five companies, including some of the world's largest drug concerns, were still using ingredients from those countries to make nine widely used vaccines.Some of the companies say that they found the F.D.A.'s request unclear and do not believe they did anything wrong. Others say they could not keep up with the government's expanding list of countries where cattle could be infected. One, however, acknowledged that it could have moved more quickly.The nine vaccines include some regularly given to millions of American children, including common vaccines to prevent polio, diphtheria and tetanus. They also include the anthrax vaccine, which the government requires for soldiers serving in the Persian Gulf.Federal health officials stress that the vaccines are still considered safe. They calculate that the odds of these vaccines passing on the disease, in the worst eventualities, are between one in 40 million and one in 40 billion doses.The officials say that the very slight chance that someone could be infected is far outweighed by the benefits that these vaccines bring in fighting disease and preventing death. Indeed, it is now only a scientific theory that a vaccine could infect someone with the human form of mad cow disease -- called new variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease. No one is known to have contracted the disease this way.''Any risk is very remote,'' said Dr. Karen Midthune, director of the F.D.A.'s Office of Vaccine Research and Review. ''But if we have the ability to bring this remote risk to zero, that is something we want to do.''Nonetheless, the fact that these suspect materials slipped into the nation's vaccine supply -- and that the F.D.A. did not discover it for seven years -- raises questions about the agency's ability to ensure that all medicines are free of the infectious proteins that can cause mad cow disease.The F.D.A. so far has only investigated the vaccine makers and has not looked to see whether other medicine is free of possible mad cow contaminants. Some experts say they worry more about dietary supplements. Unlike drugs, supplements are largely unregulated. The F.D.A. is not even sure how many supplement makers there are.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/02/business/patent-lawsuit-is-settled.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Patent Lawsuit Is Settled<date>Published: November 02, 2000</date><text>Baxter International Inc. has settled a patent lawsuit with the Spectranetics Corporation, which says it will take a $4 million charge to resolve the litigation. Baxter sued in federal court in Delaware in August 1999, saying Spectranetics was infringing three patents awarded since 1987 for laser-surgery equipment. Spectranetics will pay back royalties and license the technology from Baxter through 2005.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/business/company-news-baxter-gains-approval-to-expand-production-of-a-drug.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER GAINS APPROVAL TO EXPAND PRODUCTION OF A DRUG<date>Published: October 06, 2000</date><text>Baxter International said yesterday that it had won approval from the Food and Drug Administration to expand production of its blood-clotting drug to treat hemophilia. The treatment, a genetically engineered protein, is produced at Baxter's plant in Thousand Oaks, Calif. The company, based in Deerfield, Ill., said demand for the therapy, known as recombinant Factor VIII, had almost doubled in the last five years. Bruce Cranna, an analyst for ABN Amro, said the expanded production could mean $200 million to $240 million in new annual sales. Baxter's recombinant Factor VIII had 1999 sales of about $450 million, he said. The company is the biggest maker of the drug. Baxter shares rose $5.44, closing at $82.13.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/30/business/online-exchange-for-health-care-companies-could-cut-costs.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Online Exchange for Health Care Companies Could Cut Costs<date>Published: March 30, 2000</date><text>Five big health care companies, which account for about 70 percent of the equipment, drugs and other supplies bought by the nation's hospitals, said yesterday that they planned to form an online exchange that would provide information about products and enable customers to place and track orders.The companies -- Johnson &amp; Johnson, Baxter International Inc., Abbott Laboratories, Medtronic Inc. and GE Medical Systems, a unit of the General Electric Company -- say the exchange's purpose is to cut hundreds of millions of dollars out of the costs that they and their customers incur while handling the drudge work of processing orders. Although customers would continue to negotiate prices with individual manufacturers, they would use the exchange to place orders under previously negotiated contracts, check on the status of orders, arrange delivery, check supporting documentation and learn more about products.The companies, which will own equal shares of the exchange, say they expect little opposition from regulators. They are not banding together on prices, and they are inviting all other medical suppliers to join. ''There will be a firewall so that we can't even see each other's prices,'' said Miles White, the chief executive of Abbott.The five companies are still in the process of hiring the exchange's managers and putting the finishing touches on its software. They expect the exchange, to be based in Chicago, to go online in the United States this summer and to expand globally next year. A free service to customers, the exchange will be financed by fees from participating suppliers, including the five companies.''We'll never take this entity public, because we don't want to have to maximize profits for shareholders,'' said Jeffrey Immelt, the chief executive of GE Medical.Arthur D. Collins Jr., Medtronic's president, added: ''The C.E.O. of this exchange will be gauged on how efficiently he can move large volumes of transactions and how well customers are satisfied, not on earnings per share.''Still, the companies do stand to benefit financially in more ways than just cutting costs. Many Web-based exchanges, including Neoforma.com, Medcenterdirect.com, Promedix and Broadlane, already offer health care customers one-stop shopping for medical products. Those companies take their fees from suppliers. By forming their own exchange, the five companies avoid such fees.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/23/business/company-news-baxter-in-130-million-deal-to-buy-swedish-dialysis-unit.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER IN $130 MILLION DEAL TO BUY SWEDISH DIALYSIS UNIT<date>Published: December 23, 1999</date><text>Baxter International, a maker of medical devices based in Deerfield, Ill., agreed to buy the unprofitable dialysis equipment maker Althin Medical A.B. of Sweden for about $130 million in cash, stock and debt to expand in the $7 billion renal care market. Baxter said it had exchanged an unspecified number of its own shares for those of Althin's chairman, Anders Althin, and his family, and would offer 100 kronor a share for the rest -- a 47 percent premium to the stock's closing price on Monday. Althin's debt is about $50 million, according to Baxter. Shares of Baxter gained $1.25, to $60.6875.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/19/business/company-news-baxter-international-buying-north-american-vaccine.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL BUYING NORTH AMERICAN VACCINE<date>Published: November 19, 1999</date><text>Baxter International Inc., the world's leading manufacturer of medical devices, said yesterday that it was acquiring North American Vaccine Inc. for about $257 million in stock. Baxter will pay $7 a share in stock and cash for North American Vaccine, and assume $133 million in debt. North American Vaccine, based in Columbia, Md., develops, manufactures and sells vaccines to prevent infectious diseases. The company has about 300 employees. Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., employs some 42,000 people worldwide. Baxter shares slipped 62.5 cents, to $67, on the New York Stock Exchange. North American Vaccine stock was up 37.5 cents, to $6.1875.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/13/business/baxter-plans-to-split-off-its-heart-products-business.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Plans to Split Off Its Heart Products Business<date>Published: July 13, 1999</date><text>Baxter International Inc. said today that it would spin off its cardiovascular business to shareholders, and investors responded by pushing up the stock of the medical products company.Harry Kraemer, the president and chief executive of Baxter, said that the spinoff, reported today in The Wall Street Journal, would create the largest United States purely cardiovascular company focused on treating late stages of cardiovascular disease. The company's products include tissue heart valves, catheters and blood oxygenators used in coronary bypass surgery.The company, which has not been named yet, enters an arena full of big competitors, including the Guidant Corporation, Medtronic Inc. and St. Jude Medical.Mr. Kraemer said he and Baxter's board had decided on the spinoff after six months of reviewing Baxter's portfolio. ''We believe that creating a separate, independent, publicly traded company clearly makes the most sense,'' he said.The cardiovascular unit was the area in which Baxter did the fewest acquisitions as the business competed for money with other divisions. Analysts said this was a critical factor hampering growth.''There's always a tug for resources at a company as broad as Baxter,'' said Michael Weinstein, an analyst at J. P. Morgan. He called the spinoff a step in the right direction toward raising Baxter's value.Baxter's shares rose $3.3125, or more than 5 percent, closing at $64.1875 today on the New York Stock Exchange.Without the cardiovascular unit and its nearly $1 billion in annual sales, Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., is left with yearly revenue of $6 billion from its three other businesses -- renal products and services, intravenous systems and medical products, and blood therapy products.Analysts said the cardiovascular segment had generated about 12 percent of Baxter's earnings and sales.The new status of the cardiovascular business as a stand-alone company will mean greater opportunities for research and development, said Michael Mussallem, who will become chief executive of the spinoff, which will be based in Irvine, Calif.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/21/us/panel-confirms-no-major-illness-tied-to-implants.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Panel Confirms No Major Illness Tied to Implants<date>Published: June 21, 1999</date><text>An independent panel of 13 scientists convened by the Institute of Medicine at the request of Congress has concluded that silicone breast implants do not cause any major diseases.''Some women with breast implants are indeed very ill and the I.O.M. committee is very sympathetic to their distress,'' the group wrote in a report to be made public on Tuesday. ''However, it can find no evidence that these women are ill because of their implants.''The report, more than 400 pages long, says the ''primary safety issue'' with implants is their tendency to rupture or deflate and to lead to infections or hardening or scarring of the breast tissue. There is little argument about these localized problems, which can be painful and disfiguring and which often lead women to have additional surgery.But the report asserts in forceful terms that there is no reason to believe that the implants cause rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, or any other systemic disease. Women who say their implants have caused them to suffer these or related problems have turned breast implants into a leading source of liability litigation.The report was provided to The New York Times by an organization that consults in the breast implant matter and, a spokesman said, that ''is pleased with the report's conclusions.'' The report is the latest in a series of evaluations that have concluded that there is no scientific evidence to support the lawsuits. Because it comes from the Institute of Medicine, the medical arm of the National Academy of Sciences, the nation's most prestigious scientific organization, it is expected to be influential in setting scientific agendas and encouraging women to accept settlements from implant makers rather than take their cases to court.In preparing the report, panel members held public hearings, met in private and evaluated more than a thousand research reports. The Institute panel did not conduct any original research. Rather, the panel relied primarily on research and other materials reported by scientists and submitted by companies and advocates for women with implants. But the report said that since lawsuits were first filed in the late 1980's and early 1990's, there have been many scientific studies upon which to make an evaluation.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/05/business/baxter-renews-shared-investment-plan.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Renews Shared Investment Plan<date>Published: May 05, 1999</date><text>Baxter International, the No. 2 medical-products maker, said today that 142 of its executives had bought about $200 million in company stock after taking out loans.The executives are participating in Baxter's second shared investment program, which was approved by Baxter's board earlier today. The company said the plan was voluntary.Executives took out loans averaging about $1.4 million apiece. They bought 3.1 million shares at Monday's closing price of $63.625. Shares closed yesterday up $1.3125, to $64.9375.The company started a similar program in 1994 in which 63 executives bought about $122 million worth of company stock after taking out personal loans. The shares of Baxter, based in Deerfield, have more than doubled since the beginning of June 1994, as Baxter spun off its slower-growing health care products and cost-management services business in 1996 to focus on medical technology products, among other things.Baxter also said it wanted to increase sales by about 10 percent in 1999 and increase earnings at a rate in the low double digits.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/07/us/maker-of-iv-system-to-stop-using-a-plastic.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Maker of IV System to Stop Using a Plastic<date>Published: April 07, 1999</date><text>Baxter International, one of the largest manufacturers of intravenous health care products, said yesterday that it had agreed to develop and introduce intravenous systems that do not use polyvinyl chloride plastic tubes and bags.The agreement followed discussions between Baxter and a group of Roman Catholic and labor union shareholders who argued that the polyvinyl chloride, or PVC, bags leach chemicals that are dangerous if the systems are used frequently.A spokeswoman for Baxter, Deborah Spak, said the company ''still stands behind PVC's.''''Where other materials are proven superior to PVC, we will switch to them,'' Ms. Spak said.Baxter already makes health care products with alternative materials for some other uses, including blood platelet storage. It did not specify when the alternative IV systems might be offered.The company announced the agreement as part of an understanding with the shareholder representatives of the retirement plans of two Catholic orders, the Sisters of Mercy Regional Community Center based in Detroit and the Sisters of Charity of Cincinnati and the pension fund manager of the Service Employees International Union.The agreement drew praise from Greenpeace, the environmental advocacy group, and Health Care Without Harm, a coalition that includes hospitals, nurses organizations and the American Public Health Association.The groups, which own about 100,000 shares of Baxter stock, withdrew a resolution asking shareholders to vote at the company's annual meeting to order Baxter to phase out vinyl I.V.'s.The critics of PVC filed a similar resolution on behalf of shareholders of Abbott Laboratories, which is also a leading manufacturer of vinyl intravenous equipment. Abbott opposed the proposal.Rhonda Luniak, a spokeswoman for Abbott, said the company was working to develop alternatives to PVC's, which she said had been shown to be safe for more than 25 years.Ms. Luniak said Abbott had signed a five-year agreement to supply products to a buying group of a dozen Catholic hospitals on March 30. The buying group, Consorta Inc., which does not include the Detroit and Cincinnati sisters, agreed to buy Abbott products, including PVC ones, she said.Health Care Without Harm said 400 million vinyl IV bags were used in the United States each year. Vivian R. Wohl, an independent securities analyst in San Francisco, said the price of the bags was 40 cents to 50 cents each.Baxter reported 1998 sales of $2.3 billion in IV products, including the bags, solutions, and pumps.Dr. Peter Orris, a professor of preventive and internal medicine at Rush Medical School in Chicago, said components of the plastics disrupted the body's endocrine system. There was ''some data'' showing harmful effects to animals, Dr. Orris said, but ''no literature that indicated the exact effects on humans.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/09/17/business/company-news-baxter-to-take-charges-and-discontinue-a-product.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER TO TAKE CHARGES AND DISCONTINUE A PRODUCT<date>Published: September 17, 1998</date><text>Baxter International Inc., the world's No. 2 medical technology company, said yesterday that it would take third-quarter charges of $293 million, mainly to settle breast-implant lawsuits, and would end production of the blood substitute Hemassist. It said it would continue to develop an experimental blood substitute acquired with its $188 million purchase of Somatogen Inc. in May. Baxter will take a $178 million charge for lawsuits, a $40 million charge to end joint ventures and a $75 million charge to end production of Hemassist. It will cut about 100 employees as it closes Hemassist operations. Shares of Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., rose 12.5 cents, to $60.9375.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/25/business/company-news-baxter-international-to-acquire-somatogen.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL TO ACQUIRE SOMATOGEN<date>Published: February 25, 1998</date><text>Aiming to strengthen its position in the emerging field of blood substitutes, Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that it would acquire Somatogen Inc. in a stock transaction worth about $189 million. Somatogen's shares rose $2.0625, or 31 percent, to $8.6875, in Nasdaq trading of more than 3.5 million shares, while Baxter fell 68.75 cents on the New York Stock Exchange, to $55.75. Shareholders of Somatogen, based in Boulder, Colo., will get $9 worth of Baxter stock for each share of Somatogen.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/30/business/company-news-3-companies-buy-boc-health-unit-for-1-billion.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; 3 COMPANIES BUY BOC HEALTH UNIT FOR $1 BILLION<date>Published: January 30, 1998</date><text>The diversified chemicals company BOC Group P.L.C. of Britain agreed yesterday to sell its Ohmeda Inc. health care business to three companies for $:640 million, or $1.05 billion. The Instrumentarium Corporation, a Finnish maker of anesthesia and intensive care technologies, will buy Ohmeda's medical systems and specialty products division for about $494 million. Becton Dickinson &amp; Company of Franklin Lakes, N.J., will acquire Ohmeda's medical devices unit for about $452 million. Baxter International Inc. of Deerfield, Ill., will take the pharmaceutical products unit for about $104 million. Baxter also said its fourth-quarter profit rose 15 percent, to $182 million, or 64 cents a diluted share, from a year earlier.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/31/business/baxter-receives-italian-approval.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Receives Italian Approval<date>Published: December 31, 1997</date><text>The Baxter International Company said today that Italian antitrust authorities had cleared its acquisition of some medical products businesses from closely held Bieffe Medital S.p.A.The company will pay $185 million and assume $50 million in debt to acquire the dialysis, intravenous therapy and irrigation solutions and nutrition businesses. Clark SRL, a Milan-based company that owns a controlling interest in Bieffe, will retain the surgical and pharmaceutical businesses.Baxter, which develops products related to the blood and circulatory system, acquired Immuno International and Research Medical Inc. earlier this year. It plans to complete the Bieffe acquisition in January.Bieffe, which is based in Lugano, Switzerland, specializes in flexible container technology for dialysis, intravenous and irrigation solutions. Italy's antitrust authorities reviewed the acquisition because Clark is based in Italy and Bieffe's primary market is there, Baxter officials said.Shares of Baxter shares rose $1.3125 today, to $49.6875, on trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/13/business/baxter-to-back-vimrx-developmental-venture.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">BAXTER TO BACK VIMRX DEVELOPMENTAL VENTURE<date>Published: June 13, 1997</date><text>Vimrx Pharmaceuticals Inc. and Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that they would form a joint venture to develop treatments for cancer, AIDS and other diseases. Vimrx will issue to Baxter 11 million common shares plus preferred stock together worth about $90 million, giving Baxter a 23 percent to 26 percent stake in Vimrx. Vimrx will invest $10 million in the venture, to be based in Irvine, Calif., and have an 80 percent stake. Baxter will invest $20 million in the as-yet unnamed venture. Vimrx shares were unchanged at $3.50, while shares of Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., fell 37.5 cents, to $54.125.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/08/business/4-drug-companies-ordered-to-pay-hemophiliacs.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">4 Drug Companies Ordered to Pay Hemophiliacs<date>Published: May 08, 1997</date><text>Four drug manufacturers whose blood products were said to have infected thousands of hemophiliacs with the virus that causes AIDS in the early 1980's will pay about $670 million in a settlement approved by a Federal judge.Six thousand hemophiliacs were each to receive $100,000. In an earlier settlement in Japan, AIDS-infected hemophiliacs were paid $450,000 each. The office of Federal District Judge John Grady confirmed today that he had granted oral formal approval to the settlement on Tuesday. The settlement had won preliminary court approval in April 1996.The settlement was ''one of the most horrible scenarios that can be imagined,'' said Ron Niederman, a spokesman for the Committee of 10 Thousand, which represents the hemophiliacs. ''In light of the damage they caused, the companies are getting off cheap.''The companies, which admitted no wrongdoing but agreed to settle, were Bayer A.G. of Germany, the Green Cross Corporation of Japan, Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc., a French and American company and Baxter International Inc. of Deerfield, Ill.Guy Esnouf, a Rhone-Poulenc spokesman, said that combined the companies would pay a total of up to about $670 million, of which about $600 million would go to individual hemophiliacs.To resolve insurance complications and insure that the hemophiliacs will be able to keep their money, the companies will pay $12 million to the Federal Government and $18 million to 25 state governments and private insurers, he said. In addition, the companies face up to $40 million in legal fees, Mr. Esnouf said.Bayer will shoulder 45 percent of the total cost, Baxter and Rhone-Poulenc 20 percent each and Green Cross 15 percent.The settlement does not entirely end the decade-old controversy stemming from the infection of 6,000 to 8,000 United States hemophiliacs by contaminated Factor VIII and Factor IX blood clotting agents. About 550 hemophiliacs opted out of the class-action settlement and might pursue litigation against the companies on their own, Mr. Niederman said. He was among those opting out and planned to press his case ''to the bitter end.''Also, the companies were still in discussions with 25 other states and the Prudential Insurance Company of America over settling remaining insurance matters, Mr. Esnouf said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/08/business/baxter-plans-to-acquire-bieffe-units-for-185-million.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">BAXTER PLANS TO ACQUIRE BIEFFE UNITS FOR $185 MILLION<date>Published: April 08, 1997</date><text>Baxter International Inc. reached an agreement yesterday to acquire the dialysis, intravenous therapy and irrigation solutions businesses of Bieffe Medital S.p.A. from Clark S.R.L. Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., said the acquisition price was $185 million plus assumption of $50 million in debt. The sale is subject to approval of antitrust authorities in Europe and other customary closing conditions. Beiffe is a Swiss-based company with 1996 revenues of about $100 million. Baxter's 1996 sales were $5.4 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/05/business/baxter-in-stock-swap-for-research-medical.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">BAXTER IN STOCK SWAP FOR RESEARCH MEDICAL<date>Published: December 05, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Research Medical Inc. in a stock swap valued at $236 million, or $23.50 a share, to expand into products for minimally invasive heart surgery. The acquisition steps up Baxter's efforts to concentrate on late-stage cardiovascular disease. Research Medical is one of the nation's largest makers of cannulae, or tubes used to transfer a patient's blood to a heart-lung machine during open-heart surgery, and cardioplegia products, used to limit damage to heart muscle. Shares of Research Medical rose $2.766, to $22.766, in Nasdaq trading. Separately, Baxter said it expected to close the previously announced purchase of Immuno International A.G. in two to six weeks.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/26/business/drug-companies-to-pursue-aids-settlement.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Drug Companies to Pursue AIDS Settlement<date>Published: November 26, 1996</date><text>Four pharmaceutical companies said today their they had decided to proceed with a settlement with thousands of hemophiliacs who contended they were infected with the AIDS virus from blood-clotting products.The companies -- the Bayer Corporation; Baxter International Inc.; the Armour Pharmaceutical Company, a unit of Rhone Poulenc S.A., and the Alpha Therapeutic Corporation, a Green Cross Corporation subsidiary -- have proposed paying $620 million to 6,200 hemophiliacs, an offer that was accepted last month by all but 540 of the victims.The companies told United States District Judge John Grady that they planned to move ahead with the settlement, despite the uncertainty of having to deal separately with those who had refused the offer.Some 350 lawsuits already have been filed by the holdouts, but the companies told Judge Grady they would continue to seek accords with those hemophiliacs.The companies and many of the victims are trying to work out agreements with Medicaid and private insurance companies that might have a claim against the settlement money. The judge has said he wants the full amount -- $100,000 for each person -- to go to the victims.In addition to the settlement amount, the drug companies have set aside $40 million to pay the victims' legal bills.The final agreement is subject to the judge's approval.The hemophiliacs contended the companies put them at risk in the early 1980's by failing to sterilize blood that was donated to make blood-clotting products, and that the companies recruited donors at a high risk for AIDS.The companies said they had no way of knowing at the time how AIDS was transmitted and were not at fault.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/19/business/premier-enters-pact-with-baxter-and-allegiance.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">PREMIER ENTERS PACT WITH BAXTER AND ALLEGIANCE<date>Published: November 19, 1996</date><text>Premier Inc., an alliance of hospital and health systems, said yesterday that it had entered a seven-year deal to buy medical supplies from Baxter International Inc. and the Allegiance Healthcare Corporation with a potential value of $1 billion a year. Premier said the pact included group purchasing agreements for intravenous solutions, drug delivery systems and surgical and respiratory therapy products. Premier resulted from the merger of American Healthcare Systems Inc., Sun Health Alliance and Premier Health Alliance Inc. It serves 700 hospitals and health care facilities and about 1,100 other affiliated hospital and health care organizations.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/02/business/allegiance-to-take-550-million-earnings-charge.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">ALLEGIANCE TO TAKE $550 MILLION EARNINGS CHARGE<date>Published: November 02, 1996</date><text>The Allegiance Corporation said yesterday that it would take a $550 million charge in the fourth quarter, its first quarter as an independent company, because of an accounting change. Allegiance, a medical products company, which was spun off from Baxter International Inc., changed its method of accounting for good will, or the value of intangible assets, like a respected business name. Good will is written off over time. Allegiance had about $1.1 billion of good will as of Sept. 30. Allegiance said the accounting change and write-down of good will will reduce amortization expenses by $4.7 million in the fourth quarter and by $18.9 million annually.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/25/business/drug-makers-aids-offer-gains-support.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Drug Makers' AIDS Offer Gains Support<date>Published: October 25, 1996</date><text>A $640 million offer to hemophiliacs to settle claims that blood-clotting products they used were infected with the virus that causes AIDS was accepted by more than 90 percent of those eligible, a spokesman for the pharmaceutical companies said yesterday.The companies have until Nov. 22 to decide whether to go along with the settlement and face lawsuits from many of the remaining claimants.The manufacturers' spokesman, Guy Esnouf of Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc., would not say what factors would be considered.The settlement offer was made in May by Bayer A.G. on behalf of its Cutter and Miles laboratories divisions; Baxter International Inc., and its Travenol and Hyland divisions; Rhone-Poulenc Rorer, the American subsidiary of Rhone-Poulenc S.A. of France, and its Armour Pharmaceutical division, and the Alpha Therapeutic Corporation, an American division of Green Cross of Japan.The companies offered the settlement, which works out to about $100,000 for each person, in an effort to end a decade of claims that they failed to protect their customers from the virus. People who used the companies' clotting products from 1978 to 1985 and contracted the virus, H.I.V., are eligible for the payment under the class-action suit.Hemophiliacs contend that the companies put them at risk in the early 1980's by failing to sterilize donated blood used to make the blood-clotting products, and that the companies intentionally recruited donors at a high risk for AIDS.Of the forms returned by hemophiliacs choosing the settlement, roughly 6,500 were deemed eligible and more than 800 of those have lawsuits pending. Fewer than 550 chose to stay out of the settlement, about 380 of whom have filed suit.If the settlements are pursued, the companies' final agreement will depend on how the court decides to handle Medicare or Medicaid claims that would have to be paid first, Mr. Esnouf, the pharmaceutical companies' spokesman, said.While refusing to admit wrongdoing, the companies proposed a $640 million settlement of all claims. Hemophiliac advocates grudgingly endorsed the deal, acknowledging that many claimants would want it. If the companies accept the settlement, it will be presented to a Federal judge.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/30/business/baxter-purchasing-immuno-swiss-blood-products-maker.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Purchasing Immuno, Swiss Blood-Products Maker<date>Published: August 30, 1996</date><text>In its latest effort to grow faster, Baxter International said yesterday that it would buy Immuno International A.G., a plodding Swiss blood-products company, for $715 million.Baxter said the acquisition would help it catch up to the world's biggest maker of blood products, Centeon, a joint venture recently formed by Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc. and Hoechst A.G. After the acquisition, Baxter said, both it and Centeon would have about 20 percent of the world market, well ahead of other blood-products makers. The deal was reported yesterday in The Wall Street Journal.Vernon R. Loucks Jr., the chairman and chief executive of Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill., said the deal would advance the company's ''focus on global expansion and technological innovations.''Analysts said the acquisition would help Baxter move to higher profit margins and faster growth. ''It's a pretty nifty deal,'' said Glenn Reicin, a health care analyst with Morgan Stanley &amp; Company.Investors welcomed the move, pushing up Baxter shares $2.50, to $45.375, yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange. Immuno stock closed at 886 Swiss francs a share, up 3 francs, on the Zurich Stock Exchange.Baxter was spurned when it tried to acquire a kidney dialysis business from W. R. Grace last winter for $3.8 billion. It is in the process of spinning off its big hospital-supply unit to shareholders next month as the Allegiance Healthcare Corporation.Immuno had about $550 million in 1995 sales, 85 percent in Europe. Baxter, after subtracting Allegiance, had $5 billion in sales, half from overseas operations, with two-thirds of profits also from overseas. Combined with Immuno, Baxter said, 60 percent of its sales and three-quarters of its profits would come from abroad.Eli Kammerman, an analyst with Salomon Brothers, said such a weighting overseas would increase Baxter's risk as foreign currency exchange rates varied. But he praised the deal as likely to add to Baxter's earnings as soon as the second half of 1997.Harry M. Kraemer Jr., the chief financial officer of Baxter, said it would take on debt to buy Immuno in two steps -- 70 percent by Dec. 31, and the rest in three years. Baxter has cut its debt ratio to 35 percent of capital in the last two years. Mr. Kraemer said that Baxter did not expect its debt ratings to be significantly changed.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/15/business/judge-approves-aids-settlement.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Judge Approves AIDS Settlement<date>Published: August 15, 1996</date><text>Federal District Judge John Grady gave preliminary approval today to a $640 million settlement of claims against four drug companies accused of knowingly selling AIDS-tainted clotting products to hemophiliacs.People with hemophilia who are H.I.V.-infected from using blood-clotting products between 1979 and 1985, or their survivors, are to get roughly $100,000 each under the deal.The settlement calls for $600 million to be distributed to plaintiffs and $40 million to pay expenses and legal fees.Some hemophilia advocates say the offer is inadequate. The judge set a Nov. 25 hearing for testimony from those affected by the settlement.The four companies are Bayer A.G. of Germany; Baxter International Inc. of Deerfield, Ill.; the Armour Pharmaceuticals unit of Rhone-Poulenc of France, and the Alpha Therapeutic Corporation, a unit of the Green Cross Corporation of Japan.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/11/business/blood-money-aids-hemophiliacs-are-split-liability-cases-bogged-down-disputes.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Blood, Money and AIDS: Hemophiliacs Are Split;Liability Cases Bogged Down in Disputes<date>Published: June 11, 1996</date><text>Last December, Corey Dubin, a hemophiliac infected with the virus that causes AIDS, met for lunch at a Carrow's restaurant in Camarillo, Calif., with John Bacich, the president of a Baxter International Inc. unit that makes blood-clotting products.Mr. Dubin, like an estimated 6,000 to 10,000 hemophiliacs nationwide, became infected with H.I.V. after receiving a tainted clotting substance made by Baxter and three other companies in the late 1970's and early 1980's. Hundreds of victims had sued. But statutes of limitations prevented thousands more from bringing claims. Mr. Dubin however had not come to lunch to pick a fight. Rather, dissatisfied with the way key plaintiffs' lawyers were handling the litigation, he was on a stealth mission to negotiate, for all those infected, a settlement with the four companies without the knowledge of key plaintiffs' lawyers.I told him they were going to have to live with us as customers when all the high-powered litigators were gone," said Mr. Dubin, a 41-year-old former journalist from Goleta, Calif., recalling the lunchtime conversation with Mr. Bacich. "If you buy a Pinto from Ford that blows up, you can tell Ford to go to hell. But I don't have that luxury."In many cases of mass litigation, corporations are able to buy themselves settlements that enrich lawyers but leave the victims -- faceless names on the cover sheets of legal documents -- with a pittance. In the hemophilia litigation, some claimants jumped off the page to try to influence the outcome of an emotionally charged dispute.The result of their revolt was a legal free-for-all for plaintiffs, lawyers and companies alike. United by their disease, hemophiliacs were divided between activists seeking to squeeze the maximum settlement out of the drug makers and others willing to accept less money so that the sickest among them, dying at the rate of one a day, could get some cash. Some actors included Mr. Dubin, president of the Committee of Ten Thousand, an activist group; Jonathan Wadleigh, the committee's founder; Robert Baldwin, who gained prominence as a counselor for hemophiliacs, and David Shrager, a plaintiffs' lawyer who guided the case until the activists challenged him.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/06/business/company-news-baxter-to-call-spinoff-allegiance-healthcare.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS;BAXTER TO CALL SPINOFF ALLEGIANCE HEALTHCARE<date>Published: June 06, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that it would call its health care products and cost-management services business, which it plans to spin off later this year, the Allegiance Healthcare Corporation. In November, Baxter announced plans to split into two publicly traded companies, separating the medical supply and services business from its medical technology group. The medical technology business, which makes drugs and devices to treat hemophilia, kidney and heart disease, plans to retain the name Baxter. The Allegiance unit had sales of $4.5 billion in 1995 and employs about 20,000 people worldwide.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/30/us/drug-companies-take-step-toward-settling-hemophiliacs-aids-lawsuits.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Drug Companies Take Step Toward Settling Hemophiliacs' AIDS Lawsuits<date>Published: May 30, 1996</date><text>Four drug companies that sold hemophiliacs blood-clotting products tainted with the virus that causes AIDS have modified the terms of their $640 million offer to settle litigation with the estimated 6,000 people who were infected with the virus as a result.Earlier this month a settlement offer by the companies was rejected by the plaintiffs because it was conditioned on no more than 100 of them rejecting the offer and pursuing their lawsuits.Yesterday the four companies said they would place no hard limit on how many people could opt out of the settlement and promised not to withdraw their offer if 150 or fewer people reject the settlement.David S. Schrager, a lawyer in Philadelphia who represents hemophiliacs in about 500 lawsuits, said the offer was a significant move toward settlement."At the end of the day the community has to decide if they want to put this behind them," Mr. Schrager said. "Everyone knows that the amount is insignificant compared to the size of the tragedy, but this proposal removes a significant obstacle."The companies proposing the settlement are Rhone-Poulenc Rorer, a unit of Rhone-Poulenc S.A. of France, Baxter International Inc., Bayer A.G. of Germany and the Alpha Therapeutic Corporation, a unit of the Green Cross Corporation of Japan.In a letter to Mr. Schrager, lawyers for the companies said that they expected each of the 6,000 infected persons, or their estates, would receive $100,000 and that legal and administrative costs would total $40 million. The 6,000 are eligible for the settlement regardless of whether they filed a lawsuit."We want to settle this as quickly as possible," said Guy Esnouf, a spokesman for the four companies.The hemophiliacs' anger at the four companies has been fueled by documents indicating that the companies did not respond quickly as the first signs of the illness now known as AIDS emerged in the late 1970's.Army physicians concluded during World War II that hepatitis was spread through plasma made from the blood of many donors and that the risk of infection rose sharply when as few as several dozen donors were in a pool. By heating plasma the hepatitis virus could be inactivated or killed, Army doctors learned in the late 1940's.The blood clotting product, known as Factor 8, is obtained from mixing the blood of thousands of donors, Mr. Esnouf said. Initially, he said, heating was rejected because it would damage the delicate clotting proteins.In the early 1980's, however, a heat treatment to kill human immunodeficiency virus, or H.I.V., which causes AIDS, was developed in Germany. The American companies started heat treating after the marketing department for one of them, in a memo disclosed through the lawsuits, said that adopting this heating technique was critical if sales volumes were to be maintained. Within a few months heat treating was the standard in the United States.The plaintiffs say the companies knew, or should have known, that Factor 8 was tainted and should have used heat treatment earlier.Mr. Esnouf said the companies followed the best scientific advice at the time. He noted that in 13 trials juries found no fault by the companies in 11 cases. In two cases juries ruled against the companies, but a judge threw out one verdict and the other was overturned on appeal. The hemophiliacs in those 13 cases are the only ones not eligible for the settlement proposed yesterday, Mr. Esnouf said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/14/business/hemophiliacs-with-hiv-reject-an-offer.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Hemophiliacs With H.I.V. Reject an Offer<date>Published: May 14, 1996</date><text>Leaders of H.I.V.-infected hemophiliacs rejected a $640 million settlement offer from four major drug companies during talks today, a lawyer for the hemophiliacs said.The offer would have provided payments of roughly $100,000 each to thousands of hemophiliacs who contracted H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, by injecting tainted blood-clotting products in the early 1980's.The proposal, for $600 million in settlements and $40 million in legal costs, would have been one of the largest product-liability payouts in history.Hemophiliacs have contended that the defendants -- Bayer A.G.; Baxter International Inc.; Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc., and Alpha Therapeutic Inc., a unit of the Green Cross Corporation -- put profits ahead of safety by knowingly selling H.I.V.-infected clotting products made from donated blood. The companies have denied that they intentionally put people at risk."Although the proposal could not be accepted, there was a candid and cordial exchange of views, and I anticipate there will be further discussions," said David Shrager, a lawyer who represented hundreds of hemophiliacs in Federal courts.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/25/business/baxter-international-s-profit-climbed-9-in-first-quarter.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter International's Profit Climbed 9% in First Quarter<date>Published: April 25, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc. reported yesterday that its first-quarter profits rose 9 percent amid strong foreign and domestic sales in its cardiovascular and biotechnology businesses.Meanwhile, the French-controlled drug maker Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc. said that takeover costs cut profits by 8 percent in the quarter, and the Swiss-owned Roche Holding Ltd. reported that its 1995 profits rose 18 percent.Baxter's net income rose to $158 million, or 58 cents a share, from $145 million, or 52 cents a share, in the corresponding quarter last year.The 1996 results include Baxter's health-cost management and hospital instrument manufacturing operations, which it expects to spin off by the end of the year. Without those businesses, net income rose 41 percent, to $138 million.Sales rose 12 percent, to $1.3 billion, from $1.16 billion a year ago.The earnings were in line with analysts' expectations. Baxter shares fell 25 cents yesterday, to $43.125.Earnings were lifted by Food and Drug Administration approval to market a new heart valve and increased sales of Recombinate AHF, a genetically engineered blood-clotting agent for hemophiliacs, said Vernon R. Loucks Jr., chairman and chief executive of Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill.Rhone-Poulenc Rorer, a unit of Rhone-Poulenc S.A. that is based in Collegeville, Pa., said that debt needed to complete the $2.9 billion takeover last year of Britain's Fisons P.L.C. cut its profits to $85 million, or 55 cents a share, from $91.9 million, or 64 cents, a year earlier.Guy Esnouf, a company spokesman, said the purchase last year of Applied Immune Sciences, a biotechnology company in Santa Clara, Calif., also diluted earnings because Applied was not yet profitable.Rhone-Poulenc Rorer has said it plans to cut 2,900 jobs, or 10 percent of its work force, during the next two years in cost-cutting prompted by the Fisons purchase.First-quarter sales rose 28 percent, to $1.27 billion, compared with $992 million in the first quarter of 1995. The increase partly reflects the additional sales of the newly acquired companies.Roche, based in Basel, Switzerland, said it earned 3.37 billion Swiss francs, or $2.74 billion, in 1995, compared with 2.86 billion Swiss francs in 1994. The result was slightly below analysts' predictions.Sales declined slightly, to 14.72 billion Swiss francs, or $12.0 billion, compared with 14.75 billion Swiss francs in 1994. Roche was hurt by the strength of the Swiss franc.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/19/business/offer-to-hemophiliacs-with-hiv-is-set.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Offer to Hemophiliacs With H.I.V. Is Set<date>Published: April 19, 1996</date><text>Four producers of blood-clotting products that are said to have infected thousands of hemophiliacs in the United States with the virus that causes AIDS said yesterday that they planned to offer $600 million to affected individuals and their families in a bid to resolve litigation against the companies.The companies, Bayer A.G. of Germany; Baxter International Inc.; Rhone-Poulenc Rorer Inc., a unit of Rhone-Poulenc S.A. of France, and the Alpha Therapeutic Corporation, a unit of the Green Cross Corporation of Japan, plan to approach lawyers for the plaintiffs today with the proposed settlement, which would include an additional $40 million to cover legal fees and administrative costs, said Thomas E. Kerr, assistant general counsel of Bayer.We believe that it is time to put an end to this protracted litigation and to make payments to persons who have been victims of this tragedy," Mr. Kerr said. In making the offer, the companies denied any liability.The proposal drew a mixed reaction. One member of Congress applauded it, but some hemophiliacs dismissed it as inadequate.Federal authorities have estimated that about half the hemophiliacs in this country, or about 8,000 people, were infected in the 1980's with the human immunodeficiency virus, which leads to AIDS, through contaminated blood-clotting substances known as Factor VIII and Factor IX. The clotting substances were derived from the blood of hundreds of donors and then concentrated to treat hemophilia.Hemophiliacs and their lawyers have charged that the companies were negligent in making the products; the companies deny that. Lawsuits against the producers have been largely unsuccessful because blood is not legally considered to be a product. As a result, manufacturers are shielded from certain types of liability claims.Under the companies' offer, settlement funds would be available to hemophiliacs who became infected with H.I.V. after they received a blood-clotting substance, Mr. Kerr said. Spouses and children who became infected as a result of contact with such a person would also qualify, as would the estates of hemophiliacs who died from such infections, he added.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/14/world/world-news-briefs-settlement-is-reported-on-aids-virus-in-japan.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">WORLD NEWS BRIEFS;Settlement Is Reported On AIDS Virus in Japan<date>Published: March 14, 1996</date><text>The Health and Welfare Ministry and five drug companies have agreed to a court-proposed settlement of suits brought by Japanese who contracted the AIDS virus from contaminated blood products, ministry officials said today.The lawsuits were brought in 1989 by about 400 infected hemophiliacs who claimed the Government continued to allow use of unheated blood products in Japan after it knew that heat treatment killed the AIDS virus.Last month the Health Minister, Naoto Kan, acknowledged Government responsibility. Details of the settlement are to be announced on Friday.One company, Baxter International, of Deerfield, Ill., announced late Wednesday that it had accepted the terms of the settlement, which includes a one-time payment of about $426,000 to each claimant, with monthly payments for life. The Government is to bear 44 percent of the cost and the companies 56 percent, Baxter said.The other companies are Bayer A.G.'s Japanese subsidiary, Bayer Yakuhin Ltd.; the Green Cross Corporation, the Chemo Sero Therapeutic Research Institute and the Nippon Zoki Pharmaceutical Company.Of an estimated 4,500 hemophiliacs in Japan, about 2,000 contracted H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, in the early 1980's from unheated imported blood products, mainly from the United States. Nearly half the plaintiffs in the suit have died.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/05/business/company-news-baxter-and-inhale-therapeutic-systems-in-venture.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS;BAXTER AND INHALE THERAPEUTIC SYSTEMS IN VENTURE<date>Published: March 05, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc. will invest about $80 million in Inhale Therapeutic Systems as part of a drug collaboration between the two companies, Inhale Therapeutic said yesterday. Baxter will initially acquire about 12 percent of Inhale's stock for $20 million, said Robert B. Chess, chief executive of Inhale. Baxter will then provide another $60 million in research financing and milestone payments. It has options to invest an additional $55 million in the company. Shares of Inhale Therapeutic soared $4.50, or 37 percent, to $16.75, yesterday, and shares of Baxter rose $1.125, to $47.125. The pair will initially use Inhale's dry-powder inhaler technology to develop four drugs.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/23/business/company-news-baxter-withdraws-bid-for-national-medical.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS;BAXTER WITHDRAWS BID FOR NATIONAL MEDICAL<date>Published: February 23, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that it was withdrawing its $3.8 billion offer to acquire the National Medical Care unit of W. R. Grace &amp; Company. Grace had recently agreed to merge National Medical Care, a kidney dialysis services business, with Fresenius A.G. of Germany. Baxter disclosed that it was giving up its bid in a letter to Grace's chief executive, Albert J. Costello. In the letter, Baxter's chief executive, Vernon R. Loucks Jr., said, "We firmly believe that our proposal is clearly more favorable." The bid was withdrawn after Grace's stock rose $1.25, to $68.625, on the New York Stock Exchange. A Grace spokesman was not immediately available for comment.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/07/business/company-reports-baxter-international-baxn.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY REPORTS;BAXTER INTERNATIONAL (BAX,N)<date>Published: February 07, 1996</date><text>Baxter International Inc.'s earnings were stronger than expected in the fourth quarter, benefiting from its medical technology businesses.The nation's largest maker of health care products said profit from continuing operations was $148 million, or 54 cents a share, up 11 percent from the year earlier.The company also had profit from discontinued operations of $54 million, and a charge of $26 million for the spinoff of its health care cost-management operations. Net income was $176 million, or 65 cents a share.That exceeded the earnings estimate of 66 cents a share of operating and discontinued earnings by 10 analysts surveyed by Zacks Investment Research -- compared with the 74 cents a share reported by Baxter.Sales from continuing operations rose 9 percent, to $1.35 billion from $1.24 billion, with double-digit growth in biotechnology and cardiovascular operations.Baxter stock rose $1.375, to $42.375 yesterday, regaining ground it lost on Monday, on the New York Stock Exchange.Harry Kraemer, Baxter's chief financial officer, said the company does not plan to increase its $3.8 billion offer for W. R. Grace &amp; Co.'s National Medical Care Inc. unit. Grace has embraced a counterproposal by Germany's Fresenius A.G., which analysts valued at $4 billion.Mr. Kraemer said that Baxter's bid was clearly better than Fresenius's and called on Grace shareholders to pressure their board into negotiating with Baxter. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/06/business/company-reports-investors-betting-on-baxter-to-sweeten-its-bid-for-grace.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY REPORTS;Investors Betting on Baxter To Sweeten Its Bid for Grace<date>Published: February 06, 1996</date><text>Betting that Baxter International would raise its $3.8 billion bid for the big kidney dialysis unit of W.R. Grace &amp; Company, Wall Street traders pushed up the price of Grace shares again yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, while Baxter shares again declined on the Big Board.But Harry Kraemer, chief financial officer for Baxter, said in an interview last night, "We will not increase our bid because we believe our offer is clearly superior" to the "definitive agreement" it announced Sunday, which would merge its dialysis business with an offshoot of Fresenius A.G. of Germany, a Baxter rival.Grace, which had rejected the Baxter bid last Friday, vigorously disagreed.That deal provides "more certainty, more cash and more upside for the shareholder," Peter Houchin, chief financial officer of Grace, said in an interview. The shareholders would have to approve any deal.Shares of Grace rose 62.5 cents, to $69.875 yesterday, an $8 gain over Friday's opening price before Baxter announced its bid. Baxter shares slid $1.50, to $41, after declining $2.50 on Friday. Shares of Fresenius were up 7.8 percent, or about 12 German marks yesterday, to about 168 marks on the Frankfurt Stock Exchange."We are in the second inning of the negotiations," said Kenneth S. Abramowitz, a health care analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, noting that Baxter has said that all aspects of its offer are open to negotiation.Mr. Kraemer of Baxter said the company would discuss its strategy with analysts today. The company had already scheduled a conference call to report its fourth-quarter earnings, which Mr. Kraemer said were "on target."The precise value of the complicated merger deal was unclear. Securities analysts and people with inside knowledge of the bidding gave estimates that ranged from $3.8 billion to $4.2 billion.Mr. Kraemer denigrated the Fresenius deal, saying that its value was "anybody's guess" because Grace shareholders would be getting "a minority interest in a German company."</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/05/business/german-merger-for-grace-s-dialysis-unit.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">German Merger for Grace's Dialysis Unit<date>Published: February 05, 1996</date><text>W. R. Grace &amp; Company said yesterday that it had agreed to spin off National Medical Care, its nationwide chain of kidney-dialysis centers, into a new company that would be controlled by Fresenius A.G., a big German medical-technology company.The tax-free transaction would yield $2.3 billion for Grace as well as stock in the new venture for its shareholders, Grace said.The two companies did not put a monetary value on the deal, but an investment banker valued National Medical at about $4 billion. Grace stockholders are to receive 44.8 percent of the new company, to be called Fresenius Medical Care.On Friday, Grace, a chemicals-based conglomerate, rejected a $3.8 billion bid for National Medical by Baxter International. At the time, it indicated that it was considering other offers, and Albert J. Costello, the chief executive, said he would disclose those plans by today.In a statement on the deal released yesterday, Mr. Costello said: "The combination of these two leaders will provide significant and immediate value for Grace shareholders. It provides more cash to Grace and more potential to our shareholders than any other alternative considered by Grace and its advisers, and it is all on a tax-free basis."Each Grace shareholder is to receive one American depository receipt in the new company. Grace and Fresenius, which is based in Bad Homburg, Germany, said that the new company would be the largest dialysis provider in the world.Baxter said last night that it believed its offer provided more value to Grace shareholders.The deal will presumably end years of expensive and often fruitless forays by Grace into businesses far afield from its basic chemicals operations, including sporting goods, restaurants and even the marketing of bull semen.Grace's dialysis business, however, was one of its financially successful operations, contributing $2.1 billion in revenue last year to overall sales of $5.8 billion.Under the plan, Grace will receive a tax-free distribution of $2.3 billion from National Medical Care, which will raise the money through bank borrowing, a Grace spokesman said.The A.D.R.'s are to trade on the New York Stock Exchange, Grace said; starting next year, each is expected to pay an annual dividend of 25 cents.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/03/business/grace-spurns-baxter-s-3.8-billion-dialysis-chain-bid.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Grace Spurns Baxter's $3.8 Billion Dialysis-Chain Bid<date>Published: February 03, 1996</date><text>Hinting that it was considering more lucrative offers, W. R. Grace &amp; Company yesterday brushed aside a $3.8 billion bid by Baxter International for National Medical Care, Grace's big chain of kidney dialysis centers. Albert J. Costello, chief executive of Grace, said he would disclose "our plans" on Monday."Baxter, a health care products manufacturer, made public its offer of cash, stock and assumed debt yesterday and said it "would be willing to negotiate all aspects of its proposal" with Grace, which is based in Boca Raton, Fla.Investors, hoping for a bidding war, drove Grace shares up $7.375, to $69.25, on the New York Stock Exchange. Baxter shares dropped $2.50, to $42.50 on the Big Board.Baxter, which had $1.3 billion in sales of kidney-therapy products last year, "is the best and most logical acquirer," said Vernon R. Loucks Jr., chief executive of Baxter, which is based in Deerfield, Ill. National Medical Care's sales were $2.1 billion in 1995.Evidently annoyed at Baxter's actions, Mr. Costello said: "Baxter chose not to participate in the orderly sale process we established. They determined instead to act unilaterally."Mr. Costello said Grace and its advisers "have been developing other alternatives" for National Medical. Two European manufacturers of kidney-dialysis equipment -- Gambro A.B., a Swedish multinational company controlled by the Wallenberg family, and Fresenius A.G. of Germany -- have been mentioned in news reports, but Grace has never confirmed holding talks with them.Mr. Loucks of Baxter said in an interview that he had held "many" talks with Mr. Costello, but "every time we get to sitting down negotiating, something stops it.""We would very much to sit down with them," he added, "but so far they have been unwilling to negotiate anything."Baxter believes it could attract 11,000 of National Medical's 46,000 kidney patients to its highly profitable system of portable and home dialysis products, which take over blood-cleansing functions from failed kidneys. Most National Medical patients are currently treated with machines in the company's 549 clinics across the country and 75 overseas.Acquiring National Medical would dilute Baxter earnings by 5 percent the first year and add to earnings after 18 months, Mr. Loucks said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/28/business/judge-approves-implant-accord.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Judge Approves Implant Accord<date>Published: December 28, 1995</date><text>A Federal judge has approved a scaled-back settlement between three makers of silicone breast implants and implant recipients, removing another hurdle for women awaiting money for health-related claims.The decision by Federal District Judge Sam C. Pointer, released Friday, clears the way for women to begin receiving forms next month to accept or reject the deal. Payments are expected to begin in 1996.The ruling was viewed as little more than a formality because Judge Pointer participated in talks that resulted in the offer to the women from the three companies: the Bristol-Myers Squibb Company, Baxter International Inc. and the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company.The agreement provides less money to women and involves far fewer implant recipients than the $4.25 billion settlement it replaced. That compromise collapsed because of the unexpectedly large number of women who sought money.About 220,000 women are expected to be eligible for the new settlement. Benefits will range from $10,000 to $250,000.Manufacturers deny that breast implants have resulted in injuries.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/29/business/baxter-plans-to-split-into-2-companies.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">Baxter Plans To Split Into 2 Companies<date>Published: November 29, 1995</date><text>Reacting to gnawing uncertainty in the hospital market, Baxter International Inc., the big, diversified health care company, announced yesterday that it would spin off its slow-growth hospital-supply business as a new company next year.In the split-up, Baxter would retain its highly profitable international and technology-related lines, which range from intravenous solutions to kidney-dialysis therapy. Vernon R. Loucks Jr. would remain its chairman and chief executive.Shares of Baxter, based in Deerfield, Ill., rose on the news, The stock, which had climbed 60 percent in the last 12 months, added $2.875 yesterday, closing at $41.375 on the New York Stock Exchange. But some analysts viewed the company's prospects with caution.The stock price is a matter of great concern for 63 Baxter executives, who have $200 million in the company's shares, about half of which is financed by personal loans guaranteed by Baxter."Their anxiety level was rising," said Kenneth S. Abramowitz, an analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company. "They saw the stock price stalling out. This is an inducement to start it going up again."Margo Vignola, an analyst with Merrill Lynch, said Baxter's medical-technology lines were "growing at a much faster clip, but the stock valuation never reflected it." She added, though, that yesterday's stock price appeared to fully reflect the extra value that the split-up would add.The slimmed-down Baxter and the new company, which has not yet been named, would each have about $5 billion in annual sales. Baxter said the split would make it easier for both companies to run their different businesses and to expand.Baxter's split-up would continue a trend among big, diversified companies, following the examples of the AT&amp;T Corporation, the ITT Corporation, and, in health care, Humana Inc., which sold its hospital chain.Analysts noted that Baxter was turning loose part of the American Hospital Supply Company, for which it borrowed heavily to buy at a price of $3.8 billion in 1985.Baxter would also maintain liability for judgments resulting from lawsuits over breast implants made by an American Hospital Supply unit, and suits involving deaths in the 1980's that plaintiffs say were linked to Baxter blood products. The company said it had insurance and reserves of more than $900 million for such claims.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/15/business/company-news-baxter-international-plans-500-million-buyback.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS;BAXTER INTERNATIONAL PLANS $500 MILLION BUYBACK<date>Published: November 15, 1995</date><text>Baxter International Inc., the provider of medical supplies, said yesterday that it planned to buy back up to $500 million worth of common shares in the next several years. The company, which is based in Deefield, Ill., has about 272 million shares outstanding. The stock closed yesterday at $38.625, up 12.5 cents, on the New York Stock Exchange. The company also said William B. Graham had retired as senior chairman and had resigned from the board, effective on Nov. 25. Mr. Graham, who is 84, joined Baxter in 1945 and was chief executive from 1953 to 1980. He had been senior chairman since 1985.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/16/business/company-news-baxter-international-completes-stock-buyback.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">COMPANY NEWS; BAXTER INTERNATIONAL COMPLETES STOCK BUYBACK<date>Published: September 16, 1995</date><text>Baxter International Inc. said yesterday that it had completed a $500 million stock buyback announced in February. Baxter, a medical products maker based in Deerfield, Ill., said it was able to complete the share repurchase ahead of schedule because of the company's financial performance and the sale of its Industrial and Life Sciences unit. Baxter announced yesterday that the sale of the unit to the VWR Corporation for $400 million had been completed. The acquisition was announced on May 25. In addition, Baxter said its board had approved plans for a $100 million plant in Europe to make its blood substitute, Diaspirin Cross-linked Hemoglobin.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/13/business/a-new-chairman-for-perkin-elmer.html?ref=baxterinternationalinc">A New Chairman For Perkin-Elmer<date>Published: September 13, 1995</date><text>The Perkin-Elmer Corporation said today that it had hired Tony L. White, a top official at Baxter International Inc., to serve as chairman, president and chief executive.He replaces the retiring chairman and chief executive, Gaynor Kelley, who will remain as a director and chairman of the board's executive committee.Mr. White, who was an executive vice president at Baxter, was part of a four-person team responsible for the company's financial turnaround last year. "He's a down-to-earth, no-nonsense manager," said Kenneth S. Abramowitz, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.Perkin-Elmer, based here, has been struggling with declining sales in its analytical instruments business. The company has cut jobs and closed a plant in Puerto Rico in an attempt to cut expenses.</text></article></page></root>
