<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Capital One Financial Corp"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/20/occupywallst-roundup-day-34/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">#OccupyWallSt Roundup, Day 34<date>October 20, 2011, 2:33 pm</date><text>wearechange via Youtube Alec Baldwin speaking truth to the power of the Fed, among other things. Protesters are gearing up as the weekend approaches — and taking in a little culture. An Occupy Wall Street-endorsed group, Occupy Museums, plans to occupy the Museum of Modern Art, the Frick and the New Museum beginning at 3 p.m. Thursday. [Paddy Johnson] #OccupyWallSt Roundup Meanwhile, a sociologist at the Baruch School of Public Affairs released a demographic study of visitors to occupywallst.org, showing that the movement is not all unemployed kids with bongos. [Fast Company] Occupy Wall Street raised enough money on the ad-financing platform LoudSauce to make a commercial. [The Observer] To help readers understand exactly what percent they belong to, The Wall Street Journal created a Percent Calculator and in a separate post, wondered why there was no protest in Stamford, Conn., home to banking giants like as UBS. [Wall Street Journal] The actor and political somethingorother Alec Baldwin took heat on Twitter after a video circulated showing him defending some aspects of capital markets in Zuccotti Park. Baldwin responded to criticism of his role as a Capital One spokesman on Twitter: @NYCDarkness @torianbrown I donated all of my fee from Capital One 2 arts charities. They have been gr8 partners in my support of the arts.Wed Oct 19 06:09:26 via Twitter for iPhoneAlec Baldwin AlecBaldwin The collective library at Occupy Wall Street doesn’t use the Dewey Decimal System, but it does have a blog, YouTube channel, a Facebook page, and a Twitter feed. A reporter for Mother Jones magazine found a number of New York City police officers who expressed sympathy with Occupy Wall Street. [Mother Jones] More celebrity sightings: the comedian Russell Brand visited Occupy Wall Street. [Daily Mail] Not to be outdone by Hot Chicks of Occupy Wall Street, now come the Dogs of Occupy Wall Street. [Buzzfeed] And cue the scary movies and sugary snacks: Parents for Occupy Wall Street are organizing another family sleepover Friday night at Zuccotti Park. [Parents for Occupy Wall Street] Have tips or links? Send them to owsroundup@gmail.com.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/10/05/assailed-for-subprime-loans-capital-one-defends-ing-deal/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Assailed for Subprime Loans, Capital One Defends ING Deal<date>October 5, 2011, 2:22 pm</date><text>Paul Sakuma/Associated PressWhat’s in your wallet? Subprime lender or benevolent bank? The two contrasting images of Capital One vied for attention on Wednesday at a hearing in San Francisco before the Federal Reserve, which is examining the bank’s proposed $9 billion takeover of ING Direct USA. To hear many consumer advocates tell it, Capital One is an aggressive credit card company that preys on low-income borrowers. And if Capital One takes over ING’s online banking unit in the United States, critics say, the combined banks will pose a systemic risk to the economy. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Capital One Says ING Direct Deal Will Create Jobs (Sept. 27, 2011) Capital One Denies ING Deal Would Make It ‘Too Big to Fail’ (Sept. 20, 2011) “Is the Federal Reserve really prepared to turn a blind eye again and watch a new subprime crisis unfold?” Ed Gorman, chief membership officer at the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, said in written testimony to the Fed, which hosted the third and final public hearing to scrutinize the deal. “Capital One’s risky and subprime credit cards generate stellar earnings three times the size of their asset base through predatory interest rates, questionable fees and confusing terms.” That is not the case, Capital One’s lawyers say. “Our products are the most customer-friendly and transparent in the industry,” John Finneran, Capital One’s general counsel, told the Fed. “Given the size of this market, responsible lending to these borrowers is not only acceptable, but also provides a source of credit and purchasing power for these customers, and is thus necessary to the functioning of our economy.” Still, Mr. Finneran acknowledged that about a third of Capital One’s credit card portfolio carries the subprime label, defined as loans to borrowers with credit scores below 660. The bank also has a heavy hand in the subprime car loan business. In June, Capital One announced plans to acquire ING Direct USA for $6.2 billion in cash. Under the terms of the deal, Capital One would also issue $2.8 billion worth of new shares to ING, giving the Dutch firm a 9.9 percent stake. The deal would make Capital One the fifth-biggest bank in the United States, up from its current No. 8 spot. The jump, critics warn, comes with plenty of risk. Capital One has received a steady barrage of complaints from consumer groups and smaller banks, which warn that the takeover would create another “too big to fail” financial giant. Under the Dodd-Frank financial regulatory overhaul, the Fed must examine whether major bank mergers would endanger the economy. When the risks outweigh the rewards, the Fed must block the deal. Unlike past hearings, when Fed officials were mostly mum on the ING Direct deal, some regulators on Wednesday seized on questions surrounding Capital One’s subprime loan business. One Fed official asked whether Capital One’s $2.6 billion bid for HSBC’s American credit card business would deepen the bank’s entrenchment in the subprime market. “It won’t change the overall proportions in a significant way in either direction,” Mr. Finneran said. Some consumer groups think otherwise. “The subprime number will only get bigger,” said Mr. Gorman of the National Community Reinvestment Coalition. With the hearings wrapping up on Wednesday, the fate of the ING Direct deal is now in the Fed’s hands. Capital One likes its chances. “The Federal Reserve has all the data regarding the scope and performance of our businesses and can distinguish between grounded facts and unfounded hyperbole,” Mr. Finneran said. “We have full confidence in the Federal Reserve’s ability to reach the appropriate conclusion.”</text></article><article index="3" href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/01/3-questions-on-financial-stability/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">3 Questions on Financial Stability<date>September 1, 2011, 5:00 am</date><text>Simon Johnson, the former chief economist at the International Monetary Fund, is the co-author of “13 Bankers.” The Dodd-Frank financial legislation of 2010 created a Financial Stability Oversight Council, tasked with taking an integrated view of risks in and around the financial sector in the United States. Known as the FSoc (pronounced EFF-sock), the council comprises all leading regulators and other responsible officials, headed by the Treasury secretary. So far, it has done little — reflecting the predominant official view that in the post-crisis recovery phase, financial risks in the United States are generally receding. Today’s Economist Perspectives from expert contributors. But three important and related issues emerged this summer that the FSoc needs to consider quickly: impending bank mergers that could create two more too-big-to-fail banks; whether to force the breakup of Bank of America; and how to rethink capital requirements for large systemically important banks, particularly as continuing European sovereign debt problems undermine the credibility of the international Basel Committee approach to bank capital. On the merger front, Capital One plans to buy the online business of ING, and PNC is acquiring the American business of Royal Bank of Canada. Both acquisitions would create banks with assets around $300 billion. (Steven Pearlstein had a very good column in The Washington Post on Sunday on the background to these deals.) In some official minds, Dodd-Frank has made it impossible for too-big-to-fail banks to exist — if any such bank got into trouble, it would be shut down without any significant costs being incurred by taxpayers. Most independent analysts and many people active in financial markets regard this proposition as unproven at best and, most likely, incorrect. For example, in a new working paper, “Too-Systemic-to-Fail: What Option Markets Imply About Sector-Wide Government Guarantees,” Bryan T. Kelly, Hanno Lustig and Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh compare the price of put options (i.e., the option to sell and therefore lock in a price) for the financial sector stock index relative to put options on individual banks’ stocks (Disclosure: I’m a research associate at the National Bureau of Economic Research, which published this paper, and co-director of its Africa Project but had nothing to do with this paper). Put options are cheaper if they are less valuable to investors as protection against price collapses, and the index puts are a lot cheaper than the appropriately weighted sum of put options on individual bank stocks, particularly during the recent financial crisis. The authors infer that “investors price in substantial government bailout guarantees for the financial sector as a whole” — thus the index puts are cheap, because you don’t need to insure privately against overall collapse — with around half of the market value of the financial sector during 2003-9 accounted for by collective bailout guarantees. No other sector in the United States economy gets anything like this kind of insurance. At the same time, the researchers point out that the government does not eliminate all idiosyncratic company-specific risk; this is why put options on individual companies stocks are relatively more valuable. In a sense this message is encouraging, because it suggests some specific companies can fail or otherwise go out of business. But presumably, at critical moments specific megabanks have a particular and complete kind of downside protection. It’s hard to envisage the potential failure of a $2 trillion bank like Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase or Bank of America without systemwide adverse consequences. The first question for the FSoc is therefore: Wouldn’t allowing mergers by Capital One and ING and by PNC and Royal Bank of Canada create financial companies whose potential risk is more likely to be systemic? The largest financial institution allowed to fail without a bailout since the collapse of Lehman Brothers was CIT Group, which had a balance sheet of around $80 billion. Perhaps Capital One and PNC are already too big to fail; PNC is No. 12 and Capital One is No. 13 on the official list of bank holding companies, ranked by assets as of June 30. We don’t know where the critical cutoff is — and perhaps more studies along the lines of the work by Professors Kelly, Lustig and Nieuwerburgh would be helpful, or the FSoc could find another way to make a reasonable and fact-based determination. But what really matters is what could happen in future systemic crises, and this is very hard to predict. So why not err on the side of caution and keep large banks from becoming bigger through merging? Or the FSoc could require these merging banks to demonstrate that they will generate social value commensurate with or in excess of the extra social risks that they are creating. The second question is closely related: Why not break up Bank of America? The Dodd-Frank legislative process ended up rejecting the idea that existing banks, as of 2010, should be broken up — as long as they continue to operate in a reasonable and sustainable fashion. But the legislative intent was also clear with regard to big banks that are in trouble: There should be preemptive action, either through pressing bank management or, if that doesn’t work, through regulator-imposed requirements. These requirements can include making the bank smaller, simpler and less systemic – in other words making sure that any kind of future “resolution” or “intervention” for that bank (both euphemisms for a form of bankruptcy) would not be a systemic event. If Bank of America were to fail today, it would create a systemic problem and presumably set off some sort of desperate policy reaction. The bank is the largest bank-holding company in the United States, with assets at the end of June of more than $2.26 trillion. If Bank of America is forced to divest various activities, like those it bought from Merrill Lynch, that would not eliminate systemic risk. But it would make this one troubled institution less central to the economy, and, if handled properly, less of a brake on economic recovery. This raises the third and arguably most important question: Why not increase capital requirements further for systemically important financial institutions? Warren Buffett’s agreement last week to invest in Bank of America has highlighted the lack of capital, at least at that one bank: It has too little equity relative to its debts, hence the need for Mr. Buffett. But Mr. Buffett, it now appears, is getting cumulative preferred stock — so he gets a guaranteed dividend before any common-stock holders get a return. This makes sense for him, without question. And his holding is loss-absorbing, in the sense that his equity would be wiped out before there was any question of defaulting on money owed to any creditors. This is presumably the best that Bank of America could do in terms of raising capital through the market. But it should not be enough from the perspective of FSoc, which is charged with overall responsibility for systemic risks. The Basel Committee on Banking Supervision has proposed a methodology for systemically important institutions, but it rests on a very weak analytical basis, as Americans for Financial Reform pointed out in a recent letter. The FSoc would be making a very bad mistake if it continued to follow the European lead that set the lowest common denominator at Basel. The evident capital problems of European banks, and the way this will slow growth, were flagged at the Jackson Hole, Wyo., meeting of policy makers last week by Christine Lagarde, the new managing director of the International Monetary Fund and, until recently, finance minister of France (see this assessment by Felix Salmon). The FSoc should listen to her warnings and think about what this means for American banks. If the Dodd-Frank legislation is to have lasting impact, the FSoc needs to establish itself as a meaningful overseer of systemic financial risks. It needs to meet and deliberate in an open and transparent manner. It should confront pressing questions of systemic risk head on, being clear about the analytical basis for its decisions. Business as usual is a recipe for disaster — in the United States, as in Europe.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/26/opinion/a-timely-bank-merger.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">A Timely Bank Merger<date>Published: August 25, 2011</date><text>To the Editor: Re “Questions on a Bank Merger” (editorial, Aug. 20), about Capital One’s proposed acquisition of ING Direct: We believe that your readers would benefit from knowing several key facts: We will remain a traditional bank with only 1.5 percent of deposits nationwide and none of the complexity that the Dodd-Frank reform bill addressed in ending “too big to fail.” The record includes scores of letters of support from not-for-profit groups. In every prior merger, we substantially increased community development lending and investments beyond that of the banks we acquired. We have not abandoned Federal Housing Administration lending. We addressed the sole issue the National Community Reinvestment Coalition raised by agreeing to accept applicants who meet lower minimum requirements. As we have historically avoided subprime mortgage lending, we will do so taking special care to ensure that these applicants have the proven ability to repay their loans. It is in their interest, and that of the taxpayers who pay for F.H.A. guarantees. Our history clearly demonstrates that our customers and communities will see numerous benefits from this acquisition. JOHN G. FINNERAN Jr. General Counsel and Corporate Secy. Capital One Financial Corporation Mclean, Va., Aug. 22, 2011To the Editor: Re “Questions on a Bank Merger” (editorial, Aug. 20), about Capital One’s proposed acquisition of ING Direct: We believe that your readers would benefit from knowing several key facts: We will remain a traditional bank with only 1.5 percent of deposits nationwide and none of the complexity that the Dodd-Frank reform bill addressed in ending “too big to fail.” The record includes scores of letters of support from not-for-profit groups. In every prior merger, we substantially increased community development lending and investments beyond that of the banks we acquired. We have not abandoned Federal Housing Administration lending. We addressed the sole issue the National Community Reinvestment Coalition raised by agreeing to accept applicants who meet lower minimum requirements. As we have historically avoided subprime mortgage lending, we will do so taking special care to ensure that these applicants have the proven ability to repay their loans. It is in their interest, and that of the taxpayers who pay for F.H.A. guarantees. Our history clearly demonstrates that our customers and communities will see numerous benefits from this acquisition. JOHN G. FINNERAN Jr. General Counsel and Corporate Secy. Capital One Financial Corporation Mclean, Va., Aug. 22, 2011</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/26/fed-to-hold-hearings-on-capital-ones-deal-for-ing-direct-usa/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Fed to Hold Hearings on Capital One's Deal for ING Direct USA<date>August 26, 2011, 5:29 pm</date><text>Andrew Harrer/Bloomberg NewsRepresentative Barney Frank, left, and the Fed chairman, Ben S. Bernanke in 2009. Mr. Frank asked the Fed to hold hearings on the deal for ING Direct USA. 6:27 p.m. | Updated with Capital One statement The Federal Reserve announced on Friday afternoon that it planned to hold hearings on Capital One Financial‘s proposed $9 billion takeover of the ING Group‘s online banking operations in America. The move follows concerns that the deal would create a new too-big-to-fail giant. By buying ING Direct USA, Capital One would become the nation’s fifth-biggest lender, with more than $200 billion in deposits. Earlier this month, Representative Barney Frank, Democrat of Massachusetts, asked the Fed to hold public hearings to gauge the deal’s potential effects on consumers and the public. “Care should be taken to thoroughly examine the impact of this purchase with respect to the consolidation of banking assets, the provision of credit by the resulting bank and compliance with the Community Reinvestment Act,” Mr. Frank wrote in a letter to the Fed chairman, Ben S. Bernanke. The Fed said that it planned to hold hearings in Washington, Chicago and San Francisco beginning Sept. 20. It will also extend the time that it will accept public comments on the deal until Oct. 12. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Federal Reserve press release Deal Professor: A Test of Dodd-Frank Several consumer groups, including the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, have already opposed the deal. Their argument is that Capital One — already considered a systemically important financial institution because it oversees more than $50 billion in deposits — would become an even bigger risk to taxpayers if it needed a bailout. Capital One has argued that unlike such institutions as Goldman Sachs, it does not engage in risky trading. Its core business is credit card lending, an operation that would benefit greatly from the deposits it would gain from ING Direct. The bank also contends that the ING deal would make it more stable, by reducing its reliance on short-term borrowing that could seize up in a financial crisis. “We will remain a traditional bank with only 1.5 percent of deposits nationwide and none of the complexity that the Dodd-Frank reform bill addressed in ending ‘too big to fail,’” Capital One said in a statement late on Friday. The firm added, “In each of our prior bank acquisitions, we have substantially increased our investments that serve lower-income communities, providing $2.2 billion over and above those predecessor banks in their footprints.” Capital One has said that it expects the deal to close by the end of the year.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/08/23/capital-ones-new-1-5-percent-cash-back-credit-card/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One's New 1.5 Percent Cash-Back Credit Card<date>August 23, 2011, 1:00 pm</date><text>Today, Capital One is introducing a new cash-back credit card that ultimately yields 1.5 percent in refunds on each purchase, as long as you’re patient. The Capital One Cash MasterCard works like so: You get 1 percent of your purchases back in the form of a cash refund. Then, on the anniversary of the date that you first activated your card, you get a 50 percent bonus on whatever you’ve already earned during the past year. For example, if you activate a new card on Oct. 1, 2011, and use it for $30,000 in purchases between then and Oct. 1, 2012, you’ll earn $300 during that year. Then, on Oct. 1, 2012, you’ll get another $150 added to your refund. You continue receiving the annual bonus on each anniversary. So where’s the fine print here? To be honest, I’m having trouble finding any other than the wait for that extra anniversary money. You can request the cash back whenever you like, even if you’ve earned only $1. You can get it in the form of a credit on your monthly bill or as a check. And you can ask the company to issue the refunds automatically, which eliminates the possibility that you will forget to request the money. There is no limit on how much you can earn. The rewards never expire. And there is no annual fee. Per usual, it’s a bad idea to run up debt on this or any credit card, since the value of the rewards is a tiny fraction of what you’ll pay in interest. Using reward cards drives up costs for merchants, who pass them along in the form of higher prices. Then again, if you sit out of the rewards game on principle, you’ll still pay those higher prices but not get any rewards. As always when a good deal like this comes around, you have to wonder whether the company will be able to sustain it. Charles Schwab introduced a 2 percent cash-back card a few years back, insisted that it knew what it was doing and then got out of the card business when it became clear that its projections were way off. Time will tell whether Capital One has it right. My primary credit card is still the Starwood Preferred Guest American Express, since I’m able to redeem the Starwood points I earn (one point per dollar spent) for Starwood hotel stays that yield a value per point of about 3 cents. That’s twice as much as the 1.5 pennies that Capital One customers will get for every dollar they spend on this new card. Still, I do carry a Capital One No Hassle Rewards cash-back Visa card for two reasons. First, I need a backup card for merchants that do not accept American Express. Plus, Capital One cards do not hit users with the outrageous fees that most other card companies do when a transaction originates outside of the United States. My No Hassle card yields just 1.25 percent cash back, so I plan to try to upgrade my current card to the new one. According to a Capital One spokeswoman, Sukhi Sahni, people like me can call the phone number on the back of our cards to make the request. How do you think this new card stacks up to the Visa and MasterCard cash-back competition?</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/23/in-feds-move-on-capital-one-deal-a-test-of-dodd-frank/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">In Fed's Move on Capital One Deal, a Test of Dodd-Frank<date>August 23, 2011, 8:02 pm</date><text>Harry Campbell Capital One is the latest bank accused of being “too big to fail.” A proposed $9.2 billion purchase of the online bank ING Direct would make Capital One the fifth-largest bank in the United States with more than $200 billion in deposits. But before this acquisition can be completed, it requires clearance from the Federal Reserve, Capital One’s chief regulator. The Dodd-Frank Act requires that the Federal Reserve weigh the systemic risk of the combined company. If the risk outweighs the benefits of the transaction, the deal must be blocked. The Fed has yet to decide what constitutes a systemically risky acquisition. So its decision on Capital One could have a broad impact on what Dodd-Frank means for the nation’s biggest banks. Community interest groups led by the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, which oppose the deal, say that Capital One is already classified under Dodd-Frank as systemically important since it has more than $50 billion in assets. Why should any such bank be allowed to get bigger? Deal Professor View all posts Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Moreover, Capital One is likely to use ING Direct’s deposits to finance its main business: credit card issuance. And Capital One is moving to expand significantly in this debt-driven consumer credit sector. Earlier this month, Capital One announced the acquisition of HSBC’s $30 billion credit card portfolio in the United States. After the HSBC deal, Capital One will remain the United State’s fifth-largest credit card issuer, but its market share will rise to about 9 percent from 7 percent. National Community suggests that this will result in ever more credit cards at high-interest rates being pushed to American consumers who presumably can’t fend for themselves. Because the Federal Reserve has yet to spell out its own “too big to fail” guidelines, Capital One has proposed its own test to the Fed. Capital One looks at bank size and its interconnectedness and importance to the financial system. Not surprisingly, Capital One fails to meet this criteria. The bank rightly notes that after the two acquisitions, it would still be a pipsqueak next to Bank of America, the largest United States bank with $2.26 trillion in assets. Capital One will have only a measly $300 billion or so. How could this increase systemic risk? Moreover, Capital One argues that it does not engage in the complex type of banking that a Goldman Sachs or Morgan Stanley does, like writing derivatives. Capital One is going to be a simple, deposit-taking institution that lends money primarily on credit cards. Some analysts have said that the ING Direct acquisition will make Capital One sounder because it will provide Capital One a more stable source of financing for its lending activities than borrowing in the short-term lending market. Who is right? Clarity, if not an answer, may have come inadvertently from National Community. The coalition argues that Capital One’s application to acquire ING Direct is suspect because Capital One refuses to lower its credit standards to extend Federal Housing Administration-insured loans to people with credit scores of 580. This is the lowest credit score allowed by the F.H.A. National Community contends that this is discriminatory against members of minority groups because they tend to have lower credit scores and have been hit harder by the financial crisis. Capital One has responded by agreeing to lower its credit score requirements by 2012. For National Community, this is not enough, because Capital One’s F.H.A. loan volume is relatively flat in growth. Capital One is now a bit player with less than 1 percent of the F.H.A. loan market. National Community wants the combined entity to make more of these loans, since they help people who could not otherwise afford a mortgage. So National Community is arguing that Capital One should take more risk when making home loans, but less risk in getting bigger and offering credit cards. Remember, the financial crisis was caused in significant part by excessive, and sometimes predatory, subprime lending. Capital One may not be predatory, but the borrowing National Community wants is lower down on the subprime scale and will create more risk. Perhaps National Community’s apparently contradictory position can be reconciled by saying that it is distinguishing between good debt to buy a home and bad debt in the form of consumer credit. The Capital One acquisition is thus really about what type of banking system we want. Do we want a large banking system that has a significant focus on consumer credit? Or do we want smaller banks focused on communities and mortgage lending? And do we want to steer our banks away from certain types of lending? Dodd-Frank left these questions unanswered. Congress was also unable to decide what it wanted from its banking system, so it kicked the can to the Fed. In truth, the ING Direct acquisition does not appear to increase Capital One’s systemic risk materially. Capital One will still be a relatively small bank. One could even argue that allowing this midsize bank to get a little bigger might create a real competitor to steal away assets and downsize the banks that are truly way too big, like Bank of America. And many argue that we need big banks in a $14 trillion economy. The real issue is their prudent operation. As for Capital One’s ability to issue yet more credit cards, this may be a problem, but the government is still grappling with the nation’s addiction to credit cards, as well as the real benefits in the form of credit this lending provides. This is why the Federal Reserve’s decision on what constitutes a systemically risky acquisition will be so important. Does it extend beyond the size of a bank and its interconnectedness to how the economy works? Because of this issue, Representative Barney Frank, the Massachusetts Democrat, has requested that the Federal Reserve hold public hearings on the matter. Whether or not a public hearing is necessary, the Federal Reserve should be particularly careful. It needs to put forth a definition that ensures that the banking system is adequately monitored under the current definition for systemic risk. The rules it makes for Capital One could govern the entire banking system going forward. For these rules will naturally extend to other Dodd-Frank provisions that allow the Fed to break up banks that pose a similar threat. But so far, the Federal Reserve has said almost nothing about how it will apply these rules. This is no way to run a banking system. Whether or not the Fed approves the Capital One/ING Direct transaction, it is time for the Fed to run public hearings on what exactly Dodd-Frank means for our banks and what we as a country want from them. It has been nearly three years since the banking system nearly collapsed, and we still have not confronted the real banking issues raised by the financial crisis. What type of banks do we really want and need? Steven M. Davidoff, writing as The Deal Professor, is a commentator for DealBook on the world of mergers and acquisitions.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/20/opinion/questions-on-the-merger-of-ing-direct-and-capital-one.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Questions on the Merger of ING Direct and Capital One<date>Published: August 19, 2011</date><text>Representative Barney Frank, a Democrat of Massachusetts, got it exactly right this week when he asked the Federal Reserve to do more than just rubber-stamp the proposed purchase of the online bank, ING Direct, by the Capital One Financial Corporation. Since that merger would create the fifth-largest bank in the United States, the Federal Reserve should make sure that the new entity is good for the banking sector generally and in full compliance with the Community Reinvestment Act, which requires banks to lend, invest and provide services in poor communities. A number of civil rights, consumer protection and housing advocacy groups have raised troubling questions about Capital One’s lending policies as they affect creditworthy, low-income minority families. The Department of Housing and Urban Development is currently investigating a formal complaint filed by the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, an advocacy group that focuses on community redevelopment issues. The complaint alleges that the company shuts out low-income borrowers by requiring higher credit scores than are necessary to meet the standards of the Federal Housing Administration, which insures mortgages mainly for low- and moderate-income families. The complaint also argues that the bank’s policy is racially discriminatory because it has a disparate impact on black and Hispanic borrowers. These issues should be fully aired before the Federal Reserve approves this proposed deal. Mr. Frank has asked the regulator to extend the public comment period on the transaction for at least 60 days instead of ending it on Monday, as was originally scheduled. Given what’s at stake, that’s a perfectly reasonable thing to do.Representative Barney Frank, a Democrat of Massachusetts, got it exactly right this week when he asked the Federal Reserve to do more than just rubber-stamp the proposed purchase of the online bank, ING Direct, by the Capital One Financial Corporation. Since that merger would create the fifth-largest bank in the United States, the Federal Reserve should make sure that the new entity is good for the banking sector generally and in full compliance with the Community Reinvestment Act, which requires banks to lend, invest and provide services in poor communities. A number of civil rights, consumer protection and housing advocacy groups have raised troubling questions about Capital One’s lending policies as they affect creditworthy, low-income minority families. The Department of Housing and Urban Development is currently investigating a formal complaint filed by the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, an advocacy group that focuses on community redevelopment issues. The complaint alleges that the company shuts out low-income borrowers by requiring higher credit scores than are necessary to meet the standards of the Federal Housing Administration, which insures mortgages mainly for low- and moderate-income families. The complaint also argues that the bank’s policy is racially discriminatory because it has a disparate impact on black and Hispanic borrowers. These issues should be fully aired before the Federal Reserve approves this proposed deal. Mr. Frank has asked the regulator to extend the public comment period on the transaction for at least 60 days instead of ending it on Monday, as was originally scheduled. Given what’s at stake, that’s a perfectly reasonable thing to do.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/18/frank-questions-capital-ones-deal-for-ing-online-bank/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Frank Questions Capital One's Deal For ING Online Bank<date>August 18, 2011, 3:23 pm</date><text>Representative Barney Frank has asked the Federal Reserve to deepen its review of Capital One Financial‘s proposed $9 billion acquisition of ING Direct USA. In a letter sent on Wednesday to Ben Bernanke, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, Mr. Frank, Democrat of Massachusetts, called on the Fed to hold public hearings to examine the possible deal’s impact on consumers and the economy. Mr. Frank also asked that the Fed grant the public at least two additional months to weigh in on the acquisition. The comment period is otherwise scheduled to end on Thursday. “This proposed purchase would create the fifth-largest bank in the United States,” said Mr. Frank, the top Democrat on the House committee that oversees the financial industry. “For this reason alone, care should be taken to thoroughly examine the impact of this purchase with respect to the consolidation of banking assets, the provision of credit by the resulting bank and compliance with the Community Reinvestment Act.” Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink The letter also raised questions about Capital One’s deal-making record, saying that consumer advocacy groups have issued concerns about its past acquisitions. The consumer groups also contend that the deal will create another behemoth bank that one day could need a government bailout. “We already have four too-big-to-fail banks, why make a fifth?” John Taylor, president of the National Community Reinvestment Coalition, said in a statement this month. A Capital One spokeswoman called the concerns “baseless.” The deal “further reduces, rather than increases, our overall risk profile,” said the spokeswoman, Tatiana Stead. Mr. Frank, however, said the concerns “merit an extension of the comment period in order to allow a thorough investigation and evaluation.” The Fed plans to respond to Mr. Frank’s letter, a spokeswoman said. Capital One, meanwhile, is eager to close the deal. In a letter this week to the Fed, the bank, based in Virginia, argued against an extension of the comment period, saying that the public has had “ample time” to express concerns. When the takeover was announced in June, Capital One said that the deal should be finalized by the end of 2011 or early next year. The deal requires Capital One, the eighth-biggest bank in the country by deposits, to buy ING Group’s online banking unit for $6.2 billion in cash and issue $2.8 billion worth of new shares to ING. It outbid General Electric’s GE Capital and the CIT Group to win the crowded auction. Representative Barney Frank’s letter to Ben Bernanke Capital One’s letter to the Federal Reserve</text></article><article index="10" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/10/capital-one-to-buy-hsbcs-u-s-card-unit-for-2-6-billion/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One to Buy HSBC's U.S. Card Unit for $2.6 Billion<date>August 10, 2011, 1:29 am</date><text>Olivia Harris/ReutersThe London headquarters of HSBC. Capital One Financial agreed early Wednesday to buy the United States credit card business of HSBC Holdings for $2.6 billion in cash and stock, in what will be Capital One’s second major deal with a European firm in recent months. The purchase will give Capital One more than $30 billion of credit card loans. It follows the firm’s agreement in June to buy the American online banking operations of ING Group of the Netherlands for $9 billion. Capital One said it expected to realize cost savings of about $350 million and incur restructuring costs of about $420 million. HSBC said that the sale represented a premium of 8.75 percent to the gross customer loan balances and that it would record a post-tax gain of $2.4 billion. The bank, based in London, also said that it would keep its $1.1 billion HSBC USA credit card program and that it would continue to offer credit cards to American customers. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links HSBC press release Capital One press release However, the deal will allow HSBC to continue paring back its consumer businesses in the United States as it refocuses on emerging markets and international corporate lending. HSBC had already announced that it was considering shedding noncore consumer operations and assets as part of a $3.5 billion cost-trimming effort. Last week, the British bank announced plans to lay off 30,000 employees. It also said that it was selling 195 bank branches, mostly in upstate New York, to the First Niagara Financial Group for about $1 billion. While the auction of the HSBC card business had attracted other potential suitors, like Wells Fargo, bankers considered Capital One the most likely buyer. Capital On, a 23-year-old firm, began life as a credit card lender, and it remains one of the biggest purveyors of such services to customers with less-than-ideal borrowing histories. Capital One’s takeover of the ING banking operations was meant in part to bolster mainline banking operations. But the deal also furnished the firm with more deposits that it could use as a source of funds for lucrative acquisitions. Analysts at Barclays Capital wrote in a research note published after the ING deal that if the firm were to buy the HSBC portfolio, it could raise its earnings per share by 10 percent or more. Capital One has already benefited from an improving environment for credit card lenders, including fewer charge-offs and lower financing costs. Its card unit more than doubled its profit last year, to $2.3 billion. HSBC was advised by JPMorgan Chase. Morgan Stanley, Centerview Partners and the Kessler Group were advising Capital One. Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen and Katz, and Morrison &amp; Foerster acted as legal advisers.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/09/hsbc-in-talks-to-sell-credit-card-portfolio/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">HSBC in Talks to Sell Credit Card Portfolio<date>August 9, 2011, 7:24 am</date><text>Olivia Harris/ReutersThe London headquarters of HSBC. HSBC Holdings said on Tuesday that it was in talks over the sale of its credit card business in the United States. HSBC, the London-based bank giant, provided no further details in its statement to the Hong Kong stock exchange except to say that “these discussions are ongoing and no decision has yet been made to proceed with any transaction.” But a person briefed on the matter told DealBook that HSBC is nearing a deal with Capital One Financial, in what would be the American company’s second major acquisition this year. Capital One is aggressively trying to expand its plate of financial services. In June, it agreed to buy the American online banking operations of ING Group of the Netherlands for $9 billion. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links HSBC's statement That takeover was meant in part to further bolster Capital One’s services beyond its traditional credit card offerings into mainline banking. Buying HSBC’s roughly $30 billion worth of credit card loans would be closer to Capital One’s core business and allow the American bank to expand its portfolio. HSBC already announced that it was considering shedding noncore consumer operations and assets as part of a $3.5 billion cost-trimming effort. Last week, the British bank announced plans to lay off 30,000 employees. It also announced that it was selling 195 bank branches, mostly in upstate New York, to the First Niagara Financial Group for about $1 billion. HSBC is being advised by JPMorgan Chase.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/05/credit-cards-without-those-pesky-foreign-transaction-fees/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Credit Cards Without Foreign Transaction Fees<date>July 5, 2011, 12:53 pm</date><text>If you’re planning a trip outside of the United States this summer, you might want to think hard about what credit card you bring along. The list of cards that have eliminated foreign transaction fees, which tack up to 3 percent onto your purchases, is growing, and using the right card can save you money on your vacation. The latest entry to the field is the Chase Sapphire Preferred Card. The card carries no foreign transaction fees and is offering a bonus of 50,000 rewards points if you spend $3,000 in the first three months. The card has a $95 annual fee, but it’s waived for the first year. The Sapphire card joins Chase’s existing offerings that don’t charge the annoying fees, including its British Airways Visa Signature Card, the Hyatt Card and the Priority Club Select Visa Card. Capital One offers several cards with no foreign exchange fees and no annual fee as well; card comparison site Cardhub.com has a list. Citigroup has eliminated the charges on its ThankYou Premier and ThankYou Prestige cards. And American Express doesn’t charge the fees on its Platinum and Centurion cards. An analysis by Cardhub showed that using credit cards with no currency conversion fees save consumers an average of 7.9 percent when compared to exchange rates offered at banks and 14.7 percent when compared to airport exchange services. Even if you are stuck with a card that charges the fee, you’ll still come out ahead using plastic, the survey found: You’ll save 4.9 percent on average and 11.7 percent, compared to banks and airport currency exchange services, respectively. What card do you use when you travel internationally?</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/30/who-is-the-mystery-hamptons-moneybags/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Who Is the Mystery Hamptons Moneybags?<date>June 30, 2011, 11:56 am</date><text>The hunt is on for the New York mogul with questionable cash management skills. Speculation bubbled on Wednesday after a receipt left hanging out of a Capital One ATM in East Hampton that displayed its owner’s remaining balance as $99,864,731.94 — yes, that would be $99 million and change — was posted on Dealbreaker. The receipt, which appears to show a $400 cash withdrawal from a savings account plus a $2.75 ATM fee, was rumored to belong to the Appaloosa Management honcho David Tepper. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink It wouldn’t be out of character for Mr. Tepper, a profligate spender and Hamptons regular who once mused to New York magazine’s Jessica Pressler about how he could spend his billions. “I could buy an island. I could buy a private jet — but I have NetJets. I could get myself a 22-year-old!” But The New York Post said on Thursday that it had contacted Mr. Tepper, who denied owning the account. Commenters over at Dealbreaker have zeroed in on the wisdom of keeping an eight-figure balance in an account that may not even pay 1 percent interest. (Bankrate.com lists the largest interest rate for a so-called “jumbo” savings account at 1.14 percent, from Delaware’s Discover Bank.) But others have noted that some brokerage firms allow you to withdraw from your trading account as if it were a savings account, in which case the account’s yield could be much higher. Until a well-heeled Hamptonite claims the ATM receipt, DealBook will be working the phones in search of an answer. Paulson? Schwarzman? Mayor Bloomberg? This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: July 18, 2011 An earlier version of this article incorrectly stated that David Tepper made billions of dollars during the housing collapse. His fund made most of its money in 2009 as a result of its investments in bank stocks.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/22/capital-ones-response-to-outrage-over-ing-direct-purchase/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One's Response to Outrage Over ING Direct Purchase<date>June 22, 2011, 12:56 pm</date><text>ING Direct USA account holders are reacting to the sale of the online bank about as well as they would if Capital One’s famous television barbarians had battered down the doors of their homes. Social media sites, including ING Direct’s own Facebook page, and banking blogs have erupted with customer antipathy for the deal, which was announced last week. A sale was required by European regulators as a condition of financial assistance given to ING’s  Dutch parent bank during the banking crisis. ING Direct, headquartered in Wilmington, Del., offers savings accounts, checking accounts, mortgages and brokerage services to 7.7 million customers. The main theme of the rants — er, posts — seems to be the concern that ING’s brand of low-fee, low-maintenance banking, combined with responsive customer service, would soon be a thing of the past under the new ownership. ING became popular offering no frills accounts, a savings account with competitive rates but no minimum balance, for instance, and no monthly fee. Users also especially like a feature that lets them easily establish subsavings accounts for specific purposes, like vacations or taxes, and have money transferred automatically from other accounts. “TERRIBLE NEWS,” said a typical entry, from someone called Red Broad on the Facebook page. “I’ve been really happy with ING, but C1 have a horrible reputation for fees and customer support, quite the opposite to ING’s business model. I’m really sad to see it go this way. I’m willing to bet that ING will lose at least 50% or more of its account holders due to this takeover. What a shame to see a truly customer oriented bank fall into the hands of a bank with probably the worst customer relations out there. I REALLY DON’T want to change banks, I LOVE my banking experience with ING, I can’t see me staying with C1 though so I guess I’ll just have to start looking around…sigh…” And this one, from Steve Bush: “I feel betrayed by a trusted friend. What a shame.” Many of the posts used language that can’t be used in a newspaper, although a few optimistic comments dismissed the predictions of banking apocalypse. “A lot of you people seem to be taking this a little too hard,” said Matt Cannon on Facebook. “No one has any idea yet what’s going to happen, but I severely doubt ING Direct will see any significant change in the way they do business, no need to run for the hills yet.” We here at Bucks wondered if this outpouring of emotion gave the folks at Capital One pause, so we asked them some questions that seem to be on customers’ minds. The bank declined to provide “yes or no” answers to queries about specific changes, saying it was too soon to do so. But the spokeswoman Tatiana Stead did offer the following responses via e-mail. To us, it looks like they’re at least leaving open the option of adding fees and minimum balances and subsuming the ING Direct brand altogether. Do you feel reassured by the responses below? Q: Why are customers of ING so upset about the sale of their bank to Capital One? ING has developed a unique connection with its customers. There are millions of “happy savers” across the country who are incredibly loyal and value their relationship with ING. We truly appreciate that, and we intend to do everything we can to maintain that trust and their enthusiasm. We deeply understand and respect the value and the loyalty ING has created.  Together with the ING team, we have the capabilities and insights to sustain and build the power of that franchise to better serve customers and create great value for our shareholders and associates. Q: What changes are you planning to make to ING Direct’s account offerings? Will subaccounts for specific savings goals remain? We have no plans to make any significant changes. ING customers should expect the same great customer experience and the “status quo” from ING for the foreseeable future. Q. Are you planning any new fees or minimum balance requirements? ING Direct has built a large and valuable franchise of engaged customers by focusing on a few simple proconsumer products.  We deeply understand the value of the loyalty and advocacy ING Direct has been able to build with its customers.  Everything we do as we integrate our businesses will be thoughtful and surefooted with a focus on sustaining and building that customer loyalty. We will focus on the customers, channels, products, and pricing strategies that build the best long-term customer relationships and deliver the best cost of funds. Q: Does the reaction suggest Capital One might need to enhance customer service? How might this be done? ING was a pioneer in direct banking and has built an incredibly successful, customer-centric model focused on building and sustaining long-term relationships. One of our primary objectives will be to ensure that we sustain and, where we can, enhance the exceptional customer experience ING delivers today. We want to reassure the current customers of ING Direct that the great products and experience they’ve come to expect will continue and, in fact, expand over time. Q. Will ING Direct be operated separately or integrated into Capital One’s operations? ING Direct and Capital One share a heritage of innovation, a strong focus on building customer franchise and an unwavering commitment to find, empower and unleash extremely talented people.  We have been impressed with the management team of ING Direct and what they have accomplished. As I am sure you will appreciate, over the upcoming weeks we want to get to know ING Direct’s management team and associates even better as we determine how best to organize to deliver the customer experience as well as the financial and strategic results we have been discussing. Capital One will work closely with the leadership team at ING Direct team to establish a management structure designed to ensure that the combined company achieves the highest quality integration and has the best leadership in place to carry on and build upon ING Direct’s great customer franchise.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/16/capital-one-to-buy-ings-u-s-online-banking-unit-for-9-billion/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One to Buy ING's Online Bank for $9 Billion<date>June 16, 2011, 4:05 pm</date><text>Peter Foley/Bloomberg News 9:54 p.m. | Updated Capital One Financial agreed on Thursday to buy the ING Group’s online banking unit in the United States for $9 billion in cash and stock, one of its biggest efforts yet to add to offerings beyond credit cards and other consumer lending. Under the terms of the deal, Capital One will pay $6.2 billion in cash and issue $2.8 billion worth of new shares to ING, giving it a 9.9 percent stake. ING will also have the right to name a director on Capital One’s board. Long known for cheeky credit card ads asking customers “What’s in your wallet?” Capital One is seeking to build up a national banking franchise. Buying ING Direct USA, one of the best-known online banks in the country, will help give Capital One a broader platform and a huge source of lower-cost funds. Currently the eighth-biggest bank in the country by deposits, Capital One will rise to the fifth-biggest through the deal. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Capital One press release ING Group press release “The acquisition of ING Direct is a game-changing transaction that delivers attractive deal economics immediately and compelling long-term strategic value,” Richard D. Fairbank, Capital One’s chairman and chief executive, said in a statement. ING was reluctant to shed its online banking business, one of its crown jewels and a leader in the expanding direct banking industry. But it was forced to sell off the unit by the European Commission as part of the bank’s 10 billion euro bailout in 2008. “Although I regret that ING Direct USA will no longer be a part of ING, I am very pleased that we have found in Capital One a good home for our customers and employees, who are very important to the continued success of the ING Direct USA Business,” Jan H. M. Hommen, ING’s chief executive, said in a statement. Capital One emerged the winner of a relatively crowded auction, one that also included General Electric’s GE Capital and the CIT Group, according to people briefed on the matter. One of the reasons Capital One prevailed was its willingness to shoulder more than $60 billion worth of mortgages and mortgage-linked securities. In order to help pay for the transaction, Capital One said it planned to raise about $2 billion from a sale of new shares and $3.7 billion from selling new debt. But the bank insists that the deal will pay for itself quickly. Capital One expects to reap $90 million in savings from combining back-end systems and staff, as well as $200 million from lowering funding costs. The transaction will also add to Capital One’s earnings per share beginning next year. Shares in Capital One began rising on Thursday afternoon after Dow Jones reported news of the impending deal, closing up $1.13, or 2.4 percent, at $49. The deal is expected to close by the end of the year or early next year, pending regulatory approval. Capital One was advised by Morgan Stanley, Barclays Capital, Centerview Partners and the law firms Mayer Brown, Loyens &amp; Loeff and Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz. ING Direct was advised by Deutsche Bank and JPMorgan Chase.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/extending-credit-card-protections-to-small-business-users/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Extending Credit Card Protections to Small Business Users<date>May 18, 2011, 12:19 pm</date><text>Courtesy Bank of AmericaBank of America’s business card doesn’t charge over-the-limit fees. Each month, Americans get more than 10 million business credit card pitches in their home mailboxes. The cards are aimed at small businesses and sole proprietors, but they generally lack the new protections that apply to consumer cards, a new report from the Pew Charitable Trusts says. That means holders of the cards are subject to a host of potentially harmful terms, like high-interest penalty rates imposed without warning. The Card Act of 2009 banned such practices for cards marketed primarily as consumer accounts, but it doesn’t apply to those labeled for “business” use — even though the holders are individually liable for the account balances, just as “ordinary” consumers are. The impact of higher rates can be significant with a business card because the small business owner usually is responsible for charges on any card linked to the account. Nick Bourke, director of Pew’s Safe Credit Cards Project and the main author of the report, says in a video that Pew “is urging policy makers to extend the protections of the Credit Card Act whenever a credit card account can hold a person individually liable.” The report analyzed disclosure documents from the 12 largest credit card issuers, which control about 85 percent of the small business credit card market. Some issuers, notably, Bank of America and Capital One, have voluntarily applied some consumer protections from the Card Act to their business cards. Bank of America, for instance, has eliminated over-the-limit fees on its business cards. And both companies have adopted procedures that apply payments first to balances with higher interest rates, like cash advances. Those banks are the exception, however. That means, in general, the Pew report says, “Households that use these products remain vulnerable to potentially harmful practices.” For instance, 67 percent of business cards charged an over-the-limit fee, typically $39. And an equal percentage applied penalty rates for late payments or over-the-limit spending. The typical penalty rate was 29.4 percent. Older, more affluent people get a higher percentage of business card pitches. But even households with annual incomes of less than $25,000 — a level near the federal poverty rate for a family of five — got a significant volume of solicitations. The authors of the Pew report recommend that issuers should at least be required to alert applicants that the business cards don’t carry the same protections as consumer cards do. It’s likely, Mr. Bourke said in a brief interview, that some individuals end up using “business” cards as their personal plastic, but it’s unclear how often that actually happens. Have you responded to a business credit card solicitation that arrived in your mailbox? Have you encountered any of the penalties associated with them?</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/03/24/s-p-warns-about-excessive-bank-dividends/?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">S.&amp;P. Warns About 'Excessive' Bank Dividends<date>March 24, 2011, 5:55 pm</date><text>Tomohiro Ohsumi/Bloomberg News Standard &amp; Poor’s issued a warning on Thursday to big banks itching to increase their dividends: proceed with caution. S.&amp;.P., one of the three largest credit rating agencies, said in a report that it “remains wary of banks aggressively increasing capital returns to shareholders at this juncture of the economic recovery.” S.&amp;.P. indicated it might downgrade credit ratings at banks that made “excessive” payouts to investors. Several big banks unveiled plans in recent days to raise their dividends and buy back stock for the first time since the financial crisis. They did so soon after getting the green light from the Federal Reserve, which recently completed a second round of stress tests on the nation’s 19 biggest banks. On the heels of receiving its stress test score, JPMorgan Chase said it would buy back stock worth $15 billion and raise its quarterly dividend to 25 cents a share, up from 5 cents. Last Friday, Goldman Sachs said it would pay back the $5 billion it received from Warren E. Buffett at the peak of the financial crisis. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Regulators waited for the banks to rebuild their capital levels and profit before blessing the payouts. But S.&amp;.P. still sees room for improvement. Banks need an 8 percent risk-adjusted capital ratio to weather another economic meltdown, the report said. The average bank in the United States featured a 7.6 percent rate in late 2010. “We are therefore wary of a bank’s possible decision to return a large portion of capital to shareholders in 2011,” the report said. S.&amp;.P. is particularly concerned about the payouts “in light of continuing global macroeconomic issues,” citing the recent rise in oil prices and the earthquake in Japan. JPMorgan and Goldman Sachs are in the safety zone, with risk-adjusted capital levels of 8.2 percent and 8.3 percent, respectively. But several banks that rushed to announce dividend bumps fall below the 8 percent threshold. State Street’s risk-adjusted capital ratio is 6.2 percent. The bank plans to raise its quarterly dividend to 18 cents, up from a penny. S.&amp;.P.’s report does not object to such “modest” dividends bumps. It instead raised concerns about share buybacks and special dividends. BB&amp;T has announced a modest 1 cent dividend increase and a 1 cent special dividend, effective May 2. Wells Fargo plans to issue a special dividend of 7 cents. State Street plans to buy back about $600 million worth of stock. The report warned that “excessive” special dividends and stock repurchases “could hinder the ability to build additional needed capital.” The report did not define “excessive” and did not call out any banks by name for drafting imprudent capital plans. Of course, not every bank has the luxury of returning capital to shareholders. The Fed, for instance, put the kibosh on Capital One’s dividend plans. The Fed also objected to Bank of America’s plans to award a “modest” dividend increase in the second half of 2011. The bank, which currently issues a token dividend of a penny a share, plans to tweak and resubmit its proposal in the coming months.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/02/sports/02college.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">New Trophy for Cumulative College Excellence: Capital One Cup<date>Published: September 1, 2010</date><text>College sports have a new trophy to hoist.At a Wednesday news conference in Manhattan, a team of former N.C.A.A. athletes unveiled the Capital One Cup, which will be awarded to the top men’s and women’s Division I programs based on cumulative on-field performance across multiple sports. Colleges will earn points based on their teams’ top-10 finishes and in final official coaches’ polls in 13 men’s and women’s sports, including cross-country, golf and tennis for men, and volleyball, softball and rowing for women. “This will be an opportunity for school administrators to see the importance of their non-revenue programs,” said Doug Flutie, the former Boston College and N.F.L. quarterback who won the 1984 Heisman Trophy. “On college campuses, the self-pride in those programs will continue to escalate.” Official standings will be released at the end of the fall, winter and spring athletic seasons. In July, the two athletic programs with the highest aggregated point totals will be announced as winners. Each university will be presented with a trophy, along with a $200,000 scholarship donation from Capital One, at the ESPY Awards. Athletic departments have competed for the Sears Cup or the Directors Cup since 1993. That award combines men’s and women’s scores and includes programs from Division I, II and III. North Carolina won that award in its first year, but Stanford has won it every year since.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/19/business/economy/19debt.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Peddling Relief, Firms Put Debtors in Deeper Hole<date>Published: June 18, 2010</date><text>PALM BEACH, Fla. — For the companies that promise relief to Americans confronting swelling credit card balances, these are days of lucrative opportunity.So lucrative, that an industry trade association, the United States Organizations for Bankruptcy Alternatives, recently convened here, in the oceanfront confines of the Four Seasons Resort, to forge deals and plot strategy. At a well-lubricated evening reception, a steel drum band played Bob Marley songs as hostesses in skimpy dresses draped leis around the necks of arriving entrepreneurs, some with deep tans. The debt settlement industry can afford some extravagance. The long recession has delivered an abundance of customers — debt-saturated Americans, suffering lost jobs and income, sliding toward bankruptcy. The settlement companies typically harvest fees reaching 15 to 20 percent of the credit card balances carried by their customers, and they tend to collect upfront, regardless of whether a customer’s debt is actually reduced. State attorneys general from New York to California and consumer watchdogs like the Better Business Bureau say the industry’s proceeds come at the direct expense of financially troubled Americans who are being fleeced of their last dollars with dubious promises. Consumers rarely emerge from debt settlement programs with their credit card balances eliminated, these critics say, and many wind up worse off, with severely damaged credit, ceaseless threats from collection agents and lawsuits from creditors. In the Kansas City area, Linda Robertson, 58, rues the day she bought the pitch from a debt settlement company advertising on the radio, promising to spare her from bankruptcy and eliminate her debts. She wound up sending nearly $4,000 into a special account established under the company’s guidance before a credit card company sued her, prompting her to drop out of the program. By then, her account had only $1,470 remaining: The debt settlement company had collected the rest in fees. She is now filing for bankruptcy. “They take advantage of vulnerable people,” she said. “When you’re desperate and you’re trying to get out of debt, they take advantage of you.” Debt settlement has swollen to some 2,000 firms, from a niche of perhaps a dozen companies a decade ago, according to trade associations and the Federal Trade Commission, which is completing new rules aimed at curbing abuses within the industry. Last year, within the industry’s two leading trade associations — the United States Organizations for Bankruptcy Alternatives and the Association of Settlement Companies — some 250 companies collectively had more than 425,000 customers, who had enrolled roughly $11.7 billion in credit card balances in their programs. As the industry has grown, so have allegations of unfair practices. Since 2004, at least 21 states have brought at least 128 enforcement actions against debt relief companies, according to the National Association of Attorneys General. Consumer complaints received by states more than doubled between 2007 and 2009, according to comments filed with the Federal Trade Commission. “The industry’s not legitimate,” said Norman Googel, assistant attorney general in West Virginia, which has prosecuted debt settlement companies. “They’re targeting a group of people who are already drowning in debt. We’re talking about middle-class and lower middle-class people who had incomes, but they were using credit cards to survive.” The industry counters that a few rogue operators have unfairly tarnished the reputations of well-intentioned debt settlement companies that provide a crucial service: liberating Americans from impossible credit card burdens. With the unemployment rate near double digits and 6.7 million people out of work for six months or longer, many have relied on credit cards. By the middle of last year, 6.5 percent of all accounts were at least 30 days past due, up from less than 4 percent in 2005, according to Moody’s Economy.com. Yet a 2005 alteration spurred by the financial industry made it harder for Americans to discharge credit card debts through bankruptcy, generating demand for alternatives like debt settlement. The Arrangement The industry casts itself as a victim of a smear campaign orchestrated by the giant banks that dominate the credit card trade and aim to hang on to the spoils: interest rates of 20 percent or more and exorbitant late fees. “We’re the little guys in this,” said John Ansbach, the chief lobbyist for the United States Organizations for Bankruptcy Alternatives, better known as Usoba (pronounced you-SO-buh). “We exist to advocate for consumers. Two and a half billion dollars of unsecured debt has been settled by this industry, so how can you take the position that it has no value?” But consumer watchdogs and state authorities argue that debt settlement companies generally fail to deliver.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/02/business/economy/02garnish.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Pay Garnishments Rise as Debtors Fall Behind<date>Published: April 1, 2010</date><text>PHOENIX — When the bank sued Leann Weaver for not paying her credit card balance, her reaction was typical for someone in that situation. Personal and financial setbacks weighed her down, and she knew she owed the $2,470. So she never went to court to defend herself.She was startled by what happened next. When she swiped her debit card at the grocery store, it was declined. It turned out Capital One Bank had taken $224.25 from her paycheck, a quarter of her wages for two weeks of work at a retail chain, and her bank account was overdrawn. “They’re kicking somebody who’s already in the dirt,” she said. One of the worst economic downturns of modern history has produced a big increase in the number of delinquent borrowers, and creditors are suing them by the millions. Concern is mounting in government and among consumer advocates that the debtors are not always getting a fair shake in these cases. Most consumers never offer a defense, and creditors win their lawsuits without having to offer proof of the debts, much less justify to a judge the huge interest charges and penalties they often tack on. After winning, creditors can secure a court order to seize part of the debtor’s paycheck or the funds in a bank account, a procedure called garnishment. No national statistics are kept, but the pay seizures are rising fast in some areas — up 121 percent in the Phoenix area since 2005, and 55 percent in the Atlanta area since 2004. In Cleveland, garnishments jumped 30 percent between 2008 and 2009 alone. Debt collectors say they are being forced into the action by combative debtors who dodge attempts to settle. “I think there’s a lack of accountability among debtors, and a lack of interest in reaching out to their creditors to resolve things amicably,” said Fred N. Blitt, president of the National Association of Retail Collection Attorneys. Bankruptcy can clear away most debts. Yet sweeping changes to federal law in 2005 — pushed by the banking lobby — complicated that process and more than doubled the average cost of filing, to more than $2,000. Many low-income debtors must save for months before they can afford to go broke. In some states, courts allow creditors to charge high interest rates for years after a lawsuit is decided in their favor. In others, creditors can win lawsuits by default and seize wages and bank accounts without a case ever appearing before a judge. Lack of participation is the most fundamental problem. Some consumers do not even know they are being sued; the people who are supposed to serve them with formal notice have sometimes been caught skipping that step and doctoring the paperwork. In far more cases, consumers are served but still do not offer a defense. Few can afford lawyers; others are intimidated or confused. In their absence, judges can offer little relief. In the rare event that a consumer battles back, creditors frequently lack the documentation to prove their claim, and cases are dropped. That is because many past-due debts are owned not by the banks that issued them, but by debt collectors who bought, for cents on the dollar, a list of names and amounts due. “If the consumers were armed with more education about how to defend against these debts, they’d be successful,” said Jeffrey Lipman, a civil magistrate in Des Moines. The case of Sidney Jones shows how punishing the system can be. In January 2001, Mr. Jones, 45, a maintenance worker from California Crossroads, Va., took out a $4,097 personal loan from Beneficial Virginia, a subprime lender now owned by HSBC, the big bank. He fell behind, and Beneficial sued. Mr. Jones did not appear in court. “I just thought they were going to take what I owed,” he said. By default, Beneficial won a judgment of $4,750, plus $900 in lawyers’ fees, with the debt accruing interest at 27.55 percent until paid in full. The bank started garnishing his wages in March 2003. Over the next six years, the bank deducted more than $10,000 from Mr. Jones’s paychecks, but he made little headway on his debt. According to a court order secured by Beneficial’s lawyers last spring, he still owed the company $3,965, a sum nearly equal to the original loan amount. Mr. Jones, who did not graduate from high school, was baffled. “Where did all this money go that I paid them?” he said. Dale Pittman, a consumer law lawyer in Petersburg, Va. , took Mr. Jones’s case without charge, and found that all but $134 of his payments had gone toward interest, fees and court costs. “It’s a perfectly legal result under Virginia law,” Mr. Pittman said. HSBC said it ceased collection shortly after Mr. Pittman took the case, but declined further comment. “We are confident we are treating our customers fairly and with integrity,” Kate Durham, a spokeswoman for HSBC North America, said in an e-mail message. The rare debtors who press their claims, and catch a sympathetic judge, have a shot at a result more to their liking. Ruth M. Owens, a disabled Cleveland woman, was sued by Discover Bank in 2004 for an unpaid credit card. Ms. Owens offered a defense, sending a handwritten note to the court. “After paying my monthly utilities, there is no money left except a little food money and sometimes it isn’t enough,” she wrote. Robert Triozzi, a judge at the time, heard the case. He found that over a period of several years, Ms. Owens had paid nearly $3,500 on an original balance of $1,900. But Discover was suing her for $5,564, mostly for late fees, compound interest, penalties and other charges. He called Discover’s actions “unconscionable” and threw the case out. Discover defended its actions. “This account was placed with an attorney only after all other efforts to reach the card member were exhausted,” Matthew Towson, a bank spokesman, said in an e-mail message. Going to court is no guarantee of victory, of course. Consumers who do go are sometimes intercepted by collection lawyers, who press them to sign papers settling without a trial. These settlements may be against the interests of debtors, but they sign anyway. “We’re signing off on a lot of settlement agreements where we shake our heads and ask, ‘Why is this person settling to this?’ ” Judge Lipman said. For the working poor, losing a lawsuit can mean disaster. Federal law permits creditors to seize as much as a quarter of a worker's paycheck, though the cutoff is lower for the lowest-paid workers, and a few states also offer greater protection. The working poor “have difficulties maintaining payments on life’s necessities with their full paycheck,” said Angela Riccetti, a lawyer with Atlanta Legal Aid who represents indigent clients whose wages are being garnished. “You lose 25 percent of it and everything folds.” For Leann Weaver, the woman at the grocery store, Capital One’s lawsuit made a bad situation worse. After being evicted from her apartment, she moved in with her grandparents. Without them, she might have ended up on the street or in a shelter, she said. Capital One declined to comment on Ms. Weaver’s case. “We encourage anyone facing difficulties meeting their financial obligations to contact us right away,” Tatiana Stead, a bank spokeswoman, said in an e-mail message. Ms. Weaver said she repeatedly asked Capital One for more time to pay her $2,470 debt, but last year the bank filed suit. She failed to show up in court, and a judgment was entered against her, swollen by $1,800 in interest and lawyers’ fees. Then the garnishment began, almost $500 a month, or a quarter of her pay. “I can’t even look at my paychecks any more,” she said.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/13/your-money/credit-and-debit-cards/13money.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">In Most Cases, Best to Pass Up Overdraft Protection<date>Published: March 12, 2010</date><text>Many millions of people will face important choices about their checking and credit card accounts in the coming months, though this week one of the biggest banks made one of the decisions for them.Bank of America shocked competitors on Wednesday when it announced it was doing away with overdraft fees for debit card purchases. Starting this summer, the bank’s checking account customers who don’t have enough money to cover their purchases will, in most instances, not be able to use their cards to complete the transaction. Bank of America (and many of its competitors) had often been letting the charge go through despite the lack of funds and then hitting the customer with a fee of about $30. Bank of America could have allowed customers to sign up for debit overdraft coverage. In fact, it would have had to, because of new rules forcing banks to set up an “opt in” system for most debit card purchases and A.T.M. withdrawals (banks will still be able to automatically cover overdrafts from recurring monthly bills and bounced checks). But the bank simply decided not to, citing feedback from checking account customers who did not want to spend money that they didn’t actually have. If you take the bank at its word, that feedback suggests that there are not a lot of people who are going to choose overdraft coverage elsewhere. And the same logic probably applies to going over the credit limit on a credit card. There, too, banks now have to get customers’ permission before allowing them to charge more than their limit. And there, too, Bank of America has elected not to ask; instead, it will either cut customers off or, at its discretion, allow some transactions to go through fee-free. Even so, some of the other big banks are betting that plenty of people will raise their hands to overspend and pay the per-transaction fee. Chase is engaged in an aggressive campaign to get customers to consider their overdraft options and to talk to a banker about them, including reminding them of the opt-in option when they take out money at an A.T.M. Chase will also allow credit card customers to opt in to go over their credit limits. Capital One has made the same bet as Chase. Citibank never had automatic overdraft coverage and is doing away with over-the-limit credit card fees as well. American Express and Discover decided to get rid of their over-the-limit option last year. Still, scores of people will need to make some choices in the next few months when their banks and card issuers reach out to them to comply with the new federal rules. Should anyone say yes? It’s pretty hard to take the idea of opting in to overdrafts seriously. Why? Well, think about it the way the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation did in a 2008 study. If you make a $20 purchase without enough money in your account to cover it, pay a $27 overdraft fee and then bring your account back above zero in, say, two weeks, you’re effectively paying interest at an annual percentage rate of 3,520 percent. Um, no thanks. Right? Banks argue that overdraft isn’t credit. They say it’s a service. Fine, but there are plenty of other cheaper services available to keep from being overdrawn in the first place. You can start by setting up free e-mail or other alerts from your bank or card issuer that tell you when you’re running out of money in your checking account or getting close to the credit limit on your card. Your bank may also offer other, cheaper overdraft coverage, too. Perhaps your checking account can tap your savings account if the checking account falls below zero. Or you can link your bank account to a credit card, home equity line of credit or a personal credit line. This will generally be cheaper than paying an overdraft fee. Chase’s current direct mail campaign invokes a broken-down car in need of an emergency tow. Wouldn’t you want overdraft protection turned on in that instance if your checking account was running low? Well, yes, but only if you didn’t have cash, a credit card or a roadside assistance plan. And that gets to the heart of the matter. When I asked what sort of person overdraft was truly best for, Scott Powell, who runs the consumer banking business for Chase, painted a picture of a person getting paid on Monday, but running low on funds the weekend before. “You don’t have enough money, but there are certain emergency things you need to do,” he said, noting that overdraft protection gives people like that options they would not otherwise have and the ability to buy some groceries or a prescription or take a pet to the vet. Overdraft, in other words, is the very last resort. After a credit card. After account alerts. After tapping home equity. Or, presumably, after you’ve maxed out or ruined your credit and have no home equity left. Sadly, there are probably enough people in that situation for banks to make money chasing and serving them. But everyone else ought to say no to overdraft, so that debit cards revert to one of their original purposes as a tool to keep you from spending more than their balance. Keep in mind that you can turn overdraft back on anytime if your financial situation gets desperate enough.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDD113FF932A25751C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Top Pay List For Bankers: Fresh Names<date>Published: February 11, 2010</date><text>The list of the biggest earners in finance usually reads like a Who's Who of Wall Street. But these days, it reads more like a Who's That? It turns out that some of the highest-paid financial executives in America work far from the canyons of Lower Manhattan, at companies that have largely avoided the outcry over the return of hefty paydays on Wall Street. Topping the list is John G. Stumpf, head of Wells Fargo, the bank based in San Francisco, according to an analysis of 2009 compensation in the industry. Mr. Stumpf was paid a personal best of $18.7 million in cash and stock for 2009 -- up 64 percent from 2007, just before the financial crisis struck. Mr. Stumpf is making twice as much as Lloyd C. Blankfein, his counterpart at Goldman Sachs. Mr. Blankfein -- who for many Americans has come to symbolize this new period of Wall Street riches -- was paid $9.7 million for 2009, less than some expected. It is a stunning reversal in the old pecking order of pay. Big names on Wall Street like Mr. Blankfein usually take home far more than staid bankers like Mr. Stumpf, whose bank's biggest business is making home mortgages and loans to corporations. But since the bailout, the rules of banker pay are bending. Some of the industry's biggest names are being paid less than relative unknowns. Chief executives, who are usually at the top of the pay heap, are taking home roughly the same amounts as executives who work for them -- and sometimes less. Mr. Stumpf and other executives have moved up the pay ladder partly because the likes of Mr. Blankfein have moved down. And for all the focus on what top executives earn, what is most startling is how many six-, seven- and eight-figure sums are being awarded to Wall Street bankers and traders whose pay often is unnoticed -- if it is disclosed at all. How much senior executives earn, in cash and stock, is made public in corporate filings. This year, the results are surprising, according to an analysis by Equilar, an executive compensation research firm. Leaders in the pay sweepstakes include the heads of the credit card giants Visa, Mastercard Worldwide, Capital One Financial and American Express. Joseph W. Saunders, who runs Visa, was paid about $15.5 million, a figure that vastly eclipses the compensation for top executives at Bank of America and Citigroup. Ajay Banga, the president of MasterCard Worldwide; Laurence D. Fink, the chairman and chief executive of the giant money management company BlackRock; and Richard B. Handler, the boss at the Jefferies Group, a midsize investment bank that is virtually unknown outside financial circles, were each paid about $13 million. Executives at certain discount brokerages, insurance companies and regional banks were close behind. The big money, as ever, is in Wall Street trading. But pay for employees with few executive responsibilities is typically exempted from disclosure requirements. Brokers and asset managers also land windfalls that are often undisclosed. ''There are probably thousands of people that are in the Millionaire Club -- or even the Ten Millionaire Club -- that have gotten no heat,'' said Alan Johnson, a longtime Wall Street compensation consultant. To be sure, a handful of prominent companies dominate the well-paid list. Senior managers from JPMorgan Chase and Goldman Sachs occupy many of the top spots. Few of those executives are boldface names, however. While Jamie Dimon, JPMorgan's chairman and chief executive, appears to be the second-highest-paid banker, at $17.6 million, one of his subordinates collected nearly as much: Ina R. Drew, JPMorgan's chief investment officer. Ms. Drew, whose correct calls on interest rates helped the bank earn several billion dollars of profit, was paid about $13 million. Despite the spotlight on Mr. Blankfein's pay at Goldman, little was said about how much Gordon Nixon of Royal Bank of Canada received. His paycheck was roughly the same amount as Mr. Blankfein's, $9.7 million, though he is hardly a household name. The Equilar analysis provides an early peek at 2009 pay and is not a comprehensive review. For consistency, any stock or options that were subject to performance hurdles were valued at the target levels; in practice, many executives receive larger payouts for surpassing the company's financial goals. Wells Fargo posted strong results, even as it struggled to contend with rising mortgage and commercial real estate losses and accepted a bailout from the government in 2008.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/19/business/media/19adco.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Agency Combines Clients’ Stocks for a Mini-Mutual Fund<date>Published: January 18, 2010</date><text>FORGET about the Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index or the Dow Jones industrial average. The latest gauge of Wall Street performance  at least on Madison Avenue  is the K.B.S.&amp; P. Client Stock Index. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Wortmann Lori Senecal, the head of Kirshenbaum Bond, began a special stock index, the brainchild of two employees: Aric Cheston, left, and Matt Powell, right. Add to Portfolio MDC Partners Incorporated Cablevision Systems Corp Go to your Portfolio » K.B.S. &amp; who? K.B.S.&amp; P. is short for Kirshenbaum Bond Senecal &amp; Partners in New York, part of MDC Partners. It is only coincidental that the S.&amp; P. in the abbreviation echoes the shorthand term for Standard &amp; Poor’s. The index, scheduled to be introduced on Tuesday, is intended to track the performance in the stock market of shares of companies that are publicly traded and clients of the agency. Eighteen of its more than 30 clients have stock that is traded on exchanges, among them BMW, Cablevision, Capital One Financial, Diageo, Kao Brands, TJX and Weight Watchers. What makes the index interesting is that it is not a fanciful construct but a real portfolio, a mini-mutual fund that will have its own ticket symbol, KBSPX. Agency executives are opening a brokerage account with another client, the Vanguard Group, into which will be deposited 300 shares of each of the 18 companies. The 300 employees of Kirshenbaum Bond will be offered long-term cash and compensation incentives to mirror the performance of the stocks in the index, which they will be able to track each trading day on an intranet on the agency’s Web site. MDC is spending an estimated $500,000 to start the index, which includes contributing four restricted shares of MDC stock to the fund for each Kirshenbaum Bond employee, for a total of 1,200 shares. The index is a version of efforts by a growing number of agencies to put skin in the game by showing clients they are willing to be paid based on how their work performs in the marketplace. Other examples include agencies taking ownership stakes in client companies or sharing revenue from the sales of products they advertise. “We’ve been hearing from a lot of clients that they want more accountability,” said Lori Senecal, who came to Kirshenbaum Bond in August as president and chief executive. “They need us to own their challenges.” “The index is a tangible way to add that belief to our culture,” she added. The index is among steps Ms. Senecal is taking since she joined Kirshenbaum Bond from McCann Erickson Worldwide to, as she put it, “reinterpret its heritage in the service of the marketing needs of the future.” Translation: shake things up. The agency, which gained a reputation in its early years for cheeky work like the “Wendy the Snapple lady” campaign for Snapple beverages, has been on a roller coaster more recently with gains of accounts like Vanguard offset by losses of clients like the Wendy’s fast-food chain. “Agencies either go forward or backward; they don’t stay the same,” said Richard Kirshenbaum, who shares the title of co-chairman at Kirshenbaum Bond with Jon Bond. Although “we’re a very healthy and successful agency, and a very profitable one,” Mr. Kirshenbaum said, “it’s time to have renewed energy and spirit at a time when the landscape is changing” for the advertising business. The index was the brainchild of two Kirshenbaum Bond employees: Aric Cheston, partner and creative director, and Matt Powell, chief technologist. They will each receive a cash bonus of $10,000 from MDC. Starting an agency mutual fund was among 50 ideas presented by employees at a crowd-sourcing meeting in October that sought proposals to help revitalize Kirshenbaum Bond from everyone who works there. Ms. Senecal is also adopting another idea from the meeting: The agency will devote the hours of 10 a.m. to noon each Friday to “hot housing,” as employees divide into groups and brainstorm new approaches for clients.“It’s motivating all levels of the organization from the bottom up,” said Miles S. Nadal, chairman and chief executive at MDC in Toronto. “If you want a behavior, you should create economic incentives to reward that behavior.” MDC will look into “rolling this out on a broader basis,” Mr. Nadal said, by starting similar indexes and funds at its other agencies. Among other moves by Ms. Senecal since she arrived at Kirshenbaum Bond were the hiring of Mick McCabe, a partner at Deutsch in New York, as the agency’s first chief strategy officer, and bringing in Marc Lucas, executive creative director at the New York office of Razorfish, as chief creative officer, assuming those duties from Mr. Kirshenbaum. Kirshenbaum Bond has landed two major assignments under Ms. Senecal. One expanded the agency’s relationship with Capital One, which awarded Kirshenbaum Bond the task of creating ads in print, radio, digital and out-of-home media. The other assignment was to be agency of record in the United States for Vanguard. Kirshenbaum Bond “understands our business metrics,” said Sean Hagerty, principal in retail marketing at Vanguard in Valley Forge, Pa., and knows how to “focus on how do we most efficiently and effectively talk to our audiences in a financially responsible manner.” The agency’s first work for Vanguard is being developed, he added, and could begin appearing in March. (Vanguard’s shares are not in the portfolio because the company is privately held.) As Kirshenbaum Bond employees watch the index, they may learn a lesson in the stock market: How the shares of a company fare does not always correspond to how the company is doing. One way gyrations could be mitigated is that “the index is based on a number of clients in diversified industries,” Mr. Nadal of MDC said. Besides, the index is intended to be “a long-term retention mechanism” for employees and “value is created over a longer period of time,” he added. “As Warren Buffett says, in the short term the stock market is a voting machine but in the long term it’s a weighting machine.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 19, 2010, on page B3 of the New York edition.FORGET about the Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index or the Dow Jones industrial average. The latest gauge of Wall Street performance  at least on Madison Avenue  is the K.B.S.&amp; P. Client Stock Index. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Wortmann Lori Senecal, the head of Kirshenbaum Bond, began a special stock index, the brainchild of two employees: Aric Cheston, left, and Matt Powell, right. Add to Portfolio MDC Partners Incorporated Cablevision Systems Corp Go to your Portfolio » K.B.S. &amp; who? K.B.S.&amp; P. is short for Kirshenbaum Bond Senecal &amp; Partners in New York, part of MDC Partners. It is only coincidental that the S.&amp; P. in the abbreviation echoes the shorthand term for Standard &amp; Poor’s. The index, scheduled to be introduced on Tuesday, is intended to track the performance in the stock market of shares of companies that are publicly traded and clients of the agency. Eighteen of its more than 30 clients have stock that is traded on exchanges, among them BMW, Cablevision, Capital One Financial, Diageo, Kao Brands, TJX and Weight Watchers. What makes the index interesting is that it is not a fanciful construct but a real portfolio, a mini-mutual fund that will have its own ticket symbol, KBSPX. Agency executives are opening a brokerage account with another client, the Vanguard Group, into which will be deposited 300 shares of each of the 18 companies. The 300 employees of Kirshenbaum Bond will be offered long-term cash and compensation incentives to mirror the performance of the stocks in the index, which they will be able to track each trading day on an intranet on the agency’s Web site. MDC is spending an estimated $500,000 to start the index, which includes contributing four restricted shares of MDC stock to the fund for each Kirshenbaum Bond employee, for a total of 1,200 shares. The index is a version of efforts by a growing number of agencies to put skin in the game by showing clients they are willing to be paid based on how their work performs in the marketplace. Other examples include agencies taking ownership stakes in client companies or sharing revenue from the sales of products they advertise. “We’ve been hearing from a lot of clients that they want more accountability,” said Lori Senecal, who came to Kirshenbaum Bond in August as president and chief executive. “They need us to own their challenges.” “The index is a tangible way to add that belief to our culture,” she added. The index is among steps Ms. Senecal is taking since she joined Kirshenbaum Bond from McCann Erickson Worldwide to, as she put it, “reinterpret its heritage in the service of the marketing needs of the future.” Translation: shake things up. The agency, which gained a reputation in its early years for cheeky work like the “Wendy the Snapple lady” campaign for Snapple beverages, has been on a roller coaster more recently with gains of accounts like Vanguard offset by losses of clients like the Wendy’s fast-food chain. “Agencies either go forward or backward; they don’t stay the same,” said Richard Kirshenbaum, who shares the title of co-chairman at Kirshenbaum Bond with Jon Bond. Although “we’re a very healthy and successful agency, and a very profitable one,” Mr. Kirshenbaum said, “it’s time to have renewed energy and spirit at a time when the landscape is changing” for the advertising business. The index was the brainchild of two Kirshenbaum Bond employees: Aric Cheston, partner and creative director, and Matt Powell, chief technologist. They will each receive a cash bonus of $10,000 from MDC. Starting an agency mutual fund was among 50 ideas presented by employees at a crowd-sourcing meeting in October that sought proposals to help revitalize Kirshenbaum Bond from everyone who works there. Ms. Senecal is also adopting another idea from the meeting: The agency will devote the hours of 10 a.m. to noon each Friday to “hot housing,” as employees divide into groups and brainstorm new approaches for clients.“It’s motivating all levels of the organization from the bottom up,” said Miles S. Nadal, chairman and chief executive at MDC in Toronto. “If you want a behavior, you should create economic incentives to reward that behavior.” MDC will look into “rolling this out on a broader basis,” Mr. Nadal said, by starting similar indexes and funds at its other agencies. Among other moves by Ms. Senecal since she arrived at Kirshenbaum Bond were the hiring of Mick McCabe, a partner at Deutsch in New York, as the agency’s first chief strategy officer, and bringing in Marc Lucas, executive creative director at the New York office of Razorfish, as chief creative officer, assuming those duties from Mr. Kirshenbaum. Kirshenbaum Bond has landed two major assignments under Ms. Senecal. One expanded the agency’s relationship with Capital One, which awarded Kirshenbaum Bond the task of creating ads in print, radio, digital and out-of-home media. The other assignment was to be agency of record in the United States for Vanguard. Kirshenbaum Bond “understands our business metrics,” said Sean Hagerty, principal in retail marketing at Vanguard in Valley Forge, Pa., and knows how to “focus on how do we most efficiently and effectively talk to our audiences in a financially responsible manner.” The agency’s first work for Vanguard is being developed, he added, and could begin appearing in March. (Vanguard’s shares are not in the portfolio because the company is privately held.) As Kirshenbaum Bond employees watch the index, they may learn a lesson in the stock market: How the shares of a company fare does not always correspond to how the company is doing. One way gyrations could be mitigated is that “the index is based on a number of clients in diversified industries,” Mr. Nadal of MDC said. Besides, the index is intended to be “a long-term retention mechanism” for employees and “value is created over a longer period of time,” he added. “As Warren Buffett says, in the short term the stock market is a voting machine but in the long term it’s a weighting machine.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDA113FF933A15752C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Treasury to Auction Off Big-Bank Warrants<date>Published: November 20, 2009</date><text>A year after the federal government rescued the nation's financial industry, the Treasury Department announced Thursday that it would auction off its remaining investments in three large banks, freeing the lenders from the federal bailout program. The Treasury will sell warrants that the government received as part of the taxpayer-financed rescue via auctions next month. The sales could raise $1.3 billion to $3.1 billion. The move will free the three banks -- JPMorgan Chase, Capital One Financial and TCF Financial -- from the Troubled Asset Relief Program, or TARP. The warrants on shares of the biggest of the three banks, JPMorgan, could fetch as much as $2.75 billion, according to an estimate by Linus Wilson of the University of Louisiana, Lafayette. Other banks, among them Goldman Sachs, negotiated deals to buy back their warrants -- which are similar to stock options -- rather than auction them off to investors. Some financial analysts argued the negotiated sales did not benefit taxpayers as much as auctions might have. Goldman Sachs -- which has made a rapid recovery from the financial crisis -- bought its warrants for $1.1 billion in July. Today, those warrants would be worth $1.24 billion to $2.1 billion given the surge in Goldman's stock price since then, according to Mr. Wilson. By buying back the warrants directly, banks like Goldman were able to retire the securities and avoid diluting the stakes of existing shareholders. In all, however, the warrants have turned out to be good investments for the Treasury. But after failing to agree on prices for the warrants with the government, JPMorgan, Capital One Financial and TCF Financial elected to auction them off and let private investors determine their value. The Treasury will sell the warrants through a so-called Dutch auction. It has hired Deutsche Bank to solicit bids from sophisticated investors and set minimum bids. The format will enable the three banks to bid for the warrants themselves. It is unclear if they will to do so. Officials from JPMorgan and Capital One declined to comment; a TCF spokeswoman did not return a phone call seeking comment. The warrants in JPMorgan, which repaid $25 billion of federal aid that it received last year, could be worth $1 billion to $2.75 billion, according to Mr. Wilson. Those in Capital One could be worth $241 million to $393 million, while those in TCF could fetch more than $12 million. It will not be the first time that the government has held such a sale. In the early 1980s, it conducted a similar sale for warrants the government received in connection with its rescue of Chrysler. Chrysler, which initially asked the government to return the warrants at no cost, submitted the winning bid that gave a tidy profit for taxpayers.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFDF1130F931A15757C0A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Banks Sway Bills to Aid Consumers<date>Published: April 22, 2009</date><text>They may be held in low esteem around the nation, but the country's largest banks still wield considerable influence in Washington. The banks have made it difficult for Congressional Democrats and the White House to give stretched homeowners a stronger hand in negotiating lower monthly payments on mortgages and to prevent credit card companies from imposing higher fees and interest rates. Having won some early skirmishes by teaming with Republican allies, the banks now appear to have the upper hand and may wind up killing -- or at least substantially diluting -- both pro-consumer measures. To turn the tide, Democrats are calling in their big gun -- President Obama -- to pressure the executives at the largest credit card lenders. In coming weeks, officials say, the administration intends to make a major push on consumer finance issues, possibly including tough new lending standards for homeowners seeking mortgages. Mr. Obama is set to meet at the White House on Thursday with executives from American Express, Bank of America, Capital One Financial, Citigroup, Discover Financial Services, JPMorgan Chase and others to discuss what officials say are abusive credit card fees and practices. During the presidential campaign, Mr. Obama made an issue of what he considered excessive credit card fees, but he has been largely silent on the matter since his arrival in Washington. As a candidate, he also favored legislation to make it easier for troubled homeowners to use bankruptcy court to ease the terms of their mortgages, a proposal he again endorsed last month. Despite the president's support and strong Democratic majorities in Congress, both proposals are in jeopardy because of lobbying by banks and their trade groups, particularly in the Senate. On Wednesday, the House Financial Services Committee is expected to approve credit card legislation proposed by senior Democrats that would reduce many of the fees and limit the ability of the companies to charge penalties. The legislation puts into law most of the credit card restrictions adopted last year by the Federal Reserve, although the industry strongly opposes the bill because it says it believes a law would be harder to overturn than a regulation. But the bill, sponsored by Representative Barney Frank, the Massachusetts Democrat who heads the Financial Services Committee, and Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, a New York Democrat, faces an uncertain future in the Senate. A tougher counterpart to the House bill was adopted on a narrow, party-line vote in the Senate banking committee three weeks ago. It has yet to find any Republican support, which would be necessary for it to survive. The banking industry has also succeeded in working closely with Republicans to water down and then block a measure that would give bankruptcy judges greater authority to modify mortgages, including reducing principal payments. Senate Republican leaders say they have the support of all 41 of their members -- enough to kill the provision by making it impossible to get the 60 votes necessary to cut off debate. Senate Democrats, hoping to resolve the impasse, have opened negotiations in recent days, but not with their Republican counterparts. Instead, in an effort to divide the industry, the Democrats, led by Richard J. Durbin of Illinois, Charles E. Schumer of New York and Christopher J. Dodd of Connecticut, have been in talks with Bank of America, JPMorgan Chase and Wells Fargo, along with a group of credit unions. The lawmakers' hope is that those institutions would exert pressure on Republican lawmakers and reluctant Democratic moderates. Even if those negotiations are successful, the Democratic lawmakers are still likely to water down the bankruptcy bill further in the industry's favor. Before the negotiations, Citigroup had been the only major bank to support the bankruptcy measure, often referred to as ''cram-down'' legislation because it would give judges the authority to dictate terms to lenders and investors who own mortgages bundled into securities.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/23/business/23bank.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Smaller Banks’ Losses Expected to Bring Mergers<date>Published: January 22, 2009</date><text>The government may view Bank of America and Citigroup as too big to fail, and dozens of smaller banks may soon find that size matters for them as well. Skip to next paragraph Al Behrman/Associated Press Fifth Third Bancorp reported a $2.2 billion quarterly loss. Multimedia Graphic Total TARP Funds Invested in Banks Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis -- The Essentials Capital One Financial, Fifth Third Bancorp, KeyCorp, Huntington Bancshares and SunTrust Banks announced sharp fourth-quarter losses on Thursday, the start of a trickle of red ink at the nation’s small and midsize lenders that could result in a flood of mergers in an industry that is already consolidating. Most of these banks were never big players in credit cards, subprime mortgages or credit-default swaps. But they were major lenders to commercial real estate developers, home builders and small corporations. As the recession tightens, losses have started to surge. “There will not be the shock and awe factor” of the big bank losses, said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. But “small and midsize banks are up to their eyeballs in commercial real estate related to residential development and business loans. We are going to see a reckoning with how bad that got” in 2009. Most small and regional banks will probably be able to slog through several more quarters of dismal results. But as their losses swell, pressure from investors and regulators could lead dozens of banks to start cutting deals. Gerard Cassidy, a veteran banking analyst, projected that 200 to 300 small banks might fail or be forced into mergers over the next year or so. While that is still a fraction of the industry’s 8,400 banks, it is up sharply from the 25 bank failures in 2008. “It is really going to be a combination of the depth of the recession and how long the regulators allow these things to stay open,” Mr. Cassidy added. Federal officials have been giving bailout money from the $700 billion Troubled Asset Relief Program to selected weaker banks. Lawmakers want them to make more loans to consumers and small businesses. Regulators, nervous about the banks’ fragile finances, have been making some investments conditional on a good-faith effort to find a stronger institution to merge with, according to several financial advisers. In other cases, like PNC Financial’s takeover of National City, regulators helped facilitate the acquisition through lucrative tax breaks and additional TARP money. PNC, which received nearly $7.6 billion in government money, was given National City’s share of the bailout funds to help it complete the deal. “If some of these guys are going to be weakened, they should be acquired,” said Bert Ely, a longtime banking industry consultant. “Regulators should really push the weak guys to do a deal.” So far, 288 small and midsize banks have received $78.8 billion of government money. That is about one-third of the nearly $249 billion awarded to the industry and less than the combined $90 billion in capital injections that Bank of America and Citigroup have received since last fall. As with larger banks, private investors are reluctant to pour capital into smaller institutions to offset their deepening losses. And because additional government support is uncertain, many small and midsize banks may be forced to take aggressive steps to survive. On Wednesday, SunTrust cut its dividend to 10 cents, from 54 cents; Huntington Bancshares slashed its dividend to a penny a share. These moves cost investors, but analysts say dozens of banks may follow suit to preserve billions of dollars’ worth of capital each year. Still others may be forced to take more drastic action. Some are already looking to sell off stronger businesses. SunTrust, for example, sold its long-held stake in the Coca-Cola Company for $2 billion last year to help it weather the credit storm. Some investment bankers expect Fifth Third to put its credit card processing unit or asset management units on the block. On a call with analysts, Fifth Third executives declined to comment. “It’s almost like the Bernie Madoff investors who have to pawn their family jewels,” said David Hendler, a financial analyst at CreditSights. “The banks have to sell what they can just to get by.” Other banks are ratcheting back on lending, even if it causes lawmakers to grumble. Bankers are already fearful about their exposure to troubled consumers running up big credit card balances and corporate loans tapping revolving credit lines. After enduring huge losses from doling out easy money in a boom economy, they are reluctant to lend into a global slump. Besides, the easiest way to free up capital is to reduce the size of their balance sheets. “The government’s rhetoric says that we want banks to lend to get the economy to expand,” Christopher Whalen, a managing partner at Institutional Risk Analytics. “The reality is the banking system is going to continue to shrink.” With stronger balance sheets and far less exposure to complex derivatives and risky trading, small and regional banks are unlikely to suffer the big quarterly losses of their larger rivals. Still, they will contend with more quarters of escalating losses. SunTrust, of Atlanta, swung to a $347.6 million loss in the fourth quarter amid rising real estate losses in Southeast. It has accepted more than $4.85 billion of government money and some analysts say it may need as much as $2.1 billion in additional capital to plug deepening holes. “We are under no illusions as to the severity of this credit cycle,” John M. Wells III, SunTrust’s chief executive, said. Capital One Financial, a credit card company with a regional banking arm in northern Virginia, reported a $1.42 billion loss amid rising consumer loan losses and a big charge tied to overpaying an auto lender. It accepted $3.6 billion in government money. Fifth Third, of Cincinnati, reported a $2.2 billion loss as consumer and commercial real estate loans soured in Florida, Michigan and Ohio. It received a $3.4 billion capital injection from the government last fall. KeyCorp, based in Cleveland, suffered a $524 million operating loss in the fourth quarter. The loss stemmed from increasing its reserves, shedding mortgage-related assets, and taking a big charge for overpaying on several earlier deals. It has received $2.5 billion in government money. Huntington Bancshares, another Ohio bank, which accepted $1.4 billion from the government, reported a $417.3 million loss in the fourth quarter. Even profitable banks were not immune. BB&amp;T, a North Carolina-based bank that accepted $3.1 billion in government money, said profit fell 26 percent to $305 million in the fourth quarter as it set aside more money to cover expected losses. Comerica, which has a big presence in Michigan and California, reported a $20 million profit, off sharply from last year. It announced plans to lay off 5 percent of its staff and freeze salaries for senior managers as it braced for more losses in 2009. Comerica accepted a $2.25 billion government infusion this fall. M&amp;T Bank, which took about $600 million in government money, has been among a handful of smaller banks where profits have remained strong. Net income at the Buffalo-based bank rose 57 percent to $102.2 million in the fourth quarter. Still, it suffered losses in its mortgage securities portfolio and expected more bad home and auto loans. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 23, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.The government may view Bank of America and Citigroup as too big to fail, and dozens of smaller banks may soon find that size matters for them as well. Skip to next paragraph Al Behrman/Associated Press Fifth Third Bancorp reported a $2.2 billion quarterly loss. Multimedia Graphic Total TARP Funds Invested in Banks Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis -- The Essentials Capital One Financial, Fifth Third Bancorp, KeyCorp, Huntington Bancshares and SunTrust Banks announced sharp fourth-quarter losses on Thursday, the start of a trickle of red ink at the nation’s small and midsize lenders that could result in a flood of mergers in an industry that is already consolidating. Most of these banks were never big players in credit cards, subprime mortgages or credit-default swaps. But they were major lenders to commercial real estate developers, home builders and small corporations. As the recession tightens, losses have started to surge. “There will not be the shock and awe factor” of the big bank losses, said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. But “small and midsize banks are up to their eyeballs in commercial real estate related to residential development and business loans. We are going to see a reckoning with how bad that got” in 2009. Most small and regional banks will probably be able to slog through several more quarters of dismal results. But as their losses swell, pressure from investors and regulators could lead dozens of banks to start cutting deals. Gerard Cassidy, a veteran banking analyst, projected that 200 to 300 small banks might fail or be forced into mergers over the next year or so. While that is still a fraction of the industry’s 8,400 banks, it is up sharply from the 25 bank failures in 2008. “It is really going to be a combination of the depth of the recession and how long the regulators allow these things to stay open,” Mr. Cassidy added. Federal officials have been giving bailout money from the $700 billion Troubled Asset Relief Program to selected weaker banks. Lawmakers want them to make more loans to consumers and small businesses. Regulators, nervous about the banks’ fragile finances, have been making some investments conditional on a good-faith effort to find a stronger institution to merge with, according to several financial advisers. In other cases, like PNC Financial’s takeover of National City, regulators helped facilitate the acquisition through lucrative tax breaks and additional TARP money. PNC, which received nearly $7.6 billion in government money, was given National City’s share of the bailout funds to help it complete the deal. “If some of these guys are going to be weakened, they should be acquired,” said Bert Ely, a longtime banking industry consultant. “Regulators should really push the weak guys to do a deal.” So far, 288 small and midsize banks have received $78.8 billion of government money. That is about one-third of the nearly $249 billion awarded to the industry and less than the combined $90 billion in capital injections that Bank of America and Citigroup have received since last fall. As with larger banks, private investors are reluctant to pour capital into smaller institutions to offset their deepening losses. And because additional government support is uncertain, many small and midsize banks may be forced to take aggressive steps to survive. On Wednesday, SunTrust cut its dividend to 10 cents, from 54 cents; Huntington Bancshares slashed its dividend to a penny a share. These moves cost investors, but analysts say dozens of banks may follow suit to preserve billions of dollars’ worth of capital each year. Still others may be forced to take more drastic action. Some are already looking to sell off stronger businesses. SunTrust, for example, sold its long-held stake in the Coca-Cola Company for $2 billion last year to help it weather the credit storm. Some investment bankers expect Fifth Third to put its credit card processing unit or asset management units on the block. On a call with analysts, Fifth Third executives declined to comment. “It’s almost like the Bernie Madoff investors who have to pawn their family jewels,” said David Hendler, a financial analyst at CreditSights. “The banks have to sell what they can just to get by.” Other banks are ratcheting back on lending, even if it causes lawmakers to grumble. Bankers are already fearful about their exposure to troubled consumers running up big credit card balances and corporate loans tapping revolving credit lines. After enduring huge losses from doling out easy money in a boom economy, they are reluctant to lend into a global slump. Besides, the easiest way to free up capital is to reduce the size of their balance sheets. “The government’s rhetoric says that we want banks to lend to get the economy to expand,” Christopher Whalen, a managing partner at Institutional Risk Analytics. “The reality is the banking system is going to continue to shrink.” With stronger balance sheets and far less exposure to complex derivatives and risky trading, small and regional banks are unlikely to suffer the big quarterly losses of their larger rivals. Still, they will contend with more quarters of escalating losses. SunTrust, of Atlanta, swung to a $347.6 million loss in the fourth quarter amid rising real estate losses in Southeast. It has accepted more than $4.85 billion of government money and some analysts say it may need as much as $2.1 billion in additional capital to plug deepening holes. “We are under no illusions as to the severity of this credit cycle,” John M. Wells III, SunTrust’s chief executive, said. Capital One Financial, a credit card company with a regional banking arm in northern Virginia, reported a $1.42 billion loss amid rising consumer loan losses and a big charge tied to overpaying an auto lender. It accepted $3.6 billion in government money. Fifth Third, of Cincinnati, reported a $2.2 billion loss as consumer and commercial real estate loans soured in Florida, Michigan and Ohio. It received a $3.4 billion capital injection from the government last fall. KeyCorp, based in Cleveland, suffered a $524 million operating loss in the fourth quarter. The loss stemmed from increasing its reserves, shedding mortgage-related assets, and taking a big charge for overpaying on several earlier deals. It has received $2.5 billion in government money. Huntington Bancshares, another Ohio bank, which accepted $1.4 billion from the government, reported a $417.3 million loss in the fourth quarter. Even profitable banks were not immune. BB&amp;T, a North Carolina-based bank that accepted $3.1 billion in government money, said profit fell 26 percent to $305 million in the fourth quarter as it set aside more money to cover expected losses. Comerica, which has a big presence in Michigan and California, reported a $20 million profit, off sharply from last year. It announced plans to lay off 5 percent of its staff and freeze salaries for senior managers as it braced for more losses in 2009. Comerica accepted a $2.25 billion government infusion this fall. M&amp;T Bank, which took about $600 million in government money, has been among a handful of smaller banks where profits have remained strong. Net income at the Buffalo-based bank rose 57 percent to $102.2 million in the fourth quarter. Still, it suffered losses in its mortgage securities portfolio and expected more bad home and auto loans.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/13/business/13gret.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">You Thought You Had an Equity Line<date>Published: April 13, 2008</date><text>IT was the nation’s lending institutions and mortgage originators that got us into this credit mess, but it is consumers, taxpayers and those companies’ shareholders who will end up shouldering most of the costs. Skip to next paragraph Related Columnist Page: Gretchen Morgenson The latest example of this is in the mass freezing of home equity lines of credit going on across the country. Reeling from losses on their wretched loan decisions of recent years, lenders are preventing borrowers with pristine credit and significant equity in their homes from tapping into credit lines that they paid dearly to secure. In the last 30 days, lenders have sent several hundred thousand letters advising borrowers that their home equity lines of credit are frozen, estimated Michael A. Kratzer, president of FeeDisclosure.com, a Web site intended to help consumers reduce fees on home loans. Major lenders  including Washington Mutual, IndyMac Bank and the Greenpoint Mortgage Unit of Capital One  say that declining property values are prompting the decisions to cut off credit. Banks have the right, of course, to rescind these credit lines at any time under the terms of the contracts they struck with borrowers. And as home prices have tumbled in many parts of the country, banks are undoubtedly trying to protect themselves from exposure to additional losses. But these actions are being taken even in areas where property prices are rising, Mr. Kratzer said. What’s worse, the letters provide no explanation for how the lenders determined that the property values underlying the equity lines had fallen. Frozen home equity lines will surely intensify the consumer spending downturn and put added pressure on an already weak economy. Indeed, on Friday, consumer confidence as measured by the University of Michigan plummeted to its lowest level since 1982. The drop was attributed mostly to higher fuel and food costs, but consumers’ views on their current and expected personal financial situations dropped to their lowest readings since November 1982 and April 1980, respectively. One especially exasperating aspect of now-you-see-them, now-you-don’t equity lines is that borrowers are not receiving refunds for fees they paid to secure the credit in the first place. These fees can be significant, Mr. Kratzer said: on a $50,000 line, for example, fees of $1,500 are common. If the line is being frozen at, say, $25,000, why shouldn’t the borrower be entitled to receive a refund of $750? Borrowers who have an excellent credit score may also find that status hurt when a home equity line is frozen. That is because when a lender suddenly caps a $50,000 line at $25,000, the borrower will appear to have tapped the entire amount of the loan, a factor that can reduce a person’s credit score. Never mind that, based on the original amount of the credit line, the borrower is using only half of it. Ronald Martin, 31, a United States naval aviator deployed in Iraq, received one of these letters recently from IndyMac Bank. “We regret to inform you that your IndyMac Bank Home Equity account has been temporarily frozen,” the letter began. Mr. Martin’s wife, Leigh Anne, a substitute teacher who lives in their Camarillo, Calif., home, said the notice surprised her because she and her husband have excellent credit scores and have not even tapped the IndyMac line. While home values in the Martins’ neighborhood have fallen, the couple are not underwater on their mortgage, which was taken out in spring 2005. “YOU paid to use that equity line and now they are saying you can’t use it,” Mrs. Martin said. “We’ve never been late on our mortgage. We have a good savings account. We pay every bill we ever had on time  what did we do wrong?” The IndyMac letter said the Martins’ credit was being suspended because “the value of the dwelling has declined significantly below its appraised value used at origination.” IndyMac said it would re-evaluate the property value each quarter and, if it improved, the freeze would be lifted. Officials representing IndyMac declined to comment. Sara Gaugl, a Washington Mutual spokeswoman, said the bank actively manages the amount of credit it extends to customers. “We have a process in place for customers who wish to appeal a credit line decrease decision,” she said. “We also will continue to assist homeowners who may have unique or special situations.” Mr. Kratzer, who has recently fielded calls and e-mail messages from more than 500 borrowers in straits similar to the Martins’, said lenders who were reining in credit should provide an explanation of how they determined that property values associated with the lines had declined sharply. “How are lenders arriving at the new loan-to-value ratios?” Mr. Kratzer asked. “When you secure a loan or home equity line, a full appraisal is generally required. But these processes aren’t being used when the lender calculates a new value to reduce an existing credit line.” Mr. Kratzer said he had heard from frozen-out borrowers in 11 metropolitan areas where the median home price actually increased in the last quarter of 2007, the most recent figures available from the National Association of Realtors. They include Yakima, Wash.; Appleton, Wis.; Raleigh-Cary, N.C.; and Champaign-Urbana, Ill. Borrowers in areas where prices remained flat have also contacted him. “Are they applying blanket values to ZIP codes, neighborhoods or entire regions?” Mr. Kratzer said. “We’re all left to wonder about the process.” Luckily for the Martins, they are not in need of additional credit on their IndyMac line. But other borrowers who have contacted Mr. Kratzer say they are in the middle of home improvement projects that they can no longer finance, or have college tuition bills that they were going to pay using the credit lines. Now they can’t. Medical expenses, another reason that borrowers tap their equity lines, are also posing problems for some homeowners. And small-business owners who use home equity lines to bridge cash-flow gaps throughout the year are also being stricken by these curbs, Mr. Kratzer said. He has also heard from people who paid down some of their home equity lines, expecting to be able to draw on them again. Now they are out of luck. “In a perfect world, lenders would fully disclose the process and criteria used to make these valuations and decisions,” Mr. Kratzer said. “These borrowers have a solid payment history, good credit scores and plenty of equity to satisfy most of the lenders’ loan-to-value formulas. Instead, the banks are just shutting them off.” More Articles in Business »IT was the nation’s lending institutions and mortgage originators that got us into this credit mess, but it is consumers, taxpayers and those companies’ shareholders who will end up shouldering most of the costs. Skip to next paragraph Related Columnist Page: Gretchen Morgenson The latest example of this is in the mass freezing of home equity lines of credit going on across the country. Reeling from losses on their wretched loan decisions of recent years, lenders are preventing borrowers with pristine credit and significant equity in their homes from tapping into credit lines that they paid dearly to secure. In the last 30 days, lenders have sent several hundred thousand letters advising borrowers that their home equity lines of credit are frozen, estimated Michael A. Kratzer, president of FeeDisclosure.com, a Web site intended to help consumers reduce fees on home loans. Major lenders  including Washington Mutual, IndyMac Bank and the Greenpoint Mortgage Unit of Capital One  say that declining property values are prompting the decisions to cut off credit. Banks have the right, of course, to rescind these credit lines at any time under the terms of the contracts they struck with borrowers. And as home prices have tumbled in many parts of the country, banks are undoubtedly trying to protect themselves from exposure to additional losses. But these actions are being taken even in areas where property prices are rising, Mr. Kratzer said. What’s worse, the letters provide no explanation for how the lenders determined that the property values underlying the equity lines had fallen. Frozen home equity lines will surely intensify the consumer spending downturn and put added pressure on an already weak economy. Indeed, on Friday, consumer confidence as measured by the University of Michigan plummeted to its lowest level since 1982. The drop was attributed mostly to higher fuel and food costs, but consumers’ views on their current and expected personal financial situations dropped to their lowest readings since November 1982 and April 1980, respectively. One especially exasperating aspect of now-you-see-them, now-you-don’t equity lines is that borrowers are not receiving refunds for fees they paid to secure the credit in the first place. These fees can be significant, Mr. Kratzer said: on a $50,000 line, for example, fees of $1,500 are common. If the line is being frozen at, say, $25,000, why shouldn’t the borrower be entitled to receive a refund of $750? Borrowers who have an excellent credit score may also find that status hurt when a home equity line is frozen. That is because when a lender suddenly caps a $50,000 line at $25,000, the borrower will appear to have tapped the entire amount of the loan, a factor that can reduce a person’s credit score. Never mind that, based on the original amount of the credit line, the borrower is using only half of it. Ronald Martin, 31, a United States naval aviator deployed in Iraq, received one of these letters recently from IndyMac Bank. “We regret to inform you that your IndyMac Bank Home Equity account has been temporarily frozen,” the letter began. Mr. Martin’s wife, Leigh Anne, a substitute teacher who lives in their Camarillo, Calif., home, said the notice surprised her because she and her husband have excellent credit scores and have not even tapped the IndyMac line. While home values in the Martins’ neighborhood have fallen, the couple are not underwater on their mortgage, which was taken out in spring 2005. “YOU paid to use that equity line and now they are saying you can’t use it,” Mrs. Martin said. “We’ve never been late on our mortgage. We have a good savings account. We pay every bill we ever had on time  what did we do wrong?” The IndyMac letter said the Martins’ credit was being suspended because “the value of the dwelling has declined significantly below its appraised value used at origination.” IndyMac said it would re-evaluate the property value each quarter and, if it improved, the freeze would be lifted. Officials representing IndyMac declined to comment. Sara Gaugl, a Washington Mutual spokeswoman, said the bank actively manages the amount of credit it extends to customers. “We have a process in place for customers who wish to appeal a credit line decrease decision,” she said. “We also will continue to assist homeowners who may have unique or special situations.” Mr. Kratzer, who has recently fielded calls and e-mail messages from more than 500 borrowers in straits similar to the Martins’, said lenders who were reining in credit should provide an explanation of how they determined that property values associated with the lines had declined sharply. “How are lenders arriving at the new loan-to-value ratios?” Mr. Kratzer asked. “When you secure a loan or home equity line, a full appraisal is generally required. But these processes aren’t being used when the lender calculates a new value to reduce an existing credit line.” Mr. Kratzer said he had heard from frozen-out borrowers in 11 metropolitan areas where the median home price actually increased in the last quarter of 2007, the most recent figures available from the National Association of Realtors. They include Yakima, Wash.; Appleton, Wis.; Raleigh-Cary, N.C.; and Champaign-Urbana, Ill. Borrowers in areas where prices remained flat have also contacted him. “Are they applying blanket values to ZIP codes, neighborhoods or entire regions?” Mr. Kratzer said. “We’re all left to wonder about the process.” Luckily for the Martins, they are not in need of additional credit on their IndyMac line. But other borrowers who have contacted Mr. Kratzer say they are in the middle of home improvement projects that they can no longer finance, or have college tuition bills that they were going to pay using the credit lines. Now they can’t. Medical expenses, another reason that borrowers tap their equity lines, are also posing problems for some homeowners. And small-business owners who use home equity lines to bridge cash-flow gaps throughout the year are also being stricken by these curbs, Mr. Kratzer said. He has also heard from people who paid down some of their home equity lines, expecting to be able to draw on them again. Now they are out of luck. “In a perfect world, lenders would fully disclose the process and criteria used to make these valuations and decisions,” Mr. Kratzer said. “These borrowers have a solid payment history, good credit scores and plenty of equity to satisfy most of the lenders’ loan-to-value formulas. Instead, the banks are just shutting them off.”</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5D7113CF937A15752C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Profit Falls 42% at Capital One<date>Published: January 24, 2008</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, the credit card issuer, said Wednesday that fourth-quarter profit fell 42 percent as more borrowers failed to repay their debts. Net income of $226.6 million, or 60 cents a share, compared with $390.7 million, or $1.14 a share, a year earlier, the company, based in McLean, Va., said Wednesday. Capital One, American Express and Citigroup have increased reserves for failed loans in the fourth quarter by more than $4 billion. Capital One is the No. 4 issuer of Visa and MasterCard credit cards by volume of purchases and cash advances, according to The Nilson Report, an industry newsletter. Bank of America, JPMorgan Chase and Citigroup are larger.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/12/business/12charts.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Some Debt Trends Are Good. This Isn’t One of Them.<date>Published: January 12, 2008</date><text>AMERICAN credit card debt is growing at the fastest rate in years, a fact that may signal coming trouble for the banks that issue them. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Credit Cards Get More Use; Home Equity Loans Rise The Federal Reserve reported this week that the amount of revolving consumer credit that is outstanding hit $937.5 billion in November, seasonally adjusted, up 7.4 percent from a year earlier. The annual growth rate has now been over 7 percent for three months running, the first such stretch since 2001, when a recession was driving up borrowing by hard-pressed consumers. The surge in credit card borrowing comes as credit card default rates are gradually rising, albeit from low levels, and may reflect the fact that it has become harder for consumers to borrow against the value of their homes, both because home values have fallen in many markets and because mortgage lending standards have tightened. “We believe that credit card performance will noticeably deteriorate during the year,” Fitch Ratings said in a report this week, “given spillover from residential mortgages, weaker economic trends and higher levels of unemployment.” One of the largest credit card issuers in the country, Capital One, warned that its profits would be lower than expected, in part because of rising credit card delinquencies. Increases in outstanding credit card debt can indicate a strong economy, as confident consumers spend more, or it can indicate the opposite, as troubled consumers find it harder to pay their bills. The fact that the November increases in credit card debt came during what appears to have been a weak holiday shopping season could be an indication of the latter. The figures in the accompanying charts are based on seasonally adjusted figures. Before such adjustments, credit card balances always build up in November and December as holiday purchases are made, and then fall in January and February. A smaller-than-normal increase in December, when the figures are reported next month, may be expected from the reports of poor sales from chain stores. If the increase in outstanding debt is a normal one, that could indicate that payments slowed because consumers are having trouble making ends meet. The same would be true if the declines in January and February are smaller than usual. A turnaround in trends for home equity loans could also be a sign of consumer worries. In the spring, as credit tightened, the amount of outstanding home equity loans fell and credit card debt rose. That could indicate that consumers turned to credit cards when new loans were no longer being approved. But the amount of outstanding home equity loans bottomed out in April, and over the past six months is up 5 percent. That increase may reflect the nature of home equity loans, which typically give consumers the right to borrow up to a certain amount of money. It seems likely that the latest increases reflect borrowing by consumers with pre-existing lines of credit that they are now tapping, rather than newly approved loans. The holiday sales data indicated that consumers cut back in late 2007. But the consumer credit numbers would seem to indicate that they wound up further in debt anyway. Those are not good signs for the economy as 2008 begins. E-mail: norris@nytimes.com More Articles in Business »AMERICAN credit card debt is growing at the fastest rate in years, a fact that may signal coming trouble for the banks that issue them. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Credit Cards Get More Use; Home Equity Loans Rise The Federal Reserve reported this week that the amount of revolving consumer credit that is outstanding hit $937.5 billion in November, seasonally adjusted, up 7.4 percent from a year earlier. The annual growth rate has now been over 7 percent for three months running, the first such stretch since 2001, when a recession was driving up borrowing by hard-pressed consumers. The surge in credit card borrowing comes as credit card default rates are gradually rising, albeit from low levels, and may reflect the fact that it has become harder for consumers to borrow against the value of their homes, both because home values have fallen in many markets and because mortgage lending standards have tightened. “We believe that credit card performance will noticeably deteriorate during the year,” Fitch Ratings said in a report this week, “given spillover from residential mortgages, weaker economic trends and higher levels of unemployment.” One of the largest credit card issuers in the country, Capital One, warned that its profits would be lower than expected, in part because of rising credit card delinquencies. Increases in outstanding credit card debt can indicate a strong economy, as confident consumers spend more, or it can indicate the opposite, as troubled consumers find it harder to pay their bills. The fact that the November increases in credit card debt came during what appears to have been a weak holiday shopping season could be an indication of the latter. The figures in the accompanying charts are based on seasonally adjusted figures. Before such adjustments, credit card balances always build up in November and December as holiday purchases are made, and then fall in January and February. A smaller-than-normal increase in December, when the figures are reported next month, may be expected from the reports of poor sales from chain stores. If the increase in outstanding debt is a normal one, that could indicate that payments slowed because consumers are having trouble making ends meet. The same would be true if the declines in January and February are smaller than usual. A turnaround in trends for home equity loans could also be a sign of consumer worries. In the spring, as credit tightened, the amount of outstanding home equity loans fell and credit card debt rose. That could indicate that consumers turned to credit cards when new loans were no longer being approved. But the amount of outstanding home equity loans bottomed out in April, and over the past six months is up 5 percent. That increase may reflect the nature of home equity loans, which typically give consumers the right to borrow up to a certain amount of money. It seems likely that the latest increases reflect borrowing by consumers with pre-existing lines of credit that they are now tapping, rather than newly approved loans. The holiday sales data indicated that consumers cut back in late 2007. But the consumer credit numbers would seem to indicate that they wound up further in debt anyway. Those are not good signs for the economy as 2008 begins. E-mail: norris@nytimes.com</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/11/business/11card.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">American Express Warns About Earnings<date>Published: January 11, 2008</date><text>American Express forecast first-quarter earnings below analysts’ estimates on Thursday and adopted a “cautious view” for 2008 because of a slowing economy. The company will take a $275 million fourth-quarter charge as more cardholders fail to repay their debts, the company, based in New York, said in a statement. Its stock fell 7 percent in extended trading. Credit card companies have been increasing their estimates of bad loans as a weakening economy makes it harder for consumers to pay their debts. American Express said its first-quarter 2008 earnings from continuing operations would be less than the 90 cents a share in the period in 2007, missing the 93-cent average estimate of 12 analysts surveyed by Bloomberg. Another credit card company, The Capital One Financial Corporation, said that its 2007 earnings would fall short of its previous expectations because of increased loan delinquencies and additional legal reserves. The company said in a statement that it expected a t fourth-quarter profit of 60 cents a share and full-year earnings of about $3.97 a share, below its forecast of “about $5 per share.” The company said it was taking a $1.9 billion provision for loan losses in the fourth quarter, including about $1.3 billion in charge-offs. More Articles in Business »American Express forecast first-quarter earnings below analysts’ estimates on Thursday and adopted a “cautious view” for 2008 because of a slowing economy. The company will take a $275 million fourth-quarter charge as more cardholders fail to repay their debts, the company, based in New York, said in a statement. Its stock fell 7 percent in extended trading. Credit card companies have been increasing their estimates of bad loans as a weakening economy makes it harder for consumers to pay their debts. American Express said its first-quarter 2008 earnings from continuing operations would be less than the 90 cents a share in the period in 2007, missing the 93-cent average estimate of 12 analysts surveyed by Bloomberg. Another credit card company, The Capital One Financial Corporation, said that its 2007 earnings would fall short of its previous expectations because of increased loan delinquencies and additional legal reserves. The company said in a statement that it expected a t fourth-quarter profit of 60 cents a share and full-year earnings of about $3.97 a share, below its forecast of “about $5 per share.” The company said it was taking a $1.9 billion provision for loan losses in the fourth quarter, including about $1.3 billion in charge-offs.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/02/sports/ncaafootball/02capital.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">The Wolverines Ride Emotion, and Henne’s Arm, to Victory<date>Published: January 2, 2008</date><text>ORLANDO, Fla.  Before Michigan played Florida in the Capital One Bowl in the final game of Coach Lloyd Carr’s career Tuesday, he addressed his team with tears in his eyes and emotion in his voice, his players said. Skip to next paragraph Related Sports of The Times: Michigan Will Miss Carr When Hes Gone (January 1, 2008) Interviews, insight and analysis from The Times on the competition and culture of college football. Go to The Quad Blog » Division I-A Scores: Top 25 | All Div. I-A Bowl Dates | Statistics Conferences and Teams 2007 B.C.S. Rankings A.P. Poll | USA Today Discuss College Football Small Colleges Div. I-AA | Div. II | Div. III Doug Benc/Getty Images Mike Hart ran for 129 yards and 2 touchdowns for Michigan, which also got 373 passing yards and 3 touchdowns from quarterback Chad Henne. Doug Benc/Getty Images Michigan receiver Mario Manningham caught a touchdown pass between Florida safety Major Wright, left, and cornerback Wondy Pierre-Louis during the Capital One Bowl. After the game ended with a 41-35 Michigan victory before 69,748 fans in Citrus Bowl Stadium, the Wolverines started to carry Carr off the field on their shoulders. But the 62-year-old Carr ordered them to put him down. He said he wanted to speak with Urban Meyer, the coach of the Gators. “Lloyd said, ‘Some day, you’re going to retire,’” Meyer said of their conversation, “‘and your players are going to play as hard as my guys did.’” Both teams played hard and Michigan came from behind in the fourth quarter after squandering a two-touchdown lead. The game was filled with dramatic moments, trick plays, fluke twists, violent collisions and lots of trash-talking. The finish was frantic, and both teams wound up with 9-4 records. The Gators were the national champions last season and the Wolverines have been a powerhouse for a century. Michigan might have scored even more, but it turned over the ball four times, twice on fumbles by running back Mike Hart near the Florida goal line. “We knew we could move the ball,” quarterback Chad Henne said. “We stopped ourselves. They didn’t really stop us.” Jake Long, an offensive tackle, said Henne told the linemen to give the receivers time to get open “and he’ll pick them apart.” Henne, who threw two interceptions, completed 25 of 39 passes for 373 yards and 3 touchdowns. Hart gained 129 yards on 32 carries and scored 2 touchdowns. Adrian Arrington caught nine passes for 153 yards and 2 touchdowns. The Wolverines won with a version of the spread offense that they installed after the regular season to exploit the inexperience of Florida’s defense and the talent of Arrington and Mario Manningham, who caught five passes for 78 yards and a touchdown. On the other side of the ball, the Wolverines contained Florida quarterback Tim Tebow, who won this season’s Heisman Trophy as a sophomore. Although Tebow threw three touchdown passes and accumulated 209 yards through runs and passes, he was hampered by the blitzing of the Wolverines, who often knocked him to the ground after he threw the ball. It was only the second meeting between the Wolverines, of the Big Ten, and the Gators, of the Southeastern Conference. Michigan won the first in the Outback Bowl in 2003. In between, Michigan lost four consecutive bowl games. “They were a hungry team,” Tebow said. “They came out ready to fight. They heard a lot about the SEC and wanted a piece.” Among the impressive Gators was Percy Harvin, who caught nine passes for 77 yards and a touchdown and ran 13 times for 165 yards and another touchdown. The Gators ran four plays from scrimmage on fourth down, converting two, one on a fake punt. Meyer did this in part because, he said, “I didn’t think we could stop them” if the Wolverines got the ball back. Florida took its second lead of the game, 35-31, with 5 minutes 49 seconds left on a 10-yard run by Harvin. Michigan got the lead back 1:37 later on Arrington’s 18-yard reception to complete a sizzling drive of 67 yards on four plays. Florida got the ball back twice after that, but could not gain a first down. Tebow’s last six passes fell incomplete, the final one while he fell backward under intense pressure deep in Gator territory. “We got in his face,” said Shawn Crable, the Michigan linebacker who had suggested before the game that Tebow was overrated. “We hit him up high,” Crable said. “We got to him more than he thought he was going to get hit.” Crable, a senior, spoke as he sat on a folding chair beneath the grandstand. He wore a pinstriped dress suit, and his grass-stained jersey was draped over his shoulder. Like many Wolverines, Crable discussed Carr, who will be replaced next season by Rich Rodriguez, who was hired from West Virginia. “He made me into a man,” Crable said of Carr. “I came in at age 18 and I thought I knew everything. Now, I’m a little smarter. He was more than a coach.” In his postgame news conference, Carr’s eyes were moist and his voice cracked a little. He was frequently asked to sum up a career that began as a Michigan assistant to Bo Schembechler in 1980 after starting as a high school assistant in 1968. “I told them I loved them,” he said of his players. “Every guy in that locker room from here on out will be my friend. That is one of the joys of coaching.” More Articles in Sports »ORLANDO, Fla.  Before Michigan played Florida in the Capital One Bowl in the final game of Coach Lloyd Carr’s career Tuesday, he addressed his team with tears in his eyes and emotion in his voice, his players said. Skip to next paragraph Related Sports of The Times: Michigan Will Miss Carr When Hes Gone (January 1, 2008) Interviews, insight and analysis from The Times on the competition and culture of college football. Go to The Quad Blog » Division I-A Scores: Top 25 | All Div. I-A Bowl Dates | Statistics Conferences and Teams 2007 B.C.S. Rankings A.P. Poll | USA Today Discuss College Football Small Colleges Div. I-AA | Div. II | Div. III Doug Benc/Getty Images Mike Hart ran for 129 yards and 2 touchdowns for Michigan, which also got 373 passing yards and 3 touchdowns from quarterback Chad Henne. Doug Benc/Getty Images Michigan receiver Mario Manningham caught a touchdown pass between Florida safety Major Wright, left, and cornerback Wondy Pierre-Louis during the Capital One Bowl. After the game ended with a 41-35 Michigan victory before 69,748 fans in Citrus Bowl Stadium, the Wolverines started to carry Carr off the field on their shoulders. But the 62-year-old Carr ordered them to put him down. He said he wanted to speak with Urban Meyer, the coach of the Gators. “Lloyd said, ‘Some day, you’re going to retire,’” Meyer said of their conversation, “‘and your players are going to play as hard as my guys did.’” Both teams played hard and Michigan came from behind in the fourth quarter after squandering a two-touchdown lead. The game was filled with dramatic moments, trick plays, fluke twists, violent collisions and lots of trash-talking. The finish was frantic, and both teams wound up with 9-4 records. The Gators were the national champions last season and the Wolverines have been a powerhouse for a century. Michigan might have scored even more, but it turned over the ball four times, twice on fumbles by running back Mike Hart near the Florida goal line. “We knew we could move the ball,” quarterback Chad Henne said. “We stopped ourselves. They didn’t really stop us.” Jake Long, an offensive tackle, said Henne told the linemen to give the receivers time to get open “and he’ll pick them apart.” Henne, who threw two interceptions, completed 25 of 39 passes for 373 yards and 3 touchdowns. Hart gained 129 yards on 32 carries and scored 2 touchdowns. Adrian Arrington caught nine passes for 153 yards and 2 touchdowns. The Wolverines won with a version of the spread offense that they installed after the regular season to exploit the inexperience of Florida’s defense and the talent of Arrington and Mario Manningham, who caught five passes for 78 yards and a touchdown. On the other side of the ball, the Wolverines contained Florida quarterback Tim Tebow, who won this season’s Heisman Trophy as a sophomore. Although Tebow threw three touchdown passes and accumulated 209 yards through runs and passes, he was hampered by the blitzing of the Wolverines, who often knocked him to the ground after he threw the ball. It was only the second meeting between the Wolverines, of the Big Ten, and the Gators, of the Southeastern Conference. Michigan won the first in the Outback Bowl in 2003. In between, Michigan lost four consecutive bowl games. “They were a hungry team,” Tebow said. “They came out ready to fight. They heard a lot about the SEC and wanted a piece.” Among the impressive Gators was Percy Harvin, who caught nine passes for 77 yards and a touchdown and ran 13 times for 165 yards and another touchdown. The Gators ran four plays from scrimmage on fourth down, converting two, one on a fake punt. Meyer did this in part because, he said, “I didn’t think we could stop them” if the Wolverines got the ball back. Florida took its second lead of the game, 35-31, with 5 minutes 49 seconds left on a 10-yard run by Harvin. Michigan got the lead back 1:37 later on Arrington’s 18-yard reception to complete a sizzling drive of 67 yards on four plays. Florida got the ball back twice after that, but could not gain a first down. Tebow’s last six passes fell incomplete, the final one while he fell backward under intense pressure deep in Gator territory. “We got in his face,” said Shawn Crable, the Michigan linebacker who had suggested before the game that Tebow was overrated. “We hit him up high,” Crable said. “We got to him more than he thought he was going to get hit.” Crable, a senior, spoke as he sat on a folding chair beneath the grandstand. He wore a pinstriped dress suit, and his grass-stained jersey was draped over his shoulder. Like many Wolverines, Crable discussed Carr, who will be replaced next season by Rich Rodriguez, who was hired from West Virginia. “He made me into a man,” Crable said of Carr. “I came in at age 18 and I thought I knew everything. Now, I’m a little smarter. He was more than a coach.” In his postgame news conference, Carr’s eyes were moist and his voice cracked a little. He was frequently asked to sum up a career that began as a Michigan assistant to Bo Schembechler in 1980 after starting as a high school assistant in 1968. “I told them I loved them,” he said of his players. “Every guy in that locker room from here on out will be my friend. That is one of the joys of coaching.”</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/10/technology/10online.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Big Fees for Little Credit<date>Published: November 10, 2007</date><text>Correction Appended SOME issuers of credit cards are quietly collecting hundreds of millions of dollars in profits selling nearly worthless, predatory credit cards targeting vulnerable consumers, including those with bad credit, according to a report published this week by the National Consumer Law Center (consumerlaw.org). Skip to next paragraph Alex Eben Meyer Related National Consumer Law Center (consumerlaw.org) Credit Card Companies Abuse the Unwitting (npr.org) Fee-Harvester Cards: Credit Cards That Are Really Just Fee-Generating Scams (californiacreditlaw.com) World's Deepest Mines Highlight Risks of New Gold Rush (nationalgeographic.com) Dell Dude Now Tequila Dude at Tortilla Flats (nymag.com) How quietly these companies are operating may be open to question. But the report states that some companies issue cards with the sole intent of collecting fees from gullible customers  not offering them credit. A typical example the law center offered was this: a card issued with a credit limit of $250. After a $95 program fee, a $29 setup fee, a $6 monthly participation fee and a $48 annual fee, the consumer winds up with an instant debt of $178 and buying power of only $72. Included in the report is the tale of a sailor on leave who charged $85 to her new card. Because of all the fees, that put her over her $250 limit, which led to penalties and a balance of more than $300. The report names various companies that have issued these cards, including Capital One. That bank sometimes has used fee harvesting, according to the report. A Capital One spokeswoman denied that, noting that while the company offers a full spectrum of credit products, the only fees assessed, including ones on low-end cards, are late fees and those imposed on borrowers who go over their limits. Unlike other issuers of subprime cards, she said, we dont impose application, processing or other such fees. The report, she said, completely mischaracterized our business model. The report singled out CompuCredit, based in Atlanta, saying it has been frustrated in efforts to get its own bank charter. The law center said CompuCredits financial statements revealed that the issuer collected $400 million in fees from a portfolio of fee harvester cards that by mid-2007 had saddled cardholders with nearly $1 billion in debt. The company issued a statement, reported this week on National Public Radio (npr.org), calling the report misleading. It also sent a letter to the law center before the report was published insisting, among other things, that its cards meet or exceed the federal regulatory requirements and industry best practices. The California Credit Law Blog (californiacreditlaw.com), run by a San Francisco law firm, said, the fee harvester cards look like credit cards, but they have little or nothing to do with issuing credit. GOING DEEP The soaring price of gold is causing mining companies in South Africa to sink to astonishing depths. Gold Fields plans to drill to 2.5 miles at a mine outside Johannesburg, and that would be a record, reports National Geographic News (news.nationalgeographic.com). Other companies arent far below (or, above) that mark. But the deepest mine in the United States reaches just 8,000 feet. The risks of what is called ultradeep mining are high. Temperatures rise above 100 degrees and rock shatters like glass, according to Nicholas Wadhams of National Geographic. And, he says, some seismologists believe such deep mines can potentially cause tremors in the Earth. THE DUDE ABIDES Do you ever wonder what became of the Dude, youre getting a Dell dude? New York magazines Grub Street blog caught up with Ben Curtis, the onetime pitchman, at his new workplace: Tortilla Flats, a Manhattan Tex-Mex restaurant, where he tends bar (nymag.com/daily/food). Is he often recognized? Every day, he said. Its really difficult, but its a humbling experience. There were times when I made boatloads of money as an actor, but here I can be myself. Complete links are at nytimes.com/business. Correction: November 13, 2007 The “What’s Online” column in Business Day on Saturday, about a report on credit cards published by the National Consumer Law Center, misstated the organization’s Web address. The correct address is consumerlaw.org, not consumerlaw.com. More Articles in Technology »Correction Appended SOME issuers of credit cards are quietly collecting hundreds of millions of dollars in profits selling nearly worthless, predatory credit cards targeting vulnerable consumers, including those with bad credit, according to a report published this week by the National Consumer Law Center (consumerlaw.org). Skip to next paragraph Alex Eben Meyer Related National Consumer Law Center (consumerlaw.org) Credit Card Companies Abuse the Unwitting (npr.org) Fee-Harvester Cards: Credit Cards That Are Really Just Fee-Generating Scams (californiacreditlaw.com) World's Deepest Mines Highlight Risks of New Gold Rush (nationalgeographic.com) Dell Dude Now Tequila Dude at Tortilla Flats (nymag.com) How quietly these companies are operating may be open to question. But the report states that some companies issue cards with the sole intent of collecting fees from gullible customers  not offering them credit. A typical example the law center offered was this: a card issued with a credit limit of $250. After a $95 program fee, a $29 setup fee, a $6 monthly participation fee and a $48 annual fee, the consumer winds up with an instant debt of $178 and buying power of only $72. Included in the report is the tale of a sailor on leave who charged $85 to her new card. Because of all the fees, that put her over her $250 limit, which led to penalties and a balance of more than $300. The report names various companies that have issued these cards, including Capital One. That bank sometimes has used fee harvesting, according to the report. A Capital One spokeswoman denied that, noting that while the company offers a full spectrum of credit products, the only fees assessed, including ones on low-end cards, are late fees and those imposed on borrowers who go over their limits. Unlike other issuers of subprime cards, she said, we dont impose application, processing or other such fees. The report, she said, completely mischaracterized our business model. The report singled out CompuCredit, based in Atlanta, saying it has been frustrated in efforts to get its own bank charter. The law center said CompuCredits financial statements revealed that the issuer collected $400 million in fees from a portfolio of fee harvester cards that by mid-2007 had saddled cardholders with nearly $1 billion in debt. The company issued a statement, reported this week on National Public Radio (npr.org), calling the report misleading. It also sent a letter to the law center before the report was published insisting, among other things, that its cards meet or exceed the federal regulatory requirements and industry best practices. The California Credit Law Blog (californiacreditlaw.com), run by a San Francisco law firm, said, the fee harvester cards look like credit cards, but they have little or nothing to do with issuing credit. GOING DEEP The soaring price of gold is causing mining companies in South Africa to sink to astonishing depths. Gold Fields plans to drill to 2.5 miles at a mine outside Johannesburg, and that would be a record, reports National Geographic News (news.nationalgeographic.com). Other companies arent far below (or, above) that mark. But the deepest mine in the United States reaches just 8,000 feet. The risks of what is called ultradeep mining are high. Temperatures rise above 100 degrees and rock shatters like glass, according to Nicholas Wadhams of National Geographic. And, he says, some seismologists believe such deep mines can potentially cause tremors in the Earth. THE DUDE ABIDES Do you ever wonder what became of the Dude, youre getting a Dell dude? New York magazines Grub Street blog caught up with Ben Curtis, the onetime pitchman, at his new workplace: Tortilla Flats, a Manhattan Tex-Mex restaurant, where he tends bar (nymag.com/daily/food). Is he often recognized? Every day, he said. Its really difficult, but its a humbling experience. There were times when I made boatloads of money as an actor, but here I can be myself. Complete links are at nytimes.com/business. Correction: November 13, 2007 The “What’s Online” column in Business Day on Saturday, about a report on credit cards published by the National Consumer Law Center, misstated the organization’s Web address. The correct address is consumerlaw.org, not consumerlaw.com.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/11/business/11sandell.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Adviser to Pay Penalty in Short-Selling<date>Published: October 11, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, Oct. 10 (Reuters)  The New York hedge fund adviser Sandell Asset Management has agreed to pay more than $8 million to settle charges that it engaged in improper short sales in connection with the merger of Hibernia and Capital One Financial, securities regulators said on Wednesday. Thomas Sandell, chief executive of Sandell Asset Management, or SAM, also agreed to pay a $100,000 civil penalty to settle related charges, the Securities and Exchange Commission said. The defendants settled with the S.E.C. without admitting or denying the charges. The S.E.C. said that Sandell Asset, its chief executive and two other employees engaged in the short sales, believing that Capital One would lower its offering price for shares of Hibernia, a bank holding company based in New Orleans, in the wake of Hurricane Katrina in 2005. The S.E.C. said Sandell Asset held a long position in Hibernia as part of its merger arbitrage investment strategy, and began to sell short as many Hibernia shares as possible to offset an anticipated loss to a client. Short sellers borrow shares of stock they see as overvalued, sell them and wait for the price to fall. If it does, they buy back the shares, return them and pocket as profit the spread between the sale price and the buyback price. The S.E.C. said that Sandell Assets senior managing director, Patrick Burke, and its head trader, Richard Ecklord, also settled in the case, agreeing to pay $50,000 and $40,000 civil penalties, respectively. More Articles in Business »WASHINGTON, Oct. 10 (Reuters)  The New York hedge fund adviser Sandell Asset Management has agreed to pay more than $8 million to settle charges that it engaged in improper short sales in connection with the merger of Hibernia and Capital One Financial, securities regulators said on Wednesday. Thomas Sandell, chief executive of Sandell Asset Management, or SAM, also agreed to pay a $100,000 civil penalty to settle related charges, the Securities and Exchange Commission said. The defendants settled with the S.E.C. without admitting or denying the charges. The S.E.C. said that Sandell Asset, its chief executive and two other employees engaged in the short sales, believing that Capital One would lower its offering price for shares of Hibernia, a bank holding company based in New Orleans, in the wake of Hurricane Katrina in 2005. The S.E.C. said Sandell Asset held a long position in Hibernia as part of its merger arbitrage investment strategy, and began to sell short as many Hibernia shares as possible to offset an anticipated loss to a client. Short sellers borrow shares of stock they see as overvalued, sell them and wait for the price to fall. If it does, they buy back the shares, return them and pocket as profit the spread between the sale price and the buyback price. The S.E.C. said that Sandell Assets senior managing director, Patrick Burke, and its head trader, Richard Ecklord, also settled in the case, agreeing to pay $50,000 and $40,000 civil penalties, respectively.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/25/business/25offline.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Praising Private Equity<date>Published: August 25, 2007</date><text>THE conventional wisdom is that private equity firms are focused strictly on the short term. The conventional wisdom is wrong, argues Walter Kiechel III, the former editorial director of Harvard Business School Publishing. True, he concedes, private equity firms often load debt onto the public companies they acquire, sell off assets and then dispose of the acquired business in a relatively short time. But what is really going on, he contends in The Harvard Business Review, is that private equity firms are simply applying, albeit very quickly, the best of classic strategic thinking, and their actions can actually improve the acquired company’s long-term performance. The fact that a private equity firm sells the company within a relatively short period is irrelevant. Mr. Kiechel says the important thing is to look at the actions of the private equity firms. By using leverage efficiently, relentlessly cutting costs and determining the company’s major competitive advantage  and disposing of all assets that do not support it  they are actually positioning the companies they are acquiring to succeed for the long haul. “The difference between the conventional and the P.E. approach to strategy is that the private equity buckoes put their acquisitions through the formulate-a-strategy-and-start-implementing-it process in months rather than years,” he says. MORE GOVERNMENT BENEFICIARIES The opening sure does get your attention. “More than half of all Americans  53 percent  now depend on government for their income,” Katherine Mangu-Ward writes in Reason. The research comes from the economist A. Gary Shilling, who totaled “federal, state, and local government workers, plus private-sector workers who owe their jobs to the government, plus recipients of Social Security, other transfer payments and benefits such as food stamps.” As startling as that 53 percent figure is, it is not a record high. In 1980, 55 percent of Americans were receiving money from the government in one form or another. CUTTING DEBT “Two-thirds of all college graduates in America leave school with student loan debt  to the tune of $20,000 on average,” Lynnette Khalfani writes in BeE Woman, a relatively new magazine. Depressing though that can be, Ms. Khalfani outlines the following five strategies to reduce or eliminate that indebtedness: ¶Negotiate. The interest rate on federal student loans is not an absolute. While Congress sets a maximum rate, lenders are free to charge less. “Ask for a lower rate in exchange for having payments automatically deducted from your checking and/or because you have a history of paying on time,” she suggests. ¶Make the boss pay. Many employers will do so, Ms. Khalfani says, if you agree to stay with the company for a certain amount of time. ¶Work for the federal government. Under the Federal Student Loan Repayment Program, a federal agency can pay off up to $10,000 of your student loan annually, up to a maximum of $60,000. ¶Cite hardships. Sallie Mae, the nation’s biggest student lender, offers deferments for “nearly 20 different scenarios,” she says. Stay-at-home mothers with babies, new mothers re-entering the work force, the unemployed and military enlistees all qualify, she says. ¶Do good. Police officers, lawyers, teachers, nurses and doctors can have their loans forgiven, under certain conditions. FINAL TAKE This comes courtesy of Money magazine, citing research done by Capital One: “More Americans use a piggy bank (42 percent) or change jar (65 percent) than a money market account (35 percent.)” PAUL B. BROWN More Articles in Business »THE conventional wisdom is that private equity firms are focused strictly on the short term. The conventional wisdom is wrong, argues Walter Kiechel III, the former editorial director of Harvard Business School Publishing. True, he concedes, private equity firms often load debt onto the public companies they acquire, sell off assets and then dispose of the acquired business in a relatively short time. But what is really going on, he contends in The Harvard Business Review, is that private equity firms are simply applying, albeit very quickly, the best of classic strategic thinking, and their actions can actually improve the acquired company’s long-term performance. The fact that a private equity firm sells the company within a relatively short period is irrelevant. Mr. Kiechel says the important thing is to look at the actions of the private equity firms. By using leverage efficiently, relentlessly cutting costs and determining the company’s major competitive advantage  and disposing of all assets that do not support it  they are actually positioning the companies they are acquiring to succeed for the long haul. “The difference between the conventional and the P.E. approach to strategy is that the private equity buckoes put their acquisitions through the formulate-a-strategy-and-start-implementing-it process in months rather than years,” he says. MORE GOVERNMENT BENEFICIARIES The opening sure does get your attention. “More than half of all Americans  53 percent  now depend on government for their income,” Katherine Mangu-Ward writes in Reason. The research comes from the economist A. Gary Shilling, who totaled “federal, state, and local government workers, plus private-sector workers who owe their jobs to the government, plus recipients of Social Security, other transfer payments and benefits such as food stamps.” As startling as that 53 percent figure is, it is not a record high. In 1980, 55 percent of Americans were receiving money from the government in one form or another. CUTTING DEBT “Two-thirds of all college graduates in America leave school with student loan debt  to the tune of $20,000 on average,” Lynnette Khalfani writes in BeE Woman, a relatively new magazine. Depressing though that can be, Ms. Khalfani outlines the following five strategies to reduce or eliminate that indebtedness: ¶Negotiate. The interest rate on federal student loans is not an absolute. While Congress sets a maximum rate, lenders are free to charge less. “Ask for a lower rate in exchange for having payments automatically deducted from your checking and/or because you have a history of paying on time,” she suggests. ¶Make the boss pay. Many employers will do so, Ms. Khalfani says, if you agree to stay with the company for a certain amount of time. ¶Work for the federal government. Under the Federal Student Loan Repayment Program, a federal agency can pay off up to $10,000 of your student loan annually, up to a maximum of $60,000. ¶Cite hardships. Sallie Mae, the nation’s biggest student lender, offers deferments for “nearly 20 different scenarios,” she says. Stay-at-home mothers with babies, new mothers re-entering the work force, the unemployed and military enlistees all qualify, she says. ¶Do good. Police officers, lawyers, teachers, nurses and doctors can have their loans forgiven, under certain conditions. FINAL TAKE This comes courtesy of Money magazine, citing research done by Capital One: “More Americans use a piggy bank (42 percent) or change jar (65 percent) than a money market account (35 percent.)” PAUL B. BROWN</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/21/business/21mortgage.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Financial to Quit Residential Mortgage Business<date>Published: August 21, 2007</date><text>In yet another casualty of the fallout in the mortgage industry, the Capital One Financial Corporation said yesterday that it would stop making residential mortgages and close GreenPoint Mortgage, its wholesale mortgage banking unit. As part of this decision, about 1,900 employees will be laid off, most of them by the end of the year. The company will also close GreenPoints headquarters in Novato, Calif., along with 31 locations in 19 states. Capital One acquired GreenPoint as part of its purchase in December of the North Fork Bancorporation. During the first six months of 2007, GreenPoint was the 23rd largest mortgage company after making $12.3 billion in loans, a 30 percent drop from the period a year ago, according to Inside Mortgage Finance, a trade publication. Although GreenPoint declined to comment, it said in a news release that it would stop making new loan commitments immediately but that it would continue to meets contractual obligations to customers for loan commitments that are in the pipeline with rates locked. The chief executive of Capital One, Richard D. Fairbank, said that GreenPoint had made a valiant effort to weather the challenges currently facing the mortgage industry. However the market disruption is too great to continue with GreenPoints originate-and-sell business model. Capital One said that the total after-tax charge associated with the move would be roughly $860 million, or $2.15 a share, a charge that would largely be taken this year. As a result, the company is revising its 2007 earnings downwards by $2.15 a share. As the housing market has cooled, mortgage lenders have struggled to raise money in the markets. Capital One specializes in alternative loans for A-rated borrowers who fall just short of standards for regular prime mortgages. The market has become skeptical of any loans that do not conform to the standards used by Fannie Mae or Freddie Mac, the big buyers of mortgages. More Articles in Business »In yet another casualty of the fallout in the mortgage industry, the Capital One Financial Corporation said yesterday that it would stop making residential mortgages and close GreenPoint Mortgage, its wholesale mortgage banking unit. As part of this decision, about 1,900 employees will be laid off, most of them by the end of the year. The company will also close GreenPoints headquarters in Novato, Calif., along with 31 locations in 19 states. Capital One acquired GreenPoint as part of its purchase in December of the North Fork Bancorporation. During the first six months of 2007, GreenPoint was the 23rd largest mortgage company after making $12.3 billion in loans, a 30 percent drop from the period a year ago, according to Inside Mortgage Finance, a trade publication. Although GreenPoint declined to comment, it said in a news release that it would stop making new loan commitments immediately but that it would continue to meets contractual obligations to customers for loan commitments that are in the pipeline with rates locked. The chief executive of Capital One, Richard D. Fairbank, said that GreenPoint had made a valiant effort to weather the challenges currently facing the mortgage industry. However the market disruption is too great to continue with GreenPoints originate-and-sell business model. Capital One said that the total after-tax charge associated with the move would be roughly $860 million, or $2.15 a share, a charge that would largely be taken this year. As a result, the company is revising its 2007 earnings downwards by $2.15 a share. As the housing market has cooled, mortgage lenders have struggled to raise money in the markets. Capital One specializes in alternative loans for A-rated borrowers who fall just short of standards for regular prime mortgages. The market has become skeptical of any loans that do not conform to the standards used by Fannie Mae or Freddie Mac, the big buyers of mortgages.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/15/business/yourmoney/15suits.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">What’s in His Wallet? Millions in Options<date>Published: July 15, 2007</date><text>Richard D. Fairbank is the chairman and chief executive of Capital One Financial, the company whose ads ask, Whats in your wallet? Lately, the answer for Mr. Fairbank has been as much as $2 million more every week. Skip to next paragraph Podcast Weekend Business This week: The current upturn in the market; the financial affairs of the British royal family and the dangers of magnets in toys from China. How to Subscribe This Weeks Podcast (mp3) The gains are a result of a seemingly bold move Mr. Fairbank made at the end of 1997. He agreed to forgo all salary and financial benefits for the next three years in exchange for a huge grant of stock options. The options would have been worthless unless the companys stock rose by almost 75 percent before the end of 2000. In the midst of a thundering bull market, that feat was accomplished in less than six months. Now, with the 10-year options nearing their expiration, Mr. Fairbank is gradually collecting his payback. Since early May, he has exercised more than 10,000 options every day and sold the shares, collecting as much as $3.4 million before taxes each week. By the end of August, his pay for 1997 should have easily exceeded $60 million. Then he plans to start cashing in the 1.2 million options he got in 1998. They are worth more than $50 million. PATRICK McGEEHAN IN THE CARDS The World Series of Poker fills hours of air time on ESPN, a member of the ABC family. But this year, it could wind up featuring a member of the family of Leslie Moonves, the chief executive of CBS. Last Wednesday, with less than a week left in the 12-day tournament at the Rio Hotel and Casino in Las Vegas, Mr. Moonvess brother Jon, a powerful lawyer in Hollywood, had the most chips of any of the events 6,358 entrants. By Friday, his stack of chips had grown to $854,000, though he had slipped to 18th among the 337 remaining players. Jon Moonves is no novice at the card table. He is the executive producer of the Ultimate Blackjack Tour, a series of blackjack tournaments that recently was renewed for a second season on CBS. Hes a pretty serious poker player, said Larry Kopald, the marketing director of the blackjack tour. He plays in some big Hollywood games. PATRICK McGEEHAN NEVER MIND So much for sailing with Suze. Earlier this year, Harmon Travel, a travel agency based in Boise, Idaho, began taking reservations for Sail With Suze, a seven-day Caribbean cruise with Suze Orman, the television personality who has turned herself into a personal finance guru and hand-holder for people who are swamped with credit card debt. A Web site, www.sailwithsuze.com, was set up with details of the programs to be offered during the cruise  such as How to Make More Out of Less and Estate Planning. But it seems that people who vacation on a Caribbean cruise prefer fun, sun and kitschy dinner theater and would rather not think about how to make their 401(k)s work harder for them. The cruise has been canceled, said a spokeswoman for Harmon Travel, explaining that the cruise line and organizers did not meet their reservations goal. A spokeswoman for Ms. Orman declined to comment. JUSTON JONES LUNCH AND A CAUSE Fancy lunches at top restaurants have long been a perk for summer law associates. At several big New York firms, a growing number of summers are opting instead to chow down at less expensive places like Chipotle. At Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett, the downgrading from boeuf to burrito is part of a program called Chow for Charity. Summer associates who go out to lunch with a staff lawyer have a budget of $60 each. If they opt to spend $15 or less, the firm donates $45 a person to a nonprofit legal organization. Last summer, Simpson Thatcher raised $49,700 via the program, up from $27,000 in 2005, said Ken Ziman, a partner at the firm. Lawyers like having lunch with a summer associate because it means a faster meal, not the typical, time-sapping 1.5 hours, Mr. Ziman said. These efforts are part of an emerging trend to add a touch of social conscience to lavish recruiting practices for top students in a competitive market, said James G. Leipold, executive director of the National Association for Legal Placement, a trade association that serves law firm recruiters and law schools. This generation has a desire to do community work, Mr. Leipold said. Should summer associates crave fine dining, their salaries may help. An associate at Simpson makes $3,080 a week. LOUISE KRAMER AN ETERNAL BOND When John G. Duffy received the Eugene D. OKelly Award from the American Cancer Society last month in New York, he was keeping up a connection that began before the two men were born. Mr. OKelly, a chairman and C.E.O. of KPMG, died of brain cancer in 2005 at age 53. Mr. Duffy, 58, is chairman and chief executive of the investment bank Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods. He received the OKelly award for service to his company, which lost 67 employees, including one of Mr. Duffys sons, in the 9/11 terrorist attacks. Mr. Duffys mother, Anne, and Mr. OKellys father, John, came from neighboring farms in County Leitrim, Ireland. Both eventually immigrated to the United States, where they met their spouses and where their sons, who became friends, were born. JANE L. LEVERE More Articles in Business »Richard D. Fairbank is the chairman and chief executive of Capital One Financial, the company whose ads ask, Whats in your wallet? Lately, the answer for Mr. Fairbank has been as much as $2 million more every week. Skip to next paragraph Podcast Weekend Business This week: The current upturn in the market; the financial affairs of the British royal family and the dangers of magnets in toys from China. How to Subscribe This Weeks Podcast (mp3) The gains are a result of a seemingly bold move Mr. Fairbank made at the end of 1997. He agreed to forgo all salary and financial benefits for the next three years in exchange for a huge grant of stock options. The options would have been worthless unless the companys stock rose by almost 75 percent before the end of 2000. In the midst of a thundering bull market, that feat was accomplished in less than six months. Now, with the 10-year options nearing their expiration, Mr. Fairbank is gradually collecting his payback. Since early May, he has exercised more than 10,000 options every day and sold the shares, collecting as much as $3.4 million before taxes each week. By the end of August, his pay for 1997 should have easily exceeded $60 million. Then he plans to start cashing in the 1.2 million options he got in 1998. They are worth more than $50 million. PATRICK McGEEHAN IN THE CARDS The World Series of Poker fills hours of air time on ESPN, a member of the ABC family. But this year, it could wind up featuring a member of the family of Leslie Moonves, the chief executive of CBS. Last Wednesday, with less than a week left in the 12-day tournament at the Rio Hotel and Casino in Las Vegas, Mr. Moonvess brother Jon, a powerful lawyer in Hollywood, had the most chips of any of the events 6,358 entrants. By Friday, his stack of chips had grown to $854,000, though he had slipped to 18th among the 337 remaining players. Jon Moonves is no novice at the card table. He is the executive producer of the Ultimate Blackjack Tour, a series of blackjack tournaments that recently was renewed for a second season on CBS. Hes a pretty serious poker player, said Larry Kopald, the marketing director of the blackjack tour. He plays in some big Hollywood games. PATRICK McGEEHAN NEVER MIND So much for sailing with Suze. Earlier this year, Harmon Travel, a travel agency based in Boise, Idaho, began taking reservations for Sail With Suze, a seven-day Caribbean cruise with Suze Orman, the television personality who has turned herself into a personal finance guru and hand-holder for people who are swamped with credit card debt. A Web site, www.sailwithsuze.com, was set up with details of the programs to be offered during the cruise  such as How to Make More Out of Less and Estate Planning. But it seems that people who vacation on a Caribbean cruise prefer fun, sun and kitschy dinner theater and would rather not think about how to make their 401(k)s work harder for them. The cruise has been canceled, said a spokeswoman for Harmon Travel, explaining that the cruise line and organizers did not meet their reservations goal. A spokeswoman for Ms. Orman declined to comment. JUSTON JONES LUNCH AND A CAUSE Fancy lunches at top restaurants have long been a perk for summer law associates. At several big New York firms, a growing number of summers are opting instead to chow down at less expensive places like Chipotle. At Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett, the downgrading from boeuf to burrito is part of a program called Chow for Charity. Summer associates who go out to lunch with a staff lawyer have a budget of $60 each. If they opt to spend $15 or less, the firm donates $45 a person to a nonprofit legal organization. Last summer, Simpson Thatcher raised $49,700 via the program, up from $27,000 in 2005, said Ken Ziman, a partner at the firm. Lawyers like having lunch with a summer associate because it means a faster meal, not the typical, time-sapping 1.5 hours, Mr. Ziman said. These efforts are part of an emerging trend to add a touch of social conscience to lavish recruiting practices for top students in a competitive market, said James G. Leipold, executive director of the National Association for Legal Placement, a trade association that serves law firm recruiters and law schools. This generation has a desire to do community work, Mr. Leipold said. Should summer associates crave fine dining, their salaries may help. An associate at Simpson makes $3,080 a week. LOUISE KRAMER AN ETERNAL BOND When John G. Duffy received the Eugene D. OKelly Award from the American Cancer Society last month in New York, he was keeping up a connection that began before the two men were born. Mr. OKelly, a chairman and C.E.O. of KPMG, died of brain cancer in 2005 at age 53. Mr. Duffy, 58, is chairman and chief executive of the investment bank Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods. He received the OKelly award for service to his company, which lost 67 employees, including one of Mr. Duffys sons, in the 9/11 terrorist attacks. Mr. Duffys mother, Anne, and Mr. OKellys father, John, came from neighboring farms in County Leitrim, Ireland. Both eventually immigrated to the United States, where they met their spouses and where their sons, who became friends, were born. JANE L. LEVERE</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/10/business/10bank.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Chief of Capital One Applies Hockey Strategies to Banking<date>Published: July 10, 2007</date><text>Richard D. Fairbank plays center on a full-contact recreational hockey team. He coaches his youth teams at the local rink, and is a part owner of the Washington Capitals. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Michael Temchine for The New York Times Richard D. Fairbank, Capital Ones chief, hopes to turn innovative strategies from the credit card business to consumer banking. But he says he is taking a break from acquisitions for now. Enlarge This Image Ruby Washington/The New York Times Lynn Pike, Capital One Financials chief operating officer, will become president of banking in August, somewhat earlier than expected. So when Mr. Fairbank, who is also the chairman and chief executive of Capital One Financial, talks about his companys strategy, it is hardly surprising that he calls it the Gretzky Concept. If you go to where the puck is going instead of where it is, it is a lot easier, he said in a recent interview in his office at the companys sleek new headquarters outside Washington. Mr. Fairbank has been thinking about where his industry is going since the early 1990s. As a founder of Capital One, he helped transform the credit card industry with innovations like teaser rates and zero-interest balance transfers. And the companys detailed understanding of its customers spending habits fueled its growth for years. Now, he is moving into retail banking for a second act. Two years ago, Capital One did not have a single branch. Today, with the purchase of Hibernia National Bank and North Fork Bank in quick succession, it has 720 locations in five states. In the future foreseen by Mr. Fairbank, lending is national but branch operations are local. To create this banking hybrid, he is not taking the usual route of melding the franchises together. Instead, he plans to pull out the best elements of all three companies; then, reassemble the parts. Its not so much about connecting the wires, Mr. Fairbank said, noting the complexity of combining a Northeastern commercial bank (North Fork) with a Southern consumer bank (Hibernia)  and then overlaying it with Capitol Ones high-octane lending and marketing techniques. We want to be able to build a scalable new institution. So far, the timing has not worked in his favor. Just days before Capital One was set to acquire Hibernia, Hurricane Katrina slammed through dozens of branches on its home turf. The housing market slowdown has compounded the challenges behind last years purchase of North Fork, where the Greenpoint mortgage business catered to customers with credit records just above subprime levels. Last month, Capital One announced the first major cost-cutting effort in its history  after two and a half years of its stock price remaining flat. Shares closed at 78.85 yesterday, up 24 cents, but they lost an equal amount in after-hours trading. Yesterday, Capital One announced the biggest leadership change since the acquisition. It said that John A. Kanas, North Forks founder and former chief executive, would step down in early August as head of its retail bank and resign from its board. Lynn Pike, a longtime Bank of America executive who joined the company last spring, is to take over as president, somewhat earlier than expected. Mr. Kanas had pledged to work for Capital One through December 2009, but he will now be paid $100,000 annually as a consultant. With early vesting, he will be able to cash out shares worth at least $24.4 million on top of the roughly $214 million exit package he was paid at the time of the North Fork acquisition, according to a pay analysis by James F. Reda &amp; Associates, an independent compensation consultant. The challenge of digesting two banks at once has, meanwhile, caused the company to move at an unusually slow pace. In New York, for instance, the North Fork branches will not be rebranded or moved onto the companys central computer system until early next year. We are appropriately nervous about them, one big competitor said, but we havent seen anything. In a hint of what comes next, many Capital One-branded outlets in Texas have a spacious look and feel. The branches display signs claiming No Hassle Banking  a phrase it has used to woo cardholders for years. And the popular Visigoths, who first appeared in a clever series of television ads, return to rescue retail banking service stuck in the Dark Ages. The company is also drawing on its credit card expertise. Already, Capital One bankers can instantly print debit cards emblazoned with one of more than a dozen images, like Batman, Bugs Bunny, and cute little dogs; others are linked to charitable groups, like Junior Achievement and March of Dimes. And a debit card tied to a broad-based rewards program could be on the way. Like most big banks, Capital One has started offering its own credit cards, mortgages and auto loans through its branches. Small-business lending will be a priority, too. But Capital One executives say that they plan to aggressively push installment loans for consumers  a product that many competitors have ignored  and distinguish their bank on speed. Its bankers say they can prudently approve no-documentation personal loans for up to $30,000 within 24 hours. Bigger rivals can take days. But Mr. Fairbanks biggest test could be whether his grand theory of retail banking pans out in the marketplace. He says he has thought long and hard about the endgame. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »Richard D. Fairbank plays center on a full-contact recreational hockey team. He coaches his youth teams at the local rink, and is a part owner of the Washington Capitals. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Michael Temchine for The New York Times Richard D. Fairbank, Capital Ones chief, hopes to turn innovative strategies from the credit card business to consumer banking. But he says he is taking a break from acquisitions for now. Enlarge This Image Ruby Washington/The New York Times Lynn Pike, Capital One Financials chief operating officer, will become president of banking in August, somewhat earlier than expected. So when Mr. Fairbank, who is also the chairman and chief executive of Capital One Financial, talks about his companys strategy, it is hardly surprising that he calls it the Gretzky Concept. If you go to where the puck is going instead of where it is, it is a lot easier, he said in a recent interview in his office at the companys sleek new headquarters outside Washington. Mr. Fairbank has been thinking about where his industry is going since the early 1990s. As a founder of Capital One, he helped transform the credit card industry with innovations like teaser rates and zero-interest balance transfers. And the companys detailed understanding of its customers spending habits fueled its growth for years. Now, he is moving into retail banking for a second act. Two years ago, Capital One did not have a single branch. Today, with the purchase of Hibernia National Bank and North Fork Bank in quick succession, it has 720 locations in five states. In the future foreseen by Mr. Fairbank, lending is national but branch operations are local. To create this banking hybrid, he is not taking the usual route of melding the franchises together. Instead, he plans to pull out the best elements of all three companies; then, reassemble the parts. Its not so much about connecting the wires, Mr. Fairbank said, noting the complexity of combining a Northeastern commercial bank (North Fork) with a Southern consumer bank (Hibernia)  and then overlaying it with Capitol Ones high-octane lending and marketing techniques. We want to be able to build a scalable new institution. So far, the timing has not worked in his favor. Just days before Capital One was set to acquire Hibernia, Hurricane Katrina slammed through dozens of branches on its home turf. The housing market slowdown has compounded the challenges behind last years purchase of North Fork, where the Greenpoint mortgage business catered to customers with credit records just above subprime levels. Last month, Capital One announced the first major cost-cutting effort in its history  after two and a half years of its stock price remaining flat. Shares closed at 78.85 yesterday, up 24 cents, but they lost an equal amount in after-hours trading. Yesterday, Capital One announced the biggest leadership change since the acquisition. It said that John A. Kanas, North Forks founder and former chief executive, would step down in early August as head of its retail bank and resign from its board. Lynn Pike, a longtime Bank of America executive who joined the company last spring, is to take over as president, somewhat earlier than expected. Mr. Kanas had pledged to work for Capital One through December 2009, but he will now be paid $100,000 annually as a consultant. With early vesting, he will be able to cash out shares worth at least $24.4 million on top of the roughly $214 million exit package he was paid at the time of the North Fork acquisition, according to a pay analysis by James F. Reda &amp; Associates, an independent compensation consultant. The challenge of digesting two banks at once has, meanwhile, caused the company to move at an unusually slow pace. In New York, for instance, the North Fork branches will not be rebranded or moved onto the companys central computer system until early next year. We are appropriately nervous about them, one big competitor said, but we havent seen anything. In a hint of what comes next, many Capital One-branded outlets in Texas have a spacious look and feel. The branches display signs claiming No Hassle Banking  a phrase it has used to woo cardholders for years. And the popular Visigoths, who first appeared in a clever series of television ads, return to rescue retail banking service stuck in the Dark Ages. The company is also drawing on its credit card expertise. Already, Capital One bankers can instantly print debit cards emblazoned with one of more than a dozen images, like Batman, Bugs Bunny, and cute little dogs; others are linked to charitable groups, like Junior Achievement and March of Dimes. And a debit card tied to a broad-based rewards program could be on the way. Like most big banks, Capital One has started offering its own credit cards, mortgages and auto loans through its branches. Small-business lending will be a priority, too. But Capital One executives say that they plan to aggressively push installment loans for consumers  a product that many competitors have ignored  and distinguish their bank on speed. Its bankers say they can prudently approve no-documentation personal loans for up to $30,000 within 24 hours. Bigger rivals can take days. But Mr. Fairbanks biggest test could be whether his grand theory of retail banking pans out in the marketplace. He says he has thought long and hard about the endgame. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/28/business/28cards.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Says It Will Cut 2,000 Jobs<date>Published: June 28, 2007</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., June 27 (AP)  Capital One, the credit card and banking company, said Wednesday that it expected to eliminate about 2,000 jobs, or a little more than 6 percent of its work force, as part of a cost-cutting program designed to save $700 million by 2009. The company expects to incur $300 million of pretax charges for the revamping, including $90 million this quarter and $200 million in 2007. These charges are expected to reduce after-tax profit by 15 cents a share this quarter, and 33 cents a share in 2007. Approximately half of the planned job eliminations have already occurred and the affected employees have been notified, the company said. Other cuts will come through attrition and the elimination by the end of next year of selected positions that are currently vacant. Capital One currently has about 32,000 employees. The company said it expected the change to help it achieve about $400 million of pretax savings in 2008 and an additional $300 million in 2009. In 1995, Capital One was primarily a credit card issuer with five million accounts. In the decade since, it has evolved into a robust and broadly diversified Fortune 200 company with more than 50 million customer accounts worldwide and one of the most recognized brands in America. The companys American credit card business is widely known for its Whats in Your Wallet? advertising campaign. More Articles in Business »CHARLOTTE, N.C., June 27 (AP)  Capital One, the credit card and banking company, said Wednesday that it expected to eliminate about 2,000 jobs, or a little more than 6 percent of its work force, as part of a cost-cutting program designed to save $700 million by 2009. The company expects to incur $300 million of pretax charges for the revamping, including $90 million this quarter and $200 million in 2007. These charges are expected to reduce after-tax profit by 15 cents a share this quarter, and 33 cents a share in 2007. Approximately half of the planned job eliminations have already occurred and the affected employees have been notified, the company said. Other cuts will come through attrition and the elimination by the end of next year of selected positions that are currently vacant. Capital One currently has about 32,000 employees. The company said it expected the change to help it achieve about $400 million of pretax savings in 2008 and an additional $300 million in 2009. In 1995, Capital One was primarily a credit card issuer with five million accounts. In the decade since, it has evolved into a robust and broadly diversified Fortune 200 company with more than 50 million customer accounts worldwide and one of the most recognized brands in America. The companys American credit card business is widely known for its Whats in Your Wallet? advertising campaign.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/16/business/16fed.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Two Nominated for Fed<date>Published: May 16, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, May 15 (Reuters)  The White House said on Tuesday that President Bush planned to nominate two financial service company executives, Larry A. Klane and Elizabeth A. Duke, to fill vacancies on the Federal Reserve Board. In a statement, the White House also said President Bush would name a current Fed governor, Randall S. Kroszner, to serve a full 14-year term on the board once the partial term he is serving expires on Jan. 31. Mr. Klane is president for global financial services at the Capital One Financial Corporation, and Ms. Duke is chief operating officer of TowneBank in Portsmouth, Va. The positions require Senate confirmation. If approved, Mr. Klane and Ms. Duke would fill Fed seats left open by the departures of Susan S. Bies and Mark W. Olson. Mr. Olson stepped down last June, while Ms. Bies resigned at the end of March. More Articles in Business »WASHINGTON, May 15 (Reuters)  The White House said on Tuesday that President Bush planned to nominate two financial service company executives, Larry A. Klane and Elizabeth A. Duke, to fill vacancies on the Federal Reserve Board. In a statement, the White House also said President Bush would name a current Fed governor, Randall S. Kroszner, to serve a full 14-year term on the board once the partial term he is serving expires on Jan. 31. Mr. Klane is president for global financial services at the Capital One Financial Corporation, and Ms. Duke is chief operating officer of TowneBank in Portsmouth, Va. The positions require Senate confirmation. If approved, Mr. Klane and Ms. Duke would fill Fed seats left open by the departures of Susan S. Bies and Mark W. Olson. Mr. Olson stepped down last June, while Ms. Bies resigned at the end of March.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFD9133EF935A15752C1A9609C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">OPENERS: SUITS; WHAT'S IN HIS WALLET<date>Published: November 26, 2006</date><text>It's great to be honored by one's peers, but even better to be paid top dollar. Richard D. Fairbank, the founder, chairman and chief executive of Capital One Financial, is enjoying both. He will be given the 2006 Banker of the Year Award on Thursday. American Banker, the daily financial industry newspaper and sponsor of the award, says it is recognizing Mr. Fairbank for making credit more accessible, transforming lending practices and diversifying his bank's balance sheet. Not that Mr. Fairbank need worry about his personal balance sheet. Last year, he was paid an eye-catching $249 million, making him the second-highest-paid executive in America, after only the home-shopping-channel magnate Barry Diller, according to the Corporate Library, a firm that examines executive compensation. ELIZABETH OLSON Photo: Richard D. Fairbank (Photo by Bloomberg News)</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/21/business/21trader.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Ex-Financial Chief at Capital One to Pay Fine of $1.8 Million<date>Published: November 21, 2006</date><text>David M. Willey, the former finance chief at the Capital One Financial Corporation, will pay $1.8 million, including an $801,000 fine, to settle insider-trading accusations, the Securities and Exchange Commission said yesterday. Mr. Willey exercised almost 148,000 options on Capital One stock through swaps and cashless transactions, and sold 60,200 shares on the market in May 2002, after learning that federal regulators planned to downgrade their assessment of the banks overall condition, the S.E.C. said yesterday in a statement. Capital One shares fell 40 percent two months later when the company announced that regulators were forcing it to increase reserves for loan losses, the S.E.C. said. Mr. Willey arranged the transactions without telling other executives about the regulators concerns, according to the complaint. He knew that when others learned of the problems, Capital Ones standard policy would have been to ban trading by top executives, the S.E.C. said. He also failed to disclose some transactions in a regulatory filing. A lawyer for Mr. Willey, William Mann of Mayer, Brown, Rowe &amp; Maw in Washington, declined to comment. Mr. Willey, who resigned from Capital One in 2003, did not admit or deny the accusations, the S.E.C. said. Besides the fine, Mr. Willey will forfeit his profits on the trades, plus interest. The agencys 2004 lawsuit against Mr. Willey named his wife as a beneficiary of the trades without accusing her of wrongdoing. The agency dropped the case against her under the settlement with Mr. Willey. More Articles in Business »David M. Willey, the former finance chief at the Capital One Financial Corporation, will pay $1.8 million, including an $801,000 fine, to settle insider-trading accusations, the Securities and Exchange Commission said yesterday. Mr. Willey exercised almost 148,000 options on Capital One stock through swaps and cashless transactions, and sold 60,200 shares on the market in May 2002, after learning that federal regulators planned to downgrade their assessment of the banks overall condition, the S.E.C. said yesterday in a statement. Capital One shares fell 40 percent two months later when the company announced that regulators were forcing it to increase reserves for loan losses, the S.E.C. said. Mr. Willey arranged the transactions without telling other executives about the regulators concerns, according to the complaint. He knew that when others learned of the problems, Capital Ones standard policy would have been to ban trading by top executives, the S.E.C. said. He also failed to disclose some transactions in a regulatory filing. A lawyer for Mr. Willey, William Mann of Mayer, Brown, Rowe &amp; Maw in Washington, declined to comment. Mr. Willey, who resigned from Capital One in 2003, did not admit or deny the accusations, the S.E.C. said. Besides the fine, Mr. Willey will forfeit his profits on the trades, plus interest. The agencys 2004 lawsuit against Mr. Willey named his wife as a beneficiary of the trades without accusing her of wrongdoing. The agency dropped the case against her under the settlement with Mr. Willey.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/19/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/19libank.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Sundown for the Last Big Local Bank<date>Published: March 19, 2006</date><text>THERE'S the North Fork Theater at Westbury, formerly the Music Fair. There's North Fork Hall, the main theater at the Tilles Center. Skip to next paragraph And then are the Fourth of July Fireworks at Jones Beach, sponsored by  who else?  North Fork. Not to mention the 122 bank branches across Long Island that bear the name North Fork and the bank's trademark yellow sunburst sign. North Fork Bancorporation's agreement to be acquired by Capital One had been rumored for a while, but its announcement last Monday still sent ripples throughout Long Island, from the small business owners who rely on their local branch to handle their finances to the arts groups that depend on the bank's charitable giving. Beyond being a highly visible corporate presence, North Fork Bank is also the last of a breed. When it disappears into Capital One, Long Island will be left with no major commercial bank of its own. (The next largest homegrown commercial bank, the State Bank of Long Island, is about one-fortieth the size of North Fork.) Out-of-town banks, mainly from New York City, have taken an important hand in the Island's banking market for a half-century, going back to the rapid suburbanization after World War II. But they were often viewed suspiciously by local business leaders, who were concerned about the city banks using the suburbs as little more than "deposit farms," gathering in capital that would be invested elsewhere. That led to the emergence of dynamic Island-based banks like Franklin National and Meadowbrook National (later National Bank of North America), which grew rapidly while investing locally. Island banks introduced service innovations like evening hours, the first drive-up windows and some of the first credit cards. Eventually their strengths made them takeover targets, and the same has now happened to North Fork. Business and government leaders say that while they are concerned about potential job losses from the North Fork-Capital One merger, they hope the deal will ultimately help the local economy. The prospect of seeing North Fork signs vanish from the landscape, though  well, that is another matter. "North Fork personifies Long Island and the East End, where their roots were," said Mitchell H. Pally, a vice president of the Long Island Association, the Island's largest business and civic organization. "It's one of the few banks left that actually has a Long Island name in its name, and losing that will have a big perception impact." David E. Kapell, the mayor of Greenport, on the eastern end of the (geographic) North Fork, called the deal "just another step toward the homogenization and regionalization of the Long Island economy." He said that the bank clearly had been shifting its focus westward and beyond the Island for some time, especially after it moved its headquarters to Melville from Mattituck in the mid-1990's. "As a matter of reality, it's been some time since it was truly a local bank," he said. The Island's rich history of local banking has been waning for a while, said Pearl M. Kamer, chief economist at the Long Island Association. "It's all part of a trend toward a reduced number of players in all business and banking markets," she said. "And the pace of acquisitions has accelerated as it has become more and more competitive." Long Island has seen wave after wave of mergers and consolidations of banks, dating back to the Great Depression. And nearly every village Main Street seems to feature a grand old Greek Revival building facade with a bygone bank's name still incised in the stonework. But while others were being swallowed up, North Fork had been the hunter rather than the hunted. Over the last 20 years, North Fork acquired 13 smaller banks and thrift institutions as it moved west from rural Southold to Manhattan and beyond. In 1992, the bank had $2.7 billion in assets; today it is the nation's 16th-largest bank with $58 billion in assets and more than 350 branches. Richard M. Bivone, president of the Nassau Council of Chambers of Commerce, said North Fork has always been active in local chambers of commerce and has strong ties with local merchants. "That's the way they always have done business," Mr. Bivone said, "and they need to continue to be a local bank, even if they're backed by an out-of-town corporation." 1 2Next Page &gt; Eric Dash contributed reporting for this article. More Articles in New York Region &gt;THERE'S the North Fork Theater at Westbury, formerly the Music Fair. There's North Fork Hall, the main theater at the Tilles Center. Skip to next paragraph And then are the Fourth of July Fireworks at Jones Beach, sponsored by  who else?  North Fork. Not to mention the 122 bank branches across Long Island that bear the name North Fork and the bank's trademark yellow sunburst sign. North Fork Bancorporation's agreement to be acquired by Capital One had been rumored for a while, but its announcement last Monday still sent ripples throughout Long Island, from the small business owners who rely on their local branch to handle their finances to the arts groups that depend on the bank's charitable giving. Beyond being a highly visible corporate presence, North Fork Bank is also the last of a breed. When it disappears into Capital One, Long Island will be left with no major commercial bank of its own. (The next largest homegrown commercial bank, the State Bank of Long Island, is about one-fortieth the size of North Fork.) Out-of-town banks, mainly from New York City, have taken an important hand in the Island's banking market for a half-century, going back to the rapid suburbanization after World War II. But they were often viewed suspiciously by local business leaders, who were concerned about the city banks using the suburbs as little more than "deposit farms," gathering in capital that would be invested elsewhere. That led to the emergence of dynamic Island-based banks like Franklin National and Meadowbrook National (later National Bank of North America), which grew rapidly while investing locally. Island banks introduced service innovations like evening hours, the first drive-up windows and some of the first credit cards. Eventually their strengths made them takeover targets, and the same has now happened to North Fork. Business and government leaders say that while they are concerned about potential job losses from the North Fork-Capital One merger, they hope the deal will ultimately help the local economy. The prospect of seeing North Fork signs vanish from the landscape, though  well, that is another matter. "North Fork personifies Long Island and the East End, where their roots were," said Mitchell H. Pally, a vice president of the Long Island Association, the Island's largest business and civic organization. "It's one of the few banks left that actually has a Long Island name in its name, and losing that will have a big perception impact." David E. Kapell, the mayor of Greenport, on the eastern end of the (geographic) North Fork, called the deal "just another step toward the homogenization and regionalization of the Long Island economy." He said that the bank clearly had been shifting its focus westward and beyond the Island for some time, especially after it moved its headquarters to Melville from Mattituck in the mid-1990's. "As a matter of reality, it's been some time since it was truly a local bank," he said. The Island's rich history of local banking has been waning for a while, said Pearl M. Kamer, chief economist at the Long Island Association. "It's all part of a trend toward a reduced number of players in all business and banking markets," she said. "And the pace of acquisitions has accelerated as it has become more and more competitive." Long Island has seen wave after wave of mergers and consolidations of banks, dating back to the Great Depression. And nearly every village Main Street seems to feature a grand old Greek Revival building facade with a bygone bank's name still incised in the stonework. But while others were being swallowed up, North Fork had been the hunter rather than the hunted. Over the last 20 years, North Fork acquired 13 smaller banks and thrift institutions as it moved west from rural Southold to Manhattan and beyond. In 1992, the bank had $2.7 billion in assets; today it is the nation's 16th-largest bank with $58 billion in assets and more than 350 branches. Richard M. Bivone, president of the Nassau Council of Chambers of Commerce, said North Fork has always been active in local chambers of commerce and has strong ties with local merchants. "That's the way they always have done business," Mr. Bivone said, "and they need to continue to be a local bank, even if they're backed by an out-of-town corporation." 1 2Next Page &gt; Eric Dash contributed reporting for this article.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/18/business/18five.ready.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">That Other Madness This Month: Mergers<date>Published: March 18, 2006</date><text>MARCH madness is not limited to college basketball. Billions of dollars in mergers were announced this week, building on the momentum created when AT&amp;T offered to acquire BellSouth for $67 billion earlier in the month. The trend even swept up entire stock exchanges, as the Nasdaq Stock Market offered to buy the London Stock Exchange (just as the New York Stock Exchange was weighing a bid of its own), and Euronext, the owner of the Paris, Amsterdam, Brussels and Lisbon stock markets, said it was interested in buying Deutsche Börse, the German exchange. BUT FIRST, A CORRECTION Just as investors may have been recovering from General Motors' $8.6 billion loss last year, the company stepped up to say the loss was actually $10.6 billion. It said the added losses more accurately reflected the costs of scaling back its North American operations and of helping its former parts subsidiary, Delphi, restructure while in bankruptcy protection. G.M. said it would also restate five years of results and delay filing its annual report with the Securities and Exchange Commission while it looks into accounting irregularities at its residential mortgage unit. CHARGE! Eager to further diversify its business amid rising interest rates and slowing growth for credit card issuers, Capital One Financial, the big credit card company, agreed to buy the North Fork Bancorporation, a regional bank serving the Northeast, for about $14.6 billion in cash and stock. After its acquisition last fall of the Hibernia National Bank in New Orleans, Capital One would have deposits of more than $84 billion when its North Fork acquisition is completed. It would have more than 50 million customer accounts and 655 branches from White Plains to Brownsville, Tex. Credit card companies are looking for new ways of financing the debt accumulated by their customers. In the past, card issuers repackaged the debt into bonds. Teaming up with banks also lets them use relatively inexpensive bank deposits to finance card debt. HEADLINE NEWS The McClatchy Company, a California newspaper publisher, won a one-bid auction for Knight Ridder, offering $4.5 billion in cash and stock for its 32 newspapers, including The Miami Herald, The Star-Telegram of Fort Worth and The Charlotte Observer in North Carolina. To help finance the deal and head off some antitrust concerns, McClatchy, which is based in Sacramento, immediately put 12 of the papers back up for sale. Among those it plans to sell are The Mercury News in San Jose, Calif., Knight Ridder's hometown; The Akron Beacon Journal in Ohio, which was the first in the chain; and both papers in Philadelphia, The Inquirer and The Daily News. Gary Pruitt, the chief executive of McClatchy, which already owned The Star Tribune in Minneapolis, The Sacramento Bee and The News &amp; Observer in Raleigh, N.C., said he hoped he could complete both the acquisition and the sale this summer. DRUG DEAL Even some Europeans got carried away by merger furor: Merck of Germany made a hostile $17.7 billion bid for Schering of Germany, the largest maker of oral contraceptives. The businesses are unaffiliated with similarly named American companies: Merck &amp; Company and Schering-Plough. A combination of Merck and Schering would create the second-largest drug maker in Germany after Bayer, with annual sales of $13 billion. Midsize pharmaceutical companies are under pressure to buy one another as generics makers eat away at their profit margins and the cost of discovering and developing new drugs rises. Schering's board rejected the Merck offer, but it may be persuaded by a higher price from a bigger company, including Novartis of Switzerland or GlaxoSmithKline of Britain. TAX FIRM SUED The New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, sued H&amp;R Block, the nation's largest tax-preparation service, accusing it of selling retirement-savings plans without disclosing that investors would probably earn less from the plans than they would pay in fees. Last month, the California attorney general, Bill Lockyer, accused Block of illegally promoting high-cost loans as "instant" tax refunds. The company agreed last year to pay $62.5 million to settle four class-action lawsuits over those refund-anticipation loans. Perhaps even more embarrassing for the company, Block has said it will need to restate profits for two years because it understated its 2004 state tax liabilities by millions of dollars. Despite these issues, federal banking regulators have approved H&amp;R Block's plan to start its own savings bank later this year. DELAY OF GAME In an embarrassing development, Sony pushed back the introduction of its PlayStation 3 video game console to November  months after it originally planned to start selling the consoles and almost a full year after its chief rival, Microsoft, was able to put its latest hardware into stores. Sony is counting on PlayStation 3 to showcase two new technologies: the Blu-ray high-definition DVD format and the Cell processing chip. Sony had hoped the new PlayStation would help spread the use of the Blu-ray format, which is in a separate battle with a Toshiba technology to become the global standard for next-generation DVD's. Analysts said Sony would probably try to sell PlayStation 3 for about $500. While that is $100 more than the Microsoft Xbox 360, they said it was probably much less than the actual building cost. MOST VIEWED Following are the most-viewed business news articles on nytimes.com from March 11 through March 17: 1. A Cancer Drug's Big Price Rise Is Cause for Concern 2. Many Utilities Collect for Taxes They Never Pay 3. As Internet TV Aims at Niche Audiences, the Slivercast Is Born 4. TV Stations Fined Over CBS Show Deemed to Be Indecent 5. Surgical Device Poses a Rare but Serious Peril More Articles in Business &gt;MARCH madness is not limited to college basketball. Billions of dollars in mergers were announced this week, building on the momentum created when AT&amp;T offered to acquire BellSouth for $67 billion earlier in the month. The trend even swept up entire stock exchanges, as the Nasdaq Stock Market offered to buy the London Stock Exchange (just as the New York Stock Exchange was weighing a bid of its own), and Euronext, the owner of the Paris, Amsterdam, Brussels and Lisbon stock markets, said it was interested in buying Deutsche Börse, the German exchange. BUT FIRST, A CORRECTION Just as investors may have been recovering from General Motors' $8.6 billion loss last year, the company stepped up to say the loss was actually $10.6 billion. It said the added losses more accurately reflected the costs of scaling back its North American operations and of helping its former parts subsidiary, Delphi, restructure while in bankruptcy protection. G.M. said it would also restate five years of results and delay filing its annual report with the Securities and Exchange Commission while it looks into accounting irregularities at its residential mortgage unit. CHARGE! Eager to further diversify its business amid rising interest rates and slowing growth for credit card issuers, Capital One Financial, the big credit card company, agreed to buy the North Fork Bancorporation, a regional bank serving the Northeast, for about $14.6 billion in cash and stock. After its acquisition last fall of the Hibernia National Bank in New Orleans, Capital One would have deposits of more than $84 billion when its North Fork acquisition is completed. It would have more than 50 million customer accounts and 655 branches from White Plains to Brownsville, Tex. Credit card companies are looking for new ways of financing the debt accumulated by their customers. In the past, card issuers repackaged the debt into bonds. Teaming up with banks also lets them use relatively inexpensive bank deposits to finance card debt. HEADLINE NEWS The McClatchy Company, a California newspaper publisher, won a one-bid auction for Knight Ridder, offering $4.5 billion in cash and stock for its 32 newspapers, including The Miami Herald, The Star-Telegram of Fort Worth and The Charlotte Observer in North Carolina. To help finance the deal and head off some antitrust concerns, McClatchy, which is based in Sacramento, immediately put 12 of the papers back up for sale. Among those it plans to sell are The Mercury News in San Jose, Calif., Knight Ridder's hometown; The Akron Beacon Journal in Ohio, which was the first in the chain; and both papers in Philadelphia, The Inquirer and The Daily News. Gary Pruitt, the chief executive of McClatchy, which already owned The Star Tribune in Minneapolis, The Sacramento Bee and The News &amp; Observer in Raleigh, N.C., said he hoped he could complete both the acquisition and the sale this summer. DRUG DEAL Even some Europeans got carried away by merger furor: Merck of Germany made a hostile $17.7 billion bid for Schering of Germany, the largest maker of oral contraceptives. The businesses are unaffiliated with similarly named American companies: Merck &amp; Company and Schering-Plough. A combination of Merck and Schering would create the second-largest drug maker in Germany after Bayer, with annual sales of $13 billion. Midsize pharmaceutical companies are under pressure to buy one another as generics makers eat away at their profit margins and the cost of discovering and developing new drugs rises. Schering's board rejected the Merck offer, but it may be persuaded by a higher price from a bigger company, including Novartis of Switzerland or GlaxoSmithKline of Britain. TAX FIRM SUED The New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, sued H&amp;R Block, the nation's largest tax-preparation service, accusing it of selling retirement-savings plans without disclosing that investors would probably earn less from the plans than they would pay in fees. Last month, the California attorney general, Bill Lockyer, accused Block of illegally promoting high-cost loans as "instant" tax refunds. The company agreed last year to pay $62.5 million to settle four class-action lawsuits over those refund-anticipation loans. Perhaps even more embarrassing for the company, Block has said it will need to restate profits for two years because it understated its 2004 state tax liabilities by millions of dollars. Despite these issues, federal banking regulators have approved H&amp;R Block's plan to start its own savings bank later this year. DELAY OF GAME In an embarrassing development, Sony pushed back the introduction of its PlayStation 3 video game console to November  months after it originally planned to start selling the consoles and almost a full year after its chief rival, Microsoft, was able to put its latest hardware into stores. Sony is counting on PlayStation 3 to showcase two new technologies: the Blu-ray high-definition DVD format and the Cell processing chip. Sony had hoped the new PlayStation would help spread the use of the Blu-ray format, which is in a separate battle with a Toshiba technology to become the global standard for next-generation DVD's. Analysts said Sony would probably try to sell PlayStation 3 for about $500. While that is $100 more than the Microsoft Xbox 360, they said it was probably much less than the actual building cost. MOST VIEWED Following are the most-viewed business news articles on nytimes.com from March 11 through March 17: 1. A Cancer Drug's Big Price Rise Is Cause for Concern 2. Many Utilities Collect for Taxes They Never Pay 3. As Internet TV Aims at Niche Audiences, the Slivercast Is Born 4. TV Stations Fined Over CBS Show Deemed to Be Indecent 5. Surgical Device Poses a Rare but Serious Peril</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/13/business/13deal.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Reportedin Deal for North Fork<date>Published: March 13, 2006</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire the North Fork Bancorporation for about $14.6 billion in cash and stock, people involved in the negotiations said. The acquisition, which is expected to be announced today, would give Capital One a strong retail banking foothold in the Northeast as growth of its nationwide credit card franchise slows. The transaction would also the end the independence of North Fork, based in Melville, N.Y., which transformed itself over the past decade from a small community bank into a regional player through a series of acquisitions. Over the past few years, Capital One has hinted about its retail banking ambitions. Other standalone credit card companies, beset by higher borrowing costs as well as a slowdown in credit card growth, have been snapped up by larger competitors. But Capital One has been determined to remain independent and diversify its business. Last fall, the company acquired the Hibernia National Bank, which operates more than 300 branches in Louisiana and Texas. It has expanded its presence into other areas like auto, home equity and college loans. With the acquisition of North Fork, the combined company will have deposits of more than $84 billion, a managed loan portfolio of more than $143 billion, more than 50 million customer accounts and 655 branches. While the companies have little overlap, it is unclear whether the deal will affect employees. Capital One expects the deal will lead to savings of about $275 million, most likely from back office operations. John A. Kanas, North Fork's chief executive, will become the president of Capital One's banking business and report to Richard D. Fairbank, Capital One's chief executive. He will also join Capital One's board. Under the terms of the agreement, North Fork shareholders will receive cash or stock valued at $31.18 per North Fork share, which represents a 22.8 percent premium over the closing price of North Fork shares on Friday. They will get $11.25 in cash and 0.2216 Capital One shares. J. P. Morgan Chase and Citigroup advised Capital One; Cleary Gottlieb Steen &amp; Hamilton was its lawyer. Sandler O'Neill, LP and Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods advised North Fork while Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz was its lawyer. More Articles in Business &gt;The Capital One Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire the North Fork Bancorporation for about $14.6 billion in cash and stock, people involved in the negotiations said. The acquisition, which is expected to be announced today, would give Capital One a strong retail banking foothold in the Northeast as growth of its nationwide credit card franchise slows. The transaction would also the end the independence of North Fork, based in Melville, N.Y., which transformed itself over the past decade from a small community bank into a regional player through a series of acquisitions. Over the past few years, Capital One has hinted about its retail banking ambitions. Other standalone credit card companies, beset by higher borrowing costs as well as a slowdown in credit card growth, have been snapped up by larger competitors. But Capital One has been determined to remain independent and diversify its business. Last fall, the company acquired the Hibernia National Bank, which operates more than 300 branches in Louisiana and Texas. It has expanded its presence into other areas like auto, home equity and college loans. With the acquisition of North Fork, the combined company will have deposits of more than $84 billion, a managed loan portfolio of more than $143 billion, more than 50 million customer accounts and 655 branches. While the companies have little overlap, it is unclear whether the deal will affect employees. Capital One expects the deal will lead to savings of about $275 million, most likely from back office operations. John A. Kanas, North Fork's chief executive, will become the president of Capital One's banking business and report to Richard D. Fairbank, Capital One's chief executive. He will also join Capital One's board. Under the terms of the agreement, North Fork shareholders will receive cash or stock valued at $31.18 per North Fork share, which represents a 22.8 percent premium over the closing price of North Fork shares on Friday. They will get $11.25 in cash and 0.2216 Capital One shares. J. P. Morgan Chase and Citigroup advised Capital One; Cleary Gottlieb Steen &amp; Hamilton was its lawyer. Sandler O'Neill, LP and Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods advised North Fork while Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz was its lawyer.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/11/business/11place.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Breaking the Mold, a Lender Buys a Bank<date>Published: October 11, 2005</date><text>CAPITAL One, the credit card giant, has always been something of a laboratory experiment. The company was founded by a Stanford-educated management consultant with no background in lending who wanted to test the ideas he formed advising clients. Now, Capital One is about to test another contrarian thesis: at a time when most stand-alone credit card businesses have sold themselves to big banks, Capital One is doing the opposite and buying a midsize commercial bank. The company is in the process of acquiring the Hibernia Corporation, generally considered a workmanlike regional bank, with operations in Louisiana and Texas. There are several rationales for the deal. Although Capital One thrives on credit cards and auto loans, its ability to accept deposits is constrained by its being less than a full-service bank. Hibernia's commercial banking charter will give the company the ability to offer more products, using its well-honed strategy of blanketing the United States with mail offers. By diversifying into home-equity loans, mortgages and other loans with lower interest rates than cards, Capital One can expand its empire and shield its balance sheet from consumer credit cycles. Some analysts, though, maintain that the Capital One profit engine has no need for a sleepy regional bank. They contend, among other things, that the company has already figured out how to finance its lending business in the absence of a large deposit base. "The chestnut that's out there in the industry that they did this to finance their lending business - that doesn't wash," said Theodore Iacobuzio, vice president for research at TowerGroup, a banking and payments consulting firm. "For me, there are more unanswered questions than there are answered questions." Richard D. Fairbank, Capital One's founder and chief executive, says he has an answer: people like to keep their checking and savings accounts at a local bank with lots of convenient branches, but when they are taking out a loan, they care less about geography than about the best deal. In other words, financial services companies should take deposits locally and lend nationally. Although its credit card business has been doing very well - the company expects its loan portfolio to grow at a rate of 12 percent to 15 percent this year - "we came to the conclusion that the right model was to be a diversified lender with a deposit business," Mr. Fairbank said in a recent interview. After shopping a bit for the right bank, Capital One selected Hibernia, which is based in New Orleans. The deal, announced in March, has been delayed and renegotiated because of Hurricane Katrina; Capital One now plans to pay about $5 billion, 9 percent less than the original price, and to close by the end of the year. "We still believe that Hibernia can do for us what we're buying it for," Mr. Fairbank said. He would like Capital One to rely less on the capital markets; bank regulators, which forced the company to increase its loan-loss reserves in 2002, may feel the same way. Wall Street has tended to smile on Capital One because of the consistency of its profits, but its shares have fallen 12.5 percent since their high in August. The stock closed yesterday at $74.79. In a way, the purchase of Hibernia will bring Capital One full circle. The venture was born in 1988 when Mr. Fairbank persuaded Signet Bank of Richmond, Va., to buy his concept of selling consumer products through a strategy that combined technology and direct marketing. Signet, now part of Wachovia, adopted the idea in 1988, hiring Mr. Fairbank and a partner to run its credit card business. But the card operation outgrew the bank and was spun off in 1994. Today, Capital One, with its headquarters in McLean, Va., is credited with pioneering innovations like the teaser rate, dangling once-unthinkable offers like zero percent interest on credit card balances for the first six months of an account, and balance transfers. More recently, a foray into auto lending has gone very well. Capital One bought Summit Acceptance in 1998 for about $60 million, Mr. Fairbank said. Today, Capital One Auto Finance is the third-largest auto lender in the country. At the time, said Michael T. Vinciquerra, an analyst at Raymond James &amp; Associates, he questioned the move into auto lending. Now, Mr. Vinciquerra, who has a strong buy rating on Capital One, says that the premise of marrying the national lending business to a local deposit base seems logical. Mr. Fairbank and his team, he added, "always seem to be thinking a couple of years down the road." Its unorthodox aspects notwithstanding, Capital One's deal for Hibernia does fit with a shift that has been taking place in financial services, away from the single-product model. With a few big exceptions, most specialized lenders have joined forces with more diverse companies. In credit cards, American Express stands largely on its own as the last pure card company, having emphatically pared back its other operations (including, last week, its financial advisory business, which started trading as Ameriprise Financial). The Discover card continues to live on as part of Morgan Stanley. But Capital One considers Hibernia just a start, and plans to bulk up in both deposits and consumer lending. "We positioned ourselves to be one of the consolidators rather than on the receiving end of the consolidation, as most banks are," Mr. Fairbank said. Indeed, Mr. Fairbank is of the view that banks that do not already have a national lending business like his credit card franchise may find themselves at a disadvantage. Take Wachovia, for instance, which considered buying MBNA before Bank of America snapped it up. There are not many such companies left to buy, he said, but there are certainly a lot of banks left to add to Capital One's portfolio. "Would I like to be in 50 states with deposits? I might like that," Mr. Fairbank said. "I'd be shocked if five years from now, we were not already thought of as a bank." More Articles in Business &gt;CAPITAL One, the credit card giant, has always been something of a laboratory experiment. The company was founded by a Stanford-educated management consultant with no background in lending who wanted to test the ideas he formed advising clients. Now, Capital One is about to test another contrarian thesis: at a time when most stand-alone credit card businesses have sold themselves to big banks, Capital One is doing the opposite and buying a midsize commercial bank. The company is in the process of acquiring the Hibernia Corporation, generally considered a workmanlike regional bank, with operations in Louisiana and Texas. There are several rationales for the deal. Although Capital One thrives on credit cards and auto loans, its ability to accept deposits is constrained by its being less than a full-service bank. Hibernia's commercial banking charter will give the company the ability to offer more products, using its well-honed strategy of blanketing the United States with mail offers. By diversifying into home-equity loans, mortgages and other loans with lower interest rates than cards, Capital One can expand its empire and shield its balance sheet from consumer credit cycles. Some analysts, though, maintain that the Capital One profit engine has no need for a sleepy regional bank. They contend, among other things, that the company has already figured out how to finance its lending business in the absence of a large deposit base. "The chestnut that's out there in the industry that they did this to finance their lending business - that doesn't wash," said Theodore Iacobuzio, vice president for research at TowerGroup, a banking and payments consulting firm. "For me, there are more unanswered questions than there are answered questions." Richard D. Fairbank, Capital One's founder and chief executive, says he has an answer: people like to keep their checking and savings accounts at a local bank with lots of convenient branches, but when they are taking out a loan, they care less about geography than about the best deal. In other words, financial services companies should take deposits locally and lend nationally. Although its credit card business has been doing very well - the company expects its loan portfolio to grow at a rate of 12 percent to 15 percent this year - "we came to the conclusion that the right model was to be a diversified lender with a deposit business," Mr. Fairbank said in a recent interview. After shopping a bit for the right bank, Capital One selected Hibernia, which is based in New Orleans. The deal, announced in March, has been delayed and renegotiated because of Hurricane Katrina; Capital One now plans to pay about $5 billion, 9 percent less than the original price, and to close by the end of the year. "We still believe that Hibernia can do for us what we're buying it for," Mr. Fairbank said. He would like Capital One to rely less on the capital markets; bank regulators, which forced the company to increase its loan-loss reserves in 2002, may feel the same way. Wall Street has tended to smile on Capital One because of the consistency of its profits, but its shares have fallen 12.5 percent since their high in August. The stock closed yesterday at $74.79. In a way, the purchase of Hibernia will bring Capital One full circle. The venture was born in 1988 when Mr. Fairbank persuaded Signet Bank of Richmond, Va., to buy his concept of selling consumer products through a strategy that combined technology and direct marketing. Signet, now part of Wachovia, adopted the idea in 1988, hiring Mr. Fairbank and a partner to run its credit card business. But the card operation outgrew the bank and was spun off in 1994. Today, Capital One, with its headquarters in McLean, Va., is credited with pioneering innovations like the teaser rate, dangling once-unthinkable offers like zero percent interest on credit card balances for the first six months of an account, and balance transfers. More recently, a foray into auto lending has gone very well. Capital One bought Summit Acceptance in 1998 for about $60 million, Mr. Fairbank said. Today, Capital One Auto Finance is the third-largest auto lender in the country. At the time, said Michael T. Vinciquerra, an analyst at Raymond James &amp; Associates, he questioned the move into auto lending. Now, Mr. Vinciquerra, who has a strong buy rating on Capital One, says that the premise of marrying the national lending business to a local deposit base seems logical. Mr. Fairbank and his team, he added, "always seem to be thinking a couple of years down the road." Its unorthodox aspects notwithstanding, Capital One's deal for Hibernia does fit with a shift that has been taking place in financial services, away from the single-product model. With a few big exceptions, most specialized lenders have joined forces with more diverse companies. In credit cards, American Express stands largely on its own as the last pure card company, having emphatically pared back its other operations (including, last week, its financial advisory business, which started trading as Ameriprise Financial). The Discover card continues to live on as part of Morgan Stanley. But Capital One considers Hibernia just a start, and plans to bulk up in both deposits and consumer lending. "We positioned ourselves to be one of the consolidators rather than on the receiving end of the consolidation, as most banks are," Mr. Fairbank said. Indeed, Mr. Fairbank is of the view that banks that do not already have a national lending business like his credit card franchise may find themselves at a disadvantage. Take Wachovia, for instance, which considered buying MBNA before Bank of America snapped it up. There are not many such companies left to buy, he said, but there are certainly a lot of banks left to add to Capital One's portfolio. "Would I like to be in 50 states with deposits? I might like that," Mr. Fairbank said. "I'd be shocked if five years from now, we were not already thought of as a bank."</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/08/business/08bank.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Lowers Its Purchase Price for Bank Based in New Orleans<date>Published: September 8, 2005</date><text>Capital One Financial said yesterday that it reduced the price of its planned purchase of the New Orleans-based Hibernia Corporation by 7.6 percent, to $5 billion, after Hurricane Katrina left a fifth of Hibernia's branches in the affected area with "significant damage." Hibernia investors will receive $30.49 a share in cash and stock, down from $33. The companies delayed the deal's completion and will put the revised terms to a new vote by Hibernia shareholders, they said in a statement. Skip to next paragraph Katrina, which left 80 percent of New Orleans under water, affected a third of Hibernia's 321 branches, and the bank, Louisiana's biggest, has reopened only 47 since the storm hit last week. Capital One expects to complete the transaction in the fourth quarter. "I view it as a good compromise," said Kevin Fitzsimmons, an analyst at Sandler O'Neill &amp; Partners in New York who has a buy rating on Hibernia and does not own shares of the bank. "Capital One is able to appease their shareholders while at the same time being sensitive to the Hibernia shareholders and the long-term value of that franchise." Shares of Hibernia fell $1.54, or 4.9 percent, to $29.86 in New York Stock Exchange trading. Capital One declined $1.05, to $79.45. No date has been set for the new shareholder vote, a Capital One spokeswoman, Julie Rakes, said. Hibernia must first send a revised proxy statement to its shareholders. A Hibernia spokesman, Steven Thorpe, did not answer calls to a temporary office in Texas seeking comment. The prior terms were approved by a margin of more than 94 percent of the votes cast at an Aug. 3 Hibernia shareholder meeting. The companies assessed the impact of Katrina on Hibernia's branches and headquarters in New Orleans, its loan portfolio, and future prospects, including government aid and insurance proceeds, they said in the statement. "While no one can predict the impact of Katrina with certainty, I remain convinced of the strategic value of this transaction and believe that Hibernia is well positioned to grow and generate significant shareholder value over time," Capital One's chief executive, Richard D. Fairbank, said in the statement. Ms. Rakes, the Capital One spokeswoman, declined to comment further on how the companies arrived at the $350 million price reduction. The companies made independent assessments, said Tatiana Stead, another Capital One spokeswoman. Capital One, which is based in McLean, Va., wants to acquire a bank to expand its financial services and reduce the cost of financing its credit card operations. Under the revised terms, Capital One would swap 0.2055 share and $13.95 for each share of Hibernia, down from the 0.2261 share and $15.35 it agreed to pay March 6. About $2.2 billion of the new purchase price would be cash, compared with $2.4 billion previously. About two-thirds of Hibernia's branches are in Louisiana; most of the rest are in Texas. Hibernia has $22.1 billion in assets. More Articles in Business &gt;Capital One Financial said yesterday that it reduced the price of its planned purchase of the New Orleans-based Hibernia Corporation by 7.6 percent, to $5 billion, after Hurricane Katrina left a fifth of Hibernia's branches in the affected area with "significant damage." Hibernia investors will receive $30.49 a share in cash and stock, down from $33. The companies delayed the deal's completion and will put the revised terms to a new vote by Hibernia shareholders, they said in a statement. Skip to next paragraph Katrina, which left 80 percent of New Orleans under water, affected a third of Hibernia's 321 branches, and the bank, Louisiana's biggest, has reopened only 47 since the storm hit last week. Capital One expects to complete the transaction in the fourth quarter. "I view it as a good compromise," said Kevin Fitzsimmons, an analyst at Sandler O'Neill &amp; Partners in New York who has a buy rating on Hibernia and does not own shares of the bank. "Capital One is able to appease their shareholders while at the same time being sensitive to the Hibernia shareholders and the long-term value of that franchise." Shares of Hibernia fell $1.54, or 4.9 percent, to $29.86 in New York Stock Exchange trading. Capital One declined $1.05, to $79.45. No date has been set for the new shareholder vote, a Capital One spokeswoman, Julie Rakes, said. Hibernia must first send a revised proxy statement to its shareholders. A Hibernia spokesman, Steven Thorpe, did not answer calls to a temporary office in Texas seeking comment. The prior terms were approved by a margin of more than 94 percent of the votes cast at an Aug. 3 Hibernia shareholder meeting. The companies assessed the impact of Katrina on Hibernia's branches and headquarters in New Orleans, its loan portfolio, and future prospects, including government aid and insurance proceeds, they said in the statement. "While no one can predict the impact of Katrina with certainty, I remain convinced of the strategic value of this transaction and believe that Hibernia is well positioned to grow and generate significant shareholder value over time," Capital One's chief executive, Richard D. Fairbank, said in the statement. Ms. Rakes, the Capital One spokeswoman, declined to comment further on how the companies arrived at the $350 million price reduction. The companies made independent assessments, said Tatiana Stead, another Capital One spokeswoman. Capital One, which is based in McLean, Va., wants to acquire a bank to expand its financial services and reduce the cost of financing its credit card operations. Under the revised terms, Capital One would swap 0.2055 share and $13.95 for each share of Hibernia, down from the 0.2261 share and $15.35 it agreed to pay March 6. About $2.2 billion of the new purchase price would be cash, compared with $2.4 billion previously. About two-thirds of Hibernia's branches are in Louisiana; most of the rest are in Texas. Hibernia has $22.1 billion in assets.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/01/business/01hibernia.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Deal Is Put Off for Louisiana Bank<date>Published: September 1, 2005</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation and the Hibernia Corporation yesterday delayed the closing of their $5 billion merger by one week, citing the devastation and disruption caused by Hurricane Katrina. Capital One's acquisition of Hibernia, which is based in New Orleans, had been scheduled to close today, but it will now close on Sept. 7. Earlier in the day, Wall Street analysts said they expected the closing to be postponed so that the companies could review any financial damage Hibernia and its customer base may have suffered. A "material adverse change" in Hibernia's business could prompt Capital One to try to renegotiate the deal, although analysts said such a drastic move was unlikely. Hibernia's customer base could be at risk of failing to repay loans because of financial strain caused by the hurricane, analysts said. The bank also may lose deposits and accounts if customers relocate to other states, and may face higher costs if its bank branches suffered structural damage, analysts said. Citigroup Investment Research analysts said they expected the storm to put financial pressure on Hibernia for the second half of 2005. The bank could benefit in 2006, however, as customers deposit any payments insurance companies provide to rebuild homes and businesses. More Articles in Business &gt;The Capital One Financial Corporation and the Hibernia Corporation yesterday delayed the closing of their $5 billion merger by one week, citing the devastation and disruption caused by Hurricane Katrina. Capital One's acquisition of Hibernia, which is based in New Orleans, had been scheduled to close today, but it will now close on Sept. 7. Earlier in the day, Wall Street analysts said they expected the closing to be postponed so that the companies could review any financial damage Hibernia and its customer base may have suffered. A "material adverse change" in Hibernia's business could prompt Capital One to try to renegotiate the deal, although analysts said such a drastic move was unlikely. Hibernia's customer base could be at risk of failing to repay loans because of financial strain caused by the hurricane, analysts said. The bank also may lose deposits and accounts if customers relocate to other states, and may face higher costs if its bank branches suffered structural damage, analysts said. Citigroup Investment Research analysts said they expected the storm to put financial pressure on Hibernia for the second half of 2005. The bank could benefit in 2006, however, as customers deposit any payments insurance companies provide to rebuild homes and businesses.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/07/business/07capital.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Plans to Buy Hibernia<date>Published: March 7, 2005</date><text>he Capital One Financial Corporation, one of the nation's biggest credit card companies, said yesterday that it would buy the Hibernia Corporation, a regional banking company based in New Orleans, for $5.35 billion. Capital One, which is based in McLean, Va., has repeatedly told Wall Street that owning a retail bank would help it lower its cost of borrowing, increase deposits and compete more vigorously in the credit card business. The deal for Hibernia, which has $21 billion in assets and more than 300 branches in Louisiana and Texas, would do all those things, Capital One said. The company said it was particularly attracted by Hibernia's recent expansion in Texas, which is a growing market for financial services. Capital One will retain Hibernia's management, employees and branch system but eventually change the franchise's name. The companies expect to realize $135 million in cost savings and "revenue synergies" in the near term, Capital One said. "What we're doing is rounding out our banking model by going into a business that has tremendous synergy with what we do," said Richard D. Fairbank, the chief executive of Capital One, in an interview. "This is not only another growth opportunity in its own right but it also strengthens our balance sheet." The deal represents something of a full circle for Capital One, which was spun off from a regional bank a decade ago. Capital One had $80 billion in managed loans outstanding at the end of 2004.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D71230F933A15751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Capital One Names Creative Team for U.S.<date>Published: December 20, 2004</date><text>Capital One Financial has named the Chicago office of DDB Worldwide and Element 79 Partners in Chicago, units of the Omnicom Group, to handle the creative duties on its United States account, which had been handled since 2003 by McCann Erickson Worldwide in New York, part of the McCann Worldgroup division of the Interpublic Group of Companies. Billings were estimated at $170 million to $190 million. Element 79 had already handled a variety of projects for Capital One. MediaVest USA in New York, part of the Starcom MediaVest division of the Publicis Groupe, continues to handle media planning and buying.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3D6113CF933A25752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CAPITAL ONE ELIMINATES 750 JOBS IN TWO STATES<date>Published: November 10, 2004</date><text>The Capital One Corporation, a credit card issuer, said yesterday that it would eliminate 750 jobs in offices in Federal Way, Wash., and Richmond, Va., as part of an agreement to shift work to the First Data Corporation. First Data, based in Greenwood Village, Colo., said that it intended to offer jobs to some nonmanagement employees of Capital One whose positions were cut. Capital One is based in McLean, Va.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D8173CF937A35752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CAPITAL ONE PURCHASING HFS, A BRITISH HOME LOAN BROKER<date>Published: November 4, 2004</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, a credit card and auto lender, said it would pay $117 million to buy a British home equity loan broker, the HFS Group. The deal will broaden Capital One's reach in Britain, where it is already a large issuer of Visa and MasterCard credit cards. HFS, a privately held company founded in 1969, underwrites home equity loans. In the year ended March 31, 2004, it underwrote 15,000 loans worth about £350 million ($630 million). HFS, which is based in Macclesfield, Cheshire, will become a subsidiary of Capital One Bank Europe.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DA1039F930A1575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CAPITAL ONE IS BUYING ONYX FOR $191 MILLION<date>Published: September 23, 2004</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, one of the largest providers of MasterCard and Visa credit cards, said yesterday that it would buy the Onyx Acceptance Corporation for $191 million to expand its automobile lending operations. Capital One, based in McLean, Va., said that Onyx's shareholders would receive $28 a share. Capital One said that its auto finance subsidiary, Capital One Auto Finance Inc., would be combined with Onyx when the deal is completed. Onyx, based in Foothill Ranch, Calif., provides loans to new and used car dealerships.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/07/business/media/07adco.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">An Actor Working on Madison Avenue<date>Published: September 7, 2004</date><text>OME people might say that Rob Huebel, a New York comedian, has a certain je ne sais quoi about him. More simply, though, they might call him "that guy in the commercials." Mr. Huebel is riding a sudden hot streak on Madison Avenue, with starring roles in campaigns for FedEx/Kinkos, Solae brand soy products and NetZero Internet service. He has also played "Inconsiderate Cellphone Man" in theater announcements sponsored by Cingular Wireless for nearly two years. Advertisement Mr. Huebel provides the voice yelling at David Spade over the phone in current commercials for credit cards from Capital One Financial. Next month, he will appear in a new Certs commercial, too. Viewers have grown accustomed to faces in commercials before, if not always the names that go with them. Squire Fridell, for one, appeared in thousands of commercials for companies or brands like Brawny, Charmin, McDonald's and Toyota. Actors, too, often make stops on Madison Avenue as they climb or descend the Hollywood ladder. Before Jason Alexander was cast to play George Costanza on "Seinfeld," he performed a musical number in a commercial for McDonald's McDLT sandwich. After "Seinfeld" made him famous, he became an endorser for KFC, undoubtedly at a higher rate. The question for Mr. Huebel now is whether the commercials pave the way to bigger things, or just eat up his 15 minutes of fame in 30-second increments. "It's definitely worked to my benefit, although people are probably sick of seeing me," Mr. Huebel said. "My agents are definitely worried about it. We had a meeting about it the other day and they were like, 'You're going to have to lay low for a while.' " At the moment, Mr. Huebel is playing numerous characters that may seem absurd, or absurdist, but somehow still charm. In his FedEx/Kinkos spot, created by BBDO Worldwide in New York, he portrays a businessman pointing out mementos as he gives a woman an office tour. "That's a dollar bill from our first sale," he says. "And that's a note from our first client just wishing us luck." The woman asks about a chair lodged halfway through the wall. Mr. Huebel's unperturbed guide explains: "That's our first temper tantrum. We needed to ship a package and the UPS Store was closed. Steve lost it." In the Solae ads, which are riffs on classic blind taste tests, Mr. Huebel surprises and blindfolds subjects before subjecting them to the Solae Protein Quiz. He asks them to choose, for example, which contains protein: a Snapple or suckling pig. (They both do, because the Snapple contains soy protein from Solae, a joint venture between DuPont and Bunge.) "He's a very recognizable character," said John McNeil, creative director at Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide in New York, part of the WPP Group and the agency behind the Solae campaign. "It's not the everyman, because it's a little bit more highbrow, but he's got this kind of aw-shucks quality." The simultaneous commercials starring Mr. Huebel are more coincidence than anything else; the campaigns were cast and created at different times by different agencies. "I'm not sure that four different accounts at Ogilvy would ever cast Rob in ads that would be running simultaneously," Mr. McNeil said. "But we can't really control the exposure of a given actor. The only way to predict an actor's success is based on how good they are." Some of Mr. Huebel's success stems from his skill at improvisation, which he practiced as a member of a New York comedy troupe called the Upright Citizens Brigade, agency executives said. " 'Waiting for Guffman,' 'Best in Show,' even 'Curb Your Enthusiasm,' which are all loosely scripted, are all really funny right now," said Chris Corley, the copywriter at Bernstein-Rein Advertising in Kansas City, Mo., who wrote the commercials for NetZero, part of United Online. "That's what we were trying to get for our spots, too." The NetZero campaign depicts an out-of-it candidate for president - Mr. Huebel - whose platform revolves around Web access. "You know," says Candidate Zero in one spot, "America is a beautiful land of freedom, where the woodchucks can chuck and the deer can do whatever it is deer like to do." Mr. Huebel was previously rejected for the role of the Miller Brewing spokesman who declared Miller Lite a candidate for "president of beers" this year. "Miller wouldn't have me for my campaign, so I took my platform elsewhere," Mr. Huebel said. All the face time has brought Mr. Huebel a vague sort of celebrity. "I do get recognized," he said. "It depends on what I'm wearing. If I'm talking on my cellphone then people recognize Inconsiderate Cellphone Man. People will say 'mauled by a tiger!' " The tiger line is one of many exclamations Mr. Huebel makes as Inconsiderate Cellphone Man, who answers his phone in settings like movie theaters, his wedding and a couples counseling session. The campaign was created by the Atlanta office of BBDO, part of the Omnicom Group. (Cingular, owned by BellSouth and SBC Communications, pulled the spot containing the tiger reference after a tiger mauled Roy Horn of Siegfried &amp; Roy onstage in Las Vegas last October.) After the quiet period his managers have recommended, Mr. Huebel hopes to return to television more regularly. He and a comedy partner, Rob Riggle, are pitching ideas for shows to NBC and Comedy Central, and Mr. Huebel is working on a pilot for the Bravo network. Having a steady television role would at least spare Mr. Huebel the sometimes bizarre auditions he has gone through. He recalled once going to an unusual Saturday audition to try out for an unspecified project. "I walked in and it was very mysterious," Mr. Huebel said, describing a room full of Germans and a dog. The director asked him to turn around and remove his shirt, he said. "Then you hear just snickering and the director goes, 'This will be great, just great.' Then they go, 'Act like you're eating some scrambled eggs.' " "I never heard about anything again," Mr. Huebel said. "Somewhere I'm probably on some kind of German television show of weird auditions where people eat eggs."</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/27/business/capital-one-investigation-produces-suit.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Capital One Investigation Produces Suit<date>Published: July 27, 2004</date><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission filed an insider-trading lawsuit yesterday against David M. Willey, the former chief financial officer of the Capital One Financial Corporation, accusing him of selling millions of dollars' worth of stock ahead of regulatory actions against the company in 2002.The civil lawsuit, filed in Federal District Court in the District of Columbia, seeks to permanently bar Mr. Willey from serving as an officer or director of any public company and demands that he forfeit all the gains from his stock sales, plus interest and penalties. It also seeks the forfeiture of gains made by his wife, Joy S. Willey, from her husband's trades in Capital One shares. Mr. Willey resigned from Capital One on March 3, 2003.The Federal Reserve began a supervisory review of Capital One in early 2002, when the company applied to merge two subsidiaries. Regulators soon grew concerned about the bank's credit quality. On April 18, the examiner in charge of Capital One's case told Mr. Willey that he was considering downgrading the evaluation of the bank and would most likely take some regulatory action.According to the S.E.C.'s complaint, however, Mr. Willey did not tell Capital One's senior management or board about the potential problem. Instead, in the days before the Fed informed other Capital One executives, Mr. Willey exercised tens of thousands of options of Capital One stock and sold tens of thousands of shares, both for his own account and his wife's, over which he had power of attorney.On May 13, Fed officials told other company executives of the likely downgrade, and Capital One's general counsel barred senior executives from trading in the company's shares.On July 16, 2002, Capital One announced that it had entered into a memorandum of understanding with the Fed under which it would increase its reserves against bad loans and upgrade its technology and audit procedures used to provide loans and credit cards to consumers with a poor history of borrowing.After the disclosure, Capital One's stock price fell by 40 percent. But according to the complaint, Mr. Willey had already netted more than $3 million from the trades.Richard Morvillo, the lawyer for Mr. Willey, said his client would contest the case.''The Willeys are disappointed that the S.E.C. chose to initiate this action after an extended and constructive dialogue about their motivations and actions,'' Mr. Morvillo said. ''After these many months in limbo, the Willeys look forward to an early trial date and a favorable resolution.''A spokeswoman for Capital One, Tatiana Stead, noted that Mr. Willey left the company more than a year ago. ''Neither Capital One nor any member of its current management team or employees are parties to the action brought by the S.E.C.,'' she said.Capital One shares have recovered since March 2003, rising to more than $68 -- above the level they had been at before the regulatory action was disclosed in July 2002. Ms. Stead also noted that regulators lifted the memorandum of understanding last January.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/12/us/fight-against-fat-shifting-to-the-workplace.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Fight Against Fat Shifting to the Workplace<date>Published: October 12, 2003</date><text>Like other Sprint employees, Kent Turner has adjusted to the company's new office park here on a former soybean field in a suburb of Kansas City, but he does wonder why the elevators are so pokey when the buildings are new.''We believe,'' he confided, smiling, ''that it's a sinister plot to get us to take the stairs.''Sinister, no; plot, yes.Sprint planned its 200-acre world headquarters with an eye to fitness. It banned cars, forcing employees to park in garages on the far side of a road ringing the campus and walk between buildings as much as a half-mile apart. It put in hydraulic -- that is, slow -- elevators and wide, windowed staircases to encourage people to walk rather than ride between floors.Across the country, companies, states and schools are taking more aggressive -- if perhaps passive-aggressive -- measures to get an increasingly overweight society to move more and eat less. The new methods go beyond putting gyms in office buildings or teaching children (or adults) the virtues of broccoli.Union Pacific Railroad has begun offering some employees the latest prescription weight-loss drugs as part of a study to determine how best to get its workers to slim down. At the new headquarters for Capital One outside Richmond, Va., the architects set the food court at the end of a string of buildings, rather than at the center.''It's a place one has to walk to,'' said Jim Carter, an architect with Hillier, the firm that also designed the Sprint campus. ''We want people to get out of their desks and out of their offices and move around.''Programs that nudge people to move more or eat better are responding to a growing public health crisis: the federal Department of Health and Human Services puts the cost of overweight and obese Americans at $117 billion in 2000, and said that being overweight results in 300,000 deaths a year.''There are times when we as a nation feel that personal responsibility is not getting the job done, and so we have to take action,'' said Kelly D. Brownell, director of the Yale University Center for Eating and Weight Disorders. ''We could count on parents to get their children immunized, but they don't, therefore we require it. We could count on people being responsible and not smoking cigarettes, but we have a huge health crisis brought on by people smoking cigarettes.''</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/13/business/personal-business-diary-a-card-that-s-picky-about-who-can-charge.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">PERSONAL BUSINESS: DIARY; A Card That's Picky About Who Can Charge<date>Published: July 13, 2003</date><text>Not to be outdone by record-low interest rates on home mortgages and student loans, Capital One last week introduced a credit card with a fixed rate of 4.99 percent. The company says the card has the lowest fixed rate in the nation, excluding promotional rates that last only a few months.The 4.99 percent rate applies to both purchases and balances transferred from other credit cards. In addition, the new card has no annual fee and does not charge extra for cash advances or balance transfers.Consumers interested in the card, which will carry a MasterCard logo, will have to wait to see if Capital One is interested in them: the company said it is offering the card only through direct mailings to people whose credit histories qualify them for it. There is no way to request an application, Capital One said.The company said it wanted consumers with excellent credit histories. It would not disclose, however, the criteria it was using -- for instance, what kind of credit score a prospective cardholder should have.Those consumers should receive solicitations for the card sometime this summer, said Diana Don, Capital One's director of consumer education.According to a survey in July by CardWeb.com, which tracks the credit card industry, the next-lowest fixed rate on a no-fee card is 7.99 percent, which American Express offers to some of its cardholders. Jennifer Bayot</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/14/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-former-d-arcy-client-moves-to-new-agency.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Former D'Arcy Client Moves to New Agency<date>Published: April 14, 2003</date><text>In the biggest fallout yet from the decision by the Publicis Groupe to dissolve D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles, a major D'Arcy client said Friday that it was moving its creative account to an agency owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies.Capital One Financial named McCann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising in New York as creative agency of record on its account, with billings estimated at $170 million. The account had been handled on an interim basis by the Kaplan Thaler Group, part of Publicis.Bill McDonald, executive vice president for brand marketing at Capital One in McLean, Va., confirmed a report of the move on Adweek.com.The decision came after a four-month review that included McCann-Erickson and five other agencies: a team of Abbott Mead Vickers BBDO in London and Element 79 Partners in Chicago, both part of the Omnicom Group; Faulds Advertising in London; and a team of Kaplan Thaler in New York and the London office of sibling Publicis Worldwide.Publicis has been able to move most of the accounts handled by D'Arcy to other Publicis agencies, but Capital One took the closing of D'Arcy as a review opportunity.The London office of McCann-Erickson, part of the McCann-Erickson World Group unit of Interpublic, will handle advertising in Britain.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/travel/l-credit-card-woes-846953.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Credit Card Woes<date>Published: March 23, 2003</date><text>To the Editor: I read ''Credit Cards Far From Home'' (March 2) with interest because my Capital One Visa credit card was canceled while I was living and traveling in England last summer, even after I had advised the company of the itinerary for my two-month stay.Before leaving the United States, I told the credit card company that I planned to use its card to insure my rental car for two months. They told me that they could only insure the car for 30-day periods and that I would have to reinsure it.The employees of the subsidiary office of SIXT car rental rewrote the contract for a second 30-day period and sent the original to their home office in Germany.Visa, knowing that I was living in England, saw a charge of $2,000 emanating from Germany and assumed that my card had been stolen. They canceled my card, without having any way to communicate this to me. Luckily, that evening a waiter in a restaurant told me my card had been canceled, and I was able to contact Visa in the United States and reactivate my card. However, during the time my card was canceled I was driving a car without valid insurance.BRUCE GOLDFADENBoynton Beach, Fla.Diana Don, a spokeswoman for Capital One, responds: Mr. Goldfaden did call to alert us that he would be traveling to the United Kingdom. Unfortunately, he did not verify that he would be making charges in Germany. When we suspect any type of fraudulent use, we will suspend activity on the account until we can verify the charges by the cardholder.When he found out that his card had been suspended, Mr. Goldfaden did the right thing by calling Visa International (they put him in touch with our offices). Alternatively, he could have called Capital One; in these matters, we accept collect calls from anywhere in the world.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/17/business/aarp-joins-in-age-discrimination-lawsuit.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">AARP Joins in Age Discrimination Lawsuit<date>Published: March 17, 2003</date><text>AARP has joined an age discrimination lawsuit filed in Virginia against Capital One Financial.AARP, the senior citizens lobby, will participate in the suit with Butler, Williams, Pantele &amp; Skilling of Richmond.The suit accuses Capital One of instituting a plan of ''forced separation'' that was unfair to employees age 40 and older.A motion filed Friday in United States District Court in Richmond expanded the period covered in the suit from Oct. 1, 2001, to the present. The lawsuit originally covered the period from Oct. 1, 2001, to Sept. 30, 2002.As many as 60 former Capital One employees have stepped forward to become plaintiffs, said Harris D. Butler III of Butler, Williams, Pantele &amp; Skilling.Mr. Butler said he expected the judge to rule within the next four months on whether the lawsuit can proceed as a class action.A Capital One spokesman said the company did not comment on litigation. The company has said the firings were the result of poor performance under a forced-ranking employee-appraisal system.AARP, however, said the forced-ranking system has been used by some other companies to ''mask a desire to jettison older workers and other employees, even if they have previously received high ratings.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/22/business/responsible-party-kirk-watkins-paying-bills-from-your-paycheck.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">RESPONSIBLE PARTY -- KIRK WATKINS; Paying Bills From Your Paycheck<date>Published: September 22, 2002</date><text>IN the late 1990's, Kirk Watkins was the chief executive of Uniform Concepts, a company that offered payroll-deduction programs through which hospitals' employees could buy their uniforms. But for the hospitals, the program could be a nightmare of data entry and paperwork.In August 1999, Mr. Watkins arrived at a solution in an old-fashioned way. ''Literally, I woke up at 3 o'clock in the morning,'' he said, with the idea of a card that would work as a debit card. At the point of purchase, it would immediately deduct money from a person's salary, thus bypassing bank accounts and payroll offices.Over the next few months, Mr. Watkins, who is now 37, develped the idea, and in 2000 he renamed the company E-Duction. Originally, he thought the card would be accepted by a limited number of merchants. But after he and his staff polled consumers, he decided that the card would have more appeal if it could be used universally. In 2001, E-Duction reached partnership agreements with MasterCard and Capital One bank, and the Clear card was born.When a company agrees to offer the card to employees, E-Duction sets up the necessary technology. Employees can then sign up for the card, which has a $29 annual fee, and use it at any location that accepts MasterCard. The charges are taken from the employee's pay in interest-free payments over the next two months. For example, if a worker who is paid twice a month buys a $100 pair of sneakers, her next four paychecks will be $25 lighter. The employer pays nothing and the employee avoids interest payments and late fees. The merchant pays a fee of 1.6 percent, which is split by E-Duction and Capital One.Since January of this year, about a dozen companies have signed on for Clear, Mr. Watkins said, including Western Union and Reliance Standard Life Insurance.The card is useful in cash emergencies, but its real advantage is convenience, he said: ''Now you just payroll-deduct and throw the bills away.'' CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/18/business/company-news-regulatory-move-causes-drop-in-capital-one-shares.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGULATORY MOVE CAUSES DROP IN CAPITAL ONE SHARES<date>Published: July 18, 2002</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, a leading issuer of Visa and MasterCard credit cards, said regulators required it to increase reserves for loan losses, setting off a sharp decline in its stock and that of its rivals. Capital One shares fell $20.12, or 39.8 percent, to $30.48. There were also losses in the stocks of the Providian Financial Corporation and Household International Inc., rivals that, like Capital One, have lent to clients with a history of bad credit. Although Capital One has had fewer unpaid bills than rivals, regulators said they were concerned that the company had grown too fast. Capital One said yesterday that it added $247 million in reserves in the second quarter to meet federal requirements.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/14/business/personal-business-diary-oh-please-buy-me-that-gel-roller-pen.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">PERSONAL BUSINESS: DIARY; Oh, Please Buy Me That Gel Roller Pen<date>Published: July 14, 2002</date><text>Some parents would do just about anything to avoid shopping with teenagers, those wide-eyed receptacles for all things commercial. ''Please buy me this. Everyone has it.'' And those who resist, of course, are ''the meanest parents in the world.''But more than one-third of parents and teenagers consider back-to-school shopping as ''quality time,'' according to a recent nationwide survey by Capital One Financial. The survey involved 509 youngsters aged 12 to 17 and 536 parents.Capital One suggests that this mandatory shopping trip could give parents a shot at playing ''financial educator.'' After all, for most teenagers, money is something parents have and kids spend. Just 9 percent of them, the study notes, have taken a course in money management.Parents will spend $97 on school supplies this year, on average, down from $118 last year, but they will ''feel pressure,'' the survey notes gently, to spend more. Students will chip in an extra $45.And what are the hot products? Frosted three-ring binders lead the list, followed by gel roller pens, Osbournes backpacks, neon Dr. Grip pens and sparkle pencils. (Yes, you're forgiven if you don't have a clue what some of these things are.)Strangely, only 16 percent of teenagers wanted the ''newest, coolest items.'' Perhaps they were asked that question too early in the morning. Hubert B. Herring</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/24/business/buyback-at-capital-one.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">Buyback at Capital One<date>Published: February 24, 2000</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, a credit card provider, said today that it would buy back up to 10 million of its shares. The buyback, which will take place in the next two years, will involve about 5.1 percent of the company's 197.2 million shares outstanding. Capital One's latest buyback program is in addition to previous plans that were announced in 1997 and 1998. The company can still buy back 2.25 million shares under those programs. Shares of Capital One, which is based in Falls Church, Va., rose 50 cents, to $34.4375, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/12/business/america-s-turn-to-colonize-credit-card-issuers-invade-britain-with-us-firepower.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">America's Turn to Colonize; Credit Card Issuers Invade Britain, With U.S. Firepower<date>Published: November 12, 1998</date><text>What, precisely, is Billy Connolly, the Scottish comedian, doing in biblical robes and beard in a commercial with floating goldfish that fill the television screen?Improbably, the answer lies in a remarkable American invasion of the credit card industry in Britain that has left big British credit card issuers smarting. For the goldfish represent the Goldfish card, which has gained 800,000 customers since it was first issued in 1996 by a British subsidiary of Household International Inc. of Prospect Heights, Ill., in conjunction with a British gas utility.Indeed, in just a few years, Household and other American companies -- including MBNA of Wilmington, Del.; People's Bank of Bridgeport, Conn.; American Express, and Capital One Financial of Falls Church, Va. -- have captured 10.2 percent of the cards issued in a $136.7 billion market that was once controlled exclusively by four big British banks led by Barclays P.L.C. with its Barclaycard. The Americans have shaken up the industry with innovative marketing and by offering interest rates that are lower than the average rates of 22 and 23 percent charged by British issuers.''It's a battleground,'' acknowledged John Eaton, the managing director of Barclaycard. The company is still the dominant issuer of cards in Britain, but its share of the market here has fallen to 31 percent last year from 37.1 percent in 1995, and the number of different cards available in Britain has grown to 1,200, from 40 in 1990.''It's a tough, competitive market,'' Mr. Eaton said.Some American companies see further gains ahead. The credit card business in Britain is similar to the way the United States market was in the 1980's, said Patrick Nelson, corporate communications manager for Capital One.''If you look back at the U.S. market in 1986, and look at it now, you will find only three or four of the big players in '86 are still there,'' he said. ''And there is that same potential here in the United Kingdom. U.K. High Street banks have been charging far too much for far too long.''The American beachhead in Britain could serve as a springboard into a much bigger and largely untapped market: Continental Europe. The Continent has outstanding Visa and Mastercard debt estimated at $49 billion -- much less than the $397 billion in Visa and Mastercard debt in the United States. Credit cards have failed to win mass acceptance in much of Europe, where big banks dominate with debit cards and personal checking accounts.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/17/business/company-news-capital-one-plans-purchase-of-auto-financing-company.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CAPITAL ONE PLANS PURCHASE OF AUTO FINANCING COMPANY<date>Published: July 17, 1998</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, the ninth-largest credit card issuer, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the privately held Summit Acceptance Corporation, a Dallas-based auto finance company specializing in loans to consumers with troubled credit histories, for about $55 million in stock. The acquisition will give Capital One about $260 million in serviced loans. Capital One, which is based in Falls Church, Va., said the purchase will probably have no effect on its earnings per share in 1998, but predicted it will add to them in 1999. Its shares fell $2.4375 each, to $124.6875.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/18/business/capital-one-to-buy-deposits-from-j-c-penney.html?ref=capitalonefinancialcorporation">CAPITAL ONE TO BUY DEPOSITS FROM J. C. PENNEY<date>Published: June 18, 1997</date><text>The Capital One Financial Corporation, the credit card issuer, said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire $425 million in deposits from the J. C. Penney Company for an undisclosed amount. The Capital One FSB unit, formed last year, will assume the deposits from JCPenney National Bank. The sale would allow J. C. Penney, based in Plano, Tex., to focus on its stores and catalogues. Capital One, of Falls Church, Va., has $12.6 billion in loans outstanding and 9.1 million card holders. Its shares closed at $33.75 yesterday, down 50 cents, while J. C. Penney rose $1, to $52.75.</text></article></page><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
