<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Caterpillar Inc"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/25/business/caterpillar-profit-rises-44.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Profit Rises 44%<date>Published: October 24, 2011</date><text>Caterpillar reported a surprising 44 percent increase in quarterly profit and forecast strong demand through next year in a sign of optimism for the global economy.The company said on Monday that it expected full-year 2011 profit and revenue to set records as a result of surging sales for mining equipment and construction machinery in most markets around the world. Caterpillar executives said they expected that momentum to carry into next year, with sales rising up to 20 percent above the $58 billion in sales it expects to have this year. “We’re having a great year in 2011, and 2012 is shaping up to be better,” said Douglas R. Oberhelman, Caterpillar’s chief executive. Caterpillar said it had hired nearly 5,000 people in the quarter. The bullish news from Caterpillar came after strong forecasts from General Electric and United Technologies. Caterpillar’s stock rose $4.38, or 5 percent, to $91.77. Caterpillar said it ended the third quarter in one of the healthiest positions in its recent history. Backlogged orders stood at record levels and higher commodity prices helped its growing mining business, which performed well in markets around the world. Caterpillar reported third-quarter net income of $1.14 billion, or $1.71 a share, compared with $792 million, or $1.22 a share, a year before. Analysts on average expected Caterpillar to earn $1.54 a share in the third quarter. Sales rose 41 percent to $15.7 billion, a record, according to the company. Caterpillar earned $1.93 a share on $14.58 billion in sales excluding the impact of the acquisition of the Bucyrus mining business earlier this year. It expects annual sales of $58 billion, including the impact of its acquisition of Bucyrus, in 2011. Its previous forecast was a range of $56 billion to $58 billion. Profit is expected to be $6.75 a share for the year, compared with a previous forecast of $6.25 to $6.75.Caterpillar reported a surprising 44 percent increase in quarterly profit and forecast strong demand through next year in a sign of optimism for the global economy.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/27/opinion/factory-field-trip.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Factory Field Trip<date>Published: September 26, 2011</date><text>Charlotte, N.C.If you want to feel optimistic about the state of manufacturing in America, you ought to spend a day with Stephen Gray. Then again, if you want to feel depressed about the state of manufacturing in America, you ought to spend a day with — yep — Stephen Gray. Gray, 46, is chief executive of Gray Construction, a family-owned company, based in Lexington, Ky., that builds factories for big firms. As a result, far more than most people, he has his finger on the pulse of manufacturing in this country. Not so long ago, Gray told me, the future looked grim. Manufacturing companies were canceling construction projects. The 10 or so factories Gray was building were nearing completion, yet there was nothing new in the pipeline. Gray was forced to lay off employees. The recession was taking a terrible toll. But, in the summer of 2010, Gray Construction began to turn around because manufacturing itself began to turn around. There were six big jobs up for bid, including a Siemens factory in Charlotte, N.C., and a Caterpillar plant in Winston-Salem. Gray won them all. It now has 22 projects in various stages of development. With the two North Carolina plants nearly done, Gray asked me if I wanted to tour them. I said yes. It is impossible not to be impressed with modern manufacturing plants like the Siemens and Caterpillar facilities. They are, first of all, immense; the Caterpillar plant in Winston-Salem, for instance, which will make gigantic axles for its mining trucks, is 850,000 square feet. Both plants use complex robotics, yet still convey the brawn we associate with manufacturing, with giant cranes that lift — in the case of the Siemens plant — the 280-ton gas turbines the plant will soon be making. Secondly, these plants offer something that has become increasingly rare: middle-class jobs that don’t require a college degree. The jobs pay between $20 and $30 an hour, plus benefits, allowing a skilled machinist to make a decent middle-class living. The key word, of course, is “skilled.” One reason Siemens and Caterpillar chose North Carolina is that Charlotte and Winston-Salem have community colleges that stress manufacturing skills. In Winston-Salem, Forsyth Tech, a local community college, was involved in wooing Caterpillar and created a program, in cooperation with the company, to make sure its graduates have the machining skills the company needs. Job training was part of the incentives packages that were dangled in front of the companies to lure them to North Carolina. When I asked Richard Voorberg of Siemens why the German company chose to put its new plant in Charlotte instead of, say, China, he said that for highly skilled work, the labor cost differential wasn’t very big and that, in any case, factors like shipping costs and efficiency mattered more. “For this kind of manufacturing,” he said, “the U.S. can compete with China.” Gray Construction’s backlog of projects suggests that other manufacturers — many of them foreign companies — have come to the same conclusion. That’s the optimistic part. Now for the depressing part. Despite the size of the factories, the tens of millions in investments the companies are making, not to mention the millions in incentives and tax abatements that Charlotte and Winston-Salem used to land them, neither Siemens nor Caterpillar is going to employ that many people. Caterpillar is getting an estimated $14 million in incentives, yet it will employ only 500 or so workers in Winston-Salem. Siemens doesn’t expect to employ more than 800 people in the Charlotte facility. The same robotics technology that makes these plants so efficient also means they don’t need many people on the factory floor. At the airport, on my way back to New York, I saw a headline from that day’s Winston-Salem Journal: “Lost,” it read, “108,000 Jobs.” The article was about a study, conducted by the left-leaning Economic Policy Institute, that claimed that North Carolina had lost that many jobs, most of them in manufacturing, “due in part to the trade deficit with China.” In particular, North Carolina’s once thriving furniture industry has been decimated in the last decade. But I saw another example just down the street from Caterpillar: a Dell factory that had employed more than 900 people — and had only been open four years — shut down in late 2010. The Caterpillar factory won’t even replace the lost Dell jobs next door, much less put a dent in all the jobs lost in the last decade. Manufacturing is terribly important. “More than any other sector, manufacturing creates additional jobs in the supply chain,” says Andrew Liveris, the chief executive of Dow Chemical, who has been pushing for a national manufacturing strategy. It’s encouraging, for sure, that manufacturers again see America as a place where they can build things profitably. But my day in North Carolina suggests that the road back to true manufacturing prosperity is going to be a long one indeed.Charlotte, N.C.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/23/business/caterpillar-profit-rises-but-misses-wall-st-estimates.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Profit Rises but Misses Wall St. Estimates<date>Published: July 22, 2011</date><text>Continued robust demand for Caterpillar’s heavy equipment raised the company’s second-quarter profit 44 percent, the company said Friday, but higher costs and cautious comments about China’s economy set off a 5.8 percent decline in its share price. The company raised its sales outlook for the year, but cost increases, mostly related to its recent acquisition of the mining equipment maker Bucyrus, will prevent rising sales from helping profit more than previously expected. Caterpillar’s quarterly profit fell short of Wall Street estimates for the first time since the recession ended. Many investors that were very optimistic about Caterpillar appeared to pause and reassess the prospects for months ahead, said Jeff Windau, an analyst at Edward Jones, who thinks Caterpillar still has strong long-term growth potential. “There’s a lot to digest in this quarter,” Mr. Windau said. The company said it earned $1.02 billion, or $1.52 a share, up from $707 million, or $1.09 a share, a year earlier. Excluding costs associated with the Bucyrus acquisition, profit per share would have been $1.72. Revenue rose 37 percent to $14.2 billion, easily topping Wall Street estimates. Caterpillar predicts 2011 sales of $56 billion to $58 billion with Bucyrus. Previously, it predicted sales of $52 billion to $54 billion. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell $6.45 to close at $105.15 a share.Continued robust demand for Caterpillar’s heavy equipment raised the company’s second-quarter profit 44 percent, the company said Friday, but higher costs and cautious comments about China’s economy set off a 5.8 percent decline in its share price. The company raised its sales outlook for the year, but cost increases, mostly related to its recent acquisition of the mining equipment maker Bucyrus, will prevent rising sales from helping profit more than previously expected. Caterpillar’s quarterly profit fell short of Wall Street estimates for the first time since the recession ended. Many investors that were very optimistic about Caterpillar appeared to pause and reassess the prospects for months ahead, said Jeff Windau, an analyst at Edward Jones, who thinks Caterpillar still has strong long-term growth potential. “There’s a lot to digest in this quarter,” Mr. Windau said. The company said it earned $1.02 billion, or $1.52 a share, up from $707 million, or $1.09 a share, a year earlier. Excluding costs associated with the Bucyrus acquisition, profit per share would have been $1.72. Revenue rose 37 percent to $14.2 billion, easily topping Wall Street estimates. Caterpillar predicts 2011 sales of $56 billion to $58 billion with Bucyrus. Previously, it predicted sales of $52 billion to $54 billion. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell $6.45 to close at $105.15 a share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/05/16/joy-global-buys-letorneau-technologies-for-1-1-billion/?ref=caterpillarinc">Mining Equipment Maker Expands With $1.1 Billion Deal<date>May 16, 2011, 9:21 am</date><text>6:26 p.m. | Updated The Rowan Companies, a drilling services provider, has agreed to sell its LeTourneau Technologies manufacturing business to Joy Global for $1.1 billion in cash. With LeTourneau, Joy Global will be able to expand its portfolio of mining equipment and access the oil and natural gas industry. LeTourneau, which designs and builds drilling and mining products, makes a range of heavy-duty earthmoving equipment, like large wheel loaders. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Joy Global press release LeTourneau’s drilling products business, which makes up about two-thirds of its revenue, is a top supplier of parts for offshore and land drilling rigs. LeTourneau will become part of Joy Global’s P&amp;H Mining Equipment business. “LeTourneau gives us a great entry point into this sector,” Michael W. Sutherlin, Joy Global’s chief executive, said in a statement on Monday. “Oil and gas has been defined as a strategic growth opportunity for a number of years.” Joy Global’s move to bulk up comes on the heels of Caterpillar’s $7.6 billion purchase of Bucyrus International, which specializes in surface and underground equipment for the extraction of coal, copper and other minerals. Under that deal, announced last November, Caterpillar agreed to pay $92 a share, 32 percent above the closing price the previous day. Joy Global predicts the LeTourneau transaction will add to earnings by this fiscal year, and will result in cost savings of about $40 million by 2013. Rowan said it wanted to focus on its core business. “This transaction is consistent with our stated strategy to separate noncore businesses, and we expect that most of the after-tax proceeds, estimated at approximately $875 million, will ultimately be redeployed into our offshore drilling business,” W. Matt Ralls, the chief executive of Rowan, said in a statement on Monday. The deal, which is awaiting regulatory clearance, has been approved by both boards. Joy Global hired Bank of America Merrill Lynch to act as financial adviser, and Covington &amp; Burling is its legal adviser. Barclays Capital advised Rowan. Latham &amp; Watkins was the legal adviser. This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: May 16, 2011 In an earlier version of this post, the name of the mining equipment manufacturer being acquired by Joy Global was misspelled in the headline. It is LeTourneau Technologies, not LeTorneau.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/30/business/30caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Raises 2011 Outlook as Earnings Soar<date>Published: April 29, 2011</date><text>Caterpillar, the heavy equipment maker, said Friday that its first-quarter profit soared more than fivefold. It also raised its financial outlook for the year as a growing economic recovery increased demand for its mining and construction equipment. The results topped analysts’ expectations, and shares rose $2.77, or 2.46 percent, to $115.41. Its first-quarter profit reflected an industrial sector that is growing again, with most of its sales growth coming from the sale of big machines. When the recession hit in 2007, construction and mining companies cut back their spending on heavy machinery first, Mike DeWalt, Caterpillar’s director of investors, told analysts Friday. For more than two years, companies held back their investment. But now they appear to have no choice but to replace aging machinery, raising Caterpillar’s sales, Mr. DeWalt said. That means spending is likely to continue as companies replace more vehicles and even expand on growing demand. The company said its net income climbed to $1.23 billion, or $1.84 a share, from $233 million, or 36 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 57 percent, to $12.95 billion from $8.24 billion. Analysts had expected earnings of $1.30 a share on revenue of $11.43 billion. Revenue at Caterpillar’s machinery and power systems division surged to $12.28 billion from $7.55 billion. Based on its higher-than-expected sales, Caterpillar raised its 2011 outlook, forecasting revenue of $52 billion to $54 billion and net income of $6.25 to $6.75 a share. It previously forecast revenue above $50 billion and net income of roughly $6 a share. Caterpillar said its outlook would have been higher if not for the earthquake and tsunami in Japan, which damaged many of its suppliers. Supply disruptions and delays are likely to cost it $300 million in lost sales and $100 million in lost profit.Caterpillar, the heavy equipment maker, said Friday that its first-quarter profit soared more than fivefold. It also raised its financial outlook for the year as a growing economic recovery increased demand for its mining and construction equipment. The results topped analysts’ expectations, and shares rose $2.77, or 2.46 percent, to $115.41. Its first-quarter profit reflected an industrial sector that is growing again, with most of its sales growth coming from the sale of big machines. When the recession hit in 2007, construction and mining companies cut back their spending on heavy machinery first, Mike DeWalt, Caterpillar’s director of investors, told analysts Friday. For more than two years, companies held back their investment. But now they appear to have no choice but to replace aging machinery, raising Caterpillar’s sales, Mr. DeWalt said. That means spending is likely to continue as companies replace more vehicles and even expand on growing demand. The company said its net income climbed to $1.23 billion, or $1.84 a share, from $233 million, or 36 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 57 percent, to $12.95 billion from $8.24 billion. Analysts had expected earnings of $1.30 a share on revenue of $11.43 billion. Revenue at Caterpillar’s machinery and power systems division surged to $12.28 billion from $7.55 billion. Based on its higher-than-expected sales, Caterpillar raised its 2011 outlook, forecasting revenue of $52 billion to $54 billion and net income of $6.25 to $6.75 a share. It previously forecast revenue above $50 billion and net income of roughly $6 a share. Caterpillar said its outlook would have been higher if not for the earthquake and tsunami in Japan, which damaged many of its suppliers. Supply disruptions and delays are likely to cost it $300 million in lost sales and $100 million in lost profit.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/19/business/19bizbriefs-CATERPILLARP_BRF.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Equipment Sales Grew in February<date>Published: March 18, 2011</date><text>Caterpillar said February was another strong month for sales of its mining and construction equipment, and global sales grew 59 percent over February of last year. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., reported sales figures on Friday in documents filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission. Caterpillar said equipment sales were strongest in Latin America, which reported a 76 percent increase over the previous year. But even in the weakest region of Europe, Africa and the Middle East, sales grew 53 percent in February. Caterpillar shares rose $1.94, to $105.06.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DB143AF932A25751C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">In China, Tentative Steps Toward a Global Currency<date>Published: February 11, 2011</date><text>CORRECTION APPENDED SHANGHAI -- Now that it has passed Japan to become the world's second-largest economy after the United States, China is considering the next step as a world power: making its money a global currency. No one expects that to happen immediately. And even the Chinese government is wary of making some of the free-market moves that would enable the renminbi to take its place alongside the dollar, euro and Japanese yen as a fully convertible reserve currency. Still, over the last year Beijing has begun to gradually loosen its tight currency controls. For the first time, for example, American companies like McDonald's and Caterpillar have been allowed to finance their China projects by selling renminbi-denominated bonds in Hong Kong. Richard Lavin, a group president at Caterpillar, said his company's $150 million Hong Kong offering last November was less expensive than taking out a loan in China or raising the money in dollars and then converting those dollars into renminbi. The bonds were issued to help finance Caterpillar's equipment leasing business in China. ''This was a successful issue,'' Mr. Lavin said. ''Before, we were funding our operations by bringing in dollars and changing them to RMB.'' Meanwhile, in Russia, Vietnam and Thailand, some cross-border trades with China can now be settled in renminbi, so that trading partners do not have to convert in and out of dollars. One pilot program lets Russian companies like Sportmaster, a retail chain based in Moscow, buy or sell goods using Chinese currency. And in New York, the Chinese government has permitted an overseas branch of Bank of China to accept deposits in renminbi. That enables depositors outside China to bet on a currency that is widely expected to appreciate against the dollar over the next few years. ''This is all encouraging the internationalization of the renminbi,'' Kelvin Lau, an economist at Standard Chartered Bank who is based in Hong Kong, said of Beijing's recent moves. ''They want to make the Chinese currency a popular currency.'' At Thursday's exchange rates, renminbi were trading just below 6.59 to the United States dollar -- a level that many experts say values the Chinese currency artificially low, as a result of Beijing's intervention efforts. Five years ago, the renminbi was trading at slightly more than 8 to the dollar. Beyond mere bragging rights, China has economic motives for trying to go global with the renminbi. Analysts say the moves, if successful, could strengthen China's influence in overseas financial markets and begin to erode the dollar's dominance. Beijing could also eventually reap the rewards, like cheaper debt financing, that come with being recognized as a world reserve currency. Global investors eager to bet on China's growth story, meanwhile, could find that looser controls on the renminbi make it easier to invest directly in bonds and other assets denominated in renminbi. And importers and exporters could reduce their currency-fluctuation risks by settling China-related trade deals in renminbi rather than dollars or euros. Robert A. Mundell, a Nobel laureate economist whose research is credited with helping develop the euro, says the renminbi's rise is all but inevitable. ''The RMB is likely to become a reserve currency in the future, even if the government of China does nothing about it,'' Professor Mundell said in an e-mail response to questions. He noted that the renminbi was already a regional currency in Southeast Asia, where China had become the dominant trading partner of many countries. If China does eventually open its capital market by eliminating currency exchange controls, he said, ''the progress of the RMB as an international currency will be assured.'' But analysts caution that right now the renminbi is far from ready to mount a serious challenge to the United States dollar as the world's leading reserve currency. For one thing, China needs to assure investors that its political system is stable and that its economy still has plenty of growth ahead. For all its rapid growth over the last 30 years, China remains relatively poor compared with the United States, the Europe Union or Japan.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/26/former-caterpillar-ceo-joins-k-k-r/?ref=caterpillarinc">Former Caterpillar Chief Joins K.K.R.<date>January 26, 2011, 9:46 am</date><text>James W. Owens, a former chairman and chief executive of Caterpillar, has joined Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company as a senior adviser to the firm’s portfolio management committee. “I am honored to offer my knowledge and counsel to the firm,” Mr. Owens said in a statement. Mr. Owens retired from Caterpillar last year after a 38-year career at the construction equipment manufacturer. He started as an in-house economist, and become chief executive in 2004. “During Jim’s exceptional tenure as C.E.O. of Caterpillar, he led the company in achieving rapid growth and successfully navigated Caterpillar through the recent economic recession,” Henry R. Kravis and George R. Roberts, who co-founded K.K.R. and serve as its chairmen and chief executives, said in a joint statement. “We will benefit greatly from both his depth of experience in the industrial sector and his recognized leadership on global economic issues as we pursue new investments and support our existing portfolio companies.” Mr. Owens serves on the boards of Alcoa, IBM and Morgan Stanley. He was also a member of the President’s Economic Recovery Advisory Board, an external panel that advised the White House during the financial crisis. K.K.R., which focuses on alternative assets, has $55.5 billion in assets under management.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/21/bucyrus-shareholders-support-caterpillar-deal/?ref=caterpillarinc">Bucyrus Shareholders Support Caterpillar Deal<date>January 21, 2011, 7:26 am</date><text>Seth Perlman/Associated PressCaterpillar is paying $92 a share for Bucyrus. Bucyrus, the mining equipment maker set to be acquired by Caterpillar for $7.6 billion, said Thursday in a regulatory filing that shareholders had voted to approve the deal. In a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission, the company said that 73.8 percent of its shareholders had voted for the transaction, and 99.7 percent of all those who voted had approved. The deal, announced in November, will get them $92 per share, a 32 percent premium over where it was trading. The company expects the merger to close in the middle of this year. The two companies also said Thursday that the Justice Department had requested additional information in an antitrust inquiry. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Based in South Milwaukee, Wis., Bucyrus makes equipment used to mine deposits like coal, copper and potash.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/20/regulators-seek-more-data-on-bucyrus-deal/?ref=caterpillarinc">Regulators Seek More Data on Bucyrus Deal<date>January 20, 2011, 10:19 am</date><text>Antitrust regulators have stepped up their scrutiny of Caterpillar’s proposed $7.6 billion acquisition of Bucyrus International. The companies said on Thursday that the antitrust division of the Justice Department had asked for “additional information and documentary material.” Such a move, known as a second request, is not uncommon in large deals but it does indicate that regulators are seriously examining possible antitrust issues. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink When Caterpillar announced the deal in November, it emphasized that the mining equipment produced by Bucyrus would complement Caterpilar’s offerings. As mining companies have become bigger and more global through consolidation, there is more demand for a one-stop shopping approach. Bucyrus, based in South Milwaukee, Wis., specializes in large-scale surface and underground mining equipment. Caterpillar is offering $92 a share in cash for the company.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/11/15/caterpillar-in-7-6-billion-deal-for-bucyrus/?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Gets Bucyrus for $7.6 Billion<date>November 15, 2010, 7:46 pm</date><text>7:46 p.m. | Updated Caterpillar is paying $92 a share for Bucyrus, which represents a 32 percent premium over Friday’s closing price. Caterpillar said that it would locate the headquarters of its mining business in South Milwaukee, Wis., where Bucyrus is based, and that it would preserve the Bucyrus brand, which dates back to 1880. Caterpillar announced Monday that it had agreed to buy Bucyrus International for $7.6 billion in cash, making a big bet that emerging markets like China will continue to fuel the commodities boom in the years to come. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Caterpillar Press Release The purchase of Bucyrus will help Caterpillar expand its global footprint in the mining equipment industry and enable it to offer one-stop shopping for its customers, selling things like mining trucks, hydraulic excavators and electric-rope shovels. Caterpillar executives said that no other company came close to matching that variety of equipment offerings. “Customers have asked us for a broader product line, and with this move we are answering that call,” Edward J. Rapp, the Caterpillar chief financial officer, said in a conference call with analysts. “These two companies were meant for each other.” Bucyrus specializes in large-scale surface and underground equipment for the extraction of coal, copper and other minerals. The company reported $313 million in net income on $2.65 billion in revenue last year, with more than 60 percent of its sales originating outside of the United States. Caterpillar is paying $92 a share for Bucyrus, which represents a 32 percent premium over Friday’s closing price. Caterpillar said that it would locate the headquarters of its mining business in South Milwaukee, Wis., where Bucyrus is based, and that it would preserve the Bucyrus brand, which dates to 1880. The deal bets heavily on emerging markets like China, India and Brazil, where continued urbanization is expected to drive demand for commodities like coal, copper and iron ore. “There’s still arguably several billion people out there that will modernize and progress, and that’s the play we’re making here,” said Douglas R. Oberhelman, Caterpillar’s chief executive. “It’s a macroeconomic play — that this thing continues and sustains itself, which we think it does. And long term, it will be great for this company.” There is little overlap between Caterpillar’s offerings and the products sold by Bucyrus, the companies said. Caterpillar noted that at many mine sites, workers use Bucyrus shovels to load Caterpillar mining trucks. In large part because of the complementary product lines, Caterpillar said the acquisition should exceed $400 million in cost savings by 2015. Timothy W. Sullivan, the Bucyrus president and chief executive, said he came to an agreement with Caterpillar after Mr. Oberhelman approached him and the two executives realized how tightly the companies’ offerings would fit together. The deal is the biggest splash yet by Mr. Oberhelman, who became chief on July 1. “It is a strong statement about our belief in the bright future of the mining industry,” he said. There had been little indication that Bucyrus was planning to sell. To the contrary, the company agreed last December to pay $1.3 billion for the mining business of the heavy-equipment manufacturer Terex, which has a strong presence in China and Indonesia. Shares of Bucyrus rose $20.18, or 29 percent, to $89.80. Shares of Bucyrus’s most comparable peer, Joy Global, also rose, increasing more than 7 percent on speculation that it could be a takeover target for a Caterpillar competitor like Komatsu or Hitachi Construction. Investors in Caterpillar evidently approved, too. Its shares rose 78 cents, or about 1 percent, to $81.82. Analysts said that while there was no question that Caterpillar was paying a hefty price for Bucyrus, the availability of cheap debt made that premium acceptable. They said the clout that the combined company would have would make it appealing to customers, who increasingly wanted to save money by reducing the number of suppliers with which they contracted. Above all else, perhaps, the deal signals that Caterpillar is doubling down its mining business. “It’s a big bet on commodities, a big bet on emerging economies,” said Adam Fleck, an analyst with Morningstar. He added, “With a purchase price this full, it doesn’t give much in terms of wiggle room if they are wrong.” The deal is the third significant purchase by Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., in recent months. Three weeks ago, the company purchased the German engine maker MWM Holding from the British private equity firm 3i, and in June, Caterpillar bought the locomotive manufacturer Electro-Motive Diesel. JPMorgan Chase advised Caterpillar, and will provide financing. Mayer Brown, Sidley Austin and Howrey served as legal advisers for Caterpillar. Deutsche Bank and UBS advised Bucyrus. Sullivan &amp; Cromwell and Arnold &amp; Porter served as legal advisers for Bucyrus. Caterpillar is paying $92 a share for Bucyrus, which represents a 32 percent premium over Friday’s closing price. Caterpillar said that it would locate the headquarters of its mining business in South Milwaukee, Wis., where Bucyrus is based, and that it would preserve the Bucyrus brand, which dates back to 1880. This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: November 15, 2010 A previous version of this post misstated a deal between Bucyrus and Terex. Bucyrus recently purchased the mining operation of Terex, not the entire company.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/10/25/morgan-stanley-picks-caterpillar-chairman-for-board/?ref=caterpillarinc">Morgan Stanley Picks Caterpillar Chairman for Its Board<date>October 25, 2010, 9:24 am</date><text>Morgan Stanley said on Monday that it had expanded its board by appointing the departing chairman of Caterpillar, James W. Owens, as a director. The term of Mr. Owens, 64, who is leaving Caterpillar at the end of October, will begin on Jan. 1. Morgan Stanley’s board will then have 13 directors. Mr. Owens’ career at Caterpillar, the construction equipment giant, stretches back nearly 40 years. In addition to being chairman, he was also chief executive from 2004 to June. Mr. Owens serves as a director on the boards of Alcoa and I.B.M.. Go to Morgan Stanley Press Release »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/10/22/caterpillar-to-buy-german-engine-maker-from-3i/?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar to Buy Engine Maker From 3i<date>October 22, 2010, 6:38 am</date><text>Caterpillar said Friday that it would buy MWM Holding, a German engine maker, from the British private-equity firm 3i for $810 million in cash. MWM, short for Motoren-Werke Mannheim, focuses on sustainable power generation through the manufacture of combustion engines that use natural gas, diesel and other gases. 3i has been involved in the firm for three years, during which time it repositioned MWM in the market, and has realized a return double its investment. Go to Statement from Caterpillar via PRNewswire » Go to Article from DealBook »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/13/business/13cat.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar to Build Texas Plant to Make Excavators<date>Published: August 12, 2010</date><text>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) — Caterpillar said Thursday it would build a new plant in Texas to manufacture hydraulic excavators that would employ more than 500 workers.The plant, in the south central town of Victoria, will triple Caterpillar’s hydraulic excavator production capacity in the United States, and double the number of Caterpillar’s employees making excavators in the country. Construction of the 600,000-square-foot structure will begin next month, with production expected to start in mid-2012. “Based on our comprehensive review of possible locations, Victoria’s proximity to our supply base, access to ports and other transportation, as well as the positive business climate in Texas made this the ideal site for this project,” said Gary Stampanato, Caterpillar vice president with responsibility for excavators. Caterpillar received a $1.18 million grant from the Texas Enterprise Fund as part of its commitment to build in the state, Gov. Rick Perry said Thursday. Since its creation in 2003, the fund has invested more than $397 million in securing job-creating projects in the state. Currently in the United States, Caterpillar produces two excavator models at a facility in Aurora, Ill., where it also makes wheel loaders, soil and landfill compactors, wheel dozers and components. Caterpillar also makes excavators in Belgium, Brazil, China, France, Indonesia, Japan and Russia. The new plant will manufacture the two models now made in Aurora, as well as several other models now produced in Akashi, Japan, and exported to the United States. In July, Caterpillar reported a 91 percent surge in second-quarter earnings driven by strong sales, particularly in emerging markets like China.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/08/03/caterpillar-unit-acquires-locomotive-maker/?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Unit Acquires Locomotive Maker<date>August 3, 2010, 4:05 am</date><text>Caterpillar said its rail-services unit completed the acquisition of locomotive maker Electro-Motive Diesel for $820 million plus a post-closing adjustment estimated at $108 million, The Associated Press reported. Electro-Motive Diesel, or EMD, was made a subsidiary of Caterpillar’s Progress Rail Services. Caterpillar bought the company from private equity firms Berkshire Partners and Greenbriar Equity Group. The final deal will include a net working capital adjustment. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Caterpillar Press Release »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/23/business/23caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar’s Profit Rises 91% as Sales Grow 31%<date>Published: July 22, 2010</date><text>The heavy machinery manufacturer Caterpillar reported Thursday that its second-quarter earnings rose 91 percent on a big increase in sales of equipment for industries like mining, infrastructure and energy.The company, considered a bellwether of industrial activity, also raised its 2010 profit outlook, saying orders were growing and production would increase in the second half of the year. Caterpillar had net income of $707 million, or $1.09 a share, up from $371 million, or 60 cents a share a year earlier. Sales rose 31 percent, to $10.4 billion, with gains in machinery sales in all four of its global regions. Dealers built up inventories during the quarter after slashing them during the recession a year ago. Manufacturing costs also fell by $316 million, helping profits. Analysts were looking for 85 cents a share of earnings on revenue of $9.8 billion. For all of 2010, Caterpillar expects to earn between $3.15 to $3.85 a share, up from a previous forecast of $2.50 to $3.25 a share. It also tightened its revenue forecast, bumping up the lower range by $100 million. Caterpillar now expects between $39 billion to $42 billion in revenue. Analysts foresee $3.29 a share of net income and $38.92 billion of revenue. Early this year, Caterpillar began rebounding as governments poured money into stimulus projects like roadwork and companies cautiously started to spend money again. The company has had a resurgence particularly in areas like Asia because of China’s brisk growth and in sectors like mining because of a rebound in commodity prices. Asia was again the fastest-growing market in the second quarter, with sales improving by 62 percent, to $1.7 billion. Caterpillar said overall sales of machinery were helped by factors like low interest rates, higher metal prices that spurred mining activity, and the brighter global economic picture. Sales in the North American market, Caterpillar’s biggest, rose 43 percent. The company said the growth was driven by an improvement in home construction, a modest increase in federal spending for highways and better prices in sectors like metals, coal and lumber.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/19/business/19bizbriefs-MACHINERYSAL_BRF.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Machinery Sales Jump 11% at Caterpillar<date>Published: June 18, 2010</date><text>Caterpillar, the world’s largest maker of construction equipment, said worldwide retail sales of machinery measured over three months rose for the first time in almost two years. Sales as reported by dealers climbed 11 percent in the period through May, the company reported Friday. The previous gain was posted in September 2008, said Jim Dugan, a spokesman. North American sales rose 15 percent in the period, the first improvement since August 2006.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/06/02/caterpillar-buys-locomotive-maker/?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Buys Locomotive Maker<date>June 2, 2010, 6:02 am</date><text>Heavy equipment maker Caterpillar said its railroad service unit will spend $820 million to acquire locomotive maker Electro-Motive Diesel, The Associated Press reported. Caterpillar’s Progress Rail Services division agreed to buy E.M.D. from private equity firms Berkshire Partners and Greenbriar Equity Group. Caterpillar’s vice chairman, Doug Oberhelman, said the deal will help his Peoria, Ill.-based company increase its presence in the railroad industry, which has a bright future because it can efficiently move lots of freight. In 2009, E.M.D. generated $1.8 billion revenue on sales of diesel-electric locomotives. The deal is expected to close by year-end. E.M.D. will keep its chief executive and remain in LaGrange, Ill. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Article from Bloomberg News via BusinessWeek » Go to Press Release from Caterpillar (PDF) »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/27/business/27caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Posts Strong Profit and Raises Outlook<date>Published: April 26, 2010</date><text>Caterpillar reported a stronger-than-expected quarterly profit Monday and raised its full-year sales forecast above Wall Street estimates, citing an improving global economy, especially in Asia and Latin America.A rebound in most metal prices resulted in firm orders for much of the company’s available 2010 production of large mining trucks and large track-type tractors, Caterpillar said. Some of its largest mining vehicles were sold out for the year. “Economic conditions are definitely improving, particularly in the world’s developing economies,” Caterpillar said. But the company cut its outlook for 2010 housing starts in the United States by 20 percent. Caterpillar reported a first-quarter profit of $233 million, or 36 cents a share, compared with a year-earlier loss of $112 million, or 19 cents a share. Stripping out one-time charges, including tax expenses of $90 million related to the recently signed health care legislation, earnings were 50 cents a share, better than the 39 cents expected by analysts. Sales, including revenue from Caterpillar’s financial services arm, fell 11 percent to $8.23 billion, pulled down by a 28 percent decline in its engine and turbine business. Analysts had forecast $8.84 billion. Caterpillar said it now expected a full-year profit of $2.50 to $3.25 a share on sales of $38 billion to $42 billion. The analysts’ average estimates are for a profit of $2.69 a share and sales of $37 billion. Caterpillar, which laid off nearly 30,000 full-time and contract workers worldwide during the recent downturn, said it had begun adding to its payroll again.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/30/business/30subsidy.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Companies Push to Repeal Provision of Health Law<date>Published: March 29, 2010</date><text>An association representing 300 large corporations urged President Obama and Congress on Monday to repeal a provision of the health care overhaul that prompted AT&amp;T, Caterpillar and other companies to announce substantial charges for the current quarter.The association, the American Benefits Council, said the provision — which reduces the tax deductions for companies with drug coverage for their retired employees — would deal a significant blow to corporate profits and would discourage companies from hiring more workers. AT&amp;T announced last week that it was taking a $1 billion charge because of the provision. Deere &amp; Company announced a $150 million charge, Caterpillar a $100 million charge, and 3M a $90 million charge. Many companies said they were taking these charges now, before the current quarter ended, to comply with accounting rules. But some corporate critics asserted that the companies’ rapid response to the health legislation was aimed at pressing the administration to repeal the provision. James A. Klein, the president of the American Benefits Council, called the provision “a serious mistake that is having negative and unintended consequences.” White House officials defended the provision, saying it was a deliberate effort to eliminate what they said was an unusually generous tax loophole. They said the overall health care overhaul would save businesses more than $150 billion over the next decade by reducing health care inflation. “We’re confident that the benefits are going to accrue and strengthen business’s bottom line,” said Linda Douglass, the communications director for the White House Health Reform Office. When Congress and President George W. Bush enacted a prescription drug plan for seniors in 2003, the legislation encouraged companies to continue providing prescription coverage to retirees, instead of shifting retirees to Medicare Part D, by having the government give those companies large subsidies for each retiree — and also allowing them to deduct those subsidies from their income taxes. Under the health care overhaul, the federal government will continue providing those subsidies — amounting to 28 percent of a drug plan’s costs — but companies will lose the tax break. In a telephone news conference on Monday, Mr. Klein cited a study by Towers Watson, a consulting firm, saying the loss of the deduction would cost companies $14 billion in future years. “Particularly in this economic environment, it makes no sense to impose this type of a hit on companies’ financial statements,” Mr. Klein said. The provision takes effect in 2013, but accounting rules require companies to take immediate charges equal to the current value of any known hit to future profits. Defending the provision, White House officials said it was rare for companies to obtain a tax-free federal subsidy and be able to deduct it as well. These officials added that the health care legislation contained a $5 billion subsidy for companies that maintain health plans to early retirees. “Let’s put these changes into perspective,” Ms. Douglass said. “While accounting rules required companies to book this cost upfront, there are a whole set of benefits that will accrue to companies over time that they’re not booking upfront.” Federal officials estimate that the provision will raise $4.5 billion to $5 billion in revenue over 10 years, but Mr. Klein maintained that it would cost the government more than it raised. About 6.3 million retirees — an estimated two-thirds of them from the private sector — are covered by employer drug plans. Mr. Klein cited a study by the Moran Company, a health care consulting group, estimating that as a result of the legislation, drug coverage would be altered for 1.5 million to 2 million retirees. Many companies, he said, will stop providing drug coverage to retirees and will instead push them into Medicare Part D, causing the government to pay for their coverage. AT&amp;T said in a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission, “As a result of this legislation, including the additional tax burden, AT&amp;T will be evaluating prospective changes to the active and retiree health care benefits offered by the company.” Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, criticized the charges by the companies, asserting that the health reform would save companies more money than it cost them. Mr. Waxman sent AT&amp;T, Caterpillar and Deere a sharp letter, questioning the charges and saying he wanted top officials from those companies to testify at an April 21 hearing he has scheduled on the issue. Mr. Waxman and Bart Stupak, a Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the House Commerce Committee’s subcommittee on oversight and investigations, wrote to AT&amp;T’s chairman, Randall L. Stephenson, “The new law is designed to expand coverage and bring down costs, so your assertions are a matter of concern.” Their letter said AT&amp;T’s moves “appear to conflict with independent analyses,” including a finding by the Business Roundtable, an association of chief executives, that health care reform would reduce insurance cost trends for businesses by more than $3,000 for each employee over the next 10 years. Responding to such criticism, Mr. Klein said: “These announcements are required under accounting rules, and we should all expect more of such announcements in coming days and weeks. We’re very troubled that these announcements have been challenged by officials in Obama administration and Congress.” Many employer plans for retiree drug coverage are part of union contracts. In December, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.’s legislative director, Bill Samuel, joined Mr. Klein in writing to Senator Harry Reid, the majority leader, urging the Senate not to enact this provision. Gerry Shea, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.’s chief strategist on health care, stopped short of calling for a repeal of the provision. “We’re very concerned about the disruption that could be caused because of this, with people being pushed out of employer plans,” he said. “With all the changes we’re looking at because of the new health legislation, we feel you don’t need this.” Mr. Klein argued that the provision would undercut Mr. Obama’s job creation plans. “If companies are going to take a hit like this on their financial statements that will certainly hurt their ability to borrow in the marketplace and make the type of investments that will retain and create jobs,” he said. But White House officials said the provision would not affect job creation because it does not take effect for three years and any charge for a given year would not be large.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/28/us/28cncpulse.html?ref=caterpillarinc">The Pulse: Scrutinizing the Numbers in Caterpillar’s Complaint<date>Published: March 27, 2010</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. of Peoria has jumped to the forefront of manufacturing companies complaining about the cost of the federal health care overhaul. On March 18 the company sent a letter to Speaker Nancy Pelosi and Representative John A. Boehner, the Republican leader, saying mandated changes would cost it “$100 million in the first year alone.”Caterpillar’s complaint led to dozens of headlines, but a closer look at the impact of the new law indicates it is not quite the budget buster that the company’s human resources executive, Gregory Folley, implied in his missive. According to a regulatory filing by the company last week, the $100 million figure is Caterpillar’s estimated total cost for as long as the newly enacted Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act remains in effect. And the $100 million charge is an accounting change, a noncash cost that has no affect on the company’s operations. In addition, the $100 million figure does not arise from changes to decades-long practices at Caterpillar. Rather, it comes about because the new law removes a tax break codified in 2003. No company sneezes at the elimination of a $100 million tax break. But in 2008, Caterpillar had $51 billion in sales, and profits topped $3.5 billion for the third straight year. The projected profits for 2010 are a relatively weak $1.56 billion, and the $100 million tax charge would mean an additional 6 percent reduction. Most companies steer away from politics, but Jim Owens, left, the company’s soon-to-retire chief executive, has held forth on climate change and other controversial issues. Most notably, in February 2009, Mr. Owens contradicted President Obama’s claim that the stimulus package would help Caterpillar rehire some of its 22,000 laid-off workers. He did so on the day Mr. Obama visited Caterpillar’s Peoria factory.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1D6153CF934A25751C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">3 Companies Quit Group Over Moves On Climate<date>Published: February 17, 2010</date><text>Three large corporations are quitting the Climate Action Partnership, a group in Washington that has sought to find common ground among corporations and environmental groups in battling global warming. The three companies cited concerns over the direction that climate change legislation has taken in Congress. Oil companies are particularly upset about concessions Congress has made to the coal and utility industries. In separate statements, BP America, ConocoPhillips and Caterpillar said Tuesday that they were discontinuing membership in the lobbying group, which includes corporate giants like Alcoa and DuPont, and influential environmental organizations like the Nature Conservancy and the Environmental Defense Fund. In a statement that played down the significance of the departures, the Climate Action Partnership said that ''all three companies have provided invaluable assistance, expertise and significant commitments of time and resources'' in seeking to advance climate legislation. In the proposed legislation, Congress granted free emission allowances to coal-burning utilities to forestall the possibility of huge increases in electric bills. Oil companies, by contrast, would have to pay for their emissions if the bill became law, most likely driving up the price of gasoline. (The legislation is stalled at the moment on Capitol Hill, though the Obama administration is trying to revive it.) James J. Mulva, the chief executive of ConocoPhillips, said Tuesday that ''House climate legislation and Senate proposals to date have disadvantaged the transportation sector and its consumers, left domestic refineries unfairly penalized versus international competition, and ignored the critical role that natural gas can play in reducing'' greenhouse gas emissions. BP echoed that view, with a spokesman, Ronnie Chappell, saying the company believes it can do more to influence the outcome of pending House and Senate legislation on its own. ''Our views are that there are segments of the economy that are largely untouched or aren't carrying as big a piece of the burden that they might,'' he said. Caterpillar said it would spend its energy on new technologies that could help to cut emissions.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/28/business/28caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Profit Falls 65%<date>Published: January 27, 2010</date><text>Caterpillar, the heavy equipment maker, said on Wednesday that fourth-quarter profit fell as demand remained weak but that it expected sales to rebound in 2010 as the economy improved and dealers replaced inventory. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Leading the way will be China and other developing countries, where an increasing share of the company’s machinery is sold. Caterpillar said its profit last quarter fell 65 percent, to $232 million, or 36 cents a share, from $661 million, or $1.08 a share, a year earlier. Sales fell 39 percent, to $7.9 billion, from $12.92 billion. Though sales will probably pick up next year, Caterpillar’s profit estimate for the year, about $2.50 a share, fell short of what many analysts had expected. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell $2.41, or 4.3 percent, to $53.44 a share. Mike DeWalt, the company’s director of investor relations, said he thought Wall Street overestimated Caterpillar’s earnings capability after the company said in October that it expected revenue to climb 10 to 25 percent in 2010. “They got a little ahead of expectations because we weren’t able to provide them profit guidance in the third quarter,” Mr. DeWalt said. Caterpillar said that sales in China had rebounded strongly, but that markets in North America, Europe and other developed regions continued to struggle. The company said it expected growth of more than 10 percent in China and 8 percent in India in 2010. That is much more robust than the 3.5 percent growth Caterpillar predicted for the United States and the 1 percent growth in Europe. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 28, 2010, on page B4 of the New York edition.Caterpillar, the heavy equipment maker, said on Wednesday that fourth-quarter profit fell as demand remained weak but that it expected sales to rebound in 2010 as the economy improved and dealers replaced inventory. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Leading the way will be China and other developing countries, where an increasing share of the company’s machinery is sold. Caterpillar said its profit last quarter fell 65 percent, to $232 million, or 36 cents a share, from $661 million, or $1.08 a share, a year earlier. Sales fell 39 percent, to $7.9 billion, from $12.92 billion. Though sales will probably pick up next year, Caterpillar’s profit estimate for the year, about $2.50 a share, fell short of what many analysts had expected. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell $2.41, or 4.3 percent, to $53.44 a share. Mike DeWalt, the company’s director of investor relations, said he thought Wall Street overestimated Caterpillar’s earnings capability after the company said in October that it expected revenue to climb 10 to 25 percent in 2010. “They got a little ahead of expectations because we weren’t able to provide them profit guidance in the third quarter,” Mr. DeWalt said. Caterpillar said that sales in China had rebounded strongly, but that markets in North America, Europe and other developed regions continued to struggle. The company said it expected growth of more than 10 percent in China and 8 percent in India in 2010. That is much more robust than the 3.5 percent growth Caterpillar predicted for the United States and the 1 percent growth in Europe.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/24/automobiles/autoreviews/24DOZER.html?ref=caterpillarinc">A New Heavyweight Among Hybrids<date>Published: January 21, 2010</date><text>TESTED: Caterpillar D7E WHAT IS IT? A diesel-electric bulldozer. HOW MUCH? Base price is $560,000; as tested, $600,000. Loading up with options like a heated seat, rear camera, rock guards, GPS tracking device and autopilot blade controls can run the sticker to $650,000. WHAT MAKES IT RUN? A 9.3-liter 6-cylinder Caterpillar turbodiesel, rated at 235 horsepower and 719 pound-feet of torque, bolts to a 480-volt generator. Two 107-horsepower electric motors power the tracks to a top speed of 7 miles per hour. IS IT THIRSTY? Not for a bulldozer. The D7E pushes 25 percent more m.p.g.  material per gallon, that is  than its nonhybrid counterpart, the D7R. AT the controls of a machine that stands 11 feet tall, weighs 60,000 pounds and can move mountains, you quickly realize that the word hybrid is a relative term. Officially, the Caterpillar D7E is not a hybrid bulldozer. Before 2009, in fact, Cat did not use the h-word to describe the earthmoving machine, a 10-year effort that generated over 100 patents. Caterpillar engineers told me during a drive at the company’s test facility in Edwards, Ill., that they prefer to call it an electric tractor with a diesel-electric hybrid powertrain. This fuzzy marketing terminology echoes the strategy of General Motors, which calls its plug-in hybrid, the 2011 Chevrolet Volt, an extended-range electric car.Yet aside from the differences in weight (roughly 28 tons) and price (about half a million dollars), the Cat D7E could easily play big brother to the Volt. Both vehicles use powertrains that directly couple an internal-combustion engine with an electric generator, though the Volt carries a lithium-ion battery pack enabling it to drive some 40 miles without starting its gas engine. “We just don’t have the battery-storage element,” Mike Betz, chief engineer of the D7E, said. A hybrid tractor, I discovered, drives much like a nonhybrid tractor. (I’m not an expert bulldozer pilot, though I am a certified crane operator). The cab is comfortable, and the controls are intuitive. The air-suspension seat gave welcome relief as I bounced over bumps and dips. On each of the chair’s telescoping armrests are joysticks. The left side controls direction; the joystick on the right moves the blade up, down or angles it for a cross-slope. Simple as that. Sculpturing the dirt into small trenches and hills, I found the powertrain far smoother than those of typical construction machines. Keeping the ground level was where my skills ran out. Part of the D7E’s smoothness comes from the steady speed of its engine, which hums along at about 1,500 to 1,800 r.p.m. Normal tractors’ engines rev up and down more; a nudge of the joystick is followed by a loud clatter, a plume of smoke and, finally, a jerk to the tracks. Not so with the D7E. And even without a battery pack or idle-stop system, the powertrain wrings efficiency out of the engine by running it in a narrower r.p.m. range. That also makes this machine quieter  almost eerily so  than conventional tractors. Swing the doors closed and the noise peters out even more, to about the same level you’d expect in a car traveling down a freeway. Like automotive hybrids, the D7E does recapture energy that would otherwise be wasted, though not in the traditional sense of a regenerative braking system. During forward and reverse shifts, which happen hundreds of times a day in a bulldozer, the electric motors momentarily push energy back into the engine’s flywheel. In bulldozers, miles per gallon is not the defining measure of fuel efficiency. The D7E burns 6.2 gallons of diesel an hour, drawing from a 126-gallon tank, but Cat says it can push 25 percent more material  rocks, dirt, whatever  per gallon than the nonhybrid D7R. Aside from improving fuel consumption, the hybrid powertrain also spits out fewer pollutants in its exhaust. For this reason the Environmental Protection Agency graced the D7E with its Clean Air Excellence award last spring. Even so, Caterpillar was reluctant to stick the hybrid label on the D7E. “In some circles, that’s not necessarily a selling point yet,” said Daniel Sperling, a professor of engineering at the University of California, Davis, a member of the state’s Air Resources Board and co-author of “Two Billion Cars: Driving Toward Sustainability.” But it was Mr. Sperling who prodded the Cat people to step up the hybrid lingo. “They were kind of struggling with how to describe it, both for their management as well as their customers,” he said. Perhaps one day Caterpillar will make electric bulldozers. But even now the yellow construction machines are showing a tinge of green. TUDOR VAN HAMPTON Tudor Van Hampton writes about heavy equipment for Engineering News-Record, published by McGraw-Hill. More Articles in Automobiles » A version of this article appeared in print on January 24, 2010, on page AU9 of the National edition.TESTED: Caterpillar D7E WHAT IS IT? A diesel-electric bulldozer. HOW MUCH? Base price is $560,000; as tested, $600,000. Loading up with options like a heated seat, rear camera, rock guards, GPS tracking device and autopilot blade controls can run the sticker to $650,000. WHAT MAKES IT RUN? A 9.3-liter 6-cylinder Caterpillar turbodiesel, rated at 235 horsepower and 719 pound-feet of torque, bolts to a 480-volt generator. Two 107-horsepower electric motors power the tracks to a top speed of 7 miles per hour. IS IT THIRSTY? Not for a bulldozer. The D7E pushes 25 percent more m.p.g.  material per gallon, that is  than its nonhybrid counterpart, the D7R. AT the controls of a machine that stands 11 feet tall, weighs 60,000 pounds and can move mountains, you quickly realize that the word hybrid is a relative term. Officially, the Caterpillar D7E is not a hybrid bulldozer. Before 2009, in fact, Cat did not use the h-word to describe the earthmoving machine, a 10-year effort that generated over 100 patents. Caterpillar engineers told me during a drive at the company’s test facility in Edwards, Ill., that they prefer to call it an electric tractor with a diesel-electric hybrid powertrain. This fuzzy marketing terminology echoes the strategy of General Motors, which calls its plug-in hybrid, the 2011 Chevrolet Volt, an extended-range electric car.Yet aside from the differences in weight (roughly 28 tons) and price (about half a million dollars), the Cat D7E could easily play big brother to the Volt. Both vehicles use powertrains that directly couple an internal-combustion engine with an electric generator, though the Volt carries a lithium-ion battery pack enabling it to drive some 40 miles without starting its gas engine. “We just don’t have the battery-storage element,” Mike Betz, chief engineer of the D7E, said. A hybrid tractor, I discovered, drives much like a nonhybrid tractor. (I’m not an expert bulldozer pilot, though I am a certified crane operator). The cab is comfortable, and the controls are intuitive. The air-suspension seat gave welcome relief as I bounced over bumps and dips. On each of the chair’s telescoping armrests are joysticks. The left side controls direction; the joystick on the right moves the blade up, down or angles it for a cross-slope. Simple as that. Sculpturing the dirt into small trenches and hills, I found the powertrain far smoother than those of typical construction machines. Keeping the ground level was where my skills ran out. Part of the D7E’s smoothness comes from the steady speed of its engine, which hums along at about 1,500 to 1,800 r.p.m. Normal tractors’ engines rev up and down more; a nudge of the joystick is followed by a loud clatter, a plume of smoke and, finally, a jerk to the tracks. Not so with the D7E. And even without a battery pack or idle-stop system, the powertrain wrings efficiency out of the engine by running it in a narrower r.p.m. range. That also makes this machine quieter  almost eerily so  than conventional tractors. Swing the doors closed and the noise peters out even more, to about the same level you’d expect in a car traveling down a freeway. Like automotive hybrids, the D7E does recapture energy that would otherwise be wasted, though not in the traditional sense of a regenerative braking system. During forward and reverse shifts, which happen hundreds of times a day in a bulldozer, the electric motors momentarily push energy back into the engine’s flywheel. In bulldozers, miles per gallon is not the defining measure of fuel efficiency. The D7E burns 6.2 gallons of diesel an hour, drawing from a 126-gallon tank, but Cat says it can push 25 percent more material  rocks, dirt, whatever  per gallon than the nonhybrid D7R. Aside from improving fuel consumption, the hybrid powertrain also spits out fewer pollutants in its exhaust. For this reason the Environmental Protection Agency graced the D7E with its Clean Air Excellence award last spring. Even so, Caterpillar was reluctant to stick the hybrid label on the D7E. “In some circles, that’s not necessarily a selling point yet,” said Daniel Sperling, a professor of engineering at the University of California, Davis, a member of the state’s Air Resources Board and co-author of “Two Billion Cars: Driving Toward Sustainability.” But it was Mr. Sperling who prodded the Cat people to step up the hybrid lingo. “They were kind of struggling with how to describe it, both for their management as well as their customers,” he said. Perhaps one day Caterpillar will make electric bulldozers. But even now the yellow construction machines are showing a tinge of green. TUDOR VAN HAMPTON Tudor Van Hampton writes about heavy equipment for Engineering News-Record, published by McGraw-Hill.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/01/business/01caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Buys a Manufacturer in South Korea<date>Published: November 30, 2009</date><text>PEORIA, Ill. (AP)  Caterpillar said Monday it plans to buy a subsidiary of a South Korean manufacturer of components for earthmoving and other machinery. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company said it would acquire JCS Company Ltd., a subsidiary of the Jinsung T.E.C. Company. Terms were not disclosed. The acquisition builds on a relationship between Caterpillar, based in Peoria, and Jinsung T.E.C., which supplies Caterpillar with equipment for its machines. The deal is subject to regulatory approval and is expected to be completed early next year. Jinsung T.E.C. specializes in the design and manufacture of heavy equipment spare parts, including track rollers, seal groups and front idlers for excavators and bulldozers. The transaction will give Caterpillar its first factory in South Korea. Caterpillar already has plants in China, India, Indonesia and Australia. Caterpillar has made significant investments in the Asia Pacific region to support a growing base of customers, said David Bozeman, Caterpillar vice president with responsibility for undercarriage production. “This strategic acquisition will improve Caterpillar’s supply chain and component capacity in support of Caterpillar’s long-term machine capacity expansion plans in Asia,” he said. Rich Lavin, Caterpillar group president with responsibility for Asia Pacific, said South Korea is an increasingly important market for Caterpillar products and as a potential site for manufacturing in the region. This year, Caterpillar has laid off more than 22,000 workers as it scaled back production because of the recession. Caterpillar has said it is counting on Asian customers to buy more of its mining and construction equipment next year to help the company move beyond the recession. More Articles in Business »PEORIA, Ill. (AP)  Caterpillar said Monday it plans to buy a subsidiary of a South Korean manufacturer of components for earthmoving and other machinery. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company said it would acquire JCS Company Ltd., a subsidiary of the Jinsung T.E.C. Company. Terms were not disclosed. The acquisition builds on a relationship between Caterpillar, based in Peoria, and Jinsung T.E.C., which supplies Caterpillar with equipment for its machines. The deal is subject to regulatory approval and is expected to be completed early next year. Jinsung T.E.C. specializes in the design and manufacture of heavy equipment spare parts, including track rollers, seal groups and front idlers for excavators and bulldozers. The transaction will give Caterpillar its first factory in South Korea. Caterpillar already has plants in China, India, Indonesia and Australia. Caterpillar has made significant investments in the Asia Pacific region to support a growing base of customers, said David Bozeman, Caterpillar vice president with responsibility for undercarriage production. “This strategic acquisition will improve Caterpillar’s supply chain and component capacity in support of Caterpillar’s long-term machine capacity expansion plans in Asia,” he said. Rich Lavin, Caterpillar group president with responsibility for Asia Pacific, said South Korea is an increasingly important market for Caterpillar products and as a potential site for manufacturing in the region. This year, Caterpillar has laid off more than 22,000 workers as it scaled back production because of the recession. Caterpillar has said it is counting on Asian customers to buy more of its mining and construction equipment next year to help the company move beyond the recession.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/11/30/caterpillar-to-buy-south-korean-equipment-maker/?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar to Buy South Korean Equipment-Maker<date>November 30, 2009, 9:35 am</date><text>Caterpillar plans to buy a subsidiary of a South Korean manufacturer of components for earth moving and other machinery, The Associated Press reported. Caterpillar, the maker of mining and construction equipment, says it will acquire JCS, a subsidiary of Jinsung T.E.C. Terms were not disclosed. The acquisition builds on a relationship between Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., and Jinsung T.E.C., which supplies Caterpillar with equipment for its machines. The transaction will give Caterpillar its first factory in South Korea. Caterpillar already has plants in China, India, Indonesia and Australia. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/23/business/23caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Picks Next C.E.O.<date>Published: October 22, 2009</date><text>PEORIA, Ill. (AP)  Caterpillar, the world’s largest maker of construction and mining equipment, said Thursday that Douglas R. Oberhelman will become the company’s next chief executive. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company said Mr. Oberhelman, 56, will succeed the current chief executive, James W. Owens on July 1. Mr. Owens will stay on as chairman until he retires Oct. 31 under a mandatory retirement policy. Mr. Owens, 63, told the company in 2008 he was planning to retire in the fall of 2010 and has worked with its board over the last year to develop a succession plan. He became the company’s top executive in 2004. Mr. Oberhelman, a 34-year Caterpillar veteran, currently is the company’s group president, responsible for its engine and gas turbine businesses, human services, rail services and remanufacturing divisions. Earlier, he was its chief financial officer. Shares of Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell 73 cents, to $57.21, in early trading. More Articles in Business »PEORIA, Ill. (AP)  Caterpillar, the world’s largest maker of construction and mining equipment, said Thursday that Douglas R. Oberhelman will become the company’s next chief executive. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company said Mr. Oberhelman, 56, will succeed the current chief executive, James W. Owens on July 1. Mr. Owens will stay on as chairman until he retires Oct. 31 under a mandatory retirement policy. Mr. Owens, 63, told the company in 2008 he was planning to retire in the fall of 2010 and has worked with its board over the last year to develop a succession plan. He became the company’s top executive in 2004. Mr. Oberhelman, a 34-year Caterpillar veteran, currently is the company’s group president, responsible for its engine and gas turbine businesses, human services, rail services and remanufacturing divisions. Earlier, he was its chief financial officer. Shares of Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., fell 73 cents, to $57.21, in early trading.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/21/business/21caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Raises Forecast for Year<date>Published: October 20, 2009</date><text>Caterpillar, the maker of bulldozers and excavators, posted third-quarter earnings that beat analysts’ estimates and issued a full-year forecast that exceeded the highest prediction. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Profit dropped to $404 million, or 64 cents a share, from $868 million, or $1.39, a year earlier, the company said Tuesday in a statement. The average estimate in a Bloomberg survey of analysts was 5 cents a share. Caterpillar has slashed inventories and production amid the worst decline in its markets since the Great Depression. The company cut about 18,700 full-time jobs and about the same amount of temporary workers since December 2008 as demand faltered. Sales fell 44 percent to $7.3 billion, from $12.98 billion in the third quarter of 2008. “We believe the third quarter marked the low point for Caterpillar sales and revenues in what has been the toughest recession since the 1930s,” Jim Owens, the chief executive, said. Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., narrowed its 2009 forecast range to $1.85 to $2.05 a share, from $1.15 to $2.25. The average estimate was $1.48 a share. The highest prediction was $1.75. The revenue forecast is now $32 billion to $33 billion, compared with the previous forecast of $32 billion to $36 billion. The company said Tuesday that it expected the world economy to improve in 2010 with growth of about 3 percent, the highest growth rate since 2007. Caterpillar rose $1.76, or 3 percent, to $59.61 in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. The shares have gained 33 percent this year. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 21, 2009, on page B8 of the New York edition.Caterpillar, the maker of bulldozers and excavators, posted third-quarter earnings that beat analysts’ estimates and issued a full-year forecast that exceeded the highest prediction. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Profit dropped to $404 million, or 64 cents a share, from $868 million, or $1.39, a year earlier, the company said Tuesday in a statement. The average estimate in a Bloomberg survey of analysts was 5 cents a share. Caterpillar has slashed inventories and production amid the worst decline in its markets since the Great Depression. The company cut about 18,700 full-time jobs and about the same amount of temporary workers since December 2008 as demand faltered. Sales fell 44 percent to $7.3 billion, from $12.98 billion in the third quarter of 2008. “We believe the third quarter marked the low point for Caterpillar sales and revenues in what has been the toughest recession since the 1930s,” Jim Owens, the chief executive, said. Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., narrowed its 2009 forecast range to $1.85 to $2.05 a share, from $1.15 to $2.25. The average estimate was $1.48 a share. The highest prediction was $1.75. The revenue forecast is now $32 billion to $33 billion, compared with the previous forecast of $32 billion to $36 billion. The company said Tuesday that it expected the world economy to improve in 2010 with growth of about 3 percent, the highest growth rate since 2007. Caterpillar rose $1.76, or 3 percent, to $59.61 in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. The shares have gained 33 percent this year.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/22/business/22caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">2nd-Quarter Earnings Top Expectations at Caterpillar<date>Published: July 21, 2009</date><text>Caterpillar posted a second-quarter profit on Tuesday that exceeded analysts’ highest estimates, aided by job cuts and a lower tax rate. The company, the maker of construction equipment, raised its full-year forecast, saying stimulus programs were starting to support global demand. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » “We are seeing signs of stabilization that we hope will set the foundation for an eventual recovery,” Caterpillar’s chief executive, James W. Owens, said in a statement. “Credit markets have improved significantly. Fiscal policy and monetary stimulus have been introduced around the world, and we are seeing signs, particularly in China, that they are beginning to work.” Net income dropped to $371 million, or 60 cents a share, compared with $1.11 billion, or $1.74 a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales fell 41 percent, to $7.98 billion. Full-year profit, the company said, will be $1.15 to $2.25 a share excluding some items, exceeding analysts’ average estimate of $1.12. Sales will be $32 billion to $36 billion, in line with the average estimate of $34.8 billion. Shares of Caterpillar rose 7.67 percent, or $2.81, to $39.46. Mr. Owens has pressed the government for tax and trade policies to bolster sales and has eliminated about 17,100 full-time jobs since December. More than 17,000 contract and temporary workers also were cut. Caterpillar’s effective tax rate in the second quarter was 10 percent, less than the estimated annual rate of 31.3 percent, the company said. CAT Financial Services reported after-tax profit of $89 million, a 32 percent decline from a year earlier. Revenue declined 10 percent, to $700 million. “They exceeded expectations due to a lower tax rate than analysts expected, lower costs and better-than-expected profit at CAT finance,” said Lawrence T. De Maria, an analyst with Sterne, Agee &amp; Leach in New York. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on July 22, 2009, on page B9 of the New York edition.Caterpillar posted a second-quarter profit on Tuesday that exceeded analysts’ highest estimates, aided by job cuts and a lower tax rate. The company, the maker of construction equipment, raised its full-year forecast, saying stimulus programs were starting to support global demand. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » “We are seeing signs of stabilization that we hope will set the foundation for an eventual recovery,” Caterpillar’s chief executive, James W. Owens, said in a statement. “Credit markets have improved significantly. Fiscal policy and monetary stimulus have been introduced around the world, and we are seeing signs, particularly in China, that they are beginning to work.” Net income dropped to $371 million, or 60 cents a share, compared with $1.11 billion, or $1.74 a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales fell 41 percent, to $7.98 billion. Full-year profit, the company said, will be $1.15 to $2.25 a share excluding some items, exceeding analysts’ average estimate of $1.12. Sales will be $32 billion to $36 billion, in line with the average estimate of $34.8 billion. Shares of Caterpillar rose 7.67 percent, or $2.81, to $39.46. Mr. Owens has pressed the government for tax and trade policies to bolster sales and has eliminated about 17,100 full-time jobs since December. More than 17,000 contract and temporary workers also were cut. Caterpillar’s effective tax rate in the second quarter was 10 percent, less than the estimated annual rate of 31.3 percent, the company said. CAT Financial Services reported after-tax profit of $89 million, a 32 percent decline from a year earlier. Revenue declined 10 percent, to $700 million. “They exceeded expectations due to a lower tax rate than analysts expected, lower costs and better-than-expected profit at CAT finance,” said Lawrence T. De Maria, an analyst with Sterne, Agee &amp; Leach in New York.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/22/business/22caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar’s Quarterly Loss Was Its First in 17 Years<date>Published: April 21, 2009</date><text>Caterpillar reported its first quarterly loss in 17 years on Tuesday, hurt by plunging sales and the cost of laying off thousands of workers. It also said the Obama administration should have allocated more money for roads, bridges and other public works under its stimulus plans. The $112 million loss highlighted the depth and breadth of the global downturn, as Caterpillar recorded double-digit sales declines in most of its businesses. Its vast geographic reach and array of products, including bulldozers, engines for cargo ships and mining trucks that haul materials like iron ore, make it a bellwether of the global economy. The company, which is based in Peoria, Ill., also said the global slowdown was worse than it had predicted, despite government stimulus plans and better-than-expected commodity prices. With lending still tight and the United States recession tougher than expected in the first quarter, Caterpillar cut its outlook for the year. Revenue at Caterpillar, dropped 22 percent, to $9.22 billion, from $11.8 billion in the first quarter a year ago. The company posted a loss of $112 million, or 19 cents a share, compared with a net income of $922 million, or $1.45 a share, a year earlier. The 2009 results included charges of 58 cents a share for layoffs. Without those charges, Caterpillar would have earned 39 cents, beating Wall Street expectations of 4 cents on revenue of $8.54 billion. This year Caterpillar will have “the most significant percentage decline in our sales since the early ’30s,” James W. Owens, the company’s chief executive, said in a conference call. “We modeled a worldwide recession, but not one quite as severe as we’re currently seeing.” Caterpillar also called the infrastructure spending in President Obama’s stimulus package “disappointing” compared with that of other countries, like China, which allocated more than three times as much for public works. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on April 22, 2009, on page B10 of the New York edition.Caterpillar reported its first quarterly loss in 17 years on Tuesday, hurt by plunging sales and the cost of laying off thousands of workers. It also said the Obama administration should have allocated more money for roads, bridges and other public works under its stimulus plans. The $112 million loss highlighted the depth and breadth of the global downturn, as Caterpillar recorded double-digit sales declines in most of its businesses. Its vast geographic reach and array of products, including bulldozers, engines for cargo ships and mining trucks that haul materials like iron ore, make it a bellwether of the global economy. The company, which is based in Peoria, Ill., also said the global slowdown was worse than it had predicted, despite government stimulus plans and better-than-expected commodity prices. With lending still tight and the United States recession tougher than expected in the first quarter, Caterpillar cut its outlook for the year. Revenue at Caterpillar, dropped 22 percent, to $9.22 billion, from $11.8 billion in the first quarter a year ago. The company posted a loss of $112 million, or 19 cents a share, compared with a net income of $922 million, or $1.45 a share, a year earlier. The 2009 results included charges of 58 cents a share for layoffs. Without those charges, Caterpillar would have earned 39 cents, beating Wall Street expectations of 4 cents on revenue of $8.54 billion. This year Caterpillar will have “the most significant percentage decline in our sales since the early ’30s,” James W. Owens, the company’s chief executive, said in a conference call. “We modeled a worldwide recession, but not one quite as severe as we’re currently seeing.” Caterpillar also called the infrastructure spending in President Obama’s stimulus package “disappointing” compared with that of other countries, like China, which allocated more than three times as much for public works.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/01/business/global/01caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Workers Detain Bosses in France<date>Published: March 31, 2009</date><text>PARIS  Workers at a Caterpillar plant in the French Alps briefly held five of their bosses in a dispute over their severance packages, workers and union officials said Tuesday. “There is no violence or sequestration, but simply pressure so they restart negotiations,” Pierre Piccarreta, a representative from the C.G.T. union, told The Associated Press. Workers had detained the director of the plant and his associates. “At a time when the company is making a profit and distributing dividends to shareholders,” Mr. Piccarreta said, “we want to find a favorable outcome for all the workers and know as quickly as possible where we are going.” A member of the worker’s council, who refused to identify himself, said “the employees just want a fair deal.” The move at Caterpillar was at least the third time in the last few weeks that French workers had detained their bosses to protest job losses. Caterpillar, which in January and February announced 22,000 job cuts worldwide, is seeking to lay off 733 workers  about a quarter of the work force  at its factories in the towns of Grenoble and Échirolles. Combined with those already laid off and those whose short-term contracts will not be renewed, a total of about 1,000 workers at the French factories are losing their jobs. Caterpillar France has said the job cuts were necessary because its order book had been cut in half. Jim Dugan, a spokesman for Caterpillar at the company’s headquarters in Peoria, Ill., said he could not immediately comment. The Caterpillar dispute marks just the latest incident in which bosses have been held. Workers at a 3M plant in the plant in Pithiviers, in central France, held their boss last week for more than 24 hours in a labor dispute. Workers at a Sony plant in Pontonx-sur-l’Adour, in southwest France, held their boss overnight to gain better severance packages. France, with a long history of labor militancy, has becoming increasingly restless as the impact of the global economic crisis deepens. The French unemployment rate rose to 8.3 percent in February, according to the European Union. Demonstrations in recent months have drawn millions of protesters to the streets to challenge President Nicolas Sarkozy’s handling of the economic crisis. Opponents of Mr. Sarkozy’s government say he has focused on bailouts for banks and industrial companies while ignoring the fate of workers. More Articles in Business »PARIS  Workers at a Caterpillar plant in the French Alps briefly held five of their bosses in a dispute over their severance packages, workers and union officials said Tuesday. “There is no violence or sequestration, but simply pressure so they restart negotiations,” Pierre Piccarreta, a representative from the C.G.T. union, told The Associated Press. Workers had detained the director of the plant and his associates. “At a time when the company is making a profit and distributing dividends to shareholders,” Mr. Piccarreta said, “we want to find a favorable outcome for all the workers and know as quickly as possible where we are going.” A member of the worker’s council, who refused to identify himself, said “the employees just want a fair deal.” The move at Caterpillar was at least the third time in the last few weeks that French workers had detained their bosses to protest job losses. Caterpillar, which in January and February announced 22,000 job cuts worldwide, is seeking to lay off 733 workers  about a quarter of the work force  at its factories in the towns of Grenoble and Échirolles. Combined with those already laid off and those whose short-term contracts will not be renewed, a total of about 1,000 workers at the French factories are losing their jobs. Caterpillar France has said the job cuts were necessary because its order book had been cut in half. Jim Dugan, a spokesman for Caterpillar at the company’s headquarters in Peoria, Ill., said he could not immediately comment. The Caterpillar dispute marks just the latest incident in which bosses have been held. Workers at a 3M plant in the plant in Pithiviers, in central France, held their boss last week for more than 24 hours in a labor dispute. Workers at a Sony plant in Pontonx-sur-l’Adour, in southwest France, held their boss overnight to gain better severance packages. France, with a long history of labor militancy, has becoming increasingly restless as the impact of the global economic crisis deepens. The French unemployment rate rose to 8.3 percent in February, according to the European Union. Demonstrations in recent months have drawn millions of protesters to the streets to challenge President Nicolas Sarkozy’s handling of the economic crisis. Opponents of Mr. Sarkozy’s government say he has focused on bailouts for banks and industrial companies while ignoring the fate of workers.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/29/jobs/29boss.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar, the World Tour<date>Published: March 28, 2009</date><text>I WAS the first of my family to go to college and had relatively low expectations. I entered the general engineering program at North Carolina State University and went from that into textile engineering. Until my junior year, I was more social than academic. Skip to next paragraph JIM OWENS Chief executive, Caterpillar, Peoria, Ill. AGE 63 HOMETOWN Elizabeth City, N.C. HEROES Nelson Mandela and Milton Friedman I married, had a son and reassessed my priorities. After several years with a 4.0 average, I was offered a full-time fellowship to earn a master’s in textile technology. I took economics courses and was offered a position in the Ph.D. program. It was two years of rigorous academics, then qualifying exams. Only half of us passed. When I graduated, I had an interview with a textile company that thought a Ph.D. was a waste of time. Caterpillar, though it wasn’t a textile company, actually wanted the degree. I joined for $18,000 a year in 1972. Within three years, I was promoted to chief economist, with responsibility for Europe, the Middle East and Africa. By then, I had an 8-year-old and a 2-year-old. I joined a community of 200 to 300 Caterpillar ex-pats in Geneva. I was a Cub Scout leader, coached baseball and became commissioner of the local Little League. I was welcoming but insisted that parents stay involved; they could not just drop off their kids and leave. After four years, my wife and I separated and she moved to London. I kept custody of the kids, and after a year I moved back to Illinois. Within a few years, I was a division manager of product source planning and happily remarried, and I got the opportunity to move to a suburb of Jakarta, Indonesia, as a managing director of a manufacturing plant. By that time, my oldest son was in college; my younger son was just starting high school. I also had a daughter who was 7. To convince my family, I developed a slide show of the lifestyle we would have there, including pictures of homes with pools in the backyard. After three years, just as my son was getting ready for his senior year of high school, I got a call from Caterpillar to become president of the gas turbine division in San Diego. We debated letting my son live with another family while he finished school. He had been president of the student body. We thought it would be a harder move for him but he never asked to stay. Three years later, I got a call from the vice chairman in the executive office about coming back to Peoria to be chief financial officer. My first reaction was, no way. About a week later, I was in Peoria for a meeting, seated next to the chairman. He asked, “About ready to come home?” I asked, “Is this something we can discuss?” He said: “It’s not what you enjoy doing. It’s what the company needs you to do.” I went home and told my wife that returning to Peoria was a condition of employment. I was running my own show and didn’t want to leave. I took a huge loss on my house in San Diego. I asked the chairman, “If it doesn’t work out, can I have another business unit to run?” He asked, “Don’t you have the confidence to get this one right?” After 18 months, I was promoted to the executive office as group president with responsibilities for the Asia-Pacific theater and all financial and administrative divisions. In 1998, I was considered for C.E.O. but was passed over. A lot of headhunters told me that if I wanted to be a C.E.O., I had better leave. I thought I had one more shot. I thought that if the next time didn’t work out, I’d teach for a few years and go off into the sunset. Five years ago, three of us in the executive office were being considered for C.E.O. When I got the job, I walked around in the middle of the night, letting the new responsibilities sink in. The last few months of layoffs have been very difficult. I’ve lost more sleep over that than anything. It’s really tough when individuals are involved, but I have to think about the long-term health of the enterprise. I can’t control the global economy. It’s much more fun running a growing company. As told to Amy Zipkin. More Articles in Job Market » A version of this article appeared in print on March 29, 2009, on page BU14 of the New York edition.I WAS the first of my family to go to college and had relatively low expectations. I entered the general engineering program at North Carolina State University and went from that into textile engineering. Until my junior year, I was more social than academic. Skip to next paragraph JIM OWENS Chief executive, Caterpillar, Peoria, Ill. AGE 63 HOMETOWN Elizabeth City, N.C. HEROES Nelson Mandela and Milton Friedman I married, had a son and reassessed my priorities. After several years with a 4.0 average, I was offered a full-time fellowship to earn a master’s in textile technology. I took economics courses and was offered a position in the Ph.D. program. It was two years of rigorous academics, then qualifying exams. Only half of us passed. When I graduated, I had an interview with a textile company that thought a Ph.D. was a waste of time. Caterpillar, though it wasn’t a textile company, actually wanted the degree. I joined for $18,000 a year in 1972. Within three years, I was promoted to chief economist, with responsibility for Europe, the Middle East and Africa. By then, I had an 8-year-old and a 2-year-old. I joined a community of 200 to 300 Caterpillar ex-pats in Geneva. I was a Cub Scout leader, coached baseball and became commissioner of the local Little League. I was welcoming but insisted that parents stay involved; they could not just drop off their kids and leave. After four years, my wife and I separated and she moved to London. I kept custody of the kids, and after a year I moved back to Illinois. Within a few years, I was a division manager of product source planning and happily remarried, and I got the opportunity to move to a suburb of Jakarta, Indonesia, as a managing director of a manufacturing plant. By that time, my oldest son was in college; my younger son was just starting high school. I also had a daughter who was 7. To convince my family, I developed a slide show of the lifestyle we would have there, including pictures of homes with pools in the backyard. After three years, just as my son was getting ready for his senior year of high school, I got a call from Caterpillar to become president of the gas turbine division in San Diego. We debated letting my son live with another family while he finished school. He had been president of the student body. We thought it would be a harder move for him but he never asked to stay. Three years later, I got a call from the vice chairman in the executive office about coming back to Peoria to be chief financial officer. My first reaction was, no way. About a week later, I was in Peoria for a meeting, seated next to the chairman. He asked, “About ready to come home?” I asked, “Is this something we can discuss?” He said: “It’s not what you enjoy doing. It’s what the company needs you to do.” I went home and told my wife that returning to Peoria was a condition of employment. I was running my own show and didn’t want to leave. I took a huge loss on my house in San Diego. I asked the chairman, “If it doesn’t work out, can I have another business unit to run?” He asked, “Don’t you have the confidence to get this one right?” After 18 months, I was promoted to the executive office as group president with responsibilities for the Asia-Pacific theater and all financial and administrative divisions. In 1998, I was considered for C.E.O. but was passed over. A lot of headhunters told me that if I wanted to be a C.E.O., I had better leave. I thought I had one more shot. I thought that if the next time didn’t work out, I’d teach for a few years and go off into the sunset. Five years ago, three of us in the executive office were being considered for C.E.O. When I got the job, I walked around in the middle of the night, letting the new responsibilities sink in. The last few months of layoffs have been very difficult. I’ve lost more sleep over that than anything. It’s really tough when individuals are involved, but I have to think about the long-term health of the enterprise. I can’t control the global economy. It’s much more fun running a growing company. As told to Amy Zipkin.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/27/business/economy/27layoffs.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Layoffs Spread to More Sectors of the Economy<date>Published: January 26, 2009</date><text>Furloughs, wage reductions, hiring freezes and shorter hours simply did not do enough. A year into this recession, companies across the board are resorting to mass job cuts. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Related Your Money: Preparing Your Budget for Disaster (January 17, 2009) Times Topics: Credit Crisis — The Essentials Home Depot, Caterpillar, Sprint Nextel and at least eight other companies announced on Monday they would cut more than 75,000 jobs in the United States and around the world  a gloomy start to the workweek for employees anxious about holding their own as the economy sinks. Caterpillar, the maker of heavy equipment, is slashing its payrolls by 16 percent. Texas Instruments said late in the day that it would eliminate 3,400 jobs, or 12 percent of its work force. Jobs began disappearing in home building and mortgage operations early in the recession, then across finance and banking more generally. Now the ax is falling across large swaths of manufacturing, retailing and information technology, taking out workers from New York to Seattle. Just last week, Microsoft announced its first significant job cuts ever. Because companies like Microsoft have invested in their workers’ skills and knowledge, they usually delay major work force reductions as long as they can. But with orders for new products and services drying up and financing tight, employers are looking to shrink their costs drastically and are slashing their payrolls, anticipating a protracted decline for business in 2009. Monday’s parade of negative news comes after months of announcements from other prominent companies like Citigroup, General Electric, Nokia and Harley-Davidson. As part of its acquisition of Wyeth, Pfizer said it would cut the combined workforce by 19,500 employees. On Wednesday, the tally of mass layoffs for December will be released by the Bureau of Labor Statistics. Already, the bureau says the United States economy has shed 2.55 million jobs since the recession began, pushing the unemployment rate up to 7.2 percent last month. The latest round of job cuts  and the additional rounds likely to come as these move through the economy  mean more pain ahead for states as unemployment insurance claims rise and deplete state budgets. Congress has proposed setting aside $43 billion to assist the states and to provide for new and current recipients of unemployment checks. That money is intended to increase the weekly benefit amounts; to extend how long people can collect payments; to cover more types of workers, like part-timers; and to help states distribute benefits more quickly. It is based largely on an estimate that the unemployment rate will rise to 8 to 9 percent this year even with a stimulus package, according to the proposal summary from the House Appropriations Committee. But if unemployment soars into double digits, as some economists expect, the financing may not be enough. “The economy is deteriorating at a faster clip than even the most dreary forecasts had expected,” said Joseph Brusuelas, an economist who, bucking the current job market trend, will soon start a new job at Moody’s Economy.com. “At the current trend, $43 billion will not be sufficient should we breach 9 percent unemployment and maybe reach into the double digits.” President Obama cited the layoff announcements in remarks Monday urging Congress to approve an $825 billion economic stimulus package of tax cuts, emergency benefits and public spending projects. “These are not just numbers on a page,” he said. “As with the millions of jobs lost in 2008, these are working men and women whose families have been disrupted and whose dreams have been put on hold.” Charles DiGisco, of Randolph, N.J., is one casualty of the downturn. He said he had been looking for work since Sept. 18, when he lost his job as a vice president for sales and marketing at Master Cutlery, a knife maker. He frequently hears a familiar refrain from would-be employers: “We would hire you, but we’re not hiring anybody.” His family’s monthly expenses are four times what Mr. DiGisco collects from unemployment, and he said his family was selling two of its three cars and might dispose of some stocks or dip into retirement funds to keep paying the mortgage. “It takes me 20 years to save it, and it takes me five months to go through it,” Mr. DiGisco said. While stimulus spending on public works may take some time to get going, some companies could bring back displaced workers quickly if the government initiative generated new orders. Caterpillar, for example, had announced buyouts, wage freezes and work stoppages around the holidays because of “a dramatic decline in orders,” said Jim Dugan, a spokesman for the company, based in Peoria, Ill. On Monday, the company said that a total of 15,000 permanent and temporary jobs, out of about 125,000, would have been eliminated by the end of this week, and that it would trim 5,000 more by the end of the first quarter. Should orders for earthmovers and other heavy equipment improve, which some expect as countries around the world start building bridges, highways and other public works to help create jobs, Caterpillar can recall some workers quickly. Many companies, though, may not rush to increase staffs even if business begins to pick up. Andrew Stettner, deputy director of the National Employment Law Project, said downturns often motivate companies to restructure business models permanently, meaning jobs they cut now are unlikely to be replaced. “Structural change is put into overdrive because of the recession,” he said, “so who knows for sure how a company like Microsoft will fare?” Sprint Nextel, which announced Monday that it was eliminating 8,000 jobs, or roughly 14 percent of its work force, is similarly facing some tough restructuring decisions as it continues to hemorrhage subscribers. After a dismal holiday shopping season, retailers are letting employees go in droves. More than 66,600 retailing jobs were lost in December, the worst period since the late 1930s. Home Depot, the home improvement retailer, said Monday it would cut 7,000 jobs, or 2 percent of its workers. Some 5,000 cuts will come through store closings, largely of its upscale Expo chain; the rest will come from corporate support, many at its Atlanta headquarters. Carol B. Tomé, Home Depot’s chief financial officer, said the company had explored ways to save Expo, but “as we kept looking at alternatives, the business kept getting softer and softer.” For most of last year, relatively healthy demand for exports gave global companies like Caterpillar a cushion. But with downturns deepening across Europe and Asia, and the dollar strengthening, global demand for costlier American goods has faltered. “There really isn’t any hiding place for companies anymore,” said Nigel Gault, chief United States economist at IHS Global Insight. “The recent numbers coming in from the rest of the world are disastrous.” Jack Healy, Stephanie Rosenbloom, Louis Uchitelle and Jenna Wortham contributed reporting. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 27, 2009, on page A1 of the New York edition.Furloughs, wage reductions, hiring freezes and shorter hours simply did not do enough. A year into this recession, companies across the board are resorting to mass job cuts. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Related Your Money: Preparing Your Budget for Disaster (January 17, 2009) Times Topics: Credit Crisis — The Essentials Home Depot, Caterpillar, Sprint Nextel and at least eight other companies announced on Monday they would cut more than 75,000 jobs in the United States and around the world  a gloomy start to the workweek for employees anxious about holding their own as the economy sinks. Caterpillar, the maker of heavy equipment, is slashing its payrolls by 16 percent. Texas Instruments said late in the day that it would eliminate 3,400 jobs, or 12 percent of its work force. Jobs began disappearing in home building and mortgage operations early in the recession, then across finance and banking more generally. Now the ax is falling across large swaths of manufacturing, retailing and information technology, taking out workers from New York to Seattle. Just last week, Microsoft announced its first significant job cuts ever. Because companies like Microsoft have invested in their workers’ skills and knowledge, they usually delay major work force reductions as long as they can. But with orders for new products and services drying up and financing tight, employers are looking to shrink their costs drastically and are slashing their payrolls, anticipating a protracted decline for business in 2009. Monday’s parade of negative news comes after months of announcements from other prominent companies like Citigroup, General Electric, Nokia and Harley-Davidson. As part of its acquisition of Wyeth, Pfizer said it would cut the combined workforce by 19,500 employees. On Wednesday, the tally of mass layoffs for December will be released by the Bureau of Labor Statistics. Already, the bureau says the United States economy has shed 2.55 million jobs since the recession began, pushing the unemployment rate up to 7.2 percent last month. The latest round of job cuts  and the additional rounds likely to come as these move through the economy  mean more pain ahead for states as unemployment insurance claims rise and deplete state budgets. Congress has proposed setting aside $43 billion to assist the states and to provide for new and current recipients of unemployment checks. That money is intended to increase the weekly benefit amounts; to extend how long people can collect payments; to cover more types of workers, like part-timers; and to help states distribute benefits more quickly. It is based largely on an estimate that the unemployment rate will rise to 8 to 9 percent this year even with a stimulus package, according to the proposal summary from the House Appropriations Committee. But if unemployment soars into double digits, as some economists expect, the financing may not be enough. “The economy is deteriorating at a faster clip than even the most dreary forecasts had expected,” said Joseph Brusuelas, an economist who, bucking the current job market trend, will soon start a new job at Moody’s Economy.com. “At the current trend, $43 billion will not be sufficient should we breach 9 percent unemployment and maybe reach into the double digits.” President Obama cited the layoff announcements in remarks Monday urging Congress to approve an $825 billion economic stimulus package of tax cuts, emergency benefits and public spending projects. “These are not just numbers on a page,” he said. “As with the millions of jobs lost in 2008, these are working men and women whose families have been disrupted and whose dreams have been put on hold.” Charles DiGisco, of Randolph, N.J., is one casualty of the downturn. He said he had been looking for work since Sept. 18, when he lost his job as a vice president for sales and marketing at Master Cutlery, a knife maker. He frequently hears a familiar refrain from would-be employers: “We would hire you, but we’re not hiring anybody.” His family’s monthly expenses are four times what Mr. DiGisco collects from unemployment, and he said his family was selling two of its three cars and might dispose of some stocks or dip into retirement funds to keep paying the mortgage. “It takes me 20 years to save it, and it takes me five months to go through it,” Mr. DiGisco said. While stimulus spending on public works may take some time to get going, some companies could bring back displaced workers quickly if the government initiative generated new orders. Caterpillar, for example, had announced buyouts, wage freezes and work stoppages around the holidays because of “a dramatic decline in orders,” said Jim Dugan, a spokesman for the company, based in Peoria, Ill. On Monday, the company said that a total of 15,000 permanent and temporary jobs, out of about 125,000, would have been eliminated by the end of this week, and that it would trim 5,000 more by the end of the first quarter. Should orders for earthmovers and other heavy equipment improve, which some expect as countries around the world start building bridges, highways and other public works to help create jobs, Caterpillar can recall some workers quickly. Many companies, though, may not rush to increase staffs even if business begins to pick up. Andrew Stettner, deputy director of the National Employment Law Project, said downturns often motivate companies to restructure business models permanently, meaning jobs they cut now are unlikely to be replaced. “Structural change is put into overdrive because of the recession,” he said, “so who knows for sure how a company like Microsoft will fare?” Sprint Nextel, which announced Monday that it was eliminating 8,000 jobs, or roughly 14 percent of its work force, is similarly facing some tough restructuring decisions as it continues to hemorrhage subscribers. After a dismal holiday shopping season, retailers are letting employees go in droves. More than 66,600 retailing jobs were lost in December, the worst period since the late 1930s. Home Depot, the home improvement retailer, said Monday it would cut 7,000 jobs, or 2 percent of its workers. Some 5,000 cuts will come through store closings, largely of its upscale Expo chain; the rest will come from corporate support, many at its Atlanta headquarters. Carol B. Tomé, Home Depot’s chief financial officer, said the company had explored ways to save Expo, but “as we kept looking at alternatives, the business kept getting softer and softer.” For most of last year, relatively healthy demand for exports gave global companies like Caterpillar a cushion. But with downturns deepening across Europe and Asia, and the dollar strengthening, global demand for costlier American goods has faltered. “There really isn’t any hiding place for companies anymore,” said Nigel Gault, chief United States economist at IHS Global Insight. “The recent numbers coming in from the rest of the world are disastrous.” Jack Healy, Stephanie Rosenbloom, Louis Uchitelle and Jenna Wortham contributed reporting.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/23/business/23caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar to Cut Its Managers’ Pay<date>Published: December 22, 2008</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the mining and construction equipment maker, said Monday that it would cut executive compensation by up to 50 percent next year because of weakening global demand. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Pay for senior managers also will be reduced next year by 5 to 35 percent, the company said. Other management and support staff members will see a reduction of up to 15 percent. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., said the cuts reflected planned reductions in its incentive program and equity-based compensation. It has instituted a hiring freeze and plans to suspend merit increases for managers and support employees. American-based management and support employees were also being offered incentives to leave voluntarily, the company said. Eligible employees have until Jan. 12 to join the program. “We understand these decisions will disrupt the lives of many of our employees and their families, and we regret the need to take these steps,” the chief executive, James W. Owens, said in a statement. The announcement was the latest cost-cutting measure by the company, which has laid off employees and cut contract workers in response to the global economic turmoil that has hurt demand for its products. The company said Monday that it would continue to carry out cost-saving measures, including temporary factory shutdowns and more layoffs as needed. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on December 23, 2008, on page B2 of the New York edition.Caterpillar Inc., the mining and construction equipment maker, said Monday that it would cut executive compensation by up to 50 percent next year because of weakening global demand. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » Pay for senior managers also will be reduced next year by 5 to 35 percent, the company said. Other management and support staff members will see a reduction of up to 15 percent. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., said the cuts reflected planned reductions in its incentive program and equity-based compensation. It has instituted a hiring freeze and plans to suspend merit increases for managers and support employees. American-based management and support employees were also being offered incentives to leave voluntarily, the company said. Eligible employees have until Jan. 12 to join the program. “We understand these decisions will disrupt the lives of many of our employees and their families, and we regret the need to take these steps,” the chief executive, James W. Owens, said in a statement. The announcement was the latest cost-cutting measure by the company, which has laid off employees and cut contract workers in response to the global economic turmoil that has hurt demand for its products. The company said Monday that it would continue to carry out cost-saving measures, including temporary factory shutdowns and more layoffs as needed.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/23/business/23caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Earnings at Caterpillar Climb 34%<date>Published: July 23, 2008</date><text>The construction and mining equipment company Caterpillar said on Tuesday that quarterly earnings rose 34 percent, widely beating expectations, as strong growth in emerging economies offset weakness in North America, Western Europe and Japan. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company also raised its full-year outlook, despite its forecast of significantly higher material costs in the second half. Caterpillar, a component of the Dow Jones industrial average and a business bellwether, reported a second-quarter profit of $1.11 billion, or $1.74 a share, compared with $823 million, or $1.24 a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 20 percent, to $13.64 billion. Analysts, on average, had expected the company, based in Peoria, Ill., to earn $1.54 a share on sales of $11.87 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. In North America, Caterpillar said economic conditions in construction and quarrying continued to deteriorate during the quarter, offsetting some improvements in commodity sectors. But strength in Asia, where machinery sales surged 50 percent during the quarter, more than offset weakness there and in Western Europe. China continued to be a big area of strength, and Indonesia, which is benefiting from high coal prices and strong construction growth, also contributed to Caterpillar’s gains. The company announced separately on Tuesday that it was raising prices 5 to 7 percent worldwide, effective January 2009. Caterpillar shares rose 2.4 percent, or $1.75, to $74.98. More Articles in Business »The construction and mining equipment company Caterpillar said on Tuesday that quarterly earnings rose 34 percent, widely beating expectations, as strong growth in emerging economies offset weakness in North America, Western Europe and Japan. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Caterpillar Inc Go to your Portfolio » The company also raised its full-year outlook, despite its forecast of significantly higher material costs in the second half. Caterpillar, a component of the Dow Jones industrial average and a business bellwether, reported a second-quarter profit of $1.11 billion, or $1.74 a share, compared with $823 million, or $1.24 a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 20 percent, to $13.64 billion. Analysts, on average, had expected the company, based in Peoria, Ill., to earn $1.54 a share on sales of $11.87 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. In North America, Caterpillar said economic conditions in construction and quarrying continued to deteriorate during the quarter, offsetting some improvements in commodity sectors. But strength in Asia, where machinery sales surged 50 percent during the quarter, more than offset weakness there and in Western Europe. China continued to be a big area of strength, and Indonesia, which is benefiting from high coal prices and strong construction growth, also contributed to Caterpillar’s gains. The company announced separately on Tuesday that it was raising prices 5 to 7 percent worldwide, effective January 2009. Caterpillar shares rose 2.4 percent, or $1.75, to $74.98.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/19/business/19caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar’s Profit Climbs on Strength of Foreign Sales<date>Published: April 19, 2008</date><text>CHICAGO (AP)  The heavy equipment maker Caterpillar parlayed an increased reliance on international markets to surprisingly strong sales and a 13 percent jump in first-quarter profits, impressing investors who had expected the company to be slowed more by the weak American economy and dollar. The stock surged more than 8 percent in Friday trading after company easily beat Wall Street’s earnings estimates, benefiting from its strategy of diversification. Shares rose $6.69, to $85.28, in afternoon trading and are now up more than 40 percent since mid-January, to within $2 of their record high. Sales were up 37 percent in the Asia-Pacific region, 30 percent in the Europe-Africa-Middle East region and 24 percent in Latin America, compared with just 4 percent in North America. Caterpillar executives said the weak dollar hurt the bottom line, with raw materials and other costs up at its international plants. But in sales alone, the currency impact added $310 million in the quarter. Caterpillar earned $922 million, or $1.45 a share, in the January-March period, compared with $816 million, or $1.23 a share, a year earlier. That blew past the $1.33-a-share estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue rose 18 percent, to $11.8 billion, from $10.02 billion a year earlier, with $10.98 billion coming from machinery and engines sales and $817 million from financial products. A sales breakdown showed 58 percent came from outside North America, up from 53 percent a year earlier. The company lowered its expectations for the United States economy, pegging gross domestic product growth at 0.5 percent for 2008, down from 1 percent in January. But Caterpillar still expects 2008 earnings per share to rise 5 percent to 15 percent over 2007, and sales to improve 5 percent to 10 percent. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO (AP)  The heavy equipment maker Caterpillar parlayed an increased reliance on international markets to surprisingly strong sales and a 13 percent jump in first-quarter profits, impressing investors who had expected the company to be slowed more by the weak American economy and dollar. The stock surged more than 8 percent in Friday trading after company easily beat Wall Street’s earnings estimates, benefiting from its strategy of diversification. Shares rose $6.69, to $85.28, in afternoon trading and are now up more than 40 percent since mid-January, to within $2 of their record high. Sales were up 37 percent in the Asia-Pacific region, 30 percent in the Europe-Africa-Middle East region and 24 percent in Latin America, compared with just 4 percent in North America. Caterpillar executives said the weak dollar hurt the bottom line, with raw materials and other costs up at its international plants. But in sales alone, the currency impact added $310 million in the quarter. Caterpillar earned $922 million, or $1.45 a share, in the January-March period, compared with $816 million, or $1.23 a share, a year earlier. That blew past the $1.33-a-share estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue rose 18 percent, to $11.8 billion, from $10.02 billion a year earlier, with $10.98 billion coming from machinery and engines sales and $817 million from financial products. A sales breakdown showed 58 percent came from outside North America, up from 53 percent a year earlier. The company lowered its expectations for the United States economy, pegging gross domestic product growth at 0.5 percent for 2008, down from 1 percent in January. But Caterpillar still expects 2008 earnings per share to rise 5 percent to 15 percent over 2007, and sales to improve 5 percent to 10 percent.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/26/business/worldbusiness/26caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Increases Profit With Strong Overseas Growth<date>Published: January 26, 2008</date><text>Caterpillar, one of the world’s largest construction equipment makers, said Friday that its fourth-quarter earnings rose 11 percent on strong international growth. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., said it expected solid profit growth from overseas sales this year as well. Caterpillar earned $975 million, or $1.50 a share, compared with $882 million, or $1.32 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 10 percent, to $12.14 billion, from $11 billion in the prior-year period. Analysts were expecting a profit of $1.50 a share on revenue of $11.79 billion, according to a poll by Thomson Financial. Caterpillar expects economic growth in the Unites States to slow to 1 percent this year, partly because of continued weakness in home construction. But Caterpillar’s chief executive, James W. Owens, said strong economic growth outside the United States would offset weak domestic demand. “Global markets for mining, energy and infrastructure development are booming,” he said in a statement. The company is predicting profit growth of 5 to 15 percent in 2008, on revenue that will rise 5 to 10 percent year-over-year. The prediction implies 2008 profit of $5.64 to $6.18 a share on revenue of $44.06 billion to $46.16 billion. Almost 60 percent of Caterpillar’s fourth-quarter sales were outside North America, an almost 10 percent increase from just a year earlier. The company said it also benefited from the weak dollar. Currency fluctuations added $334 million to fourth-quarter revenue, Caterpillar said. The company plans to spend $2.3 billion this year to add production capacity to deal with order backlogs of construction equipment and other products, a 35 percent increase. Caterpillar shares rose 68 cents, to $65.93. More Articles in Business »Caterpillar, one of the world’s largest construction equipment makers, said Friday that its fourth-quarter earnings rose 11 percent on strong international growth. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., said it expected solid profit growth from overseas sales this year as well. Caterpillar earned $975 million, or $1.50 a share, compared with $882 million, or $1.32 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 10 percent, to $12.14 billion, from $11 billion in the prior-year period. Analysts were expecting a profit of $1.50 a share on revenue of $11.79 billion, according to a poll by Thomson Financial. Caterpillar expects economic growth in the Unites States to slow to 1 percent this year, partly because of continued weakness in home construction. But Caterpillar’s chief executive, James W. Owens, said strong economic growth outside the United States would offset weak domestic demand. “Global markets for mining, energy and infrastructure development are booming,” he said in a statement. The company is predicting profit growth of 5 to 15 percent in 2008, on revenue that will rise 5 to 10 percent year-over-year. The prediction implies 2008 profit of $5.64 to $6.18 a share on revenue of $44.06 billion to $46.16 billion. Almost 60 percent of Caterpillar’s fourth-quarter sales were outside North America, an almost 10 percent increase from just a year earlier. The company said it also benefited from the weak dollar. Currency fluctuations added $334 million to fourth-quarter revenue, Caterpillar said. The company plans to spend $2.3 billion this year to add production capacity to deal with order backlogs of construction equipment and other products, a 35 percent increase. Caterpillar shares rose 68 cents, to $65.93.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/10/technology/10ecom.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Web Retailers Get Into Employee Gifts<date>Published: December 10, 2007</date><text>FOR years, employees have had to hide their online shopping habit. Now they can start coming out of the closet. Internet retailers and corporations have grown chummy in recent years, with merchants offering companies corporate gift and incentive programs. Emboldened, online retailers are designing technology and Web pages to capture more of the roughly $32 billion in merchandise sales spent on workers and clients annually. This year, for example, Amazon introduced the merchandise rewards program, aimed not at consumers, but at companies like USMotivation, MotivAction Worldwide and Maritz, which manage employee incentive programs for businesses like Caterpillar, Motel 6 and others. In these programs, corporations typically reward workers with points (as in frequent-flier programs) for achieving company goals, or as year-end gifts. Workers use their company-specific Web site to track and redeem points for Margarita mixers, iPods or even flat-screen televisions. For the vendors that administer the rewards programs on a company’s behalf, Amazon’s entry into the market gives workers a wider range of items to select from. For Amazon, it means a connection to businesses that buy hundreds of thousands of items annually, and a new way to market itself to consumers.  Scott Merlino, the senior manager of the merchandise rewards service, said the service has helped employers offer gifts specifically suited to a worker’s tastes. One client, for example, has already bought more than 100,000 items from Amazon, and 25,000 of those items were for single orders. Hans-Eric Gosch, senior business development manager of the service, would not say how many customers it has attracted, but said he was pleased with the growth. “It’s not been a hard sell,” he said. The merchandise rewards program also brings some residual marketing benefits. Even though employees do not know they are selecting items from Amazon, they receive shipments in Amazon boxes, usually within five days of ordering. “If they haven’t already ordered from us before, it could get them to check out the Web site,” Mr. Merlino said. While Amazon has a foot in the door of this market, it still faces a lot of competition in increasing its share of merchandise through these systems. According to Bruce Bolger, the managing director for the Incentive Performance Center, an industry group, more manufacturers and retailers are lining up to sell their wares to employees as corporations shift more money into incentive programs. Mr. Bolger said that since 2000, when corporations spent about $13 billion on merchandise gifts for employees, executives have devoted much more energy and money to rewarding workers. Among other things, corporations are stepping up their employee retention programs, in anticipation of a labor shortage caused by retirements, said Mark Peterman, a vice president for marketing for Maritz Motivation, a division of Maritz Inc., located in Fenton, Mo. “Companies are putting more thought into how to maximize the benefit to the corporation while genuinely saying thank you,” Mr. Peterman said. While bonus cash tends to get mixed in with regular compensation, he added, “when they select an item, that’s something they can point back to and remember, along with the company.” Mr. Peterman said his clients now use the Internet almost exclusively to select goods, where in 1999, 83 percent of the items selected by employees were ordered offline. The trend toward buying business gifts online has attracted the attention of other Internet companies, like IAC/InterActiveCorp’s Gifts.com, a gift-related search site. According to William Lynch, Gifts.com’s chief, about 9 percent of the searches conducted in November were for business gifts, compared with about 7 percent a year earlier. Based on that trend, the company recently added a business gifts section to the site, filled with items like business-card scanners, personalized laptop covers and Starbucks gift baskets. Gifts.com will also negotiate bulk discounts next year on behalf of businesses that want to buy, for example, a thousand desktop accessories for employees or clients. “This market is huge, and there’s not a service out there that’s really helping human resources managers come up with creative gifts within their budgets,” Mr. Lynch said.  Sales of gift cards, one of the most popular business gifts in recent years, are also growing online, said Jonathan Price, who oversees the business gifts division of GiftCertificates.com. Mr. Price said his company has recently been printing more customized gift cards that bear a corporation’s logo. So-called virtual gift certificates, which employees receive and redeem entirely online, are also increasingly popular, he said. Harry &amp; David, the food retailer, is bracing for the busiest two weeks of the year for business gifts starting today, according to William Ihle, a spokesman. Mr. Ihle would not say exactly how much the company’s business-related Internet sales have grown. “But it’s a very, very strong business for us, and we’re seeing solid growth,” he said. This year, Mr. Ihle said, Harry &amp; David overhauled its Web site to, among other things, better promote its business-related service, including a feature that shows the most popular business gifts at various price levels. Tiffany, too, has experienced growth in the number of business gifts bought on its Web site, said Mark L. Aaron, a spokesman. Executives will often go online, and pick up a few items for their most valued clients while also buying for loved ones, he said. “And since it saves the time of our account executives,” he added, “it’s more efficient for us, too.” More Articles in Technology »FOR years, employees have had to hide their online shopping habit. Now they can start coming out of the closet. Internet retailers and corporations have grown chummy in recent years, with merchants offering companies corporate gift and incentive programs. Emboldened, online retailers are designing technology and Web pages to capture more of the roughly $32 billion in merchandise sales spent on workers and clients annually. This year, for example, Amazon introduced the merchandise rewards program, aimed not at consumers, but at companies like USMotivation, MotivAction Worldwide and Maritz, which manage employee incentive programs for businesses like Caterpillar, Motel 6 and others. In these programs, corporations typically reward workers with points (as in frequent-flier programs) for achieving company goals, or as year-end gifts. Workers use their company-specific Web site to track and redeem points for Margarita mixers, iPods or even flat-screen televisions. For the vendors that administer the rewards programs on a company’s behalf, Amazon’s entry into the market gives workers a wider range of items to select from. For Amazon, it means a connection to businesses that buy hundreds of thousands of items annually, and a new way to market itself to consumers.  Scott Merlino, the senior manager of the merchandise rewards service, said the service has helped employers offer gifts specifically suited to a worker’s tastes. One client, for example, has already bought more than 100,000 items from Amazon, and 25,000 of those items were for single orders. Hans-Eric Gosch, senior business development manager of the service, would not say how many customers it has attracted, but said he was pleased with the growth. “It’s not been a hard sell,” he said. The merchandise rewards program also brings some residual marketing benefits. Even though employees do not know they are selecting items from Amazon, they receive shipments in Amazon boxes, usually within five days of ordering. “If they haven’t already ordered from us before, it could get them to check out the Web site,” Mr. Merlino said. While Amazon has a foot in the door of this market, it still faces a lot of competition in increasing its share of merchandise through these systems. According to Bruce Bolger, the managing director for the Incentive Performance Center, an industry group, more manufacturers and retailers are lining up to sell their wares to employees as corporations shift more money into incentive programs. Mr. Bolger said that since 2000, when corporations spent about $13 billion on merchandise gifts for employees, executives have devoted much more energy and money to rewarding workers. Among other things, corporations are stepping up their employee retention programs, in anticipation of a labor shortage caused by retirements, said Mark Peterman, a vice president for marketing for Maritz Motivation, a division of Maritz Inc., located in Fenton, Mo. “Companies are putting more thought into how to maximize the benefit to the corporation while genuinely saying thank you,” Mr. Peterman said. While bonus cash tends to get mixed in with regular compensation, he added, “when they select an item, that’s something they can point back to and remember, along with the company.” Mr. Peterman said his clients now use the Internet almost exclusively to select goods, where in 1999, 83 percent of the items selected by employees were ordered offline. The trend toward buying business gifts online has attracted the attention of other Internet companies, like IAC/InterActiveCorp’s Gifts.com, a gift-related search site. According to William Lynch, Gifts.com’s chief, about 9 percent of the searches conducted in November were for business gifts, compared with about 7 percent a year earlier. Based on that trend, the company recently added a business gifts section to the site, filled with items like business-card scanners, personalized laptop covers and Starbucks gift baskets. Gifts.com will also negotiate bulk discounts next year on behalf of businesses that want to buy, for example, a thousand desktop accessories for employees or clients. “This market is huge, and there’s not a service out there that’s really helping human resources managers come up with creative gifts within their budgets,” Mr. Lynch said.  Sales of gift cards, one of the most popular business gifts in recent years, are also growing online, said Jonathan Price, who oversees the business gifts division of GiftCertificates.com. Mr. Price said his company has recently been printing more customized gift cards that bear a corporation’s logo. So-called virtual gift certificates, which employees receive and redeem entirely online, are also increasingly popular, he said. Harry &amp; David, the food retailer, is bracing for the busiest two weeks of the year for business gifts starting today, according to William Ihle, a spokesman. Mr. Ihle would not say exactly how much the company’s business-related Internet sales have grown. “But it’s a very, very strong business for us, and we’re seeing solid growth,” he said. This year, Mr. Ihle said, Harry &amp; David overhauled its Web site to, among other things, better promote its business-related service, including a feature that shows the most popular business gifts at various price levels. Tiffany, too, has experienced growth in the number of business gifts bought on its Web site, said Mark L. Aaron, a spokesman. Executives will often go online, and pick up a few items for their most valued clients while also buying for loved ones, he said. “And since it saves the time of our account executives,” he added, “it’s more efficient for us, too.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/20/business/worldbusiness/20global.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Companies Bolster Sales Abroad to Offset Weakness at Home<date>Published: November 20, 2007</date><text>SALISBURY, N.C., Nov. 16  If the fortunes of the Power Curbers company were tied solely to business in the United States, these would be grim days at its factory on the fringes of this Piedmont town. The small, family-owned company makes machines that turn concrete into curbs, and with the American construction industry in distress, domestic sales are expected to drop at least 10 percent this year. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Chris Keane for The New York Times Tray Hawkins works at the Power Curbers plant in Salisbury, N.C. The company has been increasing its overseas sales. Related Managing Globalization Blog: Heres That Silver Lining, Finally But fortunately for Power Curbers, and indeed for the national economy, the company has transcended geography. Aided by the falling dollar, which makes American goods cheaper on world markets, Power Curbers, like thousands of other companies in the United States, is tapping rapid growth abroad to compensate for sluggish sales at home. It just overlapped as if youd scripted it, said the companys president and chief executive officer, Dyke Messinger, the third generation to head the company begun by his grandfather in 1953. Without that foreign business, these would be some tough days. Wed have had some layoffs for sure. As the United States heads into what many economists predict will be a substantial economic slowdown, the success of American firms in building sales abroad may cushion the blow. It could help prevent the economy from slipping into a recession. In the first half of the year, profits earned at home by American companies grew not at all compared with a year earlier, according to an analysis by Moodys Economy.com. But profits abroad soared by 22 percent. Caterpillar, the maker of construction machines and engines, said its North American sales fell by 11 percent during the summer, according to its most recent earnings report, as the housing and construction slowdown in the United States cooled demand. But during those same months, Caterpillars sales surged by roughly a third in Africa, Asia, Europe and the Middle East and by 20 percent in Latin America. Overall, the companys sales grew 9 percent. McDonalds, a symbol of globalization, said its sales in Africa, Asia, Europe and the Middle East grew at 2 ½ times the pace of sales at home. Look at the top 30 economies in the world: Every one is in expansion except for two  Denmark and Japan, said David Huether, chief economist at the National Association of Manufacturers. For the next year or so, the global economy is strong. But whether strong business abroad can in the longer term offset weakness at home is far from certain. Though the global economy has been growing at more than twice the pace of the United States economy  propelled by the breakneck development of China, Russia and India  some economists see signs of slackening. The International Monetary Fund recently predicted a slight easing in global growth next year while warning that the downturn in mortgage markets could spawn wider troubles. If institutions in Europe follow Wall Street banks in logging huge losses on their mortgage-related holdings, that could crimp new investment and slow the economy. European exporters are already struggling with the effects of a soaring euro, which makes their products more expensive. Factories across Asia, Latin America and Europe are bracing for the consequences of tighter American spending, which could curb demand for Guatemalan-made clothing, Chinese-built computers and German-produced cars. Recently, economists have been debating whether it is possible for the global economy to continue expanding even if fortunes dim in the United States. Some argue that the needs of rapidly developing societies are so vast that they can compensate for slack growth in the industrial countries. Think of 400 million people in China going from the 6th century to the 21st century over the last 15 years, said Robert Barbera, chief economist at ITG, a brokerage and advisory firm. The same thing is going on in India as well. Thats still the big driver for growth. It could self-destruct for any number of reasons, but that underlying story is decades away from being over. But if that is the future, some economists assert that the present remains shaped primarily by conditions in the United States  by far the worlds largest economy. If declining house prices cause Americans to spend less, that would most likely diminish demand for, say, DVD players made in factories in southern China. And that could in turn limit demand for the American-made chips at the heart of DVD players and the American-made machines used to build them. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »SALISBURY, N.C., Nov. 16  If the fortunes of the Power Curbers company were tied solely to business in the United States, these would be grim days at its factory on the fringes of this Piedmont town. The small, family-owned company makes machines that turn concrete into curbs, and with the American construction industry in distress, domestic sales are expected to drop at least 10 percent this year. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Chris Keane for The New York Times Tray Hawkins works at the Power Curbers plant in Salisbury, N.C. The company has been increasing its overseas sales. Related Managing Globalization Blog: Heres That Silver Lining, Finally But fortunately for Power Curbers, and indeed for the national economy, the company has transcended geography. Aided by the falling dollar, which makes American goods cheaper on world markets, Power Curbers, like thousands of other companies in the United States, is tapping rapid growth abroad to compensate for sluggish sales at home. It just overlapped as if youd scripted it, said the companys president and chief executive officer, Dyke Messinger, the third generation to head the company begun by his grandfather in 1953. Without that foreign business, these would be some tough days. Wed have had some layoffs for sure. As the United States heads into what many economists predict will be a substantial economic slowdown, the success of American firms in building sales abroad may cushion the blow. It could help prevent the economy from slipping into a recession. In the first half of the year, profits earned at home by American companies grew not at all compared with a year earlier, according to an analysis by Moodys Economy.com. But profits abroad soared by 22 percent. Caterpillar, the maker of construction machines and engines, said its North American sales fell by 11 percent during the summer, according to its most recent earnings report, as the housing and construction slowdown in the United States cooled demand. But during those same months, Caterpillars sales surged by roughly a third in Africa, Asia, Europe and the Middle East and by 20 percent in Latin America. Overall, the companys sales grew 9 percent. McDonalds, a symbol of globalization, said its sales in Africa, Asia, Europe and the Middle East grew at 2 ½ times the pace of sales at home. Look at the top 30 economies in the world: Every one is in expansion except for two  Denmark and Japan, said David Huether, chief economist at the National Association of Manufacturers. For the next year or so, the global economy is strong. But whether strong business abroad can in the longer term offset weakness at home is far from certain. Though the global economy has been growing at more than twice the pace of the United States economy  propelled by the breakneck development of China, Russia and India  some economists see signs of slackening. The International Monetary Fund recently predicted a slight easing in global growth next year while warning that the downturn in mortgage markets could spawn wider troubles. If institutions in Europe follow Wall Street banks in logging huge losses on their mortgage-related holdings, that could crimp new investment and slow the economy. European exporters are already struggling with the effects of a soaring euro, which makes their products more expensive. Factories across Asia, Latin America and Europe are bracing for the consequences of tighter American spending, which could curb demand for Guatemalan-made clothing, Chinese-built computers and German-produced cars. Recently, economists have been debating whether it is possible for the global economy to continue expanding even if fortunes dim in the United States. Some argue that the needs of rapidly developing societies are so vast that they can compensate for slack growth in the industrial countries. Think of 400 million people in China going from the 6th century to the 21st century over the last 15 years, said Robert Barbera, chief economist at ITG, a brokerage and advisory firm. The same thing is going on in India as well. Thats still the big driver for growth. It could self-destruct for any number of reasons, but that underlying story is decades away from being over. But if that is the future, some economists assert that the present remains shaped primarily by conditions in the United States  by far the worlds largest economy. If declining house prices cause Americans to spend less, that would most likely diminish demand for, say, DVD players made in factories in southern China. And that could in turn limit demand for the American-made chips at the heart of DVD players and the American-made machines used to build them. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/21/business/21caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Profit Down 21%; Slump in Home Building Cited<date>Published: July 21, 2007</date><text>PEORIA, Ill., July 20 (AP)  Shares of Caterpillar tumbled Friday as the company posted a 21 percent drop in profit, missing Wall Street expectations amid weak North American machinery sales and higher-than-expected operating costs. The companys shares, which had risen to record highs over the last month, fell $3.78, or 4.35 percent, to $83.20. Shares, which have traded in a 52-week range of $57.98 to $87, dipped to $78.26 before rebounding in late trading. Caterpillar, one of the worlds largest makers of heavy equipment, said net earnings fell even though revenue rose 7 percent, to $11.36 billion  a company record for the second quarter  from $10.61 billion last year. The company cited sluggish housing construction and engine sales in North America, higher-than-expected operating costs and a planned reduction in inventories for the decline. Caterpillar earned $823 million, or $1.24 a share, in the three months ended June 30, down from $1.05 billion, or $1.52 a share, in the period last year, when the company posted its strongest earnings in at least four decades. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expected a profit of $1.49 a share on revenue of $11.12 billion. Alexander Blanton, an analyst with Ingalls &amp; Snyder, called the second-quarter earnings decline a blip, saying the company would continue to ride strong demand fueled by construction in China, India and other rapidly developing nations. This is a very strong trend, and its not going to go away, Mr. Blanton said. Its a factor of people in emerging countries wanting a better life, and they have to have infrastructure to do that. The company has projected full-year revenue of about $44 billion, up from $41.5 billion last year. Profit is forecast for $5.30 to $5.80 a share, up from $5.17 in 2006. Sales outside of North America are expected to be up 24 percent for the year, more than offsetting a projected 12 percent dip in North America, the company said. More Articles in Business »PEORIA, Ill., July 20 (AP)  Shares of Caterpillar tumbled Friday as the company posted a 21 percent drop in profit, missing Wall Street expectations amid weak North American machinery sales and higher-than-expected operating costs. The companys shares, which had risen to record highs over the last month, fell $3.78, or 4.35 percent, to $83.20. Shares, which have traded in a 52-week range of $57.98 to $87, dipped to $78.26 before rebounding in late trading. Caterpillar, one of the worlds largest makers of heavy equipment, said net earnings fell even though revenue rose 7 percent, to $11.36 billion  a company record for the second quarter  from $10.61 billion last year. The company cited sluggish housing construction and engine sales in North America, higher-than-expected operating costs and a planned reduction in inventories for the decline. Caterpillar earned $823 million, or $1.24 a share, in the three months ended June 30, down from $1.05 billion, or $1.52 a share, in the period last year, when the company posted its strongest earnings in at least four decades. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expected a profit of $1.49 a share on revenue of $11.12 billion. Alexander Blanton, an analyst with Ingalls &amp; Snyder, called the second-quarter earnings decline a blip, saying the company would continue to ride strong demand fueled by construction in China, India and other rapidly developing nations. This is a very strong trend, and its not going to go away, Mr. Blanton said. Its a factor of people in emerging countries wanting a better life, and they have to have infrastructure to do that. The company has projected full-year revenue of about $44 billion, up from $41.5 billion last year. Profit is forecast for $5.30 to $5.80 a share, up from $5.17 in 2006. Sales outside of North America are expected to be up 24 percent for the year, more than offsetting a projected 12 percent dip in North America, the company said.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/21/business/21markets.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Shares Off as Some Profits Disappoint<date>Published: July 21, 2007</date><text>Wall Street declined yesterday, retreating from record levels in response to disappointing results from Caterpillar and Google. The drop in stocks capped a losing week for the Dow Jones industrial average after three weeks of gains, and came a day after the blue chips closed above 14,000 for the first time. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index likewise logged a record close Thursday. Yesterdays retrenchment might not be surprising after weeks of somewhat volatile trading and the big gains Thursday. Still, a big factor was Caterpillar, which has been one of the best performers among the 30 stocks that make up the Dow and a big contributor to the march to 14,000. The company, which makes heavy equipment, unnerved investors when its results came in well below expectations. Jitters over subprime lending also weighed on the stock market, and led investors to buy Treasury bonds. The price of the benchmark 10-year note rose 16/32, to 96 17/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 4.95 percent from 5.02 percent Thursday. Technology shares took a hit after a strong run Thursday. Google turned in a second-quarter profit that fell short of expectations, while the earnings report from Microsoft was not impressive enough to alleviate investors concerns about the sector. As people start to absorb the numbers and start to see the second-quarter numbers arent as good as the first quarter, that starts to create some pullback a bit, said Nick Raich, director of research at the National City Private Client Group. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 149.33 points, or 1.07 percent, to 13,851.08. The index finished the week down 0.40 percent. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index declined 18.98 points, or 1.22 percent, to 1,534.10, and ended the week 1.19 percent lower. The Nasdaq composite index fell 32.44 points, or 1.19 percent, to 2,687.60, and finished down 0.72 percent for the week. Not only was Wall Street busy digesting the first sizable disappointments of the second-quarter earnings season, but investors also dealt with added volatility because of the expiration of four types of options contracts, an occurrence known as quadruple witching. The dollar was lower against most other major currencies. Gold prices rose. Light crude oil fell 35 cents, to $75.57 a barrel, on the New York Mercantile Exchange after trading above $76 a day earlier for the first time in 11 months. Looking past high oil prices, which can stoke inflation, stocks forged gains earlier this week in part on earnings news. Of the 130 companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 that have reported quarterly results, earnings growth has been 1 percent, Mr. Raich said. He noted companies were expected to show flat profits, so the results are better than expected. Still, he said, the margin by which companies are beating estimates in the second quarter is so far the lowest weve seen in five years. With some high expectations and some complacency in the market, the chances of a near-term pullback have gone up over the past month, he said, arguing that Wall Streets expectations for corporate profit growth are too high. Caterpillar cited lackluster sales in North American construction markets as well as a bigger-than-expected increase in operating costs for its earnings decline. The company, however, left its full-year profit forecast unchanged. Shares of Caterpillar fell $3.78, or 4.4 percent, to $83.20. Google dropped $28.47, or 5.2 percent, to $520.12, after its earnings before certain costs missed Wall Streets forecast. Still, the companys revenue rose 58 percent, to $3.87 billion. Investors also fretted as profit margins narrowed because the company spent to hire more workers and acquire content for its Web sites. Microsoft decreased 35 cents, to $31.16, as its earnings met expectations but failed to dazzle investors after several robust quarters that topped forecasts. While no major economic news was released yesterday, the president of the St. Louis Federal Reserve, William Poole, weighed in on the subprime mortgage market in a speech in St. Louis. He argued that Wall Street was right to punish shares of companies that made bad bets by offering loans to borrowers with spotty credit history. More Articles in Business »Wall Street declined yesterday, retreating from record levels in response to disappointing results from Caterpillar and Google. The drop in stocks capped a losing week for the Dow Jones industrial average after three weeks of gains, and came a day after the blue chips closed above 14,000 for the first time. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index likewise logged a record close Thursday. Yesterdays retrenchment might not be surprising after weeks of somewhat volatile trading and the big gains Thursday. Still, a big factor was Caterpillar, which has been one of the best performers among the 30 stocks that make up the Dow and a big contributor to the march to 14,000. The company, which makes heavy equipment, unnerved investors when its results came in well below expectations. Jitters over subprime lending also weighed on the stock market, and led investors to buy Treasury bonds. The price of the benchmark 10-year note rose 16/32, to 96 17/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 4.95 percent from 5.02 percent Thursday. Technology shares took a hit after a strong run Thursday. Google turned in a second-quarter profit that fell short of expectations, while the earnings report from Microsoft was not impressive enough to alleviate investors concerns about the sector. As people start to absorb the numbers and start to see the second-quarter numbers arent as good as the first quarter, that starts to create some pullback a bit, said Nick Raich, director of research at the National City Private Client Group. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 149.33 points, or 1.07 percent, to 13,851.08. The index finished the week down 0.40 percent. The Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index declined 18.98 points, or 1.22 percent, to 1,534.10, and ended the week 1.19 percent lower. The Nasdaq composite index fell 32.44 points, or 1.19 percent, to 2,687.60, and finished down 0.72 percent for the week. Not only was Wall Street busy digesting the first sizable disappointments of the second-quarter earnings season, but investors also dealt with added volatility because of the expiration of four types of options contracts, an occurrence known as quadruple witching. The dollar was lower against most other major currencies. Gold prices rose. Light crude oil fell 35 cents, to $75.57 a barrel, on the New York Mercantile Exchange after trading above $76 a day earlier for the first time in 11 months. Looking past high oil prices, which can stoke inflation, stocks forged gains earlier this week in part on earnings news. Of the 130 companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 that have reported quarterly results, earnings growth has been 1 percent, Mr. Raich said. He noted companies were expected to show flat profits, so the results are better than expected. Still, he said, the margin by which companies are beating estimates in the second quarter is so far the lowest weve seen in five years. With some high expectations and some complacency in the market, the chances of a near-term pullback have gone up over the past month, he said, arguing that Wall Streets expectations for corporate profit growth are too high. Caterpillar cited lackluster sales in North American construction markets as well as a bigger-than-expected increase in operating costs for its earnings decline. The company, however, left its full-year profit forecast unchanged. Shares of Caterpillar fell $3.78, or 4.4 percent, to $83.20. Google dropped $28.47, or 5.2 percent, to $520.12, after its earnings before certain costs missed Wall Streets forecast. Still, the companys revenue rose 58 percent, to $3.87 billion. Investors also fretted as profit margins narrowed because the company spent to hire more workers and acquire content for its Web sites. Microsoft decreased 35 cents, to $31.16, as its earnings met expectations but failed to dazzle investors after several robust quarters that topped forecasts. While no major economic news was released yesterday, the president of the St. Louis Federal Reserve, William Poole, weighed in on the subprime mortgage market in a speech in St. Louis. He argued that Wall Street was right to punish shares of companies that made bad bets by offering loans to borrowers with spotty credit history.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">Today In Business | Caterpillar Tops Forecasts<date>Published: April 21, 2007</date><text>Caterpillar posted better-than-expected profit despite a weak home building market and a decline in engine sales. Profit fell 3 percent, to $816 million from $840 million a year earlier. But strong overseas sales nearly offset expected declines in North America that Wall Street had predicted would cut more deeply into profit. Earnings per share increased to $1.23 from $1.20. Caterpillar said first-quarter revenue grew 7 percent, to more than $10 billion. Sales in North America fell by $996 million but overseas sales rose nearly $900 million.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/31/washington/31bush.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Bush Promotes His Free Trade Initiatives<date>Published: January 31, 2007</date><text>EAST PEORIA, Ill., Jan. 30  With Democrats making the case that his economic policies have benefited the rich more than the middle class, President Bush struck back on Tuesday, in the first of back-to-back speeches promoting what the White House characterizes as 41 consecutive months of economic growth. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Brendan Smialowski/Agence France-Presse  Getty Images President Bush drove a Caterpillar tractor a short distance during a plant tour in East Peoria, Ill. Mr. Bush came here to East Peoria, home to Caterpillar, the worlds biggest manufacturer of earth-moving equipment, to advance his free trade initiatives and press Democrats to make his tax cuts permanent. On Wednesday, he heads to New Yorks financial district to deliver a more formal State of the Economy address at Federal Hall, where he is expected to ask Congress to extend his authority to negotiate trade agreements that cannot be amended. The temptation is to say, well, trade may not be worth it, lets isolate ourselves, lets protect ourselves, Mr. Bush told a friendly audience of Caterpillar employees, standing against a backdrop of gigantic tractors in the companys familiar colors of yellow and black. He added, Its a bad mistake for the country to lose our confidence and not compete. The president was mostly preaching to the converted. Caterpillar was carefully chosen by the White House to put Mr. Bushs policies in the best possible light. The companys exports to Chile and Australia have shot up following free trade agreements negotiated by the Bush administration. And China, which negotiated a trade deal with President Bill Clinton, is now Caterpillars fifth-largest export market. Americans wonder, can you compete in a global economy? Mr. Bush said, before answering himself. My answer is, darn right, you can. With Mr. Bushs public approval ratings having crumbled, his domestic agenda faltering and his Iraq strategy running into a wall of opposition on Capitol Hill, White House advisers are hoping to capitalize on economic growth and low unemployment figures as a way to elevate public opinion of the president. Already, the polls show a fresh hint of optimism. A survey by the Pew Research Center found that while public approval of Mr. Bushs handling of the war had dropped nine points, to 23 percent from 32 percent, from August to December 2006, approval of his handling of the economy went up six points, to 39 percent from 33 percent. A recent Gallup Poll, meanwhile, found 65 percent of respondents predicted they would be better off a year from now than they were today. But Democrats, who won control of Congress in part by arguing that Mr. Bushs economic policies are giving short shrift to the middle class, do not intend to give up that ground without a fight. The presidents twin appearances this week are setting the stage for a battle between Mr. Bush and Congressional Democrats over the economy in general and trade in particular. Already, Democrats are signaling they will resist extending the presidents fast track trade negotiating authority, unless Mr. Bush couples the plan with proposals to demand tougher labor and environmental standards from the United States trading partners and help for American workers who are displaced by foreign competition. We dont want to abandon free trade, Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, said in an interview Tuesday, but hes got to offer more protections and cushions for people who are caught in its maw through no fault of their own. On Wednesday, while Mr. Bush is delivering his speech in Manhattan, a House-Senate committee will hold a hearing on the economy, led by Mr. Schumer, who has just published a book outlining how Democrats can hold power by reclaiming their status as the party of the middle class. The chief Democratic witnesses are Robert E. Rubin and Lawrence H. Summers, both former treasury secretaries under President Bill Clinton. When the average middle class voter hears the president speak, he or she thinks, The guy doesnt know what Im going through, its not terrible, but its not so rosy either,  Mr. Schumer said, adding that the hearing is intended to be an answer to the president. In East Peoria on Tuesday, there was a preview of this same political clash. At Caterpillar, with Representative Ray LaHood, a Republican, in tow, Mr. Bush found what a pool report described as his inner boy when he drove one of the giant tractors for about 20 feet. I would suggest moving back, Mr. Bush announced as he climbed into the tractor cab. Im about to crank this sucker up. And then he did, later pronouncing it a cool experience. While the president was busy driving, the freshman Democrat who represents the district next door was busy issuing a press release arguing that Mr. Bush was ignoring the financial condition of his constituents. The congressman, Representative Phil Hare, who worked as an aide to his predecessor before winning election in November, pointed to another Illinois community, Galesburg, where he said free trade treaties drove 1,600 good-paying Maytag jobs to Sonora, Mexico. More Articles in Washington »EAST PEORIA, Ill., Jan. 30  With Democrats making the case that his economic policies have benefited the rich more than the middle class, President Bush struck back on Tuesday, in the first of back-to-back speeches promoting what the White House characterizes as 41 consecutive months of economic growth. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Brendan Smialowski/Agence France-Presse  Getty Images President Bush drove a Caterpillar tractor a short distance during a plant tour in East Peoria, Ill. Mr. Bush came here to East Peoria, home to Caterpillar, the worlds biggest manufacturer of earth-moving equipment, to advance his free trade initiatives and press Democrats to make his tax cuts permanent. On Wednesday, he heads to New Yorks financial district to deliver a more formal State of the Economy address at Federal Hall, where he is expected to ask Congress to extend his authority to negotiate trade agreements that cannot be amended. The temptation is to say, well, trade may not be worth it, lets isolate ourselves, lets protect ourselves, Mr. Bush told a friendly audience of Caterpillar employees, standing against a backdrop of gigantic tractors in the companys familiar colors of yellow and black. He added, Its a bad mistake for the country to lose our confidence and not compete. The president was mostly preaching to the converted. Caterpillar was carefully chosen by the White House to put Mr. Bushs policies in the best possible light. The companys exports to Chile and Australia have shot up following free trade agreements negotiated by the Bush administration. And China, which negotiated a trade deal with President Bill Clinton, is now Caterpillars fifth-largest export market. Americans wonder, can you compete in a global economy? Mr. Bush said, before answering himself. My answer is, darn right, you can. With Mr. Bushs public approval ratings having crumbled, his domestic agenda faltering and his Iraq strategy running into a wall of opposition on Capitol Hill, White House advisers are hoping to capitalize on economic growth and low unemployment figures as a way to elevate public opinion of the president. Already, the polls show a fresh hint of optimism. A survey by the Pew Research Center found that while public approval of Mr. Bushs handling of the war had dropped nine points, to 23 percent from 32 percent, from August to December 2006, approval of his handling of the economy went up six points, to 39 percent from 33 percent. A recent Gallup Poll, meanwhile, found 65 percent of respondents predicted they would be better off a year from now than they were today. But Democrats, who won control of Congress in part by arguing that Mr. Bushs economic policies are giving short shrift to the middle class, do not intend to give up that ground without a fight. The presidents twin appearances this week are setting the stage for a battle between Mr. Bush and Congressional Democrats over the economy in general and trade in particular. Already, Democrats are signaling they will resist extending the presidents fast track trade negotiating authority, unless Mr. Bush couples the plan with proposals to demand tougher labor and environmental standards from the United States trading partners and help for American workers who are displaced by foreign competition. We dont want to abandon free trade, Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, said in an interview Tuesday, but hes got to offer more protections and cushions for people who are caught in its maw through no fault of their own. On Wednesday, while Mr. Bush is delivering his speech in Manhattan, a House-Senate committee will hold a hearing on the economy, led by Mr. Schumer, who has just published a book outlining how Democrats can hold power by reclaiming their status as the party of the middle class. The chief Democratic witnesses are Robert E. Rubin and Lawrence H. Summers, both former treasury secretaries under President Bill Clinton. When the average middle class voter hears the president speak, he or she thinks, The guy doesnt know what Im going through, its not terrible, but its not so rosy either,  Mr. Schumer said, adding that the hearing is intended to be an answer to the president. In East Peoria on Tuesday, there was a preview of this same political clash. At Caterpillar, with Representative Ray LaHood, a Republican, in tow, Mr. Bush found what a pool report described as his inner boy when he drove one of the giant tractors for about 20 feet. I would suggest moving back, Mr. Bush announced as he climbed into the tractor cab. Im about to crank this sucker up. And then he did, later pronouncing it a cool experience. While the president was busy driving, the freshman Democrat who represents the district next door was busy issuing a press release arguing that Mr. Bush was ignoring the financial condition of his constituents. The congressman, Representative Phil Hare, who worked as an aide to his predecessor before winning election in November, pointed to another Illinois community, Galesburg, where he said free trade treaties drove 1,600 good-paying Maytag jobs to Sonora, Mexico.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED9173FF934A15752C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">TODAY IN BUSINESS | CATERPILLAR FORECAST<date>Published: January 27, 2007</date><text>The heavy equipment maker Caterpillar said that higher operating costs trimmed fourth-quarter profit growth to 4 percent, but predicted strong results for 2007 despite an expected slowdown in machine and engine sales in the United States. Net income for the fourth quarter rose to $882 million, or $1.32 a share, up from $846 million, or $1.20 a share, a year earlier. But earnings fell short of the $1.34 expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial as higher production costs offset strong sales. Revenue for the quarter rose 14 percent, to $11 billion from $9.7 billion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/06/business/06offline.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Who Is Best at R&amp;D?<date>Published: January 6, 2007</date><text>TODAYS quiz: What do Apple, Caterpillar, Google, Kellogg and Toyota have in common? Skip to next paragraph Answer: They are among the smartest companies when it comes to what they reap for their research and development dollars. That was the conclusion of three Booz Allen Hamilton consultants  Barry Jaruzelski, Kevin Dehoff and Rakesh Bordia  after they reviewed the performances of the 1,000 publicly held companies worldwide that spent the most on R&amp;D in 2005. They published the results in Strategy and Business. Over all, companies are becoming better at R&amp;D, considering that spending increased $20 billion and revenue climbed even more. But the consultants classified only 94 concerns, including the 5 mentioned above, as high-leverage innovators. Those companies did better than their peers in seven performance measures, including sales growth, operating-income growth and total shareholder returns, over a five-year period, while spending less on R&amp;D as a percentage of sales than their industry medians over the same five-year period. While the best companies took different routes to maximizing R&amp;D spending, the consultants said, one thing they shared was building multifunctional, companywide capabilities that can provide them with sustainable competitive advantage. This is the second year Booz Allen has conducted the study. Analysis of the 2005 Global Innovation 1,000 confirms the major finding from our initial study last year, the authors wrote. Money simply cannot buy effective innovation. In other words, spending a lot does not help you. Spending intelligently does. NEW TECH With breakthroughs seemingly coming every day, it is hard to keep up with all the developments in technology, even for those who earn a living with it. To make your life easier, Alex Hutchinson in Popular Mechanics has created a cheat sheet titled 10 Tech Concepts You Need to Know for 2007. Among them: ¶PRAM. Phase-change random access memory is set to overtake flash memory in consumer electronics, the magazine contends, pointing out that it is 30 times as fast as flash memory with more than 10 times the life span. ¶VoN. The first Video on the Net conference was in 1998, but the concept of watching videos on your PC is only now reaching maturity. Apple is expected to introduce an iTV video-streaming box later this year. ¶Smart pills. When swallowed, these vitamin-size sensors will transmit data about pressure, acidity and temperature to a 5-by-4-inch receiver that patients carry around with them during the pills trip through their gastrointestinal tract. ¶Data Clouds. The term given to the ability to gain access to every one of your files, from skimpy documents to gigabyte-hogging music, from any Internet connection. Versions of data clouds are available and the magazine expects the phenomenon will be widespread relatively soon. HAPPY NEW YEAR It looks as if it will be a good year  at least in the market for yachts and business aircraft. ShowBoats International reports the 2007 Global Order Book for luxury yachts shows a total of 777 yachts 90 feet and larger under contract, totaling 94,404 linear feet. This represents a 15.3 percent increase in footage from 2006. Things are equally good for the makers of business aircraft. Reporting on a survey conducted by Honeywell of 1,400 flight departments, aircraft manufacturers and other sources, Flying writes record worldwide deliveries are projected for 2006 and 2007, and the bull market for business jets is going to keep rolling along. During the survey period, 2006 to 2016, Honeywell expects some 12,000 aircraft worth $195 billion to be added. FINAL TAKE If six days into the new year you have already given up on that resolution to lose weight, here is something to ponder, courtesy of Mikhail Sedov in Fortune Small Business. Vacuuming fat from more than 455,000 patients  and some $1.2 billion out of their wallets  made liposuction the No. 1 cosmetic-surgery procedure in the U.S. in 2005. That is certainly one way to meet your goal. PAUL B. BROWN More Articles in Business »TODAYS quiz: What do Apple, Caterpillar, Google, Kellogg and Toyota have in common? Skip to next paragraph Answer: They are among the smartest companies when it comes to what they reap for their research and development dollars. That was the conclusion of three Booz Allen Hamilton consultants  Barry Jaruzelski, Kevin Dehoff and Rakesh Bordia  after they reviewed the performances of the 1,000 publicly held companies worldwide that spent the most on R&amp;D in 2005. They published the results in Strategy and Business. Over all, companies are becoming better at R&amp;D, considering that spending increased $20 billion and revenue climbed even more. But the consultants classified only 94 concerns, including the 5 mentioned above, as high-leverage innovators. Those companies did better than their peers in seven performance measures, including sales growth, operating-income growth and total shareholder returns, over a five-year period, while spending less on R&amp;D as a percentage of sales than their industry medians over the same five-year period. While the best companies took different routes to maximizing R&amp;D spending, the consultants said, one thing they shared was building multifunctional, companywide capabilities that can provide them with sustainable competitive advantage. This is the second year Booz Allen has conducted the study. Analysis of the 2005 Global Innovation 1,000 confirms the major finding from our initial study last year, the authors wrote. Money simply cannot buy effective innovation. In other words, spending a lot does not help you. Spending intelligently does. NEW TECH With breakthroughs seemingly coming every day, it is hard to keep up with all the developments in technology, even for those who earn a living with it. To make your life easier, Alex Hutchinson in Popular Mechanics has created a cheat sheet titled 10 Tech Concepts You Need to Know for 2007. Among them: ¶PRAM. Phase-change random access memory is set to overtake flash memory in consumer electronics, the magazine contends, pointing out that it is 30 times as fast as flash memory with more than 10 times the life span. ¶VoN. The first Video on the Net conference was in 1998, but the concept of watching videos on your PC is only now reaching maturity. Apple is expected to introduce an iTV video-streaming box later this year. ¶Smart pills. When swallowed, these vitamin-size sensors will transmit data about pressure, acidity and temperature to a 5-by-4-inch receiver that patients carry around with them during the pills trip through their gastrointestinal tract. ¶Data Clouds. The term given to the ability to gain access to every one of your files, from skimpy documents to gigabyte-hogging music, from any Internet connection. Versions of data clouds are available and the magazine expects the phenomenon will be widespread relatively soon. HAPPY NEW YEAR It looks as if it will be a good year  at least in the market for yachts and business aircraft. ShowBoats International reports the 2007 Global Order Book for luxury yachts shows a total of 777 yachts 90 feet and larger under contract, totaling 94,404 linear feet. This represents a 15.3 percent increase in footage from 2006. Things are equally good for the makers of business aircraft. Reporting on a survey conducted by Honeywell of 1,400 flight departments, aircraft manufacturers and other sources, Flying writes record worldwide deliveries are projected for 2006 and 2007, and the bull market for business jets is going to keep rolling along. During the survey period, 2006 to 2016, Honeywell expects some 12,000 aircraft worth $195 billion to be added. FINAL TAKE If six days into the new year you have already given up on that resolution to lose weight, here is something to ponder, courtesy of Mikhail Sedov in Fortune Small Business. Vacuuming fat from more than 455,000 patients  and some $1.2 billion out of their wallets  made liposuction the No. 1 cosmetic-surgery procedure in the U.S. in 2005. That is certainly one way to meet your goal. PAUL B. BROWN</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/21/business/21caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Earnings Rise at Caterpillar, Yet Shares Fall<date>Published: October 21, 2006</date><text>PEORIA, Ill., Oct. 20 (AP)  Caterpillar said Friday that its third-quarter profit rose 15 percent. But after reducing its forecasts, shares fell 14.5 percent. The company lowered its full-year earnings forecast, citing high operating costs and lower-than-expected sales, and said it expected a slowdown next year as well when new diesel engine emissions regulations take effect. The company also cautioned that the weak residential housing market in the United States and a decline in sales of truck engines would restrain revenue growth next year. During a conference call with analysts, Caterpillar officials called next years slowdown a pause, not the end of a sales surge that has doubled the companys annual revenue since 2002. Energy exploration, mining and infrastructure improvements remain strong worldwide and will continue to generate demand for the companys earth-moving machines, the officials said. For the third quarter, net income grew to $769 million, or $1.14 a share, from $667 million, or 94 cents a share, a year earlier. The latest period included about $80 million in legal expenses, most to settle a dispute with the truck and engine maker Navistar International over licensing and supply agreements. Sales rose 17 percent, to $10.52 billion from $8.98 billion a year earlier, helped by higher prices and increased volumes for both machines and engines. Favorable foreign currency exchange rates increased revenue by $97 million. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, fell $10.02, to $59 a share. The company said it expected full-year revenue of about $41 billion, up about 13 percent from 2005. Caterpillar forecasts profit of $5.05 to $5.30 a share for 2006, with growth coming from higher prices and sales volume. The forecast is down from Caterpillars earlier estimate for earnings of $5.25 to $5.50, on sales and revenue that had been expected to rise 12 to 15 percent. The company attributed the shortfall to increased operating costs, including the third-quarter legal expenses, as well as slightly lower-than-expected sales volumes. More Articles in Business »PEORIA, Ill., Oct. 20 (AP)  Caterpillar said Friday that its third-quarter profit rose 15 percent. But after reducing its forecasts, shares fell 14.5 percent. The company lowered its full-year earnings forecast, citing high operating costs and lower-than-expected sales, and said it expected a slowdown next year as well when new diesel engine emissions regulations take effect. The company also cautioned that the weak residential housing market in the United States and a decline in sales of truck engines would restrain revenue growth next year. During a conference call with analysts, Caterpillar officials called next years slowdown a pause, not the end of a sales surge that has doubled the companys annual revenue since 2002. Energy exploration, mining and infrastructure improvements remain strong worldwide and will continue to generate demand for the companys earth-moving machines, the officials said. For the third quarter, net income grew to $769 million, or $1.14 a share, from $667 million, or 94 cents a share, a year earlier. The latest period included about $80 million in legal expenses, most to settle a dispute with the truck and engine maker Navistar International over licensing and supply agreements. Sales rose 17 percent, to $10.52 billion from $8.98 billion a year earlier, helped by higher prices and increased volumes for both machines and engines. Favorable foreign currency exchange rates increased revenue by $97 million. Stock in Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, fell $10.02, to $59 a share. The company said it expected full-year revenue of about $41 billion, up about 13 percent from 2005. Caterpillar forecasts profit of $5.05 to $5.30 a share for 2006, with growth coming from higher prices and sales volume. The forecast is down from Caterpillars earlier estimate for earnings of $5.25 to $5.50, on sales and revenue that had been expected to rise 12 to 15 percent. The company attributed the shortfall to increased operating costs, including the third-quarter legal expenses, as well as slightly lower-than-expected sales volumes.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/25/business/25fobriefs-003.html?ref=caterpillarinc">China: Caterpillar to Start Building Factory in 2007<date>Published: July 25, 2006</date><text>The heavy machinery maker Caterpillar said it planned to build a factory in Jiangsu Province that would make midsize wheel loaders. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., said construction of the new plant was expected to begin in 2007. The loaders it produces will be sold across the Asia-Pacific region. That region is now largely supplied by a plant in Japan. More Articles in Business »The heavy machinery maker Caterpillar said it planned to build a factory in Jiangsu Province that would make midsize wheel loaders. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., said construction of the new plant was expected to begin in 2007. The loaders it produces will be sold across the Asia-Pacific region. That region is now largely supplied by a plant in Japan.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/22/business/22caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Reports 38% Increase in Earnings<date>Published: July 22, 2006</date><text>PEORIA, Ill., July 21 (AP)  Caterpillar, the construction equipment maker, said Friday that its second-quarter earnings rose 38 percent, reflecting its strongest financial performance in at least four decades. Caterpillar said higher prices helped sales top $10 billion for the quarter and it raised guidance for the full year, citing strong demand from nonresidential and highway construction markets. A slowdown in the housing industry in the United States affected results, but the impact was more than offset by sales in other industries, including mining, energy and infrastructure development. The chief executive, James W. Owens, told analysts that it was the best quarter in the company’s history and concluded Caterpillar’s most profitable first half since 1966, reflecting continuing strong fundamentals in those industries. Net income rose to $1.05 billion, or $1.52 a share, from $760 million, or $1.08 a share, in the second quarter of 2005. That was 10 cents higher than the average estimate of 12 analysts polled by Thomson Financial. Sales rose 13 percent to $10.61 billion from $9.36 billion last year, beating the Wall Street estimate of $9.96 billion. Sales of machinery rose 14 percent to $6.88 billion, while engine sales added 12 percent to $3.08 billion. Caterpillar said it expected to earn $5.25 to $5.50 a share in 2006 on sales growth of 12 percent to 15 percent, which translates into revenue of $38.09 billion to $39.11 billion. The previous outlook called for earnings of $4.85 to $5.20 a share on a 10 percent sales gain. Wall Street had been looking for full-year profit of $5.33 a share and sales of $38.84 billion. An analyst at Citigroup, David Raso, said Caterpillar’s increased diversification had made its earnings more stable and results less vulnerable to cyclical trends in heavy construction equipment and mining. The biggest risks, he said, were a bigger-than-expected decline in United States housing and any sharp drops in commodities like copper and gold. Shares of Caterpillar fell 73 cents, to $68.35. More Articles in Business »PEORIA, Ill., July 21 (AP)  Caterpillar, the construction equipment maker, said Friday that its second-quarter earnings rose 38 percent, reflecting its strongest financial performance in at least four decades. Caterpillar said higher prices helped sales top $10 billion for the quarter and it raised guidance for the full year, citing strong demand from nonresidential and highway construction markets. A slowdown in the housing industry in the United States affected results, but the impact was more than offset by sales in other industries, including mining, energy and infrastructure development. The chief executive, James W. Owens, told analysts that it was the best quarter in the company’s history and concluded Caterpillar’s most profitable first half since 1966, reflecting continuing strong fundamentals in those industries. Net income rose to $1.05 billion, or $1.52 a share, from $760 million, or $1.08 a share, in the second quarter of 2005. That was 10 cents higher than the average estimate of 12 analysts polled by Thomson Financial. Sales rose 13 percent to $10.61 billion from $9.36 billion last year, beating the Wall Street estimate of $9.96 billion. Sales of machinery rose 14 percent to $6.88 billion, while engine sales added 12 percent to $3.08 billion. Caterpillar said it expected to earn $5.25 to $5.50 a share in 2006 on sales growth of 12 percent to 15 percent, which translates into revenue of $38.09 billion to $39.11 billion. The previous outlook called for earnings of $4.85 to $5.20 a share on a 10 percent sales gain. Wall Street had been looking for full-year profit of $5.33 a share and sales of $38.84 billion. An analyst at Citigroup, David Raso, said Caterpillar’s increased diversification had made its earnings more stable and results less vulnerable to cyclical trends in heavy construction equipment and mining. The biggest risks, he said, were a bigger-than-expected decline in United States housing and any sharp drops in commodities like copper and gold. Shares of Caterpillar fell 73 cents, to $68.35.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/17/business/17caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar to Buy Supplier<date>Published: May 17, 2006</date><text>By Dow Jones/AP Caterpillar, the machinery and engine manufacturer, said yesterday that it would acquire the privately held railroad industry supplier Progress Rail Services Corporation in an $800 million cash-and-stock deal. The total deal is valued at about $1 billion. Caterpillar will assume $200 million in debt; the $800 million will be 53 percent in cash and 47 percent in stock. The company said the purchase was intended to expand its services portfolio. Progress Rail of Albertville, Ala., provides railroads with maintenance and repair services for locomotives. More Articles in Business »By Dow Jones/AP Caterpillar, the machinery and engine manufacturer, said yesterday that it would acquire the privately held railroad industry supplier Progress Rail Services Corporation in an $800 million cash-and-stock deal. The total deal is valued at about $1 billion. Caterpillar will assume $200 million in debt; the $800 million will be 53 percent in cash and 47 percent in stock. The company said the purchase was intended to expand its services portfolio. Progress Rail of Albertville, Ala., provides railroads with maintenance and repair services for locomotives.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/25/business/25caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Quarterly Net Increases 45% At Caterpillar<date>Published: April 25, 2006</date><text>CHICAGO, April 24 (Reuters)  Caterpillar reported higher-than-expected quarterly earnings on Monday and raised its full-year forecast as strong demand for commodities increased sales of its equipment. The company, a maker of earth-moving equipment, diesel engines and gas turbines, has enjoyed a string of strong quarters because of a recovery in the industrial markets, a robust global construction market and high commodity prices, which have prompted mining companies worldwide to step up production. "The company is at the right place at the right time," said Eli Lustgarten, an analyst at Longbow Research. But that performance, which has driven its shares up 75 percent over the last year and permitted Caterpillar to easily outperform its blue-chip peers, has also left some analysts wondering how much upside is left in its cyclical stock. "It's a great company, and it's doing well," said Scott Burns, a Morningstar analyst who has a $66 price target on Caterpillar. "But it looks a little pricey now. It's priced for perfection." Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., said first-quarter profit rose 45 percent, to $840 million, from $581 million a year earlier. Earnings per share increased to $1.20, from 81 cents. Sales rose 13 percent, to $9.39 billion. Analysts, on average, had expected Caterpillar to report earnings of $1.06 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Comments like his appeared to short-circuit a rally that Caterpillar shares enjoyed immediately after the results were announced. After rising as much as 2 percent earlier in the session, they fell 49 cents, to $77.38. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO, April 24 (Reuters)  Caterpillar reported higher-than-expected quarterly earnings on Monday and raised its full-year forecast as strong demand for commodities increased sales of its equipment. The company, a maker of earth-moving equipment, diesel engines and gas turbines, has enjoyed a string of strong quarters because of a recovery in the industrial markets, a robust global construction market and high commodity prices, which have prompted mining companies worldwide to step up production. "The company is at the right place at the right time," said Eli Lustgarten, an analyst at Longbow Research. But that performance, which has driven its shares up 75 percent over the last year and permitted Caterpillar to easily outperform its blue-chip peers, has also left some analysts wondering how much upside is left in its cyclical stock. "It's a great company, and it's doing well," said Scott Burns, a Morningstar analyst who has a $66 price target on Caterpillar. "But it looks a little pricey now. It's priced for perfection." Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., said first-quarter profit rose 45 percent, to $840 million, from $581 million a year earlier. Earnings per share increased to $1.20, from 81 cents. Sales rose 13 percent, to $9.39 billion. Analysts, on average, had expected Caterpillar to report earnings of $1.06 a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Comments like his appeared to short-circuit a rally that Caterpillar shares enjoyed immediately after the results were announced. After rising as much as 2 percent earlier in the session, they fell 49 cents, to $77.38.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/26/business/yourmoney/26wages.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Two Tiers, Slipping Into One<date>Published: February 26, 2006</date><text>PEORIA, Ill. Skip to next paragraph REWRITING THE SOCIAL CONTRACT Barries to Middle-Class Pay Articles in this series will periodically examine the challenges for business, government and society as corporate support for health care, pensions and other social benefits has eroded under economic pressures. For previous articles in the series go here. Kristen Schmid for The New York Times Jim Owens, the chief executive of Caterpillar, says that lowering wages has allowed the company to add jobs. R ICK DOTY is a 30-year veteran of Caterpillar, the big tractor and earth-moving equipment manufacturer. He is paid $23.51 an hour as a machinist, and he receives additional benefits worth almost as much. That sets him far above newly hired workers consigned to a much lower wage scale. To these fellow workers, Mr. Doty, who is also a local union leader, struggles to justify an inequality that he helped to negotiate. "I remind them they are making more now than they were before they came to Cat," said Mr. Doty, who spends part of his day at the one-story union hall of United Automobile Workers Local 974 arguing that $12 to $13 an hour is good pay here. "And I assure them that five years down the road, when the present contract expires, we in the union are going to improve their lot in life." That does not seem likely. After more than a decade of failed strikes and job actions  mainly in Illinois, where Caterpillar has its biggest factories  the U.A.W. reluctantly accepted a two-tier contract that provides for significantly lower wages and benefits for newly hired employees. The new second tier is as much as $20 an hour below the cost of employing Mr. Doty, 50, and a dwindling band of other veterans. As older workers depart, at Caterpillar and at other companies, the longstanding wage advantage that manufacturing workers enjoy over their counterparts in services or construction is shrinking fast. The trade-off is the promise of a manufacturing revival at long last in the old Rust Belt, as new hires come aboard at much lower labor costs. "What we've done is reposition ourselves to actually grow employment in our Midwestern plants," said Jim Owens, Caterpillar's chief executive. "We finally have a labor cost that is viable." Caterpillar is adding a significant chapter to the labor cost-cutting that is widespread in America, particularly at old-line manufacturing companies. Until recently, cutbacks in the wages and benefits of hourly workers were limited mostly to money-losing companies: failing steel mills, for example, and struggling airlines. They have said that their survival was at stake. Now, however, even healthy and highly profitable companies like Caterpillar are engaging in the practice, and as they do so, the longstanding presumption that factory workers at successful companies can achieve a secure, relatively prosperous middle-class life for themselves and their families is evaporating. "Caterpillar is a powerful symbol of this process," said Harley Shaiken, a labor economist at the University of California, Berkeley. "It dominates its field. It is one of America's largest exporters, and it is very profitable. If there ever was a company that could bring back the social contract of the mid-20th century, it is Caterpillar. But it chooses not to." AS Caterpillar's managers see it, they have no choice. "There is a balance that must be struck between being competitive and being middle class," said Douglas R. Oberhelman, a group president. Although Caterpillar's factories are among the most productive in the world, the managers argue that the company cannot afford to be more generous simply because it is doing well right now. "You could say that in good times you could afford a different kind of package and in bad times you couldn't," said Christopher E. Glynn, the director of corporate labor relations. "The real question is: What's competitive? And our target is competitiveness." The new contract reflects the company's success in imposing a "market competitive" pay scale; that is, wages and benefits that attract enough qualified workers by being slightly better than the packages offered by others in each community or region where Caterpillar has operations. In the Midwest market, the competitive wage-and-benefit package is about $23 an hour, on average, Mr. Glynn says. Caterpillar's package for new hires in the U.A.W. contract ratified 13 months ago is pegged above that, at $28 an hour, which includes about $9 an hour in benefits. Only the most skilled workers in the new lower tier  electricians and machinists, for example  make more than $20 an hour, or $41,000 a year, while in the gradually expiring upper tier, everyone does, even unskilled laborers and shop helpers. 1 2 3Next Page &gt; More Articles in Business &gt;PEORIA, Ill. Skip to next paragraph REWRITING THE SOCIAL CONTRACT Barries to Middle-Class Pay Articles in this series will periodically examine the challenges for business, government and society as corporate support for health care, pensions and other social benefits has eroded under economic pressures. For previous articles in the series go here. Kristen Schmid for The New York Times Jim Owens, the chief executive of Caterpillar, says that lowering wages has allowed the company to add jobs. R ICK DOTY is a 30-year veteran of Caterpillar, the big tractor and earth-moving equipment manufacturer. He is paid $23.51 an hour as a machinist, and he receives additional benefits worth almost as much. That sets him far above newly hired workers consigned to a much lower wage scale. To these fellow workers, Mr. Doty, who is also a local union leader, struggles to justify an inequality that he helped to negotiate. "I remind them they are making more now than they were before they came to Cat," said Mr. Doty, who spends part of his day at the one-story union hall of United Automobile Workers Local 974 arguing that $12 to $13 an hour is good pay here. "And I assure them that five years down the road, when the present contract expires, we in the union are going to improve their lot in life." That does not seem likely. After more than a decade of failed strikes and job actions  mainly in Illinois, where Caterpillar has its biggest factories  the U.A.W. reluctantly accepted a two-tier contract that provides for significantly lower wages and benefits for newly hired employees. The new second tier is as much as $20 an hour below the cost of employing Mr. Doty, 50, and a dwindling band of other veterans. As older workers depart, at Caterpillar and at other companies, the longstanding wage advantage that manufacturing workers enjoy over their counterparts in services or construction is shrinking fast. The trade-off is the promise of a manufacturing revival at long last in the old Rust Belt, as new hires come aboard at much lower labor costs. "What we've done is reposition ourselves to actually grow employment in our Midwestern plants," said Jim Owens, Caterpillar's chief executive. "We finally have a labor cost that is viable." Caterpillar is adding a significant chapter to the labor cost-cutting that is widespread in America, particularly at old-line manufacturing companies. Until recently, cutbacks in the wages and benefits of hourly workers were limited mostly to money-losing companies: failing steel mills, for example, and struggling airlines. They have said that their survival was at stake. Now, however, even healthy and highly profitable companies like Caterpillar are engaging in the practice, and as they do so, the longstanding presumption that factory workers at successful companies can achieve a secure, relatively prosperous middle-class life for themselves and their families is evaporating. "Caterpillar is a powerful symbol of this process," said Harley Shaiken, a labor economist at the University of California, Berkeley. "It dominates its field. It is one of America's largest exporters, and it is very profitable. If there ever was a company that could bring back the social contract of the mid-20th century, it is Caterpillar. But it chooses not to." AS Caterpillar's managers see it, they have no choice. "There is a balance that must be struck between being competitive and being middle class," said Douglas R. Oberhelman, a group president. Although Caterpillar's factories are among the most productive in the world, the managers argue that the company cannot afford to be more generous simply because it is doing well right now. "You could say that in good times you could afford a different kind of package and in bad times you couldn't," said Christopher E. Glynn, the director of corporate labor relations. "The real question is: What's competitive? And our target is competitiveness." The new contract reflects the company's success in imposing a "market competitive" pay scale; that is, wages and benefits that attract enough qualified workers by being slightly better than the packages offered by others in each community or region where Caterpillar has operations. In the Midwest market, the competitive wage-and-benefit package is about $23 an hour, on average, Mr. Glynn says. Caterpillar's package for new hires in the U.A.W. contract ratified 13 months ago is pegged above that, at $28 an hour, which includes about $9 an hour in benefits. Only the most skilled workers in the new lower tier  electricians and machinists, for example  make more than $20 an hour, or $41,000 a year, while in the gradually expiring upper tier, everyone does, even unskilled laborers and shop helpers. 1 2 3Next Page &gt;</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/21/business/businessspecial3/21caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Raises '05 Forecast as Sales Gain<date>Published: April 21, 2005</date><text>y Reuters Caterpillar reported stronger-than-expected quarterly profit yesterday and raised its earnings forecast for the year, citing demand for its mining, energy and construction equipment. Caterpillar said that strong sales volume and price increases more than made up for higher steel and other raw material costs. Advertisement "It looks like they're really gaining some traction in their battle against rising raw material costs and that's dropping to the bottom line," Scott Burns, an analyst with Morningstar, said. "It's pretty astonishing, the volumes are up just about everywhere." Net income rose to $581 million, or $1.63 a share. Caterpillar had earned $420 million, or $1.19 a share, in the same period a year earlier. Sales and revenue increased 29 percent, to $8.34 billion, from $6.48 billion a year earlier, exceeding analysts' estimates. Caterpillar's machinery and engine businesses each recorded strong gains in the first quarter, with most of the increases in North America, Europe, Africa, the Middle East and Russia. Machinery sales rose 30 percent, to $5.40 billion. North American machinery sales increased 28 percent; sales in Europe, Africa, Middle East and Russia grew 41 percent; and sales in Latin America were up 49 percent. Sales of machinery in the Asia-Pacific market rose 11 percent, Caterpillar said, as lower sales in China were largely offset by increases in Australia and Indonesia. Sales and revenue for 2005 should rise 16 percent to 18 percent, up from its previous estimate of 12 percent to 15 percent, the company said. Caterpillar now expects full-year profit per share to rise 35 percent to 40 percent. It had said in January that it expected profit per share to be up about 25 percent. Caterpillar said that its material costs for the year should be slightly higher than originally expected, although the rate of increase had begun to slow. It does not expect a decline in steel prices until at least the second half of this year. Shares of Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., rose $3.09, or 3.6 percent, to $88.04 on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/08/business/worldbusiness/08tax.html?ref=caterpillarinc">European Tax Opinion Could Mean Huge Refunds<date>Published: April 8, 2005</date><text>RUSSELS, April 7 - A member of Europe's highest court offered a preliminary opinion Thursday that could lead to billions of euros in tax refunds to companies at a time when many European governments can least afford them. On Thursday, Miguel Poiares Maduro, an advocate general on the European Court of Justice, said that British tax authorities erred in denying the retail chain Marks &amp; Spencer the right to offset losses incurred in other European Union countries in its British tax filing. If the judge's opinion is upheld, as often occurs, governments throughout Europe might face a threat to their already hard-pressed budgets. That possibility prompted Germany and six other countries to intervene in support of the British government at a court hearing last year. Their efforts apparently had little effect. "The advocate general rejects the German government's argument that the taking into account of foreign losses by the state concerned could not be permitted because it would lead to a reduction in tax revenue, and thus to major budgetary difficulties for the member state concerned," the court said in a statement Thursday. Marks &amp; Spencer has been seeking a tax refund of more than £30 million ($56.4 million), since 2001 from Inland Revenue, the British tax agency, to compensate it for losses in Belgium, Germany and France that it was not able to claim in those countries. Marks &amp; Spencer incurred the losses during a doomed foray into Continental Europe in the late 1990's. Adam Craig, head of the European tax practice of Deloitte Touche, commented, "Britain could face a bill of up to £1 billion." Sixty other companies have filed claims similar to Marks &amp; Spencer's in the British courts, and Thursday's opinion could become legal precedent for them. Those companies include British Telecom; the British subsidiary of BNP Paribas; and three American companies with large operations in Britain, the H. J. Heinz food company, PepsiCo and the construction equipment maker Caterpillar. "There are hundreds of others that have made similar claims in their tax returns," Mr. Craig noted. Analysts said Germany in particular had good reason to be worried about the Marks &amp; Spencer case. "If the final ruling permits retroactive claims, then the German government could face a bill of 30 billion euros," said Isabelle Kronawitter, an economist with the German bank HVB. That, she said, was her estimate of losses at German subsidiaries in other countries in the European Union from 1998 to 2002. The issue of retroactivity, however, has not yet been decided. The court will ultimately rule on whether companies are allowed to claim past losses, which will determine the impact on national treasuries across Europe. "It's 50-50," Ms. Kronawitter said of chances for retroactivity, adding that the court may decide not to allow it so that member states could have time to adjust their tax laws. Mr. Craig, however, felt sure the ruling would allow retroactive claims. "It would be surprising if the companies that have already made claims are unable to get their money back," he said. Mr. Maduro, the judge, stressed that a company should not be able to get a double tax advantage by registering the loss both at home and in the country where the losses occurred.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/13/business/yourmoney/13refresh.html?ref=caterpillarinc">An Optimist Keeps Active<date>Published: March 13, 2005</date><text>ne definition of an optimist would be someone who helps to manage a foundation working for global peace and predicts that the Chicago Cubs this year will win their first World Series since 1908. That someone would be Donald V. Fites, who ran Caterpillar Inc., the huge maker of earth-moving equipment, from 1990 to 1999. "As a C.E.O. you learn to view the glass as half full," he said. "You have to do that when some other people might just give up." Of course, the booming 90's economy gave Mr. Fites good reason for a sunny outlook. The annual revenue of Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., roughly doubled, to $20 billion, during that decade. Now, six years into retirement, Mr. Fites, 71, says he is trying to strike a balance between work and play. "I want to stay involved, and I am," he said. Mr. Fites, who earned an undergraduate degree in civil engineering at Valparaiso University and a master's degree from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, serves on the boards of five companies: AK Steel, Georgia-Pacific, Oshkosh Truck, Unitrin and Wolverine World Wide. Then there is his life as a volunteer. He heads the audit committee of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. "We're an organization that works to settle disputes," he said. "We're a nonpartisan player with offices in Moscow and Beijing. Our goals include nuclear disarmament." That may seem a long shot at a time when the United States is accusing Iran of working toward joining the world's nuclear powers and is working to tighten sanctions on the country, but Mr. Fites said the situation was not without hope. "The answers are in achieving credibility and trust," he said. He is also a 12-year veteran of the board of the Salvation Army. "We put up more people every night than some of the big hotel chains," he said. Between meetings of his various boards, Mr. Fites relaxes at his condominium in Naples, Fla., where three granddaughters often visit "for some time around the swimming pool." He also owns a condominium in Chicago. "I'm a lifelong Cubs fan and I have season tickets," he said. Making a statement far bolder than most corporate earnings forecasts, he predicted: "This is the Cubs' year, I believe. Especially after seeing the Red Sox win it all last year, I'm reminded that nothing is impossible." Robert Johnson</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DD133DF931A35750C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR TO RAISE PRICES AGAIN TO OFFSET COSTS<date>Published: March 2, 2005</date><text>Caterpillar, the heavy-equipment manufacturer, said yesterday that it would increase machinery and engine prices by 1 percent to 5 percent because of the rising costs of steel and other raw materials. Caterpillar said in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission that the increases were ''in line with general economic conditions and industry factors.'' The company, based in Peoria, Ill., raised prices by about 3 percent in July and another 3 percent in January to offset rising costs.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DF1638F932A25752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; U.A.W. APPROVES LABOR CONTRACT AT CATERPILLAR<date>Published: January 11, 2005</date><text>Caterpillar, the maker of earthmoving equipment, said that 9,000 workers represented by the United Automobile Workers had ratified a new contract, ending more than a year of negotiations. The accord covers employees in Illinois, Colorado, Pennsylvania and Tennessee for six years, Caterpillar said in a regulatory filing. The previous contract expired April 1, 2004. Union members will share some of their health care costs under the contract, which raises wages and some benefits for active employees as well as retirees. The company is based in Peoria, Ill.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/03/national/03hostage.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Hostage Incident at Caterpillar Plant<date>Published: November 3, 2004</date><text>woman armed with a shotgun took three people hostage yesterday afternoon at a Caterpillar factory in Clayton, N.C., 17 miles southeast of Raleigh, but later surrendered to the authorities, Johnston County officials said. The hostages were taken about 3:15 p.m. when the woman entered the manufacturing area of the plant. One hostage was released almost immediately, and the last was released before 6 p.m., the Johnston County sheriff, Steve Bizzell, told reporters from various news organizations. Sheriff Bizzell told reporters that the woman apparently was angry because a friend who had worked at the plant had been fired. The last hostage was freed, the authorities said, after the woman who lost her job went to the plant. The friend went to the plant in an effort to end the standoff, the sheriff said. The sheriff's department spokesman, Pat LaCarter, told The Associated Press that deputies had arrested the woman who had taken the hostages. The woman, who was not immediately identified, did not work at the plant and she did not know the hostages, The A.P. reported. The hostages, two women and a man, were in the lobby when the woman entered. Local television stations broadcast video of workers scurrying from the manufacturing area of the plant. They were taken in school buses to a nearby elementary school. The woman claimed "to have explosives around her body," Sheriff Bizzell told WRAL-TV, adding that he could not verify her claim. "It appears she is a friend or an acquaintance of an individual who was recently fired," the sheriff said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/22/business/22cat.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Profit Doubles<date>Published: October 22, 2004</date><text>EORIA, Ill., Oct. 21 (AP) - Caterpillar more than doubled its third-quarter profit, riding an economic rebound that led to record sales of heavy equipment and engines, the company reported Thursday. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, posted a net profit of $498 million, or $1.41 a share, up from $222 million, or 62 cents a share, in the quarter a year ago. Revenue was $7.65 billion, up 38 percent from $5.55 billion a year ago. Advertisement Caterpillar's chief executive, James W. Owens, credited "the strongest recovery we've ever seen across the broad spectrum of markets we serve." The company reported that profit on engine sales was up 96 percent, while machinery profit rose 78 percent.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2D9143AF935A25753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; TWO NEW DIVISIONS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES AT CATERPILLAR<date>Published: October 16, 2004</date><text>Caterpillar, the heavy-equipment manufacturer, said yesterday that it had created two new divisions to focus on its growing power-generation and specialty products. The company also announced a number of executive changes, including the retirement of its chief financial officer, Lynn McPheeters, and its global mining president, Richard Benson, effective Feb. 1. Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., said the electric power division would include products sold under the FG Wilson, Olympia and Caterpillar names and a joint venture with an industrial goods maker, the Eaton Corporation, based in Cleveland. Mr. McPheeters, 62, will be succeeded by the corporate controller, David Burritt, and Mr. Benson, 61, will be succeeded by Christopher Curfman, a manager for global mining.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D91438F93AA1575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR RAISES SALES FORECASTS FOR 2004 AND 2005<date>Published: September 29, 2004</date><text>Caterpillar, the world's biggest maker of earthmoving equipment, raised its sales forecast for this year and said revenue for next year would rise another 10 percent on growing demand. Sales this year are expected to rise 25 percent to 30 percent compared with a year earlier, up from the company's July forecast of 25 percent growth. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., had sales of $22.8 billion last year. James Owens, Caterpillar's chief executive, told analysts at the MINExpo mining industry convention yesterday in Las Vegas that the company expected to increase production by 40 percent in the second half of this year, helped by demand from China, India and Russia. The company did not change its profit forecast.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/17/business/company-news-union-at-caterpillar-votes-to-reject-contract-proposal.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; UNION AT CATERPILLAR VOTES TO REJECT CONTRACT PROPOSAL<date>Published: August 17, 2004</date><text>The main union at Caterpillar Inc. said its members voted on Sunday to reject the company's contract proposal, the second time this year the workers have voted against an offer. More than 9,000 Caterpillar workers in Colorado, Illinois, Pennsylvania and Tennessee have been working without a contract since members of the United Automobile Workers rejected a previous proposal on April 25. The latest rejection was expected; the U.A.W. made clear in advance that it was disappointed with the offer, especially its health care provisions. Caterpillar said it was disappointed that workers rejected the offer, which it said included substantial pay and benefit improvements for workers and retirees.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/10/business/company-news-cat-logistics-to-buy-mg-rover-for-185-million.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CAT LOGISTICS TO BUY MG ROVER FOR $185 MILLION<date>Published: July 10, 2004</date><text>Caterpillar Logistics Services Ltd., provider of supply chain systems, has agreed to buy the parts business of the British carmaker MG Rover for $185.1 million. Cat Logistics is part of Caterpillar Inc., the construction and industrial equipment maker based in Peoria, Ill. It said yesterday that it did not know when the deal would close and could not provide further details. The company said the acquisition includes the sourcing, marketing, distribution and sale of automotive parts and accessories to MG Rover dealers, distributors, importers and customers. MG Rover is a unit of Phoenix Venture Holdings of Britain.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/27/business/company-news-workers-at-caterpillar-reject-6-year-contract-offer.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; WORKERS AT CATERPILLAR REJECT 6-YEAR CONTRACT OFFER<date>Published: April 27, 2004</date><text>About 8,000 Caterpillar Inc. workers rejected a six-year contract that the company has called its final offer, but employees remained on the job, company and union officials said yesterday. The United Auto Workers told employees to report to work on Monday even though an extension of their contract expired Sunday night. The union's bargaining team will meet ''as soon as practical to assess the situation and plan our next steps,'' the chief U.A.W. negotiator, Cal Rapson, said. Union officials declined to comment further and did not release totals of the weekend balloting by seven locals in Colorado, Illinois, Pennsylvania and Tennessee.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/17/business/company-news-caterpillar-gives-uaw-final-labor-contract-proposal.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR GIVES U.A.W. FINAL LABOR CONTRACT PROPOSAL<date>Published: April 17, 2004</date><text>Caterpillar said yesterday that it had given the United Automobile Workers its final offer on a new labor contract. No terms of the proposal were revealed, and Caterpillar and the union declined to comment on the offer. Both sides said a contract extension set to expire Sunday night would be extended until April 25 so the union could explain the offer to its members and hold a vote. The proposed contract would cover about 8,000 union workers and 23,000 retirees or surviving spouses at plants in Illinois, Colorado, Pennsylvania and Tennessee.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/02/business/company-news-auto-workers-and-caterpillar-extend-contract-talks.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; AUTO WORKERS AND CATERPILLAR EXTEND CONTRACT TALKS<date>Published: April 02, 2004</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. and the United Automobile Workers have extended their contract until April 18 while they continue to negotiate a new agreement. The current six-year contract was to have expired Wednesday. The contract covers about 8,000 union workers and 23,000 retirees or surviving spouses at plants in Illinois, Colorado, Pennsylvania and Tennessee. Both sides declined to elaborate on the status of the negotiations, which they have agreed to keep secret. ''This extension will give both sides more time to carefully consider the issues that remain to be resolved,'' the chief U.A.W. negotiator, Cal Rapson, said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/11/business/company-news-caterpillar-s-chief-to-retire-next-month.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR'S CHIEF TO RETIRE NEXT MONTH<date>Published: December 11, 2003</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the world's largest maker of earth-moving equipment, said yesterday that the chairman and chief executive, Glen Barton, would retire Jan. 31 and be succeeded by James Owen. Mr. Owen, 57, who was appointed vice chairman yesterday, joined Caterpillar in 1972 as a corporate economist. Mr. Barton, 64, who has worked nearly 43 years at Caterpillar, was named chairman and chief executive five years ago. Mr. Barton will turn 65, Caterpillar's mandatory retirement age, in August 2004.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/06/business/caterpillar-predicts-construction-growth.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Predicts Construction Growth<date>Published: September 06, 2003</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. predicts the construction industry will grow by nearly 30 percent over the next decade as more roads and houses are built to keep pace with an expanding world population.''Growth in this industry is inevitable,'' Gerald L. Shaheen, a Caterpillar group president, told about 100 industry analysts during a daylong conference Thursday at the company's demonstration site in Tinaja Hills, Ariz.The chief executive and chairman, Glen A. Barton, said Caterpillar planned to achieve $30 billion in sales and revenue this decade, up from $20 billion in 2002.He said the bulk of the increase would come from sales of machines and engines.Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., said that the nation's housing stock was expected to grow by 1.7 million units a year over the next decade and that the nation's highways would continue to add nearly 3 percent more vehicles every year.Infrastructure needs are even greater abroad, particularly in developing countries, said Donald Western, vice president for Caterpillar's track-type tractors division.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/14/business/accusations-of-harassment-at-caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Accusations of Harassment at Caterpillar<date>Published: August 14, 2003</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the world's biggest maker of earth-moving equipment, is accused of racial and sexual harassment of workers in Illinois, according to the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.Black employees in Joliet, Ill., contend that Caterpillar management failed to act on complaints that white workers whistled at them as if they were dogs. Caterpillar is accused of retaliating against women at its Aurora, Ill., plant who said they were propositioned and subjected to inappropriate comments and touching, the agency said.Lawsuits have been filed seeking compensation for the workers and court orders requiring Caterpillar to prevent harassment at its plants. The E.E.O.C. said the lawsuits, both filed yesterday in federal court in Chicago, show that harassment remained ''a serious problem even for the world's premier employers.''Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., said the allegations had no merit and the company had ''longstanding policies prohibiting harassment and discrimination.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/10/sports/pro-basketball-a-different-kind-of-victory.html?ref=caterpillarinc">PRO BASKETBALL; A Different Kind of Victory<date>Published: June 10, 2003</date><text>Jail or the Army. Peter Holt had to choose.It was the summer of 1966 and he was taking all of South Texas on an inebriated car chase, outrunning himself as much as the law. They caught him by the fall, when Holt, a 17-year-old hellion, stood before a judge in Corpus Christi.''I never even called a lawyer or the family,'' Holt said. ''I just figured anything was better than jail.''That's how the heir to the Caterpillar tractor fortune ended up in Vietnam -- how a rich man's son fought alongside poor young men whose families did not have the connections or the money to keep them home.He returned, decorated but scarred, with the help of men nicknamed Big Red and Pineapple. Holt drank his way through the 1970's, and checked in and out of rehab clinics in the 1980's, beginning an unending battle with alcoholism. He married a young woman from Corpus Christi who loved him too much to leave him, sobered up, took over the family business and, one day, almost on a lark, bought an N.B.A. franchise, the San Antonio Spurs.With Holt watching from courtside at Continental Arena this week, the Spurs are two victories away from their second championship in five seasons.They are owned by a man with a slight drawl and piercing eyes, dressed in a jet-black blazer and polished boots and sitting inconspicuously with his wife of 21 years, Julianna Hawn Holt. In an era of often meddling men like Daniel Snyder and Jerry Jones, Holt is the antithesis of the visible and vocal modern professional sports owner. But he has a compelling yarn to tell, more enrapturing perhaps than any of them.''It's not like I've been hiding it,'' Holt said. ''I just felt it was my personal life and no reason to go into all that with everyone.''What do you want to know? I barely made it out of high school, tried to get into college, didn't even register for college, lived at the frat house, got drunk, had a damn good time and ended up in Vietnam. What else?''In 1904, Benjamin Holt, Peter's great-grandfather, invented the crawler tractor and founded Caterpillar Inc. Before mass-producing grain farms sprouted across the country, Benjamin Holt sold his contraptions to governments as far away as Russia and Argentina.By the mid-to late 20th century, Caterpillar's black-and-yellow CAT insignia, adorning baseball caps worn by farmers and truckers, became an icon of rural America. The Smithsonian Institute still salutes Benjamin Holt's contributions to industry.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/05/business/company-news-caterpillar-expects-drop-in-profits-on-flat-sales.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR EXPECTS DROP IN PROFITS ON FLAT SALES<date>Published: March 05, 2003</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. said yesterday that it still expected profits this year to be down 5 percent from 2002 on flat sales of its heavy equipment. The company also cited the increased cost of employee benefits, the weakest markets in a decade and geopolitical uncertainty as factors in its forecast. In 2002, Caterpillar's sales and revenues fell about 1 percent, to $20.15 billion, as lower sales volume offset higher pricing.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/16/business/company-news-caterpillar-cutbacks-won-t-be-as-severe-as-planned.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR CUTBACKS WON'T BE AS SEVERE AS PLANNED<date>Published: November 16, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. said yesterday that it would reduce the number of plant shutdowns planned for next month because of strong demand for its heavy-duty diesel truck engines. The revised schedules mean that some employees will not face temporary layoffs and that the layoffs that do occur will be for shorter periods. The plants are in Mossville and Pontiac, Ill., and in Jefferson and Thomasville, Ga. The company said in October that it could temporarily lay off up to 3,270 workers in the fourth quarter.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/17/business/profit-at-caterpillar-rises-4-percent-in-3rd-quarter.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Profit at Caterpillar Rises 4 Percent in 3rd Quarter<date>Published: October 17, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar reported third-quarter earnings of $213 million today, up nearly 4 percent from the same quarter last year and above analysts' expectations.Net earnings increased $8 million compared with 2001. At 61 cents a share, profits were 2 cents higher than the period a year ago. Analysts predicted profits of 55 cents a share.The company's chief financial officer, F. Lynn McPheeters, said that engine and heavy equipment sales had remained soft and that the overall economy has been slowed by the prospect of a war with Iraq.But Mr. McPheeters said Caterpillar had been able to post its first quarterly gain of the year because of the diversity of its products and markets.The company had a 26 percent earnings decline in the first quarter and a 51 percent drop in the second quarter.The profit increase stemmed in part from a reduction of Caterpillar's income tax rate, to 28 percent from 30 percent, because of a shift in its mix of domestic and foreign sales.Sales for the quarter were $5.08 billion, up $19 million from a year earlier. Mr. McPheeters said sales had been strong in Asia and the Pacific, which helped offset declines in North America and Latin America.Over all, sales of truck and bus engines were up, along with heavy construction and quarry equipment. Sales of coal mining, general construction and electrical power equipment dipped.Caterpillar repeated projections that its year-end earnings would fall about 15 percent below 2001's. Mr. McPheeters said the company expects moderate growth in 2003, though that could be affected if the nation is at war.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/15/business/company-news-caterpillar-plans-to-furlough-up-to-3270-employees.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR PLANS TO FURLOUGH UP TO 3,270 EMPLOYEES<date>Published: October 15, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar, a leading maker of heavy-duty diesel engines, announced plans yesterday to furlough 3,270 workers in December at five plants because of slow demand. The furloughs should last one to two weeks a Caterpillar spokesman, Kelly Wojda, said, and would include managers, manufacturing employees and salaried workers. Caterpillar has not announced who will be furloughed or when, Ms. Wojda said. But they will be from Illinois plants in Mossville, Mapleton and Pontiac; and in Thomasville and Jefferson, Ga., she said. Caterpillar is based in Peoria, Ill.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/09/us/bush-s-forum-on-economy-is-to-feature-gop-donors.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Bush's Forum on Economy Is to Feature G.O.P. Donors<date>Published: August 09, 2002</date><text>The speakers at a White House economic forum next week near President's Bush ranch will include major corporate donors to the Republican Party and a labor leader whom the administration is courting for support in the 2004 presidential campaign.The White House is billing the forum, which President Bush, Vice President Dick Cheney and at least seven members of the cabinet are to attend, as a diverse policy gathering of more than 200 economists, government officials, small investors, teachers, workers, corporate executives, small-business leaders and professors. White House officials said the participants would discuss the president's ''agenda to increase economic growth.''Three of eight speakers announced by the White House today are chief executives of companies that have given generously to Republicans, said the Center for Responsive Politics, a nonpartisan group.The three are Charles Schwab, the chairman and chief executive of Charles Schwab Inc., which, with its executives, gave more than $406,000 in unrestricted soft money donations to the Republicans in 2000, and nothing to the Democrats; Glen A. Barton of Caterpillar, which gave $255,000 in soft money to the Republicans in 2000 and nothing to the Democrats; and John T. Chambers, the chief executive of Cisco Systems, which gave more than $435,000 in unrestricted party contributions to the Republicans in 2000 and $255,000 to the Democrats. A fourth speaker will be Douglas J. McCarron, the general president of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. The union has often backed Democrats, including Al Gore in the 2000 presidential campaign, but Mr. McCarron has developed warm relations with Mr. Bush, and White House advisers are pursuing his support for the president's re-election.A White House spokesman said this evening that no political considerations were involved in the invitations to speak. ''The speakers were selected because of their expertise and knowledge,'' the spokesman, Scott McClellan, said. ''And the attendees and participants represent a diversity of views.''Senator Charles E. Grassley, Republican of Iowa, also defended Mr. Bush, saying the three executives were invited because of their background in investments, technology and manufacturing.''I would doubt that the president would know who contributes to his campaign,'' Mr. Grassley said. ''I would imagine he called people from Charles Schwab because of the necessity of increasing confidence in the stock market.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/17/business/company-news-caterpillar-s-second-quarter-earnings-fell-26.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR'S SECOND-QUARTER EARNINGS FELL 26%<date>Published: July 17, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. lowered its profit expectations for the year after second-quarter earnings dropped 26 percent, a performance that was far below analysts' estimates. Caterpillar, which manufactures machinery, blamed a stagnant economy for lower sales. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., reported income of $200 million, or 58 cents a share, down from $271 million, or 78 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had anticipated earnings of 73 cents a share.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/13/business/technology-industry-expertise-has-itself-become-a-product.html?ref=caterpillarinc">TECHNOLOGY; Industry Expertise Has Itself Become a Product<date>Published: May 13, 2002</date><text>Knowing the best manufacturing tricks has always been a great way to maintain a competitive edge. These days, those same tricks may help bolster the bottom line.Consider these cases:*Ford Motor, no longer content with the $3 million or so that it reaped each year from licensing its manufacturing processes to other companies, recently appointed Damian Porcari, one of its intellectual property lawyers, to be director of technology commercialization. His mission is to turn Ford's intellectual property into a $20 million a year business by 2005.*Caterpillar, also dissatistifed with the meager revenues that its two-year-old corporate licensing department gleans from Caterpillar's manufacturing expertise, now aggressively pushes its methodologies on the Web, through its home page and through Yet2.com, an Internet technology marketplace that Caterpillar partly owns.*In December, Procter &amp; Gamble, a consumer marketing titan with little experience selling to businesses, contracted with KPMG Consulting to help find licensees for Power Factory, a method for controlling quality and minimizing equipment breakdowns. ''We'll retain the patents, but they have the business relationships that can accelerate the licensing process,'' said Charles E. Eberhard, Procter's power factory program manager.Gone are the days when processes, at best, yielded low costs. These days, companies want them to yield high revenues, too -- so much so that some are even asking process engineers to take licensing potential into account as soon as they start designing a new method. ''Our goal is clear,'' said Mr. Porcari of Ford, which is doing just that. ''We want to sell things we never sold before, to more people, for more money.''Hard data quantifying how many manufacturers are licensing out process technologies is hard to come by. But experts say the anecdotal evidence is persuasive.''I am definitely sensing that more manufacturing companies are licensing out patented processes,'' said Herbert C. Wamsley, executive director of the Intellectual Property Owners Association, a trade association with about 100 member companies.Steven Y. Gold, a vice president at KPMG Consulting, said he was fielding more queries from companies that want help licensing out their cost-cutting tools. ''They are recognizing that nonproduct technologies can be more than cost centers,'' he said.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/17/business/company-news-caterpillar-reports-a-drop-in-income-for-quarter.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR REPORTS A DROP IN INCOME FOR QUARTER<date>Published: April 17, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar said yesterday that sluggish sales of heavy machinery and engines had contributed to a 51 percent decline in first-quarter earnings, which fell just below Wall Street's expectations. Net earnings were $80 million, or 23 cents a share, in the quarter, down from $162 million, or 47 cents a share, in the first quarter of 2001. Analysts had expected the company, which is based in Peoria, Ill., to earn 24 cents a share. Sales for the quarter were $4.41 billion, down from $4.81 billion. Caterpillar, the biggest maker of heavy construction machinery, said profit was down because of lower sales in two crucial markets. It reported that heavy machinery sales were down 10 percent and that engine sales fell 8 percent.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/24/business/caterpillar-reports-37-decline-in-profit.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Reports 37% Decline in Profit<date>Published: January 24, 2002</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. reported a 37 percent decline in fourth-quarter profit today, citing expenses for cost-cutting measures.The company also projected flat sales for both the company and the industry in 2002.Profit for the quarter, which ended Dec. 31, was $167 million, or 48 cents a share, down 37 percent from $264 million, or 76 cents a share, in the comparable period of 2000.Caterpillar said the restructuring resulted in an impact of about $153 million in one-time expenses, including the sale of a tractor line, the costs of plant closings and consolidations and charges associated with reducing its work force.Excluding one-time charges, earnings were 76 cents a share, matching the estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call.Fourth-quarter sales were $5.10 billion, down from $5.11 billion a year earlier.Caterpillar officials said they expected profit to be down in the first half of 2002 but hoped to end the year with earnings slightly increased over 2001 because of lower expenses.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/22/business/company-news-caterpillar-plans-to-eliminate-more-than-900-jobs.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR PLANS TO ELIMINATE MORE THAN 900 JOBS<date>Published: December 22, 2001</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. said yesterday that it would eliminate more than 900 jobs by closing an overseas plant and offering early retirement to some domestic workers. The heavy equipment manufacturer plans to cut 520 jobs through the previously announced closure of its Perkins Engines manufacturing plant in Shrewsbury, in Britain. Production from that plant will be shifted to other engine-making sites. In the United States, Caterpillar plans to cut about 420 jobs by June 30 through early retirement incentives in some of its divisions.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/18/business/company-news-caterpillar-is-selling-tractor-line-to-agco.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR IS SELLING TRACTOR LINE TO AGCO<date>Published: December 18, 2001</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. said yesterday that the Agco Corporation, a leading maker of farm equipment, had agreed to take over assembly and marketing of its Challenger line of tractors, as Caterpillar stops producing the farm equipment. Agco, which is based in Duluth, Ga., will acquire a plant in Dekalb, Ill., as part of the agreement. Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., said its earnings would be reduced by $80 million before taxes because of write-downs. Caterpillar's distribution system is aimed at construction customers, rather than farmers, making it difficult to sell agricultural products, analysts said.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/15/business/us-companies-largely-back-trade-decisions-antidumping-rules.html?ref=caterpillarinc">U.S. Companies Largely Back Trade Decisions; Antidumping Rules<date>Published: November 15, 2001</date><text>American business expects the World Trade Organization's pronouncements on antidumping rules to ease the restrictions on steel imports -- a prospect pleasing to companies like Caterpillar, a steel user, and not very pleasing to domestic steel producers like the Sandmeyer Steel Company of Philadelphia. ''Antidumping laws are becoming the trade protection law of choice around the world,'' said William Lane, Caterpillar's director in Washington for governmental affairs. ''We are opposed to the efforts to restrict the flow of fairly traded steel.'' Under American law, endorsed by the W.T.O.'s present rules, dumping occurs when a foreign company sells a product here for less than the cost of producing it, and American companies are injured as a result. Hundreds of antidumping cases are filed in the United States annually, and roughly half involve steel shipped from Brazil, Japan, South Korea, Russia and Ukraine. The W.T.O.'s declaration said that current antidumping provisions ''would benefit from clarification.'' The ministers instructed a committee to make recommendations. For Willard A. Workman, senior vice president for international affairs at the United States Chamber of Commerce, ''clarification'' means changing the rules to ease the restrictions on imports. While furniture makers and steel users are pleased, steel makers are upset, and so are lumber companies, which have filed an antidumping action against Canada. Ronald P. Sandmeyer Jr., chief executive of Sandmeyer Steel, said: ''If you look at some Southeast Asian countries and certain European countries, they can consume nowhere near what they produce. So where do they try to sell their excess production? The United States, of course.'' LOUIS UCHITELLE</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/17/business/company-news-caterpillar-s-earnings-miss-wall-street-s-forecasts.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR'S EARNINGS MISS WALL STREET'S FORECASTS<date>Published: October 17, 2001</date><text>Third-quarter earnings at Caterpillar fell 5 percent, missing Wall Street's expectations, as the company, a heavy-equipment maker, coped with higher costs. Caterpillar also forecast a larger-than-expected decrease in full-year profit because of economic uncertainty. Net profit was $205 million, or 59 cents a share, down from $216 million, or 62 cents a share, last year, Caterpillar said. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call had expected earnings of 62 cents. Third-quarter sales were $5.06 billion, up from $4.78 billion in 2000. The company, based in Peoria, Ill., said it expected profit for the year to be down 10 to 15 percent from 2000, more than the 5 percent to 10 percent forecast earlier.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/12/business/company-news-caterpillar-says-five-longtime-executives-are-retiring.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR SAYS FIVE LONGTIME EXECUTIVES ARE RETIRING<date>Published: October 12, 2001</date><text>Five longtime executives of Caterpillar, including a group president, Gerald S. Flaherty, plan to retire at the end of the year, and some of their responsibilities will be consolidated. The pending retirements announced yesterday also include four vice presidents: James E. Despain, Michael A. Flexsenhar, Siegfried R. Ramseyer and R. Rennie Atterbury III. Mr. Flaherty, who has been with the company for 42 years, will be replaced by another group president, James W. Owens, who will remain over the systems and processes division while taking responsibility for product support and logistics, component products and control systems, Latin America and human services. Douglas R. Oberhelman was named a group president to replace Mr. Owens and will oversee legal services, financial products, Shin Caterpillar Mitsubishi Ltd., Asia-Pacific, corporate auditing and compliance and corporate services.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/18/business/company-news-caterpillar-earnings-off-but-still-beat-estimates.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR EARNINGS OFF BUT STILL BEAT ESTIMATES<date>Published: July 18, 2001</date><text>Caterpillar, the heavy equipment maker, reported a 14 percent decrease in second-quarter earnings yesterday but still beat Wall Street's expectations. Caterpillar said a slight increase in sales was offset by higher costs and expenses. Net earnings were $271 million, or 78 cents a share, down from $315 million, or 90 cents a share, during the period in 2000. Second-quarter sales rose 2 percent, to $5.49 billion from $5.36 billion a year earlier. Analysts expected earnings of 71 cents a share. The company said it expected profits for the year to be down 5 percent to 10 percent from 2000. Caterpillar stock rose $3.18, to $53.55.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/22/business/cashing-world-s-energy-hunger-caterpillar-riding-high-demand-for-diesel.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Cashing in On the World's Energy Hunger; Caterpillar Is Riding High on Demand for Diesel Generators<date>Published: May 22, 2001</date><text>Ted Lewis lowers a gigantic iron block into place, clamps it down, and begins drilling holes in the skeleton of what will become an 8,000-pound diesel engine.That engine, an array of bolts, fuel lines, filters and pistons, rolls off the assembly line at the Caterpillar plant here, ready to be bolted onto a two-megawatt electric generator that will create a machine capable of delivering the power that everyone seems to crave these days.The generators, which are nearly twice as big as a midsize car, are being shipped to California so that Internet server centers there will have the uninterrupted power they need to keep the digital age humming; they are going to hospitals and police departments, which are obligated to have emergency power; and they are being installed at big manufacturing operations and office buildings, which are bracing in a few parts of the country for a summer of rolling blackouts.''These companies are saying, 'We can't rely on the utilities anymore; we're going to put our own standby units in,' '' said Jim Parker, director of electric power generation at Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill. ''And they're saying, 'How much power do you have and how fast can you get it here?' ''For Caterpillar, the world's largest manufacturer of construction and earthmoving equipment, soaring demand for diesel-powered generators is bolstering profits in a fast-growing unit and helping stabilize a company that is coping with slowing sales of construction and mining equipment.Analysts say the growth of the engine business is making Caterpillar much less of a roller coaster ride than it was in past downturns, when it invariably lost money at the low points. And they say that global energy demand is expected to continue to rise for several years, raising the company's long-term prospects. By 2006, if power generation sales continue to grow by 20 percent a year, as they have for the last six years, they could account for a fifth of the company's revenues.The strength of its engine business is helping Caterpillar transform itself into a diversified equipment supplier and service provider; it is no longer just a builder of its traditional yellow earthmovers, tractors and other equipment. Indeed, all the company's energy-related businesses -- turbines, diesel-engine generators, oil and gas exploration equipment, and coal mining trucks -- are growing rapidly, benefiting from the nation's energy shortfall.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/25/business/business-diary-medium-is-the-message-in-counterfeiting-battle.html?ref=caterpillarinc">BUSINESS: DIARY; Medium Is the Message In Counterfeiting Battle<date>Published: February 25, 2001</date><text>China is considered one of the worst offenders in counterfeiting foreign goods like CD's, videos, electronics and luxury watches, and the occasional crackdown is often publicized by showing a steamroller crushing the phony goods. But now, apparently even foreign-made steamrollers are threatened by counterfeiting.Richard Kahler, president of Caterpillar China, a subsidiary of Caterpillar Inc. of Peoria, Ill., the maker of construction equipment, says counterfeit parts for his company's products can be found no farther away than Hong Kong -- some of them in fake Caterpillar packaging.''I can walk into a shop and ask for a part, and the clerk will pull out three boxes -- he'll show a real one that costs $10, a fake one that costs $5 and might work, and a fake one that costs $1 and definitely will not work,'' Mr. Kahler said at a recent lunch sponsored by the Hong Kong Association of New York.Caterpillar, which now sells more than $400 million worth of tractors, excavators, backhoe loaders, diesel engines and other machinery annually in China, called counterfeiting a ''serious problem'' but is a vocal proponent of improved trade relations with the Chinese.Mr. Kahler said he was convinced that the Chinese government was making sincere efforts to improve, ahead of China's expected entry into the World Trade Organization. Admission to the organizaion would open more of China's markets to foreign goods.Last week, the incoming director general of the World Trade Organization, Supachai Panitchpakdi, said he expected China to be admitted to the multinational trade group in the next three months. Rick Gladstone</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/19/business/caterpillar-expects-lower-profit.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Expects Lower Profit<date>Published: January 19, 2001</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the largest maker of construction and earth-moving equipment, said today that its profit would fall and that its sales would be little changed this year because of the slowing economy and higher spending.Caterpillar shares fell $2.91, to $41.75, a drop of 6.5 percent.Caterpillar said its profit would be 5 percent to 10 percent less than it earned in 2000. Analysts had expected earnings to rise this year.The company had said that fourth-quarter net income rose a greater-than-expected 10 percent, to $264 million, or 76 cents a share, compared with $239 million, or 67 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales rose 1.9 percent, to $5.11 billion from $5.02 billion. Analysts had expected the company to earn 64 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.Caterpillar's profit had dropped seven out of the last nine quarters as higher interest rates, low commodity prices and weak overseas economies crimped sales of backhoes and cranes.Caterpillar plans to spend $350 million to initiate a quality-control program and upgrade computer systems to improve productivity, Lynn McPheeters, the chief financial officer, said in an interview. Profit would increase without the higher spending, he said.North American sales of machinery in 2001 will be hurt from excess industry capacity and pricing competition, while sales in the rest of the world will probably increase, Mr. McPheeters said. The company, based in Peoria, has sought to counter increased competition from rivals like Deere &amp; Company and CNH Global N.V. by offering incentives to dealers, which include reduced interest rates and price cuts.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/23/business/company-news-2-companies-join-to-make-parts-for-heavy-equipment.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; 2 COMPANIES JOIN TO MAKE PARTS FOR HEAVY EQUIPMENT<date>Published: November 23, 2000</date><text>Caterpillar Inc. and DaimlerChrysler announced yesterday that they had agreed to form a global alliance for vehicle parts. The companies said the alliance would develop, manufacture, market and distribute medium-duty engines, fuel systems and powertrain components for other vehicle builders and for use in their own products. Caterpillar makes construction and mining equipment like bulldozers and earthmovers; its alliance with the commercial-vehicle unit of DaimlerChrysler would involve joint ventures, supply agreements and cooperative projects, subject to regulatory approval.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/18/business/caterpillar-beats-lowered-expectations.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Beats Lowered Expectations<date>Published: October 18, 2000</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the maker of earth-moving equipment, said today that its third-quarter profit narrowly beat recently lowered estimates after softness in important markets, higher costs and unfavorable currency translations took their toll.Caterpillar said it expected revenue in 2000 and 2001 to rise 2 to 7 percent. Further increases in United States interest rates could, however, threaten that outlook.''At the moment, we do not have anything plugged in for continued increases in interest rates, so you could say there would be a risk if rates started to rise again,'' Caterpillar's chief financial officer, F. Lynn McFeeters, said in an interview.The company, which warned analysts two weeks ago that it would not meet third-quarter profit forecasts, said it earned $216 million, or 62 cents a share, on revenue of $4.78 billion in the latest quarter. That compares with $219 million, or 61 cents, on revenue of $4.72 billion in the period a year earlier.Analysts surveyed by First Call/ Thomson Financial, expected profit of 58cents a share. Analysts cut their estimates by 10 cents after the company issued its warning.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/business/company-news-caterpillar-expects-a-decline-of-15-in-its-profits.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR EXPECTS A DECLINE OF 15% IN ITS PROFITS<date>Published: September 30, 2000</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the world's largest maker of construction and mining equipment, said it expected its third-quarter profit to be about 15 percent below analysts' consensus estimate of 68 cents a share. However, the company, based in Peoria, Ill., said its outlook for the full year was unchanged, with sales and revenues expected to improve slightly over 1999 and profit expected to rise moderately. In 1999, Caterpillar reported revenue of $19.7 billion and profit of $946 million or $2.63 a share. Caterpillar said a smaller-than-expected profit in the latest quarter stemmed from weakness in the euro and the pound, continued softness in the North American construction and global mining industries, and significant and accelerating weakness in the market for truck engines.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/business/company-news-caterpillar-expects-to-cut-1-billion-in-costs.html?ref=caterpillarinc">COMPANY NEWS; CATERPILLAR EXPECTS TO CUT $1 BILLION IN COSTS<date>Published: August 31, 2000</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the maker of construction and mining equipment, expects to cut $1 billion in costs over the next several years and increase sales 50 percent, to $30 billion, by 2006, Glen Barton, the chairman and chief executive, said yesterday. Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill., plans to reach the cost-cutting goal by reducing material costs, lead times and inventory, and through attrition of the company work force, Mr. Barton told analysts in Boston. The company had $19.7 billion in revenue in 1999.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/business/clearing-the-decks-for-a-trade-pact-s-riches.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Clearing the Decks for a Trade Pact's Riches<date>Published: August 27, 2000</date><text>TO explain why he is so excited about the new trade agreement with the United States, Pham Van Tuat clambered aboard the Xin Thu, his new 89-foot wooden fishing trawler, and gestured into its spacious holds. Lower American tariffs for Vietnamese seafood products in the United States, he explained, will mean more demand for tuna and squid. And that is where this $125,000 trawler comes in.The Xin Thu, the largest of his nine boats, can travel 400 miles out to sea and bring back 200 tons of fish, Mr. Tuat said. To demonstrate how, he bundled his visitors down into the engine room. There, still bearing its maker's signature yellow paint, was something that makes many American executives here as excited as Mr. Tuat: a brand-new, $32,000, 480-horsepower Caterpillar engine.''We'll be exporting to America soon,'' Mr. Tuat said triumphantly, hurrying his guests onto a skiff to beat the ebb tide back to shore. ''I'm planning to build another boat like this one. But even bigger.''To a large extent, Mr. Tuat's plans are the fruits of seven years of toil by Anthony D. Salzman, an entrepreneur from New York. Mr. Salzman came to Hanoi from Japan in 1993, hoping to capitalize on that country's swelling investment in Vietnam. He wound up opening a dealership for Caterpillar, which was among the most vocal companies in urging the Clinton administration to lift the United States embargo that blocked trade for 19 years.Mr. Salzman, 49, is now one of Vietnam's most prominent American residents, well known for his outspoken, unrelenting style. And he is just one of many American executives here who say a trade pact will unleash a tide of exports -- and lift his fortunes with it. After five years of talks, the United States and Vietnam signed the agreement on July 13, and it is expected to be ratified by Congress, though probably not this year.Since President Clinton ended the embargo in 1994, the American commercial adventure in Vietnam has resembled its earlier military one, with optimism quickly bogged down in a quagmire of red tape, corruption and Communist recalcitrance. To skeptics, the new agreement is yet another capitulation: tariffs on Vietnamese goods would drop immediately, while Vietnamese tariffs and quotas on American products would fall only gradually, in some cases enduring as long as seven years.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/19/business/caterpillar-s-profit-up-26-in-quarter.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar's Profit Up 26% in Quarter<date>Published: April 19, 2000</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., the world's largest maker of construction equipment, said today that its first-quarter profit rose 26 percent.Net income rose to $258 million, or 73 cents a share, from $205 million, or 57 cents, in the year-earlier quarter. The profit beat the average estimate of 58 cents a share projected by analysts surveyed by First Call/Thomson Financial. Sales rose 1.1 percent, to $4.92 billion.The higher-than-expected earnings resulted from increased efficiency at Caterpillar's factories. Costs for large industrial manufacturers like Caterpillar typically drop as production is closer to capacity. Operating profit at the company's engine unit jumped fivefold, as higher gas prices increased demand for diesel engines for trucks and heavy equipment.The shares of Caterpillar, based in Peoria, fell 68.75 cents, to $40.25.Caterpillar reiterated that it expected revenue this year to be ''slightly higher'' than in 1999 and profit to increase moderately.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/20/business/caterpillar-shares-battered-after-warning-about-profit.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Shares Battered After Warning About Profit<date>Published: November 20, 1999</date><text>Shares of Caterpillar Inc. plummeted 12 percent today after the company warned that fourth-quarter earnings would not meet expectations.The profit warning was the third in the last year at Caterpillar, which said yesterday that it was suffering from weaker-than-expected sales of its heavy equipment in North America.Shares of Caterpillar, the world's largest maker of construction and earth-moving equipment, fell $6.75, to $49.1875, on the New York Stock Exchange. The drop also weighed down the Dow Jones industrial average, which lost 31.81 points, to 11,003.89.Caterpillar had warned earlier this year that it was having trouble in Asia and Latin America, as well as experiencing weakness in the demand for its mining equipment. But yesterday, company executives said that softening construction business in North America and increased price competition had forced the company to trim expectations.''Demand for our type of products'' has not risen to the level the company thought it would, said Marsha Hausser, a spokeswoman for Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill. ''North America has been down, and the industry is softening.''The company released few details about its fourth-quarter problems, saying only that its executives had been too optimistic and that some revenue that was anticipated from a federal highway construction bill had not materialized.In a statement early in the day, Caterpillar said it expected fourth-quarter revenue and profit to be slightly ahead of the third quarter, in which the company reported earnings of 61 cents a share on revenue of $4.7 billion.Analysts had been projecting profit of 97 cents a share, according to a survey by First Call/Thomson Financial. Wall Street analysts reacted to today's news by drastically revising their fourth-quarter estimates, though few made sharp cuts in their forecasts for next year.''There are three factors,'' said Tobias Levkovich, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. ''The marketplace is not as strong, a lot of equipment has already been replaced and interest rates are higher.''Among those who made revisions today, the consensus was that Caterpillar would earn 66 cents a share in the fourth quarter, according to Charles Hill, director of research at First Call, down from 83 cents a share in the fourth quarter of 1998.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/17/business/caterpillar-sees-profit-growth-slowing-in-99.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Sees Profit Growth Slowing in '99<date>Published: July 17, 1999</date><text>After months of hinting at a turnaround, Caterpillar Inc., the maker of construction and earth-moving equipment, warned investors yesterday that profit growth would continue to slide this year.The warning came after Caterpillar said that its second-quarter profits had fallen 36.5 percent from a year earlier because of slumping demand for heavy machines and equipment. It was the fourth consecutive quarterly profit decline for Caterpillar.Shares of Caterpillar fell 18.75 cents, to $58.9375, on the New York Stock Exchange.The company said it revised its outlook because sales of more profitable machines and equipment, like mining trucks, had dipped while sales of less profitable equipment, like truck engines, had gained -- upsetting the more favorable profit mix that had been the basis for an earlier projection.Second-quarter sales were $5.1 billion, Caterpillar said, down from $5.6 billion in the second quarter of last year, and profits in the latest quarter were $283 million, down from $446 million a year earlier. Earnings per share were 78 cents, slightly below Wall Street expectations and down from $1.20.Wall Street analysts said they were disappointed by the results and by the company's warning, but several analysts said investors were already looking ahead to early next year.''Caterpillar, at this point, is a 2000 story,'' said David Bleustein, an analyst at Paine Webber. ''We expect the benefits of the global recovery to more than offset any slowdown there might be here in the United States.''That turnaround, however, was expected to come earlier this year. In March, Caterpillar executives sounded an upbeat note at a convention in Las Vegas, Nev., saying that signs of a recovery in Asia, corporate belt-tightening and a push to diversify its business could put the company on sound footing in 1999.But today, the company pushed that optimism further out, saying that it did not expect a big jump in profits until the fourth quarter of this year.''We're trying to fix this,'' said F. Lynn McPheeters, chief financial officer at Caterpillar, which is based in Peoria, Ill. ''We thought the mix of business would turn a little earlier.''Although Caterpillar says its warning grew out of a slowdown in the sale of more profitable mining and oil exploration equipment, the company pegged its yearlong profit slump to a recession in parts of Asia, Latin America, Africa and the Middle East and weakness in the mining and oil exploration industry.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/01/business/international-business-hoping-bear-will-awaken-some-foreign-companies-stay.html?ref=caterpillarinc">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Hoping Bear Will Awaken; Some Foreign Companies Stay the Course in Russia<date>Published: May 01, 1999</date><text>Caterpillar had just cleared away a patch of spindly trees in this town outside St. Petersburg and begun building a new $50 million factory when, one day last August, the Russian financial system collapsed.Overnight, the Russian Government devalued its currency and simultaneously defaulted on $40 billion in domestic debt. Prices rose by two-thirds over the next seven months, and the spending power of ordinary Russians decreased 40 percent. The ruble, worth around 15 cents before the crisis, has fallen to about 4 cents. Many smaller companies, such as those Caterpillar had envisioned as customers for its Russian-made construction equipment, were ruined.''We asked ourselves some hard questions,'' said Stu Levenick, general director of Caterpillar Overseas in Moscow, ''mainly about whether this was the right time to invest $50 million.''The economic collapse seemed to confirm the worst corporate fears about Russia: It is too unstable to operate here. Companies such as Pizza Hut and Hershey have pulled out, and many that had considered entering Russia shelved their plans.Caterpillar could have easily followed the conventional wisdom. Yet a number of Western multinationals -- not just Caterpillar but Nestle, Lucent Technologies and others -- are coping with the economic crisis by settling deeper into Russia rather than pulling out.They are not blind to the problems, so they have developed a variety of strategies to cope. Most have started by picking areas where the local government now supports business, regardless of broader upheaval in Russia. This is one such area. In St. Petersburg and the surrounding region, six American projects are expected to bring more than $500 million of direct foreign investment over the next 18 months.Caterpillar is pushing ahead with its plant, and production there should begin on schedule in December. Up the highway from Tosno, the Wm. Wrigley Jr. Company opened a new factory this winter, and Gillette is building one next door. Philip Morris is constructing a $330 million plant, and International Paper recently paid an estimated $65 million to acquire controlling interest in a local paper mill.Meanwhile, Ford Motor is in final talks with the Government to invest more than $150 million in an auto plant in the region surrounding what was once the city of Leningrad.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/17/business/earnings-slip-at-caterpillar-but-drop-is-below-forecast.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Earnings Slip at Caterpillar, But Drop Is Below Forecast<date>Published: April 17, 1999</date><text>Caterpillar Inc., which had sounded an earnings warning last month, posted a decline in quarterly profit today that was smaller than analysts' latest forecasts.Citing lower prices, higher costs and slower machinery sales, the big manufacturer of construction equipment said earnings fell 52 percent in the first quarter, to $205 million, or 57 cents a share, from $430 million, or $1.15 a share, a year earlier. The per-share figure was higher than the 42 cents that analysts had expected since Caterpillar had warned on March 12 that earnings in the quarter would fall as much as 50 percent.The better-than-expected result came at the expense of the current quarter, however. Caterpillar said today that some shipments scheduled for the second quarter had been pushed into March.Because of the accelerated shipments, the company is lowering its sales projections for the second quarter. But full-year results will not be affected, it added.Shares of Caterpillar, which have climbed nearly 31 percent this week amid a rally by shares of industrial companies, rose $2, to $63.8125.The company has been vulnerable to economic weakness overseas. Machinery and engine sales in Latin America slumped 37 percent in the first quarter as Brazil's recession cut into demand. But sales rose 12 percent in Asia and 3.9 percent in North America.Still, Caterpillar was hurt by higher manufacturing costs and lower prices for its products.''They're getting hit by price on both the machine and engine segments,'' said Tobias Levkovich, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney Inc. who has a buy rating on the company's stock. ''Caterpillar was losing some market share last year and cut prices to try to win some back. They realized it wasn't a brilliant idea.''Reversing that course, Caterpillar raised prices April 1, he said.Revenue in the first quarter rose 1.7 percent, to $4.87 billion from $4.79 billion. The market in the United States accounted for 43 percent of equipment sales, down from 47 percent a year ago.Following the earnings warning last month, analysts sharply lowered their forecasts for full-year earnings. Their average per-share estimate fell to $3.21 from $3.60.Caterpillar's chairman and chief executive, Glen Barton, insisted last month that earnings would still be around $3.60 for the year. But the analysts remain unconvinced.''Our estimate is below theirs,'' said Salomon Smith Barney's Mr. Levkovich, who expects a per-share profit of $3.30. ''The Street is skeptical. The company is going to have to prove it.''In its March warning, Caterpillar said it would temporarily idle certain plants and cut jobs, spending and inventory to lower costs.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/14/business/aiming-for-greener-pastures-farm-equipment-makers-step-up-efforts-to-diversify.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Aiming for Greener Pastures; Farm-Equipment Makers Step Up Efforts to Diversify<date>Published: April 14, 1999</date><text>The name John Deere conjures up tractors, farm equipment, big green machines lingering in the distance, on a huge corn field somewhere in the Midwest.While it receives most of its revenues from the farm, Deere &amp; Company, the world's largest maker of agricultural machinery, also peddles lawn and turf products. The Case Corporation, a rival in farm machinery, has broadened its reach as well, financing dump trucks and marine equipment. And Caterpillar Inc., the world's largest maker of earthmoving equipment and a major agricultural supplier, is selling truck engines while leveraging its vast distribution network to move Chrysler auto parts and Puma sneakers.All three heavy-equipment makers -- the biggest names in farm and construction equipment -- are moving into new fields in an effort to buffer themselves from the wrenching up-and-down cycle of their core businesses. At the moment, they are trying to break out of a nasty slowdown that in the last few quarters has sapped the profits of virtually every maker of farm equipment. When the farm economy here in the Midwest sagged with the Asian economic crisis and the construction business showed signs of slowing late last year, the big-equipment makers stepped up their efforts to diversify in hopes of maintaining profitability, even in a down cycle.The sector has been upgraded recently by some Wall Street analysts who believe that the heavy-machinery cycle is likely to start moving upward, but most analysts are unimpressed by the steps toward diversification. Fundamentally, the companies are defined by their core businesses -- and so are still captives of the business cycle.''I know what they're trying to do, but it's just not showing up in the numbers,'' Tobias M. Levkovich, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said about Case. ''They've gotten reamed by the cycle, and that's with the U.S. construction business doing very well.''Still, the most recent downturn has been a big impetus in a trend that has been in place for some time.Case, for instance, now receives about a third of its revenue from sales of construction equipment. Deere receives nearly one-fifth of its revenues from lawn and consumer products. Caterpillar, which originated in 1925 with the merger of two farm tractor companies, is dominant in excavating and earthmoving machines, but now receives a third of its revenues from engine sales and about 5 percent from financial services.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/13/business/caterpillar-says-its-profits-will-be-below-expectations.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Caterpillar Says Its Profits Will Be Below Expectations<date>Published: March 13, 1999</date><text>Citing a sales slowdown in Latin America and stiff competition in North America, Caterpillar Inc., the world's largest maker of construction and earthmoving equipment, warned today that its first-quarter profits would be far below expectations. The news caused the company's stock to tumble 12.2 percent, pulling down the Dow Jones industrial average.The warning was just the latest in a series of blows to Caterpillar, which has been suffering through a gradual decline in sales and profits over the last year, largely because of the global economic crisis that began in Asia in late 1997.Caterpillar shares fell $6.1875, or 12.2 percent, on the New York Stock Exchange today, to $44.6875. The stock had the biggest decline among the 30 stocks in the industrial average, which finished the day off 21.09 points, or two-tenths of 1 percent.In a press release issued this morning, the company said it expected earnings per share to decline by as much as 50 percent from the corresponding quarter a year ago, well below the estimates of Wall Street analysts. Business is expected to strengthen in the second half of the year, the company said.Still, analysts are projecting an earnings-per-share decline of 10 to 15 percent in 1999, and Caterpillar officials say they are comfortable with those estimates.Caterpillar said it would temporarily idle plants here and abroad in the coming months and cut back on administrative costs and on research and development. Reductions in the work force are also being considered.While the company's North American business is suffering from stiff competition and pricing pressure, most of its problems are related to recessionary forces in Asia and Latin America. And that has many analysts worried that the same forces could spread to the United States.''We knew that Asia was quite depressed, and now Latin America is sinking like a stone and Europe is flattish,'' Robert McCarthy, an analyst at ABN Amro in Chicago, said. ''This means they are very vulnerable to any slowdown in North America.''While sales of construction and earthmoving equipment remain strong in the United States, sales of agricultural and mining equipment are slumping because of weakness in those sectors. Sales of engines and solar turbines are also depressed, Caterpillar said, which could force temporary plant shutdowns in Europe and Latin America.In 1998, Latin America accounted for about 9 percent of Caterpillar's sales. The company said its sales in Brazil were particularly bad.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/03/business/emerson-electric-in-deal-with-caterpillar.html?ref=caterpillarinc">Emerson Electric in Deal With Caterpillar<date>Published: February 03, 1999</date><text>The Emerson Electric Company, a maker of electric motors, agreed to acquire Kato Engineering, an electric-generator business, from Caterpillar Inc. to broaden its line of power equipment.Emerson also agreed to sell Caterpillar its stake in the companies' F. G. Wilson joint venture, which makes diesel-powered generators typically used in remote construction sites or as a backup energy source. Terms were not disclosed.Caterpillar, which makes construction equipment, turbines and engines, has owned Kato Engineering for less than a year. It bought the business, which had fiscal year 1997 sales of $70 million, from Rockwell International in April.Caterpillar, based in Peoria, Ill., will be the sole owner of F. G. Wilson after the transaction is complete.Separately, Emerson, based in St. Louis, said net income in its first quarter ended Dec. 31 rose 7.1 percent, to $302.4 million, or 69 cents a diluted share, from $282.3 million, or 64 cents, in the period a year earlier. The company's sales rose 8 percent, to $3.43 billion from $3.17 billion.</text></article></page></root>
