<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Colgate-Palmolive Co"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/28/business/colgate-profit-rises-while-procters-falls.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Profit Rises While Procter’s Falls<date>Published: October 27, 2011</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive said Thursday that its quarterly profit rose 4 percent, while Procter &amp; Gamble reported a 2 percent decline.Both said their results were helped by higher prices to consumers and hurt by increased costs for raw materials. Procter &amp; Gamble, however, said its price increases could not overcome those costs, while Colgate-Palmolive said it controlled costs and had strong sales in emerging markets. P.&amp; G. raised prices mostly on premium products like Crest 3D whitening strips and Gillette ProGlide razors, which have sold well even in the weak economy, executives said. P.&amp; G.’s prices rose an average of 4 percent in the July through September period, its fiscal first quarter. That was on top of price increases of 3 percent and 1 percent the previous two quarters. The company said its price increases had pared some market share in Western Europe, where it gets 20 percent of its revenue, and in North America, where it gets about 40 percent. But it held or gained market share in other parts of the world. Revenue increased 9 percent to $21.92 billion from $20.12 billion. That beat the $21.58 billion expected by analysts polled by FactSet, a research firm. Net income fell to $3.02 billion from $3.08 billion. Earnings were $1.03 a share, in line with analysts’ estimates, and up from $1.02 a share in the same period a year ago. Gross margin fell to 49.5 percent from 51.9 percent. P.&amp; G. said it expected revenue to increase 3 to 6 percent for the current fiscal year, which runs through June. Colgate-Palmolive said that, in addition to its strength in emerging markets, there were encouraging signs in developed markets as well, where sales had lagged for more than a year. The company earned $643 million, or $1.31 a share, for the period ended Sept. 30, compared with $619 million, or $1.21 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 11 percent to $4.38 billion. Per-share earnings edged out Wall Street expectations by a penny, according to FactSet, and the company topped revenue projections as well. The biggest gains came in the Europe/South Pacific region, with an 18.5 percent revenue increase. That region makes up 22 percent of company sales. Latin America, which accounts for 28 percent of sales, posted a 16 percent rise in revenue. Revenue in North America, where 18 percent of sales are made, climbed 3 percent. Revenue for Greater Asia/Africa, which is 20 percent of company sales, rose 9.5 percent. The company expects full-year gross profit margin to fall this year. It stuck to its earnings per share forecast for the year and forecast a double-digit percentage jump in per-share earnings for next year. Colgate-Palmolive reduced its selling, general and administrative expenses to 34 percent of sales, compared with 35.3 percent a year earlier. It also cut overhead and domestic advertising spending. Worldwide ad spending rose 4 percent.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/03/rothschild-hires-ex-colgate-palmolive-executive-as-adviser/?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Rothschild Hires Ex-Colgate-Palmolive Executive as Adviser<date>June 3, 2011, 10:48 am</date><text>Rothschild said on Friday that it had hired Steve Patrick, the former vice chairman of Colgate-Palmolive, as a senior adviser. Mr. Patrick, who was previously Colgate-Palmolive’s chief financial officer, will counsel the investment bank’s mergers and financing advisory teams, especially on consumer and retail companies. Read more »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/29/business/29consumer.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate Earnings Rise<date>Published: April 28, 2011</date><text>The Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate-Palmolive companies posted increases in profit and sales for their most recent quarters on Thursday, but warned that rising costs would affect their results and lead to higher prices for consumers.Procter &amp; Gamble lowered the high end of its profit forecast for the year after posting a profit that fell a penny short of analysts’ average estimate. Colgate said that rising costs hurt its profit margins in its last quarter but that the income still met forecasts. Procter &amp; Gamble, the world’s largest maker of household goods, now expects its costs to rise about three times as much at it had at the start of the year, with increases in diesel, resin and other materials, the chief financial officer, Jon R. Moeller, said. Procter has implemented or announced increases across brands representing about 50 percent of United States sales but is not raising prices as much as it did in 2008, the chief executive, Robert A. McDonald, said. Procter &amp; Gamble earned $2.87 billion, or 96 cents a share, up from $2.59 billion, or 83 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended March 31 and was the third quarter of the company’s fiscal year, rose to $20.23 billion from $19.18 billion. Stock in Procter, which is based in Cincinnati, rose 48 cents, to $64.50 a share. Colgate, which was reporting results for its first quarter, said it earned $576 million, or $1.16 a share, up from $3.57 million, or 69 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales rose to $3.99 billion from $3.83 billion. Excluding one-time items from the year-earlier period, its net income was down 8 percent. The chief executive, Ian M. Cook, said Colgate raised prices in many categories and in all its markets, and will keep doing so, but he declined to provide details. Stock in Colgate, which is based in New York, rose $1.91, to $82.97 a share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/03/23/colgate-buys-unilever-business-for-940-million/?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Buys Unilever Business for $940 Million<date>March 23, 2011, 9:20 am</date><text>Correction Appended 5:35 p.m. | Updated Colgate-Palmolive said on Wednesday that it had agreed to buy Sanex, the personal care unit of Unilever, for $940 million in cash, expanding its share of the skin care market in Europe. Sanex, which specializes in deodorants and body cleansing products, reported sales of $260 million last year, concentrated in Western Europe. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Colgate press release At the same time, Unilever is acquiring Colgate’s laundry detergent business in Colombia for $215 million. The two moves are part of Colgate’s strategy to focus on “high-margin, strategically important oral care, personal care and pet nutrition businesses,” said Ian M. Cook, the company’s chairman and chief executive. The Sanex deal is expected to close by the end of the second quarter, Colgate said, pending regulatory approval. The Colombian transaction will close after the first acquisition is complete. Unilever said the purchase of the detergent unit was an add-on deal that would help it double its presence in the market, where it will add the Fab, Lavomatic and Vel brands to its offering. “This acquisition will significantly enhance our position in one of the larger detergents markets in Latin America, bringing critical mass to our Colombian business,” said Michael B. Polk, head of Unilever’s personal care division. Unilever acquired the personal care business of Sara Lee for $3.7 billion in September. As a condition of approving the deal, European Union regulators required Unilever to divest Sanex. Despite the forced sale, Unilever is plowing ahead to build out its personal care division. It is on track to buy Alberto Culver, the hair products maker, for $3.7 billion. Colgate hired Citigroup Global Markets as a financial adviser and Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz as counsel for both deals. Unilever hired Slaughter and May as counsel on the Sanex deal, while Herrick and Feinstein provided legal advice on the Colombian acquisition. Shares of Colgate fell 14 cents, or 0.2 percent, to close at $78.29. Shares of Unilever were up 24 pence, or 1.33 percent, at £18.34 in London. Correction: March 24, 2011 A previous version of this article stated that Colgate shares had fallen 2 percent at the close on Wednesday. They fell just 0.2 percent.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/29/business/29colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate’s Profit Rises 4.9%<date>Published: October 28, 2010</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said Thursday that its third-quarter net income rose 4.9 percent, even though currency fluctuations reduced its revenue.Colgate, which produces Palmolive soap, Colgate toothpaste, Hill’s pet food and other top sellers, makes almost two-thirds of its sales abroad, so it is especially exposed to changes in foreign currency. In announcing its results, the company also took a cautious view of next year’s results, saying it would increase marketing spending to promote sales. Price cuts and promotions, like those many consumer companies have made to retain customers, also ate into Colgate’s revenue during the third quarter. The chief executive, Ian M. Cook, said the company’s profit rose because it cut costs, even as it invested more worldwide. The company said it earned $619 million, or $1.21 a share, in the quarter, up from $590 million, or $1.12 a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell more than 1 percent, to $3.94 billion. Analysts polled by Thomson Reuters expected the company to earn $1.19 a share on revenue of $4.03 billion in the quarter. Colgate’s revenue in the United States, which produces 19 percent of its sales, grew 2 percent, while the company sold 3 percent more products. Price cuts reduced its earnings in the United States by 1.5 percent. The company’s share of the world’s toothpaste market is now 44.2 percent, and was led by share gains in Brazil, India, China, Venezuela, France, Greece and Britain. Colgate said currency changes cut 4.5 percent from its third-quarter revenue. Stock in the company, based in New York, fell 58 cents, to $74.92 a share.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/12/business/media/12branding.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Advertisers Seek to Speak to Muslim Consumers<date>Published: August 11, 2010</date><text>KUALA LUMPUR — Thick waves of hair cascade over a woman’s shoulder. She gives a flirtatious flick of her locks and tells viewers that they too can get such a luxurious mane — if they buy the shampoo she is holding up to the camera. That is the script for your standard shampoo commercial.Cut to the television spot for Sunsilk’s Lively Clean &amp; Fresh shampoo. Another young, smiling woman is the star, but there is not a strand of hair in sight. Her tresses are completely covered by a tudung, the head scarf worn by many Muslim women in Malaysia. The pitch? Lively Clean &amp; Fresh helps remove excess oil from the scalp and hair — a common problem among wearers of tudungs, according to Unilever, the manufacturer. The company says the product is the first shampoo to speak directly to the “lifestyle of a tudung wearer.” For decades, many Western company failed to appreciate the unique needs of Muslim consumers, marketing experts say. Worse, some companies offended potential customers by not understanding religious sensitivities. But as the Islamic population has grown in size and affluence — there are now 1.57 billion Muslims worldwide — more multinationals are seeking to tap into the market. Instead of simply importing products and advertising from the West, companies are increasingly developing marketing campaigns — and formulating products themselves — with Muslims firmly in sight. “Islamic marketing,” some experts say, is the next wave in branding, and now, as the holy month of Ramadan begins, activity is surging. “For the last few years, it’s been China and India,” said Paul Temporal, an associate fellow at the Said Business School at the University of Oxford. “The next big market is the Muslim market. There’s this huge group of people who have been relatively untapped in terms of what they want and need, and they represent a tremendous opportunity.” John Goodman, Ogilvy &amp; Mather’s regional director for South and Southeast Asia, is more blunt: “It’s like being in 1990 and telling people that China doesn’t matter. Twenty years ago you might have said that, but now you’re being foolish.” With Muslim-majority countries spread from Southeast Asia to Africa, and Muslims speaking numerous languages and adhering to varying standards of dress and other customs, approaching the group as consumers can be complex. But as with all marketing exercises, experts say, rule No.1 is to avoid causing offense. Nike committed a legendary error when it released a pair of athletic shoes in 1996 with a logo on the sole that some Muslims believed resembled the Arabic lettering for Allah. Given that Muslims consider the feet unclean, “producing shoes with the name of God on the soles of the feet is not a good idea,” said Mr. Goodman, who converted to Islam in 1999. “They recalled 800,000 pairs of shoes globally.” Describing the Nike episode as a “wake-up call” for companies, Mr. Goodman said it had also been a turning point for Muslim advocates, who realized that “if they make a noise, companies would listen and change, that they had economic and social influence.” Unilever says the Sunsilk Lively Clean &amp; Fresh shampoo, which is sold in Malaysia and Singapore, was created for people who suffer from oily scalps after wearing any head covering, be it a baseball hat or head scarf. After company research showed that many women who wear the tudung complained of oily scalps, it introduced the television commercial aimed at them. The ad begins with a young woman saying that now she can do what she wants because she no longer has to worry about itchiness, before she goes on to kick a goal in a coed soccer game. Other companies are taking steps to reassure consumers that all of their products — not just food — are halal, or permissible under Islam, by having them officially certified. Colgate-Palmolive, for instance, claims to be the first international company to have obtained halal certification in Malaysia for toothpaste and mouthwash products. Some mouthwashes may contain alcohol, which would be forbidden under halal guidelines. Colgate’s products now bear the halal logo, which also is featured in the company’s television commercials. The mobile phone industry has also started focusing on Muslim consumers, with the introduction of a number of applications, including religious calendars and Koran downloads. Nokia made a concerted effort to appeal to Muslims starting in 2007, when it introduced a phone for the Middle East and North Africa markets that came loaded with a number of applications, including an Islamic Organizer with alarms for the five daily prayers, two Islamic e-books and an e-card application that lets people send SMS greeting cards for Ramadan. Starting this year, the company has been giving customers the choice of which applications they want, rather than loading them all on the phone.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/30/business/30product.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Procter, Colgate and Unilever Profit as Brands Sell Again<date>Published: April 29, 2010</date><text>Brand-name consumer products companies, by cutting prices, introducing products and pumping up promotions, are starting to win back shoppers who traded down to store brands.Procter &amp; Gamble, Colgate-Palmolive and Unilever all showed strong sales growth in Thursday’s quarterly report, although P.&amp; G.’s results were hurt by charges, including some from the American health care overhaul. Colgate was hit by Venezuela’s currency devaluation. While consumers are still minding their budgets, the rising sales are an encouraging, if tentative, sign of economic rebound after more than a year of steep shopper cuts. “These are companies that sell everyday household products,” said Jack Russo of Edward Jones, who covers Procter and Colgate. “Procter has been introducing products that have more of a value equation. I wouldn’t say that consumers are jumping back in on the premium products.” The three companies’ sales surged over all, particularly in emerging markets and after price cuts meant to lure consumers back from cheaper private label and store brands. Colgate shares rose 19 cents in afternoon trading but finished the day down 20 cents to $84, while Procter was off 97 cents, or 1.5 percent, to $62.20. Procter &amp; Gamble is trying to combine brand strength with lower-price alternatives. The company, which makes Tide detergent and Pampers diapers, said revenue rose 7 percent, to $19.2 billion, while profit dipped 1 percent to $2.59 billion, or 83 cents a share, with a charge of 5 cents a share for costs from health care changes in its third fiscal quarter. Colgate-Palmolive, maker of Colgate toothpaste, Palmolive dishwashing liquid and Ajax cleanser, said revenue rose more than 9 percent, to $3.83 billion. But first-quarter earnings fell 30 percent, to $357 million, or 69 cents a share, after the company took a charge for the currency changes in Venezuela, an important South American market. Unilever, the maker of Lipton tea, Dove soap and Ben &amp; Jerry’s ice cream, reported a 33 percent jump in first-quarter profit and a revenue increase of 6.7 percent. Unilever and Procter had to cut some prices because people were more apt to trade down to off-brand household products than health or beauty goods, said David Kolpak, managing director at Victory Capital Management in Cleveland.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/business/29product.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">P.&amp;G. and Colgate Post Higher Sales in Quarter<date>Published: January 28, 2010</date><text>The Procter &amp; Gamble Company and the Colgate-Palmolive Company increased sales in the last quarter, as a tentative recovery in consumer spending helped both consumer goods leaders post better-than-expected results on Thursday. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Jin Lee/Bloomberg News Procter &amp; Gamble's Downy fabric softener at a New York store. P.&amp; G. posted better-than-expected quarterly earnings. Related Times Topics: Procter &amp; Gamble Company | Colgate-Palmolive Company Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Go to your Portfolio » Profit at Procter &amp; Gamble, the maker of Tide laundry detergent and Pampers diapers, fell less than analysts had anticipated. A higher profit at Colgate, the toothpaste and household cleaner maker, was stronger than analysts had expected. “This idea that this economy is causing everyone to trade down is a little bit overly general and too broadly applied,” Procter &amp; Gamble’s chief executive, Robert A. McDonald, said during a conference call. Still, the companies stood by their 2010 profit forecasts as they digested new concerns like the effect from the devaluation of the bolivar in Venezuela. “It’s encouraging, there’s no question,” a JPMorgan analyst, John Faucher said of the results from the two companies. As raw material prices rebound, however, “they’re not going to put up this kind of upside without some acceleration in top-line growth going forward,” he said. Procter &amp; Gamble said sales should rise more than it previously expected this year. Both companies have felt pressure since late 2007 as consumers bought less expensive products to save money. But Colgate’s portfolio has been more resistant to such trends because most of its products, like toothpaste and soap, are less discretionary. Procter &amp; Gamble said it earned $4.66 billion, or $1.49 a share, down from $5 billion, or $1.58 a share, a year earlier. Analysts, on average, expected it to earn $1.42 a share. Sales in the period, which ended Dec. 31 and was the second quarter of Procter &amp; Gamble’s fiscal year, rose 6.4 percent, to $21.03 billion, from $19.76 billion, falling short of analysts’ forecast of $21.07 billion. Organic sales, which exclude the effect of currency fluctuations, acquisitions and divestitures, rose 5 percent, as did the volume of goods sold. Shares of Procter &amp; Gamble, which is based in Cincinnati, rose 87 cents, to $61.68. Colgate said it earned $631 million, or $1.21 a share, up 27 percent from $497 million, or 94 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales in the period, Colgate’s fourth quarter, rose 11.4 percent, to $4.08 billion from $3.66 billion, while the volume of goods sold increased 3 percent. Analysts, on average, expected a profit of $1.18 a share on $4.08 billion in sales. Shares of Colgate, which is based in New York, fell 47 cents, to $79.92. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 29, 2010, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/30/business/30procter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate and P.&amp;G. Beat Forecast<date>Published: October 29, 2009</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive reported a rise in profit on Thursday after it and other companies raised prices in the past year to cover higher ingredient costs. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Go to your Portfolio » Procter &amp; Gamble, meanwhile, reported a slight drop in profit, but the results were better than analysts had expected. It also forecast a better outlook after a year in which households cut spending and traded down to cheaper brands. Procter &amp; Gamble, whose brands include Tide and Pampers, reported Thursday that its profit was down 1 percent at $3.35 billion, or 1.06 a share, compared with $3.31 billion, or $1.03 a share, a year ago. Sales fell 6 percent to $19.8 billion, from $20.98 billion. Analysts expected the company to report a profit of 99 cents on sales of $19.83 billion. Separately, Colgate-Palmolive said that it earned $590 million, or $1.12 a share, in the quarter that ended in September. A year ago, Colgate earned $500 million, or 94 cents a share. Revenue rose to $4 billion from $3.99 billion, helped by a 5 percent rise in prices worldwide. Analysts polled by Thomson Reuters expected $1.11 a share and revenue of $3.94 billion. The amount of products sold rose 1.5 percent as consumers appeared willing to spend more for their products. Colgate’s brands are staples, like its namesake toothpaste and soap. Procter &amp; Gamble makes consumer staples, but it also sells discretionary items, such as fragrances, which shoppers are less likely to buy right now. Procter &amp; Gamble cut prices across 10 percent of its broad portfolio and stepped up advertising focused on offering value. Procter &amp; Gamble shares rose $2.31, or 4 percent, to $59.54. Colgate-Palmolive’s stock was up $1.26, or 1.6 percent, to $78.94. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 30, 2009, on page B6 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/17/business/energy-environment/17green.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Fight Grows Over Labels on Household Cleaners<date>Published: September 16, 2009</date><text>Procter &amp; Gamble, the maker of Mr. Clean, is under pressure to come clean itself. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Tony Cenicola/The New York Times The label on Clorox Green Works more than once makes a point of coming across to consumers as environmentally friendly. Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Clorox Co Go to your Portfolio » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Manufacturers of detergents, household cleansers and furniture polish, like Procter &amp; Gamble, Colgate-Palmolive and others, are facing questions from consumers about the chemicals in their products. While many of the chemicals are present only in small amounts, some have been associated with asthma, birth defects and fertility problems in higher doses. And even if the amounts are low, consumer groups say, what is the effect of using these products over a lifetime? The questions have left the industry in an awkward position. It wants to be seen as environmentally sensitive and consumer-friendly. But at the same time, companies do not want to give competitors and makers of cheap knock-offs all the details of what goes into Pine-Sol, for instance, or Windex. So they have been working with consumer groups to devise a plan that could satisfy both sides. Come January, the industry has said it will voluntarily start to disclose much of what is in its cleaning products, which now represent a $14 billion-a-year business. Consumers will be able to call an 800 number, look at a Web site or, in some cases, simply check the product label to find the ingredients. The industry’s plan has been praised by consumer groups as a step in the right direction. “The voluntary plan is not perfect, but it is worlds ahead of where the industry was before,” said Alexandra Scranton, director of science and research at Women’s Voices for the Earth, a nonprofit group that published a study in 2007, “Household Hazards,” that catalogued potential health risks. “We had been talking about this issue for years, and now it is being fast-tracked.” But whether it goes far enough for some critics is another question. Procter &amp; Gamble, Colgate-Palmolive and other major companies have been sued in New York State by consumer groups seeking fuller disclosure. A measure has been introduced in Congress to require ingredient disclosure on all product labels. And in California, which has led the nation in passing “green chemistry” laws, an influential Democrat, State Senator Joe Simitian, said he would press for mandatory disclosure if the voluntary effort came up short. The government now requires only that ingredients posing an immediate danger be reported on product labels. Representative Steve Israel, Democrat of New York, argues that consumers have a right to know what is in the products in the kitchen and bathroom cabinets. He introduced the mandatory labeling bill. “The cleaning industry uses five billion pounds of chemicals in the United States, and we have little to no idea of what chemicals are inside these products,” he said. “It’s nonsensical that we have labels on food, but not on the cleansers on kitchen counters.” Mr. Israel’s measure has been criticized by the Consumer Specialty Products Association, a lobbying group for the industry that has been working with consumer advocacy groups to devise a plan that both can live with. So far, the association has been able to get entities as diverse as the Sierra Club and Procter &amp; Gamble to support the voluntary effort. “We’ve been working on this issue for years,” said Phil Klein, senior vice president for the industry association. “We’re trying to find a balance to protect confidentiality and product formulations with the need to be more transparent as to what’s in these products.” There are still points of contention. The voluntary industry plan covers four product categories  air fresheners, automotive care, household cleaners and floor polishes. It would require that all ingredients be listed in descending order of concentration, but amounts of less than 1 percent would not have to be ranked. Preservatives, fragrances and dyes  crucial ingredients that differentiate products but can contain potentially hazardous chemicals  are exempt from disclosure plan. Big fights are breaking out over small amounts of chemicals, since that is what the industry says is the “secret sauce” that makes products special  putting the lemony smell into Lemon Pledge, for instance. “Chemicals that make up 30 percent of a product are not the secret,” said Tom Neltner, co-chairman of the Sierra Club’s Toxic Committee. “But chemicals that represent only one-half or a quarter percent  anything below 1 percent is where the information becomes really confidential and proprietary.” That, he continued, is “the nub of negotiations right now. We care because if 99.5 percent of a product is water, and the last part is a fragrance that really hurts someone with asthma, we want to know.” 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 17, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/30/business/30colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate’s Profit Beats Expectations<date>Published: January 29, 2009</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company posted a higher-than-expected quarterly profit on Thursday, aided by growth in emerging markets. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Go to your Portfolio » Executives said they were comfortable with analysts’ expectations, on average, of earnings growth on a per-share basis of 9.3 percent. That is below the double-digit growth forecast that Colgate gave in late October. “Despite hearing about a gloomy macro outlook on consumer demand into 2009, Colgate thankfully affirmed the Street’s outlook,” said Jason Gere, an analyst at Wachovia. Colgate and other household product makers have sought to keep up interest in their brands as cash-conscious shoppers opt for lower-price items. Colgate said it had not seen meaningful growth of cheaper private-label items in its categories. Colgate said its toothpaste gained market share in countries including the United States, Mexico, Brazil and China during the quarter. The company is introducing new toothpastes, Speed Stick deodorants and other products to attract American consumers. The company expects to start benefiting from lower commodity and oil costs in the first and second quarters, helping alleviate the pressure of a stronger dollar, which lowers the value of international sales. Despite some easing costs, Colgate plans to raise some prices in 2009, including an increase of about 10.5 percent on Hill’s pet food. Colgate said profit rose to $497 million, or 94 cents a share in the fourth quarter, from $414.9 million, or 77 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding revamping charges, Colgate earned $1 a share, up from 91 cents a year earlier and topping analysts’ average forecast of 98 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Sales rose 0.5 percent, to $3.66 billion, from $3.64 billion. Volume rose 1 percent. Colgate said it cut back on advertising spending in line with its competitors and got lower media rates in many markets around the world. It expects advertising spending as a percentage of sales to be roughly flat in 2009. Analysts, on average, expect Colgate to earn $4.08 to $4.35 a share this year. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/31/business/31colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Reports Quarterly Profit Up 19%<date>Published: October 30, 2008</date><text>NEW YORK (Reuters)  Colgate-Palmolive reported a 19 percent increase in its quarterly profit on Thursday and gave a positive forecast through next year, aided by price increases and demand in emerging markets. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Go to your Portfolio » Results encouraged investors who were cautious about the personal care sector after its competitor Procter &amp; Gamble lowered its forecasts the day before. “Colgate, like P.&amp; G., is very exposed overseas, and possibly even more so, to some of the currencies that are more volatile right now,” a Morningstar analyst, Lauren DeSanto, said, but added that Colgate was not as exposed on the commodity side as P.&amp; G. Colgate said a benefit from declining oil prices should offset the impact on results from the strengthening dollar, which lowers the value of international sales. On Thursday, Colgate said that it had seen little evidence of consumers opting for lower-price goods over its brands and that it had gained share in worldwide markets for toothpaste, toothbrushes, mouth rinse, bar soaps and shampoo. Colgate shares rose 7.1 percent to $64.23, while Procter &amp; Gamble was up 2.9 percent at $63.08. Colgate profit rose to $499.9 million, or 94 cents a share, in the third quarter, from $420.1 million, or 77 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding revamping charges, the company earned 99 cents a share, higher than the analysts’ average forecast of 98 cents, according to Reuters Estimates. Sales for the quarter were $3.99 billion, up 13 percent from $3.5 billion in the same quarter a year ago. Price increases accounted for 6.5 percentage points of the increase, while a weaker dollar made up 3.5 points. Volume rose 3 percent. For 2009, Colgate said it expected gross margin to be “up solidly” as higher prices, cost-cutting and benefits from lower oil and commodities costs offset a strengthening dollar. It said it expected earnings per share to increase by a double-digit percentage rate. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/30/business/30colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate’s Sales Rise Despite Higher Prices<date>Published: July 30, 2008</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive raised prices by 4.5 percent in its second quarter, the biggest increase in more than a decade, without suffering a slowdown in either sales or profit, the company said on Tuesday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Go to your Portfolio » Colgate, maker of its namesake toothpaste, Hill’s Science Diet pet food and Tom’s of Maine personal care items, said that its second-quarter profit rose 19 percent on strong sales worldwide, as the price increases helped offset rising input costs. The company forecast double-digit growth in per-share earnings for next year. In the second quarter, the company earned $493.8 million, or 92 cents a share, compared with $415.8 million, or 76 cents, a year ago. Excluding reorganization costs, Colgate earned $523.3 million, or 98 cents a share, in the latest quarter. Revenue rose 16 percent, to $3.96 billion, from $3.41 billion. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial, who typically exclude one-time charges like revamping costs, had expected earnings of 94 cents a share and revenue of $3.84 billion, on average. The company used a combination of higher pricing, cost-cutting and the addition of higher-margin products to “almost completely” offset sharply rising raw materials and packaging costs, the chief executive, Ian M. Cook, said in a statement. Shares of Colgate rose $5.59, or 8.2 percent, to $74.15. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/13/business/13habit.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Warning: Habits May Be Good for You<date>Published: July 13, 2008</date><text>A FEW years ago, a self-described “militant liberal” named Val Curtis decided that it was time to save millions of children from death and disease. So Dr. Curtis, an anthropologist then living in the African nation of Burkina Faso, contacted some of the largest multinational corporations and asked them, in effect, to teach her how to manipulate consumer habits worldwide. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Colgate-Palmolive Company Pfizer Inc Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Val Curtis Val Curtiss hand-washing campaign began in 2003 in Ghana. Dr. Curtis, now the director of the Hygiene Center at the London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, had spent years trying to persuade people in the developing world to wash their hands habitually with soap. Diseases and disorders caused by dirty hands  like diarrhea  kill a child somewhere in the world about every 15 seconds, and about half those deaths could be prevented with the regular use of soap, studies indicate. But getting people into a soap habit, it turns out, is surprisingly hard. To overcome this hurdle, Dr. Curtis called on three top consumer goods companies to find out how to sell hand-washing the same way they sell Speed Stick deodorant and Pringles potato chips. She knew that over the past decade, many companies had perfected the art of creating automatic behaviors  habits  among consumers. These habits have helped companies earn billions of dollars when customers eat snacks, apply lotions and wipe counters almost without thinking, often in response to a carefully designed set of daily cues. “There are fundamental public health problems, like hand washing with soap, that remain killers only because we can’t figure out how to change people’s habits,” Dr. Curtis said. “We wanted to learn from private industry how to create new behaviors that happen automatically.” The companies that Dr. Curtis turned to  Procter &amp; Gamble, Colgate-Palmolive and Unilever  had invested hundreds of millions of dollars finding the subtle cues in consumers’ lives that corporations could use to introduce new routines. If you look hard enough, you’ll find that many of the products we use every day  chewing gums, skin moisturizers, disinfecting wipes, air fresheners, water purifiers, health snacks, antiperspirants, colognes, teeth whiteners, fabric softeners, vitamins  are results of manufactured habits. A century ago, few people regularly brushed their teeth multiple times a day. Today, because of canny advertising and public health campaigns, many Americans habitually give their pearly whites a cavity-preventing scrub twice a day, often with Colgate, Crest or one of the other brands advertising that no morning is complete without a minty-fresh mouth. A few decades ago, many people didn’t drink water outside of a meal. Then beverage companies started bottling the production of far-off springs, and now office workers unthinkingly sip bottled water all day long. Chewing gum, once bought primarily by adolescent boys, is now featured in commercials as a breath freshener and teeth cleanser for use after a meal. Skin moisturizers  which are effective even if applied at high noon  are advertised as part of morning beauty rituals, slipped in between hair brushing and putting on makeup. “OUR products succeed when they become part of daily or weekly patterns,” said Carol Berning, a consumer psychologist who recently retired from Procter &amp; Gamble, the company that sold $76 billion of Tide, Crest and other products last year. “Creating positive habits is a huge part of improving our consumers’ lives, and it’s essential to making new products commercially viable.” Through experiments and observation, social scientists like Dr. Berning have learned that there is power in tying certain behaviors to habitual cues through relentless advertising. As this new science of habit has emerged, controversies have erupted when the tactics have been used to sell questionable beauty creams or unhealthy foods. But for activists like Dr. Curtis, this emerging research offers a type of salvation. For years, many public health campaigns that aimed at changing habits have been failures. Earlier this decade, two researchers affiliated with Vanderbilt University examined more than 100 studies on the effectiveness of antidrug campaigns and found that, in some cases, viewers’ levels of drug abuse actually increased when commercials were shown, perhaps in part because the ads reminded them about that bag of weed in the sock drawer. 1 2 3 4 Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/01/business/01consumer.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Mixed Results for Makers of Products for the Home<date>Published: May 1, 2008</date><text>Makers of household consumer and food products reported mixed results Wednesday, as they raised prices on everything from hot dogs to toothpaste to offset soaring energy and ingredient costs. The Procter &amp; Gamble Company, the maker of Pampers diapers and Gillette razors, said that higher retail prices, cost controls and strong growth in emerging markets helped lift its third-quarter profit 8 percent. The company also raised its full-year outlook, sending its shares up 3 percent. A. G. Lafley, the chief executive, said the company remains optimistic about sustaining its growth because of daily uses for its many household brands such as Charmin toilet paper, Crest toothpaste and Tide detergent. “Virtually everything we sell is not discretionary; it’s a staple,” Mr. Lafley said on a conference call. Procter &amp; Gamble, based in Cincinnati, said it expects costs to keep climbing, has increased spending on marketing, and will raise more prices this summer. Its rival, the Colgate-Palmolive Company, whose products include its namesake toothpaste and dish soap, said first-quarter earnings fell 4 percent as the company took restructuring charges and a higher provision for income taxes. Colgate, based in New York, said rising materials costs were offset by higher prices, but that margins would be pressured as the cost of raw materials keeps rising. Analysts questioned Colgate-Palmolive executives on whether they had been slow to lift prices and to anticipate the impact of rising costs for agricultural commodities. The company will raise Colgate toothpaste prices by 9 percent this summer. “If gross margin pressures persist, one leg of the Colgate growth stool falls off, which could start to impact growth as advertising spending is reduced,” a Deutsche Bank analyst, Bill Schmitz Jr., said in a note to clients. Colgate-Palmolive reported solid growth in Latin American markets and said its toothpaste business was strong in China, India and Russia. Among food companies, the Kellogg Company’s first-quarter profit fell 2 percent, despite recent price increases by the company, which makes cereal, Pop-Tarts toaster pastries and Eggo frozen waffles. Kellogg, based in Battle Creek, Mich., raised wholesale prices an average of 3.2 percent across much of its product portfolio, said a spokeswoman, Kris Charles. Prices went up for snacks at the end of December and for cereal and frozen products in late January. At Kraft Foods, the nation’s largest food and beverage maker, first-quarter earnings fell 13 percent, also amid higher costs for ingredients. Kraft, which makes Oscar Mayer hot dogs, Maxwell House coffee and Oreo cookies, benefited from nearly across-the-board price increases. Kraft’s profit decline also came because earnings in the same period last year were raised by a one-time benefit related to the company’s spinoff from the Altria Group. Kraft is based in Northfield, Ill. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/06/business/06suits.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Life and Death at the Opening Bell<date>Published: April 6, 2008</date><text>When the leaders of a health care business and a coffin maker teamed up to ring the opening bell at the New York Stock Exchange last week, traders may have wondered if they were witnessing some kind of April Fool’s prank. Skip to next paragraph Michael Falco for The International Herald Tribune Peter B. Cameron Was the spectacle a metaphor for what was happening in the health care industry, or on the Street? No, it was entirely literal. The celebrants were Peter H. Soderberg , chief executive of Hill-Rom Holdings, and Kenneth A. Camp, chief of Hillenbrand. The two businesses began trading as separate companies that day. Hill-Rom deals in medical technology and equipment. Hillenbrand is the parent company of Batesville Casket, which positions itself as “a leader in the North American deathcare industry.” Before Tuesday, Hill-Rom and Batesville Casket were units of Hillenbrand Industries, based in Batesville, Ind. Separating them, Mr. Soderberg said, “is the best way to unlock value and allow each company to focus on accelerating growth in their respective industries.” BRUCE FELTON FINAL TOAST Peter B. Cameron moved from the kitchen to the dining room when he went from All-Clad to Waterford Wedgwood, but now he’s out the door. After a little more than two and a half years as chief executive, Mr. Cameron, who is 60, left the Irish luxury goods company last week. He and the company released a statement saying he would “pursue his own business interests.” David W. Sculley will be the interim C.E.O. At Waterford Wedgwood, Mr. Cameron collaborated with Martha Stewart and other designers and promoted outsourcing. But the weak dollar has hurt the company, it could not meet Christmas demand, and sales are expected to be down 4 percent for the year ended March 31, to $1.1 billion. Last November, the company said it would cut half of its roughly 1,000 jobs near Waterford. KAREN FREEMAN NOW THAT’S A REFUND Lawrence J. Ellison, the billionaire chief of Oracle, just added $3 million to his wealth, thanks to the San Mateo County Assessor’s Office in California. The office recently ordered the return of $3 million in taxes that Mr. Ellison had paid on his 23-acre estate in Woodside, Calif. In 2004, the county assessed the property at $163 million, but Mr. Ellison’s holding company, Octopus Holdings, later had it appraised at $64 million. In agreeing to the lower valuation, the assessor’s office said that the estate, with its 16th-century Japanese architecture, suffered from “functional obsolescence” that would limit its appeal to buyers. LAURIE FLYNN REDOING THE MATH VeriFone, a maker of payment technology like PIN cards and checkout counter credit card machines, said last week that it “did not maintain effective internal control over financial reporting,” according to a company statement on Wednesday. The lapse, revealed in an internal audit, included the overstatement of $37 million in operating income for the first three quarters of 2007 and double-counting of some inventory. It also resulted in the resignation of Barry Zwarenstein, its chief financial officer, who will leave his post after a restatement of earnings is completed. The Securities and Exchange Commission has “indicated an interest in interviewing several current and former VeriFone officers and employers,” the statement said. A company spokesman did not return calls seeking comment. STACEY STOWE IT REALLY ADDS UP Reuben Mark, who retired as chief executive of Colgate-Palmolive in July after 23 years, is standing for re-election as the company’s chairman one more time on May 8. But he will not have to worry that any decision he makes could jeopardize his substantial nest egg. Mr. Mark, 69, has already cashed out his pension, collecting $36 million plus an annuity that will pay him more than $160,000 a year. He also had a gain of $149 million from exercising options on Colgate’s stock and an additional $32 million from the vesting of previous stock awards. Along with more than $3 million in cash pay, that means Mr. Mark can spend some of his golden years deciding what to do with at least $220 million, before taxes. PATRICK McGEEHAN RESISTANT TO SPIN Many C.E.O.’s are known for putting a positive spin on negative news, but that is becoming harder to do. The C.E.O. Confidence Index, measured by Chief Executive magazine since 2002, plunged to a record low last month. Not mincing words, 52 percent of top chiefs surveyed called current business conditions downright “bad.” No word on whether the magazine plans to add choices like “truly abysmal” or “utterly hopeless” to the survey, just in case “bad” ends up becoming business as usual. PHYLLIS KORKKI More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/01/business/01procter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Higher Profits for P.&amp;G. and Colgate<date>Published: February 1, 2008</date><text>Two makers of household and personal care products  Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate-Palmolive  both reported higher quarterly profits on Thursday, relying on sales in emerging markets as the United States economy slowed. Colgate shares rose $3.19, to $76.69. Procter &amp; Gamble shares were up less  33 cents, to $65.42  after the company said earnings for the current quarter would be below analysts’ estimates. Procter &amp; Gamble also announced plans to make its Folgers coffee business a separate company with stock offered to shareholders. An analyst at Goldman Sachs, Amy L. Chasen, said in a research note that Colgate’s results looked much better and could increase the focus on Procter &amp; Gamble’s weaker third-quarter outlook. Like many consumer products companies, Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate are being hit by soaring prices for energy and raw materials. Both have cut overhead costs and increased prices to help offset the rising commodity costs. Both companies sell toothpaste, soap and pet food, but Procter &amp; Gamble’s products also include things like coffee, paper towels and razors, making it more exposed to rising costs than Colgate, analysts said. “P.&amp; G. manufactures a much broader assortment of products, and their exposure is going to be greater,” an analyst at Morningstar, Lauren DeSanto, said. Procter &amp; Gamble posted a 14 percent increase in net income to $3.27 billion for its second quarter, which ended Dec. 31. Earnings were 98 cents a share, compared with the average analysts’ estimate of 97 cents compiled by Reuters Estimates. Sales rose 9 percent to $21.6 billion, helped by the weaker dollar, which increased the dollar value of overseas sales. The company had strong sales growth in China, Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East and Africa, a spokesman said. Those increases came as American growth slowed, the company said during a conference call with analysts, though the company said it had not been losing customers to lower-priced private-label brands. Colgate, meanwhile, said fourth-quarter profit rose to $414.9 million, a 3.4 percent increase, with sales up 13.5 percent to $3.64 billion. Excluding revamping charges, earnings were 91 cents a share. Analysts on average had forecast 89 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. The company is in the latter stages of a four-year overhaul aimed at oral care, personal care and pet food and is using the savings to help increase spending on marketing. Colgate also set a new plan to repurchase 30 million shares over the next two years. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/18/nyregion/18landmark.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Seeking $30 Million to Renovate, Church Finds Help in Neighbors<date>Published: December 18, 2007</date><text>Foiled long ago in its plan to raise money by replacing its landmark community house with a 59-story office tower, St. Bartholomew’s Episcopal Church on Park Avenue is now passing the plate among the very neighbors whose views would have been sliced by the skyscraper. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image New lighting is part of the plan in the $30 million capital campaign undertaken by St. Bartholomews Church, on Park Avenue. And the plate is coming back with hundreds of thousands of dollars in it. Corporate neighbors to the north, south, east and west have all responded to St. Bartholomew’s $30 million capital campaign. The goals are to repair the failing exterior mosaic tiles of its colorful dome, to fix faulty drains that have led to major water damage, to better light the sacred space, to restore the terrace, and to create a new entrance serving both the church and the adjoining community house, the future of which is secure. The church is appealing for help to New York as a whole, arguing that its presence in Midtown  its cafe, its social services, its cultural programs, its artistic patrimony and the breathing room it creates in the canyon of Park Avenue  is a civic resource. “We don’t belong here, taking up space, unless we’re open to the city and useful,” said the Rev. William McD. Tully, the rector. This approach contrasts with a bitter landmark battle in the 1980s and early ’90s, when St. Bartholomew’s sought to redevelop the community house site, saying that the income from leasing its land would further its ministry. The Landmarks Preservation Commission said no. The fight went to the Supreme Court, which refused to hear the church’s constitutional challenge to its landmark designation. The outcome was seen as a victory for historic preservation, but the episode drained and divided the congregation. And the church itself, between 50th and 51st Streets, suffered from years of inattention. That is why the Conrad N. Hilton Foundation has given $1 million toward the restoration of the dome, on behalf of the Waldorf-Astoria, immediately to the south. “If you don’t fix it now, then it’s going to be either extremely expensive to repair in the future or it could get to the point where you couldn’t salvage what’s there,” said Steven M. Hilton, president and chief executive of the foundation. Conceding that such a gift seemed to be outside the foundation’s central humanitarian mission, Mr. Hilton nevertheless found a link. “St. Bart’s is more than a church,” he said. “They serve something close to 80,000 meals a year to the homeless, and they have a 10-bed shelter. So you’d say, indirectly, the things St. Bart’s is doing touch on one of our key interests.” Rudin Management Company, the owner of office buildings north and west of the church, recognizes St. Bartholomew’s as an important institution and wants to be a “good neighbor,” said John J. Gilbert III, the chief operating officer. He declined to specify the amount given. From the opposite side of Park Avenue, contributions have also come from the Colgate-Palmolive Company, with headquarters at No. 300, and the Mutual of America Life Insurance Company, at No. 320. Most recently, the New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation gave $200,000 to help restore the dome. Mr. Tully arrived as rector in 1994, after the landmark debacle had played out. His first priority, he said, was to rebuild church membership. Attendance at Sunday services has increased to 800 or 900, he said, from 150 or so in the mid-90s. Now, the rector is focused on rehabilitating the 1918 main church, designed by Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue, and the 1928 community house. Murphy Burnham &amp; Buttrick Architects prepared a master plan for the church in 2004 that identified about $100 million worth of needed work. Then the architects winnowed the menu down to the more urgent items. Slightly more than $17 million has been raised since the capital campaign was announced in October, Mr. Tully said. Most of the money has come from within the parish. He added that St. Bartholomew’s still had to struggle against its image as a wealthy congregation, earned during the days when Vanderbilts worshiped there. The current endowment, about $6 million, is one-third of what it was before the landmark fight, he said. Mr. Tully said the opening of Café St. Bart’s in 1995  a year after contingency plans were developed to close the ailing church  drew employees from the companies that are now supporting the renovation. “The cafe, in a single stroke, projected to the street a sense of life,” he said. For the future, Mr. Tully envisions a place that would act as a forum for public debate and as a 24-hour-a-day sanctuary, for people of any faith or no faith. “If you can’t get in anywhere else,” he said, “there’s some place you can always get in. And there’s always a light on.” More Articles in New York Region »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/31/business/31goods.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Quarterly Profits Climb for Colgate and Procter &amp; Gamble<date>Published: October 31, 2007</date><text>CINCINNATI, Oct. 30 (AP)  Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate-Palmolive reported big jumps in quarterly profits Tuesday. But the two consumer product companies stocks headed in opposite directions after P.&amp; G. issued a cautious outlook in the face of rising commodity costs and consumer uncertainty. Shares of Colgate, based in New York, rose 1.4 percent after the company, the maker of Colgate toothpaste, Palmolive dishwashing liquid and Irish Spring soap, posted a 22 percent increase in profit for the third quarter. Shares of P.&amp; G., Colgates bigger Cincinnati-based competitor, whose brands include Tide detergent, Gillette shavers and Crest toothpaste, dropped by 4 percent after P.&amp; G. reported a 14 percent profit rise for its first fiscal quarter. Colgates earnings climbed to $420.1 million, or 77 cents a share, for the quarter that ended Sept. 30 from $344.1 million, or 63 cents a share, the previous year. Excluding charges, including some for reorganization, earnings totaled $466.4 million, or 86 cents a share, compared with $402.6 million, or 73 cents a share, a year earlier. On that basis, analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had expected net income of 85 cents a share on sales of $3.48 billion. Quarterly revenue rose 12 percent to $3.53 billion, from $3.14 billion in the prior year, Colgate said. P.&amp; G. said its net income grew to $3.08 billion, or 92 cents a share, from $2.7 billion, or 79 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding a German tax benefit of 2 cents a share, the company earned 90 cents a share in the latest period, a penny more than analysts had expected. Sales rose 8 percent to $20.2 billion, from $18.79 billion a year ago. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had expected revenue of $20.23 billion. P.&amp; G. expects margins to be lower temporarily because of higher commodity and energy costs and investments in concentrated formulas of Tide and other liquid detergents. P.&amp; G. plans to pass along some of its rising costs for oil and raw materials by raising prices on products including Pampers diapers, Charmin toilet paper and Olay and Ivory personal cleansing products. Both companies reported broad-based growth and strong overseas sales, helped by the weaker dollar. P.&amp; G. shares were down $2.88 to $68.95. Colgate shares rose $1, to $75.26. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/26/business/26colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Profit Rises 47% on Better Margins<date>Published: July 26, 2007</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 47 percent as it improved profit margins, cut costs and increased market share through record spending on advertising. The chief executive, Ian M. Cook, said he expected earnings growth of at least 10 percent a share to continue in the second half of the year. Net income rose to $415.8 million, or 76 cents a share, up from $283.6 million, or 51 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding reorganization charges, income in the most recent quarter was $457.5 million, or 84 cents a share, matching the forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sales totaled $3.41 billion, up from $3.01 billion a year earlier. Spending on personal care products was steady despite higher gas prices and declining home prices that have hurt sales of many household products. Were certainly seeing no slowdown in consumer purchasing, Mr. Cook said in a conference call. Mr. Cook said Colgate planned a global introduction of its Toms of Maine products next year. He declined to offer more details about the introduction or about which markets the company would enter first. Colgate said it increased spending on worldwide advertising by 22 percent and raised its market share for toothpaste in Mexico, Brazil, China, India, France and Russia. Stock in Colgate, which is based in New York, rose $1.41, to $69.66 a share. More Articles in Business »</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/10/nyregion/10paste.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">700 Tubes of Toothpaste Are Seized in Connecticut<date>Published: July 10, 2007</date><text>HARTFORD, July 9  More than 700 tubes of toothpaste containing a chemical used in some antifreeze products have been removed from 6 of 120 stores inspected since July 2, state inspectors said on Monday. The chemical, diethylene glycol, has a sweet taste like its more expensive cousin, glycerin, and can cause liver and kidney damage. So far, no illnesses have been reported in Connecticut. The federal Food and Drug Administration recalled toothpaste labeled Colgate last month and advised consumers to discard all Chinese-made toothpaste, regardless of the brand. Inspectors from the state’s Department of Consumer Protection said they seized 430 tubes of a counterfeit Colgate toothpaste reportedly made in South Africa and 275 tubes of Chinese-made Dentakleen and the strawberry and blueberry flavors of Dentakleen Junior from stores in Hartford, West Hartford, Waterbury, Derby and North Branford. The varieties of the counterfeit Colgate brand, including maximum cavity protection, gel and triple action, are listed as tainted. State officials said inspections would continue this week. Last month, about 900,000 tubes of tainted toothpaste turned up in prisons and other state institutions, mostly in Georgia and North Carolina, and at some hospitals in South Carolina and Florida. The investigation in Connecticut was prompted by a call from a consumer who reported that the toothpaste was still on the shelves of some stores, despite the recall order. The state’s attorney general, Richard Blumenthal, and the commissioner of the Consumer Protection Department, Jerry Farrell Jr., said that they had sent letters to nine distributors and makers of the toothpaste seeking the names of all state retailers who bought the products. “Our demand to Chinese manufacturers is for information necessary to track down and crack down on all these poisonous products,” Mr. Blumenthal said in a statement released by his office on Monday. Mr. Blumenthal, who said he is seeking to lead a coalition of states to protect consumers from defective or tainted products, called federal oversight policy on such imports one of “purposeful neglect.” He advised consumers to avoid buying brands like Cooldent, Dr. Cool, Everfresh, Superdent and Oral Bright. The State Department of Consumer Protection’s Web site, www.ct.gov/dcp, has photographs of the products and lists the names and addresses of the stores that stocked the tainted toothpaste. Mitul Patel, a clerk at the 99 Plus Store on Farmington Avenue here, one of the six stores where the toothpaste was found, said a state worker seized the toothpaste last week. “I hadn’t sold any yet,” said Mr. Patel, standing behind the cash register on Monday afternoon. “He just came down and took it all away.” A 22-year-old woman at the store said she had bought Colgate there, although she had not used it. “When I heard about it, I just threw it away,” she said, adding that she later discovered that it was not one of the counterfeit products. More Articles in New York Region »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EED8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">National Briefing | Recall: Toothpaste Recalled In Scare Over Chemical<date>Published: June 14, 2007</date><text>Five-ounce tubes of toothpaste labeled Colgate and sold in discount stores in four states are being recalled because they may contain a diethylene glycol, a chemical used in antifreeze, the importer said. A Food and Drug Administration official, Doug Arbesfeld, confirmed that the chemical was found in a product with the Colgate label, but he said the agency was unsure if it was Colgate or a counterfeit. The toothpaste was sold in discount stores in New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania and Maryland. ''Made in South Africa'' is printed on the box. Varieties include regular, gel, triple and herbal. The toothpaste may be returned to the place of purchase for a refund, MS USA Trading said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/31/business/31procter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">New Products and Demand in Emerging Markets Fatten Profits at P.&amp; G. and Colgate<date>Published: January 31, 2007</date><text>Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate-Palmolive reported profits yesterday that exceeded analysts estimates on consumer demand for new razors and soap and increased sales to emerging markets. Procter &amp; Gamble, the largest American maker of consumer products, said net income increased 12 percent, to $2.86 billion, or 84 cents a share. The company raised its 2007 profit forecast on demand for Fusion razors and Tide detergent. Colgate said separately that profit rose 11 percent, to $401.2 million, on record sales in Latin America. The companies introduced dozens of new products to entice customers in North America, and sales in countries like China have increased as consumers incomes expand. Emerging markets are an important part of growth for these companies, said Mariann Montagne, an analyst with Thrivent Asset Management in Minneapolis, which oversees $100 billion, including shares of both companies. Population growth and rising disposable incomes make these very attractive markets. Sales at Procter, which is based in Cincinnati, rose 7.6 percent, to $19.7 billion, the slowest pace in five quarters. The company had projected sales growth of 5 percent to 8 percent. Sales at Colgate, based in New York, gained 10 percent, to $3.21 billion. Procters profit beat the 83-cent average estimate of 12 analysts in a Bloomberg survey. Excluding some reorganization costs, Colgate earned 80 cents a share, ahead of the 77-cent estimate. Procter shares dropped 29 cents, to $64.59, on the New York Stock Exchange. Colgate rose 71 cents, to $67.42. Sales at Procter were driven in part by the 2006 introduction of Fusion razors in North America. The five-bladed razor is the companys biggest product introduction since its $57 billion acquisition of Gillette in 2005. A. G. Lafley, Procters chief executive, said he expected the units expertise in marketing razors to help the company sell Olay lotion and Crest toothpaste. Consumers in North America bought more than $400 million in Fusion razors and blades in the year since their introduction. Fusions United States share of the mens razor market was 51 percent, Procters treasurer, John Goodwin, told analysts yesterday in a conference call. Procter increased its 2007 profit forecast to $2.99 to $3.03 a share, up 13 percent to 15 percent from 2006. It earlier projected full-year profit of $2.97 to $3.02. Analysts surveyed by Bloomberg are estimating $3.02 a share. Colgates chief executive, Reuben Mark, introduced new products, helping Colgate increase market share in North America from toothpaste competitors like Procter. Fourth-quarter sales in Latin America, where Colgate has 74 percent of the market, gained 14 percent. Mr. Mark, who became chief in 1984, has focused on categories like oral and personal care, reducing costs and using the savings for advertising and product development. Colgates 2007 profit will increase by at least 10 percent a share, its president, Ian M. Cook, said in October. Mr. Cook will replace Mr. Mark as chief sometime this year. Analysts surveyed by Bloomberg are estimating $3.26 a share. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/17/business/media/17adco.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">In a Battle of Toothpastes, It’s Information vs. Emotion<date>Published: January 17, 2007</date><text>PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE is fighting to be tops in toothpaste again. Skip to next paragraph Colgate-Palmolives campaign to promote the Colgate Total brand features the actress Brooke Shields in her real-life role as a mother. Enlarge This Image The Crest Pro-Health campaign focuses on health benefits. In a bid to regain the sales lead from its rival Colgate-Palmolive, the Procter &amp; Gamble Company has introduced Crest Pro-Health, which claims to deliver in one tube everything a consumer could possibly want in a toothpaste. Procter is backing Pro-Health with a $100 million advertising campaign, its largest spending ever for a new dental product. The campaign, from the longtime Crest agency Saatchi &amp; Saatchi in New York, part of the Publicis Groupe, takes a clinical bent; one TV ad features a real dentist, and another an actor portraying a researcher. Pro-Health is a direct challenge to the strong-selling Colgate Total line introduced in 1997 by the Colgate-Palmolive Company. Total was the first toothpaste to claim that it fights gingivitis, a benefit that let Colgate inch ahead of Crest for the first time in decades. Colgate is fighting back with record advertising spending of its own, for a campaign from the Y &amp; R division of Young &amp; Rubicam Brands, part of the WPP Group. The campaign, which features the actress Brooke Shields in her real-life role as a mother, represents the first time that Colgate Total has used a celebrity in a campaign. By virtue of sheer spending power, people are going to be thinking more about toothpaste than they have in a long time, said Gary M. Stibel, chief executive at the New England Consulting Group. He compared the battle to the free-for-all in the car insurance market among brands like Allstate, Geico, Progressive and State Farm.  The battle of the toothpaste brands illustrates the intensifying warfare in consumer-product categories that are competitive and crowded. A CVS store in Manhattan was carrying 18 types of Colgate Total recently, and Crest Pro-Health comes in several sizes, in mint and cinnamon flavors. In many instances, buyers perceive little difference among such products, so ads often try to entertain consumers or play up brand image while playing down actual attributes. In this case, Procter and Colgate-Palmolive seek to persuade consumers that there are significant distinctions between their toothpastes that could potentially affect health. In contrast to promising simply that its product will help prevent cavities, Procter is claiming that Pro-Health is the only toothpaste that protects against gingivitis, plaque, cavities, sensitivity and stains  and freshens breath, too. Because of the many health claims, it made good sense to have dental experts explain the product in the ads, said Mariana Sanchez, senior vice president at Saatchi &amp; Saatchi. Product packages and some ads also show the caduceus, the medical symbol of snakes entwined on a winged staff. The target customer is quite an information seeker, said Matt Barresi, Procters marketing director for oral health care in North America. The campaign notes that Crest Pro-Health has been accepted by the American Dental Association as being effective at fighting cavities, gingivitis and plaque, as well as reducing sensitivity in teeth and helping to whiten them. To obtain the A.D.A. seal, a marketer must pay for a scientific review. An A.D.A. seal set Crest apart more than five decades ago, when Procter introduced it as the first fluoride toothpaste clinically proved to be, as the association declared, of significant value in fighting cavities, when used in a conscientiously applied program of oral hygiene and regular professional care. Soon after its introduction in 1955, Crest became the subject of one of the most popular ad campaigns of the 20th century, from what was then the Benton &amp; Bowles agency. It featured the artwork of Norman Rockwell and carried the theme, Look, mom  no cavities. The theme of the campaign for Pro-Health, by comparison, is Healthy, beautiful smiles for life. Both Colgate and Procter are flooding dental offices with product samples and informational materials, in the hope of encouraging favorable word of mouth and pushing sales in the slow-growing American toothpaste business. New advertising for Crest Pro-Health will feature real people who have tried and liked the product. Weve gotten an unprecedented amount of testimonials from consumers, Mr. Barresi said.  Rather than focus on science, the Colgate Total ads with Ms. Shields use glamour and emotion, a shift from the products previous campaign, which was centered on its germ-fighting prowess. In commercials for Colgate Total that began in October on TV and online, viewers see Ms. Shields nuzzling and playing with two children as soft music plays in the background. Ms. Shields, a former model who has a history with Colgate, having appeared in a print ad as a child, says: Having a healthy smile is important to me. Not just as an actress, but as a mom. (The children in the spots, however, are actors, not Ms. Shieldss own.) One online showing of the commercial, on the Yahoo home page in late October, received a surprisingly strong response, said Suzan F. Harrison, vice president for United States marketing at Colgate-Palmolive. The Yahoo home page was visited 94 million times that day by 16 million unique visitors, she said, and traffic to the Colgate Total site (colgatetotal.com) jumped 2,000 percent. Crest Pro-Health is already ranked sixth among top-selling toothpaste brands in the United States, according to Information Resources Inc., a market research company. For the 12 weeks that ended Nov. 5, Crest Pro-Health had sales of $13.7 million, the data showed. But Colgate-Palmolive appeared to be protecting its franchise. In the same period, Colgate Total sales jumped 13.8 percent, to $24 million, compared with the same period a year ago, according to Information Resources. (Its information does not include sales figures from Wal-Mart, the largest American retailer, which does not provide data to outside researchers.) At least one dentist approves of both brands. Mark S. Wolff, a professor at the New York University College of Dentistry, called the toothpastes essentially the same and said their claims were valid. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD81031F932A15751C1A9609C8B63&amp;ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">World Business Briefing | Americas: Clorox to Buy Bleach Plants<date>Published: December 21, 2006</date><text>Clorox agreed to buy the Colgate-Palmolive bleach business in six countries -- Canada, Uruguay, Venezuela, Columbia, the Dominican Republic and Ecuador -- for $126 million to expand in Latin America and Canada. The transaction in Canada will be completed this year, while those in Latin America will close in the first quarter of 2007.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/30/technology/30adco.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Marketers Demanding Better Count of the Clicks<date>Published: October 30, 2006</date><text>Internet companies have had great success selling advertising space, in part because the effectiveness of those ads is supposedly so easily measured. But marketers, even as they continue to push more of their ad budgets online, are starting to ask for better proof. Skip to next paragraph Related Addenda (October 30, 2006) A group of large companies, including Kimberly-Clark, Colgate-Palmolive and Ford Motor have said that by the middle of 2007, they will demand that online publishers hire auditors to check their ad and viewer counts. And analysts say they believe that online ad growth over the long haul will depend on the eagerness of large advertisers like these to shift more dollars online. Meanwhile, reacting to advertiser questions, online companies like Google, Yahoo and LookSmart have begun to meet with industry groups to answer basic questions on how click-based advertising works. Other companies are concerned that so-called click fraud may be driving up their ad bills, so they are sharing their proprietary ad data with click-trackers, which try to figure out how prevalent such devious clicks are. There are a variety of motivations behind click fraud. Sometimes, rings of click-fraud participants click on ads on affiliate ad networks  like Google AdSense  so that those sites hosts will make more money (which is sometimes shared with the ring members). Another motivation is to knock a competitors ad off a site early; many ads are posted with an agreement that they will stay up only until they have attracted a certain number of clicks. Even online measurement companies with solid reputations like Nielsen/NetR atings, a unit of VNU, are undergoing new certifications to prove their counts are up to snuff. When you grow up, you have to do certain things, said Mainak Mazumdar, NetRatings vice president of measurement science and product marketing. The Internet has matured to a place where traditional marketers  companies that have been spending much more money on television and print  are asking the questions that they would ask for the print side. I see that to be very positive because it does legitimize the Internet. Internet advertising revenue has grown upward of 30 percent for the last three years, causing many in the print and television businesses to shudder. Traditional media companies have watched advertisers and consumers increasingly move online, and the change has crimped their revenue and bruised their stock prices. Concerns about click fraud and viewer statistics do not appear to be affecting online advertising revenue right now, but ad agency executives said the issues must be resolved before large advertisers would want to pour much more money online. Indeed, the Internet draws only a sliver of the total spent on advertisements. Last year, Internet ads accounted for just 4.7 percent, or $12.5 billion, of the $267 billion spent on advertising, according to the Interactive Advertising Bureau, a trade association of online publishers. And the top 50 advertisers spent just 3.8 percent of their budgets in the first half of this year on online ads, excluding search, TNS Media Intelligence data shows. For all other advertisers, the average spent online was 6.8 percent of the budget. Procter &amp; Gamble, the nations biggest advertiser last year, spent $33.5 million  less than 1 percent of its $4.6 billion ad budget  on online ads in 2005. General Motors, the second-biggest advertiser, spent $110.5 million online, or 2.5 percent of its $4.35 billion total, according to TNS, which does not include search ads in its figures. The nature of these organizations is not to be at the leading edge of a major revolution, but rather to take a more measured approach to it, said Jon Swallen, senior vice president of research at TNS. There is a need and desire of those large advertisers for more accountability in their advertising spending decisions. Large established companies, which are mostly interested in furthering their brand recognition online, buy far more display advertisements across the Internet than search ads. Search ads are priced based on how often Internet users click on ads, whereas companies generally pay for display ads based on how many times the ads are viewed by Web users. Recently, video ads have become a hit with large companies, which view the Internet as a new venue for commercials, said Michael Zeman, director of insights and analytics at Starcom IP, the digital media group of Starcom USA. Mr. Zeman said Starcom disregarded most of the metrics reported by Web sites in favor of its own internal estimates of what types of people are visiting what types of sites. Metrics on the sites, he said, are not always reliable. Some media sites, for example, count a person as two unique visitors if that person uses both a home and a work computer to visit that site, he said. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/26/business/26colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate-Palmolive’s Profit Slips but Still Surpasses Forecasts<date>Published: October 26, 2006</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive, the maker of toothpaste, soaps, pet food and other products, said yesterday that its third-quarter profit slipped 1 percent because of restructuring charges. Colgates quarterly net income fell to $344.1 million, or 63 cents a share, compared with $347.2 million, or 63 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding charges related to a restructuring plan, as well as expenses for stock-based compensation, Colgate-Palmolive reported earnings of $421.5 million, or 77 cents a share. That beat the forecast of analysts polled by Thomson Financial, who expected earnings of 72 cents a share for the company, based in New York. The results came despite record spending on advertising worldwide, said the chief executive, Reuben Mark. The company declined to say how much it spent on advertising. Revenue rose 8 percent, to $3.14 billion from $2.91 billion a year ago. Analysts expected $3.08 billion in revenue. Colgate shares rose $1.70, or 2.8 percent, to close at $62.17. A weak spot for pricing was the United States toothpaste market where Colgate, the worlds largest toothpaste maker, was defending itself against the introduction of Crest Pro-Health. That pushed Colgate to spend more on overall advertising. Crest Pro-Healths acceleration is part of a threat from a rival, Procter &amp; Gamble. Its Crest brand toothpastes gained 4.5 percent in sales over the last year as Colgate brands lost 0.3 percent over the 52 weeks that ended Oct. 8, according to data from Information Resources Inc. Colgate brands still hold the sales lead, with about $408 million in total sales over P.&amp; G.s Crest brands $392 million for the same period. Colgate said all five operating divisions reported sales and profit increases. Regional sales showed their greatest strength in Latin America, where revenue grew 15 percent. North American sales rose 2 percent, while Europe and South Pacific sales climbed 7 percent. The company is carrying out a four-year restructuring plan it unveiled in December 2004. Looking ahead, Colgate-Palmolive forecast double-digit growth in earnings per share for 2006 and 2007, excluding restructuring and stock-based compensation charges. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/17/health/17bak.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">With a Product for Sudsing, Some Accidental Sipping<date>Published: October 17, 2006</date><text>A household cleaning product that researchers say looks and smells like a soft drink has been the cause of more than 100 accidental ingestions, according to a study published in the journal Pediatrics in August and presented Sunday at a conference of the American College of Emergency Physicians. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Colgate-Palmolive added a safety cap to its bottle and changed the label after hearing from consumers. Related Web Link Fabuloso: A Cleaning Product That Tastes and Smells Good Enough to Drink (Pediatrics) From Jan. 1 to April 20, researchers found 104 records in the Texas Poison Center database of human ingestion of Fabuloso, manufactured by Colgate-Palmolive. Of these, 94 were unintentional and 2 were occupational exposures. The rest were either related to self-harm or not characterized as to cause. None caused serious harm. Fabuloso is sold in purple, blue, yellow and green varieties, and packaged in one-liter, transparent plastic bottles that resemble soft drink containers. The studys authors say the most common reason for ingestion appeared to have been mistaking the product for a drink. More than 40 percent of the calls to the poison center involved ingestion by people over 12. Three-quarters of those 20 or older who drank it accidentally were women; of those under 6 who drank it, three-quarters were boys. The authors write that Fabuloso is a minor gastrointestinal irritant and unlikely to cause any major morbidity or mortality. The different colors have varying odors, all of them pleasantly fruity. It doesnt taste terrible, said Dr. Marc E. Levsky, a co-author of the study and an assistant program director in the department of emergency medicine at the Carl R. Darnall Army Medical Center in Fort Hood, Tex. Its a detergent solution, and it tastes like soap. Nor is it particularly poisonous. No one would drink more than a sip, said Dr. Levsky, who has tasted the cleaner, and soap is one of the less harmful things you can ingest. Worst case, you get some diarrhea and vomiting. In an e-mail message, Allison Klimerman, a spokeswoman for Colgate-Palmolive, wrote: Fabuloso, a mild cleaning product, has been sold in the United States since 1997 and meets all applicable safety regulations of the federal Consumer Product Safety Commission. Accidental ingestion could result in bad taste in the mouth or an upset stomach. After receiving consumer concerns, she continued, we changed the label to more clearly communicate the intended use of the product with a more prominent picture of a mop and bucket and the words multi-use cleaner in bold type circling the bottle. As an additional precaution, in September 2006, we began manufacturing the product with a difficult-to-open child safety cap, and this product is now reaching full distribution. Asked whether Colgate-Palmolive had any plans to change the smell or color of the product, or the shape or transparency of the bottle, Ms. Klimerman said, We are considering changes to the bottle shape. In a case of accidental ingestion of any product, Dr. Levsky said, call the poison center if you have questions, and they can tell you whether you need to go to the hospital. More Articles in Health »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/25/business/25five.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">G.M. Offers Pay for Its Workers to Go Away<date>Published: March 25, 2006</date><text>KNOCKED on their heels, several companies struggled with setbacks this week. General Motors and Microsoft took steps to cope with problems long in coming, while federal prosecutors were staggered by a reversal in a very visible corporate corruption case. SILVER HANDSHAKES Unable to sell enough cars to keep its employees busy, General Motors offered to pay them to go away. In an agreement with the United Automobile Workers union, G.M. offered $35,000 to $140,000 to its 113,000 employees in North America if they agreed to leave their jobs. It also extended the offer to more than 20,000 employees of its quasi-independent supplier, Delphi. The deal could cost G.M. billions, but the company is racing to fix its business. It lost $10.6 billion last year as sales fell but its fixed costs, including payroll and health care, remained high. G.M. also sold control of its commercial mortgage unit to a group of investors for $1.5 billion in cash and the repayment of about $7.3 billion in intercompany loans. The sale raises much-needed cash. Delphi said that if it could not sharply reduce its wage and benefit costs by the end of this month, it would ask a bankruptcy court judge for permission to impose less-generous terms  a move that could lead to a walkout, which in turn would cripple G.M. REVERSAL OF FORTUNE In a rare reversal of a jury verdict, a federal appeals court overturned the obstruction-of-justice conviction of Frank P. Quattrone, the Silicon Valley-based investment banker who became a symbol of Wall Street excesses during the boom years. A three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in Manhattan, based its decision on the judge's instructions to the jury in the case. It unanimously ruled that the trial judge failed to require that jurors agree that Mr. Quattrone intended to thwart a government investigation when he endorsed a colleague's e-mail message urging his staff to "clean up those files" after regulators began to investigate his firm. The appeals court granted Mr. Quattrone a new trial, but it was unclear if prosecutors would pursue the case, which produced a hung jury at his first trial. The United States attorney's office in Manhattan said it would review the appellate decision and consider its options. MISSING CHRISTMAS Microsoft said that its new computer operating system, Windows Vista, would not be available to consumers before Christmas, as it had planned. Corporate clients should be able to buy the system in November, the company said. Microsoft did not say why it would miss its own deadline of delivering Vista by the end of this year, but trade papers have reported that it has had difficulty in designing and debugging the system, which is particularly complex and power-hungry. Microsoft has said it is determined to make the new software secure against viruses, worms and other malicious software. The delay may disappoint retailers who expected Vista to drive a surge in PC sales this holiday season, analysts said. They added that it could increase sales of Microsoft's Xbox video game consoles over the holidays because consumers might look elsewhere to spend their cash. MERGERS MARCH ON Bayer, the drug and chemical giant best known as the inventor of aspirin, said it would pay nearly $20 billion in cash for a smaller rival, Schering, topping a $17.9 billion offer by Merck of Germany. The offer, which Schering said it would recommend to its shareholders, could help rebuild some of Germany's historic prominence in the pharmaceutical industry. Merck withdrew yesterday, leaving Bayer to complete the takeover unless another suitor enters the fray. Schering and Merck are German companies not related to the American drug giants Schering-Plough and Merck &amp; Company. Bayer's biggest business now is producing polyurethane, polycarbonates and other manufacturing materials, which accounted for about $13 billion in sales last year. Health care products account for less than 40 percent of its revenue, which was about $30.5 billion last year, but the Schering acquisition could make health care the largest part of Bayer, with projected sales of $18 billion a year. FIXING PRICES The Zurich American Insurance Company, the American subsidiary of Zurich Financial Services of Switzerland, agreed to pay $171.7 million to settle accusations of commercial insurance price fixing and bid rigging. Several state attorneys general had sued Zurich and other firms, accusing them of having worked with Marsh &amp; McLennan, the insurance broker, to inflate premiums and pay improper commissions. In related criminal cases, 17 executives at four companies  including 3 at Zurich American  have pleaded guilty to charges related to the scheme. Twenty-four other insurers are named in the civil lawsuit, in Federal District Court in New Jersey. Other settlements are expected soon. COOKING BOOKS Almost three years after regulators accused officers at Gemstar-TV Guide of inflating the company's revenue to reap a windfall from bonuses and stock sales, a federal judge found the former chief executive, Henry C. Yuen, liable for securities fraud. Judge Mariana R. Pfaelzer in Federal District Court in Los Angeles also found Mr. Yuen liable for misrepresenting facts to Gemstar's auditors and falsifying its books. Regulators contend that Mr. Yuen's actions netted him $18.8 million in salary and bonuses, $14.6 million in exercised stock options and more than $63.6 million in sales of Gemstar shares from 2000 to 2002. The Securities and Exchange Commission will now submit a proposed penalty. ETHICS SELL While a few companies dealt with ethical failures, others embraced businesses that made ethical matters central to their marketing. L'Oréal of France agreed to buy Body Shop International for about $1.14 billion, for example, while Colgate-Palmolive acquired an 84 percent stake in Tom's of Maine for $100 million. Body Shop, which sells natural cosmetics, and Tom's, best known for its natural toothpaste, are attractive because consumers are willing to pay more for their products. Colgate's chief operating officer, Ian Cook, said Tom's toothpaste had a gross profit margin 10 percentage points higher than Colgate's. Neither L'Oreal nor Colgate are likely to completely change their strategies, analysts said. As its next acquisition, for example, Colgate is considering an offer for the Listerine brand from Pfizer Inc. MOST VIEWED Following are the most-viewed business news articles on nytimes.com from March 18 through March 24: 1. Why Do So Few Women Reach the Top of Big Law Firms? 2. Major Changes Raise Concerns on Pension Bill 3. G.M. Will Offer Buyouts to All Its Union Workers 4. Microsoft to Delay Next Version of Windows 5. Airline Workers Are Left at Gate, Mourning a Perk Links are at nytimes.com/business. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/05/fashion/sundaystyles/05POSS.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">The Scent of a Man<date>Published: March 5, 2006</date><text>THE camera, one of the most artful and habitual liars ever invented, should never take the stand. And yet wouldn't it be fun to see it break down under cross-examination? Admit its disingenuous ways and woeful inadequacies? Confess that its blank Cyclopean blink is as subjective as a hostile witness? Skip to next paragraph Phil Mansfield for The New York Times The photographer Wolfgang Tillmans likes Speed Stick. It doesn't promise sex," he said. "Just speed." Tony Cenicola/The New York Times Seldom do photographers exploit this weakness. Usually they play it as would a defense lawyer coaching a key witness, carefully prepping the camera with every advantage: lighting, makeup, Photoshop. Wolfgang Tillmans, by contrast, is a traitor to his art. His photographs came to notice, in their slipshod, snapshot, scrapbook style, for suggesting just how short the camera falls at representing whatever it is pointed at. The pictures, whether the imitation grunge fashion shoots that made his name in the mid-1990's or his latest lush abstractions and extreme close-ups  now at P.S. 1 in Long Island City, Queens  never fail to dissatisfy, teetering uneasily between realness and surrealness. Never is that more true than with his male subjects. Many photographers attempt to conjure up an idealized state of masculinity, and Mr. Tillmans has pointed his lens at all manner of men: soldiers, friends in London, himself in the shower. But he does precious little more than point; the burden is on you to interpret. When he came to New York in the mid-90's, Mr. Tillmans was in a bit of the same predicament. Without a clue as to the associations of this restaurant, that jacket or this grooming product (which, like it or not, is often the way we figure out what to wear and where to eat), he just gravitated to what he liked. That is more or less how he, a man who does not really believe in deodorant, stumbled on that emblem of American manhood, Mennen Speed Stick. "I liked the lack of promise," he said. "It doesn't promise sex, or a better standard of living. Just speed." Now whenever he comes to New York, he stocks up, for he can't find it at home in London. Its very plainness is what he finds sexy. "I'm interested in normality," he said. "I find it much more interesting than hypermasculinity." And what better defines American manliness? Introduced in 1958, Speed Stick (now with dozens of variants, including the catastrophic-sounding scents Icy Surge, Clean Blast and Cool Fusion) is the leading men's stick deodorant. After aerosols like Right Guard came under fire in the late 70's, Speed Stick came to own the nation's underarms. Even men who do not use it now remember it as a kind of adolescent rite of passage. "I never went to high school here, so I never knew it would evoke any of that," Mr. Tillmans said, "but I think subconsciously the product communicated that." Maybe it's the smell. A 1962 ad described the scent as "all man!" A Colgate-Palmolive spokeswoman would not divulge the scent's ingredients, but the Speed Stick Regular label calls it a "clean masculine scent." "That seems like a contradiction in terms," Mr. Tillmans said. Indeed. Sanitize it all you want, but masculinity is like the truth: never simple, and never clean. But a little deodorant can't hurt. More Articles in Fashion &amp; Style &gt;THE camera, one of the most artful and habitual liars ever invented, should never take the stand. And yet wouldn't it be fun to see it break down under cross-examination? Admit its disingenuous ways and woeful inadequacies? Confess that its blank Cyclopean blink is as subjective as a hostile witness? Skip to next paragraph Phil Mansfield for The New York Times The photographer Wolfgang Tillmans likes Speed Stick. It doesn't promise sex," he said. "Just speed." Tony Cenicola/The New York Times Seldom do photographers exploit this weakness. Usually they play it as would a defense lawyer coaching a key witness, carefully prepping the camera with every advantage: lighting, makeup, Photoshop. Wolfgang Tillmans, by contrast, is a traitor to his art. His photographs came to notice, in their slipshod, snapshot, scrapbook style, for suggesting just how short the camera falls at representing whatever it is pointed at. The pictures, whether the imitation grunge fashion shoots that made his name in the mid-1990's or his latest lush abstractions and extreme close-ups  now at P.S. 1 in Long Island City, Queens  never fail to dissatisfy, teetering uneasily between realness and surrealness. Never is that more true than with his male subjects. Many photographers attempt to conjure up an idealized state of masculinity, and Mr. Tillmans has pointed his lens at all manner of men: soldiers, friends in London, himself in the shower. But he does precious little more than point; the burden is on you to interpret. When he came to New York in the mid-90's, Mr. Tillmans was in a bit of the same predicament. Without a clue as to the associations of this restaurant, that jacket or this grooming product (which, like it or not, is often the way we figure out what to wear and where to eat), he just gravitated to what he liked. That is more or less how he, a man who does not really believe in deodorant, stumbled on that emblem of American manhood, Mennen Speed Stick. "I liked the lack of promise," he said. "It doesn't promise sex, or a better standard of living. Just speed." Now whenever he comes to New York, he stocks up, for he can't find it at home in London. Its very plainness is what he finds sexy. "I'm interested in normality," he said. "I find it much more interesting than hypermasculinity." And what better defines American manliness? Introduced in 1958, Speed Stick (now with dozens of variants, including the catastrophic-sounding scents Icy Surge, Clean Blast and Cool Fusion) is the leading men's stick deodorant. After aerosols like Right Guard came under fire in the late 70's, Speed Stick came to own the nation's underarms. Even men who do not use it now remember it as a kind of adolescent rite of passage. "I never went to high school here, so I never knew it would evoke any of that," Mr. Tillmans said, "but I think subconsciously the product communicated that." Maybe it's the smell. A 1962 ad described the scent as "all man!" A Colgate-Palmolive spokeswoman would not divulge the scent's ingredients, but the Speed Stick Regular label calls it a "clean masculine scent." "That seems like a contradiction in terms," Mr. Tillmans said. Indeed. Sanitize it all you want, but masculinity is like the truth: never simple, and never clean. But a little deodorant can't hurt.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5DA143EF934A35752C1A9639C8B63&amp;ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">MARKETING; Gene Therapy in a Bottle of Mouthwash<date>Published: November 7, 2005</date><text>Brush your teeth and rinse with gene therapy. That could be the future of oral health care as envisioned by Colgate-Palmolive and Introgen Therapeutics, an Austin, Tex., biotechnology company. The companies announced an alliance Friday to incorporate gene therapy -- an exotic, experimental and so far largely unsuccessful form of medicine -- into mouthwashes, gels and similar products to treat and prevent oral cancers. Colgate is buying about 3.6 million shares of Introgen, or a 9.7 percent stake. Colgate will pay $20 million, or $5.54 a share, the same as Introgen's closing price on Thursday. On Friday, Introgen shares climbed 8 percent, to $5.96. Gene therapy involves putting genes into cells in the body, often to replace native genes that are malfunctioning. The technique has rarely worked in the 15 years it has been tried, largely because of the difficulty of getting enough functioning genes into cells. Introgen's method puts so-called tumor suppressor genes into cancerous cells to stop the growth of tumors. The company's most advanced drug, which is in late-stage clinical trials, is a treatment for head and neck cancer that it hopes will be the first gene therapy approved in the United States. In that treatment, viruses containing the desired gene are injected directly into tumors. Working with Colgate, Introgen will try to put the tumor suppressor genes into an oral product to treat leukoplakia, a precancerous condition characterized by lesions on the cheeks, gums or tongue. In some cases the lesions turn cancerous, usually after many years. Dr. Robert E. Sobol, Introgen's senior vice president for medical and scientific affairs, said an initial product would probably be a prescription drug that would require approval by the Food and Drug Administration. But he said he hoped eventually the product could be sold over the counter. The company is already in early stages of human testing of a mouthwash containing a tumor-suppressor gene. The mouth is ''just such an easy place to apply these therapies,'' said Dr. Sobol, explaining that it was easy to reach and see the damaged cells. Nevertheless, getting enough genes into cells in the mouth could still be difficult. Introgen puts its gene into a disarmed cold virus, called an adenovirus, which infects cells and carries in the gene. While Dr. Sobol said the technique was safe, an adenovirus was used in a gene therapy experiment that killed a teenager at the University of Pennsylvania in 1999. Dr. Sobol said that if Introgen wanted to develop a product that would be used widely by people who do not yet have cancer, it might have to use a gene therapy approach that did not involve a virus. Colgate, which is based in New York, said in a statement that the alliance would give it ''insight into a very exciting technology with potential application to oral health.'' The company said the alliance was not a move into the pharmaceutical business but rather one of many research efforts it has involving oral health. Known mostly for consumer products, Colgate sells products used by or prescribed by dentists, including the PerioGard antibiotic rinse to fight the gum disease gingivitis.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/02/business/02consumer.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Profit Higher For P.&amp; G. and Colgate<date>Published: November 2, 2005</date><text>The Procter &amp; Gamble Company and the Colgate-Palmolive Company reported higher quarterly profit yesterday as they benefited from raising prices on consumer products. First-quarter net income at Procter &amp; Gamble rose 4.5 percent, to $2.03 billion, and exceeded analysts' estimates. Third-quarter profit at Colgate increased 5.5 percent, to $347.2 million, and matched estimates. P.&amp; G.'s price increases on Pampers diapers and Colgate's on Palmolive dishwashing liquid added to each company's sales in the quarter, as did the addition of new detergents and toothpastes. "The fact that both P.&amp; G. and Colgate were able to pass on the higher costs to consumers without hurting sales is encouraging," said Keith Patriquin, an analyst at Loomis Sayles &amp; Company in Boston, which owns Procter &amp; Gamble and Colgate shares among $70 billion in assets. "These companies have been reshaping their portfolios toward higher-margin categories to drive profits. Over all, both the companies have done a decent job at new product introductions." P.&amp; G., which is based in Cincinnati, earned 77 cents a share in the quarter, more than the 76 cents forecast by 12 analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Its sales rose 7.6 percent, to $14.8 billion, Colgate, based in New York, earned 63 cents a share. Excluding costs, profit was 67 cents; on that basis, it matched the average estimate of 17 analysts. Colgate's sales increased 8 percent, to $2.91 billion. Shares of Procter &amp; Gamble fell 74 cents to close at $55.25 yesterday. Shares of Colgate fell 60 cents, closing at $52.36. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/28/business/businessspecial3/28colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Profit Is Down 11%; Expenses Up<date>Published: April 28, 2005</date><text>he Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that its profit slipped 11 percent in the first quarter as charges from a cost-cutting plan begun last year weighed on its results. The company also said that its president, Bill Shanahan, was planning to retire in the third quarter. It named the chief operating officer, Ian M. Cook, as his successor, a move analysts say could be Mr. Cook's next step along the way to taking over as chief executive. The current chief, Reuben Mark, is 66. Advertisement The company was still able to increase sales and reinforce its profit margin despite soaring commodity costs as it battles with its major rival, the Procter &amp; Gamble Company. "As you know, we and other consumer products companies are operating in a tough environment," Bina Thomson, vice president for investor relations, said on a conference call with analysts. "It's highly competitive around the world, and raw and packing material costs are sharply up. This makes the dual task of simultaneously spending to improve market shares while delivering our profit goals even more important than it normally is." Colgate-Palmolive said the savings program and a shift toward oral care products that produce higher profits offset significant increases in costs of raw material and packing items and higher spending on commercials. Quarterly income dropped to $300.1 million, or 53 cents a share, from $338.5 million, or 59 cents, last year. The latest quarter includes restructuring charges amounting to $44.6 million, or 8 cents a share, the company said. Aside from the charge, earnings were 61 cents a share, which matched the mean estimate from analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sales totaled $2.74 billion, an increase of 9 percent from $2.51 billion a year earlier. The company said sales in North America rose 7 percent in the quarter, with unit volume rising 7.5 percent - the strongest volume growth in almost two years. Colgate-Palmolive shares rose 3 cents yesterday to close at cents to $50.73. The stock is down from a recent high of about $55 in February.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/28/business/businessspecial3/28colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Sales Increase, but Colgate's Earnings Fall<date>Published: January 28, 2005</date><text>y Bloomberg News The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that its fourth-quarter earnings fell 23 percent on costs to close plants and expand marketing. Colgate's sales had the biggest gain in more than eight years. Net income declined to $285.7 million, or 50 cents a share, from $372.1 million, or 65 cents, a year earlier. Sales rose 9 percent, to $2.8 billion, with 3 percentage points of the gain coming from effects of the weaker dollar. Advertisement Colgate, based in New York, is cutting about 4,440 jobs and closing a third of its factories, reducing profit by 9 cents a share. Reuben Mark, the chief executive, plans to use savings from the revamping to increase advertising and protect Colgate's lead over Crest, the Procter &amp; Gamble Company's toothpaste brand. "They've refocused to get volumes up," said Steve Paspal, who helps manage more than $2 billion, including Colgate shares, at Sovereign Asset Management in Berwyn, Pa. "Now they need to start showing more visible profit growth." Excluding reorganizing costs of $48 million, the company said it would have earned 59 cents a share. On that basis, which does not conform to generally accepted accounting principles, the results matched the average estimate of 59 cents from 17 analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Shares of Colgate, whose products include Palmolive soap and Mennen deodorant, rose $2.81, or 5.6 percent, to close at $52.69 on the New York Stock Exchange.. Sales rose 6 percent in North America, where Colgate gets less than a quarter of its annual revenue. Its share of the United States toothpaste market increased to 34.8 percent in 2004, widening 60 basis points from 2003, Colgate said, citing data by A. C. Nielsen, the marketing information company. European sales jumped 19 percent, aided by Gaba, the Swiss toothpaste maker that Colgate bought in June 2004. Sales rose 4.5 percent in Latin America and 5.5 percent in the Asia-Africa region, helped by China. Colgate increased advertising spending by 13 percent.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/10/business/10procter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Upbeat Talk From Procter as Big Rival Is Retrenching<date>Published: December 10, 2004</date><text>rocter &amp; Gamble used a presentation for investors yesterday to champion its recent performance, in sharp contrast to a gathering held this week by Colgate-Palmolive, which announced it was regrouping after disappointing results. But beneath the surface the two companies share some similarities, both in the challenges they are confronting in the consumer products industry and the strategies they are using to surmount them. Alan G. Lafley, Procter's chairman and chief executive, who has led the company's turnaround since taking the helm four years ago, said that his plan emphaszing "balanced growth" continues to work. "We're confident we have the strategies, brands, innovation pipeline and new market opportunities to sustain strong growth," he said. But even with top-line success, Procter said operating profit margins were expected to improve only "modestly," and it did not raise its quarterly or annual earnings goals. Rising commodity costs led the company, meanwhile, to raise the price of some Folgers coffee products by 14 percent yesterday. It has also raised prices about 5 percent on some tissue and pet food goods this year. "We have made tough interventions that are needed to restore the health of our business," said Clayton C. Daley, Procter's chief financial officer, who did not rule out increases on more products. Earlier in the week, Reuben Mark, Colgate's chairman and chief executive, expressed a similar determination to take action amid the sobering news of a sweeping reorganization. During a conference call with investors on Tuesday, he said Colgate would close about one-third of its 78 factories and eliminate 12 percent of its work force worldwide over the next four years. The changes should help Colgate improve its profitability, and he said the company would devote much of the cost savings to increasing sales. Investors appeared to like what both companies said. Shares of Procter climbed $1.35, or 2.45 percent, yesterday to $56.38, while Colgate rose 70 cents, or 1.4 percent, to $50.25. The consumer products industry is entering a challenging period, however, and analysts say no company is immune. Price pressure is growing as retail giants like Wal-Mart push for low prices and carry cheaper private-label brands. Rising commodity prices add to production costs. On top of that, intense competition is causing companies to spend more on advertising just to retain the market share they already have. "The market doesn't fully appreciate the challenges ahead," said William H. Steele, a household goods analyst for Banc of America Securities. "Companies like to tap you on the shoulder before they slap you in the face, and Unilever and Colgate were tapping people on the shoulder when they issued profit warnings this fall." Even with its recent success, he said, Procter has been sacrificing some profit margin to maintain strong top-line growth. Having improved their balance sheets and operations, the road ahead for Colgate and Procter is very much the same: trying to drive revenue growth by introducing innovative products and capturing new customers, particularly those in fast-growing markets like China, Latin America and Eastern Europe. Colgate's restructuring plans call for directing the savings, expected to total more than $300 million a year by 2008, into more money for product development and marketing. Mr. Mark also said the company would step up its sales efforts in China, Eastern Europe, and Latin America, where it once had a commanding lead. Procter, which concluded its own restructuring effort last year, has already adjusted its strategy and analysts say its global position is strong. Its innovation pipeline has effectively introduced products like Crest Whitestrips, and Mr. Lafley said yesterday that new products that extend core brands like Tide, Herbal Essence, and Olay would hit store shelves early next year. The company, meanwhile, has reached new consumers by improving the efficiency of its advertising and placing products like Iams superpremium pet food in shops other than pet stores. Procter executives described developing countries as a "disproportionate growth opportunity" to expand the business even more. "For our top brands, there are still a lot of markets where we don't compete," said Robert A. McDonald, Procter's vice chairman for global operations. Total sales in developing markets have increased an average of 12 percent over the last three years, contributing about one-third of overall sales growth excluding a gain from a major acquisition. "In areas where our competitors entered at the same time, like Latin America and Asia," he added, "we are the clear market leader."</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/08/business/08colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate to Cut Jobs and Use Savings to Spur Sales<date>Published: December 8, 2004</date><text>olgate-Palmolive, the consumer products company, said yesterday that it would close about a third of its factories and cut more than 4,400 jobs over the next four years as part of a major restructuring effort to increase profit margins. The company plans to use the savings for advertising and product development as it seeks more robust growth in an industry that has been battered by rising raw material costs and increasingly tough competition. Colgate, best known for its brand-name toothpaste and detergent, has had trouble keeping up with Procter &amp; Gamble, which has stepped up its marketing and product development efforts with innovations like Crest Whitestrips. Colgate said yesterday that it expected to take a total of $550 million to $650 million in restructuring charges after taxes as it begins more than 100 initiatives over the next four years, including the centralization of its back-office and purchasing operations and a 12 percent reduction of its 37,000 jobs. The changes are intended to save as much as $300 million a year by 2008. The company, based in New York, said it still expected to meet its fourth-quarter earnings estimates, excluding restructuring costs of about $45 million. It also projected an immediate cost savings of about $45 million next year, but the company said its plans would soon require the immediate closing of eight factories worldwide and that it informed workers at those plants of the decision yesterday. "The savings come from hard stuff, and stuff that is culturally and socially not terrific," Reuben Mark, Colgate's chief executive, said on a conference call with investors. But Mr. Mark said that the changes were necessary to maintain the company's market share and reach profit margin goals as it faces aggressive competition. Earlier this fall, Colgate and another rival, Unilever, issued profit warnings in the face of growing pressure from retailers for lower prices and product innovations from P.&amp; G. that have stripped away existing customers. As P.&amp; G.'s profit has soared this year, Colgate said that its second-half earnings would fall well short of expectations and Unilever said its full-year forecast of 10 percent earnings growth would be cut in half. All of the consumer giants, meanwhile, have pledged to step up advertising and development efforts just to hold onto existing market share. While Colgate posted double-digit earnings growth for much of the last decade, analysts said it mainly did so by improving its balance sheet and internal operations rather than by investing heavily in its brands. But with yesterday's announcement, some analysts saw an inflection point. "It's fair to say they were stretching to make their numbers the past few years, and as a result have not invested as much as they should have," said Amy Chasen, a Goldman Sachs analyst who upgraded Colgate stock yesterday on the news. "With this restructuring, they will have the flexibility to post better earnings growth while redeploying funds into marketing and new product development to help drive top-line growth." Investors reacted positively to the announcement, with shares of Colgate rising $3.78, to $50.07. The restructuring comes as Colgate experienced its first decline in quarterly profit in eight years, and investors have complained that the company has been slower to innovate than its peers. With the cost savings from the effort, Mr. Mark said, Colgate plans to increase its investment in the development of pet nutrition, dental and personal care products as well as some potentially new categories. But he promised no immediate big hits. "We will continue to build on quiet innovation that gives us consistent growth in volume and market share," Mr. Mark said. "The one time we talked about torrid innovation was Simply White, and look where that got us." That Colgate product, a tooth-whitening liquid that came in a nail polish container with a small brush, hit store shelves and stayed there. But P.&amp; G.'s Crest Whitestrips was a blockbuster. The company said the restructuring effort entailed closing a total of about two dozen factories worldwide over the next four years, concentrating its manufacturing in "fewer, more sophisticated" centers around the world. Although Colgate shut 24 of its 112 factories and eliminated more than 3,000 jobs when it went through a restructuring less than a decade ago, analysts said that many of its existing plants in the United States were old, unionized, and did not have the manufacturing- line efficiency of rivals. There are no senior management departures expected as part of the reorganization, and Mr. Mark did not say which factories would be shut or how many jobs would be lost in the United States. He said the effort was not a major attempt at outsourcing. "The great bulk of it is in our key products where we don't outsource," he said. Still, Mr. Mark hinted of at least a subtle shift in the company's plans in emerging economies - it is stepping up marketing efforts in China, Russia and Eastern Europe, where rivals have been spending even more. "I am not sure it is a shift in strategy," he said, "but it is a de-emphasis of production to marketing."</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/23/business/media/23adco.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">New Image for a Wine Maker<date>Published: November 23, 2004</date><text>OLLA is seeking to shed its staid image as a classic Italian wine in favor of a fresher, more informal approach - "rockin' the boat," as one new ad puts it. After neglecting the brand's marketing and seeing Bolla's sales suffer, the Brown-Forman Beverages division of the Brown-Forman Corporation is undertaking an ambitious revival attempt. A campaign, with a budget estimated at $12 million, includes print, outdoor, radio and Internet advertising; redesigned labels; and even a new variety, Chianti. The marketing initiative, produced by a new agency for Bolla, Price Weber in Louisville, Ky., has begun. It is indicative of attempts being made by major advertisers to increase substantially the spending on aging brands to attract the attention of younger potential customers as well as renewing interest among longtime buyers. Brown-Forman also recently signaled it would step up marketing of its Finlandia vodka by naming an agency, Northlich in Cincinnati, to create worldwide campaigns for that brand. In refocusing on brands like Bolla and Finlandia, Brown-Forman joins a long list of marketers seeking to rejuvenate venerable products, which include Coca-Cola, Colgate-Palmolive, PepsiCo and Unilever. But not all such brands are being deemed eligible for makeovers. For instance, the Campbell Soup Company has decided to discontinue one aging brand, Franco-American, The Philadelphia Inquirer reported last week, and it is relabeling Franco-American products like SpaghettiOs with the Campbell's name. "We did consumer research and found the Campbell's name scored higher on quality and nutritional equity than the Franco-American name," said Juli Mandel Sloves, a spokeswoman for Campbell Soup in Camden, N.J. The Franco-American brand dates to 1887 and was acquired by Campbell Soup in 1915. Bolla dates to 1883 and was first imported into the United States in 1946. But the wine market has been changing far faster than packaged-foods categories like canned pasta. "Bolla is a good brand, with solid credentials," said Michael Bellas, chairman and chief executive of the Beverage Marketing Corporation, a consultant in New York, who recalled "growing up lifting those cases" of Bolla while working for his family's wine and spirits distributorships in Ohio. "But in the last four, five years, the real excitement in the category has been coming from Australian wines," Mr. Bellas said. One of them is Yellow Tail, whose drinkability, low price and lighthearted image helped it grow rapidly into America's best-selling imported wine, dropping Bolla to eighth place from seventh. At one time, when Bolla was sold as Soave Bolla, it had been the No. 1 import. Brown-Forman "needs to make Bolla exciting again," Mr. Bellas said, particularly to "that younger group" of wine drinkers who are still forming their brand preferences. Donald Freytag, marketing director for Bolla at Brown-Forman, also in Louisville, acknowledged the mistakes that were made by not advertising Bolla enough as well as the difficulties that lie ahead in bringing back the brand. "We really feel we'd taken our eye off the ball," Mr. Freytag said. "We were very complacent and ended up in a challenging position. It was a missed opportunity." "Consumers have warm feelings toward Bolla," he added, "but we came to be a little bit irrelevant compared with what else is out there," from new Italian wines produced by E.&amp; J. Gallo under names like Ecco Domani and Bella Sera to the other Australian entrants like Jacob's Creek and Black Swan. And in reaching out to younger drinkers ages 25 to 39 to "broaden the franchise, which over the years has become more mature," Mr. Freytag said, "we don't want to alienate our older, loyal consumer base." In studying potential strategies, Mr. Freytag said, "We decided we needed to be true to what the brand is, but not the old-world Italian imagery of authenticity" so prevalent in the category. "Instead, we want to convey the Italian passion for life, how Italians live life to the fullest," he added, "spinning it with a fresh tone to be relevant to today's wine drinkers who are going for warm, fuzzy animals." His reference was to the menagerie led by the kangaroo on the Yellow Tail label and the dark bird on the Black Swan label. So the campaign carries a new theme, "Open up," as well as a spirited advisory, "Live passionately, but drink responsibly." The print and outdoor ads present younger models and use language that is far less formal than before. For instance, one ad, showing a couple embracing in a gondola, says, "Here's to rockin' the boat." Another ad, depicting the open door of a restaurant, says, "Here's to the original chat rooms." A third ad shows a couple slurping a single strand of spaghetti between them, invoking the familiar scene from the Disney animated film, "Lady and the Tramp." The headline declares, "Here's to sharing the good stuff." And the outdoor ads for the Chianti invite drinkers to "Meet the new Italian in town." "We wanted to freshen up the look and give it a more contemporary feel without alienating our core followers," said Leigha Dorsey, senior account executive at Price Weber. "That's definitely tricky, but we think we've succeeded." "The strength of Bolla is as a true- and-trusted Italian," she added, "but you can put those characteristics in a new light and still have them be appealing." Brown-Forman recently awarded the agency the Bolla account, which had previously been handled by Carmichael Lynch in Minneapolis, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies. Price Weber has worked for Brown-Forman for more than 35 years, Ms. Dorsey said, on vintage products that include its so-called heritage brands like Canadian Mist whiskey and two bourbons, Early Times and Old Forrester. The Bolla print, outdoor and radio ads will be concentrated, Mr. Freytag said, in the markets where the brand displays "pockets of regional strength," which include the East Coast from Washington to Boston; Chicago, Dallas, Denver and Phoenix; and in Florida. The new campaign will also be featured on the brand's Web site (www.bolla.com), he added, and television commercials are being considered.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/21/business/21colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Material Costs and Marketing Hurt Colgate<date>Published: October 21, 2004</date><text>he Colgate-Palmolive Company, the consumer products company, said yesterday that its profit fell in the third quarter, as it had warned a month ago, because of increased spending on marketing and higher costs for raw materials. Colgate also said it would stand by its outlook for the current quarter and said its board had voted to authorize a new stock repurchasing plan. The company earned $329 million, or 58 cents a share, down from $365.4 million, or 63 cents, a year earlier. Advertisement A month ago, Colgate issued its first formal earnings warning in almost a decade, in part because of higher costs. Analysts lowered their profit outlooks to an average of 58 cents a share, from 67 cents before the announcement, according to Reuters Estimates. Shares of Colgate, which hit a 12-month low of $42.89 on Tuesday, closed yesterday at $45.35, up $2.29 a share. An analyst at Banc of America Securities, William Steele, said that he thought investors would be "somewhat relieved" to hear that Colgate did not lower estimates again for the fourth quarter or next year. Colgate's net sales rose to $2.70 billion from $2.52 billion, in line with analysts' expectations. Sales and unit volume each grew 8.5 percent, excluding divestments, with the recent acquisition of a Swiss toothpaste maker, Gaba, adding 2 percent. The chairman and chief executive, Reuben Mark, said in a statement that while sales growth was excellent, it had come at a cost to short-term profits. Colgate, based in New York, said its share of the United States toothpaste market climbed to 37.3 percent in September, more than seven share points ahead of a rival brand, Crest, by Procter &amp; Gamble. The company stood by its fourth-quarter earnings forecast of 57 cents to 59 cents a share. Analysts expect a fourth-quarter profit of 57 cents to 59 cents a share, matching the outlook Colgate gave in September. That view is down from the average of 68 cents a share analysts had expected before the company's warning. The new stock buyback plan will allow Colgate to repurchase 20 million shares between now and the end of 2005. That would be twice the rate purchased in 2003 and so far this year, it said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/21/business/21place.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Unilever and Colgate Issue Profit Warnings for Rest of the Year<date>Published: September 21, 2004</date><text>ONDON, Sept. 20 - Two big consumer products companies, Unilever and Colgate-Palmolive, issued profit warnings on Monday, underscoring an increasingly tough competitive landscape for makers of some of the world's best-known brands. Unilever, which makes products like Dove soap and Hellmann's mayonnaise, announced that its full-year earnings would grow by less than half the amount it had forecast earlier. Colgate-Palmolive, whose products include toothpaste and dish soap, said its second-half profit would come in well short of earlier forecasts. Shares of both companies fell sharply and pulled down the shares of competitors. While Unilever and Colgate do not overlap in all the same markets, their warnings seemed to suggest that both were suffering from growing competition in some areas, particularly from Procter &amp; Gamble, and from growing demands from retailers for lower prices. Both companies said they would have to increase their spending on marketing and advertising to protect their brands. Unilever, the world's biggest maker of ice cream and tea, said it expected earnings per share for the full year to grow by less than 5 percent compared with earlier forecasts of just over 10 percent. It also said it expected third-quarter sales to fall compared with a year earlier, when the company benefited from unusually warm weather in Europe. Unilever, based in London and Rotterdam in the Netherlands, owns brands like Magnum ice cream and Lipton tea. It also owns Ben and Jerry's in the United States. In its warning, the company cited bad summer weather in northern Europe for declines in sales of ice cream and ice tea, but executives also acknowledged that its spending on advertising and promotion had lagged. "The protection of the health of our brands and a return to long-term profitable growth remain our overriding priorities," Unilever said in a statement. "Planned brand support activities for the rest of the year will therefore be maintained and in certain areas reinforced." Unilever also said it had faced stiff competition in health and personal care markets in Europe and in laundry products in Asia. In India in particular, Procter &amp; Gamble has cut prices of soap powders to attack Unilever's market share. And in Europe, said Richard Workman, an analyst at Oriel Securities, there is "growing evidence that the big continental European markets are becoming more competitive" as big retailers like discount supermarket chains demand ever-lower prices. "That appears to have accelerated a bit in the third quarter," he said. "Anybody with a big German business has been finding life difficult." In a note, Numis Securities said there was "much to do to turn things around while the competition will no doubt be keeping a keen eye on Unilever's plans." Julian Hardwick, an analyst with ABN Amro, said, "It will take time for them to be able to implement the changes which are necessary to return the business to growth." "The key area is increased investment" in advertising and promotion, he said. Colgate cited increased promotional spending and higher costs of raw materials as the reason for the reduction in its forecast. It now expects earnings to be 57 to 59 cents a share in both the third and fourth quarters, down from Wall Street expectations of 64 to 69 cents in the third quarter and 66 to 71 cents in the fourth. "As planned, we have sharply increased marketing spending to build market share and aggressively improve our brand franchises here and abroad," Reuben Mark, Colgate's chairman and chief executive, said in a statement. "It is vital that we maintain the aggressive commercial spending to build market share and blunt competitive efforts." Mr. Mark said third-quarter volume was expected to be up more than 7 percent, with dollar sales rising about the same. "We are confident that we are taking the right measures to accelerate our growth and profitability for 2005 and beyond," Mr. Mark said. The shares of both companies dropped sharply on the profit warnings, with Colgate sliding $6.10, or 11.2 percent, to $48.23, and the American depository receipts of Unilever falling $1.82, or 5.2 percent, to $33.22. Shares of other consumer product companies decreased as well. Procter &amp; Gamble fell $1.88, or 3.3 percent, to $54.38; Gillette fell $1.14, to $41.26; and Kimberly-Clark fell $1.12, to $65.50. At Unilever, the reduced expectations came as the company approached a turning point in its leadership. Niall FitzGerald, 59, who has been with Unilever for 37 years, is set to retire as co-chairman at the end of this month but has been playing a less public role for several months. He is to be succeeded by Patrick Cescau, 55, who will become joint chairman with Antony Burgmans, who will be based in the Netherlands. The end of this year also marks the conclusion of a five-year, $5 billion strategy called "path to growth" in which Unilever cut its brands to about 400 major ones from about 1,600, including Knorr soup and Sunsilk shampoo. The major brands now account for some 95 percent of its sales. At its inception, the program had aimed to meet high growth targets, but those ambitions have not been fulfilled. Indeed, in a statement Monday, Mr. FitzGerald and Mr. Burgmans said, "Top-line growth is key to long-term sustainable value creation, and here the recent performance is unacceptable."</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/11/nyregion/c-corrections-272450.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Corrections<date>Published: July 11, 2004</date><text>Because of an editing error, an article on Page 25 of Arts &amp; Leisure today about bands that receive group therapy misidentifies the instrument played by Lars Ulrich of Metallica, a group whose therapy is chronicled in the film ''Some Kind of Monster.'' It is drums, not bass. The article also misspells the name of another group that has received counseling. It is Audioslave, not Audio Slave.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/10/business/colgate-executive-promoted-spurring-talk-about-top-post.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Executive Promoted, Spurring Talk About Top Post<date>Published: July 10, 2004</date><text>Correction AppendedThe Colgate-Palmolive Company named Ian M. Cook as chief operating officer Friday, a move that analysts said signaled that he would most likely become the next chief executive.Mr. Cook and two other Colgate executives, Javier G. Teruel and Lois D. Juliber, have been seen as the potential successors to Reuben Mark, the 65-year-old chairman and chief executive who has run the company for 20 years.Mr. Juliber, who had been chief operating officer, and Mr. Teruel, an executive vice president, were both named vice chairmen of Colgate, which makes a wide range of consumer products, from toothpaste to dishwashing liquid.''The way the press release reads and after talking to the company, it appears Ian Cook is being groomed to continue the ascension to the C.E.O. position after some period of time,'' said William Steele, an analyst at Banc of America Securities.A Colgate spokeswoman declined to comment on speculation that Mr. Cook would eventually be named chief executive.Mr. Mark said in February that he would most likely stay at the company two to four years. He said that at some point he would hand over the chief executive post.Mr. Cook, who had been an executive vice president, will keep responsibility for the company's most competitive businesses in North America and Europe and will add operating responsibility for Asia, Central Europe and Africa, the company said. He will report to William S. Shanahan, the president, and will travel extensively with him in coming months to Colgate operations around the world.''I think Ian is the heir apparent,'' said Ken Harris, a marketing consultant at Cannondale Associates.Mr. Teruel will continue to oversee the Hill's pet food business and will assume responsibility for worldwide strategy, also reporting to Mr. Shanahan, the company said.Mr. Juliber will continue to head business development, research and development, product supply chain, technology and corporate development, as well as responsibility for Latin America and communications.Correction: July 11, 2004, Sunday Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the appointment of Ian M. Cook as chief operating officer at the Colgate-Palmolive Company referred incorrectly to another executive who was named a vice chairman. The executive, Lois D. Juliber, is a woman.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/04/business/profit-increases-9.2-at-colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Profit Increases 9.2% at Colgate<date>Published: February 04, 2004</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit increased 9.2 percent, exceeding expectations, as higher international sales helped to counter a second consecutive decline in revenue from North America.Net income increased to $372.1 million, or 65 cents a share, from $340.9 million, or 59 cents, in the year-earlier period. Sales rose 6.3 percent, to $2.57 billion, from $2.42 billion in the year-earlier period.Revenue topped forecasts in Latin America, while Europe and Asia helped to make up for lower sales of Simply White, a tooth-whitening gel, and the Colgate toothpaste in the United States. The company's chief executive, Reuben Mark, is increasing marketing and adding products after losing the top spot in the American toothpaste market to Crest, a product of Procter &amp; Gamble, for the first time in six years.The company, which is based in New York, bought GABA Holding, a Swiss company that makes toothpaste. Expenses from the sale of some laundry detergent brands in Europe offset most of the gains.Volume, or the number of products sold, increased 5.5 percent in Latin America, 3 percent in Europe and 6 percent in Asia and Africa, while declining 6 percent in North America. The company, which generates more than three-quarters of its revenue overseas, did not break out gains from currency exchange.Shares of Colgate rose $1.51, to $51.85. They had dropped 1.1 percent over the last year.Colgate expects first-quarter profit to rise to as much as 59 cents a share, the average forecast of 11 analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call, executives said on a conference call with analysts and investors.Analysts had expected Colgate to earn 63 cents in the fourth quarter.Sales declined 7.5 percent in North America, mainly because of the lower-than-expected sales in the United States of Simply White.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/19/business/world-business-briefing-europe-switzerland-toothpaste-maker-acquired.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">World Business Briefing | Europe: Switzerland: Toothpaste Maker Acquired<date>Published: December 19, 2003</date><text>The Col-gate-Palmolive Company said it had agreed to buy a Swiss toothpaste maker, Gaba Holding A.G., for as much as $830 million. Colgate, based in New York, also forecast a decline in North American sales in the fourth quarter. The company said that the number of units sold would fall for a second consecutive quarter because of lower-than-expected sales in the United States of Simply White, a whitening gel for teeth. Gaba, which makes Meridol toothpaste, has sales of about $300 million in Europe. Colgate will pay from $630 million to $830 million for Gaba, which is based in Therwil, Switzerland. Colgate said the acquisition would reduce its earnings by 3 percent in 2004 and would begin adding to profit by 2006. Its shares fell 6.6 percent.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/21/business/company-news-procter-gamble-to-buy-5-colgate-brands-in-europe.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE TO BUY 5 COLGATE BRANDS IN EUROPE<date>Published: October 21, 2003</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that it would sell its European laundry detergent brands to the Procter &amp; Gamble Company for an undisclosed sum in a move to focus on core businesses like toothpaste, mouthwash and soap. Colgate said as a result of the sale it expected to record a one-time gain that would be offset by charges from divesting the brands. The detergent brands include Axion and Gama in France, Ajax in Sweden, Dynamo in Denmark, and Dinamo in Italy, a spokesman for Procter &amp; Gamble said. Terms of the sale were not disclosed.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/23/business/company-news-colgate-palmolive-profit-rises-10-on-strong-sales.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE PROFIT RISES 10% ON STRONG SALES<date>Published: July 23, 2003</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive said yesterday that its second-quarter earnings increased 10 percent, bolstered by higher sales in Europe and demand for new products. Net income was $359.8 million, or 62 cents a share, compared with $327 million, or 55 cents, a year earlier, Colgate said. Revenue increased 7 percent to $2.46 billion. Colgate gained sales from rivals including Procter &amp; Gamble in the domestic toothpaste market, and introduced whitening products in countries including Spain and Hungary. Sales in North America rose 7.5 percent, buoyed by new products including Herbal White toothpaste.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/18/business/company-news-nestle-announces-partnership-with-colgate-palmolive.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; NESTLÉ ANNOUNCES PARTNERSHIP WITH COLGATE-PALMOLIVE<date>Published: June 18, 2003</date><text>NestlÃ©, the Swiss food company with an empire that includes chocolates and sugar-sweetened ice tea, said yesterday that it was joining with the Colgate-Palmolive Company, the toothpaste maker, to market oral care products. The joint venture will seek to ''pursue on a worldwide basis the development, marketing, distribution and sale of a portfolio of portable oral care products'' that ''taste good, clean teeth and freshen breath,'' the companies said. The initial product will be Colgate Dental Gum, in its current test markets in Britain, Ireland and Canada, they said. NestlÃ© and Colgate-Palmolive, which is based in New York, said their agreement, subject to regulatory approval, is expected to become effective early next year.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/media-business-advertising-giants-tooth-whitening-see-spinoff-products-expanding.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING; The giants of tooth whitening see spinoff products expanding a fast-growing market.<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>IF a front-page assault in The Onion, the weekly satirical newspaper, is any indicator that a new trend has reached cultural critical mass, the marketers of tooth-whitening products must have been dancing in the cubicle aisles last week.In the story, fictional dentists lash out at Americans' growing demands for achieving impossibly bright smiles with whitening products. ''What happens once, at long last, you people get your teeth pure white?'' one dentist demands. ''Will you finally be satisfied? Of course not. Then you'll want clear teeth.''At Procter &amp; Gamble, the maker of Crest Whitestrips, and Colgate-Palmolive, which makes Simply White gel, executives hope their consumers will be satisfied, perhaps, but never satiated. The two companies, which take in 84 percent of the money Americans spend on tooth whiteners, and which last year spent an estimated $81 million marketing them, are now trying to rope in new customers with offshoot products for nighttime use.In the process, the two companies have risked competing with their own daytime whiteners and tangled over charges of false advertising.''It's gotten a little down and dirty,'' said Joseph Altobello, analyst at CIBC World Markets.While whitener sales are just a small portion of revenue for Colgate-Palmolive and Procter &amp; Gamble, the products' growth is too valuable to pass up, he said. For the 52 weeks ended March 23, Americans spent nearly $297 million on home-use whitening products, up 90 percent over the comparable period a year earlier, Information Resources said.The importance both companies attach to their whitening products was made plain in November, when Colgate-Palmolive challenged the accuracy of some Crest commercials, filing a complaint with the Better Business Bureaus. Those commercials said that whitening gels wash off within minutes, rendering them less effective than Crest Whitestrips. Crest produced research that it said supported its claim.The National Advertising Division of the Council of Better Business Bureaus has not yet made a decision on the challenge. But Crest went ahead with ads introducing Night Effects that repeat the comparison. ''Unlike that paint-on,'' one print ad reads, ''Crest Night Effects won't wash away in minutes.'' The television commercials use time-lapse video to show an unnamed product melting away while Night Effects lasts.Executives at Colgate-Palmolive, which is introducing Simply White Night, declined to comment.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/18/business/colgate-aided-by-profit-margin-and-sales-posts-12-net-gain.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate, Aided by Profit Margin And Sales, Posts 12% Net Gain<date>Published: April 18, 2003</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive said yesterday that its net income increased by about 12 percent in the first quarter, lifted by both sales growth and a record gross profit margin.Colgate, the consumer products company, reported net income of $324 million, or 56 cents a share. That was up from $289.7 million, or 49 cents a share, in the same period a year earlier.Colgate, which reported unit volume growth in all of its regional divisions, beat Wall Street's first-quarter earnings forecasts by a penny a share.The company said worldwide dollar sales rose about 7 percent, to $2.35 billion from almost $2.20 billion in the year-earlier quarter. That was the largest increase in more than seven years, Colgate said. It added that global unit volume grew 6 percent in the first quarter, with every operating division contributing strong volume gains.Colgate said its gross profit margin increased by a half of a percentage point to 55.3 percent -- a record.The company said North American unit volume grew 6 percent in the first quarter, driven by continued new-product activity across categories.Last week, analysts forecast improved results for Colgate, which makes Palmolive and Ajax products. The analysts said currency exchange rates would help. William Steele, a Banc of America Securities analyst, said Latin American currencies were strengthening, and that would likely help Colgate's results.Colgate said its Latin American operations achieved a higher-than-expected 6.5 percent unit volume growth in the first quarter, helped by new-product success and market-share increases. Latin American currency weaknesses caused dollar sales to decline 7 percent and operating profit to fall 6 percent, the company said. But in local currencies, sales grew 17 percent, and operating profit increased 18 percent.European unit volume rose 3 percent, helped by widespread success of new products throughout the region, the company said, adding that the Asia-Africa unit volume grew an unexpectedly strong 8.5 percent in the first quarter.At 4 p.m. in New York Stock Exchange composite trading, Colgate fell 60 cents, or about 1.1 percent, to $55.75 a share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/05/business/new-products-aid-colgate-net.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">New Products Aid Colgate Net<date>Published: February 05, 2003</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive, the consumer products company, said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit rose 15 percent after new products like its teeth-whitening gel led to the biggest sales gain in five years.Net income climbed to $340.9 million, or 59 cents a share, from $295.3 million, or 49 cents, a year earlier. Sales increased 3.9 percent, to $2.42 billion, and product development will raise revenue even more this year, the chief executive, Reuben Mark, said.Profit per share was 1 cent more than the forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Sales in North America rose 5.5 percent after the introduction of the Simply White gel, while new varieties helped sales of Hill's pet food increase 9 percent.Colgate, which sells products in more than 200 countries, said sales in Asia rose 9.5 percent, while the rising value of the euro helped European sales increase 11 percent. Sales in Latin America fell 8 percent because of currency declines, while the number of products sold in the region rose 4 percent.Shares of Colgate rose $1.44, to close at $52.19.Mr. Mark said the company expected sales in the United States to rise 4 percent to 7 percent this year. Simply White will eventually add $100 million to $200 million in annual sales in America, he said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/18/business/company-news-colgate-reports-profit-increase-and-3-promotions.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE REPORTS PROFIT INCREASE AND 3 PROMOTIONS<date>Published: October 18, 2002</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive reported a 12 percent increase in quarterly profit yesterday and the fastest rise in sales in five years. Net income climbed to $330.7 million, or 57 cents a share, from $296.2 million, or 49 cents, a year earlier, and sales increased 3.3 percent, to $2.38 billion. The company also said that it had promoted three top managers in advance of the eventual retirement of its chairman, Reuben Mark, 63. The executives are Lois D. Juliber, Javier G. Teruel and Ian M. Cook. Ms. Juliber, chief operating officer, will become responsible for the Latin American unit as well as research and technology. Mr. Teruel will oversee the Asian business and the Hill's pet food unit, while Mr. Cook will supervise the European business as well as the North American operations.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/04/nyregion/following-up.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">FOLLOWING UP<date>Published: August 04, 2002</date><text>Sometimes It Passes, Sometimes It Stands StillEast Side, West Side, either side of town,Just look across the river, see two landmarks not torn down.And the promise is that they will continue to stand, even though the building on which one of them rests will soon be demolished, and the building on which the other once stood has already been razed.The landmarks are the big Colgate clock, on the Jersey City waterfront across the Hudson River from Lower Manhattan, and the huge Pepsi-Cola sign in Queens, across the East River from mid-Manhattan.The Colgate-Palmolive Company ended operations at its century-and-a-half-old riverfront manufacturing plant in Jersey City in the late 1980's to make way for an office and recreational development on the site.The plant's most prominent fixture, a clock with a 55-foot diameter that had been atop one of the buildings since 1924, was preserved after the building was demolished in 1989.The company said it would integrate the well-known clock into the reborn site, and today, from a temporary spot in a park, the clock's hands still glow in brilliant red toward Manhattan.In Long Island City, Queens, PepsiCo Inc. will soon be ending its operations at a plant near the water's edge. The plant will be sold to the Rockrose Development Corporation, which is to demolish it for an apartment complex.PepsiCo and Rockrose have said that the 100-by-60-foot red neon sign, which for more than 60 years has displayed the old Pepsi-Cola logo with a swirl of letters and the image of a tilted bottle, will remain a conspicuous part of the view from Manhattan.Last week plans were revealed about the permanent, digital-age stages planned for both icons of the industrial age.''The plan is to move the Colgate clock to its permanent location on the Sussex Street pier in 2003,'' a Colgate-Palmolive spokeswoman, Allison Klimerman, said.Jon McMillan, Rockrose's planning director, said that because the Pepsi plant is to be razed and new housing built, the Pepsi sign would stand on a temporary site nearby. In about four years, he estimated, it would be moved permanently ''more or less to the same location as it is now,'' where it will rise from ground-based pylons.The Comings and Goings Of a Casino Cruise BoatSince 1996, a company now called Casino New York has been mounting repeated efforts to run casino boat cruises from Sheepshead Bay in Brooklyn, only to sail into red ink, which the company insists has flowed from government restrictions.The first effort ended in 1997 after, the authorities said, a change in federal law required that the boats be 12 miles from shore, rather than 3, for gambling to take place. This increased travel time and cut gambling time -- and patronage -- the company said.A judge restored the three-mile limit. But a new zoning law that limited the number of people boarding each boat to 200 despite a 600-passenger capacity, made a 1999 relaunch of the trips unprofitable, the company's president, Joseph Kelleher, said last week. Last January, the cruises resumed, with operators hoping to obtain a temporary waiver ''to put more people on the vessel,'' he said.But that did not happen, and in June the cruises ceased again.Refusing to throw in the cards, Mr. Kelleher says he is trying to get the boarding limit permanently raised so that cruises can be resumed profitably.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/19/business/company-news-colgate-s-profit-rises-8-but-revenue-drops-slightly.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE'S PROFIT RISES 8%, BUT REVENUE DROPS SLIGHTLY<date>Published: April 19, 2002</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive said yesterday that its profit rose 8 percent in the first quarter despite a slight decline in sales. The results matched Wall Street expectations and the company said it expected to meet profit expectations for the year. The consumer products company said it earned $289.7 million, or 49 cents a share, in the three months ended March 31, up from $267.9 million, or 44 cents a share, a year ago. Revenue slipped to $2.19 billion from $2.21 billion a year ago. Shares of Colgate-Palmolive fell $3.80, or 6.6 percent, to $53.95.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/11/business/executives-beyond-enron-took-months-to-report-sales.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Executives Beyond Enron Took Months To Report Sales<date>Published: February 11, 2002</date><text>Corporate executives have found a way, without breaking the law, to delay telling the public when they sell their own companies' stock.Fifteen executives at Colgate-Palmolive combined to sell more than $40 million in Colgate stock in 2000 and waited until early last year to disclose their sales.The retiring president of Procter &amp; Gamble's tissues-and-towel division sold $2.8 million of company stock last June but did not report the sale for more than two months.Two top executives at Tyco International sold more than $100 million in Tyco shares in late 2000 and 2001, but the sales did not become public for as long as a year. Today, Tyco shares are worth about half what they were at the time of the transactions.All these sellers, and dozens of others, have taken advantage of an 11-year-old loophole in federal securities laws that allows executives to wait as long as 13 months to disclose their sales when the buyer of their shares is the company itself. The loophole is the same one that enabled Kenneth L. Lay, the former chief executive of Enron, to sell millions of dollars of Enron shares in the months that the stock was plummeting, without filing the usual federal disclosure forms for insider sales.In the wake of Enron's collapse and new questions about Tyco's accounting methods, corporate governance experts say the rule should be changed so that investors can have a clear, prompt picture of executive stock sales.The Securities and Exchange Commission, to prevent executives from unfairly profiting from their knowledge by selling company stock shortly before releasing bad news, requires them to report any such transactions. Even when executives are not selling shares because of pending bad news, many investors consider a management team's stockholdings to be an important measure of their confidence in the company.''For the life of me, I cannot imagine why investors shouldn't know that an executive is selling large chunks of stock to the company, whatever the reason,'' said Paul Elliott, an analyst at Thomson Financial/First Call, who tracks insider trades. ''After all, the shareholders are essentially the ones buying the stock.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/06/business/company-news-lower-costs-aid-rise-in-profit-at-colgate-palmolive.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; LOWER COSTS AID RISE IN PROFIT AT COLGATE-PALMOLIVE<date>Published: February 06, 2002</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company reported a 3 percent increase in fourth-quarter profit, helped by lower costs, a foreign tax credit and strength from product introductions. The company, which is based in New York and is best known for Colgate toothpaste, Speed Stick deodorant and Palmolive dish detergent, said yesterday that it had earned $295.3 million, or 49 cents a share, in the quarter ended Dec. 31, compared with $286.7 million, or 46 cents a share, a year earlier.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/05/nyregion/for-difrancesco-fighting-words-in-deodorant-ad.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">For DiFrancesco, Fighting Words In Deodorant Ad<date>Published: May 05, 2001</date><text>It is not often that the chief executive of a big state demands an apology for a deodorant ad. But Acting Gov. Donald T. DiFrancesco appears to have caught Devils fever.The Toronto Maple Leafs and the New Jersey Devils are tied, 2-2, in the National Hockey League playoffs, with Game 5 of their four-of-seven series set for Saturday night at Continental Arena in East Rutherford, N.J.At least one corporate citizen of both Canada and New Jersey -- the Colgate-Palmolive Company -- appears to have taken sides in the series. On Thursday, an ad for the company's Mennen Speed Stick ran in both The Toronto Star and The Toronto Sun, showing a map of New Jersey and a picture of the deodorant. ''Unfortunately, there are some smells even we can't do anything about,'' the ad reads. ''Go Leafs Go.''The ad provoked Mr. DiFrancesco to make an outburst of indignation today, punctuated with clunky hockey references. ''What stinks is a company trying to further their economic interests at the expense of New Jersey's reputation,'' he said. ''I can understand trying to score with Maple Leafs fans who must be sweating right now, but this slap shot at the Garden State has put Colgate in the penalty box with me.''The, er, power play did not last long, however. Mr. DiFrancesco fired off a semi-serious letter of protest to Reuben Mark, the chief executive of Colgate-Palmolive, noting that it employs nearly 2,000 people in New Jersey and that the Mennen Company was a leading New Jersey manufacturer until Colgate bought it in 1992.Mr. Mark put up no resistance, saying in a statement and in letters to a few dozen people who complained today, that Colgate was sorry ''for the disrespectful and disparaging advertisement.''Asked if Mr. DiFrancesco would have dropped the gloves to battle Mr. Mark had he not apologized, the acting governor's spokeswoman, Rae Hutton, said Mr. DiFrancesco ''believed that our hockey team would have taken care of things anyway.''</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/23/nyregion/c-corrections-990710.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Corrections<date>Published: April 23, 2001</date><text>An article on Friday about Colgate-Palmolive's first-quarter earnings misstated the decline in market share for Procter &amp; Gamble's Crest toothpaste in the period. The share dropped to 26.3 percent from 27 percent a year earlier, not to 24.3 percent.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/02/business/company-news-new-products-help-colgate-post-10-increase-in-profit.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; NEW PRODUCTS HELP COLGATE POST 10% INCREASE IN PROFIT<date>Published: February 02, 2001</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company, said yesterday that its fourth-quarter profit rose 10 percent as new products increased sales in North America. Net income rose to $286.7 million, or 46 cents a share, compared with $260.6 million, or 41 cents a share, a year earlier, Colgate said. Sales rose 2.9 percent, to $2.41 billion from $2.34 billion. Analysts had expected the company to earn 45 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial. The company said earnings in the first quarter would rise at least 10 percent. Oral-care products and lower costs lifted Colgate's results even though falling currencies in Europe and Asia hurt its competitors. Shares of Colgate-Palmolive rose $1, to $61.08.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/30/business/company-news-henkel-household-chemicals-maker-in-colgate-deal.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; HENKEL, HOUSEHOLD CHEMICALS MAKER, IN COLGATE DEAL<date>Published: December 30, 2000</date><text>The German household chemicals group Henkelsaid yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the Colgate-Palmolive Company's Mexican detergent business. Financial terms were not disclosed. Colgate has been de-emphasizing detergents in favor of personal care and oral care businesses, where margins are higher. The Mexican unit has annual sales of $77.42 million.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/business/colgate-results-increase-15-in-3rd-quarter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Results Increase 15% in 3rd Quarter<date>Published: October 25, 2000</date><text>Colgate-Palmolive, the consumer products giant that told analysts last month to cut sales forecasts because of the falling euro, said yesterday that its third-quarter profit rose 15 percent as new products helped in North America.Net income rose to $275.3 million, or 44 cents a diluted share, compared with $239.7 million, or 38 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Sales rose 2.3 percent, to $2.37 billion from $2.31 billion.Analysts had expected Colgate to earn 43 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.New products and lower costs will allow Colgate to increase earnings about 15 percent next year, said Reuben Mark, the chief executive.Colgate, based in New York, rose $4.29, to $53.50.While the euro has declined 22 percent the last year, Colgate said it would meet analysts' forecasts for the fourth quarter and 2001. More than 20 percent of its sales are from Europe.The company is expected to earn 46 cents a share in the fourth quarter and $1.90 in 2001, according to First Call.Analysts reduced their sales forecasts to an increase of 2 percent to 3 percent from about 5 percent after Colgate told them to cut estimates.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/study-finds-that-many-large-companies-pay-no-taxes.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Study Finds That Many Large Companies Pay No Taxes<date>Published: October 20, 2000</date><text>Goodyear, Texaco, Colgate-Palmolive, MCI WorldCom and eight other large corporations earned more than $12.2 billion in profits in 1996 through 1998, but none of them ended up owing corporate income taxes over that period, according to a study released yesterday. Indeed, as a group, the companies received $535 million in credits or refunds, the report found.The study of 250 large publicly traded companies showed that 24 owed no tax or received credits against past or future tax obligations in 1998, up from 13 in 1997 and 16 in 1996. The study also found that 71 of the 250 companies paid taxes at less than half the official 35 percent corporate rate during the three-year period.The study was conducted by the Institute on Taxation and Economic Policy, a Washington research organization associated with Citizens for Tax Justice, a nonprofit group supported in part by labor unions. The group argues that the tax system favors the rich and politically connected.Corporate profits overall soared 23.5 percent during the three-year period, but corporate tax revenues grew just 7.7 percent, a disjunction that has drawn intense interest from the Treasury Department and some members of Congress who are concerned about the growing market for tax shelters and their abuse.In recent years, Congress has watered down the 1986 overhaul of the tax laws, which lowered rates and eliminated most tax shelters, and was supposed to simplify reporting. The recent changes have opened fresh opportunities for corporations to cut their taxes, the study found.''Corporate taxes are not rising along with profits because companies have found all sorts of ways to get around the reforms in the 1986 tax act,'' said Robert S. McIntyre, the director of Citizens for Tax Justice. ''Companies also have gotten a lot of help from Congress, especially in gutting the minimum tax rules.''Mr. McIntyre said that he and T. D. Coo Nguyen, the co-author, spent more than two years examining financial statements the companies sent to shareholders.All but 18 of the companies studied are on the Fortune 500 list, and the others are in the Fortune 1000. He said companies were excluded if they lost money or their tax disclosures ''were crafted so that you could not figure them out.''At least two companies objected to the study's methodology.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/15/business/colgate-shares-drop-16-after-reports-by-analysts.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Shares Drop 16% After Reports by Analysts<date>Published: September 15, 2000</date><text>Shares of Colgate-Palmolive tumbled nearly 16 percent yesterday after analysts expressed doubts that the company would meet sales targets, citing the yearlong plunge in the euro.Stubbornly high petroleum prices, meanwhile, are expected to limit Colgate's ability to cut costs.In recent quarters, Colgate, the maker of America's best-selling toothpaste and dishwashing liquid, has been a bastion of strength in the consumer products industry, consistently meeting and exceeding analysts' forecasts at a time when some of its principal competitors -- including Procter &amp; Gamble, Clorox, and Dial -- have repeatedly warned of lethargic sales. As a result, investor enthusiasm for Colgate has surged, propelling its stock price to 35 times earnings as of Wednesday, up to 60 percent higher than others in the category, analysts said.But after Colgate executives discussed operations with several analysts on Wednesday, they began predicting that sales would fall short.Andrew Shore, an influential analyst with Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown, said that the company's third-quarter results ''will signal a reversal of fortune.'' Mr. Shore downgraded the company's stock from ''buy'' to ''market perform,'' unleashing a sell-off that clipped nearly $5 billion from Colgate's market value before lunch. Shares of Colgate dropped $8.81 to $47.38, and other consumer products stocks fell, as well, on word of the downgrade.Reuben Mark, Colgate's chairman and chief executive, issued a midday statement saying the company expected to meet analysts' earnings expectations, but that did little to reverse the stock's slide. Though Colgate may report high earnings this quarter, analysts fear that the company will have to tap into its reserves and cut back on expenses like advertising to do so, moves that would hurt its future prospects.Some analysts speculated that, even if temporary, the company's dip in stock price could make it an acquisition target for overseas companies looking to break into the American market. Both Henkel, the giant German consumer products giant, and Kao, Asia's powerhouse in the industry, are seeking a foothold in the United States. Marketing their own products here would be futile, analysts say, because Americans are fiercely loyal to the brands they recognize, so a takeover of a momentarily rattled company might be appealing.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/22/business/colgate-net-up-12-in-quarter.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Net Up 12% in Quarter<date>Published: October 22, 1999</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company, the world's largest toothpaste maker, said yesterday that its third-quarter earnings rose 12 percent as it sold more products in North America and Asia and cut costs.Net income for the company, which makes Total toothpaste, Mennen deodorant and other consumer products, rose to $239.7 million, or 38 cents a share, from $214.9 million, or 33 cents, a year ago. Sales increased 2.1 percent, to $2.31 billion, from $2.27 billion.New York-based Colgate, which gets a quarter of its sales in Latin America, was hurt by Brazil's balky economy and falling currency, while helped by new products like Total gel toothpaste in North America. The company also pared costs by using fewer suppliers and package sizes. Colgate rose $3.75, to $57.75, on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday.The New York-based company had been expected to earn 37 cents, the average estimate of analysts surveyed by the First Call Corporation.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/14/business/company-news-playtex-is-acquiring-baby-magic-brand-from-colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; PLAYTEX IS ACQUIRING BABY MAGIC BRAND FROM COLGATE<date>Published: May 14, 1999</date><text>Playtex Products Inc. signed an agreement to acquire the Baby Magic brand in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico from the Colgate-Palmolive Company for $90 million in cash. Colgate will retain the rights to the brand for all geographic regions outside the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. The brand includes infant-related bath, lotion, shampoo, oil and powder products. In 1998, the Baby Magic brand generated net sales of $48.9 million in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. Playtex had sales of $669.6 million in 1998.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/23/business/colgate-s-appeal-on-tax-shelter-is-rejected.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate's Appeal on Tax Shelter Is Rejected<date>Published: March 23, 1999</date><text>The Supreme Court rejected without comment today a bid by the Colgate-Palmolive Company to gain tens of millions of dollars in tax benefits through an offshore shelter devised by Merrill Lynch &amp; Company.Merrill Lynch had set up an unusual partnership to create losses that Colgate could deduct from its taxable income. A lower court barred use of the losses, saying they were ''sham transactions'' that had no purpose other than tax avoidance, and the high court rejected the partnership's appeal.The decision means Colgate cannot take a $98 million deduction, which lawyers say would have given the company more than $25 million in tax savings.Ten other Merrill Lynch clients -- including Allied Signal, American Home Products, the Brunswick Corporation and Schering-Plough -- are seeking to use the same device. Several are fighting similar court cases, so far without success. ''Each case will be judged on its own set of facts,'' said Bill Halldin, a Merrill Lynch spokesman. He said Merrill, the nation's largest brokerage firm, was disappointed with the decision.A spokeswoman for Colgate said the case ''has no impact on the company's current or future profits'' and declined to comment further.In 1989, Merrill Lynch approached Colgate with the idea for the partnership as a way to offset $105 million in capital gains that Colgate, the New York-based consumer products company, had incurred when it sold its Kendall Company subsidiary in 1988.A Merrill subsidiary set up a partnership in Bermuda with Algemene Bank Nederland N.V., now a unit of ABN Amro Holding N.V., the largest Dutch bank. The partnership engaged in a series of transactions that allowed the bank to claim a paper profit in 1989 and Colgate to claim roughly the same amount in losses -- $98 million -- in later years.Since ABN was not an American taxpayer, it did not have to pay taxes on the gain. Colgate still sought to take advantage of the loss on its taxes. Merrill received almost $8 million in fees.The Internal Revenue Service said Colgate could not claim the loss because the transactions were ''devoid of economic substance.'' A Tax Court judge agreed, and the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit upheld that ruling last year in a 2-to-1 decision.The Supreme Court's decision came as the second-ranking official in the Treasury Department, Lawrence H. Summers, promoted a crackdown on corporate tax shelters. The Clinton Administration has proposed higher penalties and an end to tax-avoidance plans that have no economic purpose.''We believe there is a major problem,'' Mr. Summers told the Tax Executives Institute today. He cited an estimate that tax-shelter arrangements cost the Treasury $10 billion a year in lost revenue.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/16/nyregion/faulty-repair-seen-in-97-helicopter-crash.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Faulty Repair Seen in '97 Helicopter Crash<date>Published: December 16, 1998</date><text>A corporate helicopter that snapped apart at the tail just after takeoff in April 1997, crashing into the East River and killing a passenger, had been improperly repaired with a part that is vulnerable to metal fatigue, members of the National Transportation Safety Board said today.The part, a type of hollow rivet, has also probably been used in other aircraft in places where it might fail, officials said. One safety board member said that the Federal Aviation Administration may eventually need to require that aircraft brought in for maintenance be inspected for hollow rivets installed in inappropriate places.''This problem is probably more widespread than we can imagine,'' said the board member, John Goglia, a former aircraft mechanic who said he himself had installed many such hollow rivets as substitutes for solid ones.The fasteners, called blind rivets, resemble the heavy-duty picture hooks sold at hardware stores that can be pushed through a small hole, expanded behind the wall and pulled snug without the installer's having access to the other side. Blind rivets can hasten aircraft repairs because they do not require mechanics to remove internal parts to get access to the inside.Mechanics at the Colgate-Palmolive Company, the owner of the helicopter that crashed in New York, installed the blind rivets in December 1992 when they replaced a part of the tail that had cracked. When the tail later cracked again, leading to the 1997 crash, the rivets were partly to blame, investigators say.A Federal Aviation Administration advisory document, which was cited by safety board members meeting today to discuss their staff's findings in the East River crash, says blind rivets can be used with the approval of the aircraft or rivet manufacturer. But Les Dorr Jr., an F.A.A. spokesman, said that the wording of the document ''could be confusing'' and that the aviation administration did not mean for mechanics to rely solely on the rivet manufacturer's advice.At the safety board's meeting, Mr. Goglia displayed a technical document from Textron Inc., the manufacturer of the rivets used on the Colgate-Palmolive helicopter, saying that blind rivets could be used to replace solid rivets. But other Textron documents noted that while blind rivets are as strong as solid ones in resisting shearing or stretching, they are less able to withstand repeated bending, which is exactly the stress they were subject to on the helicopter's tail.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/03/business/company-news-first-brands-to-acquire-2-product-lines-from-colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; FIRST BRANDS TO ACQUIRE 2 PRODUCT LINES FROM COLGATE<date>Published: July 03, 1998</date><text>The First Brands Corporation agreed yesterday to buy Handi Wipes re-usable cleaning cloths and Wash'n Dri pre-moistened towelettes from the Colgate-Palmolive Company for an undisclosed price to expand its household products business. First Brands, which generated $1.12 billion in sales in the 1997 fiscal year through consumer products such as Jonny Cat cat-box litter and STP automotive products, said the two towel brands, each market leaders in their respective categories, had combined sales of $20 million in 1997. First Brands shares fell $4, to $21.9375, and Colgate's shares fell 37.5 cents, to $88.25.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/25/business/company-news-colgate-palmolive-paid-chairman-3.85-million-in-1997.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE PAID CHAIRMAN $3.85 MILLION IN 1997<date>Published: March 25, 1998</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company paid its chairman and chief executive, Reuben Mark, $3.85 million last year, up 44 percent from 1996, and awarded him 2.6 million stock options after a directors' compensation committee study found his pay ranked below that of comparable executives. Mr. Mark, 59, received $1.12 million in salary, a $2.72 million bonus and $3.38 million in restricted stock, as well as 2.6 million options with strike prices ranging from $68.6125 to $106.0375, or 10 percent to 70 percent over the price of the stock when the options were granted. They are the only stock options he will receive until 2003, the New York-based company said. It makes Colgate toothpaste and Hill's Science Diet pet foods. Mr. Mark had a gain of $18.2 million last year from exercising older options and still holds $148.6 million in other options.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/24/science/tough-tactics-in-one-battle-over-animals-in-the-lab.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Tough Tactics In One Battle Over Animals In the Lab<date>Published: March 24, 1998</date><text>ALAN STAPLE, the president of a New Jersey company that conducts animal tests for other companies, was attending a conference in England last May when he was jolted awake by a telephone call at 3 A.M. from his company's vice president.There was a corporate emergency, the company officer said. An animal rights group had asserted that the company mistreated dogs in tests it had done for Colgate-Palmolive. The group, People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals, or PETA, was starting a wide campaign calling for consumers to boycott Colgate products.Colgate had been testing an antibacterial agent it wanted to add to toothpaste, Mr. Staple said. The company soon canceled all of its contracts with Mr. Staple's company, Huntingdon Life Sciences of East Millstone, N.J. But that was only the beginning of Huntingdon's troubles. The company said it later learned that an undercover investigator for the animal rights group, who had been employed at Huntingdon, had used a camera hidden in her eyeglasses to secretly make 50 hours of videotapes of the company's laboratories. She had also made 4 audiotapes of 90 minutes each, photocopied 8,000 company documents, many of them containing corporate trade secrets, and copied the company's client list, Mr. Staple said. And the group had contacted the clients, asking them to reconsider doing business with the company.Within months, Huntingdon had lost more than half of its clients. But unlike any other company or research group that had been investigated by PETA, Huntingdon fought back. And thus ensued a battle between those who support the use of animals in research and those who oppose it. The result was a look at how PETA, the most vocal animal rights organization, gathers its evidence and wins victories.The organization's public campaign against Huntingdon was the culmination of an immense effort, said Ingrid Newkirk, the group's president, and resulted from an investigation so arduous that the group can only undertake one every year or two. She acknowledged that the group's investigator had copied company documents, including a client list, and had made videotapes, but said the tactics were necessary to show what was going on in the lab.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/20/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-colgate-palmolive-sweeps-awards.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Colgate-Palmolive Sweeps Awards<date>Published: March 20, 1998</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company cleaned up last night at the 12th annual presentation of the Edison Best New Product Awards, sponsored by the American Marketing Association.At a ceremony in New York, Colgate-Palmolive was awarded the Grand Edison New Product Marketer of the Year award for the introductions of 10 products including the hot-selling Colgate Total toothpaste. Colgate-Palmolive also won a gold Edison for Total and two silver Edisons for the Colgate Wave Toothbrush and Softsoap Aquarium Series Liquid Soap.Offices of Foote, Cone &amp; Belding, part of True North Communications, was honored as the New Product Agency of the Year, winning eight gold, silver and bronze Edisons for clients including the Campbell Soup Company, S. C. Johnson &amp; Son, Kraft Foods, Nabisco and the 3Com Corporation.Two Edison Achievement Awards for contributions to marketing throughout a career were presented. The recipients were Martha Stewart, chairwoman of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia L.L.C. in New York, and Reuben Mark, chairman and chief executive of Colgate-Palmolive in New York.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/02/business/company-news-colgate-to-sell-heating-fuel-business-for-70-million.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE TO SELL HEATING FUEL BUSINESS FOR $70 MILLION<date>Published: October 02, 1997</date><text>Blyth Industries said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the portable heating fuel business, including the Sterno and Handy Fuel brand names, from a unit of the Colgate-Palmolive Company for $70 million. Blyth Industries, based in Greenwich, Conn., makes candles and home-fragrance products. Colgate Palmolive, based in New York, makes consumer products including Colgate toothpaste and Mennen deodorants. The purchase, which is expected to close by the end of the year, includes manufacturing and distribution operations in Texarkana, Tex.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/15/business/new-toothpaste-from-colgate-set.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">New Toothpaste From Colgate Set<date>Published: July 15, 1997</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that it had cleared the last regulatory hurdle for selling Colgate Total toothpaste, the first paste approved for marketing as effective in simultaneously fighting gingivitis, plaque and cavities.The product, which had been bogged down in negotiations between the manufacturer and the Food and Drug Administration over product labeling, has received the agency's approval for marketing and is expected to be on store shelves within six months.Colgate Total is the latest product to be introduced in a push by toothpaste manufacturers to add new ingredients and therapeutic benefits to their brands in an attempt to grab market share in this hotly contested consumer products category. Colgate Total is expected to compete with the Procter &amp; Gamble Company's Crest Multicare toothpaste, which the company introduced this month. Crest, the best-selling brand in the country, has been losing market share as P.&amp; G.'s competitors, including Colgate-Palmolive, have been quicker to introduce new formulas.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/26/nyregion/flaw-cited-in-fatal-crash-had-been-found-in-3-other-copters.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Flaw Cited in Fatal Crash Had Been Found in 3 Other Copters<date>Published: April 26, 1997</date><text>Three helicopters of the type that crashed in Manhattan last week, killing a passenger, had earlier been found to have cracks in their tails, the same flaw blamed in the accident. But the Federal Aviation Administration said it had not learned of those cracks until after last week's crash.The F.A.A. today ordered the grounding of all 132 helicopters in the United States of that model, the German-made BK-117, so mechanics could check for cracks in the tail. Any helicopters found to have cracks will be grounded indefinitely, the F.A.A. said, because there is no approved repair procedure.On April 15, a helicopter owned by Colgate-Palmolive crashed into the East River just after taking off from the 60th Street heliport in Manhattan. The company's chief technology officer, Craig B. Tate, 51, was killed. Another passenger and one of the two pilots were seriously injured. Investigators said the tail broke off.The F.A.A. said a crack began in a U-shaped rib in the tail and gradually spread ''until only the outer skin was carrying the flight load.''Then, the agency said, it spread ''until catastrophic overstress occurred.''''This condition, if not corrected, could result in failure of the vertical fin and subsequent loss of control of the helicopter,'' the agency said.The helicopter was a BK-117, manufactured by Eurocopter Deutschland, a German company. F.A.A. officials said today that three helicopters of that model had previously had cracks in the tail, though none had resulted in accidents.The F.A.A. said the earlier cracks had been repaired by the manufacturer, but Timothy Ruddick, a spokesman for Eurocopter's American office in Grand Prairie, Tex., said his company had not done the repair work. He said the cracks could have been repaired on a case-by-case basis under authorizations by engineers designated by the F.A.A.Larry M. Kelly, acting manager of the F.A.A.'s rotocraft directorate, said one question is ''how the earlier ones didn't make it into the system.'' Any such operating problems are supposed to be reported to the F.A.A. and entered into its databases.Mr. Kelly said the cracks were caused by metal fatigue, meaning that the metal had been bent too often or too severely or both. The probable reason is a design flaw, he said in a telephone interview from his office in Fort Worth.The agency has been repeatedly criticized in recent years by Congressional auditors and others for gaps in data collection.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/19/nyregion/helicopter-crash-inquiry-focuses-on-broken-parts.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Helicopter Crash Inquiry Focuses on Broken Parts<date>Published: April 19, 1997</date><text>Federal investigators said yesterday that it could take more than a week to determine the cause of a fatal crash of a corporate helicopter in the East River on Tuesday. They said they had narrowed the search for an explanation to the helicopter's tail rotor and drive shaft.Bob Hancock, who is directing the investigation for the National Transportation Safety Board, said part of the helicopter's tail had broken off where the drive shaft and the rotor were coupled. He said he sent pieces of the helicopter to the board's laboratory in Washington to try to determine whether the parts broke on impact or the break might have caused the crash.The helicopter, which is owned by Colgate-Palmolive, crashed just after taking off at about 5:30 P.M. on Tuesday, killing one passenger, Craig B. Tate, 51, Colgate-Palmolive's chief technological officer. The other passenger, James. M. Serafino, 44, a lawyer for Colgate-Palmolive, remained in critical but stable condition yesterday at New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center.The condition of the pilot, Edward Thurn, 52, was upgraded yesterday to stable. The co-pilot, Rick Bird, was released from the hospital on Wednesday.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/17/nyregion/investigators-say-part-helicopter-s-tail-broke-off-before-fatal-crash-into-river.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Investigators Say Part of Helicopter's Tail Broke Off Before Fatal Crash Into River<date>Published: April 17, 1997</date><text>Federal investigators said yesterday that the helicopter that plunged into the East River Tuesday, killing a corporate executive, crashed after a three-foot section of the aircraft's tail that included the rear rotor broke off shortly after takeoff from the 60th Street heliport.Bob Hancock, an air safety investigator for the National Transportation Safety Board, said the BK-117 helicopter was operating normally until it was approximately 30 feet above the heliport landing pad. At that moment, a ''loud bang'' and sparks came from the rear of the helicopter, and it spun to the right before dropping upside down into the river, he said. The tail section of the helicopter flew through the window of the heliport terminal building.Mr. Hancock said there was no indication that the helicopter, which was owned by the Colgate-Palmolive Company, hit the one-story heliport building as it took off, which city officials said Tuesday night was a possible cause of the accident. Mr. Hancock also said that the cockpit controls appeared to be set appropriately for takeoff, an indication the two-man crew was following procedures. In addition, he said there appeared to be no problem with the helicopter's engines.Investigators interviewed Rick Bird, the helicopter's co-pilot, who escaped without serious injuries and was released from the hospital yesterday. The pilot, Edward Thurn, 52, of Sparta, N.J., and one of the passengers, James M. Serafino, 44, of Stamford, Conn., a corporate lawyer for Colgate-Palmolive, remained in critical condition yesterday at New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center after nearly drowning, according to a statement from the hospital. Mr. Serafino was unconscious, but Mr. Thurn had regained consciousness.The crash took the life of Craig B. Tate, 51, of New Canaan, Conn., Colgate's chief technical officer.Although Mr. Hancock said investigators had not determined what caused the accident, the crash added fuel to protests from residents and politicians from the East Side who had been complaining of helicopter traffic because of noise and safety concerns.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/17/nyregion/praise-for-executive-who-died-in-helicopter-crash.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Praise for Executive Who Died in Helicopter Crash<date>Published: April 17, 1997</date><text>Craig B. Tate, the Colgate-Palmolive executive who died Tuesday when a company helicopter plunged into the East River, was as much a family man and a man of faith as he was a businessman.Mr. Tate, who was on his way to White Plains Airport, climbed the corporate ladder in a 28-year career with Colgate-Palmolive, handling a number of overseas assignments, including a stint as vice president for global marketing. But friends say he still carved out time to help his four children with their homework and to sing in the church choir. $(Obituary, page B13.$)''He was a prime example of a Christian corporate executive who refused to separate his business life from his family life from his faith life,'' said the Rev. Gary A. Wilburn, senior pastor of the First Presbyterian Church of New Canaan, Conn., where Mr. Tate was a deacon, a church elder and the church clerk.Mr. Wilburn recalled that Mr. Tate, 51, had flown to New Canaan, his home of 20 years, from Indonesia when he was president of Colgate-Palmolive's Far East division, so he could go Christmas caroling and attend his children's birthday parties.''I asked him, 'How do you find the time to do everything?' '' Mr. Wilburn recalled. ''And he said: 'I don't have the time. I choose to make the time, because it's important to me.' ''Robert Murray, a Colgate-Palmolive spokesman, who once reported to Mr. Tate, recalled him as ''a great intellect'' and a great tennis player, always carrying a tennis racket with him on his global travels. Like Mr. Wilburn, he was struck by Mr. Tate's ability to juggle the professional and the personal.''He was an amazing person, a bright hard worker, yet an incredible family man, who had great love for his wife and family, and was a valued member of his church,'' Mr. Murray said. ''His ability to balance was amazing.''Mr. Tate, who was named Colgate-Palmolive's chief technological officer in 1994, was pronounced dead on arrival at New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center. He was pulled from the wrecked helicopter in the murk of the East River together with James M. Serafino, 44, a lawyer for Colgate-Palmolive, who survived the crash.Mr. Serafino, a Stamford, Conn., resident who is married and the father of two children, was unconscious and remained in critical condition yesterday in the hospital's surgical intensive care unit. A hospital spokesman said he was being treated for respiratory failure, exposure, hypothermia and the effects of near-drowning.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/17/nyregion/craig-butler-tate-51-executive-for-colgate-palmolive-company.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Craig Butler Tate, 51, Executive For Colgate-Palmolive Company<date>Published: April 17, 1997</date><text>Craig B. Tate, a corporate executive who began his lifelong career with the Colgate-Palmolive Company as a summer intern and rose to become its chief technological officer with primary responsibility for product development, died on Tuesday evening in a helicopter crash in the East River off Manhattan. He was 51 and lived in New Canaan, Conn.The cause of death was cardiac arrest, said Myrna Manners, a spokeswoman for New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center, where he was taken after the crash.In his 28-year career at Colgate-Palmolive, a multinational consumer products manufacturer that is the world's largest seller of toothpaste, toothbrushes and deodorants, Mr. Tate served in a number of executive positions, including high posts in Europe, Asia and the United States. He opened the company's first manufacturing plant in China.As chief technological officer since 1994, Mr. Tate had ''global responsibility for research and development, patents, manufacturing engineering technology, information technology, strategic materials and environmental affairs,'' according to a biographical statement from the company.Craig Butler Tate was born on June 16, 1945 in Winston-Salem, N.C. He grew up in Omaha, Neb., and received a bachelor's degree in economics from Stanford University in 1967. In 1969, he received a master's degree from Dartmouth College's Amos Tuck School of Business Administration.It was in the summer before graduating from the Tuck School that Mr. Tate worked as an intern with Colgate-Palmolive. After graduating, he returned to Colgate-Palmolive and worked in various marketing and product management jobs. In 1984 and 1985, he worked as vice president and executive assistant to Reuben Mark, the company's chief executive officer. Later, he became the vice president for worldwide new products and vice president for global marketing.Mr. Tate was elected an officer of the corporation in 1989 and in 1992 was named president of Colgate-Palmolive's Far East division.He is survived by his wife, Sharon; and four children, Christopher, who is studying at Stanford, Andrew, Melissa and Carrie.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/16/nyregion/short-trip-home-from-plant-ends-in-tragedy-for-executive.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Short Trip Home From Plant Ends in Tragedy for Executive<date>Published: April 16, 1997</date><text>Craig B. Tate, the executive who died yesterday in the crash of a Colgate-Palmolive Company helicopter, was a driven corporate man who climbed the company ladder and an equally driven family man who enjoyed barbecues and pool parties with his family, neighbors in Connecticut said last night.Mr. Tate, who was pronounced dead of cardiac arrest upon arrival at New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center, was pulled from the wrecked helicopter in the murk of the East River together with James M. Serafino, 44, a lawyer for Colgate-Palmolive, who survived the crash.Mr. Serafino, who is married with two children and is also from Connecticut, was in critical condition at the hospital last night.Robert A. Murray, vice president for corporate relations at Colgate-Palmolive, said the helicopter had flown to New York from the company's development plant in Piscataway, N.J., and was headed to White Plains. But he would not release information on the victims of the crash, citing concern for their families.But newspaper clippings and corporate reference books show that at Colgate-Palmolive, the multibillion-dollar consumer products manufacturer, Mr. Tate, who was in his 50's, rose to the position of chief technical officer, according to the Standard &amp; Poor's Register.But while dedicated to his work, which often sent him traveling around the world, his neighbors said, he loved to be at home on his leafy street in New Canaan, Conn., where there was a swimming pool in the backyard.''I used to take the train home with him from New York every day and he would bury himself in his work because he said when he got home he wanted to spend all his time with his family, helping his kids with their homework,'' said Joseph Espeso, who has lived across the street from Mr. Tate for 14 years.Mr. Serafino, Colgate-Palmolive's vice president and senior associate general counsel for technology and marketing, lives with his wife and two children in Stamford, the same city where he grew up, said his sister-in-law, Sally Serafino.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/16/nyregion/executive-dies-and-3-are-hurt-in-an-east-river-copter-crash.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Executive Dies and 3 Are Hurt in an East River Copter Crash<date>Published: April 16, 1997</date><text>A corporate executive was killed and three other people were injured when their helicopter crashed into the East River moments after lifting off from the heliport at 60th Street in Manhattan.Witnesses said the helicopter plunged into the river about 15 feet from shore after the rear rotor flew off the aircraft and lodged in the heliport's one-story terminal. Police officials said the pilot and co-pilot of the six-seat BK-117 helicopter escaped on their own, but the two passengers were underwater for 10 to 15 minutes before being pulled from helicopter by police divers.The passengers were both executives of Colgate-Palmolive and were riding in a helicopter owned by the company. The police identified the dead passenger as Craig Tate, of New Canaan, Conn., who was in his 50's and identified in corporate records as the company's chief technical officer.Robert A. Murray, the company's vice president for corporate relations, said the helicopter was one of two owned by the company and was used to ferry employees between its corporate headquarters in New York and its research and development plant in Piscataway, N.J.The helicopter had just come from Piscataway, had let off two passengers in Manhattan and was taking off for White Plains about 5:35 P.M. when the accident occurred, said Police Commissioner Howard Safir.''It appears the tail rotor came off the helicopter for whatever reason and the helicopter went into the river,'' Mr. Safir said.It was the sixth helicopter crash in 12 years in the East River, and came as traffic has been increasing at East River heliports, drawing complaints from residents and politicians.The National Transportation Safety Board said it was investigating whether the helicopter hit the building as it rose, knocking off the rotor. But witnesses said the aircraft was above the building when the rear rotor sparked and broke off.''It rose about 30, 35 feet and it started sparking in the rear,'' said Jose Collado, a livery-cab driver who was waiting at the heliport for someone to arrive. ''You heard cracking in the back and then the helicopter turned and and went into the water.''The accident happened at rush hour in the middle of a maze of traffic. The heliport, bounded to the west by the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive, is just north of the Queensboro Bridge and the tramway to Roosevelt Island. Nearby streets and esplanades were full of joggers and strollers taking advantage of the late afternoon sunshine.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/07/business/tax-court-rejects-phantom-loss-by-colgate.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Tax Court Rejects 'Phantom Loss' by Colgate<date>Published: March 07, 1997</date><text>The Federal Tax Court has rejected as a sham an elaborate maneuver devised by Merrill Lynch &amp; Company that had enabled the Colgate-Palmolive Company to avoid paying taxes on $98 million of gains it made in selling a subsidiary.The decision, issued Wednesday, dismissed as without substance the elaborate maneuvers, which involved a partnership that allocated capital gains largely to one partner -- a foreign bank not subject to American tax -- and capital losses to Colgate, which used the losses to offset the capital gains on the sale of a subsidiary.The case had attracted attention because it involved a clever stream of transactions that seemed to fit within the tax laws, and because Merrill, at the trial before the tax court, was forced to disclose that it had put together similar deals for such companies as Allied Signal, American Home Products, Borden, Dun &amp; Bradstreet and Schering-Plough. At least some of those transactions have also been challenged by the Internal Revenue Service, but Wednesday's decision was the first by a court on the issue.In the decision, the tax court ruled that it did not find any ''economic substance'' to the transactions, other than to avoid taxes. It said that Colgate was not motivated by the pursuit of an investment profit, but by a desire to avoid taxes on another transaction.''We do not suggest that a taxpayer refrain from using the tax laws to the taxpayer's advantage,'' the court said. ''In this case, however, the taxpayer desired to take advantage of a loss that was not economically inherent in the object of the sale, but which the taxpayer created artificially through the manipulation and abuse of the tax laws. A taxpayer is not entitled to recognize a phantom loss from a transaction that lacks economic substance.''Steven Surdell, a partner in the Chicago law firm of Block &amp; Jenner, said the ruling was the first to apply sophisticated analysis of interest rate swaps and various other financial techniques, and then to use that analysis to conclude that the transaction lacked economic substance.Colgate issued a statement saying that the ruling would have no effect on its cash position or reported profits, since it involved a tax bill that had been previously paid and that Colgate was trying to recover. A Merrill Lynch spokesman declined to comment.The Colgate maneuver involved setting up a partnership, owned by it, ABN-Amro Holding N.V., a Dutch bank, and Merrill Lynch. The partnership bought some Citibank notes in 1989, then sold most of them later that year. Using a section of the tax law, it allocated only part of the cost of the notes to the ones sold, thus creating a large paper profit, most of which was allocated to ABN-Amro.Then, ABN-Amro left the partnership. The sale of the rest of the Citibank notes in later years created a large paper loss, most of which was allocated to Colgate. Colgate then applied to use that loss to recover taxes previously paid on the profit from the sale of a subsidiary. The I.R.S. rejected that move, and Colgate appealed to tax court.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/05/business/p-g-sues-colgate-on-tv-commercial.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">P.&amp; G. Sues Colgate On TV Commercial<date>Published: December 05, 1996</date><text>The Procter &amp; Gamble Company yesterday sued the Colgate-Palmolive Company and its agency, Young &amp; Rubicam Inc. in New York, contending that they deliberately copied a television commercial for Crest toothpaste that P.&amp; G. has run since 1989.In the lawsuit, filed in Federal District Court in New York, P.&amp; G. contends that a Colgate commercial by Y.&amp; R. -- using a seashell to demonstrate how the fluoride in Colgate toothpaste protects the calcium in teeth -- copies the Crest commercial, which uses an eggshell to make the same point.The suit seeks unspecified damages for copyright infringement and unfair competition.Bob Murray, a spokesman for Colgate-Palmolive in New York, said the Colgate demonstration ''is an independently created and distinctive execution of an idea which has been used by educators and the dental profession for decades.''Philippe Krakowsky, a spokesman for Y.&amp; R., declined to comment.The Crest spot was created by the D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles unit of MacManus Group in New York.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/15/realestate/jersey-city-s-waterfront-showing-signs-of-an-upturn.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Jersey City's Waterfront Showing Signs of an Upturn<date>Published: September 15, 1996</date><text>A ROLLER-COASTER office market took the commercial revitalization of the Hudson River waterfront here from the heights of the mid-80's to the depths of the early 90's, when construction ground to a halt. But in the years since, the riverfront has slowly rebounded, rekindling interest in building at the water's edge.At the northern end of the riverfront, the Lefrak Organization of Rego Park, Queens, is gearing up to build the 17-story, 750,000-square-foot Newport Office Centre III at its 400-acre Newport Center mixed-used project. About a mile south, on Colgate-Palmolive's 20-acre Colgate Center site, once occupied by a toothpaste factory, plans are advancing for a 12-story 435,000-square-foot building.Both projects have their approvals in place and will move forward once tenants are found to sign preconstruction leases, which are needed to obtain construction financing. The Lefrak Organization said it would build after 30 percent of its building was preleased. Colgate said it would go ahead when it had a tenant for half the space.Many commercial brokers say the plans reflect the strengthening of the office market along the Hudson County portion of the waterfront in general and of Jersey City's in particular. In turn, they said, the next round of office construction is not far behind.''The waterfront has been a major growth corridor for North Jersey since 1984 and since then Jersey City has given companies a lot of justification to move there,'' said Robert P. Antonicello, president of the ACI Group, a local real estate services concern. ''It is no longer a frontier. ''In that time some 8.6 million square feet of offices were built, initially for a flow of financial services companies from Manhattan seeking larger and less expensive space. A 1.2-million-square-foot regional mall was also constructed, as were thousands of residences within the waterfront redevelopment district, which stretches for 1.7 miles along the riverfront and roughly eight blocks inland.But then the 1987 stock market crash, followed by the real estate recession, stemmed the flow of tenants, leaving the riverfront with blocks of empty space and a vacancy rate that as recent as 1992 was as high as 36 percent. Under current zoning, at least 13.4 million more square feet of offices can be built on the remaining land in the district.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/07/realestate/postings-tenants-sought-for-2-planned-office-buildings-jersey-city-some-action.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">POSTINGS: Tenants Sought for 2 Planned Office Buildings;In Jersey City, Some Action on the Waterfront<date>Published: July 07, 1996</date><text>Plans are advancing for two office buildings along Jersey City's Hudson River waterfront that, if realized, would end a five-year lull in commercial construction at the river's edge.At the 600-acre Newport mixed-use project at the northern end of the waterfront the Lefrak Organization of Rego Park, Queens, is pushing Newport Office Centre III, which would have 750,000 square feet of space in a 17-story building.The complex is now home to 1.5 million square feet of mostly occupied offices in two buildings, most in Newport Tower.At the southern end of the Jersey City waterfront, on Colgate-Palmolive's 20-acre Colgate Center tract, which once held a toothpaste factory, a parcel is being readied for 90 Hudson Street, a 12-story, 435,000-square-foot structure.It would join 101 Hudson, a 1.2 million-square foot fully leased tower.Both projects are ready to go, their developers say, except for one thing. Each needs to find tenants to sign preconstruction leases for a significant portion of the space -- a financing prerequisite.Why are the developers choosing this time to push their search for tenants for the proposed buildings? Brokers say, and the developers agree, that in the last three years much of the 8.6 million square feet of offices along this city's waterfront has been leased, especially large blocks of Class A space. The vacancy rate for such space is 7.5 percent, according to Cushman &amp; Wakefield, the brokerage.Robert Cotter, the city's planning director, said the construction plans were "positive for the city to continue the waterfront's revival."Since the early 80's much has been built, from the office towers to a 1.2 million-square-foot mall and thousands of residences, to change the face of this gritty industrial strip.But empty lots still punctuate the waterfront redevelopment area, stretching 1.7 miles along the river and eight blocks inland, where Mr. Cotter said "we have the capacity for 13.4 million more square feet of offices."</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/30/business/executive-changes-082309.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Executive Changes<date>Published: May 30, 1996</date><text>COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO., New York, said its controller, Stephen C. Patrick, would become chief financial officer, succeeding Robert Agate, who will retire on July 1.DELOITTE &amp; TOUCHE CONSULTING GROUP, Chadds Ford, Pa., named Alfred Grunwald chief executive, succeeding Michael Pehl. E. W. SCRIPPS CO., Cincinnati, a newspaper publisher, has promoted its president and chief operating officer, William R. Burleigh, to chief executive. Mr. Burleigh succeeds Lawrence A. Leser, who will continue as chairman.ZURICH REINSURANCE CENTER HOLDINGS INC., New York, appointed Richard Smith, its president, to the additional position of chief executive. Steven Gluckstern will continue as chairman.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/07/nyregion/giving-a-hand-to-the-hands-of-time.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Giving a Hand to the Hands of Time<date>Published: April 07, 1996</date><text>This item appeared in the paper as a stand alone photograph. Caption information is provided below.Photos: Joe Horak, a caretaker of the Colgate Clock in Jersey City, setthe clock one hour ahead yesterday for the resumption of daylight saving time. The landmark clock, top right, built in 1924, overlooks the Hudson River and downtown Manhattan. Mr. Horak, right, cranked the timepiece's giant arms from a shed that houses the clock. (Photographs by LIBRADO ROMERO/The New York Times)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/09/business/company-reports-colgate-palmolive-co-cln.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY REPORTS;COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO. (CL,N)<date>Published: February 09, 1996</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that earnings fell about 11 percent in the fourth quarter, partly because of the peso devaluation and recession in Mexico.The company, whose brands include Colgate toothpaste, Irish Spring soap and Ajax cleanser, also pointed to lower sales growth in its pet food division. For the quarter that ended Dec. 31, Colgate earned $122.5 million, or 80 cents a share, compared with $137.1 million, or 91 cents a share, in the corresponding quarter in 1994. Sales rose about 8 percent, to $2.15 billion, bolstered by overseas growth. The results slightly exceeded Wall Street estimates.Reuben Mark, the company's chairman, said a revamping announced in September would lead to annual savings of $100 million beginning in the second half of the year.In addition, he said in a statement, "We have consolidated all worldwide advertising with one global agency, which will lead to better and more efficient advertising backed by further increases in media in 1996." (AP)</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/01/business/the-media-business-colgate-planning-a-big-shift-of-its-advertising-to-y-r.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS;Colgate Planning a Big Shift Of Its Advertising to Y.&amp; R.<date>Published: December 01, 1995</date><text>In one of the largest realignments ever for an advertising account, the Colgate-Palmolive Company unexpectedly announced yesterday that it would dismiss one of the two giant worldwide agencies that have shared the bulk of its assignments. The billings in the consolidation, affecting familiar household brands like Ajax and Mennen, involve about $550 million of the company's worldwide total of $625 million to $650 million.Colgate-Palmolive will remove from its agency roster Foote, Cone &amp; Belding, owned by True North Communications in Chicago, and shift about $150 million to $200 million in billings to Young &amp; Rubicam Inc. in New York. Those gains are expected to lift Colgate-Palmolive into the ranks of the four largest accounts at Y.&amp; R., along with the AT&amp;T Corporation, the Ford Motor Company and the Philip Morris Companies.For Colgate-Palmolive, it is the second big advertising realignment in less than two years. The consolidations reflect the new efforts of multinational marketers to make their ad budgets more efficient and their campaigns more effective.For instance, in 1994, I.B.M. consolidated its account, with billings estimated at $500 million, at the Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide unit of the WPP Group. Some companies, though, like Coca-Cola, have chosen not to consolidate; instead, they are hiring additional agencies to cast a wider net for creative ideas.Though "FCB has been a long-term and valued partner" said Reuben Mark, chairman and chief executive of Colgate-Palmolive in New York, the consolidation was "a further step to achieve increased efficiency." He said the company had also introduced an agency compensation system based on costs and performance, which would "generate savings that will be invested in additional media" spending.In essence, Y.&amp; R. has been the primary Colgate-Palmolive agency since a consolidation in February 1994 that awarded it lead status on important, faster-growing product categories like oral care (Colgate toothpaste) and personal care (Palmolive soap and shampoo).</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/21/business/colgate-sees-job-cuts-and-lower-earnings.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Colgate Sees Job Cuts And Lower Earnings<date>Published: September 21, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company took Wall Street by surprise yesterday when it announced that dismal results in Mexico would lower its operating earnings by more than 30 cents a share this year and that it would cut 8.5 percent of its work force in a sweeping reorganization.The company, whose products include Colgate toothpaste, Ajax cleanser and Fab detergent, said the revamping was not related to its problems in Mexico. The long-planned reorganization of manufacturing and administrative operations will eliminate 3,000 of the company's 36,000 jobs and close or consolidate 24 factories in the United States and Europe. The work force reduction is part of Colgate's third reorganization since 1987.A restructuring charge of $369 million, or $2.54 a share, will result in a third-quarter loss, said Reuben Mark, the company's chairman and chief executive.The effect on earnings caught the attention of Wall Street analysts. "This is a big jump downwards in earnings for any consumer products company, which as a group usually have small variances in earnings forecasts," said Terry Bivens, a consumer products analyst for Donald &amp; Company. "That's why people buy the stocks, and it may take the Street a while to warm up to Colgate again. I remember once Sara Lee missed its earnings by a penny and got punished for it."Shares of Colgate-Palmolive dropped $4.625, to $67.125, in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange."The negative response in the stock price is primarily due to the announcement of the reduction in earnings," said Heather Hay, a household-products analyst with J. P. Morgan Securities. "This is a surprise. Everyone knew Mexico was weak, but the magnitude of this was not expected."When asked why the company's projections were wrong, Mr. Mark said in an interview that "the Mexican Government projected a certain rate of recovery and that is not happening.""The recession has deepened more than was anticipated," he added. As a result, he said, "the reduction in real wages forced contraction in the size of our markets" and led to a decline in inventories among retailers. It also prevented Colgate from raising prices to counter the effects of the devaluation of the peso last year, he said."It is probable that we would not want to raise prices aggressively in the immediate future," he added.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/21/business/company-reports-colgate-palmolive-co-cln.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY REPORTS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO. (CL,N)<date>Published: July 21, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company reported sluggish second-quarter earnings yesterday, citing lower profits in Mexico.The company, which makes Colgate toothpaste, Ajax cleanser and other consumer products, earned $143.2 million, or 95 cents a share, compared with $142.5 million, or 93 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. But the previous year's results included a $5.2 million charge. Before the charge, Colgate earned $147.7 million, or 97 cents a share.While the results were in line with a forecast made by the company last Friday, they were lower than Wall Street expectations of $1 a share, according to a survey of analysts by Zacks Investment Research.Lower profits in Mexico reduced the company's earnings by about 12 cents a share, Colgate said.Sales in Latin America increased 19 percent on unit volume growth of 23 percent, despite a 9 percent unit volume decline in Mexico because of economic problems caused by the devaluation of the peso in December. The region accounts for about 25 percent of Colgate's sales.In North America, sales rose about 12 percent on unit volume increases of 10 percent, the best performance in nine quarters. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/14/business/company-news-mexican-economy-to-hurt-colgate-palmolive-earnings.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; MEXICAN ECONOMY TO HURT COLGATE-PALMOLIVE EARNINGS<date>Published: July 14, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said late yesterday that it expects its second-quarter earnings to be below Wall Street's expectations because of economic conditions in Mexico. The consumer-products company said profits from other operations would not offset the lower profit from Mexico. Colgate-Palmolive, based in New York, said it expects earnings of 95 cents a share for the second quarter. First Call Inc. had reported a consensus earnings prediction of $1.05 a share. For the second quarter of 1994, Colgate-Palmolive reported net income of $142.5 million, or 93 cents a share, on sales of $1.89 billion. Colgate-Palmolive made its projection after the close of trading on the New York Stock Exchange, where its shares closed at $72.125, down 62.5 cents.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/01/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-cbs-and-nbc-take-promotion-partners.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA;CBS and NBC Take Promotion Partners<date>Published: June 01, 1995</date><text>To publicize their prime-time programming for the 1995-96 season, the CBS and NBC television networks are sponsoring large promotional partnerships.CBS has teamed up with Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company for an integrated promotion meant to create awareness of the new CBS fall schedule and attract customers to Sears stores for an annual anniversary sale. The network declined to discuss the budget.The promotion, called "Where It's At," begins in September with print and broadcast advertising; on-line promotions on Prodigy, owned by Sears and I.B.M., and on the World Wide Web of the Internet, and a "CBS Fall Viewing Guide" booklet. A sweepstakes will offer consumers a grand prize to "Be a TV Hotshot" -- the chance to "get an inside look at life as a network executive." CBS previously sponsored promotions with the Kmart Corporation.NBC, a unit of the General Electric Company; Nintendo of America and Blockbuster Video, which is owned by Viacom Inc., have joined for a $5 million promotion touting the NBC fall lineup and Virtual Boy, a new Nintendo 3-D video game that will be available to rent at Blockbuster. The promotion begins on Aug. 14 in 3,000 Blockbuster stores, with a sweepstakes offering prizes like trips to the tapings of NBC shows.NBC and the Colgate-Palmolive Company will also join forces for a $30 million promotional campaign, also beginning in August, that includes a contest called Star With the Stars. The campaign, for NBC shows and Colgate-Palmolive products, will offer such prizes as a 40-second appearance on NBC with actors from the network's fall programs.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/05/business/company-news-colgate-palmolive-to-speed-up-product-development.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE TO SPEED UP PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT<date>Published: May 05, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that it expected to expand by introducing more products faster throughout the world. The company, which makes Colgate toothpaste, Irish Spring soap and other consumer items, introduced 493 products last year, more than twice the number it created in 1990. Colgate-Palmolive, based in New York, has accelerated its worldwide product development through improved research, the company said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/22/business/company-reports-colgate-palmolive-registers-4.6-earnings-gain.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY REPORTS; Colgate-Palmolive Registers 4.6% Earnings Gain<date>Published: April 22, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that earnings rose 4.6 percent in the first quarter, fueled by improving results in the United States and strong results in Latin America.The maker of consumer products said net income rose to $156.5 million, or $1.05 a share, from $149.6 million, or 98 cents a share, in the 1994 first quarter. The most recent results included an earnings dilution of 6 cents a share, which had been expected, from the company's January purchase of the Kolynos South American oral-care business.Colgate's share price closed up 75 cents yesterday at $69.875.Colgate, whose products include Colgate toothpaste, Irish Spring soap and Ajax cleaner, said revenue rose 12 percent, to $1.98 billion from $1.77 billion. Most of the sales increase was recorded by Colgate-International and Colgate-North America. "Our North American operations had very encouraging increases in unit volume, gross margin and operating profit," said Reuben Mark, chairman and chief executive officer. He said the increases came as Colgate bolstered advertising.Sales by Colgate-North America, which accounts for 20 percent of total revenue, rose 6 percent, while unit volume rose 3 percent. The sales improvement was the best in the last eight quarters. The company said all three products it introduced in late 1994 -- Palmolive Dishwashing Liquid and Antibacterial Hand Soap, Irish Spring Waterfall Clean soap and Murphy's Kitchen Care cleaners -- had helped market share.Sales were partly offset in the United States by changes in distribution of the company's Hill's pet food.Colgate said its Latin American sales, gross profit margins and income from operations set records even before the acquisition of the Kolynos oral-care business. Gross margins rose to 49 percent of sales from 48.7 percent a year earlier. Selling, general and administrative expenses climbed to 34.6 percent from 34.5 percent.Sales by Colgate-Latin America, which represent 25 percent of total revenue, increased 5 percent, and unit volume rose 12 percent, excluding Kolynos. Colgate said sales and profits were especially strong in its key Latin markets of Brazil, Venezuela and Colombia. New products helped contribute to sales increases in Latin America. In Mexico, unit volume growth combined with price increases partly offset the impact of the peso's devaluation on Colgate's dollar results.Including the recently acquired Kolynos business, overall sales for Colgate-Latin America increased 22 percent and volume advanced 30 percent.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/02/03/business/company-reports-colgate-palmolive-co-cln.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY REPORTS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO. (CL,N)<date>Published: February 03, 1995</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company reported yesterday an increase of 12.3 percent in fourth-quarter profits, with sales gains in its developing markets and pet food business offsetting declines in North America.Colgate-Palmolive, the consumer products giant based in New York, earned $137.1 million, or 91 cents a share -- 1 cent higher than analysts' expectations -- in the quarter that ended on Dec. 31, compared with $122.1 million, or 78 cents a share, in the corresponding period in 1993. Sales rose 8.5 percent, to $2 billion.Colgate-Palmolive said its Asia-Africa division posted an increase of 16 percent in sales, while sales in Latin America grew by 15 percent. In Europe the company's sales gained 13 percent, but in North America sales dropped 3 percent.In addition, the Hill's Pet Nutrition division recorded an increase of 18 percent in worldwide sales, with strong growth in both the domestic and international markets.Shares of Colgate-Palmolive rose 50 cents, to $62.375, on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/01/10/business/company-news-colgate-in-1.04-billion-acquisition.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; Colgate in $1.04 Billion Acquisition<date>Published: January 10, 1995</date><text>Moving to reduce debt and improve its recently lowered credit rating, the American Home Products Corporation announced yesterday that it had agreed to sell its Kolynos toothpaste, dental floss and mouthwash businesses in South America to the Colgate-Palmolive Company for $1.04 billion.American Home Products, a health care and consumer products company, said the money would go primarily to repay debt. The company borrowed most of the $9.7 billion it paid to acquire American Cyanamid last year, and analysts said American Home might try to cut debt further by selling other businesses.The oral health business, primarily under the Kolynos trademark, is entirely overseas. It had sales of about $290 million in 1994, mainly in Brazil, as well as Argentina, Colombia, Peru and Uruguay. The deal also includes oral health lines in Hungary, Greece and Taiwan.Analysts said the sale made sense for both sides. "It looks like they are getting a good price, more than three times sales and at least 20 times earnings," said David Lippman, a pharmaceutical analyst at Prudential Securities.Brenda Lee Landry, a consumer products analyst at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company, said the deal "sounds terrific" for Colgate Palmolive, which is based in New York. She said Colgate's share of the Latin American oral care market would soar to 79 percent from 54 percent, far ahead of Unilever, with about 11 percent, and Proctor &amp; Gamble, about 4 percent.Worldwide demand for toothpaste is growing by 5.8 percent, she said, and it is a very profitable product for Colgate-Palmolive, which already has 16 percent operating profit margins in Latin America. She estimated Colgate-Palmolive had $7.55 billion in 1994 sales.American Home Products, based in Madison, N.J., said it would keep a "significant presence in South America" as a producer of prescription and over-the-counter drugs and agricultural weed- and pest-killers. Its products include Advil and Anacin analgesics; Premarin, an estrogen replacement drug; Norplant contraceptives, and infant formula. The company will have $12.6 billion in annual sales following the American Cyanamid merger.Standard &amp; Poor's had lowered its credit rating for American Home Products from triple-A to A-minus in September after the purchase of American Cyanamid. David Lugg, a pharmaceutical analyst at S.&amp; P., said yesterday that reducing the debt would be "a positive, but not enough to change the American Home's credit rating."Also yesterday, Moody's Investors Service said it was reviewing Colgate's credit rating for a possible downgrade.Neil B. Sweig, a health care analyst at Ladenburg, Thalmann &amp; Company, said yesterday's agreement was "a wonderful price." To pare its debt further, he said, American Home Products might consider selling its food business, "a good cash cow" that includes Chef Boy-ArDee pasta and Gulden's mustard; some medical device lines, or portions of American Cyanamid's medical products business. A spokesman for American Home said the company had no comment on its plans.On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, American Home Products fell 50 cents, to $63.25 a share, and Colgate-Palmolive fell 25 cents, to $59.75.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/07/business/company-news-no-plan-for-revamping-colgate-palmolive-says.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; NO PLAN FOR REVAMPING, COLGATE-PALMOLIVE SAYS<date>Published: September 07, 1994</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that it had no current plans for a restructuring. The company was responding to a report last week that it would undertake a $100 million reorganization that would eliminate up to 3,000 jobs. The report was issued Thursday evening by Bloomberg Business News, and Colgate's offices in New York were closed Friday through Monday. Reuben Mark, the company's chief executive, said in a statement, "Colgate is always looking for ways to increase productivity, to streamline operations worldwide and increase value to shareholders." Colgate stock closed yesterday at $56.625, down 12.5 cents, on the New York Stock Exchange. Heather Hay, an analyst who follows Colgate for J. P. Morgan Securities, said, "My sense is that they are probably mulling something over but haven't come to a decision."</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/03/business/company-news-colgate-may-eliminate-up-to-3000-positions.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; Colgate May Eliminate Up to 3,000 Positions<date>Published: September 03, 1994</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company will reportedly undertake a $100 million restructuring soon that would eliminate up to 3,000 jobs.Colgate-Palmolive had no response to the report, issued Thursday evening by Bloomberg Business News. Its New York headquarters offices were closed yesterday, until Tuesday.The report was based on the statement of an unnamed "management consultant who was familiar with the situation." Yesterday some equity analysts said that based on their conversations with Colgate-Palmolive executives, they thought a restructuring was possible soon. If it occurs, it would be the third in the last 10 years.According to Bloomberg, the consolidation or closing of some North American plants, as well as of some European businesses, was possible. Stock Down 75 CentsColgate stock closed yesterday at $56.75, down 75 cents on the New York Stock Exchange."I'm surprised that the stock is down," said Heather Hay, an analyst who follows Colgate for J. P. Morgan Securities. A restructuring, she said, "would help the company, since it needs to improve the profitability of its United States businesses."A factor indicating that a restructuring is possible is the track record of the company's chief executive, Reuben Mark, "who is very focused on efficiency and is an advocate of restructuring," Ms. Hay said.Walter Beach, an analyst who follows Colgate for Widmann, Siff &amp; Company of Bryn Mawr, Pa., said that a restructuring would be "a very positive event.""They might change the structure to be more reactive," he said. "The detergent business is the weak spot in their domestic operations." Wall Street SurprisedThe company surprised Wall Street in July by reporting disappointing second-quarter revenues in its North American consumer-product business. Overall earnings increased 4 percent, to $147.7 million, or 97 cents a share, from $142.4 million, or 86 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.Colgate North America reported 9 percent lower volume in its consumer-products units and said that sales of its Colgate products had been flat for the last six months.Wall Street was expecting earnings of 99 cents a share, said Constance M. Maneaty, an analyst at Bear, Stearns &amp; Company. "The bottom line," she said, "is that the international business in developing markets is doing well, business in Europe is rebounding, but in the United States it's under pressure."Deepak D. Raj, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, said a restructuring "would not be surprising, given recent results."</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/18/business/company-news-colgate-buys-oral-hygiene-business-in-india.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY NEWS; COLGATE BUYS ORAL HYGIENE BUSINESS IN INDIA<date>Published: August 18, 1994</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company said yesterday that its Indian unit would acquire the oral hygiene business of Hindustan Ciba-Geigy Ltd. for $41.7 million. Hindustan Ciba-Geigy is 40 percent owned by Ciba-Geigy A.G. of Switzerland. Under the agreement, Colgate-Palmolive (India) Ltd. will take over Hindustan Ciba-Geigy's Cibaca toothpaste and other brands, as well as the company's distribution and manufacturing arrangements. The purchase will increase Colgate's share in India's toothbrush market to more than 70 percent, analysts said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/22/business/company-reports-colgate-palmolive-co-cln.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">COMPANY REPORTS; COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO. (CL,N)<date>Published: July 22, 1994</date><text>The Colgate-Palmolive Company surprised Wall Street yesterday by reporting disappointing second-quarter revenues in its North American core consumer-products businesses yesterday, prompting an early selloff that leveled off by the end of the day.The company announced that earnings increased 4 percent, to $147.7 million, or 97 cents a share, from $142.4 million, or 86 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. It took a one-time charge of $5.2 million, or 4 cents a share, for the sale of Princess House, its crystal tableware unit, resulting in net income of $142.5 million, or 93 cents a share.Wall Street was expecting earnings of 99 cents a share, said Constance M. Maneaty, an analyst at Bear, Stearns &amp; Company. "The bottom line," she said, "is that the international business in developing markets is doing well, business in Europe is rebounding, but in the United States it's under pressure."Colgate North-America reported 9 percent lower volume in its consumer-products units, and said that sales of its Colgate products had been flat for the last six months. The company attributed the results to inventory reductions by American retailers.Shares of Colgate-Palmolive fell as low as $49.50 in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, before rebounding to close at $50.50, down $1.75.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/05/13/nyregion/timely-repairs-for-a-historic-clock.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">Timely Repairs for a Historic Clock<date>Published: May 13, 1994</date><text>This item appeared in the paper as a stand alone photograph. Caption information is provided below.Photo: The Colgate Clock in Jersey City, built in 1924, was shut down in 1989 for refurbishment. The world's largest single-faced clock, it is scheduled to resume ticking on Tuesday when a ferry service from the Colgate Pier to the World Financial Center in Manhattan is to be inaugurated. (Sam D'Amico for The New York Times)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/30/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-mommies-replace-madge-for-palmolive.html?ref=colgatepalmolivecompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; 'Mommies' Replace Madge for Palmolive<date>Published: March 30, 1994</date><text>Three years after sending Madge the manicurist to advertising character heaven, the Colgate-Palmolive Company has doubled the number of spokeswomen to replace her in pitching its Palmolive dishwashing products line.Marilyn Kentz and Caryl Kristensen, co-stars of the low-rated NBC sitcom "The Mommies," began appearing last night in the first of two Palmolive television commercials. The spots, by FCB/Leber Katz Partners of New York, focus on the grease-cutting and hand-softening abilities of Palmolive Plus dishwashing liquid and the stain-removing qualities of new Palmolive Ultra concentrated dishwater detergent. The actress Jan Miner spent 26 years as the Madge character, promoting Palmolive liquid; in one spot, the comedy team invokes Madge's name.</text></article></page></root>
