<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Devon Energy"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/12/business/global/12bp.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">BP to Pay Devon $7 Billion for Fuel Assets<date>Published: March 11, 2010</date><text>LONDON — BP, the British oil giant, agreed on Thursday to pay Devon Energy $7 billion in cash for oil and gas assets in Brazil, the Gulf of Mexico and Azerbaijan, seeking to increase production.The transaction would give BP access to the sought-after area off the coast of Brazil, which analysts expect to have great potential for oil discoveries. Rivals like Exxon Mobil have already accessed the area through partnerships. The deal is “offering us significant additional long-term growth potential with an emphasis on high-margin oil,” the BP chief executive, Tony Hayward, said in a statement. “As well as giving us a broad portfolio of assets in the exciting Brazilian deepwater, it will strengthen our position in the Gulf of Mexico, enhance our interests in Azerbaijan and enable us to progress the development of Canadian assets.” As part of the agreement, Devon, based in Oklahoma City, will buy half of BP’s Kirby oil sands project in Alberta, Canada, for $500 million to create a joint venture. The venture would be operated by Devon, and Devon committed to pay $150 million of BP’s capital costs. Devon decided in November to sell its offshore and international oil and gas assets to focus on its less expensive businesses in the United States and Canada. For BP, the acquisition means it can move closer to fulfilling its pledge to increase production and profitability. Last year, BP produced more oil and gas than Exxon for the first time. Oil giants like BP are looking to increase production by investing in assets that have huge potential but where natural resources are more difficult to get to. Industry experts have long seen Brazil as the new battleground for the big oil companies, but any oil reservoirs lie deep under the sea and would require large investments in technology to explore. The new assets would give BP access to eight license blocks in Brazil’s Campos and Camamu-Almada basins about 330 to 9,100 feet below the water’s surface, and two onshore licenses. Beyond Brazil, the acquisition allows BP to strengthen its position in the deep waters around the Gulf of Mexico, where BP is already the largest producer of oil and gas. It would add 240 leases, including the Zia, Magnolia, Merganser and Nansen producing oil fields, in the region. BP said that it planned to increase its pretax profitability by $3 billion a year over the next three years. Mr. Hayward’s stringent cost-cutting program has improved profitability, and the company exceeded its own cost reduction targets for last year.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/27/realestate/commercial/27devon.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">A Downtown Becomes Full of Life Again<date>Published: January 26, 2010</date><text>Most companies have shelved expansion plans until the economy recovers — but not the Devon Energy Corporation, one of the country’s biggest independent energy companies.Flush with cash from the energy boom, Devon broke ground in October for a 50-story tower in Oklahoma City that is among the tallest buildings under construction nationwide. The company’s new headquarters building will be the state’s tallest when it opens in 2012. Despite the building’s $750 million price, Devon is betting the new tower will save money and make the company more efficient. All of its 1,500 employees in Oklahoma City, who are now scattered in five buildings around downtown, will be in a single location. The building, designed by Pickard Chilton, will have 80,000 square feet of ground floor space with retail and food, open to the public. “It’s a great time to build a building. We can get it done faster and cheaper than during the boom,” said Larry Nichols, Devon’s chief executive. “We’re ahead of schedule and under budget.” Devon’s building, however, is not the only construction project in Oklahoma City. In December, residents approved a $777 million tax package for a 70-acre central park, convention center, streetcar system, aquatic centers, boating facilities and trails that will be built over the next nine years. A $140 million makeover of downtown, including new sidewalks, bicycle lanes and two-way streets, also starts in May courtesy of Devon. “We’re assured of a 10-year economic stimulus plan,” said Roy H. Williams, chief executive of the Greater Oklahoma City Chamber. While Devon’s tower is the only office building under construction, Oklahoma City’s commercial real estate market has been less affected than some markets by the downturn unfolding across the country. Rents and vacancy rates have not shown the wild swings that characterize other markets, although the vacancy rate was up to 20 percent at the end of the year, from 16.5 percent at the end of 2008, according to CB Richard Ellis, a commercial brokerage firm. “We are still strongly dominated by the oil and natural gas industry. As long as it performs, we’re O.K.,” said Jim Austin, a vice president at CB Richard Ellis in Oklahoma City. “When everyone was tanking, we were doing well.” Natural gas prices have skyrocketed over the last few years, bolstered by high energy demand and technological advances that opened up previously tapped fields, and climbed to more than $14 a thousand cubic feet in July 2008. Although the recession has depressed prices, they have started to recover as energy companies close wells and reduce drilling. While Devon is making a contribution, much of the revival of downtown is being financed by taxpayers, who have a history of approving taxes to improve the city. In 1993, city voters approved a temporary one-cent increase in the sales tax to redevelop the riverfront, renovate the fairgrounds and build a ballpark, sports arena, library, trolley system, and a mile-long canal. For the next 15 years, residents have voted to continue paying for renovations on all the city’s public schools and the river. “It’s pay as you go,” said Ronald J. Norick, who was Oklahoma City’s mayor from 1987 to 1998. “People can see where their money goes and what their money bought.” After the collapse of the energy boom in the early 1980s, Oklahoma City struggled for well over a decade. Unemployment was around 10 percent, the only hotel downtown was on the verge of closing and the convention center’s roof leaked. “Our city was dying. You could shoot a cannon at 5 p.m. and you wouldn’t hit anybody,” Mr. Norick said. When Oklahoma City lost bids, in quick succession, for the maintenance hubs for United and American Airlines more than a decade ago, it decided to do something about it. When Mr. Norick visited Indianapolis, he saw a lively downtown full of hotels, restaurants, cafes and people on the streets and realized that companies were going elsewhere because Oklahoma City had “a dead downtown.” Over the next year, Mr. Norick worked with a small group of people to come up with what would eventually become the city’s first taxpayer-financed project, or MAPS for Metropolitan Area Projects. All the projects were placed downtown to attract new hotels, restaurants and other businesses. “Initially, we took a city that was a nice place to live and raise a family, but was not a great place to visit,” said the current Oklahoma City mayor, Mick Cornett. “We’ve now created a city that we want to show off and we’re proud of.” The projects have infused the city with a sense of enthusiasm and attracted more businesses downtown. After a nationwide search, the American Automobile Association picked Oklahoma City for the site of its new customer service center because of its low business costs and vibrant economy, said Paula Downey, president of AAA Northern California, Nevada and Utah. “What was most impressive about Oklahoma City was how well its various city departments worked together and followed through with us,” she said. “They’re a role model for other cities.” Oklahoma City University is moving its law school downtown to be closer to the courthouse, legal agencies and law firms. When its $30 million renovation of a former Ford Motor factory is completed in two to three years, it will have doubled its space. “We just want to be part of the downtown renaissance,” said Tom J. McDaniel, Oklahoma City University’s president.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/12/23/maersk-to-pay-13-billion-for-devon-projects/?ref=devonenergycorporation">Maersk to Pay $1.3 Billion for Devon Projects<date>December 23, 2009, 5:00 am</date><text>Devon Energy will sell interests in three Gulf of Mexico energy development projects to Maersk Oil for $1.3 billion, MarketWatch reported. The agreement covers Devon’s three projects in the Walker Ridge federal lease area off the shore of Louisiana. Devon said the move fit its November announcement to divest Gulf of Mexico and international assets and focus on North American onshore oil and gas production. Maersk will pay $1.3 billion in cash to Devon and also plans to separately invest up to $4 billion in the projects over time, the news service said. Go to Article from MarketWatch » Go to Maersk Press Release »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/08/business/energy-environment/08fracking.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Dark Side of a Natural Gas Boom<date>Published: December 7, 2009</date><text>DIMOCK, Pa.  Victoria Switzer dreamed of a peaceful retirement in these Appalachian hills. Instead, she is coping with a big problem after a nearby natural gas well contaminated her family’s drinking water with high levels of methane. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Fred R. Conrad/The New York Times Environmental concern about hydraulic fracturing is creating political obstacles for gas drilling companies. Related Times Topics: Energy Efficiency Add to Portfolio Devon Energy Corporation EnCana Corporation Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Fred R. Conrad/The New York Times Victoria Switzer at her home in Dimock, Pa., where 13 water wells, including hers, are contaminated. A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Through no design of hers, Ms. Switzer has joined a rising chorus of voices skeptical of the nation’s latest energy push. “It’s been ‘drill, baby, drill’ out here,” Ms. Switzer said bitterly. “There is no stopping this train.” Across vast regions of the country, gas companies are using a technology called hydraulic fracturing to produce natural gas from previously untapped beds of shale. The push has been so successful that the country’s potential gas reserves jumped by 35 percent in two years. The new supplies have driven down natural gas prices for consumers and might help the global environment by allowing more production of electricity from natural gas, which emits fewer global warming emissions than coal. What the drilling push will do to local environments is another matter. The drilling boom is raising concern in many parts of the country, and the reaction is creating political obstacles for the gas industry. Hazards like methane contamination of drinking water wells, long known in regions where gas production was common, are spreading to populous areas that have little history of coping with such risks, but happen to sit atop shale beds. And a more worrisome possibility has come to light. A string of incidents in places like Wyoming and Pennsylvania in recent years has pointed to a possible link between hydraulic fracturing and pollution of groundwater supplies. In the worst case, such pollution could damage crucial supplies of water used for drinking and agriculture. So far, the evidence of groundwater pollution is thin. Environmental groups contend that is because governments have been slow to react to the drilling boom and are not looking hard for contamination. Gas companies acknowledge the validity of some concerns, but they claim that their technology is fundamentally safe. The debate is becoming more urgent as gas companies move closer to more populated areas, especially in the Northeast, where millions of people are likely to find themselves living near drilling operations in coming years. “To be able to scale up our drilling, clearly we have to be in sync with people’s concerns about water,” said Aubrey K. McClendon, chief executive of the Chesapeake Energy Corporation, a leading gas company. “It’s our biggest challenge.” Hydraulic fracturing consists of injecting huge volumes of water at high pressure to break shale rocks and allow natural gas to flow out more easily. The water is mixed with sand, chemicals and gels to lubricate the process and help keep the rocks open. After refining the technique in Western states in recent years, gas companies are moving to tap the nation’s largest shale structure, the Marcellus shale, which stretches from Virginia to New York. “It’s a very reliable, safe, American source of energy,” said John Richels, president of the Devon Energy Corporation. Environmental activists, however, say there is at least scattered evidence that fracturing operations can pose risks to groundwater sources, particularly when mistakes are made in drilling operations. They have also questioned how some companies deal with the wastewater produced by their operations, warning that liquids laced with chemicals and salt from drilling can overload public sewage treatment plants or pollute surface waters. Deborah Goldberg, a lawyer for the nonprofit environmental group Earthjustice who is fighting to toughen Pennsylvania’s discharge rules, said the state “is facing enormous pressure from gas drillers, who are generating contaminated water faster than the state’s treatment plants can handle it.” According to the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, which is going through a public review of its new rules on hydraulic fracturing, gas companies use at least 260 types of chemicals, many of them toxic, like benzene. These chemicals tend to remain in the ground once the fracturing has been completed, raising fears about long-term contamination. The most immediate hazard from the national drilling bonanza, it is clear, involves contamination of residential drinking water wells by natural gas. In Bainbridge, Ohio, an improperly drilled well contaminated groundwater in 2007, including the water source for the township’s police station, according to a complaint filed this year. After building to high pressures, gas migrated through underground faults, and blew up one house. Here in Dimock, about 30 miles north of Scranton, Pa., 13 water wells, including that of Ms. Switzer, were contaminated by natural gas. One of the wells blew up. Under prodding, environmental regulators are stepping up the search for groundwater contamination. In Pavilion, Wyo., for instance, the Environmental Protection Agency has begun an investigation into contamination of several drinking water wells. Luke Chavez, an E.P.A. investigator, said that traces of methane and 2-butoxyethanol phosphate, a foaming agent, had been found in several wells near an area where the EnCana Corporation, a Canadian gas company, had used hydraulic fracturing in recent years. He said the compounds could have come from cleaning products or oil and gas production, but “it tells us something is happening here that shouldn’t be here.” 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on December 8, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.DIMOCK, Pa.  Victoria Switzer dreamed of a peaceful retirement in these Appalachian hills. Instead, she is coping with a big problem after a nearby natural gas well contaminated her family’s drinking water with high levels of methane. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Fred R. Conrad/The New York Times Environmental concern about hydraulic fracturing is creating political obstacles for gas drilling companies. Related Times Topics: Energy Efficiency Add to Portfolio Devon Energy Corporation EnCana Corporation Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Fred R. Conrad/The New York Times Victoria Switzer at her home in Dimock, Pa., where 13 water wells, including hers, are contaminated. A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Through no design of hers, Ms. Switzer has joined a rising chorus of voices skeptical of the nation’s latest energy push. “It’s been ‘drill, baby, drill’ out here,” Ms. Switzer said bitterly. “There is no stopping this train.” Across vast regions of the country, gas companies are using a technology called hydraulic fracturing to produce natural gas from previously untapped beds of shale. The push has been so successful that the country’s potential gas reserves jumped by 35 percent in two years. The new supplies have driven down natural gas prices for consumers and might help the global environment by allowing more production of electricity from natural gas, which emits fewer global warming emissions than coal. What the drilling push will do to local environments is another matter. The drilling boom is raising concern in many parts of the country, and the reaction is creating political obstacles for the gas industry. Hazards like methane contamination of drinking water wells, long known in regions where gas production was common, are spreading to populous areas that have little history of coping with such risks, but happen to sit atop shale beds. And a more worrisome possibility has come to light. A string of incidents in places like Wyoming and Pennsylvania in recent years has pointed to a possible link between hydraulic fracturing and pollution of groundwater supplies. In the worst case, such pollution could damage crucial supplies of water used for drinking and agriculture. So far, the evidence of groundwater pollution is thin. Environmental groups contend that is because governments have been slow to react to the drilling boom and are not looking hard for contamination. Gas companies acknowledge the validity of some concerns, but they claim that their technology is fundamentally safe. The debate is becoming more urgent as gas companies move closer to more populated areas, especially in the Northeast, where millions of people are likely to find themselves living near drilling operations in coming years. “To be able to scale up our drilling, clearly we have to be in sync with people’s concerns about water,” said Aubrey K. McClendon, chief executive of the Chesapeake Energy Corporation, a leading gas company. “It’s our biggest challenge.” Hydraulic fracturing consists of injecting huge volumes of water at high pressure to break shale rocks and allow natural gas to flow out more easily. The water is mixed with sand, chemicals and gels to lubricate the process and help keep the rocks open. After refining the technique in Western states in recent years, gas companies are moving to tap the nation’s largest shale structure, the Marcellus shale, which stretches from Virginia to New York. “It’s a very reliable, safe, American source of energy,” said John Richels, president of the Devon Energy Corporation. Environmental activists, however, say there is at least scattered evidence that fracturing operations can pose risks to groundwater sources, particularly when mistakes are made in drilling operations. They have also questioned how some companies deal with the wastewater produced by their operations, warning that liquids laced with chemicals and salt from drilling can overload public sewage treatment plants or pollute surface waters. Deborah Goldberg, a lawyer for the nonprofit environmental group Earthjustice who is fighting to toughen Pennsylvania’s discharge rules, said the state “is facing enormous pressure from gas drillers, who are generating contaminated water faster than the state’s treatment plants can handle it.” According to the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, which is going through a public review of its new rules on hydraulic fracturing, gas companies use at least 260 types of chemicals, many of them toxic, like benzene. These chemicals tend to remain in the ground once the fracturing has been completed, raising fears about long-term contamination. The most immediate hazard from the national drilling bonanza, it is clear, involves contamination of residential drinking water wells by natural gas. In Bainbridge, Ohio, an improperly drilled well contaminated groundwater in 2007, including the water source for the township’s police station, according to a complaint filed this year. After building to high pressures, gas migrated through underground faults, and blew up one house. Here in Dimock, about 30 miles north of Scranton, Pa., 13 water wells, including that of Ms. Switzer, were contaminated by natural gas. One of the wells blew up. Under prodding, environmental regulators are stepping up the search for groundwater contamination. In Pavilion, Wyo., for instance, the Environmental Protection Agency has begun an investigation into contamination of several drinking water wells. Luke Chavez, an E.P.A. investigator, said that traces of methane and 2-butoxyethanol phosphate, a foaming agent, had been found in several wells near an area where the EnCana Corporation, a Canadian gas company, had used hydraulic fracturing in recent years. He said the compounds could have come from cleaning products or oil and gas production, but “it tells us something is happening here that shouldn’t be here.” 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/27/business/27drilling.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Rigs on the Skyline and Gas Far Below<date>Published: October 27, 2006</date><text>Correction Appended Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Map Mike Fuentes for The New York Times Three years ago, Lawrence B. Dale, president of a small drilling company, began leasing about 90 sites around Fort Worth for natural gas wells. FORT WORTH, Oct. 20  Boston had the Big Dig. Now Fort Worth has the big drill. Under golf courses, schools, parks, libraries, airports and dozens of neighborhoods, some of the nations leading independent energy companies are scouring the city in search of the best locations to recover one of the largest concentrations of natural gas in the United States. Everyone seems to be lining up for a share in the bonanza. The American Cancer Society recently made $5 million just by selling its mineral rights to land that had been donated years ago. The Girl Scouts leased their mineral rights for drilling under a summer camp for an undisclosed amount. It may not be a rerun of The Beverly Hillbillies. And energy executives say it will not tear up the heart of the city, as Bostons trouble-plagued highway construction project did. But it is a replay of sorts of the oil drilling booms that roused and remade Los Angeles and Oklahoma City in the 1920s and 1930s. And with rigs lighted up like Christmas trees on the citys periphery at night, it is the biggest urban drilling boom in the nation today. The surging interest in tapping gas trapped in the so-called Barnett Shale that veins through Fort Worth is only the beginning of a new far-flung search by wildcatters now exploring Alabama, Illinois, Ohio, Pennsylvania and West Texas for a big new source of shale natural gas. The new drilling wave comes not only at a time when domestic gas production has stalled and demand for cleaner gas energy is increasing, but when new drilling technologies and relatively high gas prices make the exploitation of shale economically feasible for the first time. Not everybody in Fort Worth is happy about the prospect of all this drilling. But this time the advances in exploration technologies mean that most residents are not going to hear, smell or even see the drilling under their land. That is because the holes are dug as much as a mile away, and the drills, thousands of feet down, reach out horizontally  not straight down  to the shale gas underneath the city. Only a few people are actually going to get rich, but there will be a lot of money floating around. Its manna from heaven! said Bishop Kenneth B. Spears of the First St. John Baptist Church, whose predominantly black neighborhood in southeast Fort Worth suddenly finds itself in the middle of one very big energy play. Still, some in the neighborhood fear potential accidents, while others are suspicious of the motives of rich energy companies. For all his enthusiasm, Bishop Spears, who recently received a $21,000 signing bonus to allow Dale Resources to drill for natural gas in the underground shale directly beneath his church, acknowledges the mixed feelings. He promises to use any new church riches to start a fund that will help people get out of debt and start businesses in the neighborhood. He also leads a Y.M.C.A. across the street, which got an even fatter check, and Dale money is going to fix up a baseball field down the block as a good will gesture to the neighborhood. In a recent sermon, Bishop Spears compared Dales payments to the gifts given by Joseph to his brethren in the Old Testament. I got a lot of amens and hallelujahs, but there was also a loud hmm,  he recalled in an interview. Its just not every day a white guy comes up and wants to give any black a check. People are concerned that someone is going to come and take what I own.  The big hmm reflects an anxiety in Fort Worth neighborhoods of all races that drilling could bring some kind of explosion or accident that could ruin drinking water. Trucks carrying water to the rigs could disrupt sleep, many fear, and some claim the companies are not paying residents fairly. Fears grew when a gas well explosion in April killed a drilling company employee in Forest Hill, a suburb. Several other suburban neighborhoods are upset over new wells appearing almost in their backyards and that concern has spread to urban communities. One neighborhood association in Morningside Park, another black neighborhood, has rejected all drilling under a three-block area. So far the organized opposition has been small, but some politicians and activists predict protests may pick up as drilling in the center of the city becomes more intense. Money isnt everything, said Paul Moss, 62, an aluminum factory supervisor who lives in Morningside Park. Peace of mind is better than money. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: Nov. 2, 2006 An article in Business Day on Friday about drilling for natural gas in Fort Worth misstated the number of wells on public property for which the city receives royalties and bonuses totaling $10.4 million. It is 18 wells  not 613, which is the total number of wells in development around Fort Worth. More Articles in Business »Correction Appended Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Map Mike Fuentes for The New York Times Three years ago, Lawrence B. Dale, president of a small drilling company, began leasing about 90 sites around Fort Worth for natural gas wells. FORT WORTH, Oct. 20  Boston had the Big Dig. Now Fort Worth has the big drill. Under golf courses, schools, parks, libraries, airports and dozens of neighborhoods, some of the nations leading independent energy companies are scouring the city in search of the best locations to recover one of the largest concentrations of natural gas in the United States. Everyone seems to be lining up for a share in the bonanza. The American Cancer Society recently made $5 million just by selling its mineral rights to land that had been donated years ago. The Girl Scouts leased their mineral rights for drilling under a summer camp for an undisclosed amount. It may not be a rerun of The Beverly Hillbillies. And energy executives say it will not tear up the heart of the city, as Bostons trouble-plagued highway construction project did. But it is a replay of sorts of the oil drilling booms that roused and remade Los Angeles and Oklahoma City in the 1920s and 1930s. And with rigs lighted up like Christmas trees on the citys periphery at night, it is the biggest urban drilling boom in the nation today. The surging interest in tapping gas trapped in the so-called Barnett Shale that veins through Fort Worth is only the beginning of a new far-flung search by wildcatters now exploring Alabama, Illinois, Ohio, Pennsylvania and West Texas for a big new source of shale natural gas. The new drilling wave comes not only at a time when domestic gas production has stalled and demand for cleaner gas energy is increasing, but when new drilling technologies and relatively high gas prices make the exploitation of shale economically feasible for the first time. Not everybody in Fort Worth is happy about the prospect of all this drilling. But this time the advances in exploration technologies mean that most residents are not going to hear, smell or even see the drilling under their land. That is because the holes are dug as much as a mile away, and the drills, thousands of feet down, reach out horizontally  not straight down  to the shale gas underneath the city. Only a few people are actually going to get rich, but there will be a lot of money floating around. Its manna from heaven! said Bishop Kenneth B. Spears of the First St. John Baptist Church, whose predominantly black neighborhood in southeast Fort Worth suddenly finds itself in the middle of one very big energy play. Still, some in the neighborhood fear potential accidents, while others are suspicious of the motives of rich energy companies. For all his enthusiasm, Bishop Spears, who recently received a $21,000 signing bonus to allow Dale Resources to drill for natural gas in the underground shale directly beneath his church, acknowledges the mixed feelings. He promises to use any new church riches to start a fund that will help people get out of debt and start businesses in the neighborhood. He also leads a Y.M.C.A. across the street, which got an even fatter check, and Dale money is going to fix up a baseball field down the block as a good will gesture to the neighborhood. In a recent sermon, Bishop Spears compared Dales payments to the gifts given by Joseph to his brethren in the Old Testament. I got a lot of amens and hallelujahs, but there was also a loud hmm,  he recalled in an interview. Its just not every day a white guy comes up and wants to give any black a check. People are concerned that someone is going to come and take what I own.  The big hmm reflects an anxiety in Fort Worth neighborhoods of all races that drilling could bring some kind of explosion or accident that could ruin drinking water. Trucks carrying water to the rigs could disrupt sleep, many fear, and some claim the companies are not paying residents fairly. Fears grew when a gas well explosion in April killed a drilling company employee in Forest Hill, a suburb. Several other suburban neighborhoods are upset over new wells appearing almost in their backyards and that concern has spread to urban communities. One neighborhood association in Morningside Park, another black neighborhood, has rejected all drilling under a three-block area. So far the organized opposition has been small, but some politicians and activists predict protests may pick up as drilling in the center of the city becomes more intense. Money isnt everything, said Paul Moss, 62, an aluminum factory supervisor who lives in Morningside Park. Peace of mind is better than money. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: Nov. 2, 2006 An article in Business Day on Friday about drilling for natural gas in Fort Worth misstated the number of wells on public property for which the city receives royalties and bonuses totaling $10.4 million. It is 18 wells  not 613, which is the total number of wells in development around Fort Worth.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/09/business/09five.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Musical Chairs in the Executive Suites<date>Published: September 9, 2006</date><text>TUMULT in executive suites shook up some storied corners of corporate America, including Ford, Boeing and Viacom, as underperforming chief executives were effectively fired  or, in one case, fired himself  and several boardroom bridesmaids were finally given their shot at the top. Skip to next paragraph MOST POPULAR Following are the most-popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Sept. 2 through Sept. 8: 1. The Last Stand of the 6-Percenters? 2. Online Game, Made in U.S., Seizes the Globe 3. For New Lawyers, the Going Rate Has Gone Up 4. Ford Brings in Outsider to Help Run the Company 5. In a Sea of Cellphones, a Pearl Whether the changes prove to be good news for investors remains to be seen, but some unequivocally good news came from the Gulf of Mexico, where deepwater drilling has turned up evidence of potentially huge new oil deposits. SHIFTING GEARS William Clay Ford Jr., a great-grandson of the founder of the Ford Motor Company, replaced himself as chief executive with an aerospace executive in an effort to turn around the company, which has lost roughly $1.5 billion so far this year and is in danger of being overtaken by Toyota as the nations second-biggest carmaker. Though the new C.E.O., Alan R. Mulally, has never worked in the auto industry, he did gain some useful experience while he ran Boeings commercial-aircraft division. Aerospace and auto companies both deal with powerful labor unions, require billion-dollar bets on products that take years to get to market, and require close relationships with many suppliers. While overhauling Boeings commercial airplane division, Mr. Mulally studied how Ford pulled off an earlier revival, in particular how it developed the Taurus, which outsold rival models from Toyota and Honda to become the best-selling car in America. Mr. Mulally is also a student of Toyotas production system, which stresses minimizing waste, improving continuously and involving workers in fixing problems. Mr. Ford, 49, will remain chairman, and plans to help Mr. Mulally run the company. Boeing said Scott Carson, who had been in charge of the airplane divisions sales, would succeed Mr. Mulally as its chief executive of commercial aviation. This month, Ford is expected to announce more job cuts, plant closings and other steps under a restructuring plan it unveiled in January. The plan initially called for Ford to eliminate 30,000 jobs and close 14 factories through 2012. HOLLYWOOD ENDING Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman of Viacom, forced out the companys chief executive, Thomas E. Freston, reasserting his control over the media giant just eight months after he split it into two parts: CBS and Viacom. Mr. Redstone said that Philippe P. Dauman would succeed Mr. Freston, and that Thomas E. Dooley, will be the senior executive vice president and chief administrative officer. Mr. Dauman and Mr. Dooley worked with Mr. Redstone for many years at Viacom and left only after Viacom acquired CBS in 2000. When Mr. Redstone spun off CBS five years later, he said that he expected Viacom to be the faster-growing company, but its share price has lagged behind that of CBS. He criticized Mr. Freston for being indecisive, and recently overstepped his C.E.O. to order Paramount Pictures, which is part of Viacom, to sever ties with the actor Tom Cruise. Investors will wait to see if the new managers try to revive Viacoms share price by making big acquisitions quickly, a strategy that could backfire, analysts said. INVENT, OR INVESTIGATE? Californias attorney general said he would review the methods Hewlett-Packards board used to track down how some of its internal discussions became public knowledge. Attorney General Bill Lockyers investigation followed Hewlett-Packards disclosure that its chairwoman, Patricia C. Dunn, authorized an investigation that led to private detectives monitoring the calls that other board members made from home and on their cellphones. The company, which uses the one-word slogan Invent, denied it had recorded calls or eavesdropped on conversations, but did say that its agents had misrepresented themselves to obtain records showing whom board members had spoken to. When the report was presented to the full board in May, the directors asked one member, George A. Keyworth II, to resign; he refused. But another director, Thomas J. Perkins, did resign, to protest the investigation. Hewlett-Packards next board election is scheduled for March. The company said Mr. Keyworth would not be renominated for his seat. GUSHER IN THE GULF Chevron, Devon Energy and Statoil, the Norwegian oil giant, said they had found as much as 15 billion barrels of oil in several ultra-deepwater wells in the Gulf of Mexico about 270 miles southwest of New Orleans. While more wells will have to be drilled  some as deep as 30,000 feet below the surface of the sea  to know for sure how big the fields are, the oil companies said they had the potential of being even larger than those at Prudhoe Bay, off the northern coast of Alaska. The United States has reserves of 29 billion barrels, meaning that at the high end of the estimates, the discovery could increase reserves by 50 percent. Since the country uses 20.5 million barrels of crude oil every day, the new areas would be able to meet the nations needs for about two years. The three companies said they would drill another test well next year to confirm the extent of their find, and would probably decide on developing the field late in 2007 or in 2008. STAGFLATION AFOOT? Labor Department statistics on productivity and hourly pay showed that wage pressures from January through June increased faster than first forecast, even as growth was slowing in many parts of the country. The department found unit labor costs  which take into account changes in productivity and hourly wages  increased sharply in the first half, suggesting that the threat of higher inflation had not diminished and that it might take more interest rate increases to hold prices down. The Federal Reserve, which sets short-term rates, faces the prospect of both slower growth and higher prices, creating a quandary over whether to risk even further economic weakness to contain inflation. BANKRUPTCY BRAKE Setting the stage for the first test of a new law aimed at curbing retention bonuses for officers of bankrupt companies, the Justice Department joined with unions and creditors of the Dana Corporation in opposing a proposed pay system for top executives of the company. New contracts for Danas chief executive, Michael J. Burns, and other executives propose to give them big bonuses when the company, a major auto parts maker, emerges from bankruptcy, and could pay additional bonuses based on the value of the companys securities six months after the bankruptcy ends. At issue is whether that amounts to a retention provision because the targets are sure to be met, as opponents say, or whether they are performance bonuses because the targets are difficult to meet. The bankruptcy trustee assigned to the case, Diana G. Adams, said she might ask an independent examiner to review the pay plan. More Articles in Business »TUMULT in executive suites shook up some storied corners of corporate America, including Ford, Boeing and Viacom, as underperforming chief executives were effectively fired  or, in one case, fired himself  and several boardroom bridesmaids were finally given their shot at the top. Skip to next paragraph MOST POPULAR Following are the most-popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Sept. 2 through Sept. 8: 1. The Last Stand of the 6-Percenters? 2. Online Game, Made in U.S., Seizes the Globe 3. For New Lawyers, the Going Rate Has Gone Up 4. Ford Brings in Outsider to Help Run the Company 5. In a Sea of Cellphones, a Pearl Whether the changes prove to be good news for investors remains to be seen, but some unequivocally good news came from the Gulf of Mexico, where deepwater drilling has turned up evidence of potentially huge new oil deposits. SHIFTING GEARS William Clay Ford Jr., a great-grandson of the founder of the Ford Motor Company, replaced himself as chief executive with an aerospace executive in an effort to turn around the company, which has lost roughly $1.5 billion so far this year and is in danger of being overtaken by Toyota as the nations second-biggest carmaker. Though the new C.E.O., Alan R. Mulally, has never worked in the auto industry, he did gain some useful experience while he ran Boeings commercial-aircraft division. Aerospace and auto companies both deal with powerful labor unions, require billion-dollar bets on products that take years to get to market, and require close relationships with many suppliers. While overhauling Boeings commercial airplane division, Mr. Mulally studied how Ford pulled off an earlier revival, in particular how it developed the Taurus, which outsold rival models from Toyota and Honda to become the best-selling car in America. Mr. Mulally is also a student of Toyotas production system, which stresses minimizing waste, improving continuously and involving workers in fixing problems. Mr. Ford, 49, will remain chairman, and plans to help Mr. Mulally run the company. Boeing said Scott Carson, who had been in charge of the airplane divisions sales, would succeed Mr. Mulally as its chief executive of commercial aviation. This month, Ford is expected to announce more job cuts, plant closings and other steps under a restructuring plan it unveiled in January. The plan initially called for Ford to eliminate 30,000 jobs and close 14 factories through 2012. HOLLYWOOD ENDING Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman of Viacom, forced out the companys chief executive, Thomas E. Freston, reasserting his control over the media giant just eight months after he split it into two parts: CBS and Viacom. Mr. Redstone said that Philippe P. Dauman would succeed Mr. Freston, and that Thomas E. Dooley, will be the senior executive vice president and chief administrative officer. Mr. Dauman and Mr. Dooley worked with Mr. Redstone for many years at Viacom and left only after Viacom acquired CBS in 2000. When Mr. Redstone spun off CBS five years later, he said that he expected Viacom to be the faster-growing company, but its share price has lagged behind that of CBS. He criticized Mr. Freston for being indecisive, and recently overstepped his C.E.O. to order Paramount Pictures, which is part of Viacom, to sever ties with the actor Tom Cruise. Investors will wait to see if the new managers try to revive Viacoms share price by making big acquisitions quickly, a strategy that could backfire, analysts said. INVENT, OR INVESTIGATE? Californias attorney general said he would review the methods Hewlett-Packards board used to track down how some of its internal discussions became public knowledge. Attorney General Bill Lockyers investigation followed Hewlett-Packards disclosure that its chairwoman, Patricia C. Dunn, authorized an investigation that led to private detectives monitoring the calls that other board members made from home and on their cellphones. The company, which uses the one-word slogan Invent, denied it had recorded calls or eavesdropped on conversations, but did say that its agents had misrepresented themselves to obtain records showing whom board members had spoken to. When the report was presented to the full board in May, the directors asked one member, George A. Keyworth II, to resign; he refused. But another director, Thomas J. Perkins, did resign, to protest the investigation. Hewlett-Packards next board election is scheduled for March. The company said Mr. Keyworth would not be renominated for his seat. GUSHER IN THE GULF Chevron, Devon Energy and Statoil, the Norwegian oil giant, said they had found as much as 15 billion barrels of oil in several ultra-deepwater wells in the Gulf of Mexico about 270 miles southwest of New Orleans. While more wells will have to be drilled  some as deep as 30,000 feet below the surface of the sea  to know for sure how big the fields are, the oil companies said they had the potential of being even larger than those at Prudhoe Bay, off the northern coast of Alaska. The United States has reserves of 29 billion barrels, meaning that at the high end of the estimates, the discovery could increase reserves by 50 percent. Since the country uses 20.5 million barrels of crude oil every day, the new areas would be able to meet the nations needs for about two years. The three companies said they would drill another test well next year to confirm the extent of their find, and would probably decide on developing the field late in 2007 or in 2008. STAGFLATION AFOOT? Labor Department statistics on productivity and hourly pay showed that wage pressures from January through June increased faster than first forecast, even as growth was slowing in many parts of the country. The department found unit labor costs  which take into account changes in productivity and hourly wages  increased sharply in the first half, suggesting that the threat of higher inflation had not diminished and that it might take more interest rate increases to hold prices down. The Federal Reserve, which sets short-term rates, faces the prospect of both slower growth and higher prices, creating a quandary over whether to risk even further economic weakness to contain inflation. BANKRUPTCY BRAKE Setting the stage for the first test of a new law aimed at curbing retention bonuses for officers of bankrupt companies, the Justice Department joined with unions and creditors of the Dana Corporation in opposing a proposed pay system for top executives of the company. New contracts for Danas chief executive, Michael J. Burns, and other executives propose to give them big bonuses when the company, a major auto parts maker, emerges from bankruptcy, and could pay additional bonuses based on the value of the companys securities six months after the bankruptcy ends. At issue is whether that amounts to a retention provision because the targets are sure to be met, as opponents say, or whether they are performance bonuses because the targets are difficult to meet. The bankruptcy trustee assigned to the case, Diana G. Adams, said she might ask an independent examiner to review the pay plan.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/06/business/worldbusiness/06oil.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Big Oil Find Is Reported Deep in Gulf<date>Published: September 6, 2006</date><text>An announcement yesterday by three oil companies of a successful production test in the Gulf of Mexico  potentially the largest American oil find in a generation  was seen by experts as ushering in a new era in ultra-deepwater offshore drilling. Chevron, Devon Energy and Statoil ASA, the Norwegian oil giant, reported that they had found 3 billion to 15 billion barrels in several fields 175 miles offshore, 30,000 feet below the gulfs surface, among formations of rock and salt hundreds of feet thick. While it is too early to know exactly how big the fields are, the oil companies expressed hope that they had the potential of being even larger than those at Prudhoe Bay, off the northern coast of Alaska. The United States has reserves of 29 billion barrels, meaning that at the high end of the estimates, the discovery could increase reserves by 50 percent. It comes as the output of oil and gas in shallower wells in the Gulf of Mexico, with about one-quarter of American oil reserves, is ebbing and environmental resistance to offshore drilling in areas closer to coastlines remains strong. This is frontier stuff, said Daniel Yergin, president of Cambridge Energy Research Associates, noting that the discovery is at levels deeper than deep-sea fields in the North Sea and off North Africa. Success at these depths in the Gulf of Mexico would facilitate ultra-deepwater exploration elsewhere in the world because it will have proven the technology and capabilities. It will take more than a year of drilling to confirm the value of the find, and the depth of the water will make extraction extremely expensive  profitable only if oil prices remain at least $40 a barrel, according to oil industry analysts. The analysts cautioned that there was little likelihood the report would give drivers much relief at the pump because full production might not come on line for five years or more. By itself, it also appears that the discovery could make little more than a dent in the countrys energy dependence. And given that the United States uses 20.5 million barrels of crude oil a day, the new areas at most hold supplies that would quench the nations oil thirst for two years. In addition, there is a shortage of rigs able to drill in deep water, another constraint in exploiting the find quickly. But Chevron and the other companies involved expressed excitement. The discovery in American waters, said J. Larry Nichols, chairman of Devon Energy, could not have happened in a better place. According to Chevron, the successful test was the culmination of about two years of drilling by the three companies, using seismic and drilling equipment at record depths and pressure. Our strong strategic position in the deepwater Gulf of Mexico, said George L. Kirkland, a Chevron executive vice president, will continue to be a platform for future growth for years to come. Shell, BP, Exxon Mobil, Anadarko Petroleum and Petróleo Brasileiro have leases on comparable waters in the gulf, and the successful test is likely to set off a wave of drilling in deep water as well as the building of platforms and the laying of pipelines. Its going to attract deep-pocket and patient investment to work these fields, said Wayne Andrews, oil analyst at Raymond James &amp; Associates. These are very expensive wells to drill, and the production facilities required to produce the reserves are also going to be very expensive operations. Chevron reported that the test on the Jack No. 2 well, situated 270 miles southwest of New Orleans, broke a record for the deepest successful well test in company history. It has sustained a daily flow of more than 6,000 barrels, a quantity thought to mean considerable reserves. The successful test was first reported yesterday by The Wall Street Journal. The stock prices of the three companies rose yesterday. Chevron, which owns 50 percent of the field, gained $1.51, or 2.33 percent, closing at $66.34. Devon Energy, which owns 25 percent of the field, was up sharply, rising $7.99, or 12.5 percent, to $72.14. American depository receipts of Statoil, which owns the other 25 percent, rose 66 cents, or 2.4 percent, to close at $28.17. The three oil partners said they would drill another appraisal well next year to confirm the extent of their find, and would probably decide on developing the field late in 2007 or in 2008. The deep waters of the Gulf of Mexico may represent the last area in the United States where large oil and gas reserves remain to be discovered, although some experts see the potential for big discoveries deep off the Atlantic and Pacific coasts, which would require Congressional action to exploit. This is a breakthrough that confirms very large reserves of recoverable oil in the gulf, Mr. Yergin of Cambridge Energy Research Associates said. This announcement also reflects how the oil industry is marching offshore into deeper and deeper waters around the world. Successful exploitation of the reserves requires new drill technology and computerized seismic technology to work in water more than a mile deep. This would have been unthinkable 10 years ago, Mr. Yergin said, but the technology keeps advancing. The oil in the area is considered top quality, light and sweet, unlike the oil in many new fields around the world that is heavier and more difficult to process. Because the new reserves are so far off the gulf coast, they seem unlikely to attract the intense opposition from environmentalists who oppose drilling close to beaches. More Articles in Business »An announcement yesterday by three oil companies of a successful production test in the Gulf of Mexico  potentially the largest American oil find in a generation  was seen by experts as ushering in a new era in ultra-deepwater offshore drilling. Chevron, Devon Energy and Statoil ASA, the Norwegian oil giant, reported that they had found 3 billion to 15 billion barrels in several fields 175 miles offshore, 30,000 feet below the gulfs surface, among formations of rock and salt hundreds of feet thick. While it is too early to know exactly how big the fields are, the oil companies expressed hope that they had the potential of being even larger than those at Prudhoe Bay, off the northern coast of Alaska. The United States has reserves of 29 billion barrels, meaning that at the high end of the estimates, the discovery could increase reserves by 50 percent. It comes as the output of oil and gas in shallower wells in the Gulf of Mexico, with about one-quarter of American oil reserves, is ebbing and environmental resistance to offshore drilling in areas closer to coastlines remains strong. This is frontier stuff, said Daniel Yergin, president of Cambridge Energy Research Associates, noting that the discovery is at levels deeper than deep-sea fields in the North Sea and off North Africa. Success at these depths in the Gulf of Mexico would facilitate ultra-deepwater exploration elsewhere in the world because it will have proven the technology and capabilities. It will take more than a year of drilling to confirm the value of the find, and the depth of the water will make extraction extremely expensive  profitable only if oil prices remain at least $40 a barrel, according to oil industry analysts. The analysts cautioned that there was little likelihood the report would give drivers much relief at the pump because full production might not come on line for five years or more. By itself, it also appears that the discovery could make little more than a dent in the countrys energy dependence. And given that the United States uses 20.5 million barrels of crude oil a day, the new areas at most hold supplies that would quench the nations oil thirst for two years. In addition, there is a shortage of rigs able to drill in deep water, another constraint in exploiting the find quickly. But Chevron and the other companies involved expressed excitement. The discovery in American waters, said J. Larry Nichols, chairman of Devon Energy, could not have happened in a better place. According to Chevron, the successful test was the culmination of about two years of drilling by the three companies, using seismic and drilling equipment at record depths and pressure. Our strong strategic position in the deepwater Gulf of Mexico, said George L. Kirkland, a Chevron executive vice president, will continue to be a platform for future growth for years to come. Shell, BP, Exxon Mobil, Anadarko Petroleum and Petróleo Brasileiro have leases on comparable waters in the gulf, and the successful test is likely to set off a wave of drilling in deep water as well as the building of platforms and the laying of pipelines. Its going to attract deep-pocket and patient investment to work these fields, said Wayne Andrews, oil analyst at Raymond James &amp; Associates. These are very expensive wells to drill, and the production facilities required to produce the reserves are also going to be very expensive operations. Chevron reported that the test on the Jack No. 2 well, situated 270 miles southwest of New Orleans, broke a record for the deepest successful well test in company history. It has sustained a daily flow of more than 6,000 barrels, a quantity thought to mean considerable reserves. The successful test was first reported yesterday by The Wall Street Journal. The stock prices of the three companies rose yesterday. Chevron, which owns 50 percent of the field, gained $1.51, or 2.33 percent, closing at $66.34. Devon Energy, which owns 25 percent of the field, was up sharply, rising $7.99, or 12.5 percent, to $72.14. American depository receipts of Statoil, which owns the other 25 percent, rose 66 cents, or 2.4 percent, to close at $28.17. The three oil partners said they would drill another appraisal well next year to confirm the extent of their find, and would probably decide on developing the field late in 2007 or in 2008. The deep waters of the Gulf of Mexico may represent the last area in the United States where large oil and gas reserves remain to be discovered, although some experts see the potential for big discoveries deep off the Atlantic and Pacific coasts, which would require Congressional action to exploit. This is a breakthrough that confirms very large reserves of recoverable oil in the gulf, Mr. Yergin of Cambridge Energy Research Associates said. This announcement also reflects how the oil industry is marching offshore into deeper and deeper waters around the world. Successful exploitation of the reserves requires new drill technology and computerized seismic technology to work in water more than a mile deep. This would have been unthinkable 10 years ago, Mr. Yergin said, but the technology keeps advancing. The oil in the area is considered top quality, light and sweet, unlike the oil in many new fields around the world that is heavier and more difficult to process. Because the new reserves are so far off the gulf coast, they seem unlikely to attract the intense opposition from environmentalists who oppose drilling close to beaches.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DA1738F93BA1575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON ENERGY TO SELL ASSETS AND BUY BACK STOCK<date>Published: September 28, 2004</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation, an oil and natural gas producer, said yesterday that it planned to sell older North American oil and gas properties to raise as much as $1.5 billion and buy back up to 10 percent of its stock. The company also said that it had set a two-for-one stock split and planned to list its shares on the New York Stock Exchange by Oct. 12. The company, based in Oklahoma City, said it expected to raise $1 billion to $1.5 billion from the sales. (Reuters)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/27/business/funds-want-oil-companies-to-report-on-climate.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Funds Want Oil Companies To Report On Climate<date>Published: February 27, 2004</date><text>Pension fund managers representing public employees in Connecticut, New York, Maine and New York City said yesterday that they had filed shareholder resolutions calling on 10 North American oil companies to report to investors on their plans to deal with the potential impact of global warming and related climate change on their businesses.The resolutions added the heft of some of the nation's largest investors to the ranks of shareholder activists who have been using resolutions to confront the petroleum industry on climate change issues. The resolutions also took aim at a broader range of companies, including midsize oil companies like Anadarko Petroleum, Devon Energy and Valero Energy that previously had flown below the radar of the activists.''This is the first climate change-related resolution we have filed,'' said Alan G. Hevesi, the New York State comptroller, who as the sole fiduciary of the New York Common Retirement Fund, manages the second-largest public pension fund in the nation after the California fund. ''I believe it's going to become a major issue for institutional investors.''Andrew Logan, the oil industry analyst at the Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies, said the inclusion of smaller companies, which focus on exploration and production of oil and gas, reflected the sense that they could be more vulnerable than the more diversified giants like Exxon Mobil and ChevronTexaco to regulatory changes and taxes on greenhouse gas emissions.The coalition is an umbrella group of environmental organizations and businesses that has been coordinating the shareholder efforts along with the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, a coalition of 275 religious institutional investors.Many oil companies have asked the Securities and Exchange Commission to rule that there is no need to present the resolutions to shareholders at their annual meetings. ''We feel we have already been responsive to these queries in a number of forums, most recently in our energy trends report posted on our Web site early this month,'' a spokeswoman for Exxon Mobil, Lauren Kerr, said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/16/business/company-news-devon-energy-to-sell-project-to-quest-resource.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON ENERGY TO SELL PROJECT TO QUEST RESOURCE<date>Published: December 16, 2003</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to sell its coal-bed methane project in Southeast Kansas and Northeast Oklahoma to the Quest Resource Corporation for $126 million to focus on exploration in other areas like the Gulf of Mexico. The purchase price is about equal to Devon's investment in the Cherokee Basin properties, the company said. Quest will buy about 330 producing wells, an estimated 200 miles of pipelines and interests in about 375,000 leasehold acres in a transaction that is expected to close on Dec. 22. Both companies are based in Oklahoma City.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/04/business/company-news-anadarko-announces-change-in-chief-executive.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Anadarko Announces Change in Chief Executive<date>Published: December 04, 2003</date><text>The Anadarko Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that Robert J. Allison Jr. is stepping down as chief executive and president and will be succeeded in those jobs by James T. Hackett, who has been president and chief operating officer at the Devon Energy Corporation. Anadarko said that Mr. Allison, 64, had retired after 30 years with the company and 17 years as chief executive but would stay on as nonexecutive chairman. Mr. Hackett, 49, previously served as chief executive of Ocean Energy after its merger with the Seagull Energy Corporation in 1999. During Mr. Allison's tenure, the company has grown from 300 employees to 3,400 working in about a dozen countries.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/25/business/company-news-devon-to-buy-ocean-energy-for-3.5-billion.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON TO BUY OCEAN ENERGY FOR $3.5 BILLION<date>Published: February 25, 2003</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation, an oil and gas producer, has agreed to buy the Ocean Energy Corporation for $3.5 billion in stock, creating the largest independent exploration and production company based in the United States. Devon, which is based in Oklahoma City, will also assume $1.8 billion of Ocean's debt and other obligations. The transaction will enable Devon to increase its natural gas reserves without the risk of exploration at a time of price volatility, higher operating costs and industry complaints about lack of access to land. The combined company expects to save $50 million to $100 million annually by reducing costs, including the elimination of Ocean's headquarters in Houston and an undetermined number of layoffs.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/10/business/company-news-devon-energy-sells-properties-worth-953-million.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON ENERGY SELLS PROPERTIES WORTH $953 MILLION<date>Published: April 10, 2002</date><text>The oil and gas producer Devon Energy Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to sell noncore North American oil and gas properties worth $953 million in an effort to pay down debt incurred by recent acquisitions. The properties sold had estimated reserves of crude oil and oil equivalent of about 126.7 million barrels as of Dec. 31 and included previously disclosed sales of 43 million barrels of proven reserves in Canada worth $366 million. A company spokesman would not disclose who bought the properties. Devon paid $6.5 billion last year for Mitchell Energy and a Canadian company, Anderson Exploration.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/04/business/2-big-mergers-are-reached-as-oil-industry-consolidates.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">2 Big Mergers Are Reached As Oil Industry Consolidates<date>Published: September 4, 2001</date><text>Two mergers were agreed upon yesterday in the oil and gas industry, as rivals relentlessly consolidate in an effort to cash in on emerging exploration and production opportunities throughout the world. In one deal, the offshore drilling companies Global Marine and Santa Fe International said they had agreed to merge in a $3 billion stock swap that would make the combined company, to be called GlobalSanteFe, the second-largest offshore drilling contractor in the world. Santa Fe will also assume about $900 million in debt. The new company would have a market value around $6 billion. Separately, Devon Energy, among the largest independent oil and natural gas companies in the United States, agreed to buy a Canadian company, Anderson Exploration, for about $3.4 billion in cash and the assumption of $1.2 billion in debt. The deal comes less than three weeks after Devon, of Oklahoma City, had agreed to buy the Mitchell Energy and Development Corporation for $3.1 billion in cash and stock. A formal announcement of Devon's acquisition of Anderson is expected today. The transaction could make Devon the largest independent oil and gas exploration and production company in the country, analysts said, outstripping Anadarko Petroleum. The latest deals underscore the growing pressure on companies throughout the various segments of the oil and gas industries to join forces or risk losing business to larger competitors. C. Steadman Garber Jr., Santa Fe's president and chief executive, said: ''If you look at what our major customers are doing -- there's Exxon Mobil and BP that's dropped the 'Amoco,' and Chevron acquiring Texaco, and TotalFinaElf -- they are consolidating. And they are looking for contractors on an extended basis, in any market, and we now cover them all.'' There are two ways for oil and gas companies to grow, analysts say, either by drilling new wells and finding greater reserves, or by buying a company that already has them. Drilling is riskier because a million-dollar well may turn up empty. Because buying another company is usually safer, Wall Street so far has applauded consolidation efforts. ''Wall Street likes predictability more than it likes the chance of dry holes,'' said John P. Herrlin Jr., global coordinator of research into exploration and production companies at Merrill Lynch. Global Marine, of Houston, and Sante Fe, which is based in Dallas, have been discussing the possibility of a merger for about two years now, said Robert E. Rose, Global Marine's chairman and chief executive. They wanted to configure a deal so it would be a merger of equals, but the share prices of the two companies have been too far apart until recently to proceed in such a way, Mr. Garber said. Under the terms of the transaction, Global Marine stockholders would receive 0.665 share of the newly issued GlobalSanteFe stock for each share of Global Marine, which would ultimately give them a 50.6 percent stake in the new company. Santa Fe shareholders will have a 49.4 percent stake. Santa Fe would end up paying an 18 percent premium for the Global Marine shares, although it is the smaller company. Even in a merger of equals, one company, for accounting purposes, must be the buyer. Mr. Rose will serve as chairman of the merged company, and Mr. Garber, as its president and chief executive. The new concern will have its headquarters in Houston and trade on the New York Stock Exchange under the symbol GSF. Although Santa Fe has some land-based drilling operations, the bread-and-butter for both companies is offshore drilling, and more recently, the expensive and technologically complex realm of deepwater exploration. The merger is expected to yield few cost savings, said Arvind Sanger, oil field services analyst at Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown. The new company will still lag behind the market leader, Transocean Sedco Forex, but its new strength will flow from its size. Each company has 23 mobile offshore rigs used in shallower waters, and between them, they will have six semi-submersible rigs and four advanced drilling ships that can be used at depths exceeding 4,000 feet, Mr. Sanger said. Increasingly, the biggest oil and gas reservoirs being found are in the deep waters off West Africa, Brazil and in the Gulf of Mexico. ''This gives them a lot more flexibility in markets when at some point the Gulf of Mexico is hot,'' Mr. Sanger said, ''or the North Sea is hot, or West Africa is hot, and they can move the assets to serve those markets.'' Devon's acquisition of Anderson Exploration surprised analysts because of its suddenness in the wake of the Mitchell deal. Mr. Herrlin of Merrill Lynch said that while Devon has a good track record of smart acquisitions, two deals at once will be complicated and somewhat risky. By purchasing Anderson Exploration, which has a market value of $2.24 billion, Devon has staked out a long-term position in the natural gas fields of the Canadian Arctic, said John Bailey, exploration and production analyst at Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown. Anderson has accumulated acreage in the rich fields of the Mackenzie River Delta of the Northwest Territories. Under the terms of the transaction, Devon will be paying a 51 percent premium for shares of Anderson based on the latter's closing price of $17.07 Friday on the New York Stock Exchange. Devon's purchase of Anderson continues a series of acquisitions by American companies of Canadian natural gas producers over the last year. In that period, Conoco has bought Gulf Canada Resources; Anadarko has acquired Berkley Petroleum, and the Williams Companies purchased Encal Energy. With demand for natural gas growing in the United States, and Canada providing much of the fuel, the Americans are absorbing small and medium-size Canadian concerns with sizable gas holdings. ''The bottom line is that this is a great frontier for natural gas drilling,'' Mr. Bailey said. ''There's a lot of natural gas drilling in areas that haven't gotten a lot of attention so far from the industry.'' Credit Suisse First Boston served as financial adviser and Shearman &amp; Sterling provided legal counsel to Santa Fe. Morgan Stanley was financial adviser and Baker Botts provided legal counsel to Global Marine.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/15/business/company-news-devon-energy-offers-3-billion-for-mitchell.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON ENERGY OFFERS $3 BILLION FOR MITCHELL<date>Published: August 15, 2001</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation is buying Mitchell Energy and Development in a cash-and-stock deal worth $3.1 billion that would make Devon the second-largest independent natural gas producer in the United States. Under the agreement, Devon of Oklahoma City, would also assume about $400 million in debt and other obligations of Mitchell, which is based in Woodlands, Tex. George P. Mitchell, Mitchell's chairman, and his wife own about 46 percent of the outstanding common stock and have agreed to vote in favor of the acquisition. Under the deal, Mitchell shareholders would receive $31 cash and 0.585 of a share of Devon common stock for each share, valuing Mitchell at $59.40 a share.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/02/business/company-news-kinder-morgan-buys-into-a-texas-gas-pipeline-and-unit.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; KINDER MORGAN BUYS INTO A TEXAS GAS PIPELINE AND UNIT<date>Published: June 02, 2000</date><text>Kinder Morgan Energy Partners L.P., the No. 1 United States seller of carbon dioxide, agreed yesterday to pay $55 million for the Devon Energy Corporation's stakes in a Texas pipeline that ships gas and a project that injects it into oil reservoirs. Oil companies use carbon dioxide to improve production from aging fields. Kinder Morgan will acquire 81 percent of the 150-mile Canyon Reef Carriers Pipeline and 71 percent of the Sacroc unit, both in the Permian Basin of West Texas. Kinder Morgan, based in Houston, also will get minority stakes in two Permian Basin carbon-dioxide projects operated by the Exxon Mobil Corporation and the Spirit Energy 76 unit of the Unocal Corporation.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/14/business/9-oil-concerns-to-pay-223-million-claim.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">9 Oil Concerns to Pay $223 Million Claim<date>Published: December 14, 1999</date><text>The Chevron Corporation, BP Amoco P.L.C., Conoco Inc., Texaco Inc. and five other oil companies have agreed to pay $223 million to settle United States claims they undervalued oil pumped from American Indian and government land, according to lawyers and company officials.Attorneys for the companies advised a federal judge of settlements in whistle-blower lawsuits contending that a total of 18 companies underpaid hundreds of millions of dollars in royalties on oil pumped from 27 million acres of government and tribal land. The lawsuits were brought under the False Claims Act, a Civil War-era statute that allows whistle-blowers to bring claims on behalf of the United States government.At a hearing on Friday, lawyers told United States District Judge John H. Hannah Jr. that Chevron would pay $95 million, BP Amoco $32 million and Texaco $43 million, according to Scott Powell, a lawyer in Birmingham, Ala., who represents private plaintiffs in the case.Also, Conoco has tentatively agreed to a $26 million settlement.Lawyers for the Kerr-McGee Corporation, Sunoco Inc., Union Pacific Resources Group Inc., Canadian Occidental Petroleum Ltd. and the Devon Energy Corporation, which bought PennzEnergy this year, agreed to pay a total of $27 million, Powell said.Although Texaco believes it correctly paid the royalties, a spokeswoman, Tyra Metoyer, said, the company reached the tentative $43 million settlement to avoid protracted litigation.Kerr-McGee, Union Pacific Resources and Devon Energy said they had reached tentative settlements and declined to disclose the sums they had agreed to pay. A Union Pacific Resources spokesman, Dan Sullivan, said the company had settled to avoid the ''cost and uncertainty of litigation.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/21/business/company-news-devon-energy-to-buy-unit-spun-off-by-pennzoil.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON ENERGY TO BUY UNIT SPUN OFF BY PENNZOIL<date>Published: May 21, 1999</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the Pennzenergy Company, the oil exploration and production business spun off last year by the Pennzoil Company for $675 million. Devon, based in Oklahoma City, had revenue of $388 million last year. Pennzenergy, based in Houston, was created last year when Pennzoil merged with the Quaker State Corporation. Under the agreement, Pennzenergy shareholders will receive 0.4475 share of the new company for each share held. Based on Wednesday's closing prices, the deal valued each Pennzenergy share at $14.10. Shares of Pennzenergy fell 12.5 cents, to $14.50. Shares of Devon rose $2.25, to $33.75.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/30/business/company-news-oil-and-gas-companies-in-565-million-merger.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OIL AND GAS COMPANIES IN $565 MILLION MERGER<date>Published: June 30, 1998</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation of Oklahoma City said yesterday that it intended to issue 15.4 million shares of stock to acquire the Northstar Energy Corporation of Calgary, Alberta. Devon announced the deal after its shares closed at $36.6875, up 18.75 cents. At that price the deal is worth about $565 million. Devon will also assume Northstar debt of $312 million and other obligations. The combined company would have total reserves of 1.2 trillion cubic feet of gas and 117 million barrels of oil. Both boards have approved the deal.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/12/business/company-news-rival-offer-emerges-for-burlington-trust-units.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; RIVAL OFFER EMERGES FOR BURLINGTON TRUST UNITS<date>Published: February 12, 1998</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation of Oklahoma City said yesterday that it would make a tender offer of $8.75 in cash for each of the 8.8 million units of Burlington Resources Coal Seam Gas Royalty Trust, giving it ownership of a methane field in New Mexico. The offer, valued at as much as $77 million, is the second for units of the trust in three weeks. On Jan. 20, San Juan Partners L.L.C., a closely held oil and gas partnership in Houston, offered to buy 5.45 million units for $8.25 each. The holdings of the Dallas-based Burlington Resources trust include an interest in the Northeast Blanco field in New Mexico. Burlington Resources trust units rose 87.5 cents, to $8.9375. Devon Energy fell $1, to $34.75.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/18/business/oil-and-gas-fields-change-hands-for-297-million.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">OIL AND GAS FIELDS CHANGE HANDS FOR $297 MILLION<date>Published: October 18, 1996</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation is buying North American oil and gas fields from the Kerr-McGee Corporation for $297 million in stock, the two Oklahoma City companies announced yesterday. The fields, which contain 53 million barrels of oil and gas reserves, are in West Texas, the Oklahoma and Texas panhandles, the Rocky Mountains and western Canada. Devon will also get drilling rights to 370,000 more acres. Devon will pay for the fields with 9.95 million new shares of stock. Devon's stock rose 11 percent yesterday, gaining $3.125, to $30 on the American Stock Exchange. Kerr-McGee closed up 12.5 cents, at $63.125, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/05/19/business/company-news-devon-shareholders-approve-acquisition-of-alta.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON SHAREHOLDERS APPROVE ACQUISITION OF ALTA<date>Published: May 19, 1994</date><text>The shareholders of the Devon Energy Corporation approved the acquisition of the Alta Energy Corporation of Midland, Tex., for $64.6 million in cash, stock and assumed debt. Alta shareholders of record will receive 35 cents a share in cash and three-tenths of a Devon common share if they own more than 334 shares. Holders of fewer Alta shares will get $7.14 a share in cash. The price includes $39 million in debt that Devon will assume. Devon, based in Oklahoma City, will pay about $1.4 million in cash and issue 1.18 million of its common shares to Alta shareholders.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/01/05/business/company-news-devon-to-acquire-alta-energy-for-31.2-million.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DEVON TO ACQUIRE ALTA ENERGY FOR $31.2 MILLION<date>Published: January 05, 1994</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation agreed yesterday to purchase Alta Energy Inc. for $31.2 million, or $7.79 a share, in cash and stock, based on Friday's stock prices. The transaction between the two independent petroleum producers would increase the size of Devon's reserves by 38.9 percent, or 28.8 million barrels of oil equivalent. Alta shareholders would get $1.20 a share in cash for each of the 4.006 million shares Alta estimates will be outstanding. Alta holders would also get 0.3189 Devon share for each Alta share. Devon, of Oklahoma City, said it would also assume $37 million in debt and other obligations, making the purchase of the Midland, Tex., company worth about $69 million, based on Friday's closing price of $20.625 for Devon shares. Alta shares plunged $1.875, to $7, on the American Stock Exchange yesterday where the 21 percent decline was the worst of the day, while Devon shares dropped 37.5 cents, to $20.25.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/02/29/business/company-news-hondo-oil-offer.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Hondo Oil Offer<date>Published: February 29, 1992</date><text>The Devon Energy Corporation has offered $140 million to the Hondo Oil and Gas Company for most of Hondo's domestic oil and gas reserves and seven natural gas processing plants. Adjustments for reserves produced and cash flow from operations before to closing are expected to reduce the net purchase price to $130 million, Devon said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/07/07/business/making-a-difference-showdown-in-the-gas-patch.html?ref=devonenergycorporation">Making a Difference; Showdown in the Gas Patch<date>Published: July 07, 1991</date><text>In the San Juan basin of northwest New Mexico, a handful of energy companies have sold natural gas from an unlikely source, underground coal deposits, for $1.50 or more per 1,000 cubic feet in the last few years.Spot prices routinely vary widely depending on the heating season, but an unusually warm winter and recession sent prices tumbling to their lowest levels in 20 years this spring, below $1.20. When big gas buyers in southern California bargained last week for a deeper cut, to 95 cents, J. Larry Nichols balked.Mr. Nichols, operator of the region's biggest coal gas alliance, which includes Amoco, Burlington Northern's Meridian Oil, Conoco, Texaco and his own Devon Energy Corporation, cut daily production of the partnership nearly in half, to 65 million cubic feet a day for the month of July.The maneuver meant stopping or curtailing production at 50 wells of the group's Northeast Blanco unit.Many gas buyers had believed coal gas producers like Devon were in a bind and would have to produce at any price because of potential problems with water draining back into inactive well bores in the coal layers. Mr. Nichols, Devon's 49-year-old president and chief executive, said the shutdowns ordered last week sent a message that those buyers were wrong: wells in the region can be water-proofed.Meanwhile, he said, Devon and its partners have the financial strength to wait for higher prices in the winter.Low prices forced Devon to take a $25 million writedown in the first quarter, resulting in a loss of $17.8 million. But Devon has staying power, Mr. Nichols said, adding that its debt was a moderate 32 percent of equity at the end of March, and production costs were cut to 60 cents a 1,000 cubic feet from $1 two years ago."We needed to draw the line somewhere to tell buyers that we weren't going to be traded down forever," Mr. Nichols said.</text></article></page><page index="4" /><page index="5" /><page index="6" /><page index="7" /><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
