<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="EMC Corporation"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/03/keep-your-tech-friends-close-but-keep-your-enemies-closer/?ref=emccorporation">Keep Your Tech Friends Close, but Keep Your Enemies Closer<date>October 3, 2011, 7:20 pm</date><text>If you are in business, you probably do not spend resources praising your competitor. But then, you’re probably also not the chief executive of a large tech company that is competing with the Oracle Corporation. Oracle OpenWorld Dispatches from the conference. On Monday morning, Joseph Tucci, chief executive of the data storage giant EMC, gave a talk at the Oracle OpenWorld trade show in San Francisco. That seems odd, considering Oracle makes its own data storage devices. And on Tuesday, Michael Dell, chief executive of Dell Inc., whose computer servers compete with Oracle’s machines, will take the stage. What’s with the corporate frenemies? “I walk past our booth and it’s packed,” Mr. Tucci said. “It’s great of Oracle to pound their point of view out there — it’s their show — but we can get ours out too.” In other words, the 45,000 people who show up here are all potential sales targets. Why not show up, praise Oracle onstage, and go at it on the sales floor? Indeed, the claims of Larry Ellison, Oracle’s chief executive, on Sunday that Oracle’s data analysis system was eight times faster than the competition was fresh meat for Mr. Tucci. “They’re eight times faster in what way?” he said. “Let’s hear a few specifics on that.” Like Mr. Ellison, Mr. Tucci is a veteran of the business and enjoys the competition. “I’m happy to have someone come straight at me, versus someone putting their arm around me and acting like my friend. One thing about Oracle, they tell you what they are doing.” Not all the onstage corporate talent is as kind as Mr. Tucci. Marc Benioff, the head of Salesforce.com and a onetime top protege of Mr. Ellison, spent part of his Monday morning on Facebook and Twitter, reposting the work of bloggers who panned Mr. Ellison’s Sunday night keynote speech. “A low bar has been set. See you Wednesday at 10 a.m.!” Mr. Benioff wrote on Twitter. At last check, Oracle still plans to have him onstage. The love among antagonists is also a mark of the industry changes wrought by new computer architectures and old-fashioned industry consolidation. John Chambers, the chief executive of the computer networking company Cisco Systems, will be speaking Wednesday. While Oracle does not yet have a significant networking business, Cisco makes online storage and computer server products, putting it in conflict with Oracle and EMC. But Cisco also has a joint venture to sell products with EMC and its majority-owned affiliate VMWare. EMC has also purchased analytic software companies that compete with the analytics products Oracle announced Sunday. It may be a mark of an industry in transition, but it is unlikely to end soon. Mr. Tucci recently said he will retire at the end of 2012, moving to chairman of the EMC board for two to four years. His successor is almost certain to be Pat Gelsinger, EMC’s president and chief operating officer for infrastructure products (Mr. Tucci would not comment on succession.) On Monday, Mr. Gelsinger followed Mr. Tucci onstage, where he demonstrated a new EMC data storage device that can fit right into a server — the kind made by Oracle and Dell.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/09/data-explosion-lifts-the-storage-market/?ref=emccorporation">Data Explosion Lifts the Storage Market<date>September 9, 2011, 10:20 am</date><text>Workers suffering from information overload, and companies drowning in the Internet-era exaflood of data? These are good problems indeed, if you are in the data storage business. In a shaky economy, companies are spending cautiously on most things, but computer storage in data centers is an exception. The most recent evidence came earlier this month, when IDC reported that sales of disk storage systems in the second quarter grew more than 10 percent, to $7.5 billion. The dollars understate the storage boom, since this is an industry working the way technology is supposed to — that is, you get more for less. Measured by the amount of data storage capacity, shipments jumped by 47 percent, compared with the year-earlier quarter. The fastest growth is in the more sophisticated storage systems that can quickly shuttle data back and forth. A major trend in data centers is the adoption of virtualization software that juggles computing tasks among many computers, saving money and electricity. That, too, is spurring demand. “You need both more capacity and more high-performing storage,” said Mark Peters, an analyst at Enterprise Strategy Group, a research firm. The biggest winner from the surge in demand for storage is EMC, the industry leader. In recent years, EMC has been buying up software companies to move beyond its core storage business, including VMware, the major supplier of virtualization software. But analysts estimate that $12 billion of the company’s nearly $20 billion in revenue this year will come from the storage business. “Storage is the underpinning, and we build on top of that,” Howard Elias, president of EMC’s information infrastructure and cloud services division, said in an interview this week. EMC continues to gain share, holding 28.7 percent of the merchant disk storage market in the second quarter, up from 25.6 percent year-ago quarter. Indeed, it is two storage specialists, EMC and NetApp, that have consistently increased their share of the market over the last five years, analysts say. The broader computer companies that also sell storage, like Hewlett-Packard, I.B.M., Dell and Sun Microsystems (bought by Oracle in 2009), have not gained ground. Mr. Elias, a former H.P. executive, points out that EMC invests about $1.5 billion a year research and development to improve and refine its storage technology, far more than its more diversified computer rivals. “It’s the focus and specialization that enables us to gain share,” Mr. Elias said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/04/02/the-rsa-hack-how-they-did-it/?ref=emccorporation">The RSA Hack: How They Did It<date>April 2, 2011, 3:17 pm</date><text>The hack last month at RSA Security has been shrouded in mystery. How did a hacker manage to infiltrate one of the world’s top computer-security companies? And could the data that was stolen be used to impair its SecurID products, which are used by 40 million businesses that are trying to keep their own networks safe from intruders? The division of the EMC Corporation is staying mum about what exactly was stolen from its computer systems, aside from that it was data related to SecurID. But on Friday RSA shed some light on the nature of the attack. In a blog post titled “Anatomy of an Attack,” the company’s head of new technologies, Uri Rivner, described a three-stage operation that was similar to several other recent prominent attacks on technology companies, including a 2009 attack on Google that it said originated in China. In the attack on RSA, the attacker sent “phishing” e-mails with the subject line “2011 Recruitment Plan” to two small groups of employees over the course of two days. Unfortunately, one was interested enough to retrieve one of these messages from his or her junk mail and open the attached Excel file. The spreadsheet contained malware that used a previously unknown, or “zero-day,” flaw in Adobe’s Flash software to install a backdoor. RSA said that Adobe had since released a patch to fix that hole. After installing a stealthy tool that allowed the hacker to control the machine from afar, he stole several account passwords belonging to the employee and used them to gain entry into other systems, where he could gain access to other employees with access to sensitive data, Mr. Rivner said. Then came stage three: spiriting RSA files out of the company to a hacked machine at a hosting provider, and then on to the hacker himself. The attacker left few traces. But an unclassified document from the United States Computer Emergency Readiness Team (US-CERT) obtained by the blogger Brian Krebs revealed three Web addresses used in the intrusion, one of which includes the letters “PRC,” which could refer to the People’s Republic of China — or it could be a ruse. According to Mr. Rivner, it’s difficult for companies with the world’s most sophisticated defenses to stop this newfangled “advanced persistent threats,” which are made potent by the combination of low-tech “social-engineering” cons and a high-tech zero-day attack that antivirus software won’t recognize. That RSA detected the attack in progress was a victory, he argued. Many other companies hit by similar attacks “either detected the attacks after months, or didn’t detect them at all and learned about it from the government,” he said. “As an industry, we have to act fast and develop a new defense doctrine; the happy days of good old hacking are gone, and gone too are the old defense paradigms.” But some security experts ridiculed the notion that the attack was sophisticated. Jeremiah Grossman, founder of WhiteHat Security, posted on Twitter: “I can’t tell if this RSA APT blog post is actually being serious or an April 1st gag. The content is absurd either way.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/19/technology/19secure.html?ref=emccorporation">Maker of SecurID Is Vague About an Attack<date>Published: March 18, 2011</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO — More than a day after RSA security posted an “urgent” alert warning that a sophisticated intruder might be able to initiate a “broad attack” on a password device used by millions of customers, the announcement and its meaning remain shrouded in mystery.RSA, a division of the data management company EMC Corporation, will not say how its system was compromised and what specific kinds of threats its customers are facing. But from its extremely limited disclosure on Thursday afternoon about what might have been taken, customers and computer security specialists are scratching their heads about what the risks may actually be. There was wide bewilderment about the company’s claim that the intruder was “extremely sophisticated,” as it suggested that one of the nation’s premier security firms had no better security than dozens of companies that have fallen victim to a computer break-in that deceives employees and exploits unknown software vulnerabilities. On Friday, a spokesman for RSA said it was briefing its customers individually but added that its executives were declining to speak publicly about the breach. The announcement touched off intense speculation about whether RSA’s popular SecurID tokens, which are carried on key chains and in wallets of millions of corporate and government users, have been significantly compromised. “It’s a weird situation,” said Dan Kaminsky, an independent Internet security specialist. Referring to the Tokyo Electric Power Company, he said, “It’s like the Tepco situation in Japan, but here everyone is freaking out” and “nobody has Geiger counters.” The system is intended to provide additional security beyond a simple user name and password by requiring users to append a unique number generated by the token each time they connect to their corporate or government network. A potential weakness that could be exploited involves a factory-installed key called a seed. Typically 16 characters, it is different for each token and is stored on a corresponding computer server program, which authenticates the session each time a user connects to a secure network. If the database containing customers seeds was taken, the intruder might still not know which user had which seed, but cryptographers said it would be possible to use a reverse-engineered version of the RSA algorithm to determine that information by simply capturing a single log-in session. That would be a potentially serious vulnerability that could be exploited by a sophisticated attacker. A technical expert in New York whose financial services firm uses the SecurID system said that even after listening to a telephone briefing on Thursday evening, he was uncertain about which potential threats he should be concerned about. The company offered only extremely general “belt and suspenders” advice, the expert said. A copy of the company’s terse “RSA Securcare Online Note” posted on the Securities and Exchange Commission Web site on Thursday offers such advice as “Focus on security for social media applications” and “We recommend customers re-educate employees on the importance of avoiding suspicious e-mails.” RSA notified the federal government, whose agencies widely use the tokens to guard access to its networks, some time before the public announcement was made. On Wednesday, the Computer Emergency Readiness Team in the Department of Homeland Security posted a “Technical Information Paper” on its Web site describing a set of security practices meant to limit vulnerability to attacks based on the stolen information, according to a person close to the organization. “We have notified all of the federal agency chief information officers to take remediation steps,” said a government official who declined to be identified because he had not been authorized to speak about the breach. What the actual risk is and what precautions a user of the key fobs and wallet-size cards depends on what was taken in the theft. “I’m speculating, but I’m pretty confident that somebody has the root seed file,” said a former RSA employee, referring to the master file at the company, which is based in Bedford, Mass. He asked not to be identified because he still has a business relationship with the firm. The worst case, many security consultants say, is that the vulnerability created by the theft might require companies to replace the secure tokens, which, according to analysts, cost $15 a year or more to maintain. The vulnerability might also force RSA to rethink the design of its SecurID system. “They may have to change their security model to one where a third party does not hold the keys to your devices,” said Paul Kocher, president of Cryptography Inc., a San Francisco computer security consulting firm.SAN FRANCISCO — More than a day after RSA security posted an “urgent” alert warning that a sophisticated intruder might be able to initiate a “broad attack” on a password device used by millions of customers, the announcement and its meaning remain shrouded in mystery.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/18/technology/18secure.html?ref=emccorporation">SecurID Company Suffers Security Breach<date>Published: March 17, 2011</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO — The RSA Security division of the EMC Corporation said Thursday that it had suffered a sophisticated data breach, potentially compromising computer security products widely used by corporations and governments. The company, which pioneered an advanced cryptographic system during the 1980s, sells products that offer stronger computer security than simple password protection. Known as multifactor authentication, the technology is typically based on an electronic token carried by a user that repeatedly generates a time-based number that must be appended to a password when a user logs in to a computer system. RSA, which is based in Bedford, Mass., posted an urgent message on its Web site on Thursday referring to an open letter from its chairman, Art Coviello. The letter acknowledged that the company had suffered from an intrusion Mr. Coviello described as an “advanced persistent threat.” In recent years a number of United States companies and government agencies have been the victim of this type of attack, in which an intruder either exploits an unknown software vulnerability or in some way compromises the trust of an employee to take command of a computer or an entire network within a company. In 2009, for example, Google fell victim to an attack that it said had originated in China, and it ended commercial operations in the country in response. Mr. Coviello said that the company’s investigation had revealed that the intruder successfully stole digital information from the company that was related to RSA’s SecurID two-factor authentication products. He did not give precise details about the nature of the information, but said it could potentially reduce the effectiveness of the system in the face of a “broader attack.” The company said that there was currently no indication that the information had been used to attack its customers. “We took a variety of aggressive measures against the threat to protect our business and our customers, including further hardening of our I.T. infrastructure,” Mr. Coviello said. “We also immediately began an extensive investigation of the attack and are working closely with the appropriate authorities.” Company officials did not return phone calls seeking comment on Thursday. Despite the lack of detail, several computer security specialists said the breach could pose a real threat to companies and government agencies who rely on the technology. One possibility, said Whitfield Diffie, a computer security specialist who was an inventor of cryptographic systems now widely used in electronic commerce, is that a “master key” — a large secret number used as part of the encryption algorithm — might have been stolen. The worst case, he said, would be that the intruder could produce cards that duplicate the ones supplied by RSA, making it possible to gain access to corporate networks and computer systems. Mr. Diffie is vice president for information security and cryptography at the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers. In addition to posting the chairman’s letter, the company submitted a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission in which it stated that it did not expect the theft to have a financial impact. RSA was founded in 1982 by a small group of technologists who at times were actively opposed by the National Security Agency, which was trying to limit the spread of sophisticated cryptography technology. In 2009, the company said publicly that its SecurID system was being used by 40 million customers. Last year it said its technology was used to secure the identities and assets of more than 250 million people.SAN FRANCISCO — The RSA Security division of the EMC Corporation said Thursday that it had suffered a sophisticated data breach, potentially compromising computer security products widely used by corporations and governments. The company, which pioneered an advanced cryptographic system during the 1980s, sells products that offer stronger computer security than simple password protection. Known as multifactor authentication, the technology is typically based on an electronic token carried by a user that repeatedly generates a time-based number that must be appended to a password when a user logs in to a computer system. RSA, which is based in Bedford, Mass., posted an urgent message on its Web site on Thursday referring to an open letter from its chairman, Art Coviello. The letter acknowledged that the company had suffered from an intrusion Mr. Coviello described as an “advanced persistent threat.” In recent years a number of United States companies and government agencies have been the victim of this type of attack, in which an intruder either exploits an unknown software vulnerability or in some way compromises the trust of an employee to take command of a computer or an entire network within a company. In 2009, for example, Google fell victim to an attack that it said had originated in China, and it ended commercial operations in the country in response. Mr. Coviello said that the company’s investigation had revealed that the intruder successfully stole digital information from the company that was related to RSA’s SecurID two-factor authentication products. He did not give precise details about the nature of the information, but said it could potentially reduce the effectiveness of the system in the face of a “broader attack.” The company said that there was currently no indication that the information had been used to attack its customers. “We took a variety of aggressive measures against the threat to protect our business and our customers, including further hardening of our I.T. infrastructure,” Mr. Coviello said. “We also immediately began an extensive investigation of the attack and are working closely with the appropriate authorities.” Company officials did not return phone calls seeking comment on Thursday. Despite the lack of detail, several computer security specialists said the breach could pose a real threat to companies and government agencies who rely on the technology. One possibility, said Whitfield Diffie, a computer security specialist who was an inventor of cryptographic systems now widely used in electronic commerce, is that a “master key” — a large secret number used as part of the encryption algorithm — might have been stolen. The worst case, he said, would be that the intruder could produce cards that duplicate the ones supplied by RSA, making it possible to gain access to corporate networks and computer systems. Mr. Diffie is vice president for information security and cryptography at the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers. In addition to posting the chairman’s letter, the company submitted a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission in which it stated that it did not expect the theft to have a financial impact. RSA was founded in 1982 by a small group of technologists who at times were actively opposed by the National Security Agency, which was trying to limit the spread of sophisticated cryptography technology. In 2009, the company said publicly that its SecurID system was being used by 40 million customers. Last year it said its technology was used to secure the identities and assets of more than 250 million people.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/11/15/the-shrinking-data-storage-sector/?ref=emccorporation">The Shrinking Data Storage Sector<date>November 15, 2010, 7:09 pm</date><text>Gurinder Osan/Associated Press Joe Tucci, EMC’s chief executive, is seeking to become a larger player in “big data.” With EMC’s $2.25 billion purchase of Isilon Systems on Monday, yet another data storage company has fallen into the eager hands of a larger rival. Over the last two years, the data storage market has been defined by a wave of consolidation, as a handful of market leaders paid hefty premiums for acquisitions. EMC is certainly paying a high price to add Isilon to its stable. EMC, the world’s largest storage company, agreed to pay $33.85 a share, a 28.8 percent premium over Friday’s closing price and about nine times estimated revenue for Isilon in 2011, according to Kaushik Roy, a Wedbush Morgan Securities analyst. “I guess this is the new normal,” Mr. Roy said in a phone interview. “It’s a little irritating that it’s a pricey deal, but it’s more of a strategic deal — EMC wanted to take it off the market.” Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Indeed, a long list of data storage companies are now off the market: 3Par, Data Domain, ONStor and Netezza have all been acquired in the last 18 months. Hewlett-Packard and Dell’s weeks-long tussle for 3Par was particularly heated, featuring a string of counteroffers and a final price tag of $33 a share, or $2.35 billion, for H.P. Before Dell kicked off the bidding war with its first offer in mid-August, 3Par’s stock was trading at about $10 a share. Data storage companies have become hot commodities in the technology sector as corporations shift to cloud computing and storage needs grow. According to a January report by William Blair &amp; Company, the total amount of data generated by consumers and businesses will double every 18 months. Meanwhile, the entire data storage market, which includes software, is about $45 billion and is expected to grow in a range of 5 to 10 percent on a yearly basis. Beyond the greater market potential, large technology companies, like H.P. and Dell, covet the industry’s generous margins, which typically surpass 50 percent. For comparison, Dell reported third quarter gross margins of 17.3 percent in the third quarter, weighed down by the notoriously slim margins of its desktop and laptop businesses. EMC, which has purchased about two dozen data storage companies in the last decade, said it bought Isilon to become a larger player in “big data.” Isilon specializes in scale-out network attached storage, a scalable storage infrastructure that can handle up to 10 petabytes of data. Although EMC has products like Atmos and Celerra that compete somewhat with Isilon in the big data space, the new acquisition will help EMC better address the $2 billion market. “The unmistakable waves of cloud computing and ‘big data’ are upon us,” Joe Tucci, EMC’s chief executive, said in a statement. Pat Gelsinger, president of information infrastructure products, said this market would grow to $6 billion in 2014 and disagreed with the notion that EMC wanted merely to get Isilon off the market. “This is the fastest growing segment of the market,” he said, adding that EMC looked at Isilon strategically and financially. ”It’s certainly not about just getting it off the market,” he said According to EMC, Isilon is on track to hit $200 million in revenue this year, while Atmos is close to $100 million, and by the second half of 2012, the two combined should be posting revenue equivalent to $1 billion a year. Although Mr. Roy of Wedbush Morgan believes that Isilon will add to EMC’s earnings very soon, he said it was impossible to ignore the role that competitive dynamics played in this acquisition. Mr. Roy, who previously worked for EMC in corporate development, said EMC might have purchased the company so that Dell — its business partner and increasing its rival — could not. According to his calculations, Dell sells about $800 million worth of EMC storage. He believes that the company does not want to disrupt its relationship with EMC, but that Dell is under significant pressure to increase its margins. “It could have been Dell, it could have been Oracle, the worst thing would have been if Dell wanted to buy it, because they’re going to be competing more and more with their partner,” he said. “It’s a signal to Dell.” Meanwhile, EMC is also trying to steal back momentum from its closest rival, Netapp. In the first quarter for fiscal year 2011, which ended July 30, Netapp recorded a 36 percent increase in revenue, to $1.14 billion. Several analysts said this competitive fire will continue to fuel acquisitions in the data storage space at rich premiums. As larger companies, like H.P., Dell, EMC and I.B.M., carve up the market, however, the number of midsize data storage businesses available for purchase is rapidly dwindling. Mr. Roy noted that there were not many public targets left, but said Compellent Technologies, a data storage company with a market capitalization of $780 million, was likely to be next. Jason Ader, an analyst with William &amp; Bair, estimated that industry consolidation was only about 50 percent complete and that as acquisitions continued, premiums would rise. Mr. Ader said Compellent, CommVault and even NetApp, a company with a market capitalization of $19 billion), are likely acquisition targets. Mr. Ader does see one problem with the continuing consolidation of the storage industry: “I’m running out of companies to cover.”</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/10/19/can-emc-and-dell-kiss-and-make-up/?ref=emccorporation">Can EMC and Dell Kiss and Make Up?<date>October 19, 2010, 5:43 pm</date><text>EMC felt like a jilted lover when Dell made an unsuccessful run at 3Par, EMC’s rival in the data storage business. But now that Hewlett-Packard has trumped Dell’s takeover bid for 3Par, EMC and Dell are trying to patch up their bruised relationship. “We are again in discussions to see if we could do something more meaningful and lasting,” EMC’s chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, said Tuesday, according to Reuters. “Both companies would like to do that, but the key is, it’s got to be meaningful, and it’s got to be lasting for me to tell you that it’s back on track” Dell’s affection has been fading for a number of years, with EMC reporting a decline in the percentage of revenue it gets from Dell. And as Reuters notes, the 3Par bid caused a severe strain that had the potential to be final: Mr. Tucci told investors on Tuesday that Dell’s bid for 3Par undermined the two companies’ relationship. Dell has resold billions of dollars of EMC’s data storage equipment, mostly to small and mid-sized businesses. “Dell went after 3Par and obviously cooled things off,” Mr. Tucci said in a conference call with analysts discussing EMC’s third-quarter results. But the two tech giants are now trying to resolve their differences, he said. Indeed, Dell also made an effort on Tuesday to smooth over the relationship. “EMC is a strategic partner and plays an important role in our storage portfolio,” a Dell spokesman, David Frink, said in a statement. He noted to Reuters that Dell had started selling two new EMC product lines this year. So can this relationship be saved? One analyst told Reuters he thinks so — at least in the short term: “EMC is not going to risk all that business just because they got a little egg on their face,” said Steve Duplessie, an analyst with the Enterprise Strategy Group. “I’m sure they’ll get over it.” Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D9103EF93BA25753C1A9669D8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">BITS; EMC's Swipe At Rivals in Data<date>Published: October 18, 2010</date><text>Big data is like the testosterone of business computing right now. It has put technology's largest players on an aggression bender. The latest tech giant to flex its big-data muscle is EMC. On Wednesday, the storage specialist introduced the EMC Greenplum Data Computing Appliance. EMC acquired Greenplum in July, giving it some of the top data warehousing software in the market. The company has taken that code and wrapped it in a metal bundle, adding servers, storage units and networking to make a so-called appliance, which is data-center speak for a system that's meant to perform a single function well. The product stands out as EMC's first real foray into selling customers a complete system rather than just storage bits and bobs. (Look under the covers, though, and you'll find that Dell actually makes the server part of the appliance.) Data warehousing systems vacuum up information from huge databases and then let companies poke and prod at that information in the hopes of gleaning insights about their business. Typically, these computing products munch away on inventory, sales, shipping, employee and customer data. EMC's move follows I.B.M.'s acquisition last month of the data warehouse appliance maker Netezza for $1.7 billion. Oracle too spent most of its recent customer conference talking about its data warehousing appliances made out of hardware it acquired in the purchase of Sun Microsystems. Hewlett-Packard and Microsoft have built out their data warehousing arsenals in recent years as well through a combination of in-house work and acquisitions. And Teradata remains the independent market leader. These companies are all racing to make bigger, faster systems that can keep up with the flood of data being produced by people and all types of things with digital heartbeats. ''Before it was just humans entering data, but now the machines are generating their own information,'' said Scott Yara, a co-founder of Greenplum and now a vice president at EMC. ''There are wireless networks, switches, routers and sensors. The machines are generating 10 times more data than the humans.'' Greenplum specialized in making software capable of running across many computers linked together. This technique allows customers to analyze huge data sets in a reasonable amount of time. The bigger the data sets, the better for the technology companies because they're selling more gear and getting closer to their customers by handling prized information. ''I think data will become so synonymous to computing,'' Mr. Yara said. This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/05/07/vmwares-springsource-buys-gemstone/?ref=emccorporation">VMware's SpringSource Buys GemStone<date>May 7, 2010, 3:35 am</date><text>From Joan Jackson at IDG News Service: VMware‘s SpringSource is acquiring database-caching software company GemStone Systems, the company announced Thursday. Terms of the deal were not disclosed. With this purchase, VMware will obtain a set of technologies and expertise to address one of the major bottlenecks in cloud computing, that of scaling databases. “GemStone solves a really important problem: If you are building applications that need to scale out in the enterprise or move to the cloud, you need to scale your applications without major architectural changes. GemStone’s technology has a proven capability of doing that,” said Rod Johnson, general manager of the SpringSource division of VMware, itself an EMC company. Go to Article from IDG News via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/05/06/michael-capellas-to-lead-acadia-joint-venture/?ref=emccorporation">Michael Capellas to Lead Acadia Joint Venture<date>May 6, 2010, 4:40 am</date><text>From Sumner Lemon at IDG News Service: EMC and Cisco have tapped former Compaq Computer chief executive, Michael Capellas, to head their Acadia services joint venture, the companies said Thursday. Acadia was created to support a partnership between EMC, Cisco and VMware announced in November called the Virtual Computing Environment coalition. As chief executive of Acadia, Mr. Capellas will have overall responsibility for the VCE partnership and will report to John Chambers, chairman and chief of Cisco, and Joe Tucci, chairman and chief of EMC, the companies said in a statement. Mr. Capellas was chief executive of Compaq when it was acquired by Hewlett-Packard and most recently served as chief and chairman of First Data, a payment processing company. He also serves on Cisco’s board of directors. Go to Article from IDG News Service via The New York Times »</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/08/technology/08blue.html?ref=emccorporation">Bundling Hardware and Software to Do Big Jobs<date>Published: February 8, 2010</date><text>In data-center computing, the big trend today is to move from building blocks to bundles. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image John Marshall Mantel for The New York Times Rodney Adkins, senior vice president for systems and technology at I.B.M., which is ahead in developing customized systems. Suppliers are offering customers assembled bundles of hardware and software to make it easier and less expensive for customers to cope with the Internet-era surge in data  an information flood coming from internal databases, but also from Web-based collaboration and smartphone applications, sensors that monitor electrical use, environmental contamination and food shipments, even biological and genetic research. The shift to packaging hardware and software together is behind the recent big deals and partnerships in the technology industry: Oracle’s purchase of Sun Microsystems for $7.4 billion, an alliance between Hewlett-Packard and Microsoft announced last month, and a similar partnership between Cisco Systems and EMC. But computer scientists at universities and technology companies say that simply putting the hardware and software building blocks together more efficiently for customers is not enough. “The huge challenge is to take all this data and generate useful knowledge from it,” said Kunle Olukotun, a computer scientist at Stanford. “It’s an enormous opportunity in science and business, but it also presents a massive computing problem.” The path to intelligently mining the explosion of data, Mr. Olukotun said, involves new approaches to breaking down computing tasks into subtasks that can be processed simultaneously  a concept known as parallel computing  and new system designs optimized for specific kinds of work. Designing computer systems around the work to be done is a departure from the dominant approach of general-purpose design, in which machines are built to be capable of handling all kinds of chores and are then programmed to do specific tasks. Several companies are beginning to bring workload-optimized systems design into the mainstream of corporate and government computing. The promise, analysts say, is to not only open the door to exploiting the data flood for competitive advantage, but also to reduce energy costs and help automate the management and administration of computer systems  a labor-intensive expense that is rising four times faster than the cost of hardware. I.B.M., according to industry analysts, is at the forefront of the effort to develop more customized systems. And on Monday, the company is making the first of a series of announcements this year that embody the new approach. I.B.M. is introducing a line of big computer servers using its Power 7 32-core microprocessors. They are priced at $190,000, typically run Unix or Linux, and are aimed at industries like finance and utilities, as well as scientific researchers. Next month, I.B.M. plans to unveil far less costly server systems based on industry-standard microprocessors made by Intel. Those machines, which typically run Unix or Microsoft Windows, will be used for Web collaboration, e-mail and other applications. “These are not simply hardware products, but the result of years of work and investment at every level from the silicon up through the software,” said Rodney C. Adkins, I.B.M.’s senior vice president for systems and technology. “And the real challenge is to optimize it all, not just the hardware.” The early deployment of so-called smart utility grids points to the challenges of handling ever-vaster amounts of data. Smart electric meters can measure room temperatures and energy use hourly or at 15-minute intervals instead of the old pattern of utility service workers reading electro-mechanical meters every month or two. The goal of smart grids, which governments are starting to heavily subsidize, is to give households and businesses timely information so they can change their electricity consumption habits to reduce energy use and pollution, and save money. That involves not only collecting the data, but also analyzing and presenting it to consumers in ways that are easily understood  typically a personalized Web site graphically showing household electricity consumption and pricing. EMeter, a maker of smart-grid software in San Mateo, Calif., said that using I.B.M.’s workload-tuned P-7 systems should more than double its capacity to manage smart meters, bringing it up to 50 million. In one eMeter project, the utilities in Ontario are going to install 4.5 million smart meters by 2011. Before, meters were read once every month or two. Under the digital system, readings will be made hourly, a hundredfold increase in the data generated. “If you can’t continually measure energy use down to the granular level in homes and businesses, the smart grid doesn’t work,” said Scott Smith, director of technical solutions at eMeter. “You need a tremendous amount of computing power to do that at scale.” Computer scientists, biologists and researchers from Rice University and the Texas Medical Center have been working with I.B.M. scientists to fine-tune P-7 systems for cancer research. Genetic and protein-folding simulations require vast amounts of specialized high-speed processing and computer memory, said Kamran Khan, vice provost for information technology at Rice. I.B.M., he said, dispatched three Ph.D. biologists to work with the cancer researchers. “They really understand computational biology,” Mr. Khan said. The more bespoke approach to computer-systems design does increase the risk that customers are locked into one or two powerful companies. Indeed, the reason data-center customers long preferred the building-block approach to hardware and software was that it guaranteed competition among suppliers. But the tradeoff has been that customers had to put the hardware and software together themselves, even as computing complexity and data-handling demands surged. Many companies, it seems, are willing to accept less competition among suppliers for the convenience and cost savings from prepackaged systems. “It’s a balancing act,” said Frank Gens, chief analyst at IDC. “It does take away some choice, but also makes things a lot simpler. And that, after all, is the model that Apple used so successfully in consumer technology.” More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on February 8, 2010, on page B4 of the New York edition.In data-center computing, the big trend today is to move from building blocks to bundles. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image John Marshall Mantel for The New York Times Rodney Adkins, senior vice president for systems and technology at I.B.M., which is ahead in developing customized systems. Suppliers are offering customers assembled bundles of hardware and software to make it easier and less expensive for customers to cope with the Internet-era surge in data  an information flood coming from internal databases, but also from Web-based collaboration and smartphone applications, sensors that monitor electrical use, environmental contamination and food shipments, even biological and genetic research. The shift to packaging hardware and software together is behind the recent big deals and partnerships in the technology industry: Oracle’s purchase of Sun Microsystems for $7.4 billion, an alliance between Hewlett-Packard and Microsoft announced last month, and a similar partnership between Cisco Systems and EMC. But computer scientists at universities and technology companies say that simply putting the hardware and software building blocks together more efficiently for customers is not enough. “The huge challenge is to take all this data and generate useful knowledge from it,” said Kunle Olukotun, a computer scientist at Stanford. “It’s an enormous opportunity in science and business, but it also presents a massive computing problem.” The path to intelligently mining the explosion of data, Mr. Olukotun said, involves new approaches to breaking down computing tasks into subtasks that can be processed simultaneously  a concept known as parallel computing  and new system designs optimized for specific kinds of work. Designing computer systems around the work to be done is a departure from the dominant approach of general-purpose design, in which machines are built to be capable of handling all kinds of chores and are then programmed to do specific tasks. Several companies are beginning to bring workload-optimized systems design into the mainstream of corporate and government computing. The promise, analysts say, is to not only open the door to exploiting the data flood for competitive advantage, but also to reduce energy costs and help automate the management and administration of computer systems  a labor-intensive expense that is rising four times faster than the cost of hardware. I.B.M., according to industry analysts, is at the forefront of the effort to develop more customized systems. And on Monday, the company is making the first of a series of announcements this year that embody the new approach. I.B.M. is introducing a line of big computer servers using its Power 7 32-core microprocessors. They are priced at $190,000, typically run Unix or Linux, and are aimed at industries like finance and utilities, as well as scientific researchers. Next month, I.B.M. plans to unveil far less costly server systems based on industry-standard microprocessors made by Intel. Those machines, which typically run Unix or Microsoft Windows, will be used for Web collaboration, e-mail and other applications. “These are not simply hardware products, but the result of years of work and investment at every level from the silicon up through the software,” said Rodney C. Adkins, I.B.M.’s senior vice president for systems and technology. “And the real challenge is to optimize it all, not just the hardware.” The early deployment of so-called smart utility grids points to the challenges of handling ever-vaster amounts of data. Smart electric meters can measure room temperatures and energy use hourly or at 15-minute intervals instead of the old pattern of utility service workers reading electro-mechanical meters every month or two. The goal of smart grids, which governments are starting to heavily subsidize, is to give households and businesses timely information so they can change their electricity consumption habits to reduce energy use and pollution, and save money. That involves not only collecting the data, but also analyzing and presenting it to consumers in ways that are easily understood  typically a personalized Web site graphically showing household electricity consumption and pricing. EMeter, a maker of smart-grid software in San Mateo, Calif., said that using I.B.M.’s workload-tuned P-7 systems should more than double its capacity to manage smart meters, bringing it up to 50 million. In one eMeter project, the utilities in Ontario are going to install 4.5 million smart meters by 2011. Before, meters were read once every month or two. Under the digital system, readings will be made hourly, a hundredfold increase in the data generated. “If you can’t continually measure energy use down to the granular level in homes and businesses, the smart grid doesn’t work,” said Scott Smith, director of technical solutions at eMeter. “You need a tremendous amount of computing power to do that at scale.” Computer scientists, biologists and researchers from Rice University and the Texas Medical Center have been working with I.B.M. scientists to fine-tune P-7 systems for cancer research. Genetic and protein-folding simulations require vast amounts of specialized high-speed processing and computer memory, said Kamran Khan, vice provost for information technology at Rice. I.B.M., he said, dispatched three Ph.D. biologists to work with the cancer researchers. “They really understand computational biology,” Mr. Khan said. The more bespoke approach to computer-systems design does increase the risk that customers are locked into one or two powerful companies. Indeed, the reason data-center customers long preferred the building-block approach to hardware and software was that it guaranteed competition among suppliers. But the tradeoff has been that customers had to put the hardware and software together themselves, even as computing complexity and data-handling demands surged. Many companies, it seems, are willing to accept less competition among suppliers for the convenience and cost savings from prepackaged systems. “It’s a balancing act,” said Frank Gens, chief analyst at IDC. “It does take away some choice, but also makes things a lot simpler. And that, after all, is the model that Apple used so successfully in consumer technology.”</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/30/nyregion/30hotel.html?ref=emccorporation">State Subpoenas Hotelier in Suit Against Contractor<date>Published: October 29, 2009</date><text>The state attorney general’s office served subpoenas at the home and businesses of a developer of budget hotels Wednesday afternoon as part of a widening investigation into a construction contractor who investigators say routinely underpaid hundreds of immigrant workers and imposed a three-tiered wage system based on race. The subpoenas sought business records, documents and correspondence relating to EMC Contracting, a subcontractor that the hotelier, Sam Chang, used to build at least a half-dozen hotels on the West Side of Manhattan since 2003, according to law enforcement officials who have been briefed on the case. The attorney general also demanded that Mr. Chang testify on Nov. 11 about his relationship with EMC Contracting. Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo filed a civil suit in State Supreme Court this month claiming that EMC Contracting and its owner, Michael T. Mahoney, had underpaid immigrant workers and forced them to work as many as 70 hours a week. The company also imposed a three-tiered wage rate in which white workers were paid $25 an hour, black workers about $18 and Latino employees $15, the suit says. The attorney’s general’s office declined to comment, saying the matter was part of a continuing investigation. Mr. Chang confirmed on Thursday that he had received the subpoenas seeking information regarding EMC Contracting, characterizing the company as “the concrete contractor we hired to do work four or five years ago,” although he said he knew little about the investigation. “They want to subpoena us as a witness,” Mr. Chang said. “That’s all I know about it.” The subpoenas indicate, however, that the attorney general’s investigation may determine whether action should be taken against Mr. Chang and his companies, including the Tritel Construction Group and the McSam Hotel Group, according to the law enforcement officials. Mr. Chang has earned a reputation as New York’s budget hotel king by developing an unprecedented 37 hotels in New York City, most of them budget or limited service hotels like Holiday Inn Express, Hampton Inn, Comfort Inn and Hilton Garden Inn. His focus contrasted with most New York hotel developers, who built luxury or boutique hotels in New York. Hotel analysts and investors have lauded Mr. Chang’s ability to control costs and build cheaply. He is one of the few developers who owns his own construction company. The investigation of EMC began in 2006 after a melee at a Chang construction site on West 26th Street in Chelsea between union officials and EMC foremen. The carpenters union had been protesting what they said were EMC’s low wages, poor working conditions and discriminatory practices. Union organizers, former EMC workers and investigators say that black and Latin employees were paid less than white workers, mostly Irish immigrants, and were never promoted to supervisory positions. “Sam Chang was the developer, the general contractor,” said Andres Puerta, an organizer for the New York City District Council of Carpenters. “He knew exactly what was going on. We were there for months.” Mr. Chang said he stopped using EMC after the melee and began working with union contractors. The attorney general’s office is focused on 21 different construction sites for hotels and condominiums where EMC did concrete work, about one-third of which were Chang projects. George L. Santangelo, a lawyer for Mr. Mahoney, declined comment, saying his client had not been served with the complaint, although he does have a copy of the lawsuit. “I have no comment on a lawsuit that hasn’t begun,” Mr. Santangelo said. More Articles in New York Region » A version of this article appeared in print on October 30, 2009, on page A28 of the New York edition.The state attorney general’s office served subpoenas at the home and businesses of a developer of budget hotels Wednesday afternoon as part of a widening investigation into a construction contractor who investigators say routinely underpaid hundreds of immigrant workers and imposed a three-tiered wage system based on race. The subpoenas sought business records, documents and correspondence relating to EMC Contracting, a subcontractor that the hotelier, Sam Chang, used to build at least a half-dozen hotels on the West Side of Manhattan since 2003, according to law enforcement officials who have been briefed on the case. The attorney general also demanded that Mr. Chang testify on Nov. 11 about his relationship with EMC Contracting. Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo filed a civil suit in State Supreme Court this month claiming that EMC Contracting and its owner, Michael T. Mahoney, had underpaid immigrant workers and forced them to work as many as 70 hours a week. The company also imposed a three-tiered wage rate in which white workers were paid $25 an hour, black workers about $18 and Latino employees $15, the suit says. The attorney’s general’s office declined to comment, saying the matter was part of a continuing investigation. Mr. Chang confirmed on Thursday that he had received the subpoenas seeking information regarding EMC Contracting, characterizing the company as “the concrete contractor we hired to do work four or five years ago,” although he said he knew little about the investigation. “They want to subpoena us as a witness,” Mr. Chang said. “That’s all I know about it.” The subpoenas indicate, however, that the attorney general’s investigation may determine whether action should be taken against Mr. Chang and his companies, including the Tritel Construction Group and the McSam Hotel Group, according to the law enforcement officials. Mr. Chang has earned a reputation as New York’s budget hotel king by developing an unprecedented 37 hotels in New York City, most of them budget or limited service hotels like Holiday Inn Express, Hampton Inn, Comfort Inn and Hilton Garden Inn. His focus contrasted with most New York hotel developers, who built luxury or boutique hotels in New York. Hotel analysts and investors have lauded Mr. Chang’s ability to control costs and build cheaply. He is one of the few developers who owns his own construction company. The investigation of EMC began in 2006 after a melee at a Chang construction site on West 26th Street in Chelsea between union officials and EMC foremen. The carpenters union had been protesting what they said were EMC’s low wages, poor working conditions and discriminatory practices. Union organizers, former EMC workers and investigators say that black and Latin employees were paid less than white workers, mostly Irish immigrants, and were never promoted to supervisory positions. “Sam Chang was the developer, the general contractor,” said Andres Puerta, an organizer for the New York City District Council of Carpenters. “He knew exactly what was going on. We were there for months.” Mr. Chang said he stopped using EMC after the melee and began working with union contractors. The attorney general’s office is focused on 21 different construction sites for hotels and condominiums where EMC did concrete work, about one-third of which were Chang projects. George L. Santangelo, a lawyer for Mr. Mahoney, declined comment, saying his client had not been served with the complaint, although he does have a copy of the lawsuit. “I have no comment on a lawsuit that hasn’t begun,” Mr. Santangelo said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/16/nyregion/16cheat.html?ref=emccorporation">Contractor Is Accused of Cheating Minority Workers Out of Wages<date>Published: October 15, 2009</date><text>During the city’s recent construction boom, developers could not build fast enough to meet the demand for luxury housing and hotels, contractors had more work than they could handle and many union workers made a lot of money. Skip to next paragraph Related Little Rooms, Big Profits (October 4, 2009) But according to a civil suit filed Thursday in State Supreme Court in Manhattan by the state attorney general, Andrew M. Cuomo, one contractor routinely shortchanged hundreds of immigrant workers and forced them to work as many as 70 hours a week. The contractor, Michael Mahoney, chief executive of EMC Construction, instituted a three-tiered wage rate in which Irish workers were paid $25 an hour, African-Americans about $18 and Latino employees $15, the suit says. The lawsuit is seeking $4 million in wages and overtime pay from ECM and Mr. Mahoney’s other companies as well as an end to discriminatory practices. The workers did concrete and carpentry work for ECM and other companies controlled by Mr. Mahoney at about 10 hotel and condominium sites in Manhattan, several of them owned by Sam Chang, a prolific developer who emerged in recent years as the budget hotel king of New York. “New York is supported by the hundreds of thousands of construction workers who labor tirelessly to build and maintain this city,” Mr. Cuomo said in a statement. “To deny workers the wages guaranteed by this state, or to discriminate against them based on race and ethnicity, is a gross violation of the law and a disgraceful abuse of power.” Mr. Mahoney, 42, did not return calls to his home in Pearl River, N.Y. His lawyer, George L. Santangelo, declined to comment on the case, saying, “I haven’t seen the papers yet.” Mr. Santangelo did accompany Mr. Mahoney recently when the contractor repeatedly invoked his right against self-incrimination in declining to answer questions from the attorney general’s office about the claims, according to the lawsuit. Martin Sosa, 28, said he worked for ECM for 18 months in 2005 and 2006 at four sites in Chelsea. He said he frequently worked 70 hours a week, including on Saturday and Sunday. He said his paycheck frequently bounced. Still, he would work on the 25th floor of one hotel without a safety belt, he said. “They never gave us overtime,” said Mr. Sosa, who is from Uruguay and lives in Harrison, N.J. “The Irish worked for eight hours and did a little carpentry. Not the Latinos. They did everything. The hardest part of the work.” Andres Puerta, an organizer for the New York City District Council of Carpenters union who worked with ECM employees, said the working conditions were reminiscent of those of a “sweat shop.” “There’s a problem in the construction industry in New York City,” he said. “These aren’t the only bad jobs.” The attorney general’s investigation began in 2006 after several melees broke out at three hotel construction sites on Manhattan’s West Side between union organizers and EMC officials, fights that were first reported in The Village Voice. The union had focused on what it said was exploitation of immigrant workers by unscrupulous contractors. The hotels were being developed by Mr. Chang, whose construction company, Tritel, had hired ECM. Investigators say that the attorney general’s inquiry is continuing and that they will review whether Mr. Chang and others who hired ECM played a role in the matter. More Articles in New York Region » A version of this article appeared in print on October 16, 2009, on page A22 of the New York edition.During the city’s recent construction boom, developers could not build fast enough to meet the demand for luxury housing and hotels, contractors had more work than they could handle and many union workers made a lot of money. Skip to next paragraph Related Little Rooms, Big Profits (October 4, 2009) But according to a civil suit filed Thursday in State Supreme Court in Manhattan by the state attorney general, Andrew M. Cuomo, one contractor routinely shortchanged hundreds of immigrant workers and forced them to work as many as 70 hours a week. The contractor, Michael Mahoney, chief executive of EMC Construction, instituted a three-tiered wage rate in which Irish workers were paid $25 an hour, African-Americans about $18 and Latino employees $15, the suit says. The lawsuit is seeking $4 million in wages and overtime pay from ECM and Mr. Mahoney’s other companies as well as an end to discriminatory practices. The workers did concrete and carpentry work for ECM and other companies controlled by Mr. Mahoney at about 10 hotel and condominium sites in Manhattan, several of them owned by Sam Chang, a prolific developer who emerged in recent years as the budget hotel king of New York. “New York is supported by the hundreds of thousands of construction workers who labor tirelessly to build and maintain this city,” Mr. Cuomo said in a statement. “To deny workers the wages guaranteed by this state, or to discriminate against them based on race and ethnicity, is a gross violation of the law and a disgraceful abuse of power.” Mr. Mahoney, 42, did not return calls to his home in Pearl River, N.Y. His lawyer, George L. Santangelo, declined to comment on the case, saying, “I haven’t seen the papers yet.” Mr. Santangelo did accompany Mr. Mahoney recently when the contractor repeatedly invoked his right against self-incrimination in declining to answer questions from the attorney general’s office about the claims, according to the lawsuit. Martin Sosa, 28, said he worked for ECM for 18 months in 2005 and 2006 at four sites in Chelsea. He said he frequently worked 70 hours a week, including on Saturday and Sunday. He said his paycheck frequently bounced. Still, he would work on the 25th floor of one hotel without a safety belt, he said. “They never gave us overtime,” said Mr. Sosa, who is from Uruguay and lives in Harrison, N.J. “The Irish worked for eight hours and did a little carpentry. Not the Latinos. They did everything. The hardest part of the work.” Andres Puerta, an organizer for the New York City District Council of Carpenters union who worked with ECM employees, said the working conditions were reminiscent of those of a “sweat shop.” “There’s a problem in the construction industry in New York City,” he said. “These aren’t the only bad jobs.” The attorney general’s investigation began in 2006 after several melees broke out at three hotel construction sites on Manhattan’s West Side between union organizers and EMC officials, fights that were first reported in The Village Voice. The union had focused on what it said was exploitation of immigrant workers by unscrupulous contractors. The hotels were being developed by Mr. Chang, whose construction company, Tritel, had hired ECM. Investigators say that the attorney general’s inquiry is continuing and that they will review whether Mr. Chang and others who hired ECM played a role in the matter.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/01/business/01egan.html?ref=emccorporation">Richard Egan, a Founder of EMC Storage, Is Dead at 73<date>Published: September 1, 2009</date><text>Richard J. Egan, an entrepreneur who built EMC into one of the world’s top technology companies, died Friday at his home in Boston. A former ambassador to Ireland, he was 73. Skip to next paragraph Richard J. Egan Add to Portfolio EMC Corporation Go to your Portfolio » His family said in a statement that Mr. Egan had been suffering from lung cancer and many other illnesses. The Boston police said Monday that they had received a call from his apartment reporting that someone had been shot in the head but would not confirm that the deceased was Mr. Egan. The Boston Globe, citing a police source, reported Sunday that the gunshot wound had been self-inflicted. Mr. Egan and his former college roommate, Roger Marino, founded EMC in 1979 to sell data storage systems. After a couple of false starts, the men hit on a fresh concept, changing storage from a mere component of large computers into specialized hardware. EMC was able to charge less for the storage than its competitors while adding other functions  a recipe that proved attractive. EMC became the world’s largest data storage company, reporting revenue of $14.88 billion in 2008 and employing about 40,000 people. “There aren’t a lot of companies that reach the level of EMC or redefine an industry,” said Steve Duplessie, a storage industry analyst at the Enterprise Strategy Group and an early EMC employee. “And there aren’t many self-made billionaires like Dick, either.” After Mr. Egan retired as chairman of EMC in 2001, President George W. Bush appointed him ambassador to Ireland, a post he held until 2003. Mr. Egan had been a major fund-raiser for the Republican Party and had donated parts of his fortune to the Boy Scouts of America as well as health and education organizations. His wealth was estimated at well over $1 billion. But his roots, in Dorchester, Mass., were humble, and he used them as a motivating force, friends and acquaintances said. “He had nothing,” Mr. Duplessie said. “He was a Dorchester punk growing up in a poor, immigrant family. He was maniacally driven for whatever it was he saw, and carried a lot of people with him. He’s that self-made, violent, ruthless, tenacious, brilliant type.” Mr. Egan joined the Marine Corps after high school and served during the Korean War. He received a degree in electrical engineering from Northeastern University in Boston. Afterward he worked with a team at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in developing a spacecraft guidance system for the Apollo project and took jobs at NASA, Lockheed Aircraft and Intel, where he became proficient in computer memory. He later joined Mr. Marino to tackle the data storage business in an unconventional manner, first starting an office furniture store in Massachusetts and then using the proceeds and the connections gained from that venture to nurture the fledgling EMC. “Many of their first customers were universities,” said Peter Bell, a general partner at the investment company Highland Capital Partners, who started his career at EMC. “In those days, the guy who bought office equipment often bought the computer systems too.” EMC started by undercutting companies like I.B.M. and Digital Equipment on price, but it eventually made separate data storage systems so important and sophisticated that it could charge a premium for the products. “Dick accomplished an amazing feat,” Mr. Duplessie said. “He turned data storage from an afterthought into a crucial product. And EMC still charges twice as much as I.B.M. if you want the best.” As a manager he was known for hiring highly motivated employees fresh out of college at a time when the industry leaned toward veterans in the field. Mr. Egan frequently acknowledged his Irish heritage and demonstrated a special bond with Ireland. In Cork, for example, he established a factory that benefited the local economy. He also started an engineering center in Israel to help develop the company’s products and was credited with greatly improving Israel’s technology infrastructure. Mr. Egan stepped aside as chief executive to become chairman in 1992. Michael C. Ruettgers ran the company for the next nine years as it became one of Wall Street’s best performers. Mr. Egan is survived by his wife of 52 years, Maureen; his children, John, Michael, Maureen, Christopher and Catherine; and a sister, Beverly; and 15 grandchildren. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 1, 2009, on page A27 of the New York edition.Richard J. Egan, an entrepreneur who built EMC into one of the world’s top technology companies, died Friday at his home in Boston. A former ambassador to Ireland, he was 73. Skip to next paragraph Richard J. Egan Add to Portfolio EMC Corporation Go to your Portfolio » His family said in a statement that Mr. Egan had been suffering from lung cancer and many other illnesses. The Boston police said Monday that they had received a call from his apartment reporting that someone had been shot in the head but would not confirm that the deceased was Mr. Egan. The Boston Globe, citing a police source, reported Sunday that the gunshot wound had been self-inflicted. Mr. Egan and his former college roommate, Roger Marino, founded EMC in 1979 to sell data storage systems. After a couple of false starts, the men hit on a fresh concept, changing storage from a mere component of large computers into specialized hardware. EMC was able to charge less for the storage than its competitors while adding other functions  a recipe that proved attractive. EMC became the world’s largest data storage company, reporting revenue of $14.88 billion in 2008 and employing about 40,000 people. “There aren’t a lot of companies that reach the level of EMC or redefine an industry,” said Steve Duplessie, a storage industry analyst at the Enterprise Strategy Group and an early EMC employee. “And there aren’t many self-made billionaires like Dick, either.” After Mr. Egan retired as chairman of EMC in 2001, President George W. Bush appointed him ambassador to Ireland, a post he held until 2003. Mr. Egan had been a major fund-raiser for the Republican Party and had donated parts of his fortune to the Boy Scouts of America as well as health and education organizations. His wealth was estimated at well over $1 billion. But his roots, in Dorchester, Mass., were humble, and he used them as a motivating force, friends and acquaintances said. “He had nothing,” Mr. Duplessie said. “He was a Dorchester punk growing up in a poor, immigrant family. He was maniacally driven for whatever it was he saw, and carried a lot of people with him. He’s that self-made, violent, ruthless, tenacious, brilliant type.” Mr. Egan joined the Marine Corps after high school and served during the Korean War. He received a degree in electrical engineering from Northeastern University in Boston. Afterward he worked with a team at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in developing a spacecraft guidance system for the Apollo project and took jobs at NASA, Lockheed Aircraft and Intel, where he became proficient in computer memory. He later joined Mr. Marino to tackle the data storage business in an unconventional manner, first starting an office furniture store in Massachusetts and then using the proceeds and the connections gained from that venture to nurture the fledgling EMC. “Many of their first customers were universities,” said Peter Bell, a general partner at the investment company Highland Capital Partners, who started his career at EMC. “In those days, the guy who bought office equipment often bought the computer systems too.” EMC started by undercutting companies like I.B.M. and Digital Equipment on price, but it eventually made separate data storage systems so important and sophisticated that it could charge a premium for the products. “Dick accomplished an amazing feat,” Mr. Duplessie said. “He turned data storage from an afterthought into a crucial product. And EMC still charges twice as much as I.B.M. if you want the best.” As a manager he was known for hiring highly motivated employees fresh out of college at a time when the industry leaned toward veterans in the field. Mr. Egan frequently acknowledged his Irish heritage and demonstrated a special bond with Ireland. In Cork, for example, he established a factory that benefited the local economy. He also started an engineering center in Israel to help develop the company’s products and was credited with greatly improving Israel’s technology infrastructure. Mr. Egan stepped aside as chief executive to become chairman in 1992. Michael C. Ruettgers ran the company for the next nine years as it became one of Wall Street’s best performers. Mr. Egan is survived by his wife of 52 years, Maureen; his children, John, Michael, Maureen, Christopher and Catherine; and a sister, Beverly; and 15 grandchildren.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/09/technology/companies/09data.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Wins Data Domain With a $2.4 Billion Offer<date>Published: July 8, 2009</date><text>Waving $2.4 billion in cash, EMC finally beat out NetApp, its archrival in the storage business, for the right to acquire Data Domain and its data deduplication technology. On Wednesday, NetApp dropped out of the bidding, and Data Domain’s board approved EMC’s offer. Even in the jargon-filled world of technology nomenclature, deduplication is a chunky term. Its promise, however, is straightforward enough: the technology can reduce a company’s need for costly computer storage systems by half or more. In this difficult economy, that is very appealing to customers. “There is the potential for an enormous savings in capital expenditures,” said Thomas M. Coughlin, the president of Coughlin Associates, a storage market research company. And it helps explain the bidding war over Data Domain in the midst of a nasty recession. The battle began at the end of May, when NetApp bid $25 a share for the company, using a mix of stock and cash for a $1.5 billion offer. While uninvited to the negotiations, EMC stepped in with a larger, hostile offer. NetApp countered, and EMC again raised its offer, culminating with an all-cash offer of $33.50 a share on Monday. EMC said the net price of the deal, after subtracting Data Domain’s cash on hand, was $2.1 billion. NetApp and EMC, the two largest independent storage technology companies, have deduplication products. But, in this part of the storage market, it seems that a company can never have enough of such technology, especially for corporate customers, whose volume of data grows 50 percent a year on average. Deduplication software lets companies reduce the number of backup copies they need to make of similar files. Workers will, for example, pass around a slide presentation via e-mail and make minor changes to it along the way. With deduplication, an initial copy of the file is made and stored. From that point on, only the minor changes need to be backed up every day. “It’s those huge PowerPoint attachments that are being sent around to 20 people that are the problem,” said Garth Gibson, a computer science professor at Carnegie Mellon University. Data Domain, which is based in Santa Clara, Calif., specializes in handling the large, corporatewide backups that companies make to protect their information. It uses similar techniques to reduce the amount of data that must travel between offices, as companies look to place their data in diverse locations. EMC makes its living selling storage systems, and technology that lowers the need for such products could prove troublesome. But, according to analysts, EMC will benefit from the technology by capitalizing on the continuing shift to storage systems based on spinning disks from older tape technology. Companies have long used cheap magnetic tapes to hold backup files that are kept for emergencies rather than daily use. The problem is that the tape systems are slow and cumbersome. Companies would prefer to have their information stored on faster disks so they can retrieve files quickly. The price of such disk storage systems has fallen steadily, making them more attractive for backup procedures. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., sells only disk storage systems and sees this technology disruption as a way to take business from I.B.M. and Sun Microsystems, two major tape storage companies. “The cost of disks are now low enough that you can entertain having all your backups on disk instead of tape,” Mr. Gibson said. The San Francisco Giants baseball team has used Data Domain’s technology for two years to back up its corporate files. The 150-person organization, with annual revenue of about $250 million, used to send employees home with tapes on the weekends. Now, it shuttles information between San Francisco and an operation in Arizona over the Internet, said Bill Schlough, the team’s chief information officer. “The system compresses all of our critical e-mail and file data, and sends it across the Internet on a daily basis,” he said. “It’s something we needed just in case there’s a big disaster at the ballpark.” EMC says it expects the Data Domain acquisition to close this month, and hopes to capitalize on Data Domain’s strength in selling deduplication technology to midsize companies. EMC is expected to add some sales reach and investment heft to Data Domain’s products. As for NetApp, the company intends to assess its options and decide whether to build similar technology in-house or try to make another purchase, said Tom Georgens, NetApp’s president. “I think it was a good company,” he said. “The price was just pretty hard for us to justify.” More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on July 9, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.Waving $2.4 billion in cash, EMC finally beat out NetApp, its archrival in the storage business, for the right to acquire Data Domain and its data deduplication technology. On Wednesday, NetApp dropped out of the bidding, and Data Domain’s board approved EMC’s offer. Even in the jargon-filled world of technology nomenclature, deduplication is a chunky term. Its promise, however, is straightforward enough: the technology can reduce a company’s need for costly computer storage systems by half or more. In this difficult economy, that is very appealing to customers. “There is the potential for an enormous savings in capital expenditures,” said Thomas M. Coughlin, the president of Coughlin Associates, a storage market research company. And it helps explain the bidding war over Data Domain in the midst of a nasty recession. The battle began at the end of May, when NetApp bid $25 a share for the company, using a mix of stock and cash for a $1.5 billion offer. While uninvited to the negotiations, EMC stepped in with a larger, hostile offer. NetApp countered, and EMC again raised its offer, culminating with an all-cash offer of $33.50 a share on Monday. EMC said the net price of the deal, after subtracting Data Domain’s cash on hand, was $2.1 billion. NetApp and EMC, the two largest independent storage technology companies, have deduplication products. But, in this part of the storage market, it seems that a company can never have enough of such technology, especially for corporate customers, whose volume of data grows 50 percent a year on average. Deduplication software lets companies reduce the number of backup copies they need to make of similar files. Workers will, for example, pass around a slide presentation via e-mail and make minor changes to it along the way. With deduplication, an initial copy of the file is made and stored. From that point on, only the minor changes need to be backed up every day. “It’s those huge PowerPoint attachments that are being sent around to 20 people that are the problem,” said Garth Gibson, a computer science professor at Carnegie Mellon University. Data Domain, which is based in Santa Clara, Calif., specializes in handling the large, corporatewide backups that companies make to protect their information. It uses similar techniques to reduce the amount of data that must travel between offices, as companies look to place their data in diverse locations. EMC makes its living selling storage systems, and technology that lowers the need for such products could prove troublesome. But, according to analysts, EMC will benefit from the technology by capitalizing on the continuing shift to storage systems based on spinning disks from older tape technology. Companies have long used cheap magnetic tapes to hold backup files that are kept for emergencies rather than daily use. The problem is that the tape systems are slow and cumbersome. Companies would prefer to have their information stored on faster disks so they can retrieve files quickly. The price of such disk storage systems has fallen steadily, making them more attractive for backup procedures. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., sells only disk storage systems and sees this technology disruption as a way to take business from I.B.M. and Sun Microsystems, two major tape storage companies. “The cost of disks are now low enough that you can entertain having all your backups on disk instead of tape,” Mr. Gibson said. The San Francisco Giants baseball team has used Data Domain’s technology for two years to back up its corporate files. The 150-person organization, with annual revenue of about $250 million, used to send employees home with tapes on the weekends. Now, it shuttles information between San Francisco and an operation in Arizona over the Internet, said Bill Schlough, the team’s chief information officer. “The system compresses all of our critical e-mail and file data, and sends it across the Internet on a daily basis,” he said. “It’s something we needed just in case there’s a big disaster at the ballpark.” EMC says it expects the Data Domain acquisition to close this month, and hopes to capitalize on Data Domain’s strength in selling deduplication technology to midsize companies. EMC is expected to add some sales reach and investment heft to Data Domain’s products. As for NetApp, the company intends to assess its options and decide whether to build similar technology in-house or try to make another purchase, said Tom Georgens, NetApp’s president. “I think it was a good company,” he said. “The price was just pretty hard for us to justify.”</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/07/business/07data.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Raises Its Bid for Data Domain<date>Published: July 6, 2009</date><text>Firing the latest salvo in a bidding duel, the data storage company EMC Corporation raised its offer for Data Domain, which has already accepted a lower bid from NetApp. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio EMC Corporation Data Domain Inc Go to your Portfolio » EMC’s new offer of $33.50 a share in cash, announced Monday, is $3.50 per share above its previous offer and values Data Domain at $2.1 billion. Data Domain, based in Santa Clara, Calif., has already accepted a bid of $30 a share in cash and stock from NetApp, which said Monday its board would examine its options. Data Domain makes products that cut down on the amount of storage that customers need to buy from storage companies like EMC and NetApp. NetApp, which is based in Sunnyvale, Calif., originally offered to buy Data Domain on May 20 for $25 a share in cash and stock, or $1.5 billion. EMC then offered to pay $30 per share, or $1.9 billion, in an all-cash deal; NetApp matched that price in a cash-and-stock offer and Data Domain agreed to NetApp’s new bid. EMC’s latest offer comes on the same day NetApp said it had received clearance from the Securities and Exchange Commission for the acquisition. The company also has cleared Federal Trade Commission hurdles. In announcing its revised bid, EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said the F.T.C. had granted early clearance for the deal. In response to EMC’s new offer, NetApp’s chief executive, Dan Warmenhoven said in a statement that his company’s board ”will carefully weigh its options, keeping in mind both its fiduciary duty to its stockholders and its disciplined acquisition strategy.” More Articles in Business »Firing the latest salvo in a bidding duel, the data storage company EMC Corporation raised its offer for Data Domain, which has already accepted a lower bid from NetApp. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio EMC Corporation Data Domain Inc Go to your Portfolio » EMC’s new offer of $33.50 a share in cash, announced Monday, is $3.50 per share above its previous offer and values Data Domain at $2.1 billion. Data Domain, based in Santa Clara, Calif., has already accepted a bid of $30 a share in cash and stock from NetApp, which said Monday its board would examine its options. Data Domain makes products that cut down on the amount of storage that customers need to buy from storage companies like EMC and NetApp. NetApp, which is based in Sunnyvale, Calif., originally offered to buy Data Domain on May 20 for $25 a share in cash and stock, or $1.5 billion. EMC then offered to pay $30 per share, or $1.9 billion, in an all-cash deal; NetApp matched that price in a cash-and-stock offer and Data Domain agreed to NetApp’s new bid. EMC’s latest offer comes on the same day NetApp said it had received clearance from the Securities and Exchange Commission for the acquisition. The company also has cleared Federal Trade Commission hurdles. In announcing its revised bid, EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said the F.T.C. had granted early clearance for the deal. In response to EMC’s new offer, NetApp’s chief executive, Dan Warmenhoven said in a statement that his company’s board ”will carefully weigh its options, keeping in mind both its fiduciary duty to its stockholders and its disciplined acquisition strategy.”</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/04/technology/companies/04storage.html?ref=emccorporation">NetApp Raises Its Offer for Data Domain, Matching EMC<date>Published: June 3, 2009</date><text>NetApp raised its takeover offer on Wednesday for Data Domain, a rival maker of computer storage products, to $1.9 billion, matching an unsolicited bid from the EMC Corporation. The offer, which amounts to about $30 a share, is composed of $16.45 in cash and $13.55 in NetApp stock, the company said. EMC offered $30 in cash this week, topping NetApp’s earlier $25 bid for Data Domain. Both companies are seeking technology that helps businesses reduce the disk space needed to store data. NetApp has more at stake in the bidding war, since it is smaller than EMC and could use Data Domain to grow, said Bill Choi, an analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company in New York. There are also few attractive storage acquisition targets right now, he said. Stock in NetApp, which is based in Sunnyvale, Calif., fell 77 cents, to $18.57 a share. Stock in Data Domain, based in Santa Clara, Calif., rose 96 cents, to $32.54 a share. NetApp said its offer would lead to less overlap because it did not sell as many of the same products as Data Domain. The two companies, based in neighboring towns, also are more culturally compatible, NetApp’s chief executive, Dan Warmenhoven said. “The complementary nature of the Data Domain and NetApp product lines will result in higher aggregate growth compared to the redundancies that would result with the EMC product line,” Mr. Warmenhoven said in a statement. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., did not answer messages seeking comment. Its stock fell 37 cents, to $12.48 a share. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on June 4, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.NetApp raised its takeover offer on Wednesday for Data Domain, a rival maker of computer storage products, to $1.9 billion, matching an unsolicited bid from the EMC Corporation. The offer, which amounts to about $30 a share, is composed of $16.45 in cash and $13.55 in NetApp stock, the company said. EMC offered $30 in cash this week, topping NetApp’s earlier $25 bid for Data Domain. Both companies are seeking technology that helps businesses reduce the disk space needed to store data. NetApp has more at stake in the bidding war, since it is smaller than EMC and could use Data Domain to grow, said Bill Choi, an analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company in New York. There are also few attractive storage acquisition targets right now, he said. Stock in NetApp, which is based in Sunnyvale, Calif., fell 77 cents, to $18.57 a share. Stock in Data Domain, based in Santa Clara, Calif., rose 96 cents, to $32.54 a share. NetApp said its offer would lead to less overlap because it did not sell as many of the same products as Data Domain. The two companies, based in neighboring towns, also are more culturally compatible, NetApp’s chief executive, Dan Warmenhoven said. “The complementary nature of the Data Domain and NetApp product lines will result in higher aggregate growth compared to the redundancies that would result with the EMC product line,” Mr. Warmenhoven said in a statement. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., did not answer messages seeking comment. Its stock fell 37 cents, to $12.48 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/02/technology/companies/02storage.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Tops an Offer for Data Domain<date>Published: June 1, 2009</date><text>The EMC Corporation made an unsolicited offer on Monday to acquire Data Domain for $1.8 billion in cash, topping a bid by NetApp, which agreed to buy the company for $1.5 billion two weeks ago. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: EMC Corporation NetApp’s offer is valued at $25.56 a share, based on Monday’s closing price, making EMC’s bid 17 percent higher. Data Domain, whose customers include AT&amp;T and the Defense Department, sells products that eliminate the need to store multiple copies of the same document, cutting costs. Its revenue more than doubled last year, to $274 million. Net income was $21.6 million in 2008, compared with a loss of $3.7 million a year earlier. EMC, a maker of storage computers, said it could finance the deal with cash. NetApp would have to use more stock to match the offer, said Jayson Noland, an analyst at Robert W. Baird &amp; Company in San Francisco. “I think this will be the final outcome,” Mr. Noland said. “We didn’t expect somebody to try to outbid NetApp.” The acquisition would add to EMC’s earnings next year and would not change its profit in the current year, excluding some costs, EMC’s chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, said in a conference call. Edward Luboja, a spokesman for Data Domain, which is based in Santa Clara, Calif., declined to comment. Lindsey Smith, a spokeswoman for NetApp, also declined to comment. If Data Domain accepts EMC’s offer, it will be required to give NetApp five days to match it, EMC said. The agreement between Data Domain and NetApp has a $57 million breakup fee. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on June 2, 2009, on page B11 of the New York edition.The EMC Corporation made an unsolicited offer on Monday to acquire Data Domain for $1.8 billion in cash, topping a bid by NetApp, which agreed to buy the company for $1.5 billion two weeks ago. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: EMC Corporation NetApp’s offer is valued at $25.56 a share, based on Monday’s closing price, making EMC’s bid 17 percent higher. Data Domain, whose customers include AT&amp;T and the Defense Department, sells products that eliminate the need to store multiple copies of the same document, cutting costs. Its revenue more than doubled last year, to $274 million. Net income was $21.6 million in 2008, compared with a loss of $3.7 million a year earlier. EMC, a maker of storage computers, said it could finance the deal with cash. NetApp would have to use more stock to match the offer, said Jayson Noland, an analyst at Robert W. Baird &amp; Company in San Francisco. “I think this will be the final outcome,” Mr. Noland said. “We didn’t expect somebody to try to outbid NetApp.” The acquisition would add to EMC’s earnings next year and would not change its profit in the current year, excluding some costs, EMC’s chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, said in a conference call. Edward Luboja, a spokesman for Data Domain, which is based in Santa Clara, Calif., declined to comment. Lindsey Smith, a spokeswoman for NetApp, also declined to comment. If Data Domain accepts EMC’s offer, it will be required to give NetApp five days to match it, EMC said. The agreement between Data Domain and NetApp has a $57 million breakup fee.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D91E3EF932A15757C0A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Building a One-Stop Shop<date>Published: April 21, 2009</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO -- Most consumers do not want to get a PC by purchasing microprocessors, hard drives and operating system software from different suppliers and assembling them all into a working computer. They prefer to buy a complete, customized machine from one supplier. Corporate customers increasingly want the same thing: a one-stop shop for hardware, software and services. And the largest technology companies are deploying their huge cash hoards to make acquisitions to bolster their ability to be that single provider. That trend drove Oracle, a leader in business software, to announce Monday that it was spending $7.4 billion to buy an ailing Sun Microsystems and get into the computer hardware business. Oracle beat out rival I.B.M., which considered buying Sun to enhance its own software offerings but ended serious acquisition talks about two weeks ago. ''Oracle will be the only company that can engineer an integrated system -- applications to disk -- where all the pieces fit and work together so customers do not have to do it themselves,'' Oracle's chief executive, Lawrence J. Ellison, said Monday. The drive to consolidate has made life difficult for independent companies like Sun, and the fall of such an industry stalwart highlights the mounting pressure on smaller firms in the computer, storage and software industries to find buyers. Even larger companies like EMC and Dell could be vulnerable, industry observers say. ''I believe that we are in the fifth inning of a nine-inning consolidation game,'' said William T. Coleman III, a former Sun executive and co-founder of BEA Systems, who is now chief of the software start-up Cassatt. ''It's not over by any stretch of the imagination, and there are drastic things that still have to happen.'' Five years ago, Oracle bought PeopleSoft for more than $10 billion, igniting a furious rush to scoop up other business software makers. Oracle alone has since bought more than 40 other companies, spending close to $15 billion for BEA and Siebel Systems alone. Many of the companies purchased by Oracle had carved out a niche for themselves during the Internet build-out, providing unique functions that assisted a rapid infrastructure expansion. In the years after the dot-com bust, however, customers grew weary of visits from hordes of software salesmen peddling isolated wares. A simpler model evolved, in which a handful of companies like Oracle, I.B.M. and Hewlett-Packard bought dozens of smaller players and then competed to sell most of the software needed to run a modern business. ''The core just keeps getting denser and denser,'' said Randall N. Spratt, the chief information officer at McKesson, one of the nation's largest health care companies. ''We welcome large-scale players at the core.'' While software companies led the last round of consolidation, the hardware industry now appears poised for its own reshaping. ''I think we're at an inflection point,'' said Patricia C. Sueltz, a former I.B.M. and Sun executive, who runs the start-up LogLogic. For example, Rackable Systems, a smaller server computer maker, announced plans this month to buy Silicon Graphics for $25 million. Like Sun, Silicon Graphics started in 1982, and had been one of the fastest-growing businesses in America during its heyday, selling billions of dollars of computers a year. As the computer business has matured, companies that handcraft products for top performance face a harsh reality: Standard equipment can now handle most business tasks, and what matters most to customers now is large scale -- and the low prices that come with it. Over the last decade, H.P. has driven much of the consolidation through a series of large acquisitions. It bought Compaq Computer in 2001, which affected both the PC and server markets as other companies fought to expand and match H.P.'s reach. For example, the Chinese computer maker Lenovo bought I.B.M.'s PC business, and Acer, based in Taiwan, acquired Gateway, which had already acquired eMachines.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/28/technology/companies/28emc.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Profit Down 45% in Quarter<date>Published: January 27, 2009</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the data storage company, said Tuesday that its fourth-quarter profit fell 45 percent as one-time expenses weighed on its results. Excluding charges, the company’s results beat Wall Street estimates, but EMC said it would issue no financial guidance. EMC said its earnings for the quarter ended Dec. 31 fell to $288 million, or 14 cents a share, from $525.7 million, or 24 cents a share, a year ago. Revenue rose to $4.02 billion, from $3.83 billion a year ago. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on January 28, 2009, on page B8 of the New York edition.The EMC Corporation, the data storage company, said Tuesday that its fourth-quarter profit fell 45 percent as one-time expenses weighed on its results. Excluding charges, the company’s results beat Wall Street estimates, but EMC said it would issue no financial guidance. EMC said its earnings for the quarter ended Dec. 31 fell to $288 million, or 14 cents a share, from $525.7 million, or 24 cents a share, a year ago. Revenue rose to $4.02 billion, from $3.83 billion a year ago.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/10/business/10bear.html?ref=emccorporation">Bear to Pay $28 Million to Settle Loan Complaint<date>Published: September 9, 2008</date><text>The Bear Stearns Companies and its mortgage servicing unit agreed to pay $28 million to settle federal charges it had deceived subprime borrowers and had engaged in abusive loan practices before the investment bank’s collapse. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Bear Stearns Companies Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » The Federal Trade Commission said that Bear Stearns, acquired May 30 by JPMorgan Chase in a bailout orchestrated by the Federal Reserve, and its EMC Mortgage Corporation unit had violated consumer lending laws. The companies imposed unauthorized charges such as fees for late payments, property inspections and loan modifications, the commission said. The companies are also accused of misrepresenting to borrowers what they owed on mortgages. Many of the loans acquired by Bear Stearns and EMC were subprime mortgages, including interest-only loans, and some were made with little or no documentation of the borrowers’ income, the F.T.C. said. As of last September, EMC serviced more than 475,000 mortgage loans that had an unpaid balance of $80 billion, the agency said. The commission said the practices had occurred before JPMorgan acquired Bear Stearns for $2.3 billion. Bear Stearns, once the fifth largest securities firm in the nation, was forced to sell after its collapse during the credit crisis. A JPMorgan spokesman, Joseph Evangelisti, declined to comment on the settlement. The $28 million payment will help consumers who were injured by the illegal conduct, the F.T.C. said. The company also agreed to obey all relevant laws, including the Truth in Lending Act. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 10, 2008, on page C4 of the New York edition.The Bear Stearns Companies and its mortgage servicing unit agreed to pay $28 million to settle federal charges it had deceived subprime borrowers and had engaged in abusive loan practices before the investment bank’s collapse. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Bear Stearns Companies Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » The Federal Trade Commission said that Bear Stearns, acquired May 30 by JPMorgan Chase in a bailout orchestrated by the Federal Reserve, and its EMC Mortgage Corporation unit had violated consumer lending laws. The companies imposed unauthorized charges such as fees for late payments, property inspections and loan modifications, the commission said. The companies are also accused of misrepresenting to borrowers what they owed on mortgages. Many of the loans acquired by Bear Stearns and EMC were subprime mortgages, including interest-only loans, and some were made with little or no documentation of the borrowers’ income, the F.T.C. said. As of last September, EMC serviced more than 475,000 mortgage loans that had an unpaid balance of $80 billion, the agency said. The commission said the practices had occurred before JPMorgan acquired Bear Stearns for $2.3 billion. Bear Stearns, once the fifth largest securities firm in the nation, was forced to sell after its collapse during the credit crisis. A JPMorgan spokesman, Joseph Evangelisti, declined to comment on the settlement. The $28 million payment will help consumers who were injured by the illegal conduct, the F.T.C. said. The company also agreed to obey all relevant laws, including the Truth in Lending Act.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DD133BF93BA3575AC0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">BITS; Sun Takes Aim At Storage Market<date>Published: September 8, 2008</date><text>Sun Takes Aim At Storage Market Sun Microsystems has spent years trying to recover from a major shift in the server landscape. Sun thinks it now has a chance to disrupt a different part of the hardware business and make life tough on rivals. In November, it plans to release storage hardware and software that take aim at a part of the storage market dominated by NetApp and EMC. Storage systems no longer need as many specialized components, says Mike Shapiro, a Sun engineer. The mainstream processors produced by Intel and Advanced Micro Devices have improved to the point where they can churn through storage operations rather than hand the work off to specialized hardware. In addition, the difference between how long an expensive disk lasts compared with a cheap disk has dwindled, making cheaper disks more attractive. And Ethernet networking technology continues to gain on the costlier, faster technology used for top storage systems. Thus, a hardware vendor can build a relatively inexpensive storage system that will satisfy a broad set of customers. In November, Sun is set to show off new storage gear that has been part of a project code-named FISHworks (FISH stands for fully integrated software and hardware). A small group of Sun's top software engineers has spent months creating the layer of programming code that will feed these new systems. The software, which Sun has crowed about for more than a year, is months late and still largely secret, so it is difficult to say how much Sun has accomplished. But Sun is looking to undercut the competition on price by including the software as part of these new systems rather than charging a lofty premium, as often happens in the storage industry. ASHLEE VANCE</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/09/technology/09vmware.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Replaces the Chief and Co-Founder of VMware, Silencing Talk of a Spinoff<date>Published: July 9, 2008</date><text>For the last month, several reports from Wall Street analysts have debated whether EMC, the big computer storage company, would sell off its 85 percent stake in its crown jewel, VMware, a fast-growing software star. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Left, Brendan McDermid/Reuters Diane Greene, the chief executive of VMware, a business software maker, was replaced by Paul Maritz, an ex-Microsoft executive. EMC seems to have given its answer with a dramatic gesture on Tuesday. It fired VMware’s chief executive and co-founder, Diane Greene. She is being replaced by Paul Maritz, a former senior executive at Microsoft who joined EMC this year when it bought his Web start-up. Ms. Greene was fired after she refused to resign or take another position at VMware, according to a VMware manager who asked not to be named because he was not authorized to speak publicly. The point of conflict, the person said, was that Ms. Greene had been pushing hard for VMware to be spun off early next year. After five years of ownership, a subsidiary can be sold off in an essentially tax-free transaction. EMC bought VMware for $635 million in cash in December 2003. A spinoff was the preferred option on Wall Street, where some analysts suggested that EMC might be pressured by shareholders to do so. In a report last month, A. M. Sacconaghi, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein, wrote: “We believe an activist shareholder could pressure EMC management to completely spin off VMware.” After the announcement that Ms. Greene had been ousted, VMware shares fell 24 percent to $40.19, down $13. EMC shares dropped nearly 12 percent on the news, or $1.75, closing at $13.39. In addition to the management change, the VMware statement also said that it expected the company’s revenue growth for 2008 to be “modestly below” its previous guidance of 50 percent  perhaps an indication, some analysts said, that VMware was slipping in its execution. In an interview, Joseph M. Tucci, EMC’s chief executive, said EMC had “no plan to change the relationship with VMware.” Mr. Tucci, who is also chairman of VMware’s board, said VMware would continue to operate independently from EMC, with its own sales force, for example. Mr. Tucci said that the issue of spinning off VMware had “nothing to do” with Ms. Greene’s being replaced. Ms. Greene could not be reached for comment. Mr. Tucci praised Mr. Maritz as an executive with the background and skills needed to “lead VMware to its next stage of growth and development.” Last year, VMware’s revenue increased 88 percent to $1.33 billion, while its profit more than doubled to $218 million. In his 14 years at Microsoft, Mr. Maritz led product development and marketing groups including Windows, rising into the upper tier of management. When he left in 2000, Mr. Maritz was effectively the No. 3 executive at Microsoft, behind Bill Gates and Steven A. Ballmer. In an interview, Mr. Martiz called VMware a company with “great fundamentals” in terms of its products, technology and people. Yet as a company that now has more than 5,000 employees and is growing rapidly, management, he said, could benefit from the “the experience that comes from having seen this movie before,” as he did during Microsoft’s high-growth years. VMware, based in Palo Alto, Calif., is the clear leader in so-called virtual machine software that allows a computer to run different operating systems, or several versions of the same operating system, at the same time. In corporate data centers, this means more chores can be juggled on fewer computers, reducing spending on hardware, electricity and maintenance. Microsoft’s Windows and the open-source operating system Linux run on VMware’s virtual machine software. Microsoft last month introduced its own virtual machine software, and it will fold it into future versions of its Windows server software, as it did on the desktop by bundling Internet browsing software into Windows. VMware, according to industry analysts, is facing the challenge of moving successfully beyond its pioneering entrepreneurial stage. “One way or another, they were going to bring in new management,” said Thomas Bittman, an analyst for Gartner, a market research firm. “But I am surprised Diane Greene left, instead of putting people under her or around her.” With the sharp drop in VMware’s stock price, the financial appeal of a spinoff is more “muted,” according to Mr. Sacconaghi of Bernstein. Before the drop, VMware’s market capitalization was about $20 billion, but at the market close on Tuesday the company’s value had dropped by nearly $5 billion. More Articles in Technology »For the last month, several reports from Wall Street analysts have debated whether EMC, the big computer storage company, would sell off its 85 percent stake in its crown jewel, VMware, a fast-growing software star. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Left, Brendan McDermid/Reuters Diane Greene, the chief executive of VMware, a business software maker, was replaced by Paul Maritz, an ex-Microsoft executive. EMC seems to have given its answer with a dramatic gesture on Tuesday. It fired VMware’s chief executive and co-founder, Diane Greene. She is being replaced by Paul Maritz, a former senior executive at Microsoft who joined EMC this year when it bought his Web start-up. Ms. Greene was fired after she refused to resign or take another position at VMware, according to a VMware manager who asked not to be named because he was not authorized to speak publicly. The point of conflict, the person said, was that Ms. Greene had been pushing hard for VMware to be spun off early next year. After five years of ownership, a subsidiary can be sold off in an essentially tax-free transaction. EMC bought VMware for $635 million in cash in December 2003. A spinoff was the preferred option on Wall Street, where some analysts suggested that EMC might be pressured by shareholders to do so. In a report last month, A. M. Sacconaghi, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein, wrote: “We believe an activist shareholder could pressure EMC management to completely spin off VMware.” After the announcement that Ms. Greene had been ousted, VMware shares fell 24 percent to $40.19, down $13. EMC shares dropped nearly 12 percent on the news, or $1.75, closing at $13.39. In addition to the management change, the VMware statement also said that it expected the company’s revenue growth for 2008 to be “modestly below” its previous guidance of 50 percent  perhaps an indication, some analysts said, that VMware was slipping in its execution. In an interview, Joseph M. Tucci, EMC’s chief executive, said EMC had “no plan to change the relationship with VMware.” Mr. Tucci, who is also chairman of VMware’s board, said VMware would continue to operate independently from EMC, with its own sales force, for example. Mr. Tucci said that the issue of spinning off VMware had “nothing to do” with Ms. Greene’s being replaced. Ms. Greene could not be reached for comment. Mr. Tucci praised Mr. Maritz as an executive with the background and skills needed to “lead VMware to its next stage of growth and development.” Last year, VMware’s revenue increased 88 percent to $1.33 billion, while its profit more than doubled to $218 million. In his 14 years at Microsoft, Mr. Maritz led product development and marketing groups including Windows, rising into the upper tier of management. When he left in 2000, Mr. Maritz was effectively the No. 3 executive at Microsoft, behind Bill Gates and Steven A. Ballmer. In an interview, Mr. Martiz called VMware a company with “great fundamentals” in terms of its products, technology and people. Yet as a company that now has more than 5,000 employees and is growing rapidly, management, he said, could benefit from the “the experience that comes from having seen this movie before,” as he did during Microsoft’s high-growth years. VMware, based in Palo Alto, Calif., is the clear leader in so-called virtual machine software that allows a computer to run different operating systems, or several versions of the same operating system, at the same time. In corporate data centers, this means more chores can be juggled on fewer computers, reducing spending on hardware, electricity and maintenance. Microsoft’s Windows and the open-source operating system Linux run on VMware’s virtual machine software. Microsoft last month introduced its own virtual machine software, and it will fold it into future versions of its Windows server software, as it did on the desktop by bundling Internet browsing software into Windows. VMware, according to industry analysts, is facing the challenge of moving successfully beyond its pioneering entrepreneurial stage. “One way or another, they were going to bring in new management,” said Thomas Bittman, an analyst for Gartner, a market research firm. “But I am surprised Diane Greene left, instead of putting people under her or around her.” With the sharp drop in VMware’s stock price, the financial appeal of a spinoff is more “muted,” according to Mr. Sacconaghi of Bernstein. Before the drop, VMware’s market capitalization was about $20 billion, but at the market close on Tuesday the company’s value had dropped by nearly $5 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/24/technology/24emc.html?ref=emccorporation">Maker of Data Storage Gear Posts Strong Revenue Growth<date>Published: April 24, 2008</date><text>BOSTON (Reuters)  The EMC Corporation, the top maker of corporate data storage equipment, reported strong revenue growth in both overseas and American markets on Wednesday, despite concerns over corporate spending in a weakened United States economy. The company reiterated full-year financial targets that it issued in January, and its shares rose. EMC executives also dismissed speculation that the company would spin off its majority stake in VMware, a rapidly growing maker of business software, early next year. EMC’s first-quarter revenue climbed 17 percent, to $3.47 billion, gaining across geographic regions and all major product areas despite fears of a pullback in technology spending. Sales in North America rose 14 percent from a year earlier, while overseas revenue grew 21 percent. Net income fell as the company took charges for acquisitions and other costs, dropping to $268.8 million, or 13 cents a share, from $312.6 million, or 15 cents, a year earlier. Profit excluding a charge for research and development was 16 cents a share in the latest quarter, or 23 cents a share before other one-time items. More Articles in Technology »BOSTON (Reuters)  The EMC Corporation, the top maker of corporate data storage equipment, reported strong revenue growth in both overseas and American markets on Wednesday, despite concerns over corporate spending in a weakened United States economy. The company reiterated full-year financial targets that it issued in January, and its shares rose. EMC executives also dismissed speculation that the company would spin off its majority stake in VMware, a rapidly growing maker of business software, early next year. EMC’s first-quarter revenue climbed 17 percent, to $3.47 billion, gaining across geographic regions and all major product areas despite fears of a pullback in technology spending. Sales in North America rose 14 percent from a year earlier, while overseas revenue grew 21 percent. Net income fell as the company took charges for acquisitions and other costs, dropping to $268.8 million, or 13 cents a share, from $312.6 million, or 15 cents, a year earlier. Profit excluding a charge for research and development was 16 cents a share in the latest quarter, or 23 cents a share before other one-time items.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/09/technology/09iomega.html?ref=emccorporation">Iomega Accepts Takeover Offer<date>Published: April 9, 2008</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO (Reuters)  The Iomega Corporation said Tuesday that it had accepted an increased cash takeover offer of $213 million from the EMC Corporation and would drop a plan to buy a unit of the Great Wall Technology Company of China. The deal allows EMC, the world’s largest data-storage provider, to expand in the consumer and small-business markets. EMC will pay $3.85 for each Iomega share, 6 percent more than Iomega’s closing price on Tuesday of $3.64 and above an EMC offer in March of $3.75. Stock in Iomega, which is based in San Diego, rose 4.4 percent, to $3.80 a share, in extended trade after the announcement. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., fell 6 cents, to $14.84, in regular trading. Iomega rejected EMC’s initial offer and then began talks when EMC raised its bid to $3.75 a share, or $205.5 million, in March. Iomega reached a deal in December to buy ExcelStor, a unit of Great Wall Technology, in a stock swap valued at the time at $306 million. Iomega said Tuesday that it paid $7.5 million to terminate the ExcelStor deal. More Articles in Technology »SAN FRANCISCO (Reuters)  The Iomega Corporation said Tuesday that it had accepted an increased cash takeover offer of $213 million from the EMC Corporation and would drop a plan to buy a unit of the Great Wall Technology Company of China. The deal allows EMC, the world’s largest data-storage provider, to expand in the consumer and small-business markets. EMC will pay $3.85 for each Iomega share, 6 percent more than Iomega’s closing price on Tuesday of $3.64 and above an EMC offer in March of $3.75. Stock in Iomega, which is based in San Diego, rose 4.4 percent, to $3.80 a share, in extended trade after the announcement. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., fell 6 cents, to $14.84, in regular trading. Iomega rejected EMC’s initial offer and then began talks when EMC raised its bid to $3.75 a share, or $205.5 million, in March. Iomega reached a deal in December to buy ExcelStor, a unit of Great Wall Technology, in a stock swap valued at the time at $306 million. Iomega said Tuesday that it paid $7.5 million to terminate the ExcelStor deal.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/16/business/16gret.html?ref=emccorporation">Rescue Me: A Fed Bailout Crosses a Line<date>Published: March 16, 2008</date><text>WHAT are the consequences of a world in which regulators rescue even the financial institutions whose recklessness and greed helped create the titanic credit mess we are in? Will the consequences be an even weaker currency, rampant inflation, a continuation of the slow bleed that we have witnessed at banks and brokerage firms for the past year? Skip to next paragraph Related Run on Big Wall St. Bank Spurs Rescue Backed by U.S. (March 15, 2008) Times Topics: Gretchen Morgenson Blogrunner: Reactions From Around the Web Or all of the above? Stick around, because we’ll soon find out. And it’s not going to be pretty. Agreeing to guarantee a 28-day credit line to Bear Stearns, by way of JPMorgan Chase, the Federal Reserve Bank of New York conceded last Friday that no sizable firm with a book of mortgage securities or loans out to mortgage issuers could be allowed to fail right now. It was the most explicit sign yet of the Fed’s “Rescues ‘R’ Us” doctrine that already helped to force the marriage of Bank of America and Countrywide. But why save Bear Stearns? The beneficiary of this bailout, remember, has often operated in the gray areas of Wall Street and with an aggressive, brass-knuckles approach. Until regulators came along in 1996, Bear Stearns was happy to provide its balance sheet and imprimatur to bucket-shop brokerages like Stratton Oakmont and A. R. Baron, clearing dubious stock trades. And as one of the biggest players in the mortgage securities business on Wall Street, Bear provided munificent lines of credit to public-spirited subprime lenders like New Century (now bankrupt). It is also the owner of EMC Mortgage Corporation, one of the most aggressive subprime mortgage servicers out there. Bear’s default rates on so-called Alt-A mortgages that it underwrote also indicates that its lending practices were especially lax during the real estate boom. As of February, according to Bloomberg data, 15 percent of these loans in its underwritten securities were delinquent by more than 60 days or in foreclosure. That compares with an industry average of 8.4 percent. Let’s not forget that Bear Stearns lost billions for its clients last summer, when two hedge funds investing heavily in mortgage securities collapsed. And the firm tried to dump toxic mortgage securities it held in its own vaults onto the public last summer in an initial public offering of a financial company called Everquest Financial. Thankfully, that deal never got done. Recall, too, that back in 1998, when the Long Term Capital Management hedge fund required a Fed-arranged bailout, Bear Stearns refused to join the rescue effort. Jimmy Cayne, then chief executive at the firm, told the Fed to take a hike. And so, Bear Stearns, a firm that some say is this decade’s version of Drexel Burnham Lambert, the anything-goes, 1980s junk-bond shop dominated by Michael Milken, is rescued. Almost two decades ago, Drexel was left to die. Bear Stearns and Drexel have a lot in common. And yet their differing outcomes offer proof that we are in a very different and scarier place than in the late 1980s. “Why not set an example of Bear Stearns, the guys who have this record of dog-eat-dog, we’re brass knuckles, we’re tough?” asked William A. Fleckenstein, president of Fleckenstein Capital in Issaquah, Wash., and co-author with Fred Sheehan of “Greenspan’s Bubbles: The Age of Ignorance at the Federal Reserve.” “This is the perfect time to set an example, but they are not interested in setting an example. We are Bailout Nation.” And so we are. After years of never allowing any of our financial institutions to fail, they have become so enormous that nobody will be allowed to sink beneath the waves. Otherwise, a tsunami would swamp the hedge funds, banks and other brokerage firms that remain afloat. If Bear Stearns failed, for example, it would result in a wholesale dumping of mortgage securities and other assets onto a market that is frozen and where buyers are in hiding. This fire sale would force surviving institutions carrying the same types of securities on their books to mark down their positions, generating more margin calls and creating more failures. As of last Nov. 30, Bear Stearns had on its books approximately $46 billion of mortgages, mortgage-backed and asset-backed securities. Jettisoning such a portfolio onto a mortgage market that is not operative would, it is plain to see, be a disaster. But, who knows what those mortgages are really worth? According to Bear Stearns’s annual report, $29 billion of them were valued using computer models “derived from” or “supported by” some kind of observable market data. The value of the remaining $17 billion is an estimate based on “internally developed models or methodologies utilizing significant inputs that are generally less readily observable.” In other words, your guess is as good as mine. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »WHAT are the consequences of a world in which regulators rescue even the financial institutions whose recklessness and greed helped create the titanic credit mess we are in? Will the consequences be an even weaker currency, rampant inflation, a continuation of the slow bleed that we have witnessed at banks and brokerage firms for the past year? Skip to next paragraph Related Run on Big Wall St. Bank Spurs Rescue Backed by U.S. (March 15, 2008) Times Topics: Gretchen Morgenson Blogrunner: Reactions From Around the Web Or all of the above? Stick around, because we’ll soon find out. And it’s not going to be pretty. Agreeing to guarantee a 28-day credit line to Bear Stearns, by way of JPMorgan Chase, the Federal Reserve Bank of New York conceded last Friday that no sizable firm with a book of mortgage securities or loans out to mortgage issuers could be allowed to fail right now. It was the most explicit sign yet of the Fed’s “Rescues ‘R’ Us” doctrine that already helped to force the marriage of Bank of America and Countrywide. But why save Bear Stearns? The beneficiary of this bailout, remember, has often operated in the gray areas of Wall Street and with an aggressive, brass-knuckles approach. Until regulators came along in 1996, Bear Stearns was happy to provide its balance sheet and imprimatur to bucket-shop brokerages like Stratton Oakmont and A. R. Baron, clearing dubious stock trades. And as one of the biggest players in the mortgage securities business on Wall Street, Bear provided munificent lines of credit to public-spirited subprime lenders like New Century (now bankrupt). It is also the owner of EMC Mortgage Corporation, one of the most aggressive subprime mortgage servicers out there. Bear’s default rates on so-called Alt-A mortgages that it underwrote also indicates that its lending practices were especially lax during the real estate boom. As of February, according to Bloomberg data, 15 percent of these loans in its underwritten securities were delinquent by more than 60 days or in foreclosure. That compares with an industry average of 8.4 percent. Let’s not forget that Bear Stearns lost billions for its clients last summer, when two hedge funds investing heavily in mortgage securities collapsed. And the firm tried to dump toxic mortgage securities it held in its own vaults onto the public last summer in an initial public offering of a financial company called Everquest Financial. Thankfully, that deal never got done. Recall, too, that back in 1998, when the Long Term Capital Management hedge fund required a Fed-arranged bailout, Bear Stearns refused to join the rescue effort. Jimmy Cayne, then chief executive at the firm, told the Fed to take a hike. And so, Bear Stearns, a firm that some say is this decade’s version of Drexel Burnham Lambert, the anything-goes, 1980s junk-bond shop dominated by Michael Milken, is rescued. Almost two decades ago, Drexel was left to die. Bear Stearns and Drexel have a lot in common. And yet their differing outcomes offer proof that we are in a very different and scarier place than in the late 1980s. “Why not set an example of Bear Stearns, the guys who have this record of dog-eat-dog, we’re brass knuckles, we’re tough?” asked William A. Fleckenstein, president of Fleckenstein Capital in Issaquah, Wash., and co-author with Fred Sheehan of “Greenspan’s Bubbles: The Age of Ignorance at the Federal Reserve.” “This is the perfect time to set an example, but they are not interested in setting an example. We are Bailout Nation.” And so we are. After years of never allowing any of our financial institutions to fail, they have become so enormous that nobody will be allowed to sink beneath the waves. Otherwise, a tsunami would swamp the hedge funds, banks and other brokerage firms that remain afloat. If Bear Stearns failed, for example, it would result in a wholesale dumping of mortgage securities and other assets onto a market that is frozen and where buyers are in hiding. This fire sale would force surviving institutions carrying the same types of securities on their books to mark down their positions, generating more margin calls and creating more failures. As of last Nov. 30, Bear Stearns had on its books approximately $46 billion of mortgages, mortgage-backed and asset-backed securities. Jettisoning such a portfolio onto a mortgage market that is not operative would, it is plain to see, be a disaster. But, who knows what those mortgages are really worth? According to Bear Stearns’s annual report, $29 billion of them were valued using computer models “derived from” or “supported by” some kind of observable market data. The value of the remaining $17 billion is an estimate based on “internally developed models or methodologies utilizing significant inputs that are generally less readily observable.” In other words, your guess is as good as mine. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D7173CF936A15751C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">BITS; Cloud Computing and EMC Deal<date>Published: February 25, 2008</date><text>Cloud Computing And EMC Deal The EMC Corporation, a computer storage company, bought a Seattle start-up company on Thursday for an undisclosed price. It was small, but the deal and the forces behind it are intriguing. The founder of the start-up, the Pi Corporation, is Paul Maritz. Mr. Maritz worked for Microsoft for 14 years and became one of its top executives. When he left in 2000, he was immensely wealthy, and, it seemed, engaged in pursuits far from the corporate grind. Mr. Maritz supports rural development and education projects in Africa. Last fall, he became chairman of the board of the Grameen Foundation, a nonprofit organization that nurtures microfinance lending in the developing world. He is getting back into the game of big-time corporate technology competition as president of EMC's new Cloud Infrastructure and Services Division. The ''cloud'' here is the Web-based style of computing in which information resides in big data centers and users tap into it from any device, be it a personal computer or a cellphone. Google is the cloud computing leader, and Microsoft is desperately trying to catch it. Which, to belabor the obvious, is what Microsoft's bid for Yahoo is all about. Mr. Maritz would not say precisely what Pi would offer or when. He did say that EMC's chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, has a vision for cloud computing that resonates with him and with what Pi is doing. ''Joe believes that the cloud will exist outside the corporate environment, and that the architectures and styles of computing inside the corporation will increasingly be influenced by what is happening in the cloud outside the corporation,'' Mr. Maritz said. So to be a big cloud player, you have to have a consumer offering. Presumably, that is what Pi intends to become. ''A lot of people are looking for capabilities in cloud computing to come from places other than Google and Microsoft,'' Mr. Maritz said. ''They are looking for alternatives beyond those two companies.'' STEVE LOHR PHOTO: Joseph M. Tucci is chief executive of the EMC Corporation. (PHOTOGRAPH BY DAVID PAUL MOSSRIS/GETTY IMAGES)</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/30/technology/30emc.html?ref=emccorporation">VMware’s Troubles Hobble Its Parent<date>Published: January 30, 2008</date><text>BOSTON (Reuters)  The EMC Corporation, the maker of corporate data storage equipment, forecast better-than-expected 2008 revenue, but its shares fell after the VMware unit missed growth estimates. Shares of EMC fell $1.02, to $15.89, a day after the software maker VMware gave a disappointing earnings report and outlook. VMware’s news dwarfed EMC’s fourth-quarter results and its forecast for 2008 revenue of $15 billion, which was above the average Wall Street projection of $14.7 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. Shares of VMware plunged after the company on Monday reported quarterly revenue below analysts’ expectations and forecast slower sales growth. Its shares fell 28.1 percent Tuesday, to $54.87. More Articles in Technology »BOSTON (Reuters)  The EMC Corporation, the maker of corporate data storage equipment, forecast better-than-expected 2008 revenue, but its shares fell after the VMware unit missed growth estimates. Shares of EMC fell $1.02, to $15.89, a day after the software maker VMware gave a disappointing earnings report and outlook. VMware’s news dwarfed EMC’s fourth-quarter results and its forecast for 2008 revenue of $15 billion, which was above the average Wall Street projection of $14.7 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. Shares of VMware plunged after the company on Monday reported quarterly revenue below analysts’ expectations and forecast slower sales growth. Its shares fell 28.1 percent Tuesday, to $54.87.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/25/technology/25emc.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Profit Up 20%; Forecast Disappoints<date>Published: July 25, 2007</date><text>The EMC Corporation posted a 20 percent rise in quarterly profit yesterday on higher sales of data storage equipment, but its full-year forecast disappointed investors. The stock of EMC, the world’s No. 1 maker of corporate data storage equipment, climbed 27 percent over three months on expectations for strong earnings growth and optimism about the outcome of the coming initial public offering of its VMware software business. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said second-quarter net income rose to $334 million, or 16 cents a share, from $279 million, or 12 cents a share, a year earlier. Quarterly revenue rose 21 percent, to $3.12 billion. The results beat the average analyst estimate by a penny, according to Reuters Estimates. But EMC’s full-year profit forecast fell short of the average Wall Street forecast. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »The EMC Corporation posted a 20 percent rise in quarterly profit yesterday on higher sales of data storage equipment, but its full-year forecast disappointed investors. The stock of EMC, the world’s No. 1 maker of corporate data storage equipment, climbed 27 percent over three months on expectations for strong earnings growth and optimism about the outcome of the coming initial public offering of its VMware software business. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said second-quarter net income rose to $334 million, or 16 cents a share, from $279 million, or 12 cents a share, a year earlier. Quarterly revenue rose 21 percent, to $3.12 billion. The results beat the average analyst estimate by a penny, according to Reuters Estimates. But EMC’s full-year profit forecast fell short of the average Wall Street forecast.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/business/yourmoney/06boss.html?ref=emccorporation">Lessons From the Diamond<date>Published: May 6, 2007</date><text>IM a pretty good baseball player and a really terrible guitarist. What Ive learned from baseball has had a great impact on the kind of manager Ive become, but it was the guitar that landed me my first technical job. Skip to next paragraph Jason Grow Joseph M. Tucci Chief executive, EMC Corporation BIRTH DATE Aug. 13, 1947 HOME Nashua, N.H. FAVORITE TEAM The Yankees, of course. "I may live 40 minutes from Boston, but my roots are in New York." FAVORITE TV SHOW "24." "I usually solve mysteries right away, but this one has so many twists and turns, I just cant. Jack Bauer is my hero." Podcast Weekend Business This week: The shake-up at JetBlue, and Rupert Murdoch's corporate kingdom. How to Subscribe This Weeks Podcast (mp3) We lived in Brooklyn when I was a kid, but I spent a lot of time visiting my grandparents in the Bronx. They lived on Webb Avenue, right off the Grand Concourse, so close to Yankee Stadium that I could hear the crowd when someone hit a home run. My grandfather was the worlds most avid baseball fan, and hed take me to games all the time. When I was about 10, my family moved to Delmar, just outside Albany, and of course I signed up with a Little League team. Sometimes I played third base, but my favorite position was catcher. The catcher gets to see the whole game play out in front of him, and he gets to send the signals, to call the shots. Like lots of kids, I wanted to be a professional ball player. I drove my mom crazy  Id be tossing a ball up and down when I was watching TV, or Id be hitting pink Spaldeens against her walls. But Id promised my dad, who died when I was 16, that I would go to college. So I went to Manhattan College and studied marketing and accounting. When I was about 20, I fractured my leg on a ski slope, but even that didnt drive professional baseball entirely from my mind. My younger brother, meanwhile, was a brilliant guitarist, and he taught me to play. I was never any good, but hed let me sit in with his band once in a while. I took a job on Wall Street when I graduated in 1969, hoping theyd put me in a training program of some kind. But they relegated me to back-office chores, and I was bored. I left a few months later and found a couple of semi-pro leagues to play in. It was only then that I realized how much mobility Id lost to that skiing accident, and gave up the idea of a baseball career for good. I drove a van for the Teamsters for a while, even worked some as a lifeguard. But Id gotten married, and it was time to get serious. So I applied for a job at what was then the computer division of RCA. The interviewer asked if I played a musical instrument, and I said yes. He said that people with a musical mind usually make for good systems engineers, and he hired me. I guess Im lucky that he never asked me if I played it well. Id always thought of myself as a sales and marketing person, and I was astounded to discover I loved systems engineering. I was also pretty good at making presentations, and the sales people would often ask me to come along on calls. But it seemed so unfair  here I was, making maybe $12,500, the sales reps were making more than $30,000, and Im the one they counted on to help them sell. I asked my boss to let me switch to sales. I did well and moved up the ranks but, to put it in baseball lingo, I felt like I was constantly getting traded. Less than a year after I joined, Sperry Univac bought my division from RCA. Then, in 1986, we were bought by Burroughs, which soon became Unisys. I havent left a job, yet Im on my third team. After getting traded twice, it seemed time to make a switch on my own. So in late 1991 I accepted an offer from Wang Computer, and was part of the team that took it through bankruptcy and successfully got it out. In late 1999 EMC hired me as chief operating officer, and less than two years later I was chief executive. I keep seeing all kinds of analogies between business and baseball. Theres the need for teamwork, the need to read signals, to assess the other team. And a good leader has to know how to pitch and catch ideas. But the best chief executives are the ones who make sure the right talent is in the right spot, and who know what the competition can hit and what it cant. So I guess we business chiefs arent like baseball players at all. Were the managers in the dugout. As told to Claudia H. Deutsch. More Articles in Business »IM a pretty good baseball player and a really terrible guitarist. What Ive learned from baseball has had a great impact on the kind of manager Ive become, but it was the guitar that landed me my first technical job. Skip to next paragraph Jason Grow Joseph M. Tucci Chief executive, EMC Corporation BIRTH DATE Aug. 13, 1947 HOME Nashua, N.H. FAVORITE TEAM The Yankees, of course. "I may live 40 minutes from Boston, but my roots are in New York." FAVORITE TV SHOW "24." "I usually solve mysteries right away, but this one has so many twists and turns, I just cant. Jack Bauer is my hero." Podcast Weekend Business This week: The shake-up at JetBlue, and Rupert Murdoch's corporate kingdom. How to Subscribe This Weeks Podcast (mp3) We lived in Brooklyn when I was a kid, but I spent a lot of time visiting my grandparents in the Bronx. They lived on Webb Avenue, right off the Grand Concourse, so close to Yankee Stadium that I could hear the crowd when someone hit a home run. My grandfather was the worlds most avid baseball fan, and hed take me to games all the time. When I was about 10, my family moved to Delmar, just outside Albany, and of course I signed up with a Little League team. Sometimes I played third base, but my favorite position was catcher. The catcher gets to see the whole game play out in front of him, and he gets to send the signals, to call the shots. Like lots of kids, I wanted to be a professional ball player. I drove my mom crazy  Id be tossing a ball up and down when I was watching TV, or Id be hitting pink Spaldeens against her walls. But Id promised my dad, who died when I was 16, that I would go to college. So I went to Manhattan College and studied marketing and accounting. When I was about 20, I fractured my leg on a ski slope, but even that didnt drive professional baseball entirely from my mind. My younger brother, meanwhile, was a brilliant guitarist, and he taught me to play. I was never any good, but hed let me sit in with his band once in a while. I took a job on Wall Street when I graduated in 1969, hoping theyd put me in a training program of some kind. But they relegated me to back-office chores, and I was bored. I left a few months later and found a couple of semi-pro leagues to play in. It was only then that I realized how much mobility Id lost to that skiing accident, and gave up the idea of a baseball career for good. I drove a van for the Teamsters for a while, even worked some as a lifeguard. But Id gotten married, and it was time to get serious. So I applied for a job at what was then the computer division of RCA. The interviewer asked if I played a musical instrument, and I said yes. He said that people with a musical mind usually make for good systems engineers, and he hired me. I guess Im lucky that he never asked me if I played it well. Id always thought of myself as a sales and marketing person, and I was astounded to discover I loved systems engineering. I was also pretty good at making presentations, and the sales people would often ask me to come along on calls. But it seemed so unfair  here I was, making maybe $12,500, the sales reps were making more than $30,000, and Im the one they counted on to help them sell. I asked my boss to let me switch to sales. I did well and moved up the ranks but, to put it in baseball lingo, I felt like I was constantly getting traded. Less than a year after I joined, Sperry Univac bought my division from RCA. Then, in 1986, we were bought by Burroughs, which soon became Unisys. I havent left a job, yet Im on my third team. After getting traded twice, it seemed time to make a switch on my own. So in late 1991 I accepted an offer from Wang Computer, and was part of the team that took it through bankruptcy and successfully got it out. In late 1999 EMC hired me as chief operating officer, and less than two years later I was chief executive. I keep seeing all kinds of analogies between business and baseball. Theres the need for teamwork, the need to read signals, to assess the other team. And a good leader has to know how to pitch and catch ideas. But the best chief executives are the ones who make sure the right talent is in the right spot, and who know what the competition can hit and what it cant. So I guess we business chiefs arent like baseball players at all. Were the managers in the dugout. As told to Claudia H. Deutsch.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/18/technology/18blue.html?ref=emccorporation">I.B.M. Profit Is Up, Despite Slow U.S. Sales<date>Published: April 18, 2007</date><text>I.B.M. reported solid gains in quarterly profit and modest growth in revenue yesterday, as the company’s strategic shift toward higher-margin software and services makes gradual progress. The largest information technology services company, International Business Machines is also a major global supplier of software and hardware to corporations. So its results are closely watched as a barometer of corporate spending on technology. The results paint a picture of dynamic markets in the Asia-Pacific region, notably China and India; a rebound in Europe, with the big German market especially strong; a continuing recovery in Japan; and sluggishness in the United States. Sales in the Americas grew only 1 percent, to $9.1 billion. Within that geographic market, which is the company’s largest, business in Canada and South America held up fairly well, but the United States was the source of weakness. In a conference call yesterday afternoon, Mark Loughridge, I.B.M.’s chief financial officer, said the falloff in the United States was most pronounced in March, particularly among large corporations. Based on customer prospects and field reports, Mr. Loughridge expressed confidence that I.B.M. would see “some improvement” in the current quarter in the United States. Still, at a time when economists are concerned about whether softness in business investment will slow the American economy this year, the I.B.M. results suggest there is cause for concern. “The one surprise here was the weakness in the U.S.,” said David Grossman, an analyst at Thomas Weisel Partners in San Francisco. I.B.M. shares closed slightly higher, up 94 cents at $97.12 a share. In after-hours trading, shares slipped 63 cents, to $96.49. In contrast to the sluggish performance in the United States, the company’s sales in China rose 31 percent from a year ago, and sales in India increased 24 percent. I.B.M.’s quarterly revenue rose 7 percent, to $22 billion, but the increase was only 4 percent in constant currency after adjusting for the weakness of the dollar. Earnings per share rose 12 percent, to $1.21. That performance matched the consensus estimates of Wall Street analysts for profit and slightly exceeded their projections for revenue, as compiled by Thomson Financial. The company’s global services business grew by 8 percent, to $12.4 billion. Within the overall services business, the unit that handles high-end consulting work  helping companies use technology to streamline their procurement, manufacturing and marketing  grew 9 percent, to $4.2 billion. Profit margins in that unit, called global business services, have improved for eight consecutive quarters to 10.5 percent, or 2 percentage points higher than a year ago. That is crucial to I.B.M.’s strategy to move further up the ladder in the services business to work that requires more specialized skills. Revenue at I.B.M.’s other services unit, which includes managing data centers for corporate customers and maintenance, rose 7 percent, to $8.3 billion, but its profit margins fell 2.5 percentage points in the past year, to 7.8 percent, which the company attributed to high costs in the United States. I.B.M.’s big services business is under pressure from rivals, especially Indian outsourcing specialists, who contend that they will do to the technology services industry what the Japanese did in autos: compete first on price and later with superior quality and products. Though far smaller than I.B.M., the Indian services companies are growing rapidly. Within the last few days, Tata Consultancy Services and Infosys, for example, each reported that its most recent quarterly revenue rose more than 40 percent from the year-earlier quarter. I.B.M.’s software sales rose 9 percent, to $4.3 billion, helped by particularly strong growth products like its Websphere line, which uses Internet software standards to link a company’s programs, and its Tivoli data center management software. Hardware revenue increased only 2 percent, to $4.5 billion. Within the division, results were mixed. Mainframe sales increased 12 percent and big Unix server computers rose 14 percent, but minicomputer sales fell 13 percent. I.B.M.’s computer chip business fell 7 percent from a year ago, but the company said that was mainly because last year was a peak period of demand for video-game chips used in the Microsoft Xbox, the Sony PlayStation and the Nintendo Wii machines in the long run-up to product introductions last holiday season. The company’s storage systems business was also a disappointment, with sales falling 1 percent. Earlier yesterday, EMC, the leader in storage systems, reported that its quarterly revenue rose 17 percent, to $2.98 billion, and its earnings per share rose 36 percent, to 15 cents a share. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »I.B.M. reported solid gains in quarterly profit and modest growth in revenue yesterday, as the company’s strategic shift toward higher-margin software and services makes gradual progress. The largest information technology services company, International Business Machines is also a major global supplier of software and hardware to corporations. So its results are closely watched as a barometer of corporate spending on technology. The results paint a picture of dynamic markets in the Asia-Pacific region, notably China and India; a rebound in Europe, with the big German market especially strong; a continuing recovery in Japan; and sluggishness in the United States. Sales in the Americas grew only 1 percent, to $9.1 billion. Within that geographic market, which is the company’s largest, business in Canada and South America held up fairly well, but the United States was the source of weakness. In a conference call yesterday afternoon, Mark Loughridge, I.B.M.’s chief financial officer, said the falloff in the United States was most pronounced in March, particularly among large corporations. Based on customer prospects and field reports, Mr. Loughridge expressed confidence that I.B.M. would see “some improvement” in the current quarter in the United States. Still, at a time when economists are concerned about whether softness in business investment will slow the American economy this year, the I.B.M. results suggest there is cause for concern. “The one surprise here was the weakness in the U.S.,” said David Grossman, an analyst at Thomas Weisel Partners in San Francisco. I.B.M. shares closed slightly higher, up 94 cents at $97.12 a share. In after-hours trading, shares slipped 63 cents, to $96.49. In contrast to the sluggish performance in the United States, the company’s sales in China rose 31 percent from a year ago, and sales in India increased 24 percent. I.B.M.’s quarterly revenue rose 7 percent, to $22 billion, but the increase was only 4 percent in constant currency after adjusting for the weakness of the dollar. Earnings per share rose 12 percent, to $1.21. That performance matched the consensus estimates of Wall Street analysts for profit and slightly exceeded their projections for revenue, as compiled by Thomson Financial. The company’s global services business grew by 8 percent, to $12.4 billion. Within the overall services business, the unit that handles high-end consulting work  helping companies use technology to streamline their procurement, manufacturing and marketing  grew 9 percent, to $4.2 billion. Profit margins in that unit, called global business services, have improved for eight consecutive quarters to 10.5 percent, or 2 percentage points higher than a year ago. That is crucial to I.B.M.’s strategy to move further up the ladder in the services business to work that requires more specialized skills. Revenue at I.B.M.’s other services unit, which includes managing data centers for corporate customers and maintenance, rose 7 percent, to $8.3 billion, but its profit margins fell 2.5 percentage points in the past year, to 7.8 percent, which the company attributed to high costs in the United States. I.B.M.’s big services business is under pressure from rivals, especially Indian outsourcing specialists, who contend that they will do to the technology services industry what the Japanese did in autos: compete first on price and later with superior quality and products. Though far smaller than I.B.M., the Indian services companies are growing rapidly. Within the last few days, Tata Consultancy Services and Infosys, for example, each reported that its most recent quarterly revenue rose more than 40 percent from the year-earlier quarter. I.B.M.’s software sales rose 9 percent, to $4.3 billion, helped by particularly strong growth products like its Websphere line, which uses Internet software standards to link a company’s programs, and its Tivoli data center management software. Hardware revenue increased only 2 percent, to $4.5 billion. Within the division, results were mixed. Mainframe sales increased 12 percent and big Unix server computers rose 14 percent, but minicomputer sales fell 13 percent. I.B.M.’s computer chip business fell 7 percent from a year ago, but the company said that was mainly because last year was a peak period of demand for video-game chips used in the Microsoft Xbox, the Sony PlayStation and the Nintendo Wii machines in the long run-up to product introductions last holiday season. The company’s storage systems business was also a disappointment, with sales falling 1 percent. Earlier yesterday, EMC, the leader in storage systems, reported that its quarterly revenue rose 17 percent, to $2.98 billion, and its earnings per share rose 36 percent, to 15 cents a share.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/technology/28service.html?ref=emccorporation">New Effort to Tap Technology to Aid the Service Economy<date>Published: March 28, 2007</date><text>A group of large technology companies, universities and professional associations are creating a new organization to support and promote research into ways that technology can increase productivity and innovation in the economys service sector. The creation of the organization, the Service Research and Innovation Initiative, will be officially announced today. It represents the latest step by technology companies and some universities to promote an emerging field that is being called service science. The early academic programs are a blend of computing, social sciences, engineering and management. The aim of service science is to try to improve productivity and accelerate the development of new offerings in services, which account for about 80 percent of the United States economy and similarly large shares of other Western economies. In the last couple of years, more than three dozen universities in several countries have added service science courses, and the National Science Foundation has begun financing a few service research projects. Among corporations, I.B.M. has been a leader in promoting service science programs in universities, and it has reoriented its own research laboratories to focus more on services. We need a professional organization to help promote service science, said James C. Spohrer, director of service research at the I.B.M. Almaden Research Center in San Jose, Calif. It is one of the seed crystals around which the new discipline will form. I.B.M. and Oracle are founding corporate members of the Service Research and Innovation Initiative. Other company members of the organizations advisory board include Accenture, Cisco, Computer Sciences, EMC, Hewlett-Packard, Microsoft and Xerox. Researchers from several universities are also members, including some from the University of California, Los Angeles; the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania; and Arizona State University. The European Commission and a German research organization, the Fraunhofer Institute, are also members of the advisory committee. The new initiative is backed by two professional societies, the Technology Professional Services Association and the Service and Support Professionals Association. The executive director of the new organization, Thomas W. Pridham, is the senior vice president for advanced programs of the service and support professionals group. J. B. Wood, the chief executive of both the longstanding professional groups, said the purpose of the new effort was to have a neutral, nonprofit professional organization around which to build a community of common interest. The investment in research by companies and the government has driven so much innovation on the hardware side of information technology, Mr. Wood said. We think there is a similar opportunity in services. The new organization, according to Mr. Pridham, will provide a forum for collaboration to help set research priorities, pool corporate funds to support academic programs, and advise the government on preferred targets of basic research. It will hold a symposium on service research on May 30 in Santa Clara, Calif. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »A group of large technology companies, universities and professional associations are creating a new organization to support and promote research into ways that technology can increase productivity and innovation in the economys service sector. The creation of the organization, the Service Research and Innovation Initiative, will be officially announced today. It represents the latest step by technology companies and some universities to promote an emerging field that is being called service science. The early academic programs are a blend of computing, social sciences, engineering and management. The aim of service science is to try to improve productivity and accelerate the development of new offerings in services, which account for about 80 percent of the United States economy and similarly large shares of other Western economies. In the last couple of years, more than three dozen universities in several countries have added service science courses, and the National Science Foundation has begun financing a few service research projects. Among corporations, I.B.M. has been a leader in promoting service science programs in universities, and it has reoriented its own research laboratories to focus more on services. We need a professional organization to help promote service science, said James C. Spohrer, director of service research at the I.B.M. Almaden Research Center in San Jose, Calif. It is one of the seed crystals around which the new discipline will form. I.B.M. and Oracle are founding corporate members of the Service Research and Innovation Initiative. Other company members of the organizations advisory board include Accenture, Cisco, Computer Sciences, EMC, Hewlett-Packard, Microsoft and Xerox. Researchers from several universities are also members, including some from the University of California, Los Angeles; the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania; and Arizona State University. The European Commission and a German research organization, the Fraunhofer Institute, are also members of the advisory committee. The new initiative is backed by two professional societies, the Technology Professional Services Association and the Service and Support Professionals Association. The executive director of the new organization, Thomas W. Pridham, is the senior vice president for advanced programs of the service and support professionals group. J. B. Wood, the chief executive of both the longstanding professional groups, said the purpose of the new effort was to have a neutral, nonprofit professional organization around which to build a community of common interest. The investment in research by companies and the government has driven so much innovation on the hardware side of information technology, Mr. Wood said. We think there is a similar opportunity in services. The new organization, according to Mr. Pridham, will provide a forum for collaboration to help set research priorities, pool corporate funds to support academic programs, and advise the government on preferred targets of basic research. It will hold a symposium on service research on May 30 in Santa Clara, Calif.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/06/business/06options.html?ref=emccorporation">New Leader Is Appointed at McAfee<date>Published: March 6, 2007</date><text>McAfee, the large maker of security software, appointed David DeWalt of the EMC Corporation as its chief executive yesterday. McAfees former chief executive, George Samenuk, stepped down in October as part of a scandal over the backdating of stock options. The appointment of Mr. DeWalt, 42, EMCs head of customer operations, was confirmed yesterday by Siobhan MacDermott, a McAfee spokeswoman. EMC announced his departure early yesterday. The options scandal also led to the ouster of the company president, Kevin Weiss. The former general counsel, Kent Roberts, pleaded not guilty last week to improperly backdating grants and falsifying board minutes, which contributed to a restatement of 10 years of financial results. Mr. DeWalt, who joined EMC in 2003, will remain at the company through April 1, an EMC spokesman, Michael Gallant, said More Articles in Business »McAfee, the large maker of security software, appointed David DeWalt of the EMC Corporation as its chief executive yesterday. McAfees former chief executive, George Samenuk, stepped down in October as part of a scandal over the backdating of stock options. The appointment of Mr. DeWalt, 42, EMCs head of customer operations, was confirmed yesterday by Siobhan MacDermott, a McAfee spokeswoman. EMC announced his departure early yesterday. The options scandal also led to the ouster of the company president, Kevin Weiss. The former general counsel, Kent Roberts, pleaded not guilty last week to improperly backdating grants and falsifying board minutes, which contributed to a restatement of 10 years of financial results. Mr. DeWalt, who joined EMC in 2003, will remain at the company through April 1, an EMC spokesman, Michael Gallant, said</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/08/technology/08software.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Plans Public Offering for 10% of Software Division<date>Published: February 8, 2007</date><text>EMC announced yesterday that it planned to sell 10 percent of its fast-growing software subsidiary, VMware, in an initial public offering this summer. EMC, which specializes in data storage, bought VMware for $635 million three years ago. Today, industry analysts said the public offering could well value the company at more than 10 times that. Im 59 years old, and VMware is the best investment I ever made in my life, Joseph M. Tucci, the chief executive of EMC, said in a brief interview. VMware makes software that allows a computer to run different operating systems, or several versions of the same operating system, at the same time. This kind of software, known as a virtual machine, enables corporations to improve the efficiency of the computers in their data centers. More chores can be juggled on fewer computers, reducing the spending on hardware, electricity and maintenance. VMware is the leader in virtual machine software for server computers powered by industry-standard chips from Intel or Advanced Micro Devices, running Windows from Microsoft or Linux, an operating system distributed free. VMware has competitors. The most notable is Microsoft, which regards virtual machine software as both a sales opportunity and a threat because it has the potential to reduce the importance of operating system software. Microsoft is a latecomer to the market, however. Among VMwares other rivals are start-ups like XenSource and Virtual Iron. But there hasnt been much real competition yet, said Laura Conigliaro, an analyst at Goldman Sachs. VMware, with sales of $709 million last year, holds more than 70 percent of the market for virtual machine software, according to IDC, a research firm. In the fourth quarter of 2006, VMwares revenue grew 101 percent, to $232 million. Over the last three years, VMware, based in Palo Alto, Calif., has increased its payroll tenfold, to nearly 3,000 employees, Mr. Tucci said. A major reason for the separate listing and intial offering for VMware, he explained in a conference call, was to be able to use stock in a fast-growing company to retain and attract engineering and management talent to VMware. We want to unlock the value in VMware to make sure the company can continue to recruit the best and brightest, he said. The new VMware shares will be publicly traded, and EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., will retain a 90 percent holding. EMC has made a series of acquisitions in recent years to diversify its business. Under the terms of the partial sale, EMC will continue to consolidate VMwares revenue and earnings into its financial results. Further details will not be disclosed until EMC files its registration statement with the Securities and Exchange Commission in late March or early April, and the offering is planned for early summer, the company said. The proceeds from the offering will be partly invested in VMware, but some will also go to EMC. Those funds are likely to be used in the companys share-repurchase program. Mr. Tucci said that EMC would not sell off additional pieces of VMware in the future. We plan on holding onto this precious asset for the long term, he said. More Articles in Technology »EMC announced yesterday that it planned to sell 10 percent of its fast-growing software subsidiary, VMware, in an initial public offering this summer. EMC, which specializes in data storage, bought VMware for $635 million three years ago. Today, industry analysts said the public offering could well value the company at more than 10 times that. Im 59 years old, and VMware is the best investment I ever made in my life, Joseph M. Tucci, the chief executive of EMC, said in a brief interview. VMware makes software that allows a computer to run different operating systems, or several versions of the same operating system, at the same time. This kind of software, known as a virtual machine, enables corporations to improve the efficiency of the computers in their data centers. More chores can be juggled on fewer computers, reducing the spending on hardware, electricity and maintenance. VMware is the leader in virtual machine software for server computers powered by industry-standard chips from Intel or Advanced Micro Devices, running Windows from Microsoft or Linux, an operating system distributed free. VMware has competitors. The most notable is Microsoft, which regards virtual machine software as both a sales opportunity and a threat because it has the potential to reduce the importance of operating system software. Microsoft is a latecomer to the market, however. Among VMwares other rivals are start-ups like XenSource and Virtual Iron. But there hasnt been much real competition yet, said Laura Conigliaro, an analyst at Goldman Sachs. VMware, with sales of $709 million last year, holds more than 70 percent of the market for virtual machine software, according to IDC, a research firm. In the fourth quarter of 2006, VMwares revenue grew 101 percent, to $232 million. Over the last three years, VMware, based in Palo Alto, Calif., has increased its payroll tenfold, to nearly 3,000 employees, Mr. Tucci said. A major reason for the separate listing and intial offering for VMware, he explained in a conference call, was to be able to use stock in a fast-growing company to retain and attract engineering and management talent to VMware. We want to unlock the value in VMware to make sure the company can continue to recruit the best and brightest, he said. The new VMware shares will be publicly traded, and EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., will retain a 90 percent holding. EMC has made a series of acquisitions in recent years to diversify its business. Under the terms of the partial sale, EMC will continue to consolidate VMwares revenue and earnings into its financial results. Further details will not be disclosed until EMC files its registration statement with the Securities and Exchange Commission in late March or early April, and the offering is planned for early summer, the company said. The proceeds from the offering will be partly invested in VMware, but some will also go to EMC. Those funds are likely to be used in the companys share-repurchase program. Mr. Tucci said that EMC would not sell off additional pieces of VMware in the future. We plan on holding onto this precious asset for the long term, he said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/24/technology/24emc.html?ref=emccorporation">Profit Doubles as EMC’s Bet on Software Shows Results<date>Published: January 24, 2007</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the maker of data storage equipment, said yesterday that its quarterly profit more than doubled, helped by a tax gain and strong sales of mid-range storage gear and software. EMC also gave a 2007 outlook that was roughly in line with market expectations, according to Reuters Estimates, forecasting full-year revenue growth of at least 14 percent and net income-per-share growth of at least 19 percent. Shares in EMC rose after the results, and closed up 8 cents, at $13.55. EMC has been bolstering sales of software, which typically has greater profit margins than hardware, and last year acquired the security software maker RSA Security Inc. for $2.1 billion. Gross margins in EMC software tend to be above 70 percent compared with less than 40 percent in hardware. Executives said that the company had no plans to make big acquisitions in 2007, but would consider buying smaller companies that it could tuck in. EMC said its fourth-quarter net income climbed to $389 million, or 18 cents a share, from $148.3 million, or 6 cents a share a year earlier, when it had charges for job cuts and repatriating foreign earnings. Revenue rose 19 percent, to $3.22 billion, topping the average Wall Street forecast of $3.17 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. Excluding a tax gain of $76.7 million and charges for cutting about 1,300 jobs by the end of 2007, EMC posted a profit of 17 cents a share, beating the average forecast of 16 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. The year-earlier quarters profit was dragged down by a $316.6 million income tax provision, EMC said. During the fourth quarter, EMC said it saw double-digit revenue growth across its systems, software and services offerings. Revenue from systems including its high-end storage equipment grew 12 percent and software license and maintenance revenue increased 27 percent, for example. More Articles in Technology »The EMC Corporation, the maker of data storage equipment, said yesterday that its quarterly profit more than doubled, helped by a tax gain and strong sales of mid-range storage gear and software. EMC also gave a 2007 outlook that was roughly in line with market expectations, according to Reuters Estimates, forecasting full-year revenue growth of at least 14 percent and net income-per-share growth of at least 19 percent. Shares in EMC rose after the results, and closed up 8 cents, at $13.55. EMC has been bolstering sales of software, which typically has greater profit margins than hardware, and last year acquired the security software maker RSA Security Inc. for $2.1 billion. Gross margins in EMC software tend to be above 70 percent compared with less than 40 percent in hardware. Executives said that the company had no plans to make big acquisitions in 2007, but would consider buying smaller companies that it could tuck in. EMC said its fourth-quarter net income climbed to $389 million, or 18 cents a share, from $148.3 million, or 6 cents a share a year earlier, when it had charges for job cuts and repatriating foreign earnings. Revenue rose 19 percent, to $3.22 billion, topping the average Wall Street forecast of $3.17 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. Excluding a tax gain of $76.7 million and charges for cutting about 1,300 jobs by the end of 2007, EMC posted a profit of 17 cents a share, beating the average forecast of 16 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. The year-earlier quarters profit was dragged down by a $316.6 million income tax provision, EMC said. During the fourth quarter, EMC said it saw double-digit revenue growth across its systems, software and services offerings. Revenue from systems including its high-end storage equipment grew 12 percent and software license and maintenance revenue increased 27 percent, for example.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E5DB1F30F936A25754C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Business Briefs: Profit Falls at EMC<date>Published: July 15, 2006</date><text>The EMC Corporation's second-quarter profit fell nearly 5 percent, a result that the data storage provider warned about four days earlier when it announced it would fail to meet its financial goals because of inventory troubles for a new product. EMC also cut its earnings and revenue goals for the year after a quarter that the chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, above, said left him ''deeply disappointed.'' EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said net income for the April-June period was $279.1 million compared with $293.4 million in last year's second quarter. Profit in both quarters was 12 cents a share. Revenue rose 10 percent to $2.57 billion from $2.34 billion a year ago. EMC said it was hurt by a recent shortage of inventory to meet greater-than-expected demand for its newest Symmetrix DMX-3 storage system. ''I absolutely believe this was a self-induced execution failure on our part,'' he said.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/30/business/30emc.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Is to Acquire RSA<date>Published: June 30, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News The EMC Corporation, the world's biggest maker of storage for computers, agreed to buy RSA Security for about $2.1 billion to expand its security software business. RSA shareholders will receive $28 a share in cash, EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said yesterday in a statement. That represents a 22 percent premium to the closing stock price yesterday. The acquisition gives EMC radio tags and software to make online communication more secure. EMC is building its security offerings as data thefts raise demand for products that control access to corporate networks. Shares of RSA jumped to $27.25 in extended Nasdaq trading. The stock rose 18 percent, to $22.88, earlier yesterday. More Articles in Business »By Bloomberg News The EMC Corporation, the world's biggest maker of storage for computers, agreed to buy RSA Security for about $2.1 billion to expand its security software business. RSA shareholders will receive $28 a share in cash, EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said yesterday in a statement. That represents a 22 percent premium to the closing stock price yesterday. The acquisition gives EMC radio tags and software to make online communication more secure. EMC is building its security offerings as data thefts raise demand for products that control access to corporate networks. Shares of RSA jumped to $27.25 in extended Nasdaq trading. The stock rose 18 percent, to $22.88, earlier yesterday.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/29/technology/29deal.html?ref=emccorporation">Sale of Digital Security Firm Said to Be Near<date>Published: June 29, 2006</date><text>RSA Security, a pioneering digital security company, quietly put itself up for sale several months ago and is now near a deal with EMC or at least one other bidder, people involved in the auction process said last night. A deal, possibly worth more than $1.8 billion, could be reached in a few days, these people said. The company has a market value of $1.46 billion. RSA's board is expected to meet before the weekend to review final bids, these people said. They cautioned, however, that it remained possible that RSA could still decide against a sale. It could not be learned last night who was competing against EMC, the data storage giant. RSA, based in Bedford, Mass., makes physical security cards under the SecurID brand that are widely used in authentication systems at corporations around the world. The company is also active in developing antifraud technologies and a variety of encryption systems. RSA takes its name from the initials of its three founders: Ronald Rivest, Adi Shamir and Leonard Adelman. The three, who are academic researchers, are leading figures in the field of cryptography who developed an important algorithm in a technology known as public key cryptography. The company became a commercial success largely through the efforts of an early chief executive, Jim Bidzos, who became an outspoken advocate of commercial cryptography in the face of government opposition. He struck an early deal to use RSA technology in the Netscape browser. Today, the company has $322 million in annual revenue and $40.5 million in net income. RSA is widely known for sponsoring the RSA Security conference, a trade show and conference that has become the focus of the computer security industry. Shares of the RSA closed yesterday at $19.36, up 15 cents. More Articles in Technology »RSA Security, a pioneering digital security company, quietly put itself up for sale several months ago and is now near a deal with EMC or at least one other bidder, people involved in the auction process said last night. A deal, possibly worth more than $1.8 billion, could be reached in a few days, these people said. The company has a market value of $1.46 billion. RSA's board is expected to meet before the weekend to review final bids, these people said. They cautioned, however, that it remained possible that RSA could still decide against a sale. It could not be learned last night who was competing against EMC, the data storage giant. RSA, based in Bedford, Mass., makes physical security cards under the SecurID brand that are widely used in authentication systems at corporations around the world. The company is also active in developing antifraud technologies and a variety of encryption systems. RSA takes its name from the initials of its three founders: Ronald Rivest, Adi Shamir and Leonard Adelman. The three, who are academic researchers, are leading figures in the field of cryptography who developed an important algorithm in a technology known as public key cryptography. The company became a commercial success largely through the efforts of an early chief executive, Jim Bidzos, who became an outspoken advocate of commercial cryptography in the face of government opposition. He struck an early deal to use RSA technology in the Netscape browser. Today, the company has $322 million in annual revenue and $40.5 million in net income. RSA is widely known for sponsoring the RSA Security conference, a trade show and conference that has become the focus of the computer security industry. Shares of the RSA closed yesterday at $19.36, up 15 cents.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/21/business/21storage.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Posts 1% Rise in Quarterly Earnings<date>Published: April 21, 2006</date><text>BOSTON, April 20 (AP)  First-quarter profit at the EMC Corporation rose 1 percent, the company said on Thursday. The small gain and strong sales of its newest data storage products reversed much of the slide that its stock suffered last month amid rumors that the company was in trouble. EMC also announced that it would accelerate a plan to buy back more shares. Net income was $272.5 million, or 11 cents a share, compared with $269.8 million, or 11 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. The current quarter included costs from employee stock compensation, which reduced earnings by 3 cents a share. Revenue rose 14 percent, to $2.55 billion, just short of Wall Street expectations. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial forecast revenue of $2.58 billion, on average. The shares rose 53 cents, to $13.87. More Articles in Business »BOSTON, April 20 (AP)  First-quarter profit at the EMC Corporation rose 1 percent, the company said on Thursday. The small gain and strong sales of its newest data storage products reversed much of the slide that its stock suffered last month amid rumors that the company was in trouble. EMC also announced that it would accelerate a plan to buy back more shares. Net income was $272.5 million, or 11 cents a share, compared with $269.8 million, or 11 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. The current quarter included costs from employee stock compensation, which reduced earnings by 3 cents a share. Revenue rose 14 percent, to $2.55 billion, just short of Wall Street expectations. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial forecast revenue of $2.58 billion, on average. The shares rose 53 cents, to $13.87.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/04/business/04health.html?ref=emccorporation">Program Offers Health Care for Some Part-Time Workers<date>Published: October 4, 2005</date><text>Dozens of part-time workers at six large companies have begun to sign up for low-cost, limited health benefits in a new national program for uninsured employees. The HR Policy Association, a nonprofit organization of senior personnel executives, said enrollment was under way at units of General Electric, I.B.M., Sears, Avon Products, the computer-storage company EMC and the auto supplier Federal-Mogul. Six more large employers plan to start enrolling uninsured workers in the next few weeks, and five additional companies will join early next year, said Jeff McGuiness, the president of the association, whose members are personnel executives at 250 of the nation's largest employers. Those eligible include independent contractors like Avon sales representatives, as well as temporary and seasonal employees, and their spouses and dependents. The companies are taking a small first step toward slowing the spiraling growth of the uninsured, who now number more than 45 million. They acknowledge that the program is far from an overall solution, but they are addressing a challenge that government officials have largely ignored, said Steven M. Coppock, a senior actuary at the Hewitt Associates benefits consulting firm, which is helping the association with the program. "Because our health system is primarily employment-based, it makes sense for large employers to take collective action to try to come up with innovative, collaborative solutions to this pressing problem," said J. Randall MacDonald, a senior vice president for human resources at I.B.M. The coverage will be financed from the premiums paid by participants, with no subsidy from employers. But by pooling large numbers of their people, the employers say they hope to lower individuals' insurance costs by spreading the risks and attracting relatively healthy participants who will outnumber those in need of care. As members of an employee group, people with medical problems typically escape the higher premiums that insurers require from individuals with "preconditions." Options include a discount card for drugs and medical and dental checkups, which will also provide access to a 24-hour advice center run by nurses. The nurse line was added and the monthly cost of the card was raised to $6.99 from $4.41, after focus-group discussions with potential enrollees, Mr. Coppock said. In a revealing example of purchaser psychology, some potential enrollees expressed skepticism that any card that cost less than $5 would be worth having, he noted. The UnitedHealth Group is offering the discount card and four levels of limited coverage in all 50 states at monthly premiums ranging from $59 to $149. In 15 states, United will also offer high-deductible policies that cover major medical costs, under the same group rules with no add-on charges for people with preconditions. The major medical premiums vary based on an enrollee's age, sex and location. Humana will offer the high-deductible policies to individuals in 17 states and Cigna will offer them in Arizona only. Under these individual contracts, premiums may also be higher for those with preconditions. More Articles in Business &gt;Dozens of part-time workers at six large companies have begun to sign up for low-cost, limited health benefits in a new national program for uninsured employees. The HR Policy Association, a nonprofit organization of senior personnel executives, said enrollment was under way at units of General Electric, I.B.M., Sears, Avon Products, the computer-storage company EMC and the auto supplier Federal-Mogul. Six more large employers plan to start enrolling uninsured workers in the next few weeks, and five additional companies will join early next year, said Jeff McGuiness, the president of the association, whose members are personnel executives at 250 of the nation's largest employers. Those eligible include independent contractors like Avon sales representatives, as well as temporary and seasonal employees, and their spouses and dependents. The companies are taking a small first step toward slowing the spiraling growth of the uninsured, who now number more than 45 million. They acknowledge that the program is far from an overall solution, but they are addressing a challenge that government officials have largely ignored, said Steven M. Coppock, a senior actuary at the Hewitt Associates benefits consulting firm, which is helping the association with the program. "Because our health system is primarily employment-based, it makes sense for large employers to take collective action to try to come up with innovative, collaborative solutions to this pressing problem," said J. Randall MacDonald, a senior vice president for human resources at I.B.M. The coverage will be financed from the premiums paid by participants, with no subsidy from employers. But by pooling large numbers of their people, the employers say they hope to lower individuals' insurance costs by spreading the risks and attracting relatively healthy participants who will outnumber those in need of care. As members of an employee group, people with medical problems typically escape the higher premiums that insurers require from individuals with "preconditions." Options include a discount card for drugs and medical and dental checkups, which will also provide access to a 24-hour advice center run by nurses. The nurse line was added and the monthly cost of the card was raised to $6.99 from $4.41, after focus-group discussions with potential enrollees, Mr. Coppock said. In a revealing example of purchaser psychology, some potential enrollees expressed skepticism that any card that cost less than $5 would be worth having, he noted. The UnitedHealth Group is offering the discount card and four levels of limited coverage in all 50 states at monthly premiums ranging from $59 to $149. In 15 states, United will also offer high-deductible policies that cover major medical costs, under the same group rules with no add-on charges for people with preconditions. The major medical premiums vary based on an enrollee's age, sex and location. Humana will offer the high-deductible policies to individuals in 17 states and Cigna will offer them in Arizona only. Under these individual contracts, premiums may also be higher for those with preconditions.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DF1630F930A35756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Hewlett To Pay $325 Million To EMC<date>Published: May 3, 2005</date><text>The Hewlett-Packard Company said yesterday it had agreed to pay the EMC Corporation $325 million over five years to end lawsuits over patents. Hewlett-Packard, based in Palo Alto, Calif., can choose to buy EMC products instead of making a cash payment, an EMC spokesman said. The agreement ended three lawsuits between the companies, which are the two biggest competitors in the $14.2 billion market for data-storage computers.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB1631F933A15757C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC First-Quarter Profit Nearly Doubles<date>Published: April 20, 2005</date><text>Shares of the EMC Corporation climbed 13 percent yesterday after the data storage company reported that its first-quarter profit nearly doubled as sales grew across its data systems, software and professional services segments. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., reported its seventh consecutive quarter of double-digit revenue growth, a turnaround for a company whose fortunes plunged with the downturn in technology markets a few years ago. EMC earned $270 million, or 11 cents a share, in the January-March period, compared with a profit of $140 million, or 6 cents a share, in the same quarter a year ago. Revenue rose 20 percent to $2.24 billion. EMC forecast net income for the second quarter of 12 cents a share on revenue of $2.33 billion to $2.355 billion. EMC shares rose $1.52, to $12.99.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DF1638F932A25752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Cisco Will Resell EMC Data Storage Equipment<date>Published: January 11, 2005</date><text>Cisco Systems announced yesterday that it would resell data storage equipment from EMC to customers looking to centralize and consolidate storage in their corporate data centers. Cisco plans to begin selling EMC's network-attached storage products in the second quarter of 2005. The EMC products will be sold along with Cisco's File Engine Series, a gateway product used to increase the performance of a wide-area connection so that customers can get a complete storage package for remote offices from one vendor. In December, Cisco introduced the new File Engine gateway products, based on technology it acquired from Actona. The technology allows companies with dispersed branch offices to store content in a central data center without sacrificing performance. EMC shares rose 23 cents, to $14.08. Graph tracks EMC's share price for last week.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1030F931A15751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Deals: EMC To Acquire Smarts Inc. For $260 Million<date>Published: December 22, 2004</date><text>The EMC Corporation, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said yesterday that it would acquire Smarts Inc. for $260 million. Smarts, a privately held company, is known for its InCharge real-time network systems management software.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DE103AF933A15753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Posts 37% Profit Increase<date>Published: October 20, 2004</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the top maker of corporate data storage equipment, reported yesterday that quarterly profit rose 37 percent amid strong sales of low- and midprice systems and market-share gains from rivals. Third-quarter net income rose to $218 million, or 9 cents a share, compared with $159 million, or 7 cents a share, including an increase of 2 cents a share from tax rates, in the year-earlier quarter. Revenue rose 34 percent, to $2.03 billion from $1.51 billion. Shares of EMC gained 13 cents, to $12.28.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7D81E3BF930A25753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: I.B.M. To Sell Storage Computers<date>Published: October 13, 2004</date><text>I.B.M. has begun selling two new data-storage devices to try to win sales from EMC, the leader in the $30 billion market for such products. I.B.M. introduced a $97,000 model called the DS6000 to compete with EMC's DMX800. It also introduced a $250,000 model called the DS8000, Daniel R. Colby, general manager of I.B.M.'s storage business, said yesterday at a news conference in New York.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/21/business/technology-3-technology-giants-surge-in-quarter.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; 3 Technology Giants Surge in Quarter<date>Published: July 21, 2004</date><text>Motorola, EMC and Sun Microsystems, three former Wall Street favorites struggling to rebound from the technology recession that began in 2000, yesterday reported mostly encouraging results for the quarter.For Motorola, which sells a broad array of wireless communications and semiconductor products, and EMC, the leader in the data storage industry, the quarter brought surging earnings and market share gains.For Sun, which primarily makes server computers that run networks, unexpectedly strong sales for the quarter -- the last in its fiscal year -- ended a dismal three-year stretch in which every quarter's sales had been lower than the quarter the previous year.The three companies, while noting that the July to September quarter is typically a slow one for technology sales, expressed varying degrees of optimism about the rest of 2004. In the case of Motorola and EMC, investors shared the enthusiasm.Motorola reported a net loss of $203 million, or 9 cents a share, for the quarter ended July 3. The loss reflected a number of one-time tax losses and gains, including an $898 million accounting entry related to the future tax consequences of its spinoff of Freescale Semiconductor, its semiconductor products subsidiary.Absent such adjustments, Motorola earned 21 cents a share. Analysts had expected 18 cents a share.Revenue of Motorola, which is based in Schaumburg, Ill., rose 41 percent, to $8.7 billion.Although 30 percent of Freescale's shares were sold to the public last week in an offering that netted Motorola $1 billion, the semiconductor group will remain a subsidiary of Motorola until the rest of Freescale's shares are transferred to Motorola shareholders later this year.Motorola's cellphone unit, its largest, shipped 24.1 million phones, 52 percent more than a year ago, and operating earnings grew to $394 million from $91 million in the quarter last year. Freescale's sales climbed 31 percent, to $1.46 billion, and that unit earned $55 million, a contrast to a $125 million loss a year ago.EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said that net income in the quarter jumped to $192.8 million, or 8 cents a share, from $81.7 million, or 4 cents a share, in the second quarter of 2003. Revenue rose 33 percent, to $1.97 billion from $1.48 billion a year ago.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/16/business/technology-briefing-software-emc-reports-earnings-increase.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC Reports Earnings Increase<date>Published: April 16, 2004</date><text>The EMC Corporation, a supplier of data storage equipment and software, reported yesterday that profit rose sharply and revenue gained 35 percent in the first quarter as corporate customers increased technology spending. The company, based in Hopkinton, Mass., also said revenue in the current quarter would come in slightly above Wall Street estimates. EMC posted a first-quarter profit of $139.8 million, or 6 cents a share, compared with earnings a year earlier of $35.2 million, or 2 cents a share. Total consolidated revenue rose more than 35 percent, to $1.87 billion, from $1.38 billion. Excluding acquisitions, revenue would have risen 21 percent. Analysts' average estimates were for revenue of $1.82 billion and earnings of 6 cents a share, according to Reuters Research. EMC shares dropped 18 cents, to $13.02.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/16/business/technology-ibm-reports-11-gain-in-first-quarter-revenue.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; I.B.M. Reports 11% Gain In First-Quarter Revenue<date>Published: April 16, 2004</date><text>I.B.M., the world's largest computer company, reported solid growth in quarterly sales and earnings yesterday in a further sign that corporate spending on information technology is improving.Businesses are finally loosening their purse strings and are spending on computer technology, but the pickup appears to be a cautious one. The I.B.M. results, analyst say, indicate that corporate customers are mostly replacing and upgrading older machines and software rather than investing in many ambitious new technology projects.Other reports yesterday appeared to confirm that trend. EMC, a leading producer of storage systems for corporate data centers, reported sales and profits that were stronger than analysts' expectations. And after a holiday season when consumer sales of personal computers were strong, corporations have finally decided it is time to replace their aging personal computers, according to a report yesterday from IDC, a research firm.Worldwide PC shipments increased nearly 17 percent in the first quarter. ''We're definitely seeing a rise in corporate spending,'' said Loren Loverde, an analyst for IDC.I.B.M.'s revenue rose to $22.2 billion, an increase of 11 percent from the period a year earlier. Sales of computer hardware and software showed the biggest increases, while growth in I.B.M.'s big services business was more sluggish.''Hardware continues to be strong for I.B.M., and services signings continue to be weak,'' said A.M. Sacconaghi, an analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.Investors were apparently somewhat disappointed. In after-hours trading, shares of I.B.M. fell 3 percent, or $2.47 a share, to $91.50. In the regular session, before the company reported its results, I.B.M. shares rose 27 cents, to $93.97.In a conference call with analysts, John R. Joyce, I.B.M.'s chief financial officer, suggested that spending to modernize the basic equipment of computing would create the foundation for a broader recovery. ''Hardware and software are key indicators of the information technology environment,'' Mr. Joyce said. ''Infrastructures are just getting old and companies have to upgrade them.''Yet currency gains, from the weakness of the dollar, magnified I.B.M.'s growth. Without the currency gains, the company's sales in the quarter would have increased 3 percent instead of 11 percent.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/10/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-speeds-up-top-machines.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Speeds Up Top Machines<date>Published: February 10, 2004</date><text>The EMC Corporation, a maker of data-storage computers, said yesterday it had doubled the speed of its top machines. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., lost sales to I.B.M. in 2002 and began regaining market share in the third quarter as it added products, according to IDC, a research company. EMC's new Symmetrix DMX computers cost as much as $4 million and offer twice the performance of Symmetrix products introduced 12 months ago, a spokeswoman, Anne Pace, said. I.B.M. will keep pace or exceed EMC in speed, said Tom Hawk, a general manager in I.B.M.'s enterprise business.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/16/business/emc-acquires-software-maker-for-635-million.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Acquires Software Maker For $635 Million<date>Published: December 16, 2003</date><text>The EMC Corporation took a significant step to broaden its business yesterday with the purchase of VMware for $635 million in cash.The purchase of VMware, analysts say, is part of the shift under way at EMC to become less dependent on data storage systems and to expand further into software as price pressures steadily erode the profitability of computer hardware.The company has already made two software acquisitions in the second half of this year, spending $2.9 billion on the two all-stock deals. But Legato Systems, a maker of data backup and recovery software, and Documentum, whose software is used to manage all kinds of digital documents, are closely related to EMC's core business of data storage.VMware is more of a departure. The private company, based in Palo Alto, Calif., makes software that allows a computer to run different operating systems at the same time, or several versions of the same operating system. This kind of software, known as a virtual machine, has been used since the 1960's on mainframe computers. But VMware's technology is tailored for lower-cost machines powered by chips from Intel or Advanced Micro Devices, running Microsoft's Windows or Linux, an operating system distributed free.Such low-cost server computers are increasingly common in corporate data centers, and VMware's software increases their efficiency, yielding further cost savings. The VMware purchase moves EMC into the market for server software at the heart of the data center.''This represents a recognition by EMC that it needs to move into the mainstream of the data center instead of just trying to sell storage systems into it,'' said Galen Schreck, an analyst at Forrester Research.Strategically, the VMware purchase is somewhat different from EMC's previous acquisitions, said Joseph M. Tucci, the chief executive. But the deal, he said in an interview, is part of his company's move to increase its software and services businesses and become less reliant on hardware. After Legato, Documentum and VMware are brought into the fold, Mr. Tucci said, EMC will derive more than half of its revenue from software and services.''We've made a pretty big turn,'' he said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/05/business/technology-briefing-hardware-pricing-dispute-hurts-mcdata-results.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Pricing Dispute Hurts McData Results<date>Published: November 05, 2003</date><text>The McData Corporation, a maker of switches for data-storage computer networks, said yesterday that it would fall short of its own estimates for third-quarter revenue by as much as 17 percent because of a pricing dispute with its top customer, the EMC Corporation. Preliminary results showed that sales in the three months ended Friday rose to $93 million to $95 million, from $80.9 million in the quarter ended Sept. 30, 2002, before McData changed its fiscal year, the company said. McData, which is based in Broomfield, Colo., had projected sales of $107 million to $112 million. EMC, a maker of computer-data storage systems, had pressed McData for lower prices on switches and had refused to accept delivery of an order, said Steven B. Berg, an analyst for Punk, Ziegel &amp; Company. The dispute prevented some revenue from being recorded in the quarter, McData said. McData's Class A shares fell 40 cents, or 4 percent, to $9.63. A McData spokeswoman, Kathleen Sullivan, declined to say what ended the dispute and led to the sale's completion. An EMC spokesman, Mark Fredrickson, declined to comment.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/17/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-earnings-surge.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Earnings Surge<date>Published: October 17, 2003</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the builder of data storage computers, said yesterday that third-quarter earnings were more than seven times those in last year's third quarter, with a 20 percent sales gain outpacing growth in costs and as demand rose for more profitable software. Net income grew to $159.1 million, or 7 cents a share, from $21.3 million, or 1 cent a share, a year earlier. A tax resolution added 2 cents to profit. Sales rose to $1.51 billion from $1.26 billion, EMC said on its Web site. The chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, has cut costs and demanded more sales of software and services after losses in 2002 and 2001. Dell, which sells the company's gear, produced more than 10 percent of EMC's third-quarter sales, Mr. Tucci said. Revenue grew faster than the cost of sales in the third quarter, and expenses like research and development fell. EMC shares rose 52 cents, to $13.36.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/15/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-to-buy-documentum-in-stock-swap.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC To Buy Documentum In Stock Swap<date>Published: October 15, 2003</date><text>The EMC Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire Documentum, a management software company, in a $1.7 billion stock swap, in a bid to secure a top spot in the market for helping companies keep track of disparate information ranging from Web pages to X-rays. Documentum's shares surged $3.95, or 16 percent, to $28.37. EMC's shares fell $1.17, or more than 8 percent, to $13.28. But EMC said Documentum, which is based in Pleasanton, Calif., was perfect for EMC's strategy of looking for growth on its software side -- rather than from the big data-storage hardware devices it also sells. EMC purchased Legato Systems in July in a deal valued at $1.2 billion -- its first major purchase in years after a period of retrenchment -- and said at the time another similarly sized deal was on the horizon. Under the agreement, Documentum stockholders would receive 2.175 shares of EMC common stock for each share of Documentum common stock -- valuing each Documentum share at $28.88 based on yesterday's prices.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/07/business/technology-briefing-hardware-ibm-and-emc-to-share-data-storage-information.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: I.B.M. And EMC To Share Data Storage Information<date>Published: October 07, 2003</date><text>I.B.M. and EMC said yesterday that they would share information to ease the use of EMC data storage systems with I.B.M.'s large mainframe computers. The companies, which are fierce competitors in the data storage system market, said that they would each provide information about the programming that enables the computer and the data storage hardware to work together. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., will also license some mainframe and storage technology from I.B.M. The move comes as data storage system makers are trying to establish technology standards that will make it easier for customers to manage data stored on systems made by different companies. The agreement stops short of an exchange of application programming interfaces, or A.P.I.'s, which enable different applications like databases to communicate with each other. Some companies have agreed to share that information, which makes it easier to write software that can manage these applications. EMC shares rose 24 cents, to $13.65. Shares of I.B.M. rose 54 cents, to $91.18.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/09/business/emc-to-buy-legato-systems-for-1.2-billion.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC to Buy Legato Systems for $1.2 Billion<date>Published: July 09, 2003</date><text>After years of retrenchment, the data storage company EMC Corporation is expanding again.EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass., said today that it would acquire Legato Systems Inc. of Mountain View, Calif., in an all-stock deal valued at about $1.2 billion.The deal is another example of consolidation in data storage and the software industry generally. That trend includes Oracle's hostile takeover bid for PeopleSoft, which itself is trying to acquire J. D. Edwards.Legato is expected to help EMC fill holes in its offerings of software that helps corporate customers like banks and airlines manage data.EMC is trying to make software -- which has proved more profitable than its data-storage hardware -- account for half its business.''We have most of the pieces, not all of the pieces, and Legato really drops in nicely the pieces we didn't have,'' the chief executive of EMC, Joseph M. Tucci, said in a telephone interview.In particular, Legato would help EMC compete with I.B.M., Computer Associates and Veritas in one area where EMC has not been strong -- data backup and recovery software.Under terms of the agreement, shareholders of Legato will receive nine-tenths a share of EMC stock for each share of Legato stock. EMC shareholders will own more than 95 percent of the combined company, EMC said. The deal will add slightly to earnings in 2004, it said.EMC also announced that preliminary second-quarter results would meet or surpass Wall Street's expectations of a profit of 3 cents a share.Second-quarter sales will be at the ''high end'' of EMC's revenue forecast of $1.425 billion to $1.475 billion, the company said.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/03/business/technology-briefing-software-emc-buys-rights-to-bmc-data-storage-software.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC Buys Rights To BMC Data Storage Software<date>Published: July 03, 2003</date><text>The EMC Corporation, one of the world's largest makers of computer data-storage systems, yesterday acquired the rights to discontinued storage software from BMC Software in exchange for access to BMC's customers. BMC, which makes programs for managing mainframe and server computers, left the storage software market this year, attributing its exit to a lack of return on its investment amid intense competition from rivals like I.B.M. and Veritas Software. EMC has bought nine software makers since 2000 and has spent billions of dollars on research to sell more software, which is more profitable than hardware. BMC, whose storage software runs on systems made by many companies, offers EMC access to about 50 BMC storage software customers, 5,000 other clients and 850 sales agents, Bill Nelson, senior vice president of EMC, said. Financial terms were not disclosed. Shares of EMC fell 33 cents, or 2.9 percent, to $10.89. BMC shares rose 45 cents, or 2.8 percent, to $16.40.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/17/business/technology-emc-posts-profit-but-says-its-customers-remain-wary.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Posts Profit but Says Its Customers Remain Wary<date>Published: April 17, 2003</date><text>EMC, the largest independent vendor in the business data storage industry, joined other major technology companies yesterday in reporting solid results for the first quarter. It announced that it had returned to profitability after more than a year struggling to cut costs and update its products.EMC said revenues rose to $1.38 billion, up 6 percent from the first quarter of 2002, and profit margins expanded with the popularity of its latest version of Symmetrix, a refrigerator-size system that can cost $2 million or more. EMC's sales of products and software that are used in networks of less expensive storage devices, including devices made by rival vendors, also grew faster than expected.The results were released before trading began, and investors responded by sending EMC's shares up 62 cents, to $8.39.EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., had net earnings of $35.2 million, or 2 cents per diluted share, in the quarter compared with a loss of $76.9 million, or 3 cents a year ago. EMC said that the economic outlook remained very uncertain but repeated its earlier projections that it would be profitable every quarter of this year. And Bill Teuber, EMC's chief financial officer, forecast profits in the current quarter of 3 cents a share, a penny more than Wall Street's projections.But Mr. Teuber said that most customers were interested only in products or services that quickly cut their current storage costs, rather than large investments to support major new computer projects. And Joseph M. Tucci, EMC's president and chief executive, said that customers continued to subject investments to more review than usual, causing delays.In addition, because new technology continues to drive down the cost of storage, increases in the amount of data that businesses store do not automatically translate into growing revenues for data storage companies. ''The only way to grow in this market is to take market share,'' Mr. Tucci said in a conference call with analysts.EMC is doing just that, thanks to new products and a push to become more software and services driven. EMC said its overall equipment sales were $752 million for the quarter ended March 31, up 1 percent from a year earlier, with $575 million of that coming from its large Symmetrix systems. The Symmetrix sales were driven by the new DMX line, introduced in February, which also helped lift sales of related software.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/business/technology-data-storage-company-senses-mild-pickup.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; Data-Storage Company Senses Mild Pickup<date>Published: January 24, 2003</date><text>Fleshing out preliminary reports issued three weeks ago, EMC announced fourth-quarter earnings yesterday that confirmed a rebound in spending on information technology, and especially data-storage products, as 2002 wound down. The strength of that rebound remains suspect, though.''I believe I.T. budgets are pretty much flat,'' said William Teuber, EMC's chief financial officer, summing up independent surveys and conversations with important customers about plans for this year. ''No one is willing to commit to increased spending until they see how the full year develops.''EMC, which analysts view as a bellwether for its sector because it is the largest independent vendor of storage products, said that spending on such equipment would grow slightly faster than for other technology products. ''But the key word is slightly,'' said Joseph M. Tucci, the president and chief executive of EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass.The cautious tone seemed positively upbeat compared with the fears three months ago when EMC reported cuts in customers' budgets and an unexpected decline in October sales along with its figures for the third quarter. EMC shares, which have rebounded since reaching a low of $3.83 in early October, rose 57 cents yesterday, to $7.55.EMC's report came on the heels of strong results this week from Storage Technology, a leading vendor of tape and disk storage systems, and McData, a supplier of components for storage systems.EMC said that it had revenue of $1.49 billion in the quarter, down 2 percent from a year earlier but up 18 percent from the third quarter of 2002. The company lost $64 million, or 3 cents a share, compared with a loss of $70 million, also 3 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. EMC spent $364 million buying back shares last year.The loss in the fourth quarter included $117 million after taxes in restructuring costs. Without that, EMC would have reported net income of $53 million, or 2 cents a share.Clariion, EMC's line of midrange storage devices, was the ''star of the show'' in the quarter, Mr. Tucci said. Revenue for the products and related services topped $200 million, up 51 percent from a year earlier. But all other major product lines also improved on the third quarter.EMC said that sales might be down this month as customers await the introduction on Feb. 3 of updated versions of Symmetrix, EMC's more powerful storage system. Excluding restructuring charges, Mr. Teuber said, EMC will have profit of a penny a share in the quarter, at best, on revenue of $1.35 billion to $1.4 billion.EMC said cost-cutting lifted gross profit margins to 39.4 percent from 37 percent in the third quarter. Price declines, particularly overseas, cut about a half a percentage point from the profit margins, Mr. Teuber said. But the price wars with I.B.M. and Hitachi Data Systems that savaged EMC's earnings in 2001 and 2002 have largely abated.''We had the calmest pricing environment in the past two years'' in the fourth quarter, Mr. Tucci said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/07/business/emc-reports-strong-fourth-quarter-sales.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Reports Strong Fourth-Quarter Sales<date>Published: January 07, 2003</date><text>The EMC Corporation, a leading maker of network computer data-storage devices, said today that fourth-quarter sales topped analysts' forecasts, as less expensive systems attracted corporate customers.The company said it expected to report a net loss of 2 cents to 4 cents a share. Excluding costs for job cuts, profit would have been 1 cent to 2 cents a share. Sales were more than $1.47 billion.EMC's Clariion line, also resold by the Dell Computer Corporation, did well, EMC's chief executive, Joseph Tucci, said. The cheapest Clariion systems cost $28,000, compared with $1 million or more for EMC's larger Symmetrix machines.EMC was expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call to have a loss of 2 cents a share.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/01/business/private-sector-dismissed-and-sued-but-nothing-personal.html?ref=emccorporation">Private Sector; Dismissed and Sued, but Nothing Personal<date>Published: December 01, 2002</date><text>In 2000, Doron Kempel was an up-and-coming young executive at EMC, the data storage company. The next year, he was among the thousands of EMC employees laid off as sales and profits plummeted, but he appeared to land on his feet as chief executive of SANgate, a start-up data storage company.EMC's response was quick: it successfully sued to force him to give up the SANgate job on the ground that he had violated a promise not to work for a competitor for at least one year.Apparently, there were no hard feelings on either side. A few weeks ago, Mr. Kempel resurfaced as chairman and chief executive of a new EMC-backed data storage software company called Diligent Technologies. Diligent is based in Framingham, Mass., not far from EMC's headquarters in Hopkinton, but most of its operations are at a former EMC facility near Tel Aviv acquired by Mr. Kempel and Moshe Yanai, a former technology executive at EMC.''Even though EMC sued me, I still had good relations with the key executives,'' Mr. Kempel said. ''It was business, so we went on.'' Barnaby J. Feder</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/18/business/technology-emc-makes-a-small-profit-thanks-solely-to-a-tax-benefit.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Makes a Small Profit, Thanks Solely to a Tax Benefit<date>Published: October 18, 2002</date><text>EMC, the leading supplier of data storage systems for large corporations, said yesterday that it eked out a profit in the third quarter thanks to a one-time overseas tax benefit but that business conditions worsened as the quarter drew to an end.William Teuber, EMC's chief financial officer, said that despite stringent cost-cutting measures, including the recently announced layoffs of 1,350 employees, EMC did not expect sales to rebound strongly enough for the company to achieve break-even results before the second quarter of next year.EMC said that it earned $21 million, or a penny a diluted share, in the quarter, in contrast to a loss of $945 million, or 43 cents a diluted share, a year earlier. Excluding the tax adjustment, EMC lost $51 million, or 2 cents a share, in the most recent quarter.EMC said revenue rose 4 percent, to $1.26 billion. That was the first year-to-year sales improvement since early last year. But revenue fell 9 percent from the second quarter. Joseph M. Tucci, the president and chief executive, said that major customers were cutting back on their already reduced budgets for information technology.Such conditions once seemed inconceivable to EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass. Two years ago, as it completed a decade of rapid growth, EMC expected revenue of close to $15 billion this year. EMC preached that the amount of data essential to business was exploding, so investments in storing it were likely to soar even if the economy weakened. But data storage proved just as vulnerable to recession as the rest of the technology industry, and EMC will do well to reach $5.5 billion in revenue for the year.That reality has punished the stock price. After topping $102 two years ago, shares of EMC went into a long decline that took them as low as $3.83 early this month after it warned Wall Street about the earnings reported yesterday. With no significant new bad news in yesterday's report or the conference call that followed it, EMC's stock rose slightly in the morning before retreating to finish at $4.60, down 16 cents.Analysts said the biggest question left unanswered by the report was the degree to which the disappointing quarter reflected general market conditions as opposed to increasing competition from I.B.M. and Hitachi, EMC's major rivals at the high end of the market where storage devices can cost $1 million or more. Both rivals have updated their flagship product lines more recently than EMC, said Rob Schaefer, who follows the sector for the META Group, a market research and consulting company.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/04/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-plans-to-lay-off-1350.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Plans To Lay Off 1,350<date>Published: October 04, 2002</date><text>EMC, the leading vendor of data storage systems, said late yesterday that sales had dropped off at the end of the third quarter, making it unlikely that the company could return to profitability this year, and that it would lay off 1,350 employees, or 7 percent of its work force. EMC estimated that it had revenue of $1.25 billion in the quarter, at least 10 percent less than Wall Street had expected. ''The harsh reality of reduced budgets and the uncertainty of the economic and geopolitical climate are weighing heavily on business confidence,'' said Joseph M. Tucci, chief executive of EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass. EMC's shares, which closed at $5.01 in trading during the day, fell as much as $4.32 in after-hours trading. Shares of other data storage companies, including Emulex, Brocade Communications Systems, Network Appliance and McData also fell after EMC's report.Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/19/business/technology-briefing-software-emc-introduces-products.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC Introduces Products<date>Published: September 19, 2002</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the world's largest maker of computer data-storage machines, has developed software products that can manage information on machines of its rivals, including International Business Machines. EMC's chief executive, Joseph M. Tucci, announced the suite of software, collectively called ControlCenter, yesterday at the Storage Decisions technology conference in Chicago. The company will record sales from the new software in the fourth quarter, according to its vice president, Chuck Hollis. Because I.B.M. and its rivals -- Hitachi, Sun Microsystems and Network Appliance -- have not agreed to share technology to allow EMC programs to run on and control their machines, EMC developed its own software interfaces, Mr. Hollis said. Shares of EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., fell 46 cents, to $5.40.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/19/business/technology-briefing-software-emc-reports-profit-decline.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC Reports Profit Decline<date>Published: July 19, 2002</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the world's largest maker of computer data-storage systems, reported yesterday that it had second-quarter income of $808,000, breaking even per share; that income is down 99 percent from $108.9 million, or 5 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expected a loss of 2 cents a share for the quarter. The company, based in Hopkinton, Mass., reported a decline in quarterly profit and a 31 percent drop in revenue as companies continued to be reluctant to spend money on information technology. ''The hard cold fact is that I do not see the information-technology spending environment improving in 2002,'' said EMC's chief executive, Joe Tucci, in a conference call. ''Customers are extremely tight with their dollars right now.'' EMC's products include the hardware and software that store information for data-heavy companies like airlines, banks and insurance companies. Shares in the company fell 23 cents, or 2.7 percent, to $8.40. Andrew Zipern (NYT)</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/11/business/technology-briefing-e-commerce-emc-and-accenture-team-up-on-storage-networks.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | E-Commerce: EMC And Accenture Team Up On Storage Networks<date>Published: July 11, 2002</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the world's largest maker of computer data-storage systems, said yesterday that it would team up with Accenture to sell corporate-consulting services for storage networks. Financial terms of the five-year agreement were not disclosed. The companies will form a business unit under the direction of EMC's global-services organization. Accenture, the world's largest computer consultant, will provide consulting and management expertise, the companies said in a statement.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/19/business/technology-emc-posts-loss-of-76.9-million.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Posts Loss Of $76.9 Million<date>Published: April 19, 2002</date><text>EMC said today that it had a first-quarter loss, its third in a row, as competition with rivals prompted price reductions amid falling sales.The loss was $76.9 million, or 3 cents a share, in contrast to net income of $398.8 million, or 18 cents, a year earlier, the company said. Sales fell 44 percent, to $1.3 billion.EMC, a maker of data-storage systems, said its business last quarter came from clients' improving systems rather than placing big orders for new gear. Customers have told EMC that they will spend more when their own demand improves, its chairman, Michael C. Ruettgers, said on a conference call.The company reduced prices to battle rivals, including I.B.M. and Hitachi Data Systems.''This is the toughest environment for capital spending I have seen,'' Joseph M. Tucci, the chief executive, said on the call. ''We fell short of one key goal, and that is revenues.'' EMC had forecast first-quarter sales of about $1.4 billion, he said.Shares of EMC rose 60 cents, or 5.8 percent, to $11. They have declined 70 percent in the last year.Sales this quarter will rise from the first quarter, EMC's chief financial officer, William J. Teuber Jr., said without elaborating.Gross margin, the percentage of revenue after paying production costs, fell to 39 percent last quarter from 55 percent a year earlier, EMC said. Selling, general and administrative costs rose to 35 percent of revenue from 25 percent, and the portion spent on research and development increased to 15 percent from 9.6 percent.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/17/business/company-news-ibm-and-hitachi-to-develop-data-storage-systems.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; I.B.M. AND HITACHI TO DEVELOP DATA-STORAGE SYSTEMS<date>Published: April 17, 2002</date><text>I.B.M. and Hitachi of Japan said yesterday that they had agreed to collaborate on developing data-storage systems based on open standards as they take aim at the industry leader, EMC. Separately, International Business Machines and Hitachi also said they planned to combine their various hard-disk-drive operations into a new stand-alone joint venture. Hitachi will own 70 percent of the joint venture and pay I.B.M. for its hard-disk-drive assets, subject to the completion of negotiations, the companies said. Demand and prices have fallen sharply for hard-disk drives and other computer components. Analysts have pressured I.B.M. to sell its hard-disk-drive business, which is part of a company unit that I.B.M. pointed to last week as a reason for its poor first-quarter performance.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/13/business/company-news-emc-accuses-hitachi-of-patent-infringement.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC ACCUSES HITACHI OF PATENT INFRINGEMENT<date>Published: April 13, 2002</date><text>The EMC Corporation said yesterday that it had accused the Hitachi Data Systems Corporation, a unit of Hitachi Ltd. of Japan, of violating six patents related to EMC's storage systems and software. In a filing with the International Trade Commission and the United States District Court in Worcester, Mass., EMC contended that Hitachi Data Systems and its parent infringed on four patents related to EMC's Symmetrix remote data facility and TimeFinder software products and two patents that relate to the migration and storage of mainframe data. The Hitachi products in dispute include HORC, HOARC and ShadowImage. EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass., and has annual revenue of $7.09 billion, is asking the trade commission to block importation of the Hitachi products. Hitachi Data Systems is based in California.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/26/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-falls-on-analysts-comments.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Falls On Analysts' Comments<date>Published: March 26, 2002</date><text>Shares of the EMC Corporation, the world's largest maker of data storage systems, fell almost 5 percent yesterday after two analysts said they did not think the company would meet estimates. H. Clinton Vaughan, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney in San Francisco, said EMC could miss first-quarter revenue estimates of $1.43 billion by more than 10 percent. He lowered his estimate to $1.26 billion, saying technology managers ''seemed to come into the new year reluctant to spend.'' Thomas Mancino, an analyst with Pacific Growth Equities in San Francisco, also cut his estimate. In January, EMC forecast first-quarter revenue of $1.43 billion, 5 percent lower than the fourth quarter. Andrew Zipern (NYT)</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/25/business/technology-emc-s-loss-in-4th-quarter-was-not-as-deep-as-feared.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC's Loss in 4th Quarter Was Not as Deep as Feared<date>Published: January 25, 2002</date><text>To the delight of Wall Street, EMC, the data storage company that became a widely held technology bellwether during the 1990's, yesterday reported a narrower loss than expected in the last quarter of 2001 and projected a return to profitability as early as this spring.EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass., said that it lost $70.2 million, or 3 cents a diluted share, on revenue of $1.51 billion in the quarter. The consensus expectation of analysts had been that it would lose 7 cents a share on sales of $1.31 billion. While the quarterly results were off sharply from a year ago, when EMC earned $562.9 million, or 25 cents a share, on revenue of $2.62 billion, they provided evidence that EMC was rebounding faster than expected from huge losses in the third quarter of last year.EMC said it benefited from strong growth in business segments like storage gear linked together in networks, software and storage services. The company also had more savings than expected from cost-cutting measures.The company said that customers remained cautious about investing in information technology. It endorsed projections that overall spending would be flat or down slightly this year unless there was a strong economic recovery. But it said the parts of the technology business that EMC deals with had already begun to bounce back from levels that were depressed even before the uncertainty created by Sept. 11.''The environment felt a little more like a normal business environment,'' said William Teuber, the chief financial officer, in a conference call with analysts before trading began yesterday.Investors responded quickly, sending EMC's shares as high as $17.21 before they settled back to end at $16.83, up 16 percent from Wednesday's close.''This is more of a story of EMC executing well than the information technology market really strengthening,'' said James Berlino, an analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''The things that are in their control, they're controlling.''EMC said that it had completed nearly all of the domestic portion of the 4,000 job cuts it had announced in response to plunging sales last year. EMC said the cuts and other cost-saving measures saved it $157 million in the fourth quarter.EMC's projections of a 5 percent decline in revenue for the quarter, to $1.44 billion, are rosier than Wall Street's current estimate of $1.26 billion.The company said that the improving business climate in the last three months was most evident in the growth of storage network equipment sales, up 52 percent from the previous quarter, and software, up 45 percent.Some analysts were particularly impressed with the assertion of Joseph Tucci, the company's president and chief executive, that EMC had achieved the results without resorting to discounting at the end of December to close pending sales.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/24/business/drama-and-pragmatism-drive-fight-over-a-hiring.html?ref=emccorporation">Drama and Pragmatism Drive Fight Over a Hiring<date>Published: December 24, 2001</date><text>The news release last Friday by SANgate Systems did not tell the half of it. SANgate, a privately held data storage start-up company based in Southborough, Mass., announced that Patrick Courtin had joined the company as chairman and chief executive. Mr. Courtin, whose most recent stop on a 20-year career in technology companies was at a software company called Gensym, was quoted as being ''thrilled'' with SANgate's potential. Thomas Crotty, a board member whose venture capital firm, Battery Ventures, is a major SANgate shareholder, was said to be ''extremely pleased'' to have someone with Mr. Courtin's experience and track record on board. What SANgate did not mention was that Mr. Courtin was hired less than a month after EMC, the data storage giant, got a Massachusetts court to quash SANgate's previous choice for chief, Doron Kempel. Until SANgate tapped him in September, Mr. Kempel had been general manager of an EMC division developing products for storing and retrieving multimedia data. EMC argued that Mr. Kempel's contract barred him from moving to a potential competitor within 12 months of leaving EMC. As part of SANgate's legal response, Mr. Crotty submitted an affidavit asserting that the company would need six months to find a replacement for Mr. Kempel if he could not come aboard and that it faced ''irreparable financial damage.'' Asked on Friday to square the court testimony with the sudden appearance of Mr. Courtin, Mr. Crotty said that presenting a dire outlook in defense of Mr. Kempel had been simply ''part of the process.'' Battery Ventures was in fact prepared to move quickly to provide a successor because it has a partner, Cornel Faucher, whose sole job is maintaining a list of suitable candidates to lead the companies in which Battery invests. ''SANgate's board moved into interview mode the day after the ruling,'' Mr. Crotty said. ''Also, this happens to be a good time to be looking because of the economy. A normal search can take six months.'' Is SANgate, which has no products yet, really a threat to EMC, which will finish 2001 with revenues of about $6.8 billion? That was probably not the point to EMC, which has a reputation for strictly enforcing provisions in its employment contracts that restrict who can hire its workers. By EMC's philosophy, it is better to be paranoid than sorry. ''Does it make people think twice about hiring EMC employees?'' said Mr. Crotty. ''Absolutely. It's a business strategy that, much as I hate to admit it, is working for them.''</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/16/business/private-sector-he-knows-this-bumpy-hill-well.html?ref=emccorporation">Private Sector; He Knows This Bumpy Hill Well<date>Published: December 16, 2001</date><text>JOSEPH M. TUCCI calls himself a car nut. He says the used sports cars he acquires -- a Porsche twin turbo is his current prize -- are treated so lovingly that he can sell them at a profit. No wonder Mr. Tucci, the chief executive of EMC, sometimes slips into car-and-driver analogies when discussing the company's remarkable rise to leadership in the data storage industry, its current problems or its plans for regaining momentum. But Mr. Tucci, 54, said those slips made him impatient with himself. ''I hate car analogies,'' he said, abruptly halting one in a recent interview. They tend to lead to oversimplification, he explained. Fair enough, but a snapshot of Mr. Tucci's career might read like this: Energetic, ambitious young executive proves adept at keeping Sperry and Unisys computers from being blown off the technology racetrack by I.B.M. More mature executive pulls the onetime office automation leader Wang out of the bankruptcy ditch, soups it up with new products and gets it running smoothly enough to sell to a European competitor. Seasoned manager is rewarded with the driver's seat in the front-running car on the data storage circuit. Ready to finally experience the thrill of putting the pedal to the metal with everyone else in the rear-view mirror, he has barely tightened his seat belt when . . . kaboom! This is going to require more than a minor pit stop. Mr. Tucci has had the misfortune of starting his job at one of the worst possible times -- at least when it comes to problems beyond his control. Since his promotion almost a year ago, the country has fallen into recession, and companies have cut technology spending. The cuts have been especially deep for big-ticket products like the multimillion-dollar storage systems built around EMC's flagship, Symmetrix, a refrigerator-size box full of memory disks. EMC, which finished 2000 with a burst that lifted its sales to $8.9 billion, aimed to hit $12 billion this year. Analysts now expect sales to slump to about $6.8 billion this year and to decline as much as $1 billion more in 2002. EMC was also blindsided by a price war initiated by Hitachi Data Systems, a unit of Hitachi Ltd., the deep-pocketed Japanese company, and joined by I.B.M.'s data storage division. Fighting back in a shrinking market destroyed EMC's profits. After earning $1.8 billion last year, EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., is expected to lose at least $600 million this year. The loss will reflect about $675 million in restructuring charges that included provisions to cut 4,000 additional jobs, bringing the total to 5,500, or 23 percent of the work force. Critics say EMC has problems in addition to uncontrollable market forces. They say that its technology advantages have eroded and that years of aggressive behavior by EMC sales representatives have soured relations with many customers. Fortunately for EMC, Mr. Tucci may be even better suited to managing upheaval than the prosperity that the company projected when he joined it nearly two years ago. ''He has made a career out of stewarding transitions,'' said James Berlino, an analyst at Merrill Lynch who has known Mr. Tucci since his days at Unisys. ''He's a hands-on guy who is incredibly direct.'' Mr. Tucci is already credited with pushing a sales force reorganization on the company that helped it overtake Network Appliance, the early market leader in the fast-growing new segment of smaller storage devices attached to networks instead of mainframe computers. He used a friendship from his days at Wang with Kevin Rollins, president and chief operating officer at Dell Computer, to clear the way for a recently announced alliance in which Dell will market EMC's smaller systems. ''He seems to know someone everywhere in high tech and in all of the Fortune 1,000,'' said Frank Hauck, an EMC executive vice president. Not that Mr. Tucci is all business: in his office are photographs of him with Pope John Paul II and, reflecting the transition in athletic passions from sandlot baseball and skiing to golf, Jack Nicklaus.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/23/business/technology-briefing-software-emc-and-dell-begin-venture.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Software: EMC and Dell Begin Venture<date>Published: October 23, 2001</date><text>EMC, a market leader in large data storage systems, and Dell Computer, a leading vendor of inexpensive data equipment for smaller applications, said yesterday that Dell would adopt EMC's Clarion products as its main data storage offering to the middle market. Such equipment costs $50,000 to $500,000. The terms of the five-year alliance between the two also provide for Dell to help EMC sell EMC's larger Symmetrix line to Dell's corporate customers and for EMC to use Dell's supply chain to cut manufacturing costs for Clarion. The deal resumes a connection between Dell and Clarion that was interrupted when EMC acquired Data General, Clarion's developer, in 1999. Financial terms were not disclosed. Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/18/business/technology-emc-reports-drop-in-sales-and-a-loss-in-the-quarter.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Reports Drop in Sales And a Loss In the Quarter<date>Published: October 18, 2001</date><text>The EMC Corporation, a major supplier of data storage systems, said yesterday that sales in the third quarter that ended Sept. 30 had tumbled to $1.21 billion, down 47 percent from a year ago, and that it had its first quarterly loss since 1989. Wall Street had been expecting red ink. While the consensus of analysts polled by Thomson Financial/First Call had been for a profit of 19 cents a share when the quarter began, expectations had been slashed to a loss of 5 cents a share by this week. But EMC, which is based in Hopkinton, Mass., said it lost $270 million, or 11 cents a share, before special charges like the cost of layoffs and writedowns on inventory. Including the special charges, EMC had a net loss of $945 million, or 43 cents a share, compared with a net profit of $458.2 million, or 20 cents a share in the third quarter of 2000. EMC also said that it would lay off another 4,000 workers in addition to the 1,600 previously announced and that it did not expect to make a profit before the second half of next year. Investors, many of whom had been hoping for good news after relatively encouraging reports from I.B.M. and Intel on Tuesday, showed their displeasure by sending EMC shares down $2.24, to $11.21. Analysts expected that in the wake of the Sept. 11 attacks, growing interest in information security and quick recovery systems could help sales and that some companies would try to save money by consolidating data on new systems. But such opportunities are modest compared with the lift EMC and others received from the rapid growth of electronic commerce and booming sales of business software like programs that manage customer data. As recently as April, EMC had been projecting strong growth despite reports showing that its larger customers were trimming information technology budgets. Company executives thought -- and many Wall Street analysts agreed -- that spending on data storage was so essential to electronic commerce that corporations would continue to buy hardware, software and service support even as other investments were reined in. But that faulty analysis, poor execution of sales strategy and bad luck combined to form a financial storm that crashed into the company in the third quarter. Michael C. Ruettgers, EMC's executive chairman, said that instead of a market growing at close to 20 percent a year as EMC had anticipated, demand for data storage now appeared headed for a double-digit decline. EMC had been too slow to respond to a reality far bleaker than the endless growth it had expected, he and other executives conceded. Not only were customers putting off buying equipment, those that were investing were buying smaller systems and looking for low initial prices rather than lower operating costs over the life of the equipment. Such trends were pushing sales away from EMC's flagship Symmetrix systems, Mr. Ruettgers said, and to systems made by rivals like I.B.M. and Hitachi Data Systems. EMC's operating margin fell to 30 percent in the recent quarter from 47 percent in the second quarter, excluding inventory write-offs. Five points of the squeeze on the operating margin came from price competition rather than declining sales, said EMC's chief financial officer, William J. Teuber Jr. EMC said it compounded its problems by trying to sell its high-end Symmetrix systems at the expense of its smaller Clarion products. Finally, the company introduced its biggest product for the quarter on Sept. 10, just before the nation's attention was diverted to the terrorist attacks and the recovery efforts.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/22/business/company-news-emc-data-storage-concern-suffers-12-share-decline.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC, DATA STORAGE CONCERN, SUFFERS 12% SHARE DECLINE<date>Published: September 22, 2001</date><text>Shares of the EMC Corporation, the largest maker of data storage systems, fell 12 percent after the company forecast a loss, its first in more than 11 years. The company cited competition and the slowing economy. EMC shares fell $1.47, to $11.15, after dropping as low as $10.01. The stock has lost 83 percent of its value this year. Joseph Tucci, who became chief executive in January, said yesterday that EMC would lay off 10 percent of its workers, or about 2,400 people, in the second round of job cuts this year. Sales have slumped as corporations reduce spending on computer-related products.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/14/business/market-place-the-wait-for-a-technology-rebound-may-be-long.html?ref=emccorporation">Market Place; The Wait for a Technology Rebound May Be Long<date>Published: August 14, 2001</date><text>Eighteen months into the worst bear market for technology stocks ever, many Wall Street strategists are warning investors not to expect the sector to turn around anytime soon.The problem, they say, is that profits at first-tier technology companies like Cisco Systems and EMC have fallen as fast as -- or even faster than -- the companies' stocks. As a result, many big technology stocks are now even more expensive based on a price-to-earnings ratio than they were last year. For example, the forecast for Cisco's earnings has dropped 82 percent since last fall while the company's stock is down about two-thirds.Price-to-earnings ratios typically rise during an economic slowdown as investors bet earnings will recover quickly once the economy gains steam.But the pessimists argue that investors are refusing to accept the hard truth that technology earnings, like technology stocks, were inflated by a bubble in 1999 and early 2000.The skeptics note that Wall Street analysts are cutting their profit estimates for technology companies next year, implying that this year's slowdown is not an aberration but instead a return to permanently lower growth rates. It will take at least several years before companies like Cisco and Oracle recover fully and enjoy the profit margins and earnings they did at the peak of the millennial boom, they say.''A year ago, I thought valuations were outrageous, but I thought fundamentals were pretty solid,'' said Steven Wieting, senior economist at Salomon Smith Barney. ''Now we've found out that valuations and fundamentals were both extremely problematic.'' Earnings at technology companies in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index will fall about 50 percent this year compared with results last year, according to Charles L. Hill, research director for Thomson Financial/First Call, which tracks corporate profits. That plunge accounts for most of the expected drop in profits for the overall S.&amp; P. 500 this year, although earnings at nontechnology companies are also expected to sag slightly.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/19/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-profit-down-71.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: EMC Profit Down 71%<date>Published: July 19, 2001</date><text>The EMC Corporation said its earnings fell 71 percent in the second quarter after its customers cut back on spending. EMC, the leading maker of data-storage systems for businesses, said it had net income of $109 million, or 5 cents a share, including a 1-cent charge to cover the cost of staff reductions, in the second quarter. ''I cannot recall a more difficult environment in terms of technology spending than the one that has unfolded over the past few months,'' said Michael C. Ruettgers, above, EMC's chairman. The results met the scaled-back forecast the company issued on July 6, but were down sharply from $429 million, or 19 cents, in the period a year earlier. Sales declined 6 percent to $2.02 billion from $2.15 billion in the year-earlier quarter. EMC's shares fell $2.18, or 10.7 percent, to $18.21. Marcin Skomial (NYT)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/06/business/emc-says-quarterly-earnings-will-fall-short.html?ref=emccorporation">EMC Says Quarterly Earnings Will Fall Short<date>Published: July 06, 2001</date><text>The EMC Corporation, which makes data storage equipment for big corporate computer systems, warned today that its revenues and earnings for the second quarter would fall well short of Wall Street estimates because of the global slowdown in technology spending.EMC said it expected second-quarter revenues to be about $2 billion, and earnings per share to be 4 to 6 cents. That compared with the Wall Street consensus for earnings of 17 cents a share and revenues of $2.43 billion.Joseph M. Tucci, the company's chief executive, said EMC's business was being hurt ''with each unanticipated downward step in the global economy.''''The earnings results for EMC's major customers -- the bulk of the S.&amp; P. 500, for example -- have been like a ball rolling down a hill for each of the past three quarters,'' Mr. Tucci said. ''When our customers earn less money, most of them have less to spend on I.T.''EMC, once seen as a safe haven for investors because of booming growth in corporate computer use, has succumbed to the same technology slowdown that has hit other sectors.The company said that the slowdown in the United States had spread globally and that its impact had been aggravated by a strong dollar.''As a result, sales cycles have continued to elongate,'' said William J. Teuber Jr., EMC's chief financial officer. ''We expect gross margins for the second quarter will be in the mid-40 percent range, reflecting several factors: lower sales volume than anticipated, customer incentive programs, and our competitive pricing actions.''EMC plans to announce complete second-quarter results on July 18.Shares of EMC fell 10 percent, to $27, in after-hours trading. In the regular session, shares fell 5 percent, or $1.59, closing at $30.03.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/14/business/technology-briefing-hardware-tough-talk-on-prices-from-emc.html?ref=emccorporation">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Tough Talk On Prices From EMC<date>Published: June 14, 2001</date><text>The EMC Corporation will keep cutting prices aggressively to fight off rivals challenging its leadership in the market for data-storage computers, its chairman, Michael C. Ruettgers, said yesterday. ''The expectation is that we'll continue to be aggressive,'' Mr. Ruettgers, left, said. ''We're driving pricing down aggressively during the period, and we'll continue to do that.'' EMC has been facing increased competition from competitors like I.B.M., Compaq Computer and Hitachi.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/12/business/technology-emc-joins-motorola-in-earnings-shortfall.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Joins Motorola in Earnings Shortfall<date>Published: April 12, 2001</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the leading vendor of data storage products for business, added its influential voice yesterday morning to the chorus of companies reporting that the economy both at home and in Europe has weakened further and more rapidly than anticipated this year.As a result of the slowdown, EMC said, it will report earnings and revenue slightly below Wall Street's expectations when it issues its quarterly figures next Thursday. The shortfall occurred despite an all-out effort at the end of the quarter by the company's famously aggressive sales force to ''defy the economy'' and meet projections, said Michael C. Ruettgers, EMC's chairman.At the same time EMC was issuing its warning, Motorola was telling analysts in a conference call that it would lose even more money in the second quarter than the $206 million operating loss it reported Tuesday night for the first three months of the year.Motorola also increased by 4,000, to 26,000, the number of jobs it plans to eliminate as part of cost-cutting efforts that began late last year. It said that investments in new factories and machinery, which topped $4.1 billion last year, had been sliced to $1.4 billion this year and that a third of that had already been spent.In an interview after the conference call, Robert L. Growney, Motorola's president and chief operating officer, said the Federal Reserve Bank should immediately cut interest rates by 1 percent to stimulate the economy. He also urged Congress to approve the Bush administration's tax-cut proposals.When asked whether the Democratic alternative of immediate ''rebates'' to poor and middle-class citizens would not be a more potent lift, Mr. Growney said Motorola supported anything ''that gives consumers some dollars.''The two technology bellwethers were not entirely downbeat. Motorola predicted that it would return to profitability in its cellular phone and semiconductor businesses in the second half of the year. It projected that overall demand for cell phones would climb to 425 million to 475 million units this year, an increase from the total of 410 million last year.And EMC said that major customers were telling it that they had finished the task of reducing technology budgets to reflect the slowdown. Based on such research, EMC told Wall Street it was confident that its revenue growth would top 20 percent this year and that earnings per share would end up modestly higher than in 2000.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/27/business/technology-bluearc-is-to-introduce-a-faster-data-storage-device.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; BlueArc Is to Introduce a Faster Data Storage Device<date>Published: March 27, 2001</date><text>BlueArc, a new Silicon Valley company that promises to provide significantly better data storage performance, is proving that the technology sector has not lost its appetite for speculation about the next great thing.BlueArc says it has completed design work and initial testing with customers of a new storage device that fetches data 5 to 10 times as fast as similar equipment from companies like EMC and Network Appliance. BlueArc also says that each of its specialized servers can handle 100 times as many simultaneous connections as its potential rivals and manage 200 terabytes of data -- 30 times the capacity of any rival.BlueArc's official coming-out party is scheduled for today at PC Forum 2001 in Scottsdale, Ariz. The company is ready to take orders for the devices, which will start at about $100,000 each. But everything the audience of high technology executives, investors and reporters will hear has been carefully leaked to influential analysts in recent months with the kind of results marketers dream of.Robert C. Gray, who oversees storage systems research at the International Data Corporation, says that although benchmark tests like those cited by BlueArc do not translate directly into real-world advantages in every data storage application, they point to a real breakthrough.''It's 2 to 10 times as good as today's products,'' Mr. Gray said.George Gilder, publisher of a widely followed Silicon Valley technology report, proclaimed less cautiously in February that the BlueArc ''revolution'' could take a bite out of not just the leading storage vendors but also companies like Cisco Systems, Alteon and Extreme Networks that sell gear to balance loads on storage networks.The analysts say that BlueArc's achievement is its design of new hardware that allows data to move in and out of storage systems at roughly the same high speeds it moves across the optical networks that link computers. Today's market leaders cannot match that without adding equipment or elaborate software, the analysts say.BlueArc, which was founded in 1998 as Synaxia Networks in Britain but is now based in Mountain View, Calif., homed in on a bottleneck that occurs because most of today's major storage servers use standard Intel microprocessors as their basic building block. They rely on specialized software to adapt the processors to storage management tasks. But like a city with roadways too narrow for modern traffic loads, they jam up as the software is executed.BlueArc's solution has been to design new chips that are programmed specifically for the kinds of demands placed on them by storage management.The basic approach is not novel. Indeed, Cisco and others transformed the telecommunications business by replacing software-based switching systems with new hardware specifically tailored to the task.But established storage companies noted that most start-ups betting on specialized hardware solutions to technology problems fail, even in the best of times.''I think they are going to have trouble getting chief information officers to take their systems, even for a free look,'' said Mark Santora, senior vice president at Network Appliance, noting that budgets are under pressure. ''People aren't going to experiment with companies that have no global support and no track record at a time like this.''</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/12/business/technology-technology-leaders-get-their-bearings.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; Technology Leaders Get Their Bearings<date>Published: March 12, 2001</date><text>A slowdown. A downturn. A reset to reality. Even the dreaded ''R'' word.Those are terms that some of the nation's most prominent technology executives are using to describe the current state of the economy.In the dim past (say, six months ago), it was big news when a major information technology company missed its financial targets. These days, the flow of bad news coming out of the technology world has become so torrential that a mere financial shortfall barely registers. Now, the headlines are all about jobs -- whether established hardware companies like Intel, Cisco Systems and Nortel Networks are cutting thousands of them or whether Yahoo, one of the few remaining big dot-com companies, has its chief executive resign.A sign of the breadth and depth of the gloom may be the willingness of some technology executives to openly discuss the economic slowdown and its impact on their industries.Last week, top executives from Dell Computer, EMC, Intel, Juniper Networks, Microsoft, Motorola and Sprint took time to answer three questions:*Where is the economy right now?*What should technology companies be doing in light of current economic conditions?*What is your own company doing in light of those conditions?The executives were hardly uniform in their assessments. Craig R. Barrett, Intel's chief executive, and Christopher B. Galvin, Motorola's chairman and chief executive, both used ''recession'' to describe the current state of affairs.But Michael C. Ruettgers, chairman of the EMC Corporation, the big maker of computer storage systems, said he thought the economy was mixed. And Scott Kriens, chairman of Juniper Networks, the up-and-coming maker of high-speed Internet routers, said he did not think times were really as bad as they might seem.James T. Vanderslice, co-president and co-chief operating officer at Dell, even said that strong companies -- among which he included his own -- could take advantage of the lean season by gaining market share. ''This is our time,'' he said.Still, most executives wanted this time to end as soon as possible. And it is no wonder.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/23/business/technology-sun-revises-its-estimates-downward.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; Sun Revises Its Estimates Downward<date>Published: February 23, 2001</date><text>Sun Microsystems said yesterday that many of its large customers had sharply cut back on investments in computer equipment, making it likely that it will fall well short of projected sales and earnings in the current quarter.''We are gaining market share,'' said Ed Zander, the president and chief operating officer of Sun. ''We're disappointed in one and only one thing -- the U.S. economy.''Sun said that it now expected revenues to grow 10 percent to 13 percent in the current quarter, down from 35 percent a year ago and a previous projection of at least 20 percent for the current quarter. The expected squeeze on its profitability is likely to result in earnings of 7 cents to 9 cents a share, at least 40 percent lower than the 15 cents a share that had been the consensus of analysts polled by First Call/Thomson Financial.The warning came after a rocky day of trading for technology stocks on Wall Street following an announcement yesterday morning from EMC, the leading vendor of large data storage systems, that its growth this year might be slower than previously expected. Coming after a more pointed warning to lower earnings projections late Wednesday from Brocade Communications Systems, a leading supplier of networking equipment for storage systems, EMC's uncharacteristically cautious note helped send storage stocks sharply lower.EMC was one of the most heavily traded stocks on the Big Board yesterday, falling $2.60, to $40.35. Its shares are down 47 percent this month. Brocade fell $2.75, to $41.94, on the Nasdaq.The selling pressure also hit Veritas Software, a leading vendor of software that manages storage systems, even though Veritas announced strong quarterly earnings Wednesday and raised its projections for the year. Its shares fell $6.88, to $65.50.Sun's shares rose $1.19, to $20.81, in trading on the Nasdaq yesterday before the company's cautionary conference call with analysts. Investors initial reaction to the news was negative, and Sun tumbled as low as $18.81 in after-hours trading, falling below the 52-week low of $19.88 the company had touched on Wednesday.Sun painted a picture of its customers' senior managers as nearly paralyzed with uncertainty about the direction of the United States economy. ''Anything to do with capital spending is being slowed down,'' said Thomas Lehman, Sun's chief financial officer.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/13/business/technology-briefing-digital-emc-shares-continue-to-tumble.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: DIGITAL; EMC SHARES CONTINUE TO TUMBLE<date>Published: February 13, 2001</date><text>Shares of EMC, the world's No. 1 data storage company, fell as much as 14 percent yesterday in a sell-off that the company said was fueled by unfounded market rumors that it had missed January business targets. EMC shares slipped to as low as $51 on the New York Stock Exchange. Even though EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said it had not changed its financial outlook, its shares have fallen nearly 34 percent in the last two weeks. EMC recently cut several hundred workers as part of its annual performance management plan.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/02/business/technology-briefing-hardware-report-hurts-network-appliance.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: HARDWARE; REPORT HURTS NETWORK APPLIANCE<date>Published: February 02, 2001</date><text>Shares of Network Appliance Inc. fell $7.06, or 13 percent, to $46.56 after a Credit Suisse First Boston analyst cut his rating on the maker of network data-storage devices, saying it may lose sales to rivals. Network Appliance may lose sales to a rival, the EMC Corporation, which is selling new data storage-related products, the analyst, Amit Chopra, wrote in an advisory to clients. A spending slowdown by Internet-related companies also could hurt earnings at Network Appliance. He cut his rating on the shares to ''hold'' from ''buy.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/24/business/technology-emc-results-beat-wall-street-expectations-in-fourth-quarter.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC Results Beat Wall Street Expectations in Fourth Quarter<date>Published: January 24, 2001</date><text>The economy may be slowing, but businesses are not cutting back spending on data storage, according to the EMC Corporation, which reported fourth-quarter revenue and profit yesterday that slightly exceeded Wall Street's expectations.EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., said revenue for the last quarter of 2000 jumped 40 percent, to $2.62 billion, from $1.88 billion a year earlier.The quarter completed a year in which the rate of revenue growth accelerated as the year progressed, resulting in a 32 percent gain for the entire year to $8.87 billion. EMC told analysts that it remained confident of hitting its previously announced goal of $12 billion in revenue this year along with Wall Street's current earnings projections.Michael C. Ruettgers, the chairman of EMC, said the quarter had reinforced EMC's view that information was being created so rapidly in the networked economy and was so essential to competitiveness that demand for intelligent data storage systems was bound to remain strong.EMC reported that earnings jumped to $563 million in the last quarter of 2000, up 49 percent from $377 million in 1999, excluding a charge against 1999 earnings related to acquisitions. Earnings per share rose 47 percent, to 25 cents a share, from 17 cents a share a year earlier, excluding a charge of 8 cents a share in 1999 related to the acquisitions.International storage revenue grew 67 percent in the quarter, led by a 134 percent increase in the Asia/Pacific region.EMC also expanded its market-leading position during the quarter. The company's shares, which rose faster than any other stock on the New York Stock Exchange during the 1990's, rose $3.03 yesterday to $79.56. They are up about 20 percent this year, although still well below last September's peak of $104.94.''EMC and storage are clearly islands in the storm,'' said Thomas Kraemer, an analyst at Merrill Lynch. Mr. Kraemer said storage companies, and particularly EMC, were adding so much software to their systems that they were becoming the intelligent hub of corporate computer systems. As a result, spending on storage systems is taking a larger piece of the information technology pie and hurting the prospects of companies that rely heavily on computer sales, he said.In EMC's case, the increasing role of software in its sales mix helped lift gross margins to 59.2 percent in the fourth quarter, up from 55.1 percent a year ago. William J. Teuber, the chief financial officer, said EMC expected revenue from storage systems to grow in the mid-30's percent range this year. Revenue from services like helping customers put together storage networks is projected to grow at almost 50 percent and software revenue to grow at more than 50 percent.But EMC suggested that profit margins might decline slightly because it planned to keep up its practice of cutting prices to expand markets and increase its market share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/15/business/technology-emc-s-big-bet-on-explosion-in-data-storage.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY; EMC's Big Bet On Explosion In Data Storage<date>Published: January 15, 2001</date><text>Thanks to the Internet and the rapid global expansion of computing, humans and their machines will create more information in the next three years than in the 300,000 years of history dating to the earliest cave paintings and beyond.That was what researchers at the School of Information Management and Systems at the University of California at Berkeley forecast late last year, much to the delight of the EMC Corporation, the data storage giant that sponsored their work.EMC was quick to pitch the study to Wall Street, adding it to analysts' projections that spending on data storage products is drawing even with spending on computers themselves and that it will account for 70 percent of information technology budgets by 2005. EMC also included its own projection that an individual -- EMC likes to call him Tommy in its advertisements -- could easily have a terabyte (the equivalent of 250 million pages of text) of stored personal records, photos and other data by 2005.The obvious outcome of such trends, of course, would be mind-boggling growth for data storage products and, more to EMC's point, full-scale storage systems intelligent enough to support the Internet's need for constant access to data. ''Data needs to live someplace,'' says Michael C. Ruettgers, EMC's chief executive. ''There's almost no value if it's just put away.''EMC's need to keep Wall Street awed is directly linked to its track record. It became the biggest gainer on the New York Stock Exchange in the 1990's by grabbing leadership of the market from I.B.M., producing both astonishing profits and sizzling growth. Then, as other technology giants stumbled in 2000, its shares gained another 10 percent to finish the year at $66.50. From such a pinnacle, convincing the Street the best is yet to come will be no mean feat.But there are plenty of other companies beating the same drum, from giants like I.B.M., Compaq Computer and Sun Microsystems to fast-growing newcomers like Network Appliance, Brocade Communications and Veritas Software.''Storage is becoming the heart and soul of all business,'' said Linda Sanford, senior vice president for I.B.M.'s storage group. ''What you know about your customers, suppliers and partners will differentiate you at the end of the day.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/19/business/technology-briefing-internet-cmgi-and-emc-form-a-pact.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: INTERNET; CMGI AND EMC FORM A PACT<date>Published: December 19, 2000</date><text>EMC and CMGI announced an alliance yesterday to adapt Internet-related technology developed by CMGI-controlled companies to EMC's popular data storage systems for large enterprises. An early goal will be to create a business database version of the AltaVista search engine widely used by Web surfers. Barnaby J. Feder</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/06/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-to-offer-smaller-server.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: HARDWARE; EMC TO OFFER SMALLER SERVER<date>Published: December 06, 2000</date><text>EMC, the dominant independent supplier of electronic data storage products and services, introduced its first midrange system yesterday in the fast-growing market for equipment that makes it easy for users to share data files over the Internet and similar networks. EMC also introduced a software program called HighRoad that allows its more expensive storage system for the network market, Celerra, to avoid bottlenecks that slow some transfers of big blocks of data. Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/02/business/company-news-emc-acquires-crosstor-for-300-million.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC ACQUIRES CROSSTOR FOR $300 MILLION<date>Published: November 02, 2000</date><text>The EMC Corporation, a leading maker of data-storage systems for businesses, said it had acquired CrosStor Software Inc. for about $300 million in stock. CrosStor, based in South Plainield, N.J., makes software that allows users to maintain and have access to files on computers. EMC is based in Hopkinton, Mass.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/20/business/technology-briefing-hardware-emc-profit-jumps-50.html?ref=emccorporation">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: HARDWARE; EMC PROFIT JUMPS 50%<date>Published: July 20, 2000</date><text>The EMC Corporation reported a 50 percent jump in earnings yesterday and predicted revenue would continue to accelerate for the rest of the year. EMC, which makes corporate data-storage computers, reported second-quarter net income of $429 million, or 19 cents a share, compared with $286 million, or 13 cents a share, in the similar quarter last year. Per-share figures were adjusted for a 2-for-1 stock split on June 2. Revenue increased to $2.14 billion from $1.65 billion a year earlier. EMC shares rose $3.8125, to $83.0625.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/07/business/company-news-compaq-and-ibm-to-work-together-on-data-storage.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; COMPAQ AND I.B.M. TO WORK TOGETHER ON DATA STORAGE<date>Published: July 07, 2000</date><text>Compaq Computer and International Business Machines agreed yesterday to create data storage products that work on each other's systems. The companies also said they would sell hardware and software from each other's storage lines and would work to develop industry standards for storing data on networks. The deal, whose value could exceed $1 billion, was seen as a way for both companies to go head to head with the data storage equipment leader, EMC. Compaq, the world's No. 1 personal computer maker, and I.B.M., the world's top maker of mainframe computers, said their goal was to ensure that their storage products worked together in hopes of building customer acceptance of open storage networking products.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/01/business/company-news-emc-hopes-to-raise-100-million-to-spin-off-a-unit.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC HOPES TO RAISE $100 MILLION TO SPIN OFF A UNIT<date>Published: June 01, 2000</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the data storage equipment leader, filed yesterday for an initial public offering of Class B common stock of its McData Corporation unit. McData, which makes switching devices for enterprise-wide high-performance storage networks, is looking to raise $100 million from the offering, using the proceeds for general corporate purposes. McData also plans to use some of the proceeds for capital expenditures and working capital, according to the filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. EMC's shares were down $3.875 each, to $116.625. The precise number of Class B shares, their price range and other details will be disclosed in a later filing.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/16/business/company-news-emc-to-revise-plan-to-buy-ibm-hard-drives.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC TO REVISE PLAN TO BUY I.B.M. HARD DRIVES<date>Published: May 16, 2000</date><text>The EMC Corporation, the maker of computer data-storage systems, dropped a plan to buy $3 billion of hard drives from the International Business Machines Corporation, citing I.B.M. production delays. EMC said it had worked out a new agreement to buy drives from I.B.M., the No. 1 computer maker, that does not include a specific amount. The accord is part of an agreement the companies disclosed on Friday to settle all patent suits against each other. At his annual meeting with analysts in New York last week, I.B.M.'s chief executive, Louis V. Gerstner, repeated warnings that a delay in introducing new drives would cut into second-quarter revenue.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/19/business/blue-chips-of-the-internet-increase-quarterly-profits.html?ref=emccorporation">Blue Chips of the Internet Increase Quarterly Profits<date>Published: April 19, 2000</date><text>The engine makers, parts suppliers and plumbers of the Internet have been responsible for the snap back this week in technology stocks. Companies like Cisco Systems, Oracle and Sun Microsystems can be seen as the ballast of the new economy, established concerns with steadily growing profits as opposed to the bubble of fledgling dot-com companies with their uncertain hopes of survival.Three of the technology blue chips -- Intel, EMC and I.B.M. -- yesterday reported earnings that exceeded Wall Street's expectations. The laggard of the three was the International Business Machines Corporation, whose earnings rose but whose revenues declined 5 percent in the first quarter. Big Blue suffered from the lingering effects of the year-end decline in corporate spending on computers and computer services by companies focusing on the Year 2000 transition.That problem is mostly behind it, according to company executives, who predicted I.B.M. would achieve growth rates of 10 percent or more in the second half of the year. Until then, however, Wall Street analysts regard I.B.M. a bit uncertainly, as a company that has not really delivered the proof that its transition to become a supplier of Internet technology to corporate America has yet paid off in higher growth.But both EMC and Intel reported strong advances in revenue as well as quarterly profits. They join other leading technology companies -- like Sun Microsystems, which last week reported a surge in sales and earnings growth -- that are benefiting from the increased investment in information technology as corporations in industries from automobiles to banking retool their operations for the Internet.The first of the three companies to announce its results yesterday, the EMC Corporation, is a leading supplier of the equipment increasingly in demand by companies as they adopt Internet technology.EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., is the market leader in producing large data storage systems for corporations. As companies build Web sites, giving employees, customers and suppliers access to more and more business information, the demand for large, high-speed storage systems has mushroomed. EMC, more than any other company, has benefited from that trend.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/26/business/in-mybriefcase-michael-c-rulttgers.html?ref=emccorporation">IN MY...BRIEFCASE; MICHAEL C. RULTTGERS<date>Published: December 26, 1999</date><text>THE president and chief executive of EMC, Michael C. Ruettgers, 57, can be thought of as one of the Internet's leading plumbers.EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., makes the sophisticated storage systems used by so many big Web sites and by corporations for storing data. It has been a lucrative, if lower-profile, niche of the information technology business for years: EMC and Dell Computer are vying to be the best-performing stock of the 1990's, both up about 70,000 percent for the decade.''I meet C.E.O.'s all the time who say, 'EMC, great stock,' because it's in their personal portfolios,'' Mr. Ruettgers said. ''They are surprised when I tell them they are also customers.'' STEVE LOHR</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/22/business/company-news-emc-buys-business-software-maker-for-192-million.html?ref=emccorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EMC BUYS BUSINESS SOFTWARE MAKER FOR $192 MILLION<date>Published: December 22, 1999</date><text>In a move to bolster its storage-management software business, the EMC Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire the business software developer Softworks Inc. for $10 a share, a total of about $192 million. EMC said Softworks shareholders, with 42 percent of the company's shares outstanding. had already agreed to support the offer. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., provides business storage-management systems, software and services. Softworks, based in Alexandria, Va., provides business software and services for data and storage management. It has revenue of $53.6 million.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/10/business/with-internet-in-mind-emc-buys-memory-disk-maker-for-1.1-billion.html?ref=emccorporation">With Internet in Mind, EMC Buys Memory Disk Maker for $1.1 Billion<date>Published: August 10, 1999</date><text>Offering the latest evidence of the Internet's enormous impact on all facets of the computer industry, the EMC Corporation, a leading producer of data storage equipment, said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the Data General Corporation, in a stock swap valued at about $1.1 billion.Both companies make storage devices -- ranging from high-capacity disk drives to vast arrays of disks and tape units -- that are crucial to the operation of networks and to the distribution of data over them. EMC's products are designed for the largest mainframe computers, while Data General's are aimed at smaller midrange computers that typically run the Unix or Windows NT operating systems.The explosive growth of the Internet has significantly increased demand for both categories -- but especially for midrange computers -- for use as servers, the powerful machines that provide products like World Wide Web sites and E-mail for millions of users.Data General, the once-scrappy minicomputer maker profiled in Tracy Kidder's best-selling book, ''The Soul of a New Machine,'' has in recent years derived an ever-larger portion of its revenues from its Clariion line of storage products for mid-range computers.After the acquisition, EMC said, Data General's computer systems business, Aviion, will operate as a separate unit.The deal values Data General's shares at $19.58, 48 percent higher than they closed on Friday.EMC shares closed at $57, down $3, and Data General shares closed at $17.4375, up $4.25, both on the New York Stock Exchange.Analysts said the acquisition fit EMC's strategy of broadening its product offerings away from the mainframe market to embrace a broader range of customers -- primarily those that run network servers and other midsize computer systems. Although Data General's financial results have suffered in the last two years from tactical miscues and management issues, analysts said the company's products remained strong and would benefit from EMC's more robust sales structure.''Data General has been going through a major program during the past year to beef up their direct sales activities,'' said Jim Porter, an analyst with Disk Trend, in Mountain View, Calif., noting that the company had previously sold most of its storage products to computer systems manufacturers rather than to users.''Direct sales is an EMC specialty, so this is going to make a fundamental change in how Data General does business,'' Mr. Porter said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/26/business/ibm-challenges-emc-with-new-data-storage-line.html?ref=emccorporation">I.B.M. Challenges EMC With New Data-Storage Line<date>Published: July 26, 1999</date><text>I.B.M. is making a bid to regain its leadership position in the high-performance end of the data storage business today with the introduction of a new generation of big disk systems.The new product line, code-named Shark, arrives at a time when the demand for data storage is growing at a torrid pace because of the Internet, electronic commerce and data mining -- all of which require fast access to vast amounts of information.And the new storage line, analysts say, represents the International Business Machines Corporation's effort to challenge the current leader in high-end storage systems, the EMC Corporation.EMC may not be a household name, but it is one of the most striking success stories in high technology. By commercializing a flexible high-performance storage technology known as RAID (redundant array of independent disks), EMC grabbed the top spot in the lucrative market for large external storage systems away from I.B.M.Today, big Internet companies like America Online and many major corporations -- including those using I.B.M. mainframe computers -- employ EMC systems as their main data storehouses. EMC, based in Hopkinton, Mass., has grown to become a $4 billion-a-year company.Its stock has been the second-best performer among the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 companies during the 1990's, trailing only Dell Computer. And its market capitalization exceeds that of such corporate stalwarts as General Motors and Boeing.The I.B.M. Enterprise Storage Server line, according to analysts who have been briefed in advance by the company, promises to be stiff competition for EMC both in terms of price and performance. ''I.B.M.'s strategy is to try to come out with higher performance systems at significantly lower prices,'' said John McArthur, an analyst at the International Data Corporation, a research firm.The proof, analysts cautioned, will be in the marketplace as the big systems, which can cost $1 million or more, become generally available in September. ''But this could be just what I.B.M. needs to be competitive with EMC,'' said James Porter, president of Disk/Trend Inc., a research firm.The new high-performance storage systems, I.B.M. said, have data-retrieval times that are far faster than rival products on the market.</text></article></page></root>
