<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Exelon"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/04/the-n-r-c-goes-social/?ref=exeloncorporation">The N.R.C. Goes Social<date>October 4, 2011, 3:16 pm</date><text>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission established a YouTube channel last month. It has a Twitter account, @NRCgov, and since January it has had a blog. On Tuesday it took the next step: the chairman, Gregory B. Jaczko, hosted an online session with more than 50 bloggers, most of them pro-nuclear. He is supposed to do it again on Thursday, with anti-nuclear bloggers. Associated PressGregory B. Jaczko, chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Tuesday’s session was supposed to last an hour but stretched to 90 minutes. The bloggers submitted written questions that were read to Mr. Jaczko by Dan Yurman, a blogger who also moderates a list-serv dedicated to nuclear power and social media. The turnout “exceeded all expectations,” according to Eliot Brenner, the commission’s chief spokesman. Transcripts will be posted in a few days, Mr. Brenner said. The questions and answers covered a variety of predictable topics — Yucca Mountain and nuclear waste, new reactor construction, the possibility of a generation of small modular reactors and the commission’s response to the Fukushima Daiichi accident. But in response to questions, Mr. Jaczko did cover some ground that he does not usually discuss in more formal settings. What keeps you up at night, one blogger asked. “I do wake up at night, almost every night, thinking about the agency,’’ Mr. Jaczko said. His biggest worry is that “we’ve missed something in an analysis,’’ he said. “It’s the unknown, the thing we may have missed. ‘’ He described a tension between wanting to move in a timely manner on regulatory questions, and not wanting to go too fast. Another asked whether the state of Vermont should be allowed to shut down the Vermont Yankee reactor even though the Nuclear Regulatory Commission has given its operators a 20-year license extension. The commission is supposed to have exclusive jurisdiction over nuclear safety questions. “Well, I think the states do make decisions about nuclear reactors,’’ Mr. Jaczko replied. He pointed out that the question of whether Vermont was making a safety decision or an economic decision is now in federal court. “I think we’ll all watch with interest,’’ he said. Southern states have exercised their clout in a different way, he said, because they have “provided a much more favorable financing environment for nuclear units.” Two twin-unit plants are in the early stages of construction, one in Georgia and the other in South Carolina. And what about the agreement between Exelon and New Jersey to shut the Oyster Creek reactor in 10 years despite the fact that the commission extended its operating license for 20? A license extension is “an authorization to operate; it’s not a requirement to operate,’’ the commission chairman replied. “Ultimately, absent a safety issue, determination about whether plants continue to operate are really going to come down to economics,’’ Mr. Jaczko said. He compared it to “a car with 150 or 200,000 miles on it, and at some point you have to make a decision whether to replace the clutch or move on to another car.” Some of the other plants that have received 20-year license extensions may also close before 20 years are up, he predicted. Electronic innovation is a tradition for the commission, which held a public hearing conducted across several cities simultaneously in 1996 by using conference rooms at Kinko’s shops. Later it built twin courtrooms, in Washington and Las Vegas, linked by computer and video, to conduct hearings on the proposal for a nuclear waste repository at Yucca Mountain in Nevada. Next up for the commission, according to Mr. Brenner: Flickr.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/07/haste-vs-procrastination-on-nuclear-waste/?ref=exeloncorporation">Haste vs. Procrastination on Nuclear Waste<date>July 7, 2011, 10:27 am</date><text>Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York TimesA dry cask containing spent fuel amid some scaffolding after its removal from a pool at the LaSalle nuclear power plant in Marseilles, Ill. As I noted in Wednesday’s paper, companies that operate nuclear reactors are increasingly turning to dry casks to store nuclear waste as their pools of spent fuel fill up. Some experts suggest that such casks should be used more widely to reduce the amount of fuel in the pools as a safety measure. The idea is that with less fuel, spread out more widely, total heat production will be lower; that way, if a cataclysm like a tsunami or earthquake were to strike, it would take longer to boil off the water that covers the fuel. But the utilities point out that safety concerns arise in moving the fuel to casks, too. The details, pro and con, get interesting. When the fuel is first taken out of the reactor, it is generating a lot of heat. That’s because when the uranium is split in the nuclear reactor, it leaves behind fragments that are unstable and that seek to return to stability by giving off a subatomic particle –- an alpha or beta particle –- or an energy photon, called a gamma ray. Each time such a fragment gives off such an increment of radiation, it is generating heat. But as weeks pass, the most unstable elements cease those emissions, and heat production is reduced. When the fuel is old enough and cool enough that it cannot heat up a sealed canister to more than 752 degrees Fahrenheit, it can be loaded into a dry cask. The fuel is sealed inside a metal capsule, and air circulating on the outside of the capsule carries off the heat, with no fans or pumps. Generally, industry thinking has been that the fuel has to sit in the pool for at least five years before it can go into a dry cask. Thus at any reactor that is operating, a lot of fuel will remain in the pool even if operators make maximum use of the casks. Last month, however, Holtec International, a major cask manufacturer, announced that it would apply for permission to load three-year-old fuel into casks. The company has been working with metals that conduct heat better, so that even if there is a lot of young fuel inside the capsule, the heat will radiate away without causing temperatures to rise too high inside, it says. The number of fuel assemblies that enter the inner capsule varies depending on the type of fuel, among other factors. The one I saw being loaded at the LaSalle nuclear plant in Illinois holds 68 assemblies and is loaded so that heat production will not exceed 14.2 kilowatts. (That would be roughly the same amount of heat as that produced by a dozen standard home hand-held hair dryers, although you’d probably blow a fuse before you could witness that.) But Holtec is working on a design that would allow about five times that much heat production. The utilities still prefer moving older fuel, however. Adam Levin, the director of spent fuel at Exelon, which owns the LaSalle plant, said that his company puts the younger, more radioactive fuel near the center of the canister, and the older, less radioactive material at the periphery, so that the old fuel helps shield the radiation coming from the younger fuel. If Exelon emptied out the older, colder fuel and then started loading casks with only younger fuel, he said, that “would mean that we would be loading fuel with much higher dose rates on the periphery, exposing our staff to increased radiation doses.” More generally, aging the fuel in casks does have a silver lining, from the perspective of long-term disposal. Eventually, as heat production declines, the radiation doses that workers are exposed to in shipping the fuel to a burial will be smaller. And at the burial site, heat production may be the factor that decides how close together the waste can be packed, and how big a repository is needed. For now, the United States has no specific burial site in mind: Yucca Mountain, the site in the Nevada desert that Congress chose in 1987, was shelved by the Obama administration as unworkable. The bright side may be that because of the procrastination, the area needed to bury the nuclear waste may shrink. Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York TimesThe spent fuel pool for the Unit 2 reactor at the LaSalle nuclear plant.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/26/business/26corner.html?ref=exeloncorporation">John Rowe of Exelon, on the Importance of Decisive Action<date>Published: June 25, 2011</date><text>This interview with John W. Rowe, chairman and C.E.O. of the Exelon Corporation, the electric utility, was conducted and condensed by Adam Bryant.Q. Talk about some important leadership insights you’ve gained through the years. A. We can talk about how people follow directions. Heading a large company, I could probably decree a dress code in great precision. And while it would cause riot and insurrection, most employees would in fact obey. But on the other hand, you tell your employees you want to make the company greener while keeping your focus keenly on the bottom line — that’s all too amorphous. They think you only mean one or only mean the other. It turns out that you can give orders far more easily if they’re very detailed and precise. But telling people that this direction is really important takes a whole lot of work to get people to follow it and implement it. And so I’ve learned the importance of conveying a clear direction and the need to reinforce it, day in and day out, in what you do, whom you promote, whom you give bonuses to, what’s rewarded. Communication is one of the most difficult things. In my first C.E.O. job, a young woman who worked for me walked in one day and said, “Do you know that the gossip in the office is that the way for a woman to get ahead is to wear frilly spring dresses?” And I just looked at her and asked, “Where did this come from?” She said: “Well, you said, ‘pretty dress’ to four women who happened to be dressed that way. And so now it’s considered policy.” I said: “Well, it’s the furthest thing in the world from policy. I was just trying to be pleasant in the elevator.” People hang on a leader’s every word on what seems like trivia and can resist like badgers your words when you’re really trying to say something you think is important. Q. Why is that? A. It’s human nature to be more comfortable with very clear instructions than with general ones. Hard things are hard. I mean, there is no simple detailed instruction when you’re dealing with things that are complex and fuzzy, or when you’re dealing with two or three important trade-offs. Q. What were some leadership lessons for you growing up? A. I grew up on a farm in Wisconsin with Depression-era farming parents. And there’s just no doubt that the work ethic that they instilled is just a huge part of it. My father believed you should work most of the time and my mother couldn’t quite see why he inserted “most.” There’s just a huge influence of growing up with two people who believed so much in work, duty, responsibility. I also had bosses on my way up who taught me key lessons: One is how important action is — to always be looking for something to do that moves the ball. Don’t sit still. My aphorism for it is, better a moving turkey than a sitting duck. If you’re just standing still, whatever you’re doing is going to get shot apart. I also learned that you have to act on the best information you have, and to not wait for the nonexistent perfect level of information. Q. What about some lessons on how you deal with people? A. The first thing I try to do is use simple things, like the company vision statement. In an almost papal way, I will say: “Look, everything we do is complicated. But these things are basic.” And I’ll say to a group, “I can tell you what every word in this document means.” It’s important to explain to employees that these principles really do impact how we function in our business. And by papal I mean not so much the red shoes, but you recite the creed. And you try to convince people that you believe the creed. Because you can’t actually influence 17,000 to 18,000 people on a personal basis, day to day. So that’s one thing I try to do. I can look at people and say, “Here’s how each one of these lines affects something we do in our business.” And I’ll point out that most of what’s in the creed would be the same for most other utilities. The real difference is we believe them more deeply. At least I do. Q. How else do you make the creed stick, rather than just becoming a poster on the wall? 1 2 Next Page »This interview with John W. Rowe, chairman and C.E.O. of the Exelon Corporation, the electric utility, was conducted and condensed by Adam Bryant.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/16/the-tricky-u-s-reactor-tally/?ref=exeloncorporation">The Tricky U.S. Reactor Tally<date>June 16, 2011, 12:14 pm</date><text>Associated PressReporters viewed two containment pools for spent fuel this month at the half-built Bellefonte plant in Hollywood, Ala. The T.V.A. will decide this summer whether to finish construction. At the entrance to the unfinished Bellefonte nuclear plant in Hollywood, Ala., are morale-building posters for Tennessee Valley Authority employees. In bold type, they proclaim “106.” The number refers to how many nuclear reactors the United States would have if the Bellefonte 1 reactor were finished, but such prognostications are dicey. As I note in Thursday’s paper, the Bellefonte project was announced in 1970. Ground was broken in 1974, but the plant was ultimately abandoned in 1988 because of weak demand for its electricity. The board of directors of the Tennessee Valley Authority plans to vote in August on whether to finish Unit 1. At present there are 104 operable power reactors in the United States. (On any given day, several are shut down for one reason or another.) The T.V.A. is already working to finish another long-suspended nuclear project, Watts Bar 2 in Tennessee, a two-hour drive from Bellefonte. That plant is supposed to be completed in 2012, and Bellefonte 1 could be finished by 2020, becoming No. 106. Except that two or three of the existing 104 may be shut by then. New Jersey had pressed Exelon to build a cooling tower for its Oyster Creek reactor, in Toms River, N.J. Oyster Creek won a 20-year license extension, but then reached an agreement with the state to skip the cooling tower but retire the plant in 10 years. Vermont Yankee, in Vernon, Vt., on the Connecticut River near the Massachusetts border, has won a 20-year license extension but needs a permit from the state if it is to run beyond next spring. Vermont officials are refusing, and the case is in court . Some other plants around the country may also retire, especially in view of the very low price of natural gas, which makes nuclear power less competitive. Speculation is growing that Progress Energy might decide to shut down its Crystal River reactor near Tampa, Fla., where operators have been trying for nearly two years to fix a problem with the containment building. The Tampa Tribune reported recently that a decision is imminent. Further complicating the reactor numbers game, the Southern Company plans to finish two additional units at Plant Vogtle near Augusta, Ga., by 2020, and two more reactors are planned in South Carolina at the site of the existing V.C. Summer reactor.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/04/28/exelon-to-buy-constellation-energy-for-7-9-billion/?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon to Buy Constellation Energy for $7.9 Billion<date>April 28, 2011, 7:13 am</date><text>Exelon announced on Thursday that it would buy Constellation Energy in a $7.9 billion deal, the latest in a wave of consolidation among energy companies, particularly utilities. Under the terms of the stock-for-stock transaction, Constellation investors would receive the equivalent of $38.59 a share, about 18 percent more than the 30-day average closing price of the stock. The combined entity would have a market value of roughly $34 billion. “The combination of these two companies will drive innovation and value for customers by combining Exelon’s abundant clean energy supply and Constellation’s leading customer-facing sales and marketing platform,” Constellation’s chief executive, Mayo A. Shattuck III, said, in a statement. “This enterprise will have the scale and financial strength to drive expansion in competitive energy markets as well as new investment in the next wave of clean generation and sustainable products and services.” The utility space has been an active one for mergers and acquisitions, as companies have sought to cut costs and increase scale. On April 20, the energy producer AES said it would buy DPL, the parent company of Dayton Power &amp; Light, for $3.5 billion in cash. In January, Duke Energy announced it would acquire Progress Energy for $13.7 billion in stock. Exelon and Constellation have mixed histories as deal-makers. In 2009, Constellation, based in Baltimore, agreed to be sold to Berkshire Hathaway’s MidAmerican Energy Holdings for $4.7 billion. It eventually canceled the deal and instead sold some nuclear assets to Électricité de France for $4.5 billion. In 2008, Exelon pursued a $7.5 billion hostile bid for NRG Energy. When it could not win over NRG’s shareholders, Excelon dropped the deal. DealBook earlier reported a potential deal between Exelon and Constellation. Exelon anticipates the acquisition of Constellation will break even in 2012 and be accretive to earnings by 2013. After the deal closes, the combined entity, to be called Exelon, will be the No. 2 residential electricity and natural gas distribution company, covering 6.6 million customers in Maryland, Illinois and Pennsylvania. It will also be the largest competitive power generator, with more than 34 gigawatts of power generation and 226 terawatt-hours of expected output. “This merger creates the number one competitive energy provider with one of the industry’s cleanest and lowest-cost power generation fleets and one of the largest commercial, industrial and residential customer bases in the United States,” Exelon’s chief executive, John W. Rowe, said in a statement. The deal, pending regulatory and shareholder approval, is expected to close by early 2012. For Exelon, Barclays Capital, J.P. Morgan Securities, Evercore Partners and Loop Capital Markets served as financial advisers and Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom as legal counsel. Morgan Stanley, Goldman Sachs and Credit Suisse Securities were Constellation’s financial advisers, and Kirkland &amp; Ellis acted as legal counsel.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/exelon-nears-takeover-of-constellation-energy/?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Nears Takeover of Constellation Energy<date>April 27, 2011, 6:18 pm</date><text>8:12 p.m. | Updated The energy utility company Exelon is near a deal to buy the Constellation Energy Group for about $7.7 billion in stock, people briefed on the matter said Wednesday. A deal between the two would be the latest in a recent wave of consolidation in the energy industry, especially among utility companies. Under the terms of the proposed takeover, Exelon would issue 0.93 of a new share for each Constellation share. At Wednesday’s closing prices, that would be worth about $38.59 a share. That is about a 17 percent premium to Tuesday’s closing price, the last day before speculation about a potential deal pushed Constellation’s stock higher. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink The merger could be announced as soon as Thursday morning, the people briefed on the matter said, cautioning that talks had not yet concluded and might still collapse. An Exelon spokesman, Paul Elsberg, said: “Exelon continually evaluates all opportunities to add value for our shareholders, including M.&amp; A. However, we don’t comment on rumors about specific M.&amp; A. activity.” A representative of Constellation was not immediately available for comment. Shares of Constellation rose 4 percent, to $34.40, on Wednesday amid reports of a potential sale. Platts, an energy information company, first reported the possible deal. Exelon shares rose slightly on Wednesday, to $41.49, giving the company a market value of $27.5 billion. Utilities have sought to combine to gain more customers, in part to fight falling prices. One of the largest deals announced this year is the $13.7 billion all-stock merger of Duke Energy and Progress Energy. Constellation, based in Baltimore, has tried to sell itself before. Two years ago, it agreed to sell itself to Berkshire Hathaway’s MidAmerican Energy Holdings for $4.7 billion — only to cancel that deal in favor of selling nuclear assets to Électricité de France for $4.5 billion. Exelon has also stumbled in previous deal-making attempts. It pursued a $7.5 billion hostile bid for NRG Energy beginning in 2008, only to drop its offer after failing to win over NRG’s shareholders. This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: April 27, 2011 An earlier version of this article incorrectly stated the premium in the reported takeover offer as 18 percent.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/25/business/energy-environment/25utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Says Its 17 Reactors Are Safe<date>Published: March 24, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — Exelon, the largest operator of nuclear power plants in the United States, sought to reassure investors and the public about the safety of its 17 reactors on Thursday. The company’s chief executive, John W. Rowe, declared that the company was well prepared to “respond to emergencies not contemplated in the original design.”Nevertheless, Mr. Rowe said that he expected that American regulators would impose new safety requirements on nuclear plants after the Japanese crisis. That is likely to add pose “significant costs” to the utilities that operate the plants, he said in a conference call with investors. Mr. Rowe’s comments echo those of others in the nuclear industry, who have said that the 104 American reactors are safe and generally do not face the same earthquake and tsunami risks that played an important role in the problems at the Fukushima Daiichi complex in Japan. Two utilities planning to break ground on new nuclear plants in Georgia and South Carolina say they are committed to proceeding with their projects despite the accident in Japan. Another nuclear project, proposed in Texas by NRG, was already facing financing problems and is likely to encounter further hurdles in the new environment. Mr. Rowe, whose company has no new plants in the planning stages right now, is focusing on upgrading the output of Exelon’s existing plants. “I believe that there is little opening for new nuclear plants in the near future,” he said. “But that view has come from economics, not from safety.” Christopher M. Crane, Exelon’s president and chief operating officer, said that American plants had several design features that he did not believe were present at Fukushima Daiichi, including a system to control hydrogen buildup and a hardened vent system to safely remove such gas from the building, both of which would help prevent the type of explosions that apparently occurred in Japan. In addition, diesel fuel for the emergency generators at American plants is generally kept in buried tanks so it cannot be swept away, as it was in Japan. None of the 10 Exelon plant sites is in a zone of high seismic activity, the company said. Its only unit near the coast is Oyster Creek, on Barnegat Bay, in central New Jersey, and that plant is 23 feet above sea level and five miles from the ocean. The effect of the Fukushima disaster on the American nuclear renaissance is hard to measure. Existing plants will most likely face new rules, but the financial impact is still unknown. As for new reactors, their near-term prospects were already quite limited in the United States. The most advanced project is the Southern Company’s Vogtle 3 and 4 units, near Augusta, Ga. The utility has broken ground there, and expects to receive a combined construction and operating license later this year. It is building a new model of reactor that is expected to receive approval by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission later this year despite the events in Japan. Two days after the tsunami, Southern said it “remains committed to completing the new Vogtle units on schedule and on budget.” “Japan is seismically very active and the Vogtle site is not,” the company said. And Southern’s plant is 130 miles from the coast, at an elevation of 220 feet, and thus not likely to see a tsunami. Across the river in from Augusta in South Carolina, South Carolina Electric and Gas is moving ahead with two reactors at its V. C. Summer site. Kevin B. Marsh, the president of the company’s parent, Scana, noted that the site was not seismically active and was 400 feet above sea level. “Our intent is to remain on schedule,” he said. One complication is that Scana’s partner, Santee Cooper, is seeking to sell power or part of its ownership stake. NRG is seeking to add two new reactors at its South Texas Project with a partner, Toshiba. But NRG said on Tuesday that it was “reducing the scope of development” to give the Nuclear Regulatory Commission time to assess the lessons from Japan. While NRG said it did not expect any changes in the design it planned to use, it faces other issues. Last May, Tokyo Electric Power Company, which owns Fukushima Daiichi, took a 9 percent stake in the Texas project and said it might increase that to 18 percent. It is unclear whether the Japanese company can still afford the American commitment given the multibillion-dollar cost of the Japan disaster. Even before that crisis, the South Texas Project was having trouble lining up customers to agree to buy power — a crucial requirement of the Energy Department before it will guarantee the construction loan. The final project in the advanced stage of planning, an additional reactor at Calvert Cliffs, Md., about 60 miles from Washington, stalled last year. Constellation Energy, which owns the first two reactors at Calvert Cliffs, was in a partnership with Électricité de France to build the third reactor, but Constellation pulled out after complaining that the government’s fee for a loan guarantee was too high. The French utility then said it would seek another partner.WASHINGTON — Exelon, the largest operator of nuclear power plants in the United States, sought to reassure investors and the public about the safety of its 17 reactors on Thursday. The company’s chief executive, John W. Rowe, declared that the company was well prepared to “respond to emergencies not contemplated in the original design.”</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/25/business/energy-environment/25nuke.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Potential Exelon Reactor in Texas Draws Foes<date>Published: December 24, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTON — Twenty years ago, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission rewrote its procedure for licensing reactors to cut the time it would take to build new ones. Now an important part of the system is getting its first test, as a Chicago-based nuclear utility clashes with a well-to-do group of Texas ranchers over preapproval of a site about 120 miles southwest of Houston.The conflict involves the first application by a utility for approval of an entirely new site for a reactor without actually scheduling the construction of one. In this case, Exelon, the utility that has filed the application, has stated that it will not build on the site unless business conditions change. Meanwhile, opponents of the project figure that if they do not object now, they will never have another opportunity, and they say they have found unique problems with the geology of the spot. The Victoria County project, named for the surrounding county, is 13 miles south of the city of the same name. Exelon says that because of low prices for natural gas, and the lack of a price on carbon dioxide emissions, it does not want to build a reactor there now; instead, it is applying for early site approval, the utility version of a family shopping for a house and getting pre-approved for a mortgage. Why bother, for a project with no timetable? Nuclear proponents say winning approval could lop months or years off the lead time to get a new reactor up and running, once the decision is made to build. “I believe it is the right way to go,” said Nils J. Diaz, who was chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission during the George W. Bush administration. If a company gets a site approved and later selects a reactor design that has been pre-approved by the commission, he said, “this takes care of maybe 80 percent of all the issues.” He added, “You clear this hurdle and you bank the site for 10 or 20 years.” Under the old system, the one used to build the 104 reactors now running, the government gave a utility permission to construct a plant, and as it neared completion, the parties spent months in hearings to determine whether it was safe to run. Andrew C. Kadak, director of nuclear services at Exponent, a consulting firm, said that under the old system, a utility could get permission to build but then needed to wait, after construction was complete, for permission to run the plant. If a company must wait while an investment stands idle, he said, “you really get killed.” But some opponents are putting up a fight reminiscent of those that traumatized the industry in the 1980s. This time, though, no bulldozer has started work on the spot in question. A prominent ranching family, the descendants of D. M. O’Connor, a South Texas pioneer, hired geologists who are raising detailed objections about “growth faults,” which do not lead to earthquakes but do cause subsidence, as the basin that includes the Gulf of Mexico grows. A report, commissioned by an organization called Texans for a Sound Energy Policy, which was financed by the family, found that one fault had created a dip eight inches deep in a nearby road, according to the geology report, produced by a Colorado firm, John C. Halepaska &amp; Associates. The report quotes from Nuclear Regulatory Commission guidance documents that say, “Preferred sites are those with a minimal likelihood of surface or near-surface deformation.” Another fault runs under the area staked out for the cooling pond of the new reactors. A shift could make the dikes around the pond collapse, according to the group, letting the cooling water drain away. The report also argues that among the 65 sites where nuclear power is now generated in the United States, only one, the South Texas Project, has any oil and gas wells on it. The Victoria site is “a pincushion,” according to Bill Jones, a spokesman for the family. Old wells sometimes vent poisonous gas or combustible methane. In a telephone interview, Mr. Jones said there was simply too little water during drought periods to allow the reactor to operate. But Craig Nesbit, a spokesman for Exelon, said that the purpose of the pond was to let the plant draw water in wet periods and ride out the dry times. The pond, he said, is not part of the safety equipment required for safe shutdown. “We wouldn’t build a $10 billion facility there if we didn’t think we could,” he said. The opposition, said Mr. Nesbit, was coming from “families that have been there for many generations,” who do not want changes in a landscape that has not been substantially altered in generations, either. The project has some strong local support. The county government, the city of Victoria and the chamber of commerce have all passed resolutions supporting construction, said D. Dale Fowler, president of the nonprofit Victoria Economic Development Corporation. “It’s hard to really comprehend how many thousands of construction jobs would come in in this project,” he said, along with 700 permanent full-time jobs at an average salary of $70,000. He said the opposition was “purely a not-in-my-backyard issue.” The Nuclear Regulatory Commission’s ruling on technical details involved in the project might take an extended period. But, Mr. Kadak pointed out, time is not critical now. And, he said, “If this site passes early site permitting, that’s one less hurdle when you really need the power.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/09/nyregion/09nuke.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Oyster Creek Reactor in New Jersey to Close by 2019<date>Published: December 8, 2010</date><text>The Oyster Creek nuclear reactor in New Jersey will be shut down by 2019, at least 10 years before its license expires, in a deal with state environmental regulators that will allow it to operate until then without building costly cooling towers, its owner said on Wednesday.Exelon Nuclear, which owns the reactor, in Lacey Township in Ocean County, has been negotiating with Gov. Chris Christie on the issue since he took office this year, said Exelon’s chief nuclear officer, Christopher M. Crane. Installing cooling towers “would cost us significantly more than the current value of the plant,” Mr. Crane said in a telephone interview. Under Gov. Jon S. Corzine, the previous state administration had approved a draft environmental permit for the plant that would have required cooling towers so the plant would stop pumping hot water into Barnegat Bay. The plant, the oldest operating power reactor in the United States, was built in 1969 by Jersey Central Power and Light Company. Exelon and a partner each bought a 50 percent share in 2000, and Exelon bought the partner out in 2002. Exelon ended up buying the plant for about $10 million, and has spent about $100 million since 2000, Mr. Crane said. While the plant has been profitable, its small size and a weak market for electricity in a recession make additional major investments impractical, he said. If expensive parts need to be replaced before 2019, he said, it might close before then. Oyster Creek has about 700 employees, and Mr. Crane was en route to the plant on Wednesday night to talk to them. Exelon had planned an announcement on Thursday, but The Associated Press issued an article about the deal on Wednesday evening. The governor’s office declined to comment. A similar debate over cooling towers is getting under way over the Indian Point reactors on the Hudson River in Buchanan, in Westchester County. Like Indian Point, Oyster Creek faces various foes, including some who worry about hot water discharges into the bay and others who oppose nuclear power in general. At 630 megawatts, Oyster Creek was the first large-scale commercial reactor in the country. It survived a tortuous process to win a 20-year extension of its operating license in April 2009 from the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. In the late 1980s, operators discovered that it had suffered extensive corrosion in a steel liner, raising doubts about whether the reactor could survive an earthquake. The commission granted the permit after lengthy engineering studies. The plant supplies about 6 percent of New Jersey’s electricity. While a 1954 law gives the federal government exclusive jurisdiction over nuclear safety, the states often enforce federal environmental laws within their borders, controlling aspects like water use permits. That is the basis on which New York State is trying to force Entergy, the owner of the Indian Point plants, to build cooling towers there. Adding to the financial challenge of building cooling towers, such plants are struggling with a decline in demand for electricity, a plunge in wholesale prices and a surplus in generating capacity. What is more, the price of natural gas is low at the moment and is expected by many analysts to stay that way, making it a more attractive source of energy. Coal plants are also under pressure. In Oyster Creek’s case, the plant’s relatively modest output also limits income. “Its size is definitely a huge contributor” to the decision, Mr. Crane said. A near-twin of Oyster Creek, Vermont Yankee, may be closed in 2012 because the State of Vermont has refused to grant a permit the plant would require. Its owner, Entergy, has put the reactor up for sale, also noting that its small size limits its value. After the Oyster Creek plant is shut by the end of 2019, Exelon will take about two years to put its components “in layup” but will not tear it down for at least 10 years after that, and possibly not for 60 years, Mr. Crane said. The company has accumulated $750 million for decommissioning, which he called adequate. Exelon is the nation’s largest nuclear operator, with 17 reactors. There are 104 operable nuclear reactors in the United States. The last two to be retired was the Zion plant north of Chicago, built by Exelon’s predecessor, Commonwealth Edison, and Millstone I, in Waterford, Conn., both in 1998. Connecticut Yankee, in the town of Haddam Neck, closed in 1996, and Maine Yankee, in Wiscasset, in 1997.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/12/09/oyster-creek-nuclear-deal-draws-fire/?ref=exeloncorporation">Oyster Creek Nuclear Deal Draws Some Fire<date>December 9, 2010, 4:51 pm</date><text>Keith Meyers/The New York Times The Oyster Creek nuclear plant in Lacey Township, N.J. Some people were deeply disappointed by the deal cut by Exelon and Gov. Chris Christie of New Jersey to let the Oyster Creek nuclear plant run without a cooling tower but then cease operations by 2019, 10 years early. But they dislike it for very different reasons. Representative Fred Upton, a Michigan Republican who will take over as chairman of the subcommittee that oversees the Nuclear Regulatory Commission when the new Congress comes in next month, called Wednesday’s news the “first domino” in what could be a chain of announcements by nuclear operators, electricity generators and industrial users of cooling water, given that the Environmental Protection Agency is seeking to tighten the rules on plants that do not have cooling towers. The agency’s aim is to reduce the amount of water drawn from and then returned to bays and rivers for cooling purposes. Oyster Creek’s early retirement “should serve as a wake-up call that rampant regulations are shutting down power plants and costing jobs,’’ Mr. Upton said. The government is promulgating rules on cooling water “with no cost-benefit analysis,’’ he complained, adding that it could affect more than 400 power plants nationwide. But some environmentalists objected to the deal on the ground that, in their view, Exelon won. “When Governor Christie ran he promised that he would protect Barnegat Bay and deal with the cooling towers issue at Oyster Creek,’’ the New Jersey chapter of the Sierra Club said in a statement. “He has done neither. He has taken the side of the polluter over the bay with his decision to side with Exelon.’’ The plant’s cooling system has caused “a near collapse of the shell fishing industry’’ in the bay, the Sierra Club said. Environmentalists say there are two problems: the plant emits hot water, and it sucks in such huge volumes of water that larvae and other small organisms are pulled through the system and killed, while larger marine life is pinned against an intake screen and dies. But when Governor Christie held a news conference in Trenton on Thursday afternoon, representatives of several environmental organizations, including Clean Ocean Action, the American Littoral Society and the New Jersey Environmental Federation, appeared with him to endorse the deal. In a telephone interview, Bob Martin, the commissioner of the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, said that by the time Oyster Creek was shut, its output was likely to be replaced by a new high-efficiency plant running on natural gas. The state will have added substantial offshore wind power and solar power by then, he said. Shutting the plant involves some trade-offs, he said, but he added that it was a good environmental bargain “when you look at the whole picture.’’ Exelon said on Wednesday that the cost of building cooling towers would exceed the value of the plant. The actual math remained a bit murky; the company did not say just how it valued the plant or even specify what form of cooling system played into its calculations for construction — one hourglass-shaped tower, or a row of smaller ones. Another cost factor was that running a tower or towers would soak up perhaps 3 or 4 percent of the plant’s power output. The announcement of an agreement on closing Oyster Creek comes at a time that the nuclear industry had hoped would usher in a “renaissance.” But another reactor could close even earlier: Vermont Yankee, where the license expires in 2012 and the Vermont state Legislature has refused to permit continued operation. The last reactor to close in the United States was Millstone 1, in Waterford, Conn., in July 1998. At the moment, foundations are being poured for four new reactors, two in Georgia and two in South Carolina. By 2019, the industry hopes several others will be finished or well under way. Meanwhile, the Energy Department expects numerous electric generation stations, many of them small, antiquated coal-fired plants, to close over the next few years.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/12/07/nuclear-renaissance-is-short-on-largess/?ref=exeloncorporation">Nuclear 'Renaissance' Is Short on Largess<date>December 7, 2010, 5:53 pm</date><text>Getty Images Senator Tom Carper of Delaware, left at center, and Senator George Voinovich, right center, led a panel discussion on Tuesday at a conference on nuclear power in Washington. The federal aid now in place for new nuclear plants is far from sufficient for the so-called “nuclear renaissance” that backers are seeking, a panel made up of members of Congress, high-ranking federal officials and leaders of major nuclear companies agreed on Tuesday. Ground has been broken on only two new nuclear plants with a total of four reactors, and some companies have withdrawn their applications for licenses to build. “We can’t make the numbers work,’’ said Chip Pardee, chief nuclear officer of Exelon, the nation’s largest operator of civilian nuclear reactors, who sat on a panel of 25 at a conference organized by the Idaho National Laboratory of the Energy Department and a private group called the Third Way. Another member, Steven Chu, energy secretary, said that while new reactors were likely to be important industrial assets for 60 or 70 years, the market was focused on the short term. Low prices for natural gas, a competing fuel, and the collapse of efforts to impose a price on carbon dioxide emissions make the economic climate for new reactors quite unfavorable at the moment, he added. The administration is seeking the expansion of a loan guarantee program but has so far been unable to commit all of the loan guarantee money already approved by Congress. “In addition to loan guarantees, you need an environment that’s right, that makes it look like a good investment,’’ Dr. Chu said. But many of those factors, including the price of natural gas, are obviously beyond federal control, raising substantial doubts about how much the government could do to encourage new nuclear construction. Carol Browner, the president’s adviser on energy and climate, quoted President Obama as saying that while nuclear power was highly important to the nation’s energy supply, even some factors that the government does control through legislation may not go the way the nuclear industry wants. “A price on carbon would be hugely beneficial to this industry,’’ she said. But Congress has failed to approve a cap on carbon, she said, and “that may not be possible in the near term.’’ The Environmental Protection Agency is developing a rule to limit carbon dioxide emissions but could be blocked by the new Congress. “If it isn’t possible, what are the alternatives?’’ she said. In recent years, the utilities have shown an interest in about 30 new reactors, but the number with any serious prospect of being built is now down to about a dozen. Of the 104 plants now operating, ground was broken on all of them in 1974 or earlier. Not everyone on the panel was convinced that the demise of the nuclear renaissance was bad. Peter Bradford, a former member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and a former chairman of the public service commissions of both New York and Maine, said the technology was probably just too expensive. One challenge for the industry is to build reactors on budget and on schedule. “On budget isn’t going to do it if on budget means it’s going to sell 12-cent-a-kilowatt-hour power in a 5- cent-a-kilowatt-hour market,” he reflected. A greater reliance on nuclear power would reduce emissions of greenhouse gases that change the climate, he said, but harnessing nuclear power for that purpose was like using “caviar to fight world hunger,’’ he said. Yet another former member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, James K. Asselstine, now the managing director of high grade credit research at Barclays Capital, suggested that a window for new reactors might reopen. Demand for electricity had been growing by about 1 to 1.5 percent a year, but has actually fallen in the last two years, so it is now about 8 percent below where it would have been had no recession emerged, he said. And in the next year, a large number of old coal-fired plants are likely to be retired because of pending rules from the Environmental Protection Agency on the emission of pollutants like sulfur dioxide, soot and mercury. When that coal-fired capacity is gone, he said, nuclear’s prospects might look brighter. In a public session that lasted a little over two hours, there were few truly new ideas or even new laments. But Mr. Pardee did raise one idea that has not received much consideration. In the parts of the country where his company’s 17 reactors are operating, he said, electricity is sold in a daily auction. A company that is seeking to build reactors must arrive at estimates of the future value of the production, he noted. To encourage construction, perhaps the federal government, itself the country’s largest electricity consumer, could agree to a long-term power purchase agreement from a reactor at a preset price, he suggested. Or a fixed price could be guaranteed for the carbon dioxide not emitted, he said. The panelists, including Senator Tom Carper, Democrat of Delaware, and Senator George Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, who led the session, then adjourned and left deputies to formulate recommendations. The Obama administration seemed open to suggestions. As Dr. Chu noted, while the price of natural gas is low now, no one can say what it will be over the likely lifetime of a new reactor. So, “the government has to say, ‘O.K., for the best long-term interest of the country, what do we need to do?’’’ he said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/23/business/23nuke.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Zion Nuclear Plant to Decommission in Novel Way<date>Published: November 22, 2010</date><text>ZION, Ill. — Twelve years ago, Commonwealth Edison found itself in a bind.The Zion Station, its twin-unit nuclear reactor here, was no longer profitable. But the company could not afford to tear it down: the cost of dismantling the vast steel and concrete building, with multiple areas of radioactive contamination, would exceed $1 billion, double what it had cost to build the reactors in the 1970s. Nor could Commonwealth Edison walk away from the plant, because of the contamination. The result was that Zion Station sat in limbo for more than a decade, and Commonwealth Edison, now part of Exelon, paid about $10 million a year to baby-sit the defunct reactor. Now, though, the company is trying out a radical new approach to decommissioning the plant that promises to make the process faster, simpler and 25 percent less expensive — instead of hiring a contractor, it has turned the job and the reactors over to a nuclear demolition company that owns a nuclear dump site. The cost will be covered by the $900 million that Exelon accumulated in a decommissioning fund. If the approach is successful, it could have implications for 10 other nuclear plants around the country that are waiting to be decommissioned, and for the 104 reactors that are still in operation but will eventually be torn down. It will also save money for electricity customers, who often end up paying for the cleanup of nuclear plants through their utility bills. The decommissioning operation at Zion, which began on Sept. 1, will skip one of the slowest, dirtiest and most costly parts of tearing down a nuclear plant: separating radioactive materials, which must go to a licensed dump, from nonradioactive materials, which can go to an ordinary industrial landfill. The new idea is not to bother sorting the two. Instead, anything that could include radioactive contamination will be treated as radioactive waste. Exelon could never have done this on its own, because the fee for disposing of radioactive waste was too high. But the company has given the reactor to EnergySolutions, a conglomerate that includes companies that have long done nuclear cleanups, and which also owns a nuclear dump. “This is a first-of-a-kind arrangement,” said Adam H. Levin, director of spent fuel and decommissioning at Exelon. He added that others could do the job for less than Exelon and acknowledged, “utilities in general are not very good at tearing plants down.” Government regulations require that nuclear reactor sites be thoroughly decontaminated, so that they can be released for re-use — often a lengthy process. The plan is to return Zion’s site, in the midst of parkland on the Lake Michigan shore north of Chicago, to re-use by 2020 — 12 years earlier than expected under Exelon’s original plan, which was to begin in 2013 and finish in 2032. Any money left over from the $900 million in the plant’s decommissioning fund goes back to electricity customers in the Chicago area. On Sept. 1, Exelon transferred ownership, along with the license issued by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, to EnergySolutions, which is based in Salt Lake City. The company owns a one-square-mile area of desert about 70 miles west of there, in Clive, Utah, where most of the Zion plant is supposed to be shipped. The dump in Clive already has parts of several other defunct nuclear plants — including Maine Yankee in Wiscasset, Me., and Yankee Rowe in Rowe, Mass. In those two cases, the reactor owners tried to sort the radioactive materials from the nonradioactive, in order to dispose of ordinary concrete and steel at recycling centers or industrial landfills. It turned out to be a costly mistake, many in the industry now say. Workers used a device like a pneumatic drill to “scabble” the concrete, knocking off the surface layer. “It got to be very, very complicated and nasty work,” said Andrew C. Kadak, a nuclear consultant who at the time was president of the company that operated Yankee Rowe. Often, he said, a survey would find that the concrete was not clean, or worse: that a tiny bit of radioactive material was mistakenly shipped to a “clean” landfill. “It’s easier to suppose everything is radioactive,” Mr. Kadak said. Sometimes a contractor hired to decommission plants would also find radioactive material in unexpected places or at unexpectedly high levels, other experts said. Crowds of workers would stand idle while the contractor sought the plant owner’s authorization to deviate from the procedures specified in the contract — a costly proposition at a site with 500 workers paid collectively “$30,000 to $50,000 an hour,” said John A. Christian, president of the Commercial Services subsidiary of EnergySolutions. At Rowe, managers finally gave up and shipped vast amounts of concrete, much of it clean, to the repository in Clive. The new plan for Zion, by far the largest nuclear power plant to be decommissioned and the first twin-unit reactor to be torn down, eliminates the relationship between contractor and owner. EnergySolutions has hardly any internal cost for burial, beyond shipping. Mark Walker, a spokesman for EnergySolutions, said that the dump could accommodate all 104 of the nation’s operating nuclear plants, “with space left over.” It could also absorb plants that are shut and awaiting decommissioning, like Indian Point 1 in Buchanan, N.Y.; Millstone 1 in Waterford, Conn.; and Three Mile Island 2, near Harrisburg, Pa., the site of the 1979 accident. Not everyone is delighted with the idea of Exelon turning the job over to EnergySolutions. Tom Rielly, the executive principal of Vista 360, a community group in nearby Libertyville, Ill., said that with a monopoly provider of dump space also functioning as the contractor, it would be difficult to determine what was being charged for disposal and whether electricity customers were getting a good deal. But approval from utility regulators in Illinois was not required for the deal, and the Nuclear Regulatory Commission gave its assent, so the work is going forward. EnergySolutions cannot dispose of all the waste. Clive is licensed only for the least contaminated material. And the spent nuclear fuel is in the same situation as used reactor fuel all over the country: the Energy Department is under contract to take it, but has no place to dispose of it. Until a permanent repository is built at the proposed Yucca Mountain facility in Nevada or another location, the waste will stay at the Zion site in steel and concrete casks built to last for decades. Frank Flammini, a control room operator, has worked at the Zion Station since before it shut down. The room, filled with 1970s-style dials, used to have at least six people around the clock, but on a recent afternoon he sat alone in the control room with his coffee cup, next to the one modern piece of equipment, a flat-panel display showing the temperature, water level and humidity of the room housing the spent fuel. Mr. Flammini, 54, said he was called on now and then to make sure equipment was “tagged out” so that workers could safely dismantle it. But hours go by with little to do. The parking lot of Zion is so quiet these days that the raccoons and skunks have been joined by shy species like coyote. Mr. Flammini said he knew his job here was not permanent. “It’ll get very busy for about four years, and then it’ll go away entirely,” he said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/17/business/energy-environment/17NUCLEAR.html?ref=exeloncorporation">G.O.P. Gains May Not Advance Nuclear Power<date>Published: November 16, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTONTHE outspoken supporters of nuclear power are mostly Republicans, and the Republicans are about to take control of the House of Representatives and gain six seats in the Senate. Is this good news for nuclear power? Maybe. But the outlook for a new wave of reactors is still mixed at best. Many prominent Republicans say the United States should embark on a building campaign. Senator John McCain of Arizona, as the party’s 2008 presidential nominee, called for 45 more reactors by 2030, and Senator Lamar Alexander of Tennessee, wants 100 more reactors by then. But the party dislikes something that the nuclear industry needs: global warming rules. Republican progress in the midterm elections probably dooms prospects for a cap-and-trade system on carbon dioxide emissions for now. A price of, say, $20 a ton on carbon emissions would give coal-fired power plants a handicap of about 2 cents a kilowatt-hour and natural gas-fired plants about a penny a kilowatt-hour, large sums for a commodity that sells for an average of 10 cents a kilowatt-hour. Under such a system, nuclear power would face no charges. And while various Republicans may want to see reactors built, the government does not build them; private companies do. “The business environment is a principal driver in what the future of nuclear energy is in the United States,” Alex Flint, the senior vice president for government affairs at the industry’s trade association, the Nuclear Energy Institute, said recently. “How long is the recession going to last?” he asked. “What impact is that going to have on the overall economy? When are we going to see demand forecasts pick up?” A related question is when the price of natural gas, a competing fuel, will rise. These considerations weigh on more than just nuclear reactor construction. “There’s a whole lot of solar and wind that ain’t happening now too,” said Stewart Brand, the creator of the Whole Earth Catalog and a Silicon Valley commentator, who favors more reactors. The “nuclear renaissance” may seem mostly stalled, he said, but “a fair question to ask is, what’s the state of the wind renaissance?” An event in New York just before the election illustrates the problem. Électricité de France, eager to build in this country, ended a partnership with Constellation Energy, of Baltimore, to build a third unit at Constellation’s Calvert Cliffs complex in Maryland, because Constellation said that, with the loan terms that the Energy Department was offering, the economics were not favorable for a “merchant” plant that would sell its output in the daily power auction. In the breakup, the French company acquired a site for a reactor, adjacent to the Nine Mile Point Nuclear Station reactors, near Oswego, N.Y. But the price of electricity in the wholesale market in New York has crashed, at least in the short term. It fell from about $95 a megawatt hour in 2008 to $47 last year, and has only partly recovered. The election will not change that, unless the economy revives sharply, and the manufacturing sector, always a huge consumer of power, comes back. Robert E. Curry Jr., a member of the New York State Public Service Commission, said he could not discuss the Oswego site because the issue might come before the commission, but he spoke about the Maryland plant. “If you’ve got Calvert Cliffs 3, a merchant plant, that’s likely going to cost north of $10.5 billion, and a loan guarantee of $8.5 billion, then you then have to borrow much of the balance, $2 billion,” he said. “With natural gas prices as suppressed as they are, what kind of revenues can you pledge to lenders where the marginal price of electricity is set by gas?” “It’s almost unfinanceable in today’s environment,” he said. “I don’t see how the election changes that for good or ill.” Another indication that the problem may be beyond the powers of Congress comes from Exelon, the nation’s largest nuclear reactor operator, which is not planning any new reactors now. John W. Rowe, the chairman of Exelon, said recently that his company would not break ground until the price of natural gas was more than double today’s level and carbon emissions cost $25 a ton. Nationwide, ground has been broken for just four reactors, two twin-unit nuclear plants since the 1970s. Work is limited to digging the foundations and other site preparation, but both expect that within a few months they will get licenses to construct and operate their reactors. Both are in locations that are insulated from the market, in Georgia and South Carolina. In both locations, the business risk rests with the ratepayers, not with the shareholders. Two proposals were selected by the Energy Department for potential government help, in the form of loan guarantees, one in Texas and the other the Calvert Cliffs project in Maryland. In both places, most electricity is sold in a daily auction, and prices are depressed by gas prices. A Republican House may push Congress toward two steps that would help the nuclear industry: reviving the Yucca Mountain project, which might promise a long-term solution for nuclear waste, and providing more money for loan guarantees and perhaps easing the terms the federal government demands for those guarantees. But President Obama was already enthusiastic about more loan guarantees. And as for Yucca, the Senate majority leader, Harry Reid of Nevada, is bitterly opposed, and he survived the Republican tide. The Energy Department sought to revoke its application for a license for Yucca, and the Nuclear Regulatory Commission had begun preliminary work on determining whether it will let the Energy Department do that. In the meantime, Mr. Obama appointed a commission to consider alternative uses for spent nuclear fuel, including recycling options, and a draft report is expected in May. But it is not looking for new sites. The commission could take other steps, such as endorsing reprocessing, in which uranium and plutonium that can be used in reactors is scavenged from the used fuel, or it could recommend advanced reactors that would destroy the long-lived wastes. Some Republicans favor those ideas. John Reed, an investment banker who specializes in nuclear power plant sales, said the new Congress might “have more of an appetite to tackle the issue now.” “Right now we have zero solutions,” he added. “Anything would be an improvement.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/11/business/energy-environment/11power.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Sluggish Economy Curtails Prospects for Building Nuclear Reactors<date>Published: October 10, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTON — Just a few years ago, the economic prognosis for new nuclear reactors looked bright. The prospect of growing electricity demand, probable caps on carbon-dioxide emissions and government loan guarantees prompted companies to tell the Nuclear Regulatory Commission that they wanted to build 28 new reactors.The economic slump, which has driven down demand and the price of competing energy sources, and the failure of Congress to pass climate legislation has changed all that, at least for now. Constellation Energy’s announcement on Saturday that it had reached an impasse with the federal government over the fee for a loan guarantee on a new reactor in Maryland is a sign of how much the landscape has been transformed. Essentially, the Energy Department argued that Constellation’s project is so risky that the company must pay a high fee or provide other assurances of repayment if it wants the taxpayers to guarantee its construction loans. Constellation said the government’s demand was “unreasonably burdensome.” The government is hardly the only one to question the economics of nuclear power right now. The would-be builders of seven reactors around the country have deferred their projects in the last few months. J. Scott Peterson, a spokesman for the Nuclear Energy Institute, the industry’s trade group, said the “pause” in nuclear building plans mirrors delays in other industrial projects. “It’s principally because of the economic situation,” he said. One major factor driving the cautious stance of both the industry and the government is the fall in electricity demand, which peaked in 2007. In 2009, demand dropped by more than 4 percent from 2007. So far, it seems that demand in 2010 will be higher than last year, but not as high as 2007. These are big changes for an industry that is accustomed to growth on the order of 1 to 3 percent a year. With slack demand, there is less urgency to build new plants. The plunge in the price of natural gas has also made nuclear power far less competitive. The year the recession began, 2008, the standard unit of natural gas, one million British thermal units, sold for an average of $7.96 at the well head. Last year the same amount of gas cost just $3.71, according to preliminary Energy Department figures, and for the first six months of this year, it cost $4.43. A return to strong economic growth would push up the demand for electricity and for natural gas, but even then, natural gas prices may remain low because a technology called hydraulic fracturing has vastly increased the estimate of recoverable reserves. Also weighing on the nuclear industry is the unwillingness of Congress to pass climate change legislation that would put a price of some sort on carbon-dioxide emissions. Since nuclear power produces no carbon emissions, it would gain a competitive edge against coal and natural gas if a bill were passed. But while such legislation once seemed likely, sharp divisions in Congress and concerns about the tottering economy have stalled its prospects. Putting all that together, the Energy Department evaluated Constellation’s proposal the way a bank would look at a prospective credit card customer or home buyer and set the fee according to the borrower’s creditworthiness. Under a program created by Congress, Constellation was seeking a guarantee for 80 percent of the cost of the project. The government settled on a fee of $880 million, or 11.6 percent of the $7.6 billion loan, according to Constellation. In a letter to the Energy Department, the company called the figure “shockingly high” and said it would doom the project. Other companies have looked at the economics of building new nuclear reactors and decided to wait. In September, Exelon, the largest nuclear operator in the United States, stepped back from a plan to build a twin-unit reactor plant in Texas and decided to simply seek approval for the site, which would save it some time if it decided later to build. Exelon said it needs natural gas prices to reach about $8 per million B.T.U. — almost double today’s price — and a carbon fee of $25 a ton to make the project worthwhile economically. “We don’t have the right stimulus right now,” said Christopher M. Crane, president and chief operating officer, in a recent interview. Two utilities in Florida, Progress Energy and FPL, each want to build twin-unit reactors but have slowed their projects down. A Missouri utility has backed away from a plan to build a carbon copy of the Constellation Maryland reactor. Nuclear plant operators like Exelon and Constellation face particular challenges because after deregulation in their states, they must compete against other energy suppliers to sell electricity to the companies that actually distribute energy to customers. Two nuclear projects that have gone forward, in Georgia and South Carolina, are in states where the utilities building them also distribute the electricity and operate under traditional regulatory rules that virtually guarantee them a financial return: Whatever the companies spend to generate power, the customers will pay for, unless regulators decide the expenses were not “prudent.” That regulatory compact is so strong that the South Carolina project, on the site of the existing V. C. Summer reactor, has begun work without a loan guarantee. In Constellation’s case, the Energy Department proposed that Constellation reduce the risk of financial failure by signing a contract with its regulated subsidiary, Baltimore Gas &amp; Electric, to buy 75 percent of the new reactor’s output at a price that would allow Constellation to repay the loan. That idea would require approval of state regulators, but state officials have generally favored construction of the reactor. Such a contract would limit the builders’ upside possibilities, however, and Constellation has not pursued the idea. A spokeswoman for the Energy Department, Stephanie Mueller, said the parties were still working on a compromise. “We urge Constellation and its partner to examine the latest terms and continue working on this project important to bringing about the clean-energy economy of the future and creating many needed jobs,” she said. Some nuclear advocates say that pure economics should not be an overriding concern. Constellation Energy argues that its reactor is less risky than the government’s assessment indicates. The Maryland reactor would be the sixth or seventh instance of a new design, with Finland, France and China working out the kinks first, according to James L. Connaughton, executive vice president of Constellation Energy. He said that Constellation and its partner, Électricité de France, are experienced at this kind of job, and thus the fee from the government should be 1 or 2 percent of the guarantee. The reactor’s construction will provide thousands of well-paying jobs and clean power for decades, he said, if only the government would make a more realistic assessment of risk. But Michael Mariotte, executive director of the antinuclear group Nuclear Information and Resource Service, predicted that Constellation and the nuclear industry will experience no renaissance for the most simple of reasons: “nuclear reactors make no economic sense.”</text></article><article index="5" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/08/31/a-nuclear-giant-moves-into-wind/?ref=exeloncorporation">A Nuclear Giant Moves Into Wind<date>August 31, 2010, 7:10 pm</date><text>Exelon Corporation John Rowe, chief executive of Exelon. Exelon, the nuclear giant that recently backed away from building new nuclear plants, is moving into wind. The company announced on Wednesday that it was buying John Deere Renewables, which has 735 megawatts in operation and 230 megawatts in “advanced stages of development” in Michigan. The price was $860 million, plus $40 million if ground is broken on the Michigan projects. In March, Exelon withdrew its application for a construction and operating license for a twin-unit nuclear plant in Victoria County, Tex., citing lower projections for electric demand because of the recession. It had stopped work on the application last year. Instead, it asked the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for preapproval of the site, which would speed up the approval process if it decided later that it wanted to build. But the decision left the country’s largest nuclear operator without a direct role in what the nuclear industry hopes is a renaissance. But the company says it is sticking by its commitment two years ago to cut its carbon dioxide output in 2020 by 15 million metric tons of carbon dioxide or its equivalent in other greenhouse gases. That would be more than its total emissions in 2001, the company said. The purchase will instantly make Exelon one of the nation’s largest wind operators. John Rowe, the chief executive, who has been urging Congress to pass climate change legislation, said in a statement that the purchase was “one more way to implement a clean energy future.” The prospects for that legislation are unclear, and the Environmental Protection Agency may simply order carbon emission reductions. Mr. Rowe said, “Whether harmful emissions are priced or regulated, our combined capacity of nearly 19,000 megawatts of zero-emission wind, solar, hydro, landfill gas and nuclear power remains a clear competitive advantage that will only become more valuable.”</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/30/opinion/30wed3.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Way Behind the Curve<date>Published: September 29, 2009</date><text>The United States Chamber of Commerce’s Web site says the group supports “a comprehensive legislative solution” to global warming. Yet no organization in this country has done more to undermine such legislation. In the last Congress, the chamber attacked the rather modest Lieberman-Warner bill, with a Harry-and-Louise-style commercial. This year, it testified against the House-passed bill limiting greenhouse gases, and it is almost sure to oppose a similar measure that will be introduced this week in the Senate. The chamber has now declared war on the Environmental Protection Agency’s plan to use regulatory means to control emissions  beginning with one official’s ill-advised (and since apologized-for) demand for a “Scopes monkey trial” questioning the science behind the agency’s preliminary finding that greenhouse gas emissions endanger human health. Some responsible chamber members are so fed up that they are quitting. First out the door was Pacific Gas &amp; Electric, the big California utility whose chief executive, Peter Darbee, last week lambasted the chamber’s “extreme rhetoric and obstructionist tactics.” Two other big utilities, PNM Resources and Exelon, also announced their intention to leave the organization for similar reasons. While stopping short of quitting, Johnson &amp; Johnson has criticized the chamber’s actions. Some suggested that this was little more than a marketing strategy. It may indeed be good marketing, but most of all it is smart business. These companies are members of the United States Climate Action Partnership, a coalition of businesses and environmental groups that early this year came up with a plan for limiting emissions that helped shape the House bill. They see a carbon-constrained world coming and want to get out ahead of the curve  not behind it like the chamber. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on September 30, 2009, on page A30 of the New York edition.The United States Chamber of Commerce’s Web site says the group supports “a comprehensive legislative solution” to global warming. Yet no organization in this country has done more to undermine such legislation. In the last Congress, the chamber attacked the rather modest Lieberman-Warner bill, with a Harry-and-Louise-style commercial. This year, it testified against the House-passed bill limiting greenhouse gases, and it is almost sure to oppose a similar measure that will be introduced this week in the Senate. The chamber has now declared war on the Environmental Protection Agency’s plan to use regulatory means to control emissions  beginning with one official’s ill-advised (and since apologized-for) demand for a “Scopes monkey trial” questioning the science behind the agency’s preliminary finding that greenhouse gas emissions endanger human health. Some responsible chamber members are so fed up that they are quitting. First out the door was Pacific Gas &amp; Electric, the big California utility whose chief executive, Peter Darbee, last week lambasted the chamber’s “extreme rhetoric and obstructionist tactics.” Two other big utilities, PNM Resources and Exelon, also announced their intention to leave the organization for similar reasons. While stopping short of quitting, Johnson &amp; Johnson has criticized the chamber’s actions. Some suggested that this was little more than a marketing strategy. It may indeed be good marketing, but most of all it is smart business. These companies are members of the United States Climate Action Partnership, a coalition of businesses and environmental groups that early this year came up with a plan for limiting emissions that helped shape the House bill. They see a carbon-constrained world coming and want to get out ahead of the curve  not behind it like the chamber.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/29/business/energy-environment/29chamber.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Climate Bill Splits Exelon and U.S. Chamber<date>Published: September 28, 2009</date><text>Exelon, one of the country’s largest utilities, said Monday that it would quit the United States Chamber of Commerce because of that group’s stance on climate change. It was the latest in a string of companies to do so, perhaps a harbinger of how intense the fight over global warming legislation could become. Skip to next paragraph Andrew Harrer/Bloomberg News John W. Rowe, the chief executive of Exelon. The utility disagrees with the chambers stance on climate change. Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » “The carbon-based free lunch is over,” said John W. Rowe, Exelon’s chief executive. “Breakthroughs on climate change and improving our society’s energy efficiency are within reach.” A wave of departures from the chamber has been building for weeks. It was heralded Monday by some Congressional Democrats and environmentalists as a sign that the business community’s opposition to global warming legislation is weakening. In their view, that improves the chances that a global warming bill that narrowly passed the House in June might also pass the Senate. But others said the resignations were just a sign that businesses will have varied positions depending on whether they will be winners or losers from the legislation. Exelon, a Chicago company that sells electricity and gas in four states, is also the country’s largest operator of nuclear power plants. That type of electrical generation emits no greenhouse gases and would gain a financial advantage under the pending bills. “There will be significant vibrations from this,” said Representative Jay Inslee, a Democrat of Washington State on the Energy and Commerce Committee. “It’s a bit of an earthquake.” Pacific Gas &amp; Electric, the dominant utility in Northern California, and PNM Resources, a holding company that includes the largest utility in New Mexico, said recently that they would withdraw from the national chamber. Mr. Rowe said Exelon would not renew its membership because of the chamber’s “stridency against carbon legislation.” The United States Chamber of Commerce is one of the main business lobbies in Washington, with more than three million members. It says it not opposed in principle to tackling global warming, but is worried about any approach that would raise costs for businesses. The chamber has been especially vocal recently in opposing a proposal by the Environmental Protection Agency to use an existing law, the Clean Air Act, to set limits on greenhouse gases. The proposal would most likely take effect only if Congress failed to pass climate legislation. The utilities and other companies that are supporting climate change legislation tend to be those based in more liberal parts of the country and believe that being viewed as environmentally responsible is a good marketing strategy, energy and business analysts said. The utilities tend to be dependent on sources like nuclear power that emit fewer greenhouse gas emissions than their competitors. Before, “voicing their good fortune among higher-carbon colleagues was seen as impolite,” said Paul Bledsoe, director of communications and strategy at the National Commission on Energy Policy, a bipartisan research organization. “Now that legislation seems imminent, these companies are stepping up to support legislation because it helps their bottom lines.” What appears to have touched off the utilities’ withdrawals from the chamber was a recent article in The Los Angeles Times that cited chamber officials who called for a “Scopes monkey trial of the 21st century” about the science of climate change. The Scopes trial was a clash of creationists and evolutionists in the 1920s. Both PG&amp;E and PNM cited the possibility of such a trial as a major concern. Don Brown, a PNM spokesman, said in a statement that his company felt compelled to “particularly reject” the chamber’s “recent theatrics calling for a ‘Scopes monkey trial’ to put the science of climate change on trial.” However, David C. Chavern, the chamber’s chief operating officer, said there had been a misunderstanding. Chamber officials do not question the overall science of climate change, but rather, the group questions whether that science is enough to support the E.P.A.’s rulemaking under the specific legal requirements of the Clean Air Act. “We’re not looking at the next Scopes monkey trial,” he said. “We just think the E.P.A. is the wrong venue to be dealing with climate change issues that will impact the whole country and whole world.” He said another chamber official’s reference to the Scopes trial “was wrong, inaccurate and obscured what the chamber is really doing.” Other companies have also expressed differences with the chamber recently. Nike has said in a statement that it “fundamentally disagrees with the U.S. Chamber of Commerce’s position on climate change and is concerned and deeply disappointed with the U.S. Chamber’s recently filed petition challenging the E.P.A.’s administrative authority and action on this critically important issue.” Johnson &amp; Johnson, the big consumer products company, urged in a letter this spring that the chamber’s statements on climate change “reflect the full range of views, especially those of chamber members advocating for Congressional action” on global warming. Duke Energy, a large Southern utility that supports action against global warming, has so far stayed in the national chamber, but it withdrew from of the National Association of Manufacturers in December, citing climate as a partial factor. The manufacturers’ group has also been wary of action by the E.P.A. In August, Duke Energy also left the American Coalition for Clean Coal Electricity, citing climate policy. “It was clear that many influential members would never support climate legislation in 2009 or 2010 no matter how it was written,” Tom Williams, a Duke Energy spokesman, said in an e-mail message. Alcoa, the aluminum company, also pulled out of the coal coalition this summer, with climate policy being one factor, a spokesman said. “This is an issue that will cleave a lot of companies more than other business policy issues because there are sharper differences in strategies,” said Matthew J. Slaughter, associate dean of the Tuck School of Business at Dartmouth College. He noted that a utility that primarily used coal would logically have a different view from one dependent on nuclear power. Climate change legislation still faces a tough battle in the Senate, where legislators from coal states will seek to protect the coal industry, and where many Republicans are opposed to any action they believe would put American businesses at a disadvantage. Senator Jeff Bingaman, a New Mexico Democrat and chairman of the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said he did not know what impact the recent corporate policy announcements would have on individual senators. “But I do think it’s a sign at least some in the business community are anxious to see us provide some leadership on climate change,” he added. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 29, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.Exelon, one of the country’s largest utilities, said Monday that it would quit the United States Chamber of Commerce because of that group’s stance on climate change. It was the latest in a string of companies to do so, perhaps a harbinger of how intense the fight over global warming legislation could become. Skip to next paragraph Andrew Harrer/Bloomberg News John W. Rowe, the chief executive of Exelon. The utility disagrees with the chambers stance on climate change. Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » “The carbon-based free lunch is over,” said John W. Rowe, Exelon’s chief executive. “Breakthroughs on climate change and improving our society’s energy efficiency are within reach.” A wave of departures from the chamber has been building for weeks. It was heralded Monday by some Congressional Democrats and environmentalists as a sign that the business community’s opposition to global warming legislation is weakening. In their view, that improves the chances that a global warming bill that narrowly passed the House in June might also pass the Senate. But others said the resignations were just a sign that businesses will have varied positions depending on whether they will be winners or losers from the legislation. Exelon, a Chicago company that sells electricity and gas in four states, is also the country’s largest operator of nuclear power plants. That type of electrical generation emits no greenhouse gases and would gain a financial advantage under the pending bills. “There will be significant vibrations from this,” said Representative Jay Inslee, a Democrat of Washington State on the Energy and Commerce Committee. “It’s a bit of an earthquake.” Pacific Gas &amp; Electric, the dominant utility in Northern California, and PNM Resources, a holding company that includes the largest utility in New Mexico, said recently that they would withdraw from the national chamber. Mr. Rowe said Exelon would not renew its membership because of the chamber’s “stridency against carbon legislation.” The United States Chamber of Commerce is one of the main business lobbies in Washington, with more than three million members. It says it not opposed in principle to tackling global warming, but is worried about any approach that would raise costs for businesses. The chamber has been especially vocal recently in opposing a proposal by the Environmental Protection Agency to use an existing law, the Clean Air Act, to set limits on greenhouse gases. The proposal would most likely take effect only if Congress failed to pass climate legislation. The utilities and other companies that are supporting climate change legislation tend to be those based in more liberal parts of the country and believe that being viewed as environmentally responsible is a good marketing strategy, energy and business analysts said. The utilities tend to be dependent on sources like nuclear power that emit fewer greenhouse gas emissions than their competitors. Before, “voicing their good fortune among higher-carbon colleagues was seen as impolite,” said Paul Bledsoe, director of communications and strategy at the National Commission on Energy Policy, a bipartisan research organization. “Now that legislation seems imminent, these companies are stepping up to support legislation because it helps their bottom lines.” What appears to have touched off the utilities’ withdrawals from the chamber was a recent article in The Los Angeles Times that cited chamber officials who called for a “Scopes monkey trial of the 21st century” about the science of climate change. The Scopes trial was a clash of creationists and evolutionists in the 1920s. Both PG&amp;E and PNM cited the possibility of such a trial as a major concern. Don Brown, a PNM spokesman, said in a statement that his company felt compelled to “particularly reject” the chamber’s “recent theatrics calling for a ‘Scopes monkey trial’ to put the science of climate change on trial.” However, David C. Chavern, the chamber’s chief operating officer, said there had been a misunderstanding. Chamber officials do not question the overall science of climate change, but rather, the group questions whether that science is enough to support the E.P.A.’s rulemaking under the specific legal requirements of the Clean Air Act. “We’re not looking at the next Scopes monkey trial,” he said. “We just think the E.P.A. is the wrong venue to be dealing with climate change issues that will impact the whole country and whole world.” He said another chamber official’s reference to the Scopes trial “was wrong, inaccurate and obscured what the chamber is really doing.” Other companies have also expressed differences with the chamber recently. Nike has said in a statement that it “fundamentally disagrees with the U.S. Chamber of Commerce’s position on climate change and is concerned and deeply disappointed with the U.S. Chamber’s recently filed petition challenging the E.P.A.’s administrative authority and action on this critically important issue.” Johnson &amp; Johnson, the big consumer products company, urged in a letter this spring that the chamber’s statements on climate change “reflect the full range of views, especially those of chamber members advocating for Congressional action” on global warming. Duke Energy, a large Southern utility that supports action against global warming, has so far stayed in the national chamber, but it withdrew from of the National Association of Manufacturers in December, citing climate as a partial factor. The manufacturers’ group has also been wary of action by the E.P.A. In August, Duke Energy also left the American Coalition for Clean Coal Electricity, citing climate policy. “It was clear that many influential members would never support climate legislation in 2009 or 2010 no matter how it was written,” Tom Williams, a Duke Energy spokesman, said in an e-mail message. Alcoa, the aluminum company, also pulled out of the coal coalition this summer, with climate policy being one factor, a spokesman said. “This is an issue that will cleave a lot of companies more than other business policy issues because there are sharper differences in strategies,” said Matthew J. Slaughter, associate dean of the Tuck School of Business at Dartmouth College. He noted that a utility that primarily used coal would logically have a different view from one dependent on nuclear power. Climate change legislation still faces a tough battle in the Senate, where legislators from coal states will seek to protect the coal industry, and where many Republicans are opposed to any action they believe would put American businesses at a disadvantage. Senator Jeff Bingaman, a New Mexico Democrat and chairman of the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said he did not know what impact the recent corporate policy announcements would have on individual senators. “But I do think it’s a sign at least some in the business community are anxious to see us provide some leadership on climate change,” he added.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/22/business/22exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Drops Its Bid for NRG Energy<date>Published: July 21, 2009</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, the utility company, dropped a $7.53 billion offer for NRG Energy after shareholders rejected its board nominees, ending a nine-month takeover battle. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » Stockholders voted Tuesday in Princeton, N.J., where NRG is based, to elect the company’s slate of four directors over independent candidates nominated by Exelon. Investors also voted down a proposed expansion of the board to make room for five other Exelon nominees, according to results announced on Tuesday at NRG’s annual meeting. NRG said about 75 percent of shareholder votes were cast in favor of its director nominees. “The NRG shareholders have spoken, and Exelon will move on,” John W. Rowe, Exelon’s chief executive, said in a statement. He said he was unwilling to raise the offer to a level that would “undermine Exelon’s own value proposition.” It was the third acquisition in six years that Exelon had dropped. NRG is better off now that it can focus on running its business, said Brandon Blossman, an analyst at Tudor, Pickering, Holt &amp; Company in Houston. Exelon took its offer directly to shareholders after NRG’s board rejected its original bid in October. Last month, Exelon, the largest American operator of nuclear power plants, raised its all-stock bid 12 percent, to 0.545 share for each NRG share. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on July 22, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.The Exelon Corporation, the utility company, dropped a $7.53 billion offer for NRG Energy after shareholders rejected its board nominees, ending a nine-month takeover battle. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » Stockholders voted Tuesday in Princeton, N.J., where NRG is based, to elect the company’s slate of four directors over independent candidates nominated by Exelon. Investors also voted down a proposed expansion of the board to make room for five other Exelon nominees, according to results announced on Tuesday at NRG’s annual meeting. NRG said about 75 percent of shareholder votes were cast in favor of its director nominees. “The NRG shareholders have spoken, and Exelon will move on,” John W. Rowe, Exelon’s chief executive, said in a statement. He said he was unwilling to raise the offer to a level that would “undermine Exelon’s own value proposition.” It was the third acquisition in six years that Exelon had dropped. NRG is better off now that it can focus on running its business, said Brandon Blossman, an analyst at Tudor, Pickering, Holt &amp; Company in Houston. Exelon took its offer directly to shareholders after NRG’s board rejected its original bid in October. Last month, Exelon, the largest American operator of nuclear power plants, raised its all-stock bid 12 percent, to 0.545 share for each NRG share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/03/business/03exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Makes a Higher Offer in Its Long Pursuit of NRG<date>Published: July 2, 2009</date><text>The Exelon Corporation said Thursday that it had raised its hostile bid for NRG Energy, a rival power producer, to nearly $7.5 billion in stock, marking the latest twist in the months-long takeover feud. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » In its new offer, Exelon said NRG shareholders would receive 0.545 of an Exelon share for each share of NRG stock. That ratio is 12.4 percent higher than the initial offer by Exelon in October. Based on Wednesday’s closing prices, the new Exelon bid values each NRG share at about $28.10, which is nearly 8 percent above NRG’s closing price. NRG, a wholesale power generator based in Princeton, N.J., had repeatedly urged its shareholders not to accept Exelon’s previous offer, calling it “inadequate and uncertain.” But it has said that it remained open to a deal at a “fair price.” Exelon’s new offer values NRG at about $7.45 billion, based on NRG’s 265.3 million outstanding shares. In October, Exelon offered $6.2 billion in stock for NRG. Exelon said that part of the reason it was able to raise its offer was that it found about $1.5 billion in additional cost savings that would flow from a merger. Exelon also factored in NRG’s recent acquisition of Reliant Energy’s retail business in Texas in making the new proposal. “An exhaustive analysis by our internal team, informed by the best third-party experts, resulted in additional synergies, allowing us to increase our offer to NRG shareholders,” John Rowe, Exelon’s chairman and chief executive, said in a statement. He added that the latest bid was Exelon’s “best and final offer.” In response, NRG urged its shareholders to “take no action at this time” on the latest offer until its board is able to review it. Shares of both companies traded lower on Thursday. NRG’s decline was a bit steeper, suggesting that investors might have expected a bigger increase in Exelon’s bid. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on July 3, 2009, on page B8 of the New York edition.The Exelon Corporation said Thursday that it had raised its hostile bid for NRG Energy, a rival power producer, to nearly $7.5 billion in stock, marking the latest twist in the months-long takeover feud. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » In its new offer, Exelon said NRG shareholders would receive 0.545 of an Exelon share for each share of NRG stock. That ratio is 12.4 percent higher than the initial offer by Exelon in October. Based on Wednesday’s closing prices, the new Exelon bid values each NRG share at about $28.10, which is nearly 8 percent above NRG’s closing price. NRG, a wholesale power generator based in Princeton, N.J., had repeatedly urged its shareholders not to accept Exelon’s previous offer, calling it “inadequate and uncertain.” But it has said that it remained open to a deal at a “fair price.” Exelon’s new offer values NRG at about $7.45 billion, based on NRG’s 265.3 million outstanding shares. In October, Exelon offered $6.2 billion in stock for NRG. Exelon said that part of the reason it was able to raise its offer was that it found about $1.5 billion in additional cost savings that would flow from a merger. Exelon also factored in NRG’s recent acquisition of Reliant Energy’s retail business in Texas in making the new proposal. “An exhaustive analysis by our internal team, informed by the best third-party experts, resulted in additional synergies, allowing us to increase our offer to NRG shareholders,” John Rowe, Exelon’s chairman and chief executive, said in a statement. He added that the latest bid was Exelon’s “best and final offer.” In response, NRG urged its shareholders to “take no action at this time” on the latest offer until its board is able to review it. Shares of both companies traded lower on Thursday. NRG’s decline was a bit steeper, suggesting that investors might have expected a bigger increase in Exelon’s bid.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/10/business/10energy.html?ref=exeloncorporation">NRG Leaves Door Open After Rejecting Takeover Bid<date>Published: November 9, 2008</date><text>NRG Energy, a power generator based in Princeton, N.J., said Sunday it had rejected an unsolicited takeover bid by Exelon, saying the offer “manifestly undervalues” the company. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio NRG Energy Inc Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » The rejection forestalls, at least for now, the creation of what would be the largest power company in the nation, amid a wave of consolidation in the industry. NRG left the door open for Exelon to raise its price and said it was “agnostic” about being a buyer or seller. Exelon, one of the largest nuclear plant operators in the United States, unveiled its all-stock offer on Oct. 12, valuing NRG at $6.2 billion. Since then, Exelon’s share price has slipped to $53.82, making the bid worth roughly $6.08 billion. NRG’s shares have risen 31 percent since Exelon made its offer public. They closed at $23.86 on Friday. In rejecting the deal, NRG said its share price was undervalued and complained that its shareholders would own only 17 percent of the combined company even as NRG’s business would contribute about 30 percent of the new entity’s cash flow. In a letter to Exelon, NRG’s chairman, Howard E. Cosgrove, and chief executive, David W. Crane, wrote: “Your proposal, while undoubtedly an exceptional deal for your shareholders, is not at all right for our shareholders.” Combining the companies would create a power-generating goliath spanning the Midwest, the Middle Atlantic, Texas and Southern California. It would have a combined generating capacity of about 47,000 megawatts. Both companies run coal-fired and nuclear power plants, as well as some fired by natural gas and oil, and they are both seeking to build nuclear power plants in Texas. Exelon has argued that the combined company would have the financial strength to build even more plants. While NRG said that its primary objection was the offer price, it also said it was concerned about the amount of debt the combined utility would be assuming. Exelon said that because of covenants on NRG’s bonds, the combined company would need to refinance $8 billion in debt. With the credit markets still tight, the new debt would probably have to be repaid with an interest rate in the double digits. Exelon has not yet secured the refinancing and has suggested that it prefers to negotiate with its bondholders. “We think the offer severely undervalues the company and, with the debt markets the way they are, it’s not easily implementable,” Mr. Crane said in an interview Sunday. “In this environment, with what’s going on with the credit markets, cash is king.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on November 10, 2008, on page B5 of the New York edition.NRG Energy, a power generator based in Princeton, N.J., said Sunday it had rejected an unsolicited takeover bid by Exelon, saying the offer “manifestly undervalues” the company. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio NRG Energy Inc Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » The rejection forestalls, at least for now, the creation of what would be the largest power company in the nation, amid a wave of consolidation in the industry. NRG left the door open for Exelon to raise its price and said it was “agnostic” about being a buyer or seller. Exelon, one of the largest nuclear plant operators in the United States, unveiled its all-stock offer on Oct. 12, valuing NRG at $6.2 billion. Since then, Exelon’s share price has slipped to $53.82, making the bid worth roughly $6.08 billion. NRG’s shares have risen 31 percent since Exelon made its offer public. They closed at $23.86 on Friday. In rejecting the deal, NRG said its share price was undervalued and complained that its shareholders would own only 17 percent of the combined company even as NRG’s business would contribute about 30 percent of the new entity’s cash flow. In a letter to Exelon, NRG’s chairman, Howard E. Cosgrove, and chief executive, David W. Crane, wrote: “Your proposal, while undoubtedly an exceptional deal for your shareholders, is not at all right for our shareholders.” Combining the companies would create a power-generating goliath spanning the Midwest, the Middle Atlantic, Texas and Southern California. It would have a combined generating capacity of about 47,000 megawatts. Both companies run coal-fired and nuclear power plants, as well as some fired by natural gas and oil, and they are both seeking to build nuclear power plants in Texas. Exelon has argued that the combined company would have the financial strength to build even more plants. While NRG said that its primary objection was the offer price, it also said it was concerned about the amount of debt the combined utility would be assuming. Exelon said that because of covenants on NRG’s bonds, the combined company would need to refinance $8 billion in debt. With the credit markets still tight, the new debt would probably have to be repaid with an interest rate in the double digits. Exelon has not yet secured the refinancing and has suggested that it prefers to negotiate with its bondholders. “We think the offer severely undervalues the company and, with the debt markets the way they are, it’s not easily implementable,” Mr. Crane said in an interview Sunday. “In this environment, with what’s going on with the credit markets, cash is king.”</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/21/business/21nuclear.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon’s $6.2 Billion Bid for NRG Would Create Largest Power Utility in U.S.<date>Published: October 20, 2008</date><text>WASHINGTON  The Exelon Corporation’s unsolicited bid to buy NRG Energy, a power generator based in Princeton, N.J., would create the largest power company in the country, in terms of assets, market capitalization and generation capacity, and would benefit shareholders of both companies, Exelon said on Monday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » “There is simply no doubt that scale is important in turbulent times, and it’s important as the costs of growth continue to rise,” Exelon’s chairman, John W. Rowe, told analysts in a conference call, in which he cited the current credit crisis. But the deal would raise credit challenges; Exelon is assuming that because of bond covenants, sale of NRG would require Exelon to refinance $8 billion in debt and that interest rates would run into double digits. Executives held out some hope, though, that they might be able to renegotiate with the current bondholders, rather than refinance. The transaction would depress Exelon’s credit rating but it would remain investment grade, company executives said, and would return within two or three years to its current level. NRG, with 44 generating stations spread across Southern California, Texas, Pennsylvania, Delaware, New York and Connecticut, had no immediate comment except to say that it was evaluating the offer with its advisers. The $6.2 billion bid is an all-stock offer, 0.485 share of Exelon for each share of NRG. The offer is a 37 percent premium over NRG’s closing price last Friday, Exelon said. While the market tumble has lured various bargain-seekers into the utility business, one analyst on the call, Steve Fleishman, of Catapult Capital Management, said that the ratio in stock price between the two companies had not changed much between the beginning of the credit crisis and last Friday, when the offer was priced. Both prices are now depressed, according to analysts. Exelon, already one of the nation’s largest electric companies, covers a broad swath of the Midwest and Middle Atlantic states, combining the assets of Commonwealth Edison and Philadelphia Electric. A successful deal would require Exelon to sell some assets in Texas and in the Pennsylvania or Delaware areas. But it would give the company very broad geographic diversity, Mr. Rowe said, and access to plants using a variety of fuels. According to the Edison Electric Institute, the trade association of the investor-owned utilities, Exelon ranks sixth nationally in generating capacity and fourth in megawatt-hours produced; the merger would make it No. 1 in both categories. It has assets of $49.5 billion as of the end of last year, ranking third; combining with NRG’s $19.3 billion in assets, it would also rank first, the institute said. Exelon’s operations focus heavily on nuclear- and coal-fired plants. NRG has several coal-powered plants assets in Texas, a major share of a twin-unit nuclear plant there and plants fired by natural gas and oil. Joelle Frank, a spokeswoman for NRG, said the company had advised its shareholders to “take no action, pending review by NRG’s board.” NRG has hired Citigroup and Credit Suisse to advise it, she said. Exelon said the combination would produce an enormous combined entity with investment-grade credit ratings and the financial strength to build new power plants. NRG ranks well for creditworthiness among independent power producers, but many experts say they think that its plan to build two new nuclear reactors adjacent to its South Texas reactors faces challenges. “NRG’s South Texas Project nuclear plant and the very valuable expansion rights could be worth more in the hands of Exelon,” said John Kiani, a senior utilities and power analyst at Deutsche Bank. A year ago, NRG asked the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for permission to build two nuclear reactors at a site 90 miles southwest of Houston, the first time since the mid-1970s that anyone had sought permission for a new nuclear power plant in the country. Exelon is one of the nation’s largest and most successful nuclear operators. But the promised resurgence of nuclear power has been thrown into some doubt because of the credit crisis. Mr. Kiani said the offer “materially undervalues” NRG. Both NRG and Exelon have sold their output in advance and will probably realize higher cash flows once those contracts expire, he said. Another looming uncertainty is regulation of carbon emissions. Exelon, anticipating such regulation, has begun a project to lower emissions substantially within its service territory by 2020, and said it would devise a similar program for NRG. NRG is part of a coalition of companies seeking such regulation. If a schedule of emission limits is imposed, that could help Exelon, which has a huge fleet of zero-carbon nuclear plants. It would also create certainty for NRG. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 21, 2008, on page B3 of the New York edition.WASHINGTON  The Exelon Corporation’s unsolicited bid to buy NRG Energy, a power generator based in Princeton, N.J., would create the largest power company in the country, in terms of assets, market capitalization and generation capacity, and would benefit shareholders of both companies, Exelon said on Monday. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp NRG Energy Inc Go to your Portfolio » “There is simply no doubt that scale is important in turbulent times, and it’s important as the costs of growth continue to rise,” Exelon’s chairman, John W. Rowe, told analysts in a conference call, in which he cited the current credit crisis. But the deal would raise credit challenges; Exelon is assuming that because of bond covenants, sale of NRG would require Exelon to refinance $8 billion in debt and that interest rates would run into double digits. Executives held out some hope, though, that they might be able to renegotiate with the current bondholders, rather than refinance. The transaction would depress Exelon’s credit rating but it would remain investment grade, company executives said, and would return within two or three years to its current level. NRG, with 44 generating stations spread across Southern California, Texas, Pennsylvania, Delaware, New York and Connecticut, had no immediate comment except to say that it was evaluating the offer with its advisers. The $6.2 billion bid is an all-stock offer, 0.485 share of Exelon for each share of NRG. The offer is a 37 percent premium over NRG’s closing price last Friday, Exelon said. While the market tumble has lured various bargain-seekers into the utility business, one analyst on the call, Steve Fleishman, of Catapult Capital Management, said that the ratio in stock price between the two companies had not changed much between the beginning of the credit crisis and last Friday, when the offer was priced. Both prices are now depressed, according to analysts. Exelon, already one of the nation’s largest electric companies, covers a broad swath of the Midwest and Middle Atlantic states, combining the assets of Commonwealth Edison and Philadelphia Electric. A successful deal would require Exelon to sell some assets in Texas and in the Pennsylvania or Delaware areas. But it would give the company very broad geographic diversity, Mr. Rowe said, and access to plants using a variety of fuels. According to the Edison Electric Institute, the trade association of the investor-owned utilities, Exelon ranks sixth nationally in generating capacity and fourth in megawatt-hours produced; the merger would make it No. 1 in both categories. It has assets of $49.5 billion as of the end of last year, ranking third; combining with NRG’s $19.3 billion in assets, it would also rank first, the institute said. Exelon’s operations focus heavily on nuclear- and coal-fired plants. NRG has several coal-powered plants assets in Texas, a major share of a twin-unit nuclear plant there and plants fired by natural gas and oil. Joelle Frank, a spokeswoman for NRG, said the company had advised its shareholders to “take no action, pending review by NRG’s board.” NRG has hired Citigroup and Credit Suisse to advise it, she said. Exelon said the combination would produce an enormous combined entity with investment-grade credit ratings and the financial strength to build new power plants. NRG ranks well for creditworthiness among independent power producers, but many experts say they think that its plan to build two new nuclear reactors adjacent to its South Texas reactors faces challenges. “NRG’s South Texas Project nuclear plant and the very valuable expansion rights could be worth more in the hands of Exelon,” said John Kiani, a senior utilities and power analyst at Deutsche Bank. A year ago, NRG asked the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for permission to build two nuclear reactors at a site 90 miles southwest of Houston, the first time since the mid-1970s that anyone had sought permission for a new nuclear power plant in the country. Exelon is one of the nation’s largest and most successful nuclear operators. But the promised resurgence of nuclear power has been thrown into some doubt because of the credit crisis. Mr. Kiani said the offer “materially undervalues” NRG. Both NRG and Exelon have sold their output in advance and will probably realize higher cash flows once those contracts expire, he said. Another looming uncertainty is regulation of carbon emissions. Exelon, anticipating such regulation, has begun a project to lower emissions substantially within its service territory by 2020, and said it would devise a similar program for NRG. NRG is part of a coalition of companies seeking such regulation. If a schedule of emission limits is imposed, that could help Exelon, which has a huge fleet of zero-carbon nuclear plants. It would also create certainty for NRG.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D91139F933A15753C1A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">Nuclear Power Giant Bids for Rival<date>Published: October 20, 2008</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, the Chicago-based utility, said late Sunday that it had offered to buy NRG Energy, a power generator based in Princeton, N.J., for $6.2 billion. A combined company would produce enough electricity to serve nearly half the households in the United States, Exelon said. Exelon, one of the nation's largest electric companies that covers a broad swath of the Midwest and Middle Atlantic states, combines the assets of Commonwealth Edison and Philadelphia Electric. Its unsolicited, all-stock offer for NRG is a 37 percent premium over the closing price last Friday, Exelon said. Joelle Frank, a spokeswoman for NRG, said the company had advised its shareholders to ''take no action, pending review by NRG's board of directors.'' NRG has hired Citigroup and Credit Suisse to advise it, she said. The Exelon announcement notes that a change of control at NRG would require refinancing much of its debt, now at $8 billion. Exelon said one reason for the combination would be an enormous combined entity with investment-grade credit ratings and the financial strength to build new power plants. A year ago, NRG asked the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for permission to build two nuclear reactors at a site 90 miles southwest of Houston, the first time since the mid-1970s that anyone has sought permission for a new nuclear power plant in the country. Exelon is one of the nation's largest and most successful nuclear operators. But the promised resurgence of nuclear power has been thrown into some doubt because of the credit crisis. In a statement, Exelon said that the merged company would have ''unparalleled'' diversity in geography, in four major regions. NRG has major operations in Texas, Southern California and elsewhere. The merged company would also have diversity in fuel sources, including uranium, natural gas, coal and oil, Exelon said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/15/business/15emit.html?ref=exeloncorporation">To Set Tone, Exelon Plans Huge Cut in Emissions<date>Published: July 15, 2008</date><text>Exelon, the electric company based in Chicago, will promise on Tuesday to cut greenhouse gas emissions by 2020 by an amount larger than its total emissions in 2008, in a bid to shape the debate on carbon dioxide rules and to get a jump on compliance. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » Many academic researchers and nonprofit groups have made proposals for cutting emissions, but Exelon’s will be an unusual public presentation devised by a company that hopes to make money in the process. The plan relies heavily on conservation and having existing nuclear plants produce more power, but it includes smaller contributions from wind and sun energy. The reductions in greenhouse gas emissions will come by making Exelon’s operations more efficient, cutting the energy use of its electricity customers and building low-carbon generators that would displace older, less-efficient plants, many operated by rivals, the company said. One reason for the pledge is to seek credit for actions that cut emissions of other companies, said Exelon’s chairman and chief executive, John W. Rowe. For example, Exelon plans to help the factories that it serves do the same work with less electricity so that some generating stations, owned by Exelon or others, will burn less fuel. Exelon also wants to build generating stations that use natural gas more efficiently to replace coal plants in the Midwest and East  probably owned by other companies  that emit far more carbon dioxide. “Dealing with greenhouse gases, while essential, is very costly,” Mr. Rowe said. “If you have an adequate way of accounting for offsets and displacements, we think we can offset our carbon footprint at a reasonable price.” Some components of the plan, like trying to bolster the output of its nuclear plants, are moves that Exelon would have taken anyway, Mr. Rowe acknowledged. One major step is made financially feasible by changes in the fuel markets: the price of natural gas is now so high that efficient generating stations can be built profitably to replace older plants. The plan’s biggest components are cutting customers’ use of energy by improving efficiency and increasing the output of existing reactors. Each of those moves would contribute 23 percent to the carbon reductions. By the company’s calculation, some of those steps save money on a net basis. Some of the improvements would cut costs up to $70 a ton of carbon dioxide saved after expenses. Some of the nuclear changes would earn $60 a ton net of expenses. Operators of most of the nation’s 103 commercial nuclear reactors have raised output, usually by making small changes to pumps and valves and performing engineering analyses to show that they can safely produce more heat  akin to raising a highway speed limit. Exelon is counting on this source for about 16 percent of the savings. But it holds open the possibility that it could exceed its goal, and more than half the planned greenhouse gas reductions use this method. But the plan is remarkable for what it does not emphasize. Despite a national focus on solar and wind power, discussions in Congress about renewed tax credits for investments in windmills and solar systems and debate over a federal requirement for a minimum level of “renewable” energy, Exelon calls for relatively little. New “renewable” energy, including plants that run on landfill gas or wood or crop waste that can be burned, makes up just 7 percent of the carbon savings. In the region that the company serves in Pennsylvania, where state law requires electricity distributors to buy “renewable energy credits,” it will buy the equivalent of another 6.5 percent. Sequestering the carbon dioxide from coal-burning power plants is not a technology that Exelon thinks will be available by 2020. In contrast, the plan calls for improving the efficiency of its fossil-powered plants. It also calls for cutting the release of sulfur hexafluoride, a gas that is used to insulate circuit breakers but which is 24,000 times more potent for global warming than carbon dioxide, molecule for molecule. “This is a mix of things that any sensible person would do, and of things that you only can economically do if the cost of climate are incorporated into the marketplace,” said Mr. Rowe, referring to carbon taxes or limits that require emissions trading. Exelon’s carbon footprint is relatively small, because it has many nuclear reactors, he said. More Articles in Business »Exelon, the electric company based in Chicago, will promise on Tuesday to cut greenhouse gas emissions by 2020 by an amount larger than its total emissions in 2008, in a bid to shape the debate on carbon dioxide rules and to get a jump on compliance. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Exelon Corp Go to your Portfolio » Many academic researchers and nonprofit groups have made proposals for cutting emissions, but Exelon’s will be an unusual public presentation devised by a company that hopes to make money in the process. The plan relies heavily on conservation and having existing nuclear plants produce more power, but it includes smaller contributions from wind and sun energy. The reductions in greenhouse gas emissions will come by making Exelon’s operations more efficient, cutting the energy use of its electricity customers and building low-carbon generators that would displace older, less-efficient plants, many operated by rivals, the company said. One reason for the pledge is to seek credit for actions that cut emissions of other companies, said Exelon’s chairman and chief executive, John W. Rowe. For example, Exelon plans to help the factories that it serves do the same work with less electricity so that some generating stations, owned by Exelon or others, will burn less fuel. Exelon also wants to build generating stations that use natural gas more efficiently to replace coal plants in the Midwest and East  probably owned by other companies  that emit far more carbon dioxide. “Dealing with greenhouse gases, while essential, is very costly,” Mr. Rowe said. “If you have an adequate way of accounting for offsets and displacements, we think we can offset our carbon footprint at a reasonable price.” Some components of the plan, like trying to bolster the output of its nuclear plants, are moves that Exelon would have taken anyway, Mr. Rowe acknowledged. One major step is made financially feasible by changes in the fuel markets: the price of natural gas is now so high that efficient generating stations can be built profitably to replace older plants. The plan’s biggest components are cutting customers’ use of energy by improving efficiency and increasing the output of existing reactors. Each of those moves would contribute 23 percent to the carbon reductions. By the company’s calculation, some of those steps save money on a net basis. Some of the improvements would cut costs up to $70 a ton of carbon dioxide saved after expenses. Some of the nuclear changes would earn $60 a ton net of expenses. Operators of most of the nation’s 103 commercial nuclear reactors have raised output, usually by making small changes to pumps and valves and performing engineering analyses to show that they can safely produce more heat  akin to raising a highway speed limit. Exelon is counting on this source for about 16 percent of the savings. But it holds open the possibility that it could exceed its goal, and more than half the planned greenhouse gas reductions use this method. But the plan is remarkable for what it does not emphasize. Despite a national focus on solar and wind power, discussions in Congress about renewed tax credits for investments in windmills and solar systems and debate over a federal requirement for a minimum level of “renewable” energy, Exelon calls for relatively little. New “renewable” energy, including plants that run on landfill gas or wood or crop waste that can be burned, makes up just 7 percent of the carbon savings. In the region that the company serves in Pennsylvania, where state law requires electricity distributors to buy “renewable energy credits,” it will buy the equivalent of another 6.5 percent. Sequestering the carbon dioxide from coal-burning power plants is not a technology that Exelon thinks will be available by 2020. In contrast, the plan calls for improving the efficiency of its fossil-powered plants. It also calls for cutting the release of sulfur hexafluoride, a gas that is used to insulate circuit breakers but which is 24,000 times more potent for global warming than carbon dioxide, molecule for molecule. “This is a mix of things that any sensible person would do, and of things that you only can economically do if the cost of climate are incorporated into the marketplace,” said Mr. Rowe, referring to carbon taxes or limits that require emissions trading. Exelon’s carbon footprint is relatively small, because it has many nuclear reactors, he said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDD153CF93BA15750C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">Op-Art<date>Published: March 28, 2008</date><text>DRAWING; CHART Chart details various diary entries.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/03/us/politics/03exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Nuclear Leaks and Response Tested Obama in Senate<date>Published: February 3, 2008</date><text>When residents in Illinois voiced outrage two years ago upon learning that the Exelon Corporation had not disclosed radioactive leaks at one of its nuclear plants, the state’s freshman senator, Barack Obama, took up their cause. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Carlos Javier Sanchez/Bloomberg News John W. Rowe, chairman of Exelon and also of the Nuclear Energy Institute, a lobbying group, has been an Obama donor. Related Blogrunner: Reactions From Around the Web Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Candidate Topic Pages More Politics News Mr. Obama scolded Exelon and federal regulators for inaction and introduced a bill to require all plant owners to notify state and local authorities immediately of even small leaks. He has boasted of it on the campaign trail, telling a crowd in Iowa in December that it was “the only nuclear legislation that I’ve passed.” “I just did that last year,” he said, to murmurs of approval. A close look at the path his legislation took tells a very different story. While he initially fought to advance his bill, even holding up a presidential nomination to try to force a hearing on it, Mr. Obama eventually rewrote it to reflect changes sought by Senate Republicans, Exelon and nuclear regulators. The new bill removed language mandating prompt reporting and simply offered guidance to regulators, whom it charged with addressing the issue of unreported leaks. Those revisions propelled the bill through a crucial committee. But, contrary to Mr. Obama’s comments in Iowa, it ultimately died amid parliamentary wrangling in the full Senate. “Senator Obama’s staff was sending us copies of the bill to review, and we could see it weakening with each successive draft,” said Joe Cosgrove, a park district director in Will County, Ill., where low-level radioactive runoff had turned up in groundwater. “The teeth were just taken out of it.” The history of the bill shows Mr. Obama navigating a home-state controversy that pitted two important constituencies against each other and tested his skills as a legislative infighter. On one side were neighbors of several nuclear plants upset that low-level radioactive leaks had gone unreported for years; on the other was Exelon, the country’s largest nuclear plant operator and one of Mr. Obama’s largest sources of campaign money. Since 2003, executives and employees of Exelon, which is based in Illinois, have contributed at least $227,000 to Mr. Obama’s campaigns for the United States Senate and for president. Two top Exelon officials, Frank M. Clark, executive vice president, and John W. Rogers Jr., a director, are among his largest fund-raisers. Another Obama donor, John W. Rowe, chairman of Exelon, is also chairman of the Nuclear Energy Institute, the nuclear power industry’s lobbying group, based in Washington. Exelon’s support for Mr. Obama far exceeds its support for any other presidential candidate. In addition, Mr. Obama’s chief political strategist, David Axelrod, has worked as a consultant to Exelon. A spokeswoman for Exelon said Mr. Axelrod’s company had helped an Exelon subsidiary, Commonwealth Edison, with communications strategy periodically since 2002, but had no involvement in the leak controversy or other nuclear issues. The Obama campaign said in written responses to questions that Mr. Obama “never discussed this issue or this bill” with Mr. Axelrod. The campaign acknowledged that Exelon executives had met with Mr. Obama’s staff about the bill, as had concerned residents, environmentalists and regulators. It said the revisions resulted not from any influence by Exelon, but as a necessary response to a legislative roadblock put up by Republicans, who controlled the Senate at the time. “If Senator Obama had listened to industry demands, he wouldn’t have repeatedly criticized Exelon in the press, introduced the bill and then fought for months to get action on it,” the campaign said. “Since he has over a decade of legislative experience, Senator Obama knows that it’s very difficult to pass a perfect bill.” Asked why Mr. Obama had cited it as an accomplishment while campaigning for president, the campaign noted that after the senator introduced his bill, nuclear plants started making such reports on a voluntary basis. The campaign did not directly address the question of why Mr. Obama had told Iowa voters that the legislation had passed. Nuclear safety advocates are divided on whether Mr. Obama’s efforts yielded any lasting benefits. David A. Lochbaum of the Union of Concerned Scientists agreed that “it took the introduction of the bill in the first place to get a reaction from the industry.” “But of course because it is all voluntary,” Mr. Lochbaum said, “who’s to say where things will be a few years from now?” 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in National »When residents in Illinois voiced outrage two years ago upon learning that the Exelon Corporation had not disclosed radioactive leaks at one of its nuclear plants, the state’s freshman senator, Barack Obama, took up their cause. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Carlos Javier Sanchez/Bloomberg News John W. Rowe, chairman of Exelon and also of the Nuclear Energy Institute, a lobbying group, has been an Obama donor. Related Blogrunner: Reactions From Around the Web Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Candidate Topic Pages More Politics News Mr. Obama scolded Exelon and federal regulators for inaction and introduced a bill to require all plant owners to notify state and local authorities immediately of even small leaks. He has boasted of it on the campaign trail, telling a crowd in Iowa in December that it was “the only nuclear legislation that I’ve passed.” “I just did that last year,” he said, to murmurs of approval. A close look at the path his legislation took tells a very different story. While he initially fought to advance his bill, even holding up a presidential nomination to try to force a hearing on it, Mr. Obama eventually rewrote it to reflect changes sought by Senate Republicans, Exelon and nuclear regulators. The new bill removed language mandating prompt reporting and simply offered guidance to regulators, whom it charged with addressing the issue of unreported leaks. Those revisions propelled the bill through a crucial committee. But, contrary to Mr. Obama’s comments in Iowa, it ultimately died amid parliamentary wrangling in the full Senate. “Senator Obama’s staff was sending us copies of the bill to review, and we could see it weakening with each successive draft,” said Joe Cosgrove, a park district director in Will County, Ill., where low-level radioactive runoff had turned up in groundwater. “The teeth were just taken out of it.” The history of the bill shows Mr. Obama navigating a home-state controversy that pitted two important constituencies against each other and tested his skills as a legislative infighter. On one side were neighbors of several nuclear plants upset that low-level radioactive leaks had gone unreported for years; on the other was Exelon, the country’s largest nuclear plant operator and one of Mr. Obama’s largest sources of campaign money. Since 2003, executives and employees of Exelon, which is based in Illinois, have contributed at least $227,000 to Mr. Obama’s campaigns for the United States Senate and for president. Two top Exelon officials, Frank M. Clark, executive vice president, and John W. Rogers Jr., a director, are among his largest fund-raisers. Another Obama donor, John W. Rowe, chairman of Exelon, is also chairman of the Nuclear Energy Institute, the nuclear power industry’s lobbying group, based in Washington. Exelon’s support for Mr. Obama far exceeds its support for any other presidential candidate. In addition, Mr. Obama’s chief political strategist, David Axelrod, has worked as a consultant to Exelon. A spokeswoman for Exelon said Mr. Axelrod’s company had helped an Exelon subsidiary, Commonwealth Edison, with communications strategy periodically since 2002, but had no involvement in the leak controversy or other nuclear issues. The Obama campaign said in written responses to questions that Mr. Obama “never discussed this issue or this bill” with Mr. Axelrod. The campaign acknowledged that Exelon executives had met with Mr. Obama’s staff about the bill, as had concerned residents, environmentalists and regulators. It said the revisions resulted not from any influence by Exelon, but as a necessary response to a legislative roadblock put up by Republicans, who controlled the Senate at the time. “If Senator Obama had listened to industry demands, he wouldn’t have repeatedly criticized Exelon in the press, introduced the bill and then fought for months to get action on it,” the campaign said. “Since he has over a decade of legislative experience, Senator Obama knows that it’s very difficult to pass a perfect bill.” Asked why Mr. Obama had cited it as an accomplishment while campaigning for president, the campaign noted that after the senator introduced his bill, nuclear plants started making such reports on a voluntary basis. The campaign did not directly address the question of why Mr. Obama had told Iowa voters that the legislation had passed. Nuclear safety advocates are divided on whether Mr. Obama’s efforts yielded any lasting benefits. David A. Lochbaum of the Union of Concerned Scientists agreed that “it took the introduction of the bill in the first place to get a reaction from the industry.” “But of course because it is all voluntary,” Mr. Lochbaum said, “who’s to say where things will be a few years from now?” 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D81F31F936A25751C1A9619C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">NATIONAL BRIEFING | MIDWEST; Illinois: Security at Nuclear Plants<date>Published: December 15, 2007</date><text>The Exelon Corporation said it would replace the Wackenhut Corporation with an in-house security force at its 10 nuclear power plants after the discovery about two months ago that guards at a Pennsylvania plant were sleeping on the job. Exelon, based in Chicago, said it was acting even though a review of security at its other plants found ''no significant deficiencies.'' The change is to be made by July. Exelon has 17 reactors at 10 plants, including in Illinois, Pennsylvania and New Jersey. Officials at Wackenhut have characterized the apparent lapses as ''an anomaly.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/25/business/25security.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Security Provider at Reactor to Be Fired<date>Published: September 25, 2007</date><text>HARRISBURG, Pa., Sept. 25 (AP)  The Exelon Corporation said Monday that it would end its contract with a company that provides security at the Peach Bottom nuclear power plant in south-central Pennsylvania after security officers were caught on videotape nodding off or sleeping on the job. A video taken two to six months ago showed the guards, employed by the security firm Wackenhut, napping while sitting on chairs in a break room, said Christopher M. Crane, the chief operating officer of Exelon Generation. “This is not acceptable, and we will not tolerate it,” Mr. Crane said, adding that the actions did not affect plant safety or security. The video, which was taped by another security guard, appeared to show fewer than 10 guards, said an Exelon spokesman, Craig Nesbit. Officials with the company, which is based in Chicago, say they think the guards were recorded on the overnight shift. Wackenhut, based in Palm Beach Gardens, Fla., provides security for Exelon’s 10 nuclear power plants. Wackenhut’s senior vice president, Marc Shapiro, said officials considered the apparent lapses in attentiveness an anomaly. “At this point, it’s a small number of security personnel that were not performing as they should have,” Mr. Shapiro said. Peach Bottom is on the Susquehanna River about 60 miles west of Philadelphia. Officials with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said it would increase security inspections at the plant, including surprise visits. More Articles in Business »HARRISBURG, Pa., Sept. 25 (AP)  The Exelon Corporation said Monday that it would end its contract with a company that provides security at the Peach Bottom nuclear power plant in south-central Pennsylvania after security officers were caught on videotape nodding off or sleeping on the job. A video taken two to six months ago showed the guards, employed by the security firm Wackenhut, napping while sitting on chairs in a break room, said Christopher M. Crane, the chief operating officer of Exelon Generation. “This is not acceptable, and we will not tolerate it,” Mr. Crane said, adding that the actions did not affect plant safety or security. The video, which was taped by another security guard, appeared to show fewer than 10 guards, said an Exelon spokesman, Craig Nesbit. Officials with the company, which is based in Chicago, say they think the guards were recorded on the overnight shift. Wackenhut, based in Palm Beach Gardens, Fla., provides security for Exelon’s 10 nuclear power plants. Wackenhut’s senior vice president, Marc Shapiro, said officials considered the apparent lapses in attentiveness an anomaly. “At this point, it’s a small number of security personnel that were not performing as they should have,” Mr. Shapiro said. Peach Bottom is on the Susquehanna River about 60 miles west of Philadelphia. Officials with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said it would increase security inspections at the plant, including surprise visits.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/16/magazine/16wwln-freakonomics-t.html?ref=exeloncorporation">The Jane Fonda Effect<date>Published: September 16, 2007</date><text>Nuclear Energy Skip to next paragraph Paul Sahre and Loren Flaherty Related Post a Comment Freakonomics Authors Steven Levitt and Stephen Dubner bring their Blog to The Times. RSS Feed   Freakonomics » If you were asked to name the biggest global-warming villains of the past 30 years, heres one name that probably wouldnt spring to mind: Jane Fonda. But should it? In the movie The China Syndrome, Fonda played a California TV reporter filming an upbeat series about the states energy future. While visiting a nuclear power plant, she sees the engineers suddenly panic over what is later called a swift containment of a potentially costly event. When the plants corporate owner tries to cover up the accident, Fondas character persuades one engineer to blow the whistle on the possibility of a meltdown that could render an area the size of Pennsylvania permanently uninhabitable. The China Syndrome opened on March 16, 1979. With the no-nukes protest movement in full swing, the movie was attacked by the nuclear industry as an irresponsible act of leftist fear-mongering. Twelve days later, an accident occurred at the Three Mile Island nuclear plant in south-central Pennsylvania. Michael Douglas, a producer and co-star of the film  he played Fondas cameraman  watched the T.M.I. accident play out on the real TV news, which interspersed live shots from Pennsylvania with eerily similar scenes from The China Syndrome. While Fonda was firmly anti-nuke before making the film, Douglas wasnt so dogmatic. Now he was converted on the spot. It was a religious awakening, he recalled in a recent phone interview. I felt it was Gods hand. Fonda, meanwhile, became a full-fledged crusader. In a retrospective interview on the DVD edition of The China Syndrome, she notes with satisfaction that the film helped persuade at least two other men  the father of her then-husband, Tom Hayden, and her future husband, Ted Turner  to turn anti-nuke. I was ecstatic that it was extremely commercially successful, she said. You know the expression We had legs? We became a caterpillar after Three Mile Island. The T.M.I. accident was, according to a 1979 Presidents Commission report, initiated by mechanical malfunctions in the plant and made much worse by a combination of human errors. Although some radiation was released, there was no meltdown through to the other side of the Earth  no China syndrome  nor, in fact, did the T.M.I. accident produce any deaths, injuries or significant damage except to the plant itself. What it did produce, stoked by The China Syndrome, was a widespread panic. The nuclear industry, already foundering as a result of economic, regulatory and public pressures, halted plans for further expansion. And so, instead of becoming a nation with clean and cheap nuclear energy, as once seemed inevitable, the United States kept building power plants that burned coal and other fossil fuels. Today such plants account for 40 percent of the countrys energy-related carbon-dioxide emissions. Anyone hunting for a global-warming villain cant help blaming those power plants  and cant help wondering too about the unintended consequences of Jane Fonda. But the big news is that nuclear power may be making a comeback in the United States. There are plans for more than two dozen new reactors on the drawing board and billions of dollars in potential federal loan guarantees. Has fear of a meltdown subsided, or has it merely been replaced by the fear of global warming? The answer may lie in a 1916 doctoral dissertation by the legendary economist Frank Knight. He made a distinction between two key factors in decision making: risk and uncertainty. The cardinal difference, Knight declared, is that risk  however great  can be measured, whereas uncertainty cannot. How do people weigh risk versus uncertainty? Consider a famous experiment that illustrates what is known as the Ellsberg Paradox. There are two urns. The first urn, you are told, contains 50 red balls and 50 black balls. The second one also contains 100 red and black balls, but the number of each color is unknown. If your task is to pick a red ball out of either urn, which urn do you choose? Most people pick the first urn, which suggests that they prefer a measurable risk to an immeasurable uncertainty. (This condition is known to economists as ambiguity aversion.) Could it be that nuclear energy, risks and all, is now seen as preferable to the uncertainties of global warming? France, which generates nearly 80 percent of its electricity by nuclear power, seems to think so. So do Belgium (56 percent), Sweden (47 percent) and more than a dozen other countries that generate at least one-fourth of their electricity by nuclear power. And who is the worlds single largest producer of nuclear energy? Improbably enough, that would be . . . the United States. Even though the development of new nuclear plants stalled by the early 1980s, the countrys 104 reactors today produce nearly 20 percent of the electricity the nation consumes. This share has actually grown over the years along with our consumption, since nuclear technology has become more efficient. While the fixed costs of a new nuclear plant are higher than those of a coal or natural-gas plant, the energy is cheaper to create: Exelon, the largest nuclear company in the United States, claims to produce electricity at 1.3 cents per kilowatt-hour, compared with 2.2 cents for coal. Nuclear enthusiasm may be on the rise, but it can always be dampened by mention of a single word: Chernobyl. The 1986 Ukrainian disaster killed at least a few dozen people directly and exposed millions more to radiation. A new study by the economists Douglas Almond, Lena Edlund and Marten Palme shows that as far away as Sweden, in areas where the wind carried Chernobyl fallout, babies who were in utero at the time later had significantly worse school outcomes than other Swedish children. But coal, too, has its costs, even beyond the threat of global warming. In the United States, an average of 33 coal miners are killed each year. In China, more than 4,700 coal miners were killed last year alone  a statistic that the Chinese government has trumpeted as a vast improvement. The accident at Three Mile Island ruined one of the two reactors on the site. The other one, operated by Exelon, continues to quietly churn out electricity for 800,000 customers. Outside the plants training center is a small vegetable garden enclosed in chain-link fencing: corn, tomatoes, beets. Its output is monitored to detect radiation. Although the garden was badly in need of watering during a recent visit, the vegetables were otherwise fine. Inside, Christopher Crane, the chief operating officer of Exelon Generation, held forth on the barriers that the nuclear industry must clear before new plants can be built. Among them: the longstanding issue of how to dispose of spent fuel and whether the public has shaken its fear of new nuclear reactors. Crane sat in a conference room within the T.M.I. compound. The view outside was bleak: large, windowless buildings; fencing topped by razor wire; bulletproof sniper stands. Security at all nuclear plants has been heightened since 9/11. If you didnt know better, you would think you were looking at a maximum-security prison. This similarity suggests an answer to Cranes point about public acceptance of new nuclear construction. There was a time when people didnt want new prisons built in their backyards  until they decided that the risk was relatively low and that the rewards, in jobs and tax dollars, were substantial. Will nuclear plants ultimately get the same embrace? The market seems to think so  Exelon stock has tripled in the past five years  but it may all depend on what kind of thrillers Hollywood has in the pipeline. Stephen J. Dubner and Steven D. Levitt are the authors of Freakonomics. More information on the research behind this column is online at www.freakonomics.com. More Articles in Magazine »Nuclear Energy Skip to next paragraph Paul Sahre and Loren Flaherty Related Post a Comment Freakonomics Authors Steven Levitt and Stephen Dubner bring their Blog to The Times. RSS Feed   Freakonomics » If you were asked to name the biggest global-warming villains of the past 30 years, heres one name that probably wouldnt spring to mind: Jane Fonda. But should it? In the movie The China Syndrome, Fonda played a California TV reporter filming an upbeat series about the states energy future. While visiting a nuclear power plant, she sees the engineers suddenly panic over what is later called a swift containment of a potentially costly event. When the plants corporate owner tries to cover up the accident, Fondas character persuades one engineer to blow the whistle on the possibility of a meltdown that could render an area the size of Pennsylvania permanently uninhabitable. The China Syndrome opened on March 16, 1979. With the no-nukes protest movement in full swing, the movie was attacked by the nuclear industry as an irresponsible act of leftist fear-mongering. Twelve days later, an accident occurred at the Three Mile Island nuclear plant in south-central Pennsylvania. Michael Douglas, a producer and co-star of the film  he played Fondas cameraman  watched the T.M.I. accident play out on the real TV news, which interspersed live shots from Pennsylvania with eerily similar scenes from The China Syndrome. While Fonda was firmly anti-nuke before making the film, Douglas wasnt so dogmatic. Now he was converted on the spot. It was a religious awakening, he recalled in a recent phone interview. I felt it was Gods hand. Fonda, meanwhile, became a full-fledged crusader. In a retrospective interview on the DVD edition of The China Syndrome, she notes with satisfaction that the film helped persuade at least two other men  the father of her then-husband, Tom Hayden, and her future husband, Ted Turner  to turn anti-nuke. I was ecstatic that it was extremely commercially successful, she said. You know the expression We had legs? We became a caterpillar after Three Mile Island. The T.M.I. accident was, according to a 1979 Presidents Commission report, initiated by mechanical malfunctions in the plant and made much worse by a combination of human errors. Although some radiation was released, there was no meltdown through to the other side of the Earth  no China syndrome  nor, in fact, did the T.M.I. accident produce any deaths, injuries or significant damage except to the plant itself. What it did produce, stoked by The China Syndrome, was a widespread panic. The nuclear industry, already foundering as a result of economic, regulatory and public pressures, halted plans for further expansion. And so, instead of becoming a nation with clean and cheap nuclear energy, as once seemed inevitable, the United States kept building power plants that burned coal and other fossil fuels. Today such plants account for 40 percent of the countrys energy-related carbon-dioxide emissions. Anyone hunting for a global-warming villain cant help blaming those power plants  and cant help wondering too about the unintended consequences of Jane Fonda. But the big news is that nuclear power may be making a comeback in the United States. There are plans for more than two dozen new reactors on the drawing board and billions of dollars in potential federal loan guarantees. Has fear of a meltdown subsided, or has it merely been replaced by the fear of global warming? The answer may lie in a 1916 doctoral dissertation by the legendary economist Frank Knight. He made a distinction between two key factors in decision making: risk and uncertainty. The cardinal difference, Knight declared, is that risk  however great  can be measured, whereas uncertainty cannot. How do people weigh risk versus uncertainty? Consider a famous experiment that illustrates what is known as the Ellsberg Paradox. There are two urns. The first urn, you are told, contains 50 red balls and 50 black balls. The second one also contains 100 red and black balls, but the number of each color is unknown. If your task is to pick a red ball out of either urn, which urn do you choose? Most people pick the first urn, which suggests that they prefer a measurable risk to an immeasurable uncertainty. (This condition is known to economists as ambiguity aversion.) Could it be that nuclear energy, risks and all, is now seen as preferable to the uncertainties of global warming? France, which generates nearly 80 percent of its electricity by nuclear power, seems to think so. So do Belgium (56 percent), Sweden (47 percent) and more than a dozen other countries that generate at least one-fourth of their electricity by nuclear power. And who is the worlds single largest producer of nuclear energy? Improbably enough, that would be . . . the United States. Even though the development of new nuclear plants stalled by the early 1980s, the countrys 104 reactors today produce nearly 20 percent of the electricity the nation consumes. This share has actually grown over the years along with our consumption, since nuclear technology has become more efficient. While the fixed costs of a new nuclear plant are higher than those of a coal or natural-gas plant, the energy is cheaper to create: Exelon, the largest nuclear company in the United States, claims to produce electricity at 1.3 cents per kilowatt-hour, compared with 2.2 cents for coal. Nuclear enthusiasm may be on the rise, but it can always be dampened by mention of a single word: Chernobyl. The 1986 Ukrainian disaster killed at least a few dozen people directly and exposed millions more to radiation. A new study by the economists Douglas Almond, Lena Edlund and Marten Palme shows that as far away as Sweden, in areas where the wind carried Chernobyl fallout, babies who were in utero at the time later had significantly worse school outcomes than other Swedish children. But coal, too, has its costs, even beyond the threat of global warming. In the United States, an average of 33 coal miners are killed each year. In China, more than 4,700 coal miners were killed last year alone  a statistic that the Chinese government has trumpeted as a vast improvement. The accident at Three Mile Island ruined one of the two reactors on the site. The other one, operated by Exelon, continues to quietly churn out electricity for 800,000 customers. Outside the plants training center is a small vegetable garden enclosed in chain-link fencing: corn, tomatoes, beets. Its output is monitored to detect radiation. Although the garden was badly in need of watering during a recent visit, the vegetables were otherwise fine. Inside, Christopher Crane, the chief operating officer of Exelon Generation, held forth on the barriers that the nuclear industry must clear before new plants can be built. Among them: the longstanding issue of how to dispose of spent fuel and whether the public has shaken its fear of new nuclear reactors. Crane sat in a conference room within the T.M.I. compound. The view outside was bleak: large, windowless buildings; fencing topped by razor wire; bulletproof sniper stands. Security at all nuclear plants has been heightened since 9/11. If you didnt know better, you would think you were looking at a maximum-security prison. This similarity suggests an answer to Cranes point about public acceptance of new nuclear construction. There was a time when people didnt want new prisons built in their backyards  until they decided that the risk was relatively low and that the rewards, in jobs and tax dollars, were substantial. Will nuclear plants ultimately get the same embrace? The market seems to think so  Exelon stock has tripled in the past five years  but it may all depend on what kind of thrillers Hollywood has in the pipeline. Stephen J. Dubner and Steven D. Levitt are the authors of Freakonomics. More information on the research behind this column is online at www.freakonomics.com.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/29/business/29rating.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Illinois Questions Ratings Agencies Gave to Utilities<date>Published: March 29, 2007</date><text>Moody’s Investors Service and Standard &amp; Poor’s, the big credit ratings agencies, appear to be manipulating their reports to help the largest electric utilities in Illinois charge higher prices for power, the state’s attorney general asserted in papers filed yesterday. In a motion seeking disclosure of the drafts of reports to determine whether the utilities had a hand in editing them, the attorney general, Lisa Madigan, said that Moody’s and S.&amp; P. had “issued warnings and downgrades seemingly right on cue to promote the interests of the utilities and their parent companies.” She outlined seven actions taken over eight days last fall, and three more in the last month. The timing and nature of the credit reports, the filing said, “have raised troubling questions as to whether the credit rating agencies are providing objective information or promoting the interests of their clients.” It characterized those actions as a lobbying effort on the part of the utilities, the credit rating agencies and a front group to raise prices for electricity. Moody’s and S.&amp; P. declined to comment. Both said in December that they routinely show drafts of their credit reports to companies so errors can be detected. They denied altering their observations to benefit companies seeking rate increases, a subject that arose after disclosures that 48 changes were made to a report in September on an Oregon utility, Portland General Electric. Because of changes in the Portland report, the staff of the Oregon Public Utility Commission said “it is impossible to conclude that S.&amp; P. conducted a timely independent inquiry.” That prompted the attorneys general of Arkansas and Illinois, and consumer groups in California and other states, to file requests with utility regulators for drafts of credit rating reports to determine whether they had been changed at the request of companies. The papers filed yesterday sought to force disclosure of all correspondence between the credit rating agencies and the Ameren Corporation, a St. Louis-based holding company. It owns Ameren Illinois, which covers much of Illinois outside the Chicago market. The filing also cited Exelon, whose Commonwealth Edison unit operates in the Chicago area. It was part of a challenge by the attorney general to the integrity of an auction that resulted in a sharp rise in electricity rates paid this year by Illinois residents and businesses. Ameren has agreed to provide the documents to the Illinois Commerce Commission, which regulates electric rates, a spokeswoman for the company, Erica Abbett, said. Miss Abbett said the utility had not given the same documents to the attorney general because it did not consider them relevant to the auction case. Commonwealth Edison supplied some documents and said that it would provide more by today, said Susan Hedman, the senior assistant attorney general overseeing the case. J. Barry Mitchell, president of Commonwealth Edison, said any suggestion that the credit agencies manipulated their reports “is ludicrous.” Both Moody’s and S.&amp; P. issued reports last fall that echoed the language of a group promoting higher electric rates, one that Illinois officials say was a front for the utilities. The credit agencies warned of what Moody’s called “an increasingly contentious political and regulatory climate in Illinois” and what S.&amp; P. said was a “heightened adversarial regulatory climate in Illinois.” A third rating agency, Fitch, issued a report the same day that said “there have not been any adverse regulatory rulings” in Illinois. Fitch does not allow companies that pay it to rate the creditworthiness of their debt to suggest changes in its reports, unlike Moody’s and S.&amp; P. Ms. Madigan noted that Ameren had proposed a rate relief plan for customers, dependent on maintaining its credit ratings. Hours after the state commerce commission approved the plan, she said, “Moody’s downgraded the Ameren Illinois utilities to junk status even though there was no change in the utilities’ revenues or costs, thereby ‘forcing’ Ameren to cancel millions of dollars of rate relief that Ameren had voluntarily proposed.” She said the draft reports “will help determine whether Ameren’s credit ratings have been downgraded” because of “an actual decline in Ameren’s ratings or due to other factors.” More Articles in Business »Moody’s Investors Service and Standard &amp; Poor’s, the big credit ratings agencies, appear to be manipulating their reports to help the largest electric utilities in Illinois charge higher prices for power, the state’s attorney general asserted in papers filed yesterday. In a motion seeking disclosure of the drafts of reports to determine whether the utilities had a hand in editing them, the attorney general, Lisa Madigan, said that Moody’s and S.&amp; P. had “issued warnings and downgrades seemingly right on cue to promote the interests of the utilities and their parent companies.” She outlined seven actions taken over eight days last fall, and three more in the last month. The timing and nature of the credit reports, the filing said, “have raised troubling questions as to whether the credit rating agencies are providing objective information or promoting the interests of their clients.” It characterized those actions as a lobbying effort on the part of the utilities, the credit rating agencies and a front group to raise prices for electricity. Moody’s and S.&amp; P. declined to comment. Both said in December that they routinely show drafts of their credit reports to companies so errors can be detected. They denied altering their observations to benefit companies seeking rate increases, a subject that arose after disclosures that 48 changes were made to a report in September on an Oregon utility, Portland General Electric. Because of changes in the Portland report, the staff of the Oregon Public Utility Commission said “it is impossible to conclude that S.&amp; P. conducted a timely independent inquiry.” That prompted the attorneys general of Arkansas and Illinois, and consumer groups in California and other states, to file requests with utility regulators for drafts of credit rating reports to determine whether they had been changed at the request of companies. The papers filed yesterday sought to force disclosure of all correspondence between the credit rating agencies and the Ameren Corporation, a St. Louis-based holding company. It owns Ameren Illinois, which covers much of Illinois outside the Chicago market. The filing also cited Exelon, whose Commonwealth Edison unit operates in the Chicago area. It was part of a challenge by the attorney general to the integrity of an auction that resulted in a sharp rise in electricity rates paid this year by Illinois residents and businesses. Ameren has agreed to provide the documents to the Illinois Commerce Commission, which regulates electric rates, a spokeswoman for the company, Erica Abbett, said. Miss Abbett said the utility had not given the same documents to the attorney general because it did not consider them relevant to the auction case. Commonwealth Edison supplied some documents and said that it would provide more by today, said Susan Hedman, the senior assistant attorney general overseeing the case. J. Barry Mitchell, president of Commonwealth Edison, said any suggestion that the credit agencies manipulated their reports “is ludicrous.” Both Moody’s and S.&amp; P. issued reports last fall that echoed the language of a group promoting higher electric rates, one that Illinois officials say was a front for the utilities. The credit agencies warned of what Moody’s called “an increasingly contentious political and regulatory climate in Illinois” and what S.&amp; P. said was a “heightened adversarial regulatory climate in Illinois.” A third rating agency, Fitch, issued a report the same day that said “there have not been any adverse regulatory rulings” in Illinois. Fitch does not allow companies that pay it to rate the creditworthiness of their debt to suggest changes in its reports, unlike Moody’s and S.&amp; P. Ms. Madigan noted that Ameren had proposed a rate relief plan for customers, dependent on maintaining its credit ratings. Hours after the state commerce commission approved the plan, she said, “Moody’s downgraded the Ameren Illinois utilities to junk status even though there was no change in the utilities’ revenues or costs, thereby ‘forcing’ Ameren to cancel millions of dollars of rate relief that Ameren had voluntarily proposed.” She said the draft reports “will help determine whether Ameren’s credit ratings have been downgraded” because of “an actual decline in Ameren’s ratings or due to other factors.”</text></article><article index="10" href="http://select.nytimes.com/2006/11/05/business/yourmoney/05gret.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Executive Pay Becomes Political<date>Published: November 5, 2006</date><text>ANGER over outsize executive pay has, of course, been a feature in the election of corporate directors in recent years. But it has not really surfaced as an issue in state or local politics.Until now. As Illinois voters head to the polls Tuesday, executive compensation at the state’s two major utility companies will be much on their minds. Looming electricity rate increases — consumers’ bills are set to rise by 25 percent and those of small business by as much as 75 percent — will result in fatter pay for those running the utilities even as the very same increases lighten the wallets of consumers. First, a little history. In 1997, Illinois amended its public utility act to allow competition to determine electricity rates. Rates were discounted and a freeze was instituted while the market adjusted and competition developed. The freeze ends Jan. 2. Two companies that provide energy to Illinois customers — the Ameren Corporation and the Exelon Corporation — are delighted at the prospect of getting out from under the rate freeze. That is no surprise. But neither is the fact that the rate increase has become a huge political issue. Both Gov. Rod R. Blagojevich and his Republican opponent, Judy Baar Topinka, the state treasurer, have said they would call a special session of the Illinois legislature to extend the rate freeze. Voters have been urged to support legislators who will vote to keep rates frozen. Where does executive pay come in? Ameren and Exelon executives stand to enjoy stock option gains, not because they have worked managerial magic on their bottom lines, but simply because consumers are paying more for electricity. Opponents of the rate increase have shrewdly framed the situation in these terms. Last May, Ameren’s shareholders approved a new and considerably more generous stock incentive plan for its top executives and high-level managers. According to the company’s proxy, the plan set aside four million new shares of Ameren stock worth $214 million, well above the one million shares covered by the previous plan. Lt. Gov. Pat Quinn, a Democrat who opposes the rate increase, said the new stock plan seemed engineered to capture a windfall from the rate increase for Ameren executives. The rate increases are expected to propel the shares of both companies, making the stock options held by the executives more valuable. Last year, Mr. Quinn pointed out, the company’s top five executives received packages totaling $7.4 million. Ten family members of Ameren’s top officers received compensation of $1.3 million in 2005. Ameren is the parent company of Illinois Power and Central Illinois Public Service, among other entities. Executive pay at neighboring Exelon is even higher. The top five executives at the company, parent of the ComEd utility, received packages amounting to $47 million last year, including option exercises. They also stand to benefit from the rate increase because stock options account for much of their pay, he said. “Clearly, these multimillionaire executives have simply lost touch with the financial realities facing the average working person in the Land of Lincoln,” Mr. Quinn said. “An Illinois worker earning the minimum wage would have to work three full days to pay the proposed rate increase; it would take the C.E.O. of Exelon one minute to earn that amount.” The rate increase is the result of a reverse auction, in which energy providers bid to supply electricity to the Illinois utilities. Critics of the deal say that it was not a real auction because some of the power generators bidding to supply the energy were subsidiaries of Ameren and Exelon, affiliates of the very companies buying the power. The utility companies maintain that the auctions were fair because they were overseen by federal regulators and involved multiple parties. Both Exelon and Ameren have prospered in recent years; Exelon’s Web site says it is “the most consistently profitable electricity and gas company in the United States.” In the last three years, its income, before the effects of an accounting change, has increased by 22 percent over all. Ameren’s income, also before the accounting change, has risen 24 percent in the period. Customers have also enjoyed artificially low electricity rates throughout this time. During the freeze, both utilities have had low-cost contracts that allowed them to maintain profitability. Now they will have to pay higher prices for energy; if they cannot pass the costs on to their customers, they face enormous shortfalls. Susan Gallagher, an Ameren spokeswoman, says the company’s shortfall will be $1 billion in 2007, significantly above the $600 million the company earned last year. Both utilities predict dire consequences, even bankruptcy, if the rate increase is overturned. As required by law, Ameren has sent letters to more than 700 employees warning that mass layoffs could result if the rate freeze is extended. “We currently anticipate that layoffs, should they become necessary, will be permanent,” stated a letter dated Oct. 20, written by a manager of labor relations, and sent to a worker in Lawrenceville, Ill. “It is currently anticipated that in the event such a layoff becomes necessary, you will be laid off immediately,” the letter said. Given Ameren’s layoff warnings and talk of bankruptcy, is there any discussion of pay cuts in the executive suite? “There is obviously discussion about sacrifice on all our parts,” Ms. Gallagher said. “But our executives are among the lowest paid in the industry — our C.E.O. is at half the median in the electric power industry. And he is paid 12 times the average lineman; the average top executive was paid more than 170 times average worker earnings.” GARY SNODGRASS, chief human resources officer at Exelon, said its executive pay is purely based on performance. “We peg compensation targets at the 50th percentile of a peer group consisting of 24 companies,” he said. “Then the actual pay that people receive is based upon performance. We have consistently outperformed our competitors.” John W. Rowe, Exelon’s chief executive, gave $1.4 million to charity last year, almost half his salary and bonus, a company spokeswoman said. A bankruptcy filing by utility subsidiaries at Ameren and Exelon is a real possibility, according to Philip C. Adams, a debt analyst at Gimme Credit, an independent research firm that specializes in high-grade corporate debt. Bondholders and stockholders would be hurt, of course, but he also noted that Illinois utility customers could wind up paying higher prices in the short-term if the companies filed for bankruptcy. Sounds as if everybody loses in that ugly scenario. Except that those in the executive suite always seem to escape hardship, even when their companies file for bankruptcy. Think U.S. Airways, Delphi, United Airlines. Which is why executive pay has become an easy football for politicians to pick up and run with. As the situation in Illinois illustrates, executive pay is now much more than just a shareholder issue; it sits squarely in the political mainstream. It is no fun being a target, a whipping boy. But executives do have a choice in matters like these. They could give back some of their pay and defuse their critics. If they don’t, well, the problem is theirs to own.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/15/nyregion/15merger.html?ref=exeloncorporation">New Jersey Opposition Leads to Utility Merger’s Collapse<date>Published: September 15, 2006</date><text>TRENTON, Sept. 14  A planned merger that would have created the largest utility in the United States collapsed on Thursday, a month after New Jersey regulators demanded better terms for consumers. The Public Service Enterprise Group of Newark  the parent company of Public Service Electric and Gas, New Jersey’s largest utility  and the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation said their differences with the state over the $17 billion deal were “insurmountable.” In the 19 months that the proposed merger was before the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, it drew fierce opposition from consumer groups and many legislators, who were later joined by the state’s new public advocate, Ronald Chen. The deal had been approved by regulators in New York, Connecticut and Pennsylvania, as well as by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. And New Jersey had not turned down a merger in 20 years. But this proposal ran into serious trouble because regulators feared that the combined company would drive up electric and gas rates. In July, Exelon offered $600 million in credits to New Jersey customers through 2008 to help win approval from the Board of Public Utilities. But the board, in a counterproposal on Aug. 17, demanded that Exelon and P.S.E.&amp;G. increase their offer of credits to ratepayers and that they sell eight plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania to reduce the combined company’s market share. That led Exelon to warn last month that the deal was “no longer ‘more likely than not.’ ” In a statement on Thursday, Exelon’s chairman, John W. Rowe, said the company was “very disappointed that the merger cannot be completed.” The board issued only a brief statement on Thursday. But Mr. Chen said in a statement that the end of the merger “is in the best interests of all New Jerseyans.” “We did not believe the companies offered enough direct and real rate relief for New Jersey families and businesses,” he said. Consumer advocates celebrated the end of their battle. “Time after time, New Jersey and other states have approved utility mergers that are not in the best interests of the public,” said Suzanne Leta of the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group. “This time New Jersey regulators wouldn’t accept the federal rubber stamp.” The New Jersey utility’s stock dropped by nearly 9 percent in after-hours trading to $60.25, while Exelon stock rose about 3 percent to $59.50. Opponents of the merger, citing estimates from the board of public utilities, contended that it could increase the typical residential energy bill by about $45 a month. And Mr. Chen warned that the merger was likely to increase rates for all New Jersey ratepayers, not just P.S.E.&amp;G.’s 3.8 million customers, because all utilities in the state buy power from the same energy generators. The merger would have shored up the finances of the Public Service Enterprise Group, the weaker of the two companies. But the company’s chairman, E. James Ferland, said in a statement on Thursday that “our prospects on a stand-alone basis are bright.” The State Senate president, Richard J. Codey, said, however: “The way the business is going, companies like P.S.E.&amp;G. may be dinosaurs. These utilities may go the way of the independent pharmacies.” Gov. Jon S. Corzine had supported the merger, with some reservations. His press secretary, Anthony Coley, said on Thursday evening: “We saw some benefits with a merger, so this is unfortunate news. “P.S.E.&amp;G. has, however, served New Jersey residents well in the past, and we expect their tradition of providing good customer service will continue.” More Articles in New York Region »TRENTON, Sept. 14  A planned merger that would have created the largest utility in the United States collapsed on Thursday, a month after New Jersey regulators demanded better terms for consumers. The Public Service Enterprise Group of Newark  the parent company of Public Service Electric and Gas, New Jersey’s largest utility  and the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation said their differences with the state over the $17 billion deal were “insurmountable.” In the 19 months that the proposed merger was before the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, it drew fierce opposition from consumer groups and many legislators, who were later joined by the state’s new public advocate, Ronald Chen. The deal had been approved by regulators in New York, Connecticut and Pennsylvania, as well as by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. And New Jersey had not turned down a merger in 20 years. But this proposal ran into serious trouble because regulators feared that the combined company would drive up electric and gas rates. In July, Exelon offered $600 million in credits to New Jersey customers through 2008 to help win approval from the Board of Public Utilities. But the board, in a counterproposal on Aug. 17, demanded that Exelon and P.S.E.&amp;G. increase their offer of credits to ratepayers and that they sell eight plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania to reduce the combined company’s market share. That led Exelon to warn last month that the deal was “no longer ‘more likely than not.’ ” In a statement on Thursday, Exelon’s chairman, John W. Rowe, said the company was “very disappointed that the merger cannot be completed.” The board issued only a brief statement on Thursday. But Mr. Chen said in a statement that the end of the merger “is in the best interests of all New Jerseyans.” “We did not believe the companies offered enough direct and real rate relief for New Jersey families and businesses,” he said. Consumer advocates celebrated the end of their battle. “Time after time, New Jersey and other states have approved utility mergers that are not in the best interests of the public,” said Suzanne Leta of the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group. “This time New Jersey regulators wouldn’t accept the federal rubber stamp.” The New Jersey utility’s stock dropped by nearly 9 percent in after-hours trading to $60.25, while Exelon stock rose about 3 percent to $59.50. Opponents of the merger, citing estimates from the board of public utilities, contended that it could increase the typical residential energy bill by about $45 a month. And Mr. Chen warned that the merger was likely to increase rates for all New Jersey ratepayers, not just P.S.E.&amp;G.’s 3.8 million customers, because all utilities in the state buy power from the same energy generators. The merger would have shored up the finances of the Public Service Enterprise Group, the weaker of the two companies. But the company’s chairman, E. James Ferland, said in a statement on Thursday that “our prospects on a stand-alone basis are bright.” The State Senate president, Richard J. Codey, said, however: “The way the business is going, companies like P.S.E.&amp;G. may be dinosaurs. These utilities may go the way of the independent pharmacies.” Gov. Jon S. Corzine had supported the merger, with some reservations. His press secretary, Anthony Coley, said on Thursday evening: “We saw some benefits with a merger, so this is unfortunate news. “P.S.E.&amp;G. has, however, served New Jersey residents well in the past, and we expect their tradition of providing good customer service will continue.”</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/31/business/31exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Utility Says Regulators May Kill Merger Deal<date>Published: August 31, 2006</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, the utility owner, warned yesterday that it might be unable to complete its $18.6 billion acquisition of Public Service Enterprise Group because of problems getting approval from New Jersey regulators. Completion of the merger is no longer more likely than not,  Exelon said yesterday in a regulatory filing. The company said it would write off $35 million in costs associated with the transaction this quarter. Shares of Public Service fell yesterday on concern that demands from the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities might kill the acquisition. The takeover, announced in December 2004, is opposed by some state lawmakers. An analyst at Dahlman Rose &amp; Company, Daniele Seitz, said yesterday, The probability of completing the deal has dropped a lot, and it is certainly not in the bag for the end of this month. There must have been an additional request or requirement on behalf of the utility board, and the company didnt go for it. Shares of Public Service fell $2.32, to $68.58, and Exelon declined 18 cents, to $60.12. The acquisition of Public Service, based in Newark, would expand Exelons group of cheaply fueled nuclear power plants, already the largest in the country. The company expected regulatory approval within 18 months, even though New Jerseys top regulator said then that it could take up to two years because of the size of the transaction. The Justice Department on June 22 gave antitrust approval to the transaction on the condition that Exelon sell 5,600 megawatts of power plants. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission gave approval a year earlier. Exelons biggest obstacle among New Jersey regulators has been overcoming concern that the combined company would drive up power prices. Susan J. Vercheak, a staff attorney for the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, estimated in a January public hearing that Exelon could inflate prices by $2.3 billion a year. On July 31, Exelon offered $600 million in cash refunds to New Jersey customers through 2008 to help win the boards approval for the acquisition. A spokesman for the Board of Public Utilities, Doyle Siddell, said the agency would not comment on Exelons filing because negotiations were still under way. An Exelon spokeswoman, Jennifer Medley, said the company would not comment beyond the filing, and a Public Service spokesman, Paul Rosengren, declined to comment. More Articles in Business »The Exelon Corporation, the utility owner, warned yesterday that it might be unable to complete its $18.6 billion acquisition of Public Service Enterprise Group because of problems getting approval from New Jersey regulators. Completion of the merger is no longer more likely than not,  Exelon said yesterday in a regulatory filing. The company said it would write off $35 million in costs associated with the transaction this quarter. Shares of Public Service fell yesterday on concern that demands from the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities might kill the acquisition. The takeover, announced in December 2004, is opposed by some state lawmakers. An analyst at Dahlman Rose &amp; Company, Daniele Seitz, said yesterday, The probability of completing the deal has dropped a lot, and it is certainly not in the bag for the end of this month. There must have been an additional request or requirement on behalf of the utility board, and the company didnt go for it. Shares of Public Service fell $2.32, to $68.58, and Exelon declined 18 cents, to $60.12. The acquisition of Public Service, based in Newark, would expand Exelons group of cheaply fueled nuclear power plants, already the largest in the country. The company expected regulatory approval within 18 months, even though New Jerseys top regulator said then that it could take up to two years because of the size of the transaction. The Justice Department on June 22 gave antitrust approval to the transaction on the condition that Exelon sell 5,600 megawatts of power plants. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission gave approval a year earlier. Exelons biggest obstacle among New Jersey regulators has been overcoming concern that the combined company would drive up power prices. Susan J. Vercheak, a staff attorney for the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, estimated in a January public hearing that Exelon could inflate prices by $2.3 billion a year. On July 31, Exelon offered $600 million in cash refunds to New Jersey customers through 2008 to help win the boards approval for the acquisition. A spokesman for the Board of Public Utilities, Doyle Siddell, said the agency would not comment on Exelons filing because negotiations were still under way. An Exelon spokeswoman, Jennifer Medley, said the company would not comment beyond the filing, and a Public Service spokesman, Paul Rosengren, declined to comment.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/20/nyregion/20utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">In Huge Merger of 2 Utilities, ‘Quiet Agency’ Is in Spotlight<date>Published: August 20, 2006</date><text>Correction Appended TRENTON, Aug. 18  In New Jersey, you cannot go anywhere at home without bumping into something that is regulated by a relatively obscure agency called the Board of Public Utilities. The five-member board is supposed to make sure your electric, water and natural gas rates are fair, for example, and it monitors the reliability of your telephone service. But these days, the board has a more visible role. It is on the cusp of making one of the more significant decisions in its 95-year history: whether to approve a $17 billion merger of Exelon, a Chicago-based company, and Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent company of P.S.E.&amp; G., creating the nations largest utility. The merger, first proposed in late 2004, has been approved by regulators in New York, Pennsylvania and Connecticut, as well as by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and the federal Department of Justice. That leaves the New Jersey board as the only remaining hurdle. On Thursday, the boards staff responded with a counterproposal that was welcomed by investors but criticized by consumer groups. Neither Exelon nor Public Service offered an immediate comment. Whether the counterproposal is accepted or modified, the boards commissioners still must act, and that could be weeks away. As a result, the attention of Wall Street, consumer groups and New Jerseys governor, Jon S. Corzine, has turned to a group unaccustomed to the spotlight: the Board of Public Utilities itself. There needs to be serious analysis of the financial terms and conditions for the ratepayers in this state, Mr. Corzine said at a news conference shortly before the counterproposal was offered. And I dont think it needs to be done on a crash-course basis, he continued, just because the board of directors of one of the companies decides that Friday on some day in August is the day that they want a decision. That was a reference to an ultimatum the companies issued earlier in the month. Among the boards considerations are whether the huge new company would end up raising rates and whether it would eventually shrink its work force in New Jersey. And with the price of energy rising, the 3.8 million customers of P.S.E.&amp;G., which has played a major role in the states business and cultural scene, stand to be affected. Until recently, little attention had been paid to the Newark-based state agency, which has long been regarded as influential but has also occasionally been tarred by scandal and accusations of political patronage. It was always a quiet agency that had a lot to do with our lives, even though most people are probably like, The B.P.U.? Who are those folks?  said Victor De Luca, a board member of New Jersey Citizen Action, who has worked on utility issues for years. Gov. Woodrow Wilson created the board in 1911, primarily to oversee railroads and other utilities, and since then it has sent two of its presidents on to the governors office: Brendan T. Byrne and Christie Whitman. Louisiana is the only other state in which a member of its utility commission has made that leap, with Huey Long and the current governor, Kathleen Babineaux Blanco, according to Robert L. Schain, president of Regulatory Research Associates, an independent energy research company in Jersey City. Nevertheless, for many years, the New Jersey board was viewed as a sinecure for well-connected politicians nearing the end of their careers and looking for a prestigious full-time job to boost their salaries  now $141,000 a year for the president, and $125,000 for commissioners  and qualify for a higher pension. Moreover, the board was often criticized for being too cozy with the utility companies it regulated. The current commissioners, too, have deep political roots. The president, Jeanne M. Fox, is a former top official with the federal Environmental Protection Agency, and the wife of Steve DeMicco, a Democratic strategist who managed Mr. Corzines campaign last year and is now managing that of Senator Robert Menendez. The other Democrats on the board are Frederick F. Butler, a former executive director of the Assembly Democrats, and Joseph L. Fiordaliso, a deputy chief of staff under Gov. Richard J. Codey. The Republicans include Connie O. Hughes, who served as the chief of management and policy for Donald DiFrancesco when he was the acting governor, and Christine V. Bator, a commissioner of the states Highway Authority under Mrs. Whitman. This summer, Republican legislators demanded that the board be investigated for its handling of two bank accounts, with a total balance of about $80 million, that the legislators say were established without permission from the states Treasury Department. Yet the board has also been praised, with environmentalists  often the bane of such government agencies  saying it has promoted energy conservation and clean energy initiatives, said Jeff Tittel, the New Jersey executive director of the Sierra Club. In the matter of the merger, Exelon officials and many analysts on Wall Street say the combined utility would operate more efficiently than P.S.E.&amp;G. does, especially in generation of nuclear power. Exelon currently runs 10 nuclear power plants in New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Illinois. 1 2Next Page » Correction: Aug. 30, 2006 Because of an editing error, an article on Aug. 20 about the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, which is deciding whether to approve a merger that would create the countrys largest utility, attributed a distinction to New Jersey erroneously. It is not in fact the only state besides Louisiana in which a member of the state utility commission has gone on to the governors office. (At least four other states  Kentucky, West Virginia, Alabama and New Hampshire  have elected governors who previously served on state utility boards.) More Articles in New York Region »Correction Appended TRENTON, Aug. 18  In New Jersey, you cannot go anywhere at home without bumping into something that is regulated by a relatively obscure agency called the Board of Public Utilities. The five-member board is supposed to make sure your electric, water and natural gas rates are fair, for example, and it monitors the reliability of your telephone service. But these days, the board has a more visible role. It is on the cusp of making one of the more significant decisions in its 95-year history: whether to approve a $17 billion merger of Exelon, a Chicago-based company, and Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent company of P.S.E.&amp; G., creating the nations largest utility. The merger, first proposed in late 2004, has been approved by regulators in New York, Pennsylvania and Connecticut, as well as by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and the federal Department of Justice. That leaves the New Jersey board as the only remaining hurdle. On Thursday, the boards staff responded with a counterproposal that was welcomed by investors but criticized by consumer groups. Neither Exelon nor Public Service offered an immediate comment. Whether the counterproposal is accepted or modified, the boards commissioners still must act, and that could be weeks away. As a result, the attention of Wall Street, consumer groups and New Jerseys governor, Jon S. Corzine, has turned to a group unaccustomed to the spotlight: the Board of Public Utilities itself. There needs to be serious analysis of the financial terms and conditions for the ratepayers in this state, Mr. Corzine said at a news conference shortly before the counterproposal was offered. And I dont think it needs to be done on a crash-course basis, he continued, just because the board of directors of one of the companies decides that Friday on some day in August is the day that they want a decision. That was a reference to an ultimatum the companies issued earlier in the month. Among the boards considerations are whether the huge new company would end up raising rates and whether it would eventually shrink its work force in New Jersey. And with the price of energy rising, the 3.8 million customers of P.S.E.&amp;G., which has played a major role in the states business and cultural scene, stand to be affected. Until recently, little attention had been paid to the Newark-based state agency, which has long been regarded as influential but has also occasionally been tarred by scandal and accusations of political patronage. It was always a quiet agency that had a lot to do with our lives, even though most people are probably like, The B.P.U.? Who are those folks?  said Victor De Luca, a board member of New Jersey Citizen Action, who has worked on utility issues for years. Gov. Woodrow Wilson created the board in 1911, primarily to oversee railroads and other utilities, and since then it has sent two of its presidents on to the governors office: Brendan T. Byrne and Christie Whitman. Louisiana is the only other state in which a member of its utility commission has made that leap, with Huey Long and the current governor, Kathleen Babineaux Blanco, according to Robert L. Schain, president of Regulatory Research Associates, an independent energy research company in Jersey City. Nevertheless, for many years, the New Jersey board was viewed as a sinecure for well-connected politicians nearing the end of their careers and looking for a prestigious full-time job to boost their salaries  now $141,000 a year for the president, and $125,000 for commissioners  and qualify for a higher pension. Moreover, the board was often criticized for being too cozy with the utility companies it regulated. The current commissioners, too, have deep political roots. The president, Jeanne M. Fox, is a former top official with the federal Environmental Protection Agency, and the wife of Steve DeMicco, a Democratic strategist who managed Mr. Corzines campaign last year and is now managing that of Senator Robert Menendez. The other Democrats on the board are Frederick F. Butler, a former executive director of the Assembly Democrats, and Joseph L. Fiordaliso, a deputy chief of staff under Gov. Richard J. Codey. The Republicans include Connie O. Hughes, who served as the chief of management and policy for Donald DiFrancesco when he was the acting governor, and Christine V. Bator, a commissioner of the states Highway Authority under Mrs. Whitman. This summer, Republican legislators demanded that the board be investigated for its handling of two bank accounts, with a total balance of about $80 million, that the legislators say were established without permission from the states Treasury Department. Yet the board has also been praised, with environmentalists  often the bane of such government agencies  saying it has promoted energy conservation and clean energy initiatives, said Jeff Tittel, the New Jersey executive director of the Sierra Club. In the matter of the merger, Exelon officials and many analysts on Wall Street say the combined utility would operate more efficiently than P.S.E.&amp;G. does, especially in generation of nuclear power. Exelon currently runs 10 nuclear power plants in New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Illinois. 1 2Next Page » Correction: Aug. 30, 2006 Because of an editing error, an article on Aug. 20 about the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, which is deciding whether to approve a merger that would create the countrys largest utility, attributed a distinction to New Jersey erroneously. It is not in fact the only state besides Louisiana in which a member of the state utility commission has gone on to the governors office. (At least four other states  Kentucky, West Virginia, Alabama and New Hampshire  have elected governors who previously served on state utility boards.)</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/18/nyregion/18utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Utility Merger Hits a Snag in New Jersey<date>Published: August 18, 2006</date><text>TRENTON, Aug. 17  New Jersey regulators said on Thursday that two energy companies would have to offer more money to customers and sell more power plants to win approval of their proposed $17 billion merger that would create the nations largest utility company. Neither of the two companies  Public Service Enterprise Group nor Exelon, would comment on the counterproposal from the states Board of Public Utilities. The offer effectively addresses the rate and market power issues of the merger and is structured to maintain the high standards of reliability and safety presently delivered by P.S.E.&amp;G., the utilities board said in a two-paragraph news release. But people who were briefed on the proceedings said that the states counterproposal would require the two companies to offer about $820 million to New Jersey ratepayers  or $200 million more than the companies most recent offer, made on Aug. 2. The money would be distributed mainly through credits on customers energy bills. The new counterproposal would also require that P.S.E.&amp;G., based in Newark, and Exelon, with headquarters in Chicago, sell eight fossil-fuel plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania, or two more than the federal Department of Justice recommended in June, when it approved the merger. The counterproposal was intended to assuage concerns of consumers and business groups that the newly formed company would have too much power over the market and the cost of energy. One critic of the merger, Ronald K. Chen, the states public advocate, said in a statement on Thursday that the boards proposal, while a marked improvement, fell short. Dena Mottola, executive director of the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group, which has also been active in the negotiations, was more blunt. Any merger that would go forward under this proposal would fail the boards own standard of review, Ms. Mottola said. It would not bring positive benefits to the ratepayers of the state. People who have been following the proposed merger said it was unlikely that two companies would make a final decision for at least a few days because of the complexity of the deal and the stakes involved. The merger has been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. The utilities board of New Jersey, the state whose residents would be most affected, is the only remaining agency to act. Three weeks ago, the two companies made what they called their last and best offer. Senate President Richard J. Codey and other political leaders have urged the board to act quickly. Hours before the counterproposal was offered, Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who has said he approves of the merger, addressed the topic at a news conference, saying, I think it is time to bring this to conclusion. More Articles in New York Region »TRENTON, Aug. 17  New Jersey regulators said on Thursday that two energy companies would have to offer more money to customers and sell more power plants to win approval of their proposed $17 billion merger that would create the nations largest utility company. Neither of the two companies  Public Service Enterprise Group nor Exelon, would comment on the counterproposal from the states Board of Public Utilities. The offer effectively addresses the rate and market power issues of the merger and is structured to maintain the high standards of reliability and safety presently delivered by P.S.E.&amp;G., the utilities board said in a two-paragraph news release. But people who were briefed on the proceedings said that the states counterproposal would require the two companies to offer about $820 million to New Jersey ratepayers  or $200 million more than the companies most recent offer, made on Aug. 2. The money would be distributed mainly through credits on customers energy bills. The new counterproposal would also require that P.S.E.&amp;G., based in Newark, and Exelon, with headquarters in Chicago, sell eight fossil-fuel plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania, or two more than the federal Department of Justice recommended in June, when it approved the merger. The counterproposal was intended to assuage concerns of consumers and business groups that the newly formed company would have too much power over the market and the cost of energy. One critic of the merger, Ronald K. Chen, the states public advocate, said in a statement on Thursday that the boards proposal, while a marked improvement, fell short. Dena Mottola, executive director of the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group, which has also been active in the negotiations, was more blunt. Any merger that would go forward under this proposal would fail the boards own standard of review, Ms. Mottola said. It would not bring positive benefits to the ratepayers of the state. People who have been following the proposed merger said it was unlikely that two companies would make a final decision for at least a few days because of the complexity of the deal and the stakes involved. The merger has been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. The utilities board of New Jersey, the state whose residents would be most affected, is the only remaining agency to act. Three weeks ago, the two companies made what they called their last and best offer. Senate President Richard J. Codey and other political leaders have urged the board to act quickly. Hours before the counterproposal was offered, Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who has said he approves of the merger, addressed the topic at a news conference, saying, I think it is time to bring this to conclusion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/05/nyregion/05utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">In New Jersey, Board Rejects Utilities Plan for a Merger<date>Published: August 5, 2006</date><text>NEWARK, Aug. 4  New Jersey regulators on Friday rejected the latest proposal from two utility companies to merge and create the largest utility company in the United States, despite increasing pressure from Wall Street investors, consumer advocates and other interested parties to weigh in on the deal. The Exelon Corporation, based in Chicago, and the Public Service Enterprise Group, the Newark-based parent company of Public Service Electric and Gas, the states largest utility, had threatened by letter on Wednesday to abort the deal if the states Board of Public Utilities did not approve by Friday what they called their last and best offer. To nudge the board, the two companies offered a new proposal that they estimated would provide $1.46 billion to P.S.E.&amp;G. customers and New Jersey. But in a meeting on Friday, the board said that the current proposal still lacks clarity on several essential issues, like continuing the high standard of safety and reliability currently delivered by P.S.E.&amp;G. and whether rates would rise if the new company had too much control over pricing. The board recommended that all parties continue to negotiate. Hours after the boards decision, Exelons board of directors met in Chicago. And in a joint statement issued on Friday night, Exelon and Public Service Enterprise Group said that the Exelon board wanted to continue negotiations through Aug. 21. But Exelon also said it would stop negotiations earlier if an agreement did not appear to be imminent. Still, the top officials from both companies offered conciliatory comments, in contrast to the blunt tone of the letter. John W. Rowe, Exelons chairman, president and chief executive, said that the company was "flexible about the details. It has taken a great deal of effort to get this far, he said, and it makes sense to spend a little more time to try to make this work." E. James Ferland, P.S.E.&amp;G.s chairman, president and chief executive, said, "Both companies are prepared to continue our best efforts  working around the clock, seven days a week  to reach a resolution as quickly as possible." The merger has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. And in late June, the federal Department of Justice approved the deal, as well, on the condition that the new company sell six power plants  four in New Jersey and two in Pennsylvania  within 150 days of the deals completion. Yet in New Jersey, the board has proceeded at a pace that it says is prudent, given the scope of the deal. If nothing else, the developments cap a dizzying week highlighting the growing anxiety over the $16 billion merger, which was first proposed more than a year and a half ago. First came the letter on Wednesday from the companies. Then came a hastily arranged conference call on Thursday with irate consumer and business groups, which called the letter a bluff and continued the longstanding criticism of the deal as being bad for electricity customers. Later Thursday, the states public advocate, Ronald K. Chen, said the deal did not do enough to protect New Jersey ratepayers. More Articles in New York Region »NEWARK, Aug. 4  New Jersey regulators on Friday rejected the latest proposal from two utility companies to merge and create the largest utility company in the United States, despite increasing pressure from Wall Street investors, consumer advocates and other interested parties to weigh in on the deal. The Exelon Corporation, based in Chicago, and the Public Service Enterprise Group, the Newark-based parent company of Public Service Electric and Gas, the states largest utility, had threatened by letter on Wednesday to abort the deal if the states Board of Public Utilities did not approve by Friday what they called their last and best offer. To nudge the board, the two companies offered a new proposal that they estimated would provide $1.46 billion to P.S.E.&amp;G. customers and New Jersey. But in a meeting on Friday, the board said that the current proposal still lacks clarity on several essential issues, like continuing the high standard of safety and reliability currently delivered by P.S.E.&amp;G. and whether rates would rise if the new company had too much control over pricing. The board recommended that all parties continue to negotiate. Hours after the boards decision, Exelons board of directors met in Chicago. And in a joint statement issued on Friday night, Exelon and Public Service Enterprise Group said that the Exelon board wanted to continue negotiations through Aug. 21. But Exelon also said it would stop negotiations earlier if an agreement did not appear to be imminent. Still, the top officials from both companies offered conciliatory comments, in contrast to the blunt tone of the letter. John W. Rowe, Exelons chairman, president and chief executive, said that the company was "flexible about the details. It has taken a great deal of effort to get this far, he said, and it makes sense to spend a little more time to try to make this work." E. James Ferland, P.S.E.&amp;G.s chairman, president and chief executive, said, "Both companies are prepared to continue our best efforts  working around the clock, seven days a week  to reach a resolution as quickly as possible." The merger has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. And in late June, the federal Department of Justice approved the deal, as well, on the condition that the new company sell six power plants  four in New Jersey and two in Pennsylvania  within 150 days of the deals completion. Yet in New Jersey, the board has proceeded at a pace that it says is prudent, given the scope of the deal. If nothing else, the developments cap a dizzying week highlighting the growing anxiety over the $16 billion merger, which was first proposed more than a year and a half ago. First came the letter on Wednesday from the companies. Then came a hastily arranged conference call on Thursday with irate consumer and business groups, which called the letter a bluff and continued the longstanding criticism of the deal as being bad for electricity customers. Later Thursday, the states public advocate, Ronald K. Chen, said the deal did not do enough to protect New Jersey ratepayers.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/04/nyregion/04utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Utilities Give New Jersey Regulators Deadline to Act on Merger<date>Published: August 4, 2006</date><text>TRENTON, Aug. 3  Two utility companies planning a merger to create the largest utility company in the United States have vowed to pull out of the deal if New Jersey regulators do not agree to their terms by Friday. In a letter dated Wednesday, officials of the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation and the Newark-based Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent company of P.S.E.&amp;G., expressed frustration that the state’s Board of Public Utilities  the only agency remaining that could block the deal  had taken almost two years to act and said that they had made their “last and best offer” for a merger. P.S.E.&amp;G. is the state’s largest utility. “This is not a threat,” the letter said. “It is just a factual statement of where both companies are in terms of financial capability 20 months after entering into their merger agreement.” Threat or not, the letter intensifies the stakes over a long-simmering deal that opponents  including members of Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s cabinet, and a bipartisan coalition of legislators, consumer advocates and business groups  say would discourage competition. Though the federal Department of Justice approved the merger in June, critics contend that the typical residential bill could increase by about $45 a month should the merger go through. On Thursday, Doyal H. Siddell, a spokesman for the State Board of Public Utilities, said that “the board does not comment on the details of ongoing settlement discussions.” But he did say that the board would meet on Friday afternoon. Two people familiar with the negotiations said that they expected the board to issue a statement after the meeting. In its latest offer, the two companies proposed to provide an estimated “$1.46 billion of positive benefits to P.S.E.&amp;G. ratepayers and the state of New Jersey,” their letter said. The new company would also maintain 16 customer service centers in New Jersey and would increase charitable contributions by Public Service Enterprise, long a strong supporter of the arts in the state. But on Thursday, Ronald K. Chen, the state’s public advocate, said in a statement that the latest proposal “falls far short of protecting New Jersey ratepayers.” Mr. Chen also submitted a counterproposal. According to people involved in the negotiations, it would require, among other things, that the utility companies sell three additional power plants  or three more than the six that the Justice Department had recommended  totaling 2,546 megawatts; that the companies give the state $930 million in rate relief, or almost double what they had offered; and that they give the Board of Public Utilities the right of approval of the final buyers in the sale of power plants. In a sign of how quickly developments were moving, a coalition of consumer and business groups hastily arranged a conference call on Thursday with reporters and criticized the utility companies’ letter as a “bluff” relying on “bullying tactics and media spin.” The merger has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. But in New Jersey, the process has unfolded more slowly than the utility companies would like  though at a pace that State House officials say they believe is appropriate, given the size and importance of the deal. More Articles in New York Region »TRENTON, Aug. 3  Two utility companies planning a merger to create the largest utility company in the United States have vowed to pull out of the deal if New Jersey regulators do not agree to their terms by Friday. In a letter dated Wednesday, officials of the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation and the Newark-based Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent company of P.S.E.&amp;G., expressed frustration that the state’s Board of Public Utilities  the only agency remaining that could block the deal  had taken almost two years to act and said that they had made their “last and best offer” for a merger. P.S.E.&amp;G. is the state’s largest utility. “This is not a threat,” the letter said. “It is just a factual statement of where both companies are in terms of financial capability 20 months after entering into their merger agreement.” Threat or not, the letter intensifies the stakes over a long-simmering deal that opponents  including members of Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s cabinet, and a bipartisan coalition of legislators, consumer advocates and business groups  say would discourage competition. Though the federal Department of Justice approved the merger in June, critics contend that the typical residential bill could increase by about $45 a month should the merger go through. On Thursday, Doyal H. Siddell, a spokesman for the State Board of Public Utilities, said that “the board does not comment on the details of ongoing settlement discussions.” But he did say that the board would meet on Friday afternoon. Two people familiar with the negotiations said that they expected the board to issue a statement after the meeting. In its latest offer, the two companies proposed to provide an estimated “$1.46 billion of positive benefits to P.S.E.&amp;G. ratepayers and the state of New Jersey,” their letter said. The new company would also maintain 16 customer service centers in New Jersey and would increase charitable contributions by Public Service Enterprise, long a strong supporter of the arts in the state. But on Thursday, Ronald K. Chen, the state’s public advocate, said in a statement that the latest proposal “falls far short of protecting New Jersey ratepayers.” Mr. Chen also submitted a counterproposal. According to people involved in the negotiations, it would require, among other things, that the utility companies sell three additional power plants  or three more than the six that the Justice Department had recommended  totaling 2,546 megawatts; that the companies give the state $930 million in rate relief, or almost double what they had offered; and that they give the Board of Public Utilities the right of approval of the final buyers in the sale of power plants. In a sign of how quickly developments were moving, a coalition of consumer and business groups hastily arranged a conference call on Thursday with reporters and criticized the utility companies’ letter as a “bluff” relying on “bullying tactics and media spin.” The merger has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. But in New Jersey, the process has unfolded more slowly than the utility companies would like  though at a pace that State House officials say they believe is appropriate, given the size and importance of the deal.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/27/nyregion/27utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Assembly Tries to Thwart Utility Merger in New Jersey<date>Published: June 27, 2006</date><text>TRENTON, June 26  In an effort to derail a utility merger that many say would sharply increase energy rates across New Jersey, more than half of the General Assembly members have sponsored a resolution opposing the deal, the legislators said on Monday. The resolution is addressed to the Board of Public Utilities, the only agency remaining that could block the acquisition of the Public Service Enterprise Group, parent of the state's largest utility, by the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation. Opponents of the merger  including consumer and business groups as well as the state's new public advocate  stepped up efforts after the antitrust division of the federal Department of Justice gave its approval to the merger last Thursday. The merger would create the largest single utility company in the nation, and critics contend that its sheer size would discourage competitors in the New Jersey market. The typical residential bill would rise by about $45 a month as a result of a merger, according to the estimate of one staff member for the Board of Public Utilities. But Public Service Enterprise officials emphasized that the merger proposal was still subject to change and that they were continuing to negotiate with many parties  including competitors, large customers and state agencies  who have challenged the plan before the utilities board. The five commissioners of the board are expected to vote on the merger sometime this summer, but for now are awaiting the recommendation of an administrative law judge who has already held hearings and will issue an advisory opinion. Alternatively, the judge may accept and recommend a settlement reached by the parties. "So we say to legislators, wait until the deal is announced before you decide whether the benefits are there for New Jersey customers," Paul Rosengren, a Public Service Enterprise spokesman, said on Monday. As a condition of Justice Department approval for the merger, Public Service Enterprise and Exelon agreed to sell four power plants in New Jersey  in Linden, Hamilton Township, Jersey City and Woodbridge  and two in Pennsylvania. They also agreed to limit rate increases charged customers of Public Service Electric and Gas, a subsidiary of Public Service Enterprise that has about two million customers in New Jersey. The state's public advocate, Ronald K. Chen, has urged the administrative law judge to oppose the merger. Mr. Chen said in a statement that it "could lead to dramatic increases in electric and natural gas prices for all New Jersey ratepayers, not just P.S.E.&amp;G. customers, because all New Jersey utilities buy power from the same energy generators." The utility commissioners must also review the agreement between the Justice Department and the two companies. Assemblyman Joseph Cryan, a Democrat from Union and a primary sponsor of the Assembly resolution, said at a news conference on Monday that the measure had 43 sponsors, including 29 Democrats and 14 Republicans. A resolution in the State Senate has drawn bipartisan support as well. The Legislature has only four days left to approve a state budget, however, and it is not expected to conduct regular business again before Labor Day. The merger proposal has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. More Articles in New York Region »TRENTON, June 26  In an effort to derail a utility merger that many say would sharply increase energy rates across New Jersey, more than half of the General Assembly members have sponsored a resolution opposing the deal, the legislators said on Monday. The resolution is addressed to the Board of Public Utilities, the only agency remaining that could block the acquisition of the Public Service Enterprise Group, parent of the state's largest utility, by the Chicago-based Exelon Corporation. Opponents of the merger  including consumer and business groups as well as the state's new public advocate  stepped up efforts after the antitrust division of the federal Department of Justice gave its approval to the merger last Thursday. The merger would create the largest single utility company in the nation, and critics contend that its sheer size would discourage competitors in the New Jersey market. The typical residential bill would rise by about $45 a month as a result of a merger, according to the estimate of one staff member for the Board of Public Utilities. But Public Service Enterprise officials emphasized that the merger proposal was still subject to change and that they were continuing to negotiate with many parties  including competitors, large customers and state agencies  who have challenged the plan before the utilities board. The five commissioners of the board are expected to vote on the merger sometime this summer, but for now are awaiting the recommendation of an administrative law judge who has already held hearings and will issue an advisory opinion. Alternatively, the judge may accept and recommend a settlement reached by the parties. "So we say to legislators, wait until the deal is announced before you decide whether the benefits are there for New Jersey customers," Paul Rosengren, a Public Service Enterprise spokesman, said on Monday. As a condition of Justice Department approval for the merger, Public Service Enterprise and Exelon agreed to sell four power plants in New Jersey  in Linden, Hamilton Township, Jersey City and Woodbridge  and two in Pennsylvania. They also agreed to limit rate increases charged customers of Public Service Electric and Gas, a subsidiary of Public Service Enterprise that has about two million customers in New Jersey. The state's public advocate, Ronald K. Chen, has urged the administrative law judge to oppose the merger. Mr. Chen said in a statement that it "could lead to dramatic increases in electric and natural gas prices for all New Jersey ratepayers, not just P.S.E.&amp;G. customers, because all New Jersey utilities buy power from the same energy generators." The utility commissioners must also review the agreement between the Justice Department and the two companies. Assemblyman Joseph Cryan, a Democrat from Union and a primary sponsor of the Assembly resolution, said at a news conference on Monday that the measure had 43 sponsors, including 29 Democrats and 14 Republicans. A resolution in the State Senate has drawn bipartisan support as well. The Legislature has only four days left to approve a state budget, however, and it is not expected to conduct regular business again before Labor Day. The merger proposal has already been approved by regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, New York and Connecticut, and by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/26/us/26tut.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Antiquities in Office? Not While King Tut Rules Chicago<date>Published: May 26, 2006</date><text>Facing indignant demands from Egypt's antiquities chief, a corporate sponsor of a touring King Tut exhibition opening today in Chicago agreed yesterday to relinquish an ancient sarcophagus that is kept at its company headquarters. Zahi Hawass, the hard-charging secretary general of Egypt's Supreme Council of Antiquities, learned of the artifact's existence on Wednesday at a preview for the press at the Field Museum. At the event, Randy Mehrbert, a representative of Exelon, the giant energy company based in Chicago, observed in his formal remarks that the company's chairman, John W. Rowe, had such a passion for Egyptian antiquities that he kept one in his office. Dr. Hawass immediately demanded that organizers of the show drop Exelon as a sponsor unless it agreed to give the sarcophagus to the Field Museum or return it to Egypt. Late yesterday, after a flurry of meetings at the museum, a spokeswoman for Exelon announced the resolution. "John Rowe has offered the piece to the museum on loan for an indefinite period of time," said a company spokeswoman, Jennifer Medley. "John loves the Field Museum and is happy to share the piece." In a letter to the Field Museum, Dr. Hawass wrote, "Ancient artifacts are not for display in homes and offices; rather they are meant to be shown in museums and cultural institutions." He continued, "King Tut himself would not be pleased to see a priceless Egyptian artifact trapped inside the office of any one individual." A spokeswoman for Exelon said that Mr. Rowe had bought the mummy-shaped wood-and-plaster coffin, painted with figures and hieroglyphics, from a reputable dealer in Chicago. Nonetheless, the letter sent museum officials into action, as organizers of the show tried to come up with a solution that would meet Dr. Hawass's demands without alienating an important donor to the museum. Exelon would not say how much it had donated, but the spokeswoman said it was a six-figure sum. Mark Lach, a spokesman for Arts and Exhibitions International, the exhibit's organizer, said that his company agreed with Dr. Hawass, but added: "Our position is that we certainly don't want to affect this relationship we have with Exelon. We want them to continue as a proud partner in this exhibit." As the chief custodian of Egypt's vast treasure trove and archaeological sites, Dr. Hawass wields an uncommon power within the world of museums and archaeological research; Time magazine recently named him as one of the world's 100 most influential people. He is also known for his ability to stir controversy at an opportune moment, placing Egypt at the forefront of countries with ancient civilizations that have demanded the return of antiquities lost to Western collections. Usually those cases have involved artifacts with questionable origins. In an interview, Dr. Hawass also said he was pursuing legal action against the St. Louis Art Museum, which declined to meet a May 15 deadline he had set for the return of a funerary mask from 1550 B.C. The mask, he said, was logged in Egyptian government records in the 1950's. But the St. Louis museum said that it had consulted the Egyptian authorities and art registries to ensure that the piece was not stolen before its purchase in 1998. Dr. Hawass said he was seeking a meeting with the St. Louis museum's director, Brent Benjamin. "This is a very important case," he said. "I'm thinking of going to St. Louis to make a press conference and make his life hell." The Chicago show is being mounted for Egypt by private commercial entities led by the Anschutz Entertainment Group, which operates the Staples Center in Los Angeles and other sports and entertainment places. Tim Leiweke, president of Anschutz, has said that the Egyptians will take in more than 50 percent of the gross revenue from the tour. After stops in Los Angeles and Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and now Chicago, the show will travel to Philadelphia and London. Officials are expecting at least a million people to visit the Tut exhibition in Chicago. More Articles in National »Facing indignant demands from Egypt's antiquities chief, a corporate sponsor of a touring King Tut exhibition opening today in Chicago agreed yesterday to relinquish an ancient sarcophagus that is kept at its company headquarters. Zahi Hawass, the hard-charging secretary general of Egypt's Supreme Council of Antiquities, learned of the artifact's existence on Wednesday at a preview for the press at the Field Museum. At the event, Randy Mehrbert, a representative of Exelon, the giant energy company based in Chicago, observed in his formal remarks that the company's chairman, John W. Rowe, had such a passion for Egyptian antiquities that he kept one in his office. Dr. Hawass immediately demanded that organizers of the show drop Exelon as a sponsor unless it agreed to give the sarcophagus to the Field Museum or return it to Egypt. Late yesterday, after a flurry of meetings at the museum, a spokeswoman for Exelon announced the resolution. "John Rowe has offered the piece to the museum on loan for an indefinite period of time," said a company spokeswoman, Jennifer Medley. "John loves the Field Museum and is happy to share the piece." In a letter to the Field Museum, Dr. Hawass wrote, "Ancient artifacts are not for display in homes and offices; rather they are meant to be shown in museums and cultural institutions." He continued, "King Tut himself would not be pleased to see a priceless Egyptian artifact trapped inside the office of any one individual." A spokeswoman for Exelon said that Mr. Rowe had bought the mummy-shaped wood-and-plaster coffin, painted with figures and hieroglyphics, from a reputable dealer in Chicago. Nonetheless, the letter sent museum officials into action, as organizers of the show tried to come up with a solution that would meet Dr. Hawass's demands without alienating an important donor to the museum. Exelon would not say how much it had donated, but the spokeswoman said it was a six-figure sum. Mark Lach, a spokesman for Arts and Exhibitions International, the exhibit's organizer, said that his company agreed with Dr. Hawass, but added: "Our position is that we certainly don't want to affect this relationship we have with Exelon. We want them to continue as a proud partner in this exhibit." As the chief custodian of Egypt's vast treasure trove and archaeological sites, Dr. Hawass wields an uncommon power within the world of museums and archaeological research; Time magazine recently named him as one of the world's 100 most influential people. He is also known for his ability to stir controversy at an opportune moment, placing Egypt at the forefront of countries with ancient civilizations that have demanded the return of antiquities lost to Western collections. Usually those cases have involved artifacts with questionable origins. In an interview, Dr. Hawass also said he was pursuing legal action against the St. Louis Art Museum, which declined to meet a May 15 deadline he had set for the return of a funerary mask from 1550 B.C. The mask, he said, was logged in Egyptian government records in the 1950's. But the St. Louis museum said that it had consulted the Egyptian authorities and art registries to ensure that the piece was not stolen before its purchase in 1998. Dr. Hawass said he was seeking a meeting with the St. Louis museum's director, Brent Benjamin. "This is a very important case," he said. "I'm thinking of going to St. Louis to make a press conference and make his life hell." The Chicago show is being mounted for Egypt by private commercial entities led by the Anschutz Entertainment Group, which operates the Staples Center in Los Angeles and other sports and entertainment places. Tim Leiweke, president of Anschutz, has said that the Egyptians will take in more than 50 percent of the gross revenue from the tour. After stops in Los Angeles and Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and now Chicago, the show will travel to Philadelphia and London. Officials are expecting at least a million people to visit the Tut exhibition in Chicago.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/31/business/yourmoney/31util.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Will Fame and Fortune Change Utility Stocks?<date>Published: July 31, 2005</date><text>IF technology stocks are the market's equivalent of Ferraris in the fast lane, then utilities are Volvos driven down Main Street at two miles an hour below the speed limit. They are bought for safety and stability, not high performance. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Christophe Vorlet Better Bets Until lately, that is. Indexes of utility stocks have doubled since their lows of October 2002, far outpacing the rest of the stock market. It has been the sector's sharpest rally since World War II. The move has also produced high valuations, making some professional investors cautious. Others are unfazed; they acknowledge that the sector is not as cheap as it was, but they also say that it may not be as richly valued as a pessimist may contend. And they assert that the factors that sent prices higher are still in force. One of the skeptics is Edward Yardeni, chief investment strategist at Oak Associates. "I wish I'd owned them two years ago," Mr. Yardeni said. "They've had a good run, but they're back to being fully valued. It's unlikely they'll keep running like this." Based on its estimates of earnings over the next year, Morgan Stanley reckons that the average price-to-earnings ratio of companies in its utility index is 94 percent of the P/E of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index. That is one reason the bank advises keeping less money in the sector than its weight in the S.&amp; P. 500 warrants. Tim O'Brien, who manages two utility funds for Evergreen Investment Management, says that this near-parity in valuations has not occurred since at least the 1950's. He finds this troubling and warns investors not to expect further outsized gains. "The bulk of the significant outperformance is behind us," he said. Still, Robert Becker, a manager of utility funds for Cohen &amp; Steers, said the stability of utilities could bring in more buyers. "We believe we're in a low-return environment," Mr. Becker said. "Companies with predictable earnings and cash-flow growth are attractive, and utilities offer that." They also offer growth potential through mergers, he said. A bill passed by Congress last week allows utilities greater latitude to buy one another. If President Bush signs it, as expected, the sector may lure new investors, in Mr. Becker's opinion. Richard Bernstein, a market strategist at Merrill Lynch, is hopeful, too, in part because Mr. Becker's enthusiasm for utilities is not widely shared. The absence of much desire to hop on the bandwagon after the rally, contrary to Wall Street custom, is one reason that Mr. Bernstein describes utilities as "our favorite sector." Investors are underestimating utilities' earnings growth, he said, while counting on growth from economically sensitive sectors when the country's expansion may be running out of steam. "The only sector that is supposed to have accelerating earnings in '04 to '06 is utilities," he said. "They're like salmon swimming upstream. They deserve a superior valuation." Giving utilities more credit and factoring in a more modest outlook for other industries "does take away the egregious overvaluation that people worry about," Mr. Bernstein said. It was just a few years ago that the sector was egregiously undervalued, with a P/E barely 40 percent of the S.&amp; P. 500's, by Morgan Stanley's calculation. That discount was a byproduct of the taint from "Enron and the Enron wannabes," Mr. O'Brien said. The Enron bankruptcy and scandal, and efforts by other companies to expand their business mix beyond power generation and other staid activities considered traditional for utilities, led to a "reign of terror" by credit rating agencies, he said. Utilities are big borrowers, so they are especially sensitive to the opinions of firms that judge creditworthiness. Those firms advised many utilities that their ratings would be cut if they did not reduce debt on their books, Mr. O'Brien explained. Utilities scrambled to sell new shares to pay down the debt, sending their stock prices lower. "It got pretty ugly," Mr. O'Brien said. After "the debacle of '01, '02," he said, life became better for utilities. Rating downgrades abated, and yields on long-term government bonds plunged. Bonds and utilities tend to appeal to the same sort of investor: someone interested in safety and income. When bond yields fall, the dividend yields on utilities become more attractive and shares are snapped up. The 2003 tax cut on dividend income provided an additional incentive to buy. The lower tax rates had the effect of raising dividend yields in the hands of investors, but Mr. Yardeni says the increase in share prices has more than made up for the gain. "The dividends are worth more after taxes, and that's why P/E's went up," he said. "But they are no bargains now. The stocks are fully valued even after factoring in the lower tax rates." Mr. Becker crunches the numbers differently. The after-tax yield on utilities, compared with Treasury bond yields, remains higher than the historical average, he said. Dividends are important to Mr. Becker, who calls himself a traditionalist. He prefers owning utilities that operate in regulated markets, where the stability of earnings allows for high dividend payments. Within that segment of the industry, he favors companies that have opportunities to sell excess output elsewhere at whatever price the market will bear. Some examples are the Southern Company and Exelon. Another holding is Duke Energy. Apart from the straight-ahead utility, Duke is engaged in a number of businesses - it processes natural gas and owns pipelines - that could be spun out into separate entities, enhancing value to shareholders, he said. Now that share prices have soared, Mr. O'Brien looks abroad for companies he thinks offer better-than-average growth prospects, but without higher-than-average risk or valuations. His favorites include British water companies like Kelda, United Utilities and Pennon. "They offer really good earnings growth," he said, "and they just went through a five-year regulatory review and got a good deal." Earnings growth of 8 to 12 percent a year is "locked in" for that period, he said. Other European holdings include two German electricity producers, Eon and RWE. In the United States, Mr. O'Brien likes Exelon and TXU for their "above-average earnings growth and above-average sensitivity to energy prices." Unless they operate in states with strong regulatory constraints, utilities adjust the prices they command for electricity, based on the cost of the most expensive source of energy. When oil and gas are expensive, companies that produce much of their power from cheaper sources like nuclear energy and coal can widen their margins. That is especially true in the sweltering conditions that much of the country has faced lately, Mr. O'Brien said. Hot weather tends to coincide with higher oil and gas prices, increasing the price discrepancies with other fuel sources. Mr. Bernstein rates Cinergy, Constellation Energy and Entergy highly for their ability to benefit from differences in fuel prices. He also likes several high-yielding utilities that are less free to raise customers' rates, including PG&amp;E, Progress Energy, FPL, Dominion and Ameren. Utilities can't maintain their high-octane performance forever, but if Mr. Bernstein's and Mr. Becker's assessments are accurate, there may be plenty of mileage left in the stocks. More Articles in Business &gt;IF technology stocks are the market's equivalent of Ferraris in the fast lane, then utilities are Volvos driven down Main Street at two miles an hour below the speed limit. They are bought for safety and stability, not high performance. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Christophe Vorlet Better Bets Until lately, that is. Indexes of utility stocks have doubled since their lows of October 2002, far outpacing the rest of the stock market. It has been the sector's sharpest rally since World War II. The move has also produced high valuations, making some professional investors cautious. Others are unfazed; they acknowledge that the sector is not as cheap as it was, but they also say that it may not be as richly valued as a pessimist may contend. And they assert that the factors that sent prices higher are still in force. One of the skeptics is Edward Yardeni, chief investment strategist at Oak Associates. "I wish I'd owned them two years ago," Mr. Yardeni said. "They've had a good run, but they're back to being fully valued. It's unlikely they'll keep running like this." Based on its estimates of earnings over the next year, Morgan Stanley reckons that the average price-to-earnings ratio of companies in its utility index is 94 percent of the P/E of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index. That is one reason the bank advises keeping less money in the sector than its weight in the S.&amp; P. 500 warrants. Tim O'Brien, who manages two utility funds for Evergreen Investment Management, says that this near-parity in valuations has not occurred since at least the 1950's. He finds this troubling and warns investors not to expect further outsized gains. "The bulk of the significant outperformance is behind us," he said. Still, Robert Becker, a manager of utility funds for Cohen &amp; Steers, said the stability of utilities could bring in more buyers. "We believe we're in a low-return environment," Mr. Becker said. "Companies with predictable earnings and cash-flow growth are attractive, and utilities offer that." They also offer growth potential through mergers, he said. A bill passed by Congress last week allows utilities greater latitude to buy one another. If President Bush signs it, as expected, the sector may lure new investors, in Mr. Becker's opinion. Richard Bernstein, a market strategist at Merrill Lynch, is hopeful, too, in part because Mr. Becker's enthusiasm for utilities is not widely shared. The absence of much desire to hop on the bandwagon after the rally, contrary to Wall Street custom, is one reason that Mr. Bernstein describes utilities as "our favorite sector." Investors are underestimating utilities' earnings growth, he said, while counting on growth from economically sensitive sectors when the country's expansion may be running out of steam. "The only sector that is supposed to have accelerating earnings in '04 to '06 is utilities," he said. "They're like salmon swimming upstream. They deserve a superior valuation." Giving utilities more credit and factoring in a more modest outlook for other industries "does take away the egregious overvaluation that people worry about," Mr. Bernstein said. It was just a few years ago that the sector was egregiously undervalued, with a P/E barely 40 percent of the S.&amp; P. 500's, by Morgan Stanley's calculation. That discount was a byproduct of the taint from "Enron and the Enron wannabes," Mr. O'Brien said. The Enron bankruptcy and scandal, and efforts by other companies to expand their business mix beyond power generation and other staid activities considered traditional for utilities, led to a "reign of terror" by credit rating agencies, he said. Utilities are big borrowers, so they are especially sensitive to the opinions of firms that judge creditworthiness. Those firms advised many utilities that their ratings would be cut if they did not reduce debt on their books, Mr. O'Brien explained. Utilities scrambled to sell new shares to pay down the debt, sending their stock prices lower. "It got pretty ugly," Mr. O'Brien said. After "the debacle of '01, '02," he said, life became better for utilities. Rating downgrades abated, and yields on long-term government bonds plunged. Bonds and utilities tend to appeal to the same sort of investor: someone interested in safety and income. When bond yields fall, the dividend yields on utilities become more attractive and shares are snapped up. The 2003 tax cut on dividend income provided an additional incentive to buy. The lower tax rates had the effect of raising dividend yields in the hands of investors, but Mr. Yardeni says the increase in share prices has more than made up for the gain. "The dividends are worth more after taxes, and that's why P/E's went up," he said. "But they are no bargains now. The stocks are fully valued even after factoring in the lower tax rates." Mr. Becker crunches the numbers differently. The after-tax yield on utilities, compared with Treasury bond yields, remains higher than the historical average, he said. Dividends are important to Mr. Becker, who calls himself a traditionalist. He prefers owning utilities that operate in regulated markets, where the stability of earnings allows for high dividend payments. Within that segment of the industry, he favors companies that have opportunities to sell excess output elsewhere at whatever price the market will bear. Some examples are the Southern Company and Exelon. Another holding is Duke Energy. Apart from the straight-ahead utility, Duke is engaged in a number of businesses - it processes natural gas and owns pipelines - that could be spun out into separate entities, enhancing value to shareholders, he said. Now that share prices have soared, Mr. O'Brien looks abroad for companies he thinks offer better-than-average growth prospects, but without higher-than-average risk or valuations. His favorites include British water companies like Kelda, United Utilities and Pennon. "They offer really good earnings growth," he said, "and they just went through a five-year regulatory review and got a good deal." Earnings growth of 8 to 12 percent a year is "locked in" for that period, he said. Other European holdings include two German electricity producers, Eon and RWE. In the United States, Mr. O'Brien likes Exelon and TXU for their "above-average earnings growth and above-average sensitivity to energy prices." Unless they operate in states with strong regulatory constraints, utilities adjust the prices they command for electricity, based on the cost of the most expensive source of energy. When oil and gas are expensive, companies that produce much of their power from cheaper sources like nuclear energy and coal can widen their margins. That is especially true in the sweltering conditions that much of the country has faced lately, Mr. O'Brien said. Hot weather tends to coincide with higher oil and gas prices, increasing the price discrepancies with other fuel sources. Mr. Bernstein rates Cinergy, Constellation Energy and Entergy highly for their ability to benefit from differences in fuel prices. He also likes several high-yielding utilities that are less free to raise customers' rates, including PG&amp;E, Progress Energy, FPL, Dominion and Ameren. Utilities can't maintain their high-octane performance forever, but if Mr. Bernstein's and Mr. Becker's assessments are accurate, there may be plenty of mileage left in the stocks.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DE1F30F935A15751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">BRIEFINGS: ENERGY; BUT WHAT IF I SMELL GAS?<date>Published: December 26, 2004</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, the owner of utilities in northern Illinois and eastern Pennsylvania, said Dec. 20 that it would buy the Public Service Enterprise Group of New Jersey in a deal valued at about $12.8 billion that would create the country's largest power company. If the deal is completed by early next year as expected, the holding company combining the two utilities would generate more than 52,000 megawatts of power, serve nine million customers and have about $26 billion in annual revenue. The deal is subject to approval by federal and state regulators. Shareholders of Public Service, the parent of P.S.E.&amp;G., will receive 1.225 shares of Exelon stock for each share they own, according to terms of the agreement. That offer values Public Service shares at $51.28, about an 8.5 percent premium above the close on Dec. 17. It also includes the assumption of $14.1 billion worth of debt. The combined company, named Exelon Energy and Gas, will be based in Chicago. Eric Dash Photo: A P.S.E.&amp;G. plant in Kearney. The company is about to be bought by Exelon. (Photo by Emile Wamsteker/Bloomberg News)</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DB1030F931A15751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">Corrections<date>Published: December 22, 2004</date><text>An article in Business Day yesterday about the acquisition of the Public Service Enterprise Group of New Jersey by the Exelon Corporation referred incorrectly in some editions to the number of customers to be served by the combined utility. It is 9 million, not 18 million.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/21/business/21utility.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Plans to Buy New Jersey Utility<date>Published: December 21, 2004</date><text>he Exelon Corporation, the owner of utilities in northern Illinois and eastern Pennsylvania, said yesterday that it would buy the Public Service Enterprise Group of New Jersey in a deal valued at about $12.8 billion that would create the country's largest power company. If the deal is completed by early next year as expected, the holding company combining the two utilities would generate more than 52,000 megawatts of power, serve nine million customers and have about $26 billion in revenue each year. The deal, however, is subject to approval by federal and state regulators. Shareholders of Public Service, the parent of P.S.E.&amp; G., will receive 1.225 shares of Exelon stock for each share they own, according to the terms of the agreement. That offer values Public Service shares at $51.28, about an 8.5 percent premium above the close on Dec. 17. It also includes the assumption of $14.1 billion worth of debt, more than doubling Exelon's current load. The combined company, named Exelon Energy and Gas, will have its headquarters in Chicago, where Exelon is based, and energy trading and nuclear operations in Pennsylvania. But it will leave the main offices of P.S.E.&amp; G., a New Jersey institution for more than 100 years, in Newark and will run the combined company's power generation business from there. Exelon and Public Service executives said yesterday that they expected the merger would add to earnings, creating a pretax savings of $400 million by 2006 and $500 million annually the next year that could, at least in small part, be passed along to consumers. But for the deal to be complete, the new company will have to shed more than 1,400 jobs, or 5 percent of the combined work force of 28,000, and overcome the scrutiny of an alphabet soup of state and federal regulators. During presentations yesterday at P.S.E.&amp; G.'s headquarters in Newark, both John W. Rowe, Exelon's chief executive who will head the combined company, and E. James Ferland, Public Service's chief, who will become the new company's nonexecutive chairman, remained optimistic. Both executives acknowledged those concerns, with Mr. Ferland saying that the job cuts accounted for less than half the cost savings, and Mr. Rowe rattling off a laundry list of Exelon's contributions to the local areas it serves. Wall Street, meanwhile, seemed to react enthusiastically to the deal. Shares of Exelon closed at $43.05, up $1.19; Public Service shares traded up $3.29, to close at $50.56. According to the merger announcement, the new company expects to maintain its current dividend policy to pay 50 percent to 60 percent of earnings, a move that will lead to increases for investors at both companies. Strategically, Mr. Rowe and Mr. Ferland said the deal fitted into both companies' plans. For Exelon, the merger enables the company to expand into the Northeast, gain a foothold in the country's largest electricity market and add customers and nuclear power plants to its existing operations in Illinois and Pennsylvania. It also comes as Exelon anticipates a revenue drop in 2007, when competition for electricity service in Illinois intensifies. For P.S.E.&amp; G., the merger will provide the scale required to operate its fossil-fuel plants more efficiently and the management expertise to turn around its nuclear power plants, which have contributed to its stock's underperforming industry peers by 20 percent this year. The companies already jointly operate some of the nuclear power plants, and in anticipation of the merger, Exelon said that next month it would enter a nuclear operating services agreement with Public Service so that about two dozen of its managers could oversee some of the New Jersey utility's other plants. Public Service, meanwhile, will begin shedding its international investments in order to pave the way for the new company's domestic focus. Although Public Service has courted other utilities, Mr. Ferland said that discussions with Exelon began months ago but the talks intensified recently as he became more aware of Mr. Rowe's vision for the deal. "It's not too surprising that someone would want to do this," said Neil Kalton, a utilities analyst for A. G. Edwards based in St. Louis, who continues to rate Public Service as a hold. "Whether this thing works out remains to be seen." Moreover, Exelon and Public Service will need approval from both state and federal regulators. Within the next few months, they must file petitions with the regulatory agencies in Pennsylvania, Illinois and New Jersey for assessment. "The company says it could take 12 months to 15 months," said Jeanne Fox, president of the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities. "If it takes 24 months, that would not be highly unusual." It must also pass muster with the Justice Department, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and other federal regulators who evaluate its market power along with the Securities and Exchange Commission. Both executives acknowledged the influence of the regulatory agencies, and said they were prepared to take steps to ensure the deal goes through. The combined company, they said, could sell some gas and electricity plants or auction off the output of some of their nuclear power plants to avoid anticompetition concerns. They said that state regulators might require them to pass on some of the cost savings from the merger to consumers, but pointed out that only 30 percent of those gains come from the regulated market. The merger announced yesterday was more than twice as big as the two largest United States utility deals on record, and had been anticipated by many industry observers after word seeped out last week. It comes almost a year after Exelon abandoned its offer to buy Illinois Power from Dynegy, and Public Service has said it courted other utility companies.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/18/business/18util.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Biggest Utility in New Jersey Seen as Target of Acquisition<date>Published: December 18, 2004</date><text>he Exelon Corporation, the owner of utilities in northern Illinois and eastern Pennsylvania, is in advanced talks to acquire New Jersey's largest utility, P.S.E.&amp;G., for about $12 billion, executives involved in the negotiations said yesterday. A deal would create the largest utility holding company in the country, with annual revenue of more than $26 billion and 25,000 employees. Buying P.S.E.&amp;G. would allow John Rowe, Exelon's chief executive, to expand his business in the Northeast, the country's largest electricity market, and add both customers and nuclear power plants to his existing assets in Illinois and Pennsylvania. The Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent of P.S.E.&amp;G., also owns plants in California, Texas and Hawaii, as well as businesses abroad. The move comes a year after Exelon abandoned its offer to buy Illinois Power from Dynegy for $425 million in cash and $1.8 billion in assumed debt. Exelon is also negotiating to assume $14 billion of Public Service debt, the executives involved in the discussions said. While an announcement of a deal may come as soon as next week, the executives cautioned that the terms were not yet complete and the transaction could still fall through. The talks come a year after Exelon abandoned its offer to buy Illinois Power from Dynegy for $425 million in cash and $1.8 billion in assumed debt. Shares of Public Service spiked yesterday afternoon after chat boards talked about a possible merger and the Web site of The Wall Street Journal reported the talks. Shares of Public Service rose to a three-year high of $49.10 before retreating a bit to close up 3.6 percent, at $47.27. Exelon shares fell 1.7 percent, to $41.86. They are up 26 percent this year, compared with an 8 percent gain for Public Service. Exelon runs the largest nuclear power operation in the United States, including the Three Mile Island reactor in Middletown, Pa. The company accounts for 20 percent of the nation's nuclear power capacity, with a total of 10 power stations generating 18,000 megawatts of power. The offer comes as nuclear power advocates are pushing for the construction of new-generation power plants to offset the country's growing reliance on imported oil at a time of soaring energy costs. No nuclear plants have been built in the United States since the accident at the Three Mile Island reactor in March 1979. The acquisition fits with Exelon's pattern of buying troubled companies and turning them around by selling some assets. The companies already jointly operate some power plants. While Exelon has a reputation of being best in class, the parent of P.S.E.&amp;G. is viewed with more caution by industry analysts. The company's Salem power plant in southwestern New Jersey, for example, was cited this year for its poor management and lax maintenance. The latest deal is the largest for the industry since June 2000 when the American Electric Power Company bought the Central and South West Corporation for $12.2 billion, according to Bloomberg data. "There are a lot of economies of scale to be made in the nuclear power industry," said Paul Patterson, an analyst with Glenrock Associates. "Whether you own one plant or 10, there's a certain amount of regulatory framework and oversight to deal with. There will clearly be some synergies there." Exelon, which had revenue of over $15 billion last year, was formed in 2000 when the Philadelphia-based PECO Energy bought Unicom of Chicago. Exelon distributes electricity to 5.1 million consumers in northeastern Illinois and southeastern Pennsylvania. It also sells natural gas to 460,000 customers, according to the company's Web site. "Over time you should see more of these deals in the industry although that's not happening too rapidly because of regulatory hurdles they face," Mr. Patterson said. The offer is expected to face review from the states involved as well as the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, which has oversight over electric and gas utilities. Public Service, based in Newark, employs 10,500 people and had annual revenue of $11 billion in 2003. The company operates power plants in New Jersey and Pennsylvania and serves 2 million electric customers and 1.6 million gas customers. The company's roots go back to 1903 when more than 400 electricity and transport companies in New Jersey were amalgamated to form the Public Service Corporation. Its operations abroad include plants in Brazil, Oman and Poland.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DB163CF930A35752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DYNEGY TO BUY EXELON UNIT FOR $135 MILLION<date>Published: November 3, 2004</date><text>Dynegy, the energy company, said yesterday that it would buy ExRes SHC, a subsidiary of the Exelon Corporation, for $135 million in its first acquisition in more than two years. Dynegy will assume $919 million in debt in the deal, which will give Dynegy several more power plants. ExRes SHC is the parent company of Sithe Energies and Sithe Independence. The acquisition includes a long-term-capacity sales contract with Con Edison that will be used to pay down the debt through 2014, the company said. It eliminates a wholesale power tolling agreement lasting through 2014 in which Dynegy paid $40 million a year. The deal, which is subject to regulatory and other approvals, includes Dynegy's acquisition of a 1,042-megawatt power plant near Scriba, N.Y.; four gas-fired merchant facilities in New York; and four hydroelectric generation plants in Pennsylvania.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/20/business/company-news-exelon-raises-earnings-target-for-2004.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EXELON RAISES EARNINGS TARGET FOR 2004<date>Published: August 20, 2004</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, a utility owner, raised its 2004 earnings target for cost-cutting and it increased wholesale power prices. Profit per share, excluding certain items, will be $2.75 to $2.90 this year and $2.85 to $3.05 next year, the company said. Exelon's 2004 forecast is up from a July 28 projection of $2.68 to $2.83. The average estimate from analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial was $2.80. Exelon's cost cuts are part of a plan to increase yearly cash flow by $300 million to $600 million. The projections exclude costs of the job cuts, an accounting change, results from synthetic-fuel plants and a Boston electricity business that Exelon gave to lenders in May.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/11/business/us-settles-nuclear-case-over-burial-of-waste.html?ref=exeloncorporation">U.S. Settles Nuclear Case Over Burial Of Waste<date>Published: August 11, 2004</date><text>The federal government promised on Tuesday to pay at least $300 million in damages to the Exelon Corporation, for its failure to accept nuclear waste for burial, in a settlement that implies a total cost to the Energy Department in the billions of dollars.Exelon operates about one-sixth of the nation's nuclear reactors. Its predecessor companies, like the owners of all the power reactors in the United States, signed contracts with the Energy Department in the early 1980's agreeing to pay Washington one-tenth of a cent per kilowatt-hour of power produced at the reactors; in return, the government promised to take their nuclear waste, beginning in 1998.Exelon and 64 other companies have sued the Energy Department for failing to do so.The government would pay the $300 million if the Yucca Mountain, Nev., nuclear repository begins accepting waste in 2010, as is now scheduled, but many experts think that if it opens at all, it will be much later. Under the settlement, if it opens in 2015, the total will rise to $600 million.The Energy Department wants Congress to reverse a decision made last month by an appeals court in Washington that threw out, as too lax, some of the rules under which Yucca was to have been licensed. The nuclear industry, which wants Yucca opened in part to help pave the way for a new generation of reactors, quickly asserted that the settlement should prompt the government to open Yucca as soon as possible.Under Tuesday's agreement, Exelon will get $80 million immediately, for storage costs already incurred, and the rest of the money by 2010. The company now operates 17 reactors and has 4 more that are shut down.But Brian J. O'Connell, director of the Nuclear Waste Program Office at the National Association of Regulatory Utility Commissioners, said that if the Exelon settlement formed a pattern for other companies, total damages would clearly run into billions of dollars. Spokesmen for the Justice Department and the Energy Department said they had no estimate.The initial payment will come from a Treasury Department fund for judgments, but the Treasury will recover the money from the Energy Department, Mr. O'Connell said. He predicted that Congress would appropriate the money or redirect it from other Energy Department programs.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/22/business/company-news-utility-owner-sells-stake-in-fiber-optic-venture.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; UTILITY OWNER SELLS STAKE IN FIBER OPTIC VENTURE<date>Published: April 22, 2004</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, a utility owner, said yesterday that it had agreed to sell its stake in a Philadelphia-area fiber optic system for $49 million to its partner in the venture, TelCove, which emerged from bankruptcy protection this month. The sale to TelCove, which is closely held and based in Cannonsburg, Pa., is expected to close in this quarter, Exelon said. The joint venture, Peco TelCove, provides local and long-distance calling and data services in southeastern Pennsylvania. Exelon is based in Chicago.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/16/business/company-news-australian-bank-to-buy-exelon-unit-for-135-million.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; AUSTRALIAN BANK TO BUY EXELON UNIT FOR $135 MILLION<date>Published: December 16, 2003</date><text>Macquarie Bank of Australia said it had agreed to buy Exelon Thermal Technologies for 182 million Australian dollars ($135 million). Exelon Thermal, a unit of the Exelon Corporation, provides mainly chilled water for cooling purposes from centralized plants to customers in office buildings in Chicago. The purchase is similar to the bank's recent acquisitions of South East Water in Britain and the Arlanda Express airport rail link in Sweden, Macquarie's chief financial officer, Greg Ward, said. The plants ''provide a platform for further acquisitions'' of similar assets in North America,'' he said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/13/business/company-news-chevrontexaco-expects-charge-from-dynegy-asset-sale.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CHEVRONTEXACO EXPECTS CHARGE FROM DYNEGY ASSET SALE<date>Published: November 13, 2003</date><text>The ChevronTexaco Corporation said yesterday that it would record a charge in the fourth quarter to reflect its share of a loss from the sale of Dynegy's Illinois Power utility. ChevronTexaco owns a 26 percent stake in Dynegy, which said Nov. 3 that it expected a charge to reflect the write-down of the Illinois Power assets. Dynegy agreed to sell Illinois Power to the Exelon Corporation. ChevronTexaco announced its intentions in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The size of the loss was not disclosed, and ChevronTexaco will not know how large its expense will be until Dynegy discloses the loss on the sale of the utility, a ChevronTexaco spokeswoman, Bonnie Chaikind, said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/04/business/company-news-dynegy-to-sell-illinois-power-to-exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DYNEGY TO SELL ILLINOIS POWER TO EXELON<date>Published: November 04, 2003</date><text>The energy marketer Dynegy Inc. said yesterday that it would sell Illinois Power to the Exelon Corporation for $425 million. The sale, which is subject to regulatory approvals, will rid Dynegy of its smallest and only regulated business segment, leaving the company with power generation and natural gas liquids businesses. It will also relieve Dynegy of $1.8 billion in debt. Shares of Dynegy, which is based in Houston, rose more than 8 percent on the news. Exelon serves 3.4 million electricity customers in northern Illinois and 1.9 million electricity and natural gas customers in southeastern Pennsylvania. By acquiring Illinois Power, based in Decatur, Ill., Exelon will gain another 650,000 natural gas and electricity customers in Illinois. Exelon is based in Chicago.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/12/business/company-news-fpl-agrees-to-buy-half-of-amergen-from-british-energy.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; FPL AGREES TO BUY HALF OF AMERGEN FROM BRITISH ENERGY<date>Published: September 12, 2003</date><text>The FPL Group, owner of Florida's largest utility, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy British Energy's 50 percent stake in AmerGen Energy for $276.5 million. AmerGen owns the Three Mile Island Unit 1 nuclear plant in Pennsylvania and two other United States reactors. Combined, the plants have the capacity to generate 2,480 megawatts, enough power for about two million homes. Exelon, which owns the other half, has 30 days to match the bid, FPL said. FPL said it would sell stock to help finance the purchase. The company would receive $8.3 million from British Energy should Exelon elect to buy all of AmerGen. British Energy wants to sell AmerGen to cut debt.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/19/business/company-news-exelon-to-sell-infrastructure-unit-for-250-million.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EXELON TO SELL INFRASTRUCTURE UNIT FOR $250 MILLION<date>Published: June 19, 2003</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, which operates nuclear plants, said yesterday that it had agreed to sell its infrastructure services business for $250 million, a move that enables it to focus on its utility business. Exelon is selling its InfraSource Inc. unit to GFI Energy Ventures and Oaktree Capital Management. The sale price also includes a $30 million subordinated note maturing with interest in 2011. InfraSource provides transmission and distribution infrastructure services to electric, gas, telecommunications and cable utilities, as well as the industrial market.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/08/business/company-news-exelon-to-stay-in-venture-owning-nuclear-plants.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EXELON TO STAY IN VENTURE OWNING NUCLEAR PLANTS<date>Published: March 08, 2003</date><text>The Exelon Corporation canceled plans to sell its stake in a joint venture with British Energy that owns Three Mile Island and two other nuclear power plants in the United States because the offers it received were too low. Exelon will retain its 50 percent stake in the AmerGen Energy Company, which can produce as much as 2,500 megawatts, enough power for two million average homes, the company said. British Energy said it expected a sales agreement for its share of AmerGen by June 30.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/16/nyregion/up-front-worth-noting-anybody-want-to-buy-a-used-nuclear-plant.html?ref=exeloncorporation">UP FRONT: WORTH NOTING; Anybody Want to Buy A Used Nuclear Plant?<date>Published: February 16, 2003</date><text>The Oyster Creek nuclear plant is for sale and anti-nuclear activists are girding for battle.The plant, the oldest operating commercial reactor in the nation, is scheduled to close in 2009, unless federal regulators extend its 40-year license for 20 more years. Activists argue that the license should not be extended, and they say a new owner should not buy the plant with the expectation of keeping it running.Emily Rusch, an energy analyst for the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group, said a 40-year lifespan was long enough for the reactor.''Do we really need a 60-year-old nuclear plant within 50 miles of large population centers?'' she said.The Oyster Creek plant, in Lacey Township, in Ocean County, is owned by a partnership of the Exelon Corporation and British Energy of Scotland. It is generally considered to be well run. If the owners hope to extend the license beyond 2009, they have to apply to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission by April 2004. Craig Nesbit, a spokesman for Exelon in Chicago, said the company had not decided whether to apply for the extension in case the sale takes a long time or does not take place at all.Donald Kirchoffner, another spokesman, said Exelon had put the plant up for sale after British Energy said it wanted to sell its interest. He said the partnership had received some proposals but could not predict when a decision might be made.''The bids are coming in,'' he said. John Sullivan</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/10/business/new-uranium-plant-will-be-in-tennessee.html?ref=exeloncorporation">New Uranium Plant Will Be in Tennessee<date>Published: September 10, 2002</date><text>A partnership of American, Canadian and European nuclear companies that is seeking to build the first new uranium enrichment plant in this country in 50 years said today that it had selected a site, in Hartsville, Tenn., for the $1.1 billion project, state officials said today. Officials said the partnership hoped to apply to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for a license by the end of the year.The Tennessee Valley Authority tried to build a nuclear reactor there but abandoned it in the 1980's because of high costs. Today's announcement was made by Tennessee's governor, Don Sundquist.The consortium, Louisiana Energy Services, based in Washington, is made up of Urenco, a European enrichment company; Cameco, a Canadian uranium company; and three major nuclear power plant operators in this country: Exelon, Duke Energy and Entergy. The company that operates the only enrichment plant now running in this country, USEC, is also seeking to build a new plant.Both planned enrichment plants would be similar in technology to the one that American intelligence experts say that Saddam Hussein is trying to build in Iraq. The American plants, however, would produce low-enriched uranium, suitable for power reactors but not bombs.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/23/business/us-europe-group-wants-to-build-nuclear-fuel-plant-in-us.html?ref=exeloncorporation">U.S.-Europe Group Wants to Build Nuclear Fuel Plant in U.S.<date>Published: July 23, 2002</date><text>A consortium of European and United States nuclear companies said today that it would apply soon for a license from the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to build a $1.1 billion plant for processing reactor fuel, the first in this country in half a century and one of the largest private nuclear projects here since the 1980's.The plant would enrich uranium for use in power plants, using a technology that consumes about 5 percent as much electricity as the one now used in the United States. It would break a domestic monopoly held by USEC Inc., formerly the United States Enrichment Corporation, which runs an Atomic Energy Commission plant in Paducah, Ky., that was privatized in July 1998.USEC announced a month ago that it would also seek to build a plant but that it would first have to modernize a prototype plant tested in the 1980's.The consortium's proposal poses a serious threat to USEC, some experts said. ''As a business, they are dead,'' Thomas L. Neff, a scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said of USEC. In the 1990's, Dr. Neff came up with the idea of buying weapons-grade uranium from Russia and diluting it for use in United States reactors, a job once done by the Energy Department and now done by USEC. If USEC does not build an enrichment plant, he said, it will become merely a broker of the Russian uranium.Patrick C. Upson, the chairman of the consortium, said, ''We have a significant head-start on the technical side.''But USEC executives said their technology would be even better.''USEC remains the leading supplier of enriched uranium fuel in the United States market, and we're on track to be enriching uranium using new advanced gas centrifuges by the end of the decade,'' a spokesman for the company, Charles Yulish, said. ''We expect our technology to be proven the most efficient in the world.''The company wants to incorporate advanced composite materials into the Energy Department's older centrifuge design. When the plant was privatized four years ago, the company said it would seek to commercialize an enrichment technology using lasers, but it later dropped the idea.USEC has shut down one of two plants it took over, and it has kept itself afloat partly by winning a trade case and forcing tariffs on two European suppliers that it accused of taking government subsidies. But a plant built here using European technology would face no such tariffs.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/16/business/exelon-quitting-new-nuclear-plant-project.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Exelon Quitting New Nuclear-Plant Project<date>Published: April 16, 2002</date><text>The Exelon Corporation, the nation's biggest owner of nuclear power plants, is dropping out of an international consortium that is developing a smaller, cheaper kind of nuclear plant, an Energy Department official said today.The utility, which is based in Chicago, will halt its financing of the so-called pebble bed modular reactor, now in the design stage, said Norton Haberman, the department official.The pebble bed modular reactor produces about one-tenth of the electricity of a typical nuclear plant, which produces about 1,000 megawatts. Supporters of the new technology say it would be faster, cheaper and safer to build because it uses helium as the plant's coolant instead of pressurized water.Exelon executives were meeting with other project investors in South Africa and were expected to make an announcement on Tuesday, an Exelon vice president, Elizabeth Moler, said.Exelon holds a 12.5 percent stake in the project. Other participants include South Africa's state-owned electric utility, the Industrial Development Corporation, with 25 percent, and British Nuclear Fuels Ltd., with 22.5 percent. The consortium had planned to build a $300 million demonstration model in South Africa beginning next year.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/26/nyregion/c-corrections-248380.html?ref=exeloncorporation">Corrections<date>Published: March 26, 2002</date><text>A chart on Sunday with a front-page article about the Bush administration's endorsement of nuclear technology promoted by the Exelon Corporation referred incorrectly in some copies to the lawmaker who has received the most in campaign contributions from Exelon since 1999. He is Representative Timothy V. Johnson, Republican of Illinois, not Senator Tim Johnson, who is a South Dakota Democrat.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/24/us/donor-won-praise-in-energy-report.html?ref=exeloncorporation">DONOR WON PRAISE IN ENERGY REPORT<date>Published: March 24, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedIn Chapter 5 of Vice President Dick Cheney's national energy report, executives of the once-moribund nuclear power industry were probably thrilled to read that the White House supported ''the expansion of nuclear power in the United States as a major component of our national energy policy.''The energy report had embraced a wide array of proposals that the executives advanced in private meetings with Mr. Cheney and documents submitted to members of the task force that formulated a national energy policy.One such proposal was the development of a new nuclear reactor designed to produce electricity -- a gas-cooled reactor built on tennis-ball-size graphite spheres -- that the report said ''has inherent safety features.''''The industry has an interest in this,'' the report said, ''and other advanced reactor designs.''But only one company, the Exelon Corporation of Chicago, which provided hundreds of thousands of dollars to Republican campaigns in recent years, has an interest in promoting the so-called pebble-bed reactor.Exelon, the nation's largest nuclear energy company, is the only American corporation developing a design for the pebble-bed reactor, which it says will lead to a new generation of cheaper, smaller and more efficient nuclear reactors. The company says the pebble-bed reactor will be safer, too, though environmentalists in the United States and in other countries have sharply disputed this, calling the pebble-bed reactor a failed system vulnerable to terrorist attack.The May 2001 national energy report is filled with dozens of positive assessments of proposed new technologies, including nuclear designs and wind-generated power. Most of those assessments favor sectors of various industries, and some undoubtedly favor individual corporations.But it is impossible to know how and why the task force endorsed most of those proposals, and which corporations they help, because Mr. Cheney has steadfastly refused to release the names of industry executives who advised the energy task force as it was researching and compiling its report.Next week, more than 14,000 pages of documents related to the task force will be released by the Energy Department, which was ordered by a federal judge to make the material public under the Freedom of Information Act. The Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmentalist group, had sued for the information.Correction: March 26, 2002, Tuesday A chart on Sunday with a front-page article about the Bush administration's endorsement of nuclear technology promoted by the Exelon Corporation referred incorrectly in some copies to the lawmaker who has received the most in campaign contributions from Exelon since 1999. He is Representative Timothy V. Johnson, Republican of Illinois, not Senator Tim Johnson, who is a South Dakota Democrat.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/21/business/company-news-txu-agrees-to-sell-2-texas-electric-plants-to-exelon.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; TXU AGREES TO SELL 2 TEXAS ELECTRIC PLANTS TO EXELON<date>Published: December 21, 2001</date><text>The TXU Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to sell two gas-fired electric generating plants in North Texas to a subsidiary of the Exelon Corporation for $443 million. The plants, in Dallas and Fort Worth, have a combined capacity of 2,334 megawatts. A TXU subsidiary will be able to buy power from the plants during peak summer periods for five years, the company said. TXU, based in Dallas, said the deal would reduce its role in the Texas generation market, cut debt and position the company to expand in other markets. Plant employees will be assured of jobs for at least two years, the companies said.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/28/business/company-news-exelon-reduces-profit-forecast-450-jobs-to-be-cut.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; EXELON REDUCES PROFIT FORECAST; 450 JOBS TO BE CUT<date>Published: September 28, 2001</date><text>The Exelon Corporation is reducing its third-quarter and year-end earnings outlook because of the weakening economy and will eliminate 450 jobs, the utility said yesterday. Exelon, the electricity giant created by the merger last October of Peco Energy of Philadelphia and Unicom of Chicago, said it expected third-quarter profit of $1.10 to $1.20 a share, down from its earlier target of $1.35 to $1.80 a share. For the year, the company expects a profit of $4.30 to $4.45 a share, down from an earlier target of $4.50 a share. The 450 job cuts are in addition to 2,900 announced with last year's merger.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/14/business/company-news-regulators-allow-exelon-to-buy-power-plants-stakes.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGULATORS ALLOW EXELON TO BUY POWER PLANTS' STAKES<date>Published: December 14, 2000</date><text>The Exelon Corporation won approval from regulators to buy stakes in power plants that are part of its purchase of a 49.9 percent interest in the Sithe Energies unit of Vivendi of France for $680 million. In allowing the transfer, the regulators rejected concerns expressed by a Boston-based utility, NStar, that the transfer would give Exelon control of 60 percent of electric generation for northeastern Massachusetts during peak power periods. Exelon was formed in October by the merger of Peco Energy in Philadelphia and Unicom in Chicago. The sale will leave Vivendi with 33 percent of Sithe's North American business; Marubeni of Japan owns 15 percent and Sithe's managers, 2 percent.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/11/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-tierney-to-handle-new-utility-account.html?ref=exeloncorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Tierney to Handle New Utility Account<date>Published: July 11, 2000</date><text>Exelon, an electric utility company to be formed by the merger of Unicom and PECO Energy, has named Tierney Communications in Philadelphia, part of True North Communications, to handle its account, including television, print and out-of-home advertising; direct marketing; and public relations. Billings for a campaign to introduce the Exelon brand were estimated at $15 million.The decision came after a two-month review that had been narrowed to Tierney, which had handled the PECO account since 1986, and three agencies in Chicago: Leo Burnett USA, part of the B Com3 Group, which has handled the account of Commonwealth Edison, part of Unicom, since 1954; J. Walter Thompson, part of the WPP Group; and Young &amp; Rubicam Advertising.Tierney is opening an office in Chicago to handle the work for Exelon, which will be based there. The office is to be set up by Scott Franks, 48, executive vice president and chief operating officer at Tierney, who will also manage the Exelon account.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/08/business/company-news-new-unicom-peco-merger-terms-include-stock-buyback.html?ref=exeloncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NEW UNICOM-PECO MERGER TERMS INCLUDE STOCK BUYBACK<date>Published: January 08, 2000</date><text>The Unicom Corporation and the Peco Energy Company said yesterday that they would buy back up to $1.5 billion of common stock under revised terms for their merger into a power-industry giant to be called the Exelon Corporation. Unicom shareholders will receive 0.875 of an Exelon common share and $3 in cash for each Unicom share held. Peco shareholders will receive one Exelon share for each Peco share. The companies said they adjusted the terms of the deal to reflect the drop in their stock prices. Under the revised deal, Unicom will buy back $1 billion of its shares and Peco $500 million.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/03/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-accounts-585599.html?ref=exeloncorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Accounts<date>Published: March 03, 1999</date><text>* Exelon, Wayne, Pa., a unit of Peco Energy, to Tierney &amp; Partners, Philadelphia, a unit of True North Communications, to handle advertising and public relations. Bozell Direct, New York, a True North sibling agency, will provide direct marketing support. Billings were estimated at $8 million.</text></article></page><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
