<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Freeport-McMoran"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/13/world/asia/13indo.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Gunmen Kill Guard at a Mine in a Restive Indonesian Region<date>Published: July 12, 2009</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP)  Gunmen killed a security guard working for the American mining conglomerate Freeport on Sunday and then ambushed police officers responding to the attack, in a continuation of some of the worst violence in the restive Papua region in years. Skip to next paragraph Related Australian Is Shot Dead Near a Mine in Indonesia (July 12, 2009) The violence, outside the Grasberg mining complex, took place in the same area where a shooting on Saturday killed a 29-year-old Australian mining expert working for the company, Freeport said. Indonesian authorities blamed the Free Papua Movement, which has sought independence from the central government since the 1970s but showed few signs of life until recent months. The rebels see Freeport’s mining operations as a symbol of the Jakarta administration and a reminder that foreign investment in the area has failed to lift their standard of living. The security guard, working on contract for Freeport, was believed to have been ambushed by rebels on Sunday morning when “shots were fired at two security vehicles,” Freeport said in a statement. Five others were injured. The provincial police chief, Bagus Ekodanto, identified the guard as Markus Rattealo, according to Agence France-Presse. Police units responding to the gunfire were ambushed near the scene of the first shooting, said a national police spokesman, Sulistyo Ishak. “The attackers opened fire from distant hills, making it difficult for the police to return fire,” he said. Two police officers were hospitalized with gunshot wounds, he said. Papuan rebels were blamed for the second ambush, but no proof was provided. The Australian mining expert was shot and killed while traveling in a vehicle in the same area. Several other people in the car were unharmed, leading the police to conclude that the attack may have been the work of a rebel sniper. No arrests have been made in the shootings, the police said. The weekend killings come amid an escalation of violence in Papua  a desperately poor and militarized province on Indonesia’s easternmost tip  in recent months that has left several security personnel dead. The Grasberg mining complex, which employs thousands of local workers, is majority-owned by Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold Inc. of Phoenix. The Indonesian government holds a minority stake in the Grasberg mine. More Articles in World » A version of this article appeared in print on July 13, 2009, on page A6 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/12/world/asia/12freeport.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Australian Is Shot Dead Near a Mine in Indonesia<date>Published: July 11, 2009</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP)  An Australian working for the Freeport mining company in Papua Province was shot and killed Saturday, possibly by a sniper, the police and company officials said. The shooting happened near the Grasberg site, one of the world’s largest open-pit mines, where two Americans were killed in an ambush in 2002. Papua, a desperately poor and militarized province on Indonesia’s easternmost tip, is home to separatist rebels who denounce the huge mining operation as a symbol of the Jakarta administration. The national police identified the victim as Drew Grant, a mining technician, according to Agence France-Presse. More Articles in World » A version of this article appeared in print on July 12, 2009, on page A10 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/15/business/15mine.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Copper Merger Is Approved<date>Published: March 15, 2007</date><text>NEW ORLEANS, March 14 (AP)  Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold’s $25.9 billion cash-and-stock acquisition of a rival, Phelps Dodge, was approved Wednesday by shareholders of both companies. The deal would create the world’s largest publicly traded copper company. In separate votes by shareholders of Freeport, which is based in New Orleans, and Phelps Dodge, based in Phoenix, the buyout was approved by about 98 percent of the votes cast, the companies said in a joint statement. The deal is expected to close Monday, the companies said. Shareholders of Phelps Dodge will receive $88 in cash, or a total of $18 billion, and 0.67 share of Freeport common stock for each Phelps Dodge common share  the equivalent of $125.53, based on Freeport’s closing price on Tuesday. The combination will operate as Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold, though businesses operating as Phelps Dodge will continue under that name. Richard C. Adkerson, Freeport’s chief executive, will be the chief of the merged companies, which will be based in Phoenix but maintain an office in New Orleans. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/20/business/worldbusiness/20deal.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Smaller Rival in Agreement to Acquire Copper Giant<date>Published: November 20, 2006</date><text>Phelps Dodge, the worlds second-largest copper producer, will be acquired by Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold, a smaller rival that has been embroiled in environmental and human rights controversies, in a cash and stock deal worth $25.9 billion, the companies said yesterday. Skip to next paragraph Related Blog: Return of the Trusts News Release (pdf) The transaction, if approved by shareholders, would create the worlds largest copper producer and the largest mining company based in North America. It is the latest move in a series of mining and metals mergers. Like companies involved in other mining mergers, Freeport-McMoRan promoted the idea that increased size has become an important competitive factor. We have been watching the industry consolidation, fewer companies, larger companies, but we had not been playing a role in it, Freeport-McMoRans president and chief executive, Richard C. Adkerson, said. Now Freeport is a larger company that has a larger platform. The chairman and chief executive of Phelps Dodge, J. Steven Whisler, said yesterday that the two companies have talked about a possible merger for about a decade. The premium of about 33 percent being offered by Freeport-McMoRan, Mr. Whisler said, was a decisive factor in Phelps Dodges decision to end its 172-year history as an independent company. The boards of both companies have approved the transaction. Under its terms, stockholders in Phelps Dodge will receive $88 a share in cash plus 0.67 of a Freeport-McMoRan share. Based on Fridays closing, the deal is offering Phelps Dodge shareholders a 33 percent premium. Freeport-McMoRan, which has a market capitalization of $11.3 billion compared with Phelps Dodges value of $19.4 billion, will finance the transactions by borrowing about $17.5 billion. Freeport said it expected the deal would be accretive to the combined companys earnings per share and cash flow immediately. To a considerable extent, Phelps-Dodge now finds itself being acquired because of its failure earlier this year to bulk up with an acquisition of Inco, the large Toronto-based nickel miner. Inco had approached Phelps Dodge in an attempt to help it with its bid for another Canadian nickel miner, Falconbridge. In exchange for financing for that transaction, Incos board agreed to be acquired by Phelps Dodge in a deal cash and stock worth about $17 billion. Ultimately, however, the three-way transaction fell apart. Phelps Dodge walked away from its Inco offer after Xstrata of Switzerland emerged as the winning bidder for Falconbridge. Companhia Vale do Rio Doce of Brazil acquired Inco after offering about $17 billion in cash. Not only did the Phelps Dodge bid fail to impress Incos shareholders, it was also criticized by some of the Phoenix-based companys own shareholders largely because it would have increased the companys debt levels from almost nothing to about $24 billion. Some critics said at the time that they would prefer Phelps Dodge to sell itself rather than become larger through acquisitions, a request that has now apparently been granted. Mr. Whisler will retire when the Freeport-McMoRan takeover is completed. The resulting company, which will retain Freeport-McMoRan name but move its head office from New Orleans to Phoenix, will be led by Mr. Adkerson and retain James R. Moffett, of Freeport-McMoRan, as chairman. While Phelps Dodge has large mines in United States, Central and South America as well as Africa, Freeport-McMoRans only significant asset is a mine in Indonesia. Earlier this year, riots in the Indonesian province of Papua were directed at Freeport-McMoRan. In December 2005, The New York Times reported that Freeport had given more financial support to the Indonesian Army and police in Papua than the company had publicly reported, in some cases individual commanders received tens of thousands of dollars from the company. Mr. Adkerson said the company was still responding to requests from regulators about the timing and level of disclosure to shareholders about those payments. The Indonesian mines operations have also come under criticism for their environmental practices. Mr. Adkerson said that Freeport-McMoRan now had its environmental measures assessed and tracked by independent auditors. We operate in an unusual place, he said. Our mine is in a remarkable physical setting. Freeport-McMoRan was advised in the deal by J. P. Morgan Securities and Merrill Lynch while legal advisers were Davis Polk &amp; Wardwell and Jones, Walker, Waechter, Poitevent, Carrère &amp; Denègre. Citigroup Corporate and Investment Banking and Morgan Stanley &amp; Company worked with Phelps Dodge, and its legal counsel was Debevoise &amp; Plimpton. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/05/world/asia/05letter.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">The Papuans Say, This Land and Its Ores Are Ours<date>Published: April 5, 2006</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia, April 2  Titus Natkime, 31, the son of a tribal leader who encountered the first Americans to walk into the wilderness of Papua nearly 50 years ago, was clearly upset with his employer the American mining company, Freeport-McMoRan. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Jewel Samad/Agence France-Presse--Getty Images Miming hunger, students protest in Jakarta against foreign mines in Papua, which critics say destroy the environment. Agence France-Presse--Getty Images The Freeport-McMoRan and Rio Tinto mine, Grasberg, generates vast amounts of waste. For generations, Mr. Natkime's clan has laid claim to much of the land in Papua, the Indonesian province where Freeport mines some of the world's largest copper and gold reserves. Now it was time for a payback, he said. He brought out a draft document showing Freeport's offer: $250,000 to set up a foundation for the clan, plus $100,000 annually, a sizable amount in Indonesia's most remote and poorest province. "Why should I accept it?" asked Mr. Natkime, who works in the company's government relations department, though he is hardly an ardent spokesman. "It's an insult." In comparison, he said, Freeport was making tens of millions of dollars every day. In the end, the family accepted the money, he said, but he is planning a lawsuit and demanding royalties. Such defiance is symptomatic of the growing troubles in Papua, where four people have been killed in recent weeks in protests against Freeport. And it shows that times are changing for multinational companies and governments long used to working out concessions in remote areas with a handshake, over the heads of local people. In March, Citigroup echoed the theme, saying in a report that such companies could no longer afford to ignore environmental and social issues. "In recent years, a groundswell of public opinion has caused sustainable development to become a serious business consideration for investors," the report said. Mark Logsdon, an American geochemist who has visited the Freeport mine, agreed. Mining companies must seek and take seriously the "consent of the governed," he said. "Whether in Indonesia, Latin America or Africa, the increase in communications capability means that the essential isolation of 'resource colonies' is largely a thing of the past." The protests in Papua provide an example of what can happen when a natural resource company, backed by an unpopular central government and a heavy-handed military, fails to pay careful attention to the local people, whose lives have been disturbed and who feel the riches in the ground are theirs, not the foreigners'. At one time, there was hardly a place more remote than Papua, where Freeport's first explorers encountered Papuans armed with bows and arrows and wearing penis gourds, practices that still exist. Yet, try as the government might to preserve that isolation  for the past two years it has banned foreign journalists from the province, granting only very occasional permits  the extent of the problems is impossible to hide. In March, long-simmering tensions exploded when Indonesian riot police officers and several hundred Papuan protesters clashed in the provincial capital, Jayapura, leaving three policemen and an air force officer dead. Freeport's profits are soaring as gold prices have reached 25-year highs of more than $550 an ounce. The company, which is based in New Orleans and is in partnership in the Papua mines with the Rio Tinto group of Australia, is one of Indonesia's biggest taxpayers, and has been for many years. But Papuans argue that they have never received a fair portion of the estimated $33 billion in direct and indirect benefits the company says it provided to Indonesia from 1992 to 2004. Repeated efforts to reach the spokesman for Freeport in Indonesia, Siddharta Moersjid, were unsuccessful. As evidence of the neglect, the Papuans, who are indigenous Melanesians with broad features and curly hair that contrast with the Malay heritage of most Indonesians, point to their relative lack of progress compared to the rest of Indonesia. In the current ugly mood, the people around the mine give short shrift to the more than $150 million that the company says it has spent on community development. Instead, they complain that they have lost their most precious assets: their land; their river system, which is used as a waste chute; and their sago plants, which have disappeared under more than 90 square miles of mine waste, accumulating at a rate of some 700,000 tons a day. 1 2Next Page » More Articles in International »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4D61F3EF935A15751C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Mine Blockade Is Ended<date>Published: February 26, 2006</date><text>Protesters obstructing access to a huge mine owned by the American company Freeport-McMoRan in the remote Papua Province of Indonesia called off their blockade on Saturday. It was unclear whether operations had resumed, a senior police official said. Work at the mine, the Grasberg, stopped Wednesday a day after illegal miners with bows and arrows clashed with the authorities. ''All access to the mine is normal,'' Anton Bachrul Alam of the national police said Saturday.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/25/international/asia/25indo.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">After Clashes, Indonesian Troops Guard Gold Mine<date>Published: February 25, 2006</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Feb. 24 (Reuters)  Operations at the world's largest gold mine, owned by the American company Freeport McMoRan, were suspended for a third day on Friday after local residents clashed with security officers and the police in the remote province of Papua, government officials said. Operations had been suspended since Wednesday, a day after miners armed with bows and arrows fought with security officers and the police. On Friday, the government put the military in charge of security at the mine, Grasberg, after three days of violence that erupted when security officers and government officials tried to force out the miners, who then blocked access to the site. "The Freeport plant is still shut down this morning," said M. S. Marpaung, deputy director of investment at the mines and energy ministry. The mine also holds the world's third-largest copper reserves. Copper shipments had not been affected, Mr. Marpaung said, but he was not sure how long stocks would last. The Freeport operation has been a source of controversy in Indonesia on issues ranging from its treatment of the environment to the legality of payments to Indonesian security forces who have guarded the facility. The continued suspension of mining came a day after about 50 Papuan students attacked a building housing Freeport's offices in Indonesia's capital, Jakarta. The Papuans smashed windows in the lobby of the building and set fire to a travel agency on the ground floor, but failed to reach Freeport's offices on higher floors. After The New York Times reported in December that from 1998 through 2004 Freeport paid nearly $20 million to individual military and police officers and units in Papua, a number of Indonesian politicians called for investigations of Freeport's payments and its environment practices. Freeport said the payments were within American and Indonesian laws. Mr. Marpaung said he had asked the regional government to negotiate with the protesters to solve the problem. More Articles in International &gt;</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/30/international/asia/30indo.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Indonesia Admits 'Support' by U.S. Gold Company to the Military<date>Published: December 30, 2005</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Dec. 29 (AP) - Indonesia's military acknowledged for the first time on Thursday that an American gold company had been providing direct "support" to army units accused of human rights abuses in the remote province of Papua. A joint services spokesman, Maj. Gen. Kohirin Suganda, said the armed forces "as an institution" had never received payments from the company, Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold, based in New Orleans. "But we have heard that Freeport provides support such as vehicles, fuel and meals directly to the units in the field," General Suganda said. "That's the company's policy. It was not done because we requested it." The general was responding to an article published Tuesday in The New York Times that detailed Freeport's payments of $20 million to military commanders and units in the area in the last seven years in exchange for protection of its facilities in the remote province. Indonesia regularly ranks among the world's most corrupt countries in international surveys. The latest reports will do little to raise confidence in the army, considered one of the country's most graft-ridden institutions, or the government's pledge to eradicate official corruption. Human rights groups have criticized direct payments by foreign mining and energy companies to the military, saying they were undermining efforts to bring the politically powerful armed forces under civilian command following the collapse in 1998 of the 32-year military dictatorship of former President Suharto. Only one-third of the financing for Indonesia's armed forces comes from the state budget, while the rest is collected from nontransparent sources such as "protection payments," allowing the military brass to operate independently of the government's financial controls. The revelations are potentially embarrassing for the Bush administration, which recently lifted a ban on ties with the Indonesian military imposed in 1999 by President Bill Clinton after a rampage by Indonesian troops in East Timor that killed at least 1,500 people. When asked about the payments, Indonesia's military commander Gen. Endriartono Sutarto would say only, "Please ask Freeport, not me." Siddharta Moersjid, a spokesman for PT Freeport Indonesia, dismissed the allegations as "old news." "We have been transparent about our logistical support for the Indonesian security forces," he said. "Support for the government security institutions is provided pursuant to government requests for its legitimate requirements." Reports that Freeport was paying the military to protect the mine have circulated for years. Last year, the international watchdog Global Witness reported that Maj. Gen. Mahidin Simbolon, the region's former military commander and currently inspector general of the army, personally received $247,705 from Freeport from 2001 to 2003. In 2003, Freeport acknowledged in a report to the Securities and Exchange Commission and to New York City authorities that it had paid millions of dollars to the army. But the company never detailed its payments or acknowledged paying individual officers directly. "We've been deployed to difficult areas, don't we deserve better supplies?" General Simbolon was quoted as saying on Thursday in The Jakarta Post. He acknowledged that the military had received payments from Freeport, but denied that he had benefited personally. More Articles in International &gt;</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/27/international/asia/27gold.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Below a Mountain of Wealth, a River of Waste<date>Published: December 27, 2005</date><text>JAKARTA, Indonesia - The closest most people will ever get to remote Papua, or the operations of Freeport-McMoRan, is a computer tour using Google Earth to swoop down over the rain forests and glacier-capped mountains where the American company mines the world's largest gold reserve. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Alexandra Boulat/VII, via Associated Press A view of lowland area where Freeport has sent its mine waste, taken in 2000. By today, almost one billion tons of waste have been sent down the river from the copper and gold mine. THE COST OF GOLD Part 3: The Hidden Payroll Articles in this series examine gold mining around the world. Part 1: 30 Tons an Ounce Part 2: Treasure of Yanacocha Q&amp;A: Reporters Answer Questions RELATED LINKS "The Politics of Power: Freeport in Suharto's Indonesia," Denise Leath, University of Hawaii Press, 2003 "Grasberg: Mining the Richest and Most Remote Deposit of Copper and Gold in the World, in the Mountains of Irian Jaya, Indonesia," by George A. Mealey, published by Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold, 1996 The Cost of Gold The Cost of Gold: 30 Tons an Ounce The Cost of Gold: Treasure of Yanacocha Enlarge This Image Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold, an American company, operates this mine in the easternmost province of Indonesia, on the island of New Guinea. With a few taps on a keyboard, satellite images quickly reveal the deepening spiral that Freeport has bored out of its Grasberg mine as it pursues a virtually bottomless store of gold hidden inside. They also show a spreading soot-colored bruise of almost a billion tons of mine waste that the New Orleans-based company has dumped directly into a jungle river of what had been one of the world's last untouched landscapes. What is far harder to discern is the intricate web of political and military ties that have helped shield Freeport from the rising pressures that other gold miners have faced to clean up their practices. Only lightly touched by a scant regulatory regime, and cloaked in the protection of the military, Freeport has managed to maintain a nearly impenetrable redoubt on the easternmost Indonesian province as it taps one of the country's richest assets. Months of investigation by The New York Times revealed a level of contacts and financial support to the military not fully disclosed by Freeport, despite years of requests by shareholders concerned about potential violations of American laws and the company's relations with a military whose human rights record is so blighted that the United States severed ties for a dozen years until November. Company records obtained by The Times show that from 1998 through 2004, Freeport gave military and police generals, colonels, majors and captains, and military units, nearly $20 million. Individual commanders received tens of thousands of dollars, in one case up to $150,000, according to the documents. They were provided by an individual close to Freeport and confirmed as authentic by current and former employees. Freeport said in a written response to The Times that it had "taken appropriate steps" in accordance with American and Indonesian laws to provide a secure working environment for its more than 18,000 employees and contract workers. "There is no alternative to our reliance on the Indonesian military and police in this regard," the company said. "The need for this security, the support provided for such security, and the procedures governing such support, as well as decisions regarding our relationships with the Indonesian government and its security institutions, are ordinary business activities." While mining and natural resource companies sometimes contribute to the costs to foreign governments in securing their operations, payments to individual officers raise questions of bribes, said several people interviewed by The Times, including a former Indonesian attorney general, who said it was illegal under Indonesian law for officers to accept direct payments. The Times's investigation also found that, according to one current and two former company officials who helped set up a covert program, Freeport intercepted e-mail messages to spy on its environmental opponents. Freeport declined to comment. More than 30 current and former Freeport employees and consultants were interviewed over the past several months for this article. Very few would speak for attribution, saying they feared the company's retribution. Freeport's support of the military is one measure of its extraordinary working environment. In the 1960's, when Freeport entered Papua, its explorers were among the very first outsiders ever encountered by local tribesmen swathed only in penis gourds and armed with bows and arrows. Since then, Freeport has built what amounts to an entirely new society and economy, all of its own making. Where nary a road existed, Freeport, with the help of the San Francisco-based construction company Bechtel, built virtually every stitch of infrastructure over impossible terrain in engineering feats that it boasts are unparalleled on the planet. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9Next Page &gt; Evelyn Rusli contributed reporting for this article. More Articles in International &gt;</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/23/business/company-news-freeport-plans-offering-to-buy-back-rio-tinto-stake.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; FREEPORT PLANS OFFERING TO BUY BACK RIO TINTO STAKE<date>Published: March 23, 2004</date><text>Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc., owner of the world's biggest gold mine, plans to buy back Rio Tinto's 12 percent stake using $1 billion from the sale of preferred shares. Rio's 23.9 million Class B common shares will be bought at a ''market-based price'' once the sale of convertible preferred stock is completed, Freeport said. Rio, which is based in London, bought the stake in 1995 for $20.90 a share, or $500.2 million. Freeport shares closed at $41.95 on Friday. The Grasberg gold mine, which is in Indonesia, is the world's biggest. Freeport McMoran is based in New Orleans.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/11/business/company-news-big-copper-and-gold-miner-revises-profit-downward.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; BIG COPPER AND GOLD MINER REVISES PROFIT DOWNWARD<date>Published: November 11, 2003</date><text>Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc., owner of the world's largest gold mine, said third-quarter profit was 14 percent lower than reported last month, as some copper sales were incorrectly recorded. Net income was $53.5 million, or 29 cents a share, excluding $8.5 million, or 4 cents, of profit from copper sales that will be recorded during the current quarter, the company said in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The per-share earnings reflect payment of dividends on preferred stock. The company lowered third-quarter revenue to $632 million from the previously reported $668.8 million. Net income after payment of dividends was $47.4 million. The company had net income of $71 million, or 39 cents a share, in the third quarter of 2002.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/16/business/company-news-big-gold-mine-owner-doubles-its-dividend.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; BIG GOLD MINE OWNER DOUBLES ITS DIVIDEND<date>Published: October 16, 2003</date><text>Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc., owner of the world's biggest gold mine, more than doubled its dividend and authorized a share buyback after investors urged the company to return some excess cash. The quarterly dividend will rise to 20 cents a share from 9 cents starting with the February payment, Freeport said. The company will spend $136.4 million a year on the dividend, less than the $279.1 million in cash Freeport generated in the first six months this year. No date was set for buying as much as 20 million shares. Gold production at the Grasberg mine, in Papua, Indonesia, reached a record high in the second quarter.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/15/business/us-europe-and-canada-investigate-copper-pricing.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">U.S., Europe and Canada Investigate Copper Pricing<date>Published: May 15, 2003</date><text>Antitrust authorities in the United States, Europe and Canada are investigating whether several large copper companies colluded to fix prices, regulators said today.Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold, based in New Orleans, confirmed that it had received a grand jury subpoena for documents about its activities in the market for copper concentrate, which is later refined by smelters. European antitrust officials conducted raids on the offices of BHP Billiton and Rio Tinto in London and of Somincor in Portugal. All the companies said they were cooperating in the inquiry.''The purpose of these inspections is to ascertain whether there is evidence of a cartel agreement and related illegal practices concerning the fixing of sales prices and sales conditions, customer allocation and market sharing for this product,'' the European Commission said in a statement.Gina M. Talamona, a spokeswoman for the United States Justice Department, and Rob Levine, acting senior competition law officer in the criminal matters branch of Canada's Competition Bureau, confirmed that their offices were involved in the investigation, according to Bloomberg News.Cooperation among antitrust investigators in different jurisdictions is a recent phenomenon. The first case was in February, when regulators from the United States, Europe, Canada and Japan made coordinated raids on 14 companies in an investigation of price fixing in chemicals used to make plastic pipes. The European Commission said international cooperation among regulators had become a high priority because cartels are increasingly global.Copper prices have increased about 25 percent since 2001. Copper concentrate is an intermediate product, which becomes copper cathode when smelted and refined. The investigation into this part of the industry comes two years after European antitrust officials began an inquiry into makers of copper pipes. Companies involved in that continuing investigation include Outokumpu of Finland and units of Generale Industrie Metallurgiche of Italy.Traders and analysts said the latest investigation was most likely prompted by complaints from smelters, which refine the concentrate, according to Reuters. The fees paid to smelters by concentrate producers have declined sharply. Concentrate has been in increasingly short supply over the last few years, largely because of a sharp rise in consumption in India and China.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/07/business/shares-drop-on-bond-sale-chairman-sold-stock-earlier.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Shares Drop on Bond Sale; Chairman Sold Stock Earlier<date>Published: February 07, 2003</date><text>Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold sold $500 million in convertible bonds yesterday, and its stock fell $1.32, or 7.3 percent, to $16.84 a share.The company and experts on convertible bonds said the bond offering contributed to a drop in the share price.Such a sale, experts said, typically causes the stock to drop because the bonds have a feature that allows them to be traded for stock of the issuing company at a set price. As a result, their value is affected by changes in the stock price. Many convertibles are bought by hedge fund managers who immediately offset their exposure to the stock by selling shares in the company.Richard C. Adkerson, the company's president, said the 7 percent drop in the stock ''was something that you would typically see with an offering of convertible securities -- those securities would be sold by an underwriter to arbitrage funds, and those funds would engage in short selling to hedge their positions.''The offering came nine days after James R. Moffett, the chairman of the mining company, exercised 500,000 stock options. Mr. Moffett made a profit of about $4.3 million on the options, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. Such an exercise yesterday would have been worth almost $1 million less.Mr. Moffett returned almost 200,000 of the options, along with 66,000 shares he had previously owned, to Freeport as way to exercise the other 300,000 options without using any of his money, a so-called cashless exercise. He then sold the 300,000 shares that he received at an average price of $18.63, 10.6 percent higher than the price at which Freeport closed yesterday.The 300,000-share sale represented almost 40 percent of all the Freeport shares that Mr. Moffett owned, according to the filing. Mr. Moffett also has more than four million Freeport options, according to the company's most recent proxy statement.Mr. Adkerson said that Mr. Moffett's stock sale was unrelated to the convertible bond offering. A spokesman for Freeport said Mr. Moffett could not be reached for comment.Mr. Adkerson said Freeport had not decided to make the convertible offering when Mr. Moffett sold his shares. The bond offering ''came up in the last couple of days,'' Mr. Adkerson said. ''It was something that arose very quickly -- proposals from our investment bankers, and we reacted to it very quickly.''Freeport will use the proceeds from the offering to pay its bank lines of credit, Mr. Adkerson said. As a result, the company will be able to begin paying a dividend of 36 cents a share, something it could not do under the terms of its bank loans.''It's something we're very proud of,'' Mr. Adkerson said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/30/world/us-links-indonesian-troops-to-deaths-of-2-americans.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">U.S. Links Indonesian Troops to Deaths of 2 Americans<date>Published: January 30, 2003</date><text>Bush administration officials have determined that Indonesian soldiers carried out a deadly ambush that killed two American teachers returning from a picnic in a remote area of Indonesia last August, senior administration officials say.The conclusion, which follows a preliminary investigation by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, is likely to muddy relations between Washington and Jakarta.Indonesia is the world's most populous Muslim nation, and the Bush administration has been trying to persuade its president, Megawati Sukarnoputri, to take a more aggressive stand against terrorism and to support Washington's policy on Iraq.Last month, in a reflection of the administration's concern about the killings, President Bush secretly dispatched an influential emissary to tell President Megawati that the Indonesians must mount a serious investigation -- with F.B.I. participation. The official, Karen Brooks, is the National Security Council's senior Asian specialist; she also has a deep personal and professional relationship with President Megawati.Indonesian leaders tend to bristle at outside interference, and especially as the United States prepares for a possible war with Iraq, which the vast majority of Indonesians oppose. Even so, Ms. Brooks's mission seems to have been successful, at least in part. Two F.B.I. agents arrived in Indonesia last week to help in the investigation.The Indonesian military has denied any involvement in the ambush, which also killed an Indonesian teacher and wounded eight Americans. But a report by the country's police force last year suggested that the military was behind the killings.The two F.B.I. agents now in Indonesia are gathering evidence for the Justice Department in Washington, American and other Western officials in the region said.''There is no question there was military involvement,'' said a senior administration official. ''There is no question it was premeditated.''The administration official and diplomats from other countries said there was still a mystery about who ordered the killings and why. They said the most likely explanation was that soldiers were trying to send a message to the teachers' employer, an American company that operates one of the world's largest copper and gold mines in the area. The company, Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold, had reduced payments and other benefits to soldiers, the officials said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/02/world/mystery-surrounds-deadly-ambush-of-americans-in-indonesia.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Mystery Surrounds Deadly Ambush of Americans in Indonesia<date>Published: September 02, 2002</date><text>An ambush in Indonesia's Irian Jaya Province on Saturday that left two Americans dead and several others seriously wounded did not appear to be part of an international terrorist plot against Americans, Western diplomats said today.The F.B.I. has been interviewing survivors, who were flown to Townsville, Australia, for treatment. The wounded are reported to be in stable condition.Western officials said the attack appeared to be the latest round in the violence that had engulfed the remote, easternmost province, also called West Papua. Much of the upheaval has been directed at Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc., which operates one of the world's largest copper and gold mines there. The company has been accused by indigenous Papuans of destroying sacred lands, ravaging the environment and not sharing the mineral wealth with local communities.The ambush, on a tortuous mountain road, occurred close to the facility operated by Freeport-McMoran, one of the largest foreign investors in Indonesia. The victims were teachers and their families from the company's international school.No one has claimed responsibility for the ambush. None of the victims were robbed, nor were any demands made.[Military officials said on Sunday that troops killed a man suspected in the ambush in a shootout near the site of the attack, The Associated Press reported.]Indonesian officials have accused rebels of the Free Papua Movement, which has been waging guerrilla war for independence for many years. But diplomats warned that blaming rebels was a rush to judgment, reflecting the government's agenda. Indonesia's problems in keeping Papua, which is closer to Australia than to Jakarta, are similar to those it had in East Timor, which eventually gained independence.The diplomats noted that the Papua rebels had not attacked foreigners during their 40-year struggle for independence. ''I don't see what they gain from it,'' one diplomat said.The attackers had automatic weapons, which raises the possibility that elements of Indonesian security forces were involved, diplomats said.Indonesian police and military units provide security for Freeport-McMoran as well as for other foreign natural resource companies. These units have been accused of carrying out acts of violence in order to fuel ethnic tensions.Last November, one of the most prominent leaders of the independence movement in Papua, Theys Eluay, was killed after leaving a social gathering with soldiers. The government initially blamed rebels. But under pressure from the United States and other Western governments, which said that the evidence was clear that soldiers had killed Mr. Eluay, several soldiers have been named as suspects.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/01/world/gunmen-kill-indonesian-and-2-americans.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Gunmen Kill Indonesian and 2 Americans<date>Published: September 01, 2002</date><text>Gunmen armed with automatic weapons ambushed a convoy headed to a huge gold mine run by an American corporation today, killing two Americans and an Indonesian in troubled West Papua Province.Fourteen others, including seven Americans, were wounded in the attack near the world's largest gold mine.No group claimed responsibility, though the Papua police chief said it was possible that the separatist Free Papua Movement was involved. Government forces and separatist rebels have been fighting intermittently for almost four decades.The convoy of cars was headed from the town of Timika to the Grasberg mine, an immense open-pit dig that many local residents consider a symbol of unwanted Indonesian rule.The mine's operator -- PT Freeport Indonesia, an affiliate of New Orleans-based Freeport-McMoran Copper-and-Gold Inc. -- has been accused by human rights advocates of cooperating with Indonesian security forces in suppressing a local effort to achieve independence. Freeport denies any human rights abuses.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/10/business/freeport-drops-dividend.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport Drops Dividend<date>Published: December 10, 1998</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc. said today that it was eliminating its regular quarterly cash dividend on its class A and class B common stocks, in response to lower copper and gold prices. The move, along with other operational changes, will enable it to cut its year-end debt by $250 million if commodity prices continue at current levels, the company said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/29/business/imc-to-buy-freeport-mcmoran-inc-for-750-million.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">IMC to Buy Freeport-McMoran Inc. for $750 Million<date>Published: July 29, 1997</date><text>IMC Global Inc., fortifying its position as the world's dominant producer of phosphate fertilizers, announced an agreement yesterday to buy Freeport-McMoran Inc. for about $750 million.With the world expected to gain a billion more people by 2010, and with billions of others consuming more food, IMC is counting on rising demand for food and fertilizer.The deal undoes a snarl or two in the still-tangled corporate realm of James R. Moffett, chairman of Freeport-McMoran Inc. and of the separate and larger Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc., two among a plethora of companies bearing the Freeport-McMoran name.It also gives investors in Freeport-McMoran Inc. a premium for shares that closed Friday down by about a third from their peak of $44.50 in March 1996.The companies predicted immediate annual savings of $33 million, rising to $40 million over the next several years. They have already gained some savings by running their phosphate businesses jointly for the last four years.''This merger will represent a major step in IMC Global's growth strategy and reaffirms our commitment to being the world's leading, low-cost supplier of agricultural products and services,'' Robert E. Fowler Jr., the company's president and chief executive, said.Analysts agreed about the deal's benefits for IMC over the long term, while noting that IMC shares would suffer some earnings dilution in the short term. With an offer worth about $31.50 a share, mostly in stock, Freeport-McMoran Inc. rose $4.625, to $31.1875, while IMC Global fell 62.5 cents, to $33.125.Rene L. Latiolais, Freeport-McMoran's chief executive, said shareholders would ''participate in the growth associated with the world's largest and lowest-cost phosphate fertilizer producer.''Nothing, however, about Mr. Moffett and his businesses is ever simple. His last burst of publicity came when Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold agreed to a partnership with Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, to develop what had been billed as the century's richest gold strike, in Indonesia. In several tests, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold discovered that there was not enough gold even to warrant production.With close ties to the Suharto Government of Indonesia, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold has developed the world's largest copper mine and third-largest gold mine in that nation's remote Irian Jaya region.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/06/business/bre-x-from-rags-to-riches-back-to-rags.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Bre-X: From Rags to Riches, Back to Rags<date>Published: May 06, 1997</date><text>The American and Indonesian companies that only a few months ago were fighting for the right to help Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Canada mine in what had been touted as this century's richest gold strike walked away from the project today and left Bre-X on its own to defend what is being called one of the scams of the century.The small rags-to-riches-to-rags company, based in Calgary, Alberta, now faces the fallout from a devastating report concluding that the Indonesian mother lode at Busang was nothing but a fabulous tale backed by false hopes and counterfeit data.The finding is likely to wipe out whatever value is left in Bre-X's battered stock. It will also cast a shadow over Canadian wildcatters and miners, making it difficult for small companies to build the trust needed to raise capital for future projects.''I've never seen a fraud on this scale,'' said James R. Moffett, chairman of Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold of New Orleans. That company, Bre-X's former partner, officially withdrew today. At the same time, Mohamad (Bob) Hasan, an Indonesian businessman and confidant to President Suharto, announced that he, too, was pulling out of the Busang project.''The good guys will go on while the bad guys fall by the wayside,'' Mr. Hasan said in Jakarta. ''Life goes on.''Strathcona Mineral Services of Toronto, an independent consultant, had been hired by Bre-X in March to clear up doubts about the company's estimate that the Busang discovery contained 70 million to 200 million ounces of gold, worth $70 billion.Instead, Strathcona concluded that ''there is virtually no possibility of an economic gold deposit'' on Bre-X's Busang site in Borneo. Furthermore, Strathcona confirmed the suspicion of many experts that drilling samples had been tampered with to inflate gold estimates. The report was released early today in Jakarta, late Sunday evening in New York.The falsification of samples was done ''on a scale and over a period of time and with a precision that to our knowledge is without precedent in the history of mining anywhere in the world,'' the Strathcona report said.''The gold recovered in samples submitted by Bre-X has originated from a source other than the southeastern zone of the Busang property,'' it concluded.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/05/business/nothing-worth-mining-found-on-bre-x-site.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Nothing Worth Mining Found on Bre-X Site<date>Published: May 05, 1997</date><text>An independent consulting company has found no sign that there is gold worth mining at the Indonesian site discovered by Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Canada, which had contended that it had found the gold strike of the century.Moreover, the independent audit concluded that initial drilling results had been deliberately doctored in an elaborate scheme to make the finds appear far richer than they actually were.The audit showed ''trace amounts of gold,'' according to the report, released today in Indonesia. But there is ''virtually no possibility of an economic gold deposit'' at the Busang jungle site, on the island of Borneo, which a bit more than a month ago had been widely thought to contain from 70 million to 200 million ounces of gold, worth billions of dollars.The consulting company, Strathcona Mineral Services of Toronto, had been hired by Bre-X to clear up confusion about the drilling results, after a prospective American partner for Bre-X, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold of New Orleans, said that its preliminary tests indicated the claims of a vast gold deposit at Busang seemed false.Strathcona concluded that the inaccurate estimates of the gold deposits had been based on ''falsified data,'' and said that there had been ''tampering with samples delivered to the labs.''''The magnitude of the tampering with core samples that we believe has occurred and resulting falsification of assay values at Busang is of a scale and over a period of time and with a precision that, to our knowledge, is without precedent in the history of mining anywhere in the world,'' Strathcona concluded.The damaging report is likely to doom any chance Bre-X might have had to go forward with the project, which had made company officials millionaires without producing a single commercial ounce of gold.Instead, the small company, based in Calgary, Alberta, is likely to be hounded by infuriated stockholders, both large and small, who have seen the value of their shares plummet since the first doubts were raised in late March about the validity of Bre-X's initial findings.Several shareholder groups have already filed lawsuits in the United States and Canada against Bre-X. The Toronto Stock Exchange said it would halt trading in Bre-X stock when the session opens on Monday.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/30/business/freeport-still-skeptical-on-indonesia-gold.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport Still Skeptical on Indonesia Gold<date>Published: April 30, 1997</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold emphasized today that it would pull out of developing what had been billed as the century's richest gold strike unless further tests yielded enough of the metal.The company, based here, and Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, Freeport's prospective partner in the site at Busang, in the Indonesian region of Borneo, reported last month that preliminary results from seven holes had yielded only insignificant amounts of gold. They said that earlier claims by Bre-X, the discoverer of the strike, might have been exaggerated.At a tightly controlled annual meeting today, James R. Moffett, the chief executive of Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold, described those results as inconclusive and strongly hinted at a possible next step. Repeating a warning made by the company last month, he said, ''If we don't confirm that we have a feasible project, the company will basically withdraw.''He later added, ''The Bre-X people can either find someone else or go forward on their own.''Mr. Moffett said, and Bre-X has said, that a report is expected by the end of the week from Strathcona Mineral Services, an independent assayer.After the news last month that the area might not contain the gold it was said to, the stock of Freeport fell several points and Bre-X shares, which had soared on the company's predictions, crashed. Today, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold was unchanged at $29.125 on the New York Stock Exchange; Bre-X rose 12.5 cents, to $2.75, on Nasdaq.While Bre-X, a small exploration company, has relatively little besides this project, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold is an old hand at Indonesian mining and investment. With close ties to the Suharto Government, the company has developed the world's largest copper mine and the third-largest gold mine in Irian Jaya, another remote region, along the flanks of a dormant volcano.In February, Freeport won an agreement for developing the Busang field with Bre-X and a close associate of President Suharto's. With a 15 percent interest in the project, the American company agreed to pay as much as $400 million in costs and obtained a $1.2 billion credit line for the rest of the expenses.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/08/business/bre-x-consultant-calls-gold-find-major.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Bre-X Consultant Calls Gold Find 'Major'<date>Published: April 08, 1997</date><text>A mining consultant that had examined samples from Bre-X's controversial find in Indonesia said today that the samples indicated a major deposit.The statement by the consulting company, Normet Pty. Ltd. of Australia, was in response to an article in a Canadian mining newspaper that raised further doubts about the samples taken by Bre-X Minerals Ltd., of Calgary, Alberta.Questions about the Indonesian field, Busang, have mounted since Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc., a prospective American partner, announced two weeks ago that it had found ''insignificant amounts of gold'' at what Bre-X executives had hailed as a huge gold find.The newspaper, The Northern Miner, said on Friday that a report by Normet last July pointed to abnormalities in the samples. The report, according to the newspaper, said that the gold particles were round, consistent with placer gold, which is found in streams or riverbeds. The Busang field is bedrock.On Monday, Bre-X shares fell 53.1 cents, to $1.844, in Nasdaq trading. The stock fell 66 Canadian cents, to $2.52 (Canadian) on the Toronto Stock Exchange.But Phil Hearse, director of Normet, said today, ''We have never reported placer gold as being part of Busang.''He declined to provide details about the gold samples from Busang, saying the information belonged to its client, Bre-X.Still, when asked whether the Busang samples had indicated a major deposit, Mr. Hearse replied. ''They certainly did.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/31/business/at-end-of-a-miner-s-rainbow-a-cloud-of-confusion-lingers.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">At End of a Miner's Rainbow, A Cloud of Confusion Lingers<date>Published: March 31, 1997</date><text>By all appearances it was a golden evening, a chance for Michael T. de Guzman to have a drink, boast a bit and even sing a few verses of ''My Way,'' at a smoky Indonesian karaoke bar.And why not? The 40-year-old Filipino prospector had become a millionaire by ignoring detractors and doggedly pursuing his own unorthodox theory about how minerals form. That independent-mindedness led him in 1986 to the forbidding jungles of Borneo, where he later helped discover what came to be trumpeted as this century's greatest gold strike.To a colleague with him that night two weeks ago, Mr. de Guzman seemed on top of the world.The next day he was dead. He plummeted 800 feet from a helicopter on the way to a meeting with a prospective new partner. There, he was expected to explain why new tests had come up with hardly a trace of the 200 million ounces of gold he and his Canadian employer, Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, were supposed to have been found in a place in Borneo known as Busang.Searchers took four days to recover Mr. de Guzman's body. A funeral was held in Jakarta, Indonesia, last Friday. By then, the police had a suicide note that mentioned an incurable illness. But family and friends say they cannot believe that Mr. de Guzman had taken his own life.His death is not the only mystery in this tale of a tiny company. It has never made a penny of profit and financed its operations solely from the sale of stock. Yet it attracted hordes of investors, from sophisticated institutions to teachers, shop owners and other small-town Canadians. The shareholders dreamed of making a killing. But when word of the recent empty drilling samples became known, confidence in Bre-X was shattered, and the company dropped more than $3 billion -- 80 percent of its value -- in just minutes of frantic stock trading last Thursday. Investors demanded to know if there ever had been any gold, or whether they all had been hoodwinked.''We're more confused than angry,'' said Victor Mailloux, a businessman in St. Paul, Alberta, who bought Bre-X stock 15 months ago.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/28/business/canadian-gold-stock-investors-strike-it-poor.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Canadian Gold Stock Investors Strike It Poor<date>Published: March 28, 1997</date><text>With much of the shine already off what had only weeks ago been considered one of the richest gold strikes in history, investors who had bought into Bre-X Minerals Ltd. and its elusive gold find in Indonesia took a beating today when the stock lost more than 80 percent of its value.Trading had been suspended since Tuesday afternoon because of reports, later partly confirmed by Bre-X and its prospective American partner in developing the site, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold, that the Indonesian gold strike is probably not nearly as lucrative as Bre-X had said it was. When trading resumed late this afternoon, its stock plunged.Also today, the Indonesian Government, which retains a 10 percent share of the gold site, in the Busang area of Borneo, announced that it was suspending the project by withholding the mining rights and work contracts that are necessary for mining to begin. ''We need more time, more explanations and concrete data,'' the minister of mines, I. B. Sudjana, said in a statement.Bre-X's chairman, David G. Walsh, trying to restore some equanimity in his crumbling fortune, said Freeport's analysis was incomplete and a thorough audit of findings would take about a month.Mr. Walsh told reporters that Bre-X had acted properly in its efforts to gauge the amount of gold at the site and that there had been no attempt to deceive anyone. ''All the work we've done technically has been done appropriately,'' Mr. Walsh said, looking somewhat frazzled as he faced reporters on the sidewalk in front of Bre-X headquarters in Calgary, Alberta. ''We'll be exonerated, and the property will stand as we have indicated.''But credibility is always an issue in gold mining, particularly when relatively unknown prospecting companies like Bre-X come across what they say is a big strike in a remote region. The efforts of Mr. Walsh, a former stockbroker, were no exception, said John Woods, publisher of Stockwatch, which tracks Canadian stocks.''He struggled and struggled with this company, which never had enough money to do enough exploration,'' Mr. Woods said. ''Indonesia was a last-gasp chance for him to try to find something for Bre-X to develop. He had had no success anywhere else for more than 10 years.''</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/27/business/huge-indonesia-gold-strike-may-have-been-exaggerated.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Huge Indonesia Gold Strike May Have Been Exaggerated<date>Published: March 27, 1997</date><text>In a stunning reversal of fortune, a tiny Canadian company that once said it had made the world's richest gold strike in the jungles of Indonesia conceded today that it had probably overestimated the size of its find.The company, Bre-X Minerals of Calgary, Alberta, told its prospective American partner in developing the site, Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold of New Orleans, that estimates ranging from 70 million ounces of gold to as much as 200 million ounces at the Busang area of Indonesia may have been inflated because of invalid geologic sampling.Last month, Freeport entered an agreement to become a partner of Bre-X and to build a $400 million mining complex, contingent on the results of its own analysis. Today the company said that it had drilled seven test holes and found ''insignificant amounts of gold.''The announcements represent yet another twist in a tale with high political intrigue, fierce corporate power struggles, a mysterious fire and the strange death a week ago of the Bre-X executive directly responsible for estimating the amount of gold at Busang.The expected reduction of gold estimates is considered evidence by some analysts that big mining companies, which had jockeyed for position to develop the Indonesian find with Bre-X, may have been taken in by a seemingly irresistible pitch.Bre-X was not available to comment today, but as recently as Monday it stood behind its estimates.The interest in Bre-X and its apparent gold strike went beyond just companies like Freeport-McMoran, Barrick Gold and Placer Dome to stock market investors, who have sent the value of Bre-X shares on a dizzying rise since the company began exploring at the Busang site, in the Indonesian region of Borneo, in 1993.At that time, Bre-X shares sold for 30 cents, and the estimated amount of gold was one million ounces. The company's only real asset was its claim to Busang. But as the amount of gold thought to be there rose sharply, so did the value of the shares. At the height, Bre-X sold for $250. It was then split 10 for 1 and the value rose and fell on revised estimates of gold and continuing turmoil in securing the drilling rights from the Indonesian Government.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/22/business/size-of-indonesian-gold-deposit-is-in-dispute.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Size of Indonesian Gold Deposit Is in Dispute<date>Published: March 22, 1997</date><text>Bre-X Minerals Ltd., responding to speculation that an Indonesian gold deposit might not be as big as reported, said today that Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc., a partner in the deposit, was still conducting an examination and had not commented on its progress.Trading in Bre-X stock was halted temporarily today after word circulated of a report in Harian Ekonomi Neraca, an Indonesian newspaper, that Freeport believed the size of the deposit had been overstated. In a statement, Bre-X said Freeport and an Indonesian company had confirmed ''that they are still conducting their due diligence at the Busang site in East Kalimantan, Indonesia, and have not commented on the progress, to the press, in this regard.''An official of Freeport also said it was still examining the deposit.Before trading in Bre-X was halted this morning on the Toronto Stock Exchange, the shares fell $1.20 (Canadian), or 87 cents (United States). Trading resumed after the Bre-X statement was issued, and Bre-X closed at $15.25 (Canadian), down $2.20 (Canadian) on the day.On the New York Stock Exchange, Freeport fell 75 cents, to $30.875.The report followed the death earlier this week of the Bre-X chief geologist, Michael de Guzman, who fell from a helicopter over the province of East Kalimantan on the island of Borneo. Reports have quoted Indonesian police as saying they had found a suicide note. In the letter, the police said, Mr. de Guzman said he was ''giving up'' on life because of disease.Under a recent agreement, the New Orleans-based Freeport holds 15 percent of Busang and has the right to mine the deposit. Bre-X, which discovered the deposit, has 45 percent, and the rest is owned by the Indonesian Government and two Indonesian companies.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/19/business/indonesia-approves-deal-to-develop-gold-field.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Indonesia Approves Deal To Develop Gold Field<date>Published: February 19, 1997</date><text>As expected, the Indonesian Government formally approved a joint venture yesterday between Bre-X Minerals Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, and Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc. to develop one of the world's richest gold deposits.Bre-X, which discovered the Busang field on the island of Borneo, will own 45 percent of the project, while Freeport will own 15 percent and be its sole operator. The Indonesian Government will have a 10 percent share, and two Indonesian companies will own 15 percent each.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/18/business/ties-to-indonesian-rulers-secure-mother-lode-of-gold-deals.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Ties to Indonesian Rulers Secure Mother Lode of Gold Deals<date>Published: February 18, 1997</date><text>A century after the Klondike gold rush, a modern-day stampede marked by political intrigue and fast deals has resulted in an American mining company staking claim in Indonesia to part of one of the richest gold strikes in history.A small Canadian exploration company, Bre-X Minerals of Calgary, Alberta, announced today that it had formed a partnership to mine the gold with Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold of New Orleans, which has a long history in Indonesia and a cozy relationship with its powerful political and business leaders.Freeport beat out several corporate rivals to become sole operator of the Busang mine, situated in the Indonesian portion of Borneo. It is committed to putting as much as $1.6 billion into the project. In exchange it will receive a 15 percent stake in a joint-venture company that will be co-owned by Bre-X (with a 45 percent stake), two Indonesian companies and the Indonesian state.$(On Tuesday in Jakarta, the Indonesian Government formally announced that it had accepted the arrangement.$)The agreement brings to a close several months of bidding among some of the world's leading mining companies. Analysts say there may be more gold deep in South African mines, but what makes the Indonesian find fabulous is that no strike has ever gone from bare dirt to an estimated 100 million ounces of gold reserves as quickly as Busang.By comparison, South Africa, long the world's leading gold producer, mines about 18 million ounces of gold a year, and its biggest mine has produced about half what the Busang mine is expected to yield.Bre-X struck the mother lode late in 1995, after several other exploration companies had walked away from the area.The allure of so much gold, within such easy reach, impelled the competing companies to use whatever means they could to close a deal. This included tapping the Indonesian Government's inclination to make deals based on personal alliances, and playing up to various members of the family of President Suharto, the nation's chief since 1965. In the end, success went to the company with the closest contacts with the President and his advisers, and the longest experience in playing by Indonesia's rules.''It's no coincidence that Freeport got it,'' said Pierre Vaillancourt, a gold analyst with HSBC James Capel Canada, alluding to Freeport McMoran's links with the ruling family, and adding, ''These are the relationships that get you the deal at the end of the day.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/03/business/saskatchewan-company-in-accord-to-buy-arcadian.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Saskatchewan Company In Accord to Buy Arcadian<date>Published: September 03, 1996</date><text>The Potash Corporation of Saskatchewan Inc. said today that it would acquire the Arcadian Corporation in a transaction valued at up to $1.23 billion in cash and stock, ending an agreement for Arcadian to be bought by Freeport-McMoran Inc.The Potash bid is valued at $25 to $27 a share. Arcadian, a fertilizer and chemicals company, has 45.5 million shares outstanding, placing the transaction value at $1.14 billion to $1.23 billion. Freeport-McMoran's offer, made on Aug. 7, was valued at $23 to $24 a share, or about $1 billion.John Hunt, director of investor relations for Arcadian, which is based here, said the company had received the unsolicited offer from Potash on Aug. 23 and had informed Freeport-McMoran of it on Aug. 26.James Moffett, the chairman of Freeport-McMoran, said in a statement that entering into a bidding war would not have been in the best interests of Freeport's shareholders.Potash, which is based in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, mines and produces potash, a potassium salt used in fertilizers and other products. It owns seven potash mines and three phosphate plants.''Instead of just being the largest potash company in the world, we'll be the largest fertilizer company in the world,'' the company's chairman, Charles Childers, said.Mr. Hunt of Arcadian said the combined market capitalization of the two companies would be about $4 billion. ''It just kind of came up unexpectedly,'' he said of the offer from Potash. ''I don't know if the industry will think it was unexpected.''Mergers and acquisitions are picking up in the fertilizer industry as companies combine to gain international market share and withstand industry slumps. In March, IMC Global Inc. bought the Vigoro Corporation for $1.19 billion in stock, creating the largest fertilizer maker in North America.The agreement between Freeport-McMoran, which is based in New Orleans, and Arcadian would have created one of the world's largest makers of phosphate- and nitrogen-based fertilizers. Arcadian specializes in nitrogen fertilizers, while Freeport's fertilizer business is concentrated in phosphate-based products.Under the Freeport-McMoran offer, owners of publicly traded units of the company's fertilizer partnership, Freeport-McMoran Resource Partners L.P., would have had the option of exchanging their stakes for shares in the new company. Freeport-McMoran Inc. holds a 51.6 percent stake in the partnership. .Over all, Freeport's deal with Arcadian would have resulted in the formation of a company with a market capitalization of $3 billion.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/08/business/freeport-mcmoran-and-arcadian-agree-to-merger.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport-McMoran and Arcadian Agree to Merger<date>Published: August 08, 1996</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc., the mining and mineral giant, said yesterday that it would merge with the Arcadian Corporation in a stock deal that values Arcadian at about $1 billion.Under the deal, as outlined in a letter of intent signed by the companies, the public owners of Freeport-McMoran's 51.6 percent owned fertilizer partnership will also have an option to exchange their stakes for shares in the new company.Completion of that part of the deal, not required for the first part to go through, would essentially result in a three-way merger producing a new company with a market value of about $3 billion.Rene L. Latiolais, chief executive of Freeport-McMoran, which is based in New Orleans, and the partnership, said in an telephone interview that the two companies, Freeport-McMoran and Arcadian, would complement each other in the fertilizer production business, and that the companies would work with partnership unit holders to reach an agreeable price.Freeport-McMoran is a leader in phosphates fertilizers through the IMC-Agrico Company, a joint venture between Freeport-McMoran Resource Partners L.P., the fertilizer partnership, and IMC Global Inc. Arcadian, which is based in Memphis, is a power in nitrogen fertilizers.Combining the two companies would produce an enterprise with more than $2 billion in annual sales.Specifics such as who would run the combined entity and its board composition were not immediately determined.''Those details have not been worked out nor announced,'' Mr. Latiolais said. ''Basically, we made the offer for Arcadian and they accepted the offer. Our management team is going to remain intact.''Freeport-McMoran's merger with Arcadian is structured so that shareholders of the two companies exchange their shares for stock in the new company. Freeport-McMoran would swap shares on a 1-for-1 basis. Arcadian would get 0.658 share of the new company for each of its shares.Including preferred stock, Arcadian shareholders would end up with about 52 percent of the combined company, representing a premium for Arcadian shareholders.But with the partnership units as part of the transaction, Freeport McMoran would be the dominant entity. Freeport-McMoran Resource Partners units currently in public hands are worth about $1 billion. An exchange ratio for the partnership units is still to be negotiated.Approvals are needed from shareholders and the boards of both companies, as well as from regulators. IMC Global's approval may also be needed.Participation is also subject to approval by unit holders of Freeport-McMoran Resource partners and a special committee of Freeport-McMoran board members. Mr. Latiolais said Freeport-McMoran would leave the decision solely up to public unit holders, even though the company owns 51.6 percent.Shares of the three companies were mixed after a delayed opening yesterday. In New York Stock Exchange trading, Freeport-McMoran shares fell $1, to $35.50. Shares of Arcadian rose $1.375, to $22, and shares of Freeport-McMoran Resource Partners rose 50 cents, to $20.625.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/14/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-to-buy-back-shares.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; FREEPORT MCMORAN TO BUY BACK SHARES<date>Published: September 14, 1995</date><text>Freeport McMoran Copper and Gold Inc., a unit of Freeport McMoran Inc., said yesterday that it planned to buy back as many as 20 million of its common shares, or 10 percent. Freeport McMoran, of New Orleans, also said it would raise its quarterly dividend to 22.5 cents a share from 15 cents for both its class A and class B shares. The company said the dividend would be paid in November. The class A shares rose $1 to close at $24.75 on the New York Stock Exchange, and the class B stock gained 37.5 cents a share to close at $24.375.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/13/business/shares-sold-in-mining-unit.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Shares Sold in Mining Unit<date>Published: May 13, 1995</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc., an exploration and mining concern, said today that it had completed the sale of 21.5 million shares of its Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc. unit to the RTZ Corporation for $450 million. The sale is the centerpiece of a plan by Freeport-McMoRan to restructure and spin off mining operations.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/03/31/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-sells-indonesia-port-operation.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; FREEPORT-MCMORAN SELLS INDONESIA PORT OPERATION<date>Published: March 31, 1995</date><text>The Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc. said yesterday that its Indonesian subsidiary had sold port, marine, logistics and construction facilities for about $100 million. The buyer was the P.T. ALatieF P&amp;O Port Development Company, an Indonesian foreign investment company jointly owned by the P.T. ALatieF Nusakarya Corporation and P&amp;O Australia Ltd. (Reuters)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/03/08/business/company-news-rtz-to-buy-stake-in-unit-of-freeport.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; RTZ to Buy Stake in Unit Of Freeport<date>Published: March 08, 1995</date><text>The RTZ Corporation has agreed to buy a 10.4 percent stake in the American mining company Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold Inc. for $450 million.The two companies have also agreed to establish ventures to explore and develop Freeport-McMoran Copper's vast holdings in Indonesia, with RTZ investing as much as $850 million in the projects.Combined with RTZ's option to buy more shares in Freeport-McMoran Copper and convertible notes from its parent company, Freeport-McMoran Inc. of New Orleans, this represents a possible investment by RTZ of $1.7 billion in the two American companies.RTZ's possible expenditure "ratifies that the major mining house in the world wants to play with us, and Indonesia is the chosen place to play," said Craig Saporito, Freeport's director of investor relations.Freeport-McMoran Copper, which is in the process of being spun off by Freeport-McMoran, runs one of the world's richest copper reserves, in Indonesia's Irian Jaya province."This is quite good for RTZ," said Nick Wilson, a mining analyst at Nomura Research Institute. "The mine has a huge potential."Through its United States subsidiary RTZ America Inc., the British mining company will acquire about 21.5 million Freeport-McMoran Copper class A shares from Freeport-McMoran for about $450 million, and has the option to buy another 3.5 million shares for about $75 million.RTZ is also prepared to pay cash for about $373 million for Freeport-McMoran's 6.55 percent convertible subordinated notes. If RTZ chooses to exercise the options it will wind up with about 18 percent of Freeport-McMoran Copper's outstanding shares for a total investment of about $875 million.In the joint venture, RTZ will spend $100 million on exploration, allowing Freeport-McMoran Copper to develop its holdings. RTZ will receive a 40 percent interest in current mining operations and future expansion. RTZ will also finance all future projects in which it wishes to participate, up to $750 million.Mr. Saporito said the agreement "lets us eliminate all of the debt at Freeport-McMoran," and should let the company complete a previously announced restructuring in the second half of this year.RTZ shares closed down 10 pence at 729 pence, about $11.95, in London, today. Freeport-McMoran shares rose 50 cents, to $18.50, on the New York Stock Exchange, while those of Freeport-McMoran Copper and Gold rose 87.5 cents, to $21.875.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/06/28/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-stock-soars-on-report-of-find.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; FREEPORT-MCMORAN STOCK SOARS ON REPORT OF FIND<date>Published: June 28, 1994</date><text>Freeport-Mcmoran Inc. said yesterday that it might have struck oil or gas in an exploratory well in the Gulf of Mexico, causing the stock of its trust company to soar. The stock of Freeport-Mcmoran Oil and Gas Royalty Trust, which holds a 90 percent stake in the profits of Freeport-Mcmoran Inc., jumped $1.125, to $3.625, on the New York Stock Exchange, where its 45 percent gain was the best of the day. Freeport-Mcmoran said one of its wells in the West Cameron Block 498 off the coast of Louisiana encountered about "625 feet of net hydrocarbon pay." A spokesman said this suggested an unusually large oil or gas well that could be productive. Freeport-Mcmoran Inc. owns 23.1 percent of the lease on the block.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/06/23/business/company-news-noble-to-buy-interest-in-gulf-of-mexico-properties.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; NOBLE TO BUY INTEREST IN GULF OF MEXICO PROPERTIES<date>Published: June 23, 1993</date><text>Noble Affiliates Inc., based in Ardmore, Okla., said yesterday that it would buy Freeport-McMoRan Inc.'s 70 percent interest in some properties in the Gulf of Mexico for $100 million in cash. The letter of intent was signed by the Samedan Oil Corporation, a Noble subsidiary, and covered the Freeport-McMoran interest in the East Cameron 320, 331 and 332 Federal offshore lease blocks in the gulf. Oil and gas condensate was discovered on the blocks in 1992.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/01/31/business/freeport-mcmoran-convertible-notes.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport-McMoran Convertible Notes<date>Published: January 31, 1991</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. yesterday priced $325 million in convertible subordinated notes due 2001 through underwriters led by Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.The company's proceeds from the note sale are expected to total about $258 million, with the cash used to repay bank debt and for general corporate purposes.The 6.55 percent notes were priced at 79.50 to yield 9.814 percent at maturity. They are convertible into the company's common stock at a price of $37.75 a share, representing a 17.968 percent conversion premium over Tuesday's closing price of $32.Freeport-McMoran has the option to redeem part or all of the issue on or after Jan. 15, 1994. According to the underwriters, these notes have a below investment grade rating of Ba-3 from Moody's Investors Service and BB- by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation.Yesterday the stock closed at $33.25 a share, up $1.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/12/18/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-is-selling-more-assets.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; Freeport-McMoran Is Selling More Assets<date>Published: December 18, 1990</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc., an oil services company, said today that it planned to auction $750 million in assets. The auction is an addition to a $1.5 billion asset-sale program announced last year.The company said proceeds from the latest round of sales would be used to reduce its long-term debt of $1.6 billion.Freeport-McMoran said the new sales, mainly of oil and natural gas properties, would augment the reorganization progam it announced in November 1989."Freeport-McMoran will have generated a total of approximately $2.25 billion in gross sales proceeds when these asset sales are completed," the company's chairman and chief executive, James Moffett, said.Starting in mid-1991, the company said it planned to sell $600 million of oil and natural gas properties.The company's shares slipped 12.5 cents today, to $34.50, on the New York Stock Exchange.Freeport-McMoran took on much of its debt last year, when it bought back 7.6 million of its shares, cutting the number of common shares in circulation to about 64 million.The New Orleans-based company said that as part of the debt-reduction goal, its Freeport-McMoran Copper affiliate planned to trim its ownership in Freeport Indonesia Inc. to 80 percent from 91.1 percent. The company said it would focus on its fertilizer business, the copper and gold business in Irian Jaya, Indonesia, and the oil and gas exploration and development business.Analysts say that Freeport-McMoran's earnings have probably hit bottom. They add the company should benefit from the surge in oil prices after Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.Fertilizer sales have been strong since spring, and recent price increases are working their way through the system.Analysts said profits would probably begin to climb in 1991 to more than $2 a share, as output from the company's Indonesian copper mine starts to be reflected in earnings.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/03/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; Freeport-McMoran<date>Published: October 03, 1990</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. said it had agreed in principle to raise its payments to settle lawsuits challenging the merger with the Freeport-McMoran Oil and Gas Company. The original agreement was reached before the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, which sent oil prices soaring. The company said it had agreed to increase the price for each Freeport-McMoran Oil and Gas share to $11 from $10.50. The price will be paid in Freeport-McMoran Inc. stock. The stock of the oil and gas company rose 37.5 cents today, to $10.625, a new high for the year, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/01/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-in-stock-swap-deal.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Company News; Freeport-McMoran In Stock Swap Deal<date>Published: August 01, 1990</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. agreed to acquire the publicly held shares of its Freeport-McMoran Oil and Gas Company affiliate in a stock swap worth about $241 million. Holders of the stock will get about three shares of stock in the parent company for every 10 shares held, the company said. Freeport-McMoran valued the oil and gas unit at $10.50 a share.Stock in the affiliate rose $2 today, to $10, on the New York Stock Exchange, while the parent company's stock was off 25 cents, to $35.125. Freeport-McMoran, a diversified mining company, said there were about 23 million outstanding shares of the affiliate. The parent holds the remaining 92 million shares.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/03/14/business/company-news-asarco-fights-sale-of-freeport-unit.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; Asarco Fights Sale Of Freeport Unit<date>Published: March 14, 1990</date><text>Asarco Inc. challenged the proposed sale of the Freeport-McMoran Inc.'s gold mining subsidiary to South African-controlled Minorco S.A. In a lawsuit filed in New York Supreme Court, Asarco said its interest in a joint venture with the Freeport-McMoran unit could be violated by the sale.Asarco, based in New York, asked the court to halt the sale until its interests had been protected. Minorco's $17-a-share, or $705 million, offer expires on March 23. Asarco and the Freeport-McMoran unit each have a 50 percent interest in a copper mining project in Arizona. Freeport-McMoran, based in New Orleans, said it would contest the suit.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/02/21/business/company-news-freeport-mcmoran-sells-unit-to-minorco.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; Freeport-McMoran Sells Unit to Minorco<date>Published: February 21, 1990</date><text>Minorco said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Freeport-McMoran Gold for $705 million, sending stock in the New Orleans mining company sharply higher.Freeport's stock rose $2.625 to close at $16.625 on the New York Stock Exchange after Minorco, the world's biggest gold mining company, said it would offer $17 a share.Freeport-McMoran Gold is 61 percent owned by Freeport-McMoran Inc., which has interests in several mining and energy exploration businesses in the United States.Its gold unit mines and processes gold ore and explores for minerals and precious metals in North America.Minorco, or the Minerals and Resources Corporation, is the Luxembourg-based investment arm of Harry Oppenheimer's Anglo American Corporation of South Africa and De Beers Consolidated Mines Ltd.The Oppeneheimers are one of South Africa's wealthiest families, with a fortune built on gold and diamonds.Last year the Oppenheimer concern was defeated in its hostile $4.2 billion takeover bid for Britain's Consolidated Gold Fields P.L.C., the world's No. 2 gold producer.Under this latest expansionary move by the South African mining giant, both parties said the board of Freeport McMoran Gold had unanimously approved and recommended the sale.Freeport-McMoran Inc. has agreed to tender its 61 percent interest into the offer or to sell these shares to Minorco separately for about $428 million. Freeport-McMoran Inc. said it would have an after-tax gain of about $170 million.The parent company said proceeds from the sale would be used to reduce debt and to develop copper and gold discoveries in Indonesia and sulfur discoveries in the Gulf of Mexico.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/04/15/business/company-news-freeport-buyback-at-600-million.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; Freeport Buyback At $600 Million<date>Published: April 15, 1989</date><text>Freeport McMoran Inc. is offering up to $600 million for 15 million shares of its common stock, or about 21.8 percent of the shares outstanding. The natural resources company said it would buy the shares in what is known as a Dutch auction, setting a price between $35 and $40 a share, based on the number and prices of shares offered by stockholders.Stockholders who offer shares at or below the price set by the company will get that price in cash. Freeport, based in New Orleans, owns majority interests in divisions that drill for oil, gas and sulfur, and mine gold, copper and other minerals. Its shares jumped $2.625 on Thursday, when the plan was announced, and closed today at $27.125, down 12.5 cents a share, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/24/us/gypsum-heaps-stir-louisiana-battle.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">GYPSUM HEAPS STIR LOUISIANA BATTLE<date>Published: February 24, 1987</date><text>Hills of gypsum waste upriver from New Orleans have set off public protests and name-calling that have reached the highest corporate offices in the region.Public excoriation is hardly new in Louisiana, which has a tradition of steamy political fights. In the gypsum battle, the contenders are thousands of angry Louisiana residents protesting a proposal to dump up to 12.5 million tons of gypsum waste a year into the Mississippi River, and the officials of the corporations who want to dump it. But the fight recently intensified.James R. Moffett, who is chairman of the board and chief executive officer of Freeport-McMoRan, one of the country's 500 largest industrial companies, lashed out at the state, saying his company had been treated unfairly.This was after the Secretary of the State Department of Environmental Quality, Martha A. Madden, announced that she would not issue permits to dump the gypsum into the river. The gypsum waste is a byproduct of the phosphorous fertilizers produced by four companies, including a subsidiary of Freeport-McMoRan.Ms. Madden's announcement followed months of public protest against the plan to dump the waste into the river, which supplies drinking water for New Orleans and other communities. The protesters say that the gypsum will increase the area's cancer rate, which is already high.Ms. Madden said she was concerned that the gypsum might alter the nitrogen-phosphorous ratio of the river, harming fish and wildlife, as well as increase the level of heavy metals in the river, damaging the seafood industry and adding to the cost of treating drinking water.Freeport-McMoRan moved its corporate headquarters here from New York City in 1985, to applause from the community, badly in need of a lift after the bankruptcy of the 1984 World's Fair. Mr. Moffett himself became a symbol of hope for dynamic leadership and is chairman-elect of the board of the Chamber of Commerce. 'Banana Republic Still Lives'At his news conference he said: ''I am absolutely not going to take the character and credibility of this corporation being maligned by people who are ignorant. The definition of ignorant is that you have no knowledge, and the people who are espousing about this issue have no credentials, they are not nuclear scientists, they are not qualified.''As far as I'm concerned the banana republic still lives. I can assure you we receive better treatment in some foreign countries than we've gotten here.''Mr. Moffett said the gypsum issue had brought 160 threats on his life. His outburst evoked a flood of telephone calls to radio talk shows and other reaction.''Here in Louisiana, we may have lost 500 jobs,'' M. Richard Schroeder wrote in a letter to The New Orleans Times-Picayune in response to the threat to move the company, ''but at least we'll know our water is safe to drink and our bananas are safe to eat.''The gypsum hills have been growing between the river and nearby wetlands since the 1970's, when the Clean Water Act prohibited dumping gypsum into the Mississippi.The fertilizer companies say the soil is too unstable to continue storing gypsum waste on land.The United States Environmental Protection Agency has proposed allowing the gypsum in the river again.Roger Meacham, a spokesman for the agency, said last week that it ''will be modifying the previously proposed permits'' for dumping gypsum and put them before the public. Hearings are to be held in April.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/11/29/business/oil-concern-defaults-on-some-debt.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">OIL CONCERN DEFAULTS ON SOME DEBT<date>November 29, 1986</date><text>The Petro-Lewis Corporation, the financially troubled energy company that has agreed to be acquired by Freeport-McMoran Inc., announced yesterday that it was in default on some debt payments and that it was considering filing for bankruptcy protection. It was unclear how a Chapter 11 filing by Petro-Lewis might affect the planned takeover. The offices of both Petro-Lewis, which is in Denver, and Freeport-McMoran, in New Orleans, were closed yesterday, and their executives could not be reached by telephone for comment.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Petro-Lewis Corporation, the financially troubled energy company that has agreed to be acquired by Freeport-McMoran Inc., announced yesterday that it was in default on some debt payments and that it was considering filing for bankruptcy protection. It was unclear how a Chapter 11 filing by Petro-Lewis might affect the planned takeover. The offices of both Petro-Lewis, which is in Denver, and Freeport-McMoran, in New Orleans, were closed yesterday, and their executives could not be reached by telephone for comment.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/18/business/company-news-freeport-signs-pact-with-petro-lewis.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">COMPANY NEWS; FREEPORT SIGNS PACT WITH PETRO-LEWIS<date>October 18, 1986</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. and the Petro-Lewis Corporation said yesterday that they had signed a definitive agreement under which Freeport would buy Petro-Lewis through a bankruptcy-law reorganization. But the execution of the agreement between the two natural resources companies depends on the results of a tender offer previously made for the Denver-based Petro-Lewis by FPCO Inc., a joint venture formed by Freeport and Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company to make the acquisition.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Freeport-McMoran Inc. and the Petro-Lewis Corporation said yesterday that they had signed a definitive agreement under which Freeport would buy Petro-Lewis through a bankruptcy-law reorganization. But the execution of the agreement between the two natural resources companies depends on the results of a tender offer previously made for the Denver-based Petro-Lewis by FPCO Inc., a joint venture formed by Freeport and Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company to make the acquisition.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/09/business/petro-lewis-bid-extended.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Petro-Lewis Bid Extended<date>Published: October 9, 1986</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc., the natural resources company that is trying to acquire the Petro-Lewis Corporation, announced yesterday that it has extended its cash tender offer until next Tuesday. Freeport has been unable to gain enough senior secured bonds and units of the American Royalty Trust, a Petro-Lewis affiliate, to complete its tender offer. It said, however, that the deadline extension is absolutely its last. Freeport also said that it and Petro-Lewis, and representatives of some of Petro-Lewis's senior debtholders, are discussing whether the tender offer could form the basis for reorganizing Petro-Lewis under bankruptcy proceedings. Under this plan, Petro-Lewis would propose a reorganization in which the holders of public securities would receive no more than the amounts Freeport is offering in its tender.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/06/business/market-place-petro-lewis-deal-is-clouded.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Market Place; Petro-Lewis Deal Is Clouded<date>October 6, 1986</date><text>BARRING any last-minute developments, the fate of the Petro-Lewis Corporation, the Denver oil and gas company that is one of the nation's largest oil and gas drillers, will be decided at midnight tonight. That is when a cash tender offer for Petro-Lewis debt securites expires. The offer is being made by Freeport-McMoran Inc., a natural resources company. Oil analysts who have followed the proposed deal believe that it is too close to call. Petro-Lewis, which lost $405.6 million in its latest fiscal year, has said that, if its debtholders reject the proposed transaction, it will file for bankruptcy.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] BARRING any last-minute developments, the fate of the Petro-Lewis Corporation, the Denver oil and gas company that is one of the nation's largest oil and gas drillers, will be decided at midnight tonight. That is when a cash tender offer for Petro-Lewis debt securites expires. The offer is being made by Freeport-McMoran Inc., a natural resources company. Oil analysts who have followed the proposed deal believe that it is too close to call. Petro-Lewis, which lost $405.6 million in its latest fiscal year, has said that, if its debtholders reject the proposed transaction, it will file for bankruptcy.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/25/business/petro-lewis-accepts-to-an-offer-of-750-million.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Petro-Lewis Accepts to an Offer of $750 Million<date>July 25, 1986</date><text>The Petro-Lewis Corporation, the ailing oil and gas company, said yesterday that it had signed a letter of intent to be acquired by an investor group led by Freeport-McMoran Inc. for a total of about $750 million. The complex transaction, which must be approved by Petro-Lewis's independent board members, would involve the purchase of all of Petro-Lewis's outstanding equity and debt securities for a total of about $440 million, and the repayment of about $275 million of outstanding bank loans. The deal would include the American Royalty Trust, energy-producing properties spun off to shareholders earlier to settle a class-action lawsuit, but still managed by Petro-Lewis, based in Denver.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Petro-Lewis Corporation, the ailing oil and gas company, said yesterday that it had signed a letter of intent to be acquired by an investor group led by Freeport-McMoran Inc. for a total of about $750 million. The complex transaction, which must be approved by Petro-Lewis's independent board members, would involve the purchase of all of Petro-Lewis's outstanding equity and debt securities for a total of about $440 million, and the repayment of about $275 million of outstanding bank loans. The deal would include the American Royalty Trust, energy-producing properties spun off to shareholders earlier to settle a class-action lawsuit, but still managed by Petro-Lewis, based in Denver.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/01/02/business/occidental-sets-a-deal-for-midcon.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">OCCIDENTAL SETS A DEAL FOR MIDCON<date>January 2, 1986</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation yesterday agreed to acquire the Midcon Corporation, the owner of one of the largest natural gas pipelines in the United States, for more than $3 billion. For Occidental, the nation's ninth biggest oil company, the Midcon deal would be its second major acquisition in the last three years. In late 1982, Occidental purchased a rival, the Cities Service Company, for $7 billion. It was the acquisition of Cities Service, which has 2.5 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in the ground in addition to its oil reserves, that made the purchase of Midcon not only attractive but also necessary, according to Dr. Armand Hammer, the 87-year-old chairman of Occidental.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Occidental Petroleum Corporation yesterday agreed to acquire the Midcon Corporation, the owner of one of the largest natural gas pipelines in the United States, for more than $3 billion. For Occidental, the nation's ninth biggest oil company, the Midcon deal would be its second major acquisition in the last three years. In late 1982, Occidental purchased a rival, the Cities Service Company, for $7 billion. It was the acquisition of Cities Service, which has 2.5 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in the ground in addition to its oil reserves, that made the purchase of Midcon not only attractive but also necessary, according to Dr. Armand Hammer, the 87-year-old chairman of Occidental.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/01/01/business/occidental-said-to-bid-for-midcon.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">OCCIDENTAL SAID TO BID FOR MIDCON<date>January 1, 1986</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation has made an offer to buy the Midcon Corporation, the natural gas pipeline company that is trying to evade a hostile takeover offer, a source close to Occidental said yesterday. Spokesmen for Midcon and Occidental declined all comment. However, the source said Midcon's board was to meet at the company's headquarters in Lombard, Ill., outside Chicago, late yesterday afternoon to consider the Occidental offer. Word of an Occidental-Midcon arrangement was widely circulated on Wall Street yesterday, but a final deal was not announced. , The heightened takeover activity helped drive Midcon's stock up $3.125 yesterday, to $69.50, on the New York Stock Exchange. Occidental's shares fell $2, to $31.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Occidental Petroleum Corporation has made an offer to buy the Midcon Corporation, the natural gas pipeline company that is trying to evade a hostile takeover offer, a source close to Occidental said yesterday. Spokesmen for Midcon and Occidental declined all comment. However, the source said Midcon's board was to meet at the company's headquarters in Lombard, Ill., outside Chicago, late yesterday afternoon to consider the Occidental offer. Word of an Occidental-Midcon arrangement was widely circulated on Wall Street yesterday, but a final deal was not announced. , The heightened takeover activity helped drive Midcon's stock up $3.125 yesterday, to $69.50, on the New York Stock Exchange. Occidental's shares fell $2, to $31.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/30/business/futures-options-speculating-on-a-freeze.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Futures/Options; Speculating On a Freeze<date>December 30, 1985</date><text>ONE group of eager speculators is stalking a killer - a killer freeze, that is - but so far without much success. The weapon, or technique, involves buying futures contracts covering frozen Florida orange juice concentrate. December and January are months when the possibility of freezes excites many crop watchers, especially attracting interest to orange juice. This is a commodity that trades quietly for the rest of the year on the New York Cotton Exchange, and is probably one of the most underplayed commodity contracts. Volume for much of 1985 has been between 300 and 600 contracts a day; recently, it has run at 3,000 contracts a day.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] ONE group of eager speculators is stalking a killer - a killer freeze, that is - but so far without much success. The weapon, or technique, involves buying futures contracts covering frozen Florida orange juice concentrate. December and January are months when the possibility of freezes excites many crop watchers, especially attracting interest to orange juice. This is a commodity that trades quietly for the rest of the year on the New York Cotton Exchange, and is probably one of the most underplayed commodity contracts. Volume for much of 1985 has been between 300 and 600 contracts a day; recently, it has run at 3,000 contracts a day.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/25/business/the-bid-for-midcon-intensifies.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">THE BID FOR MIDCON INTENSIFIES<date>December 25, 1985</date><text>The struggle between the Midcon Corporation and the partnership of Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc., which wants to acquire it, intensified yesterday, as Midcon sought to derail the takeover attempt in court. Separately, rumors on Wall Street pointed to several companies as possible friendly bidders for the natural gas pipeline company. That pushed Midcon's stock to $64.50, up $1.625, on the New York Stock Exchange and made it the exchange's third-most-active stock. The day's rise pushed Midcon further above the $62.50 price offered by the partnership.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The struggle between the Midcon Corporation and the partnership of Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc., which wants to acquire it, intensified yesterday, as Midcon sought to derail the takeover attempt in court. Separately, rumors on Wall Street pointed to several companies as possible friendly bidders for the natural gas pipeline company. That pushed Midcon's stock to $64.50, up $1.625, on the New York Stock Exchange and made it the exchange's third-most-active stock. The day's rise pushed Midcon further above the $62.50 price offered by the partnership.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/24/business/partners-in-midcon-bid-arrange-for-financing.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">PARTNERS IN MIDCON BID ARRANGE FOR FINANCING<date>December 24, 1985</date><text>The partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc. to acquire the Midcon Corporation said yesterday that it had secured commitments to finance the full $1.25 billion in high-yield, high-risk securities it wants to use as part of the purchase price. In addition, WB Partners, the vehicle created for the $2.71 billion takeover attempt, said its financial adviser, Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc., was ''highly confident that under current conditions'' it could raise an additional $1.35 billion in senior debt financing for the proposed acquisition. The announcement, made by a spokesman for the partnership after the close of trading on the New York Stock Exchange, appeared to be an effort to allay concerns in the financial community that WB Partners would not be able to secure commitments for the so-called junk-bond financing before Dec. 31, when a Federal Reserve Board rule restricting their use in takeover attempts is scheduled to take effect.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc. to acquire the Midcon Corporation said yesterday that it had secured commitments to finance the full $1.25 billion in high-yield, high-risk securities it wants to use as part of the purchase price. In addition, WB Partners, the vehicle created for the $2.71 billion takeover attempt, said its financial adviser, Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc., was ''highly confident that under current conditions'' it could raise an additional $1.35 billion in senior debt financing for the proposed acquisition. The announcement, made by a spokesman for the partnership after the close of trading on the New York Stock Exchange, appeared to be an effort to allay concerns in the financial community that WB Partners would not be able to secure commitments for the so-called junk-bond financing before Dec. 31, when a Federal Reserve Board rule restricting their use in takeover attempts is scheduled to take effect.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/23/business/business-people-texans-in-midcon-bid-began-with-handshake.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">BUSINESS PEOPLE; TEXANS IN MIDCON BID BEGAN WITH HANDSHAKE<date>December 23, 1985</date><text>Some oil industry analysts say that the $2.7 billion offer made last week by WB Partners for the Midcon Corporation is too low. If that is the case, raising the ante should not prove too difficult for Cyril Wagner Jr. and Jack E. Brown, two of the richest oilmen in Texas. Mr. Wagner and Mr. Brown, along with Freeport-McMoran Inc. of New Orleans, made their bid for Midcon a week after Midcon had completed a $1.14 billion acquisition of United Energy Resources. Yesterday, Midcon rejected the bid and announced a stock buyback.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Some oil industry analysts say that the $2.7 billion offer made last week by WB Partners for the Midcon Corporation is too low. If that is the case, raising the ante should not prove too difficult for Cyril Wagner Jr. and Jack E. Brown, two of the richest oilmen in Texas. Mr. Wagner and Mr. Brown, along with Freeport-McMoran Inc. of New Orleans, made their bid for Midcon a week after Midcon had completed a $1.14 billion acquisition of United Energy Resources. Yesterday, Midcon rejected the bid and announced a stock buyback.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/23/business/midcon-s-directors-reject-bid.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">MIDCON'S DIRECTORS REJECT BID<date>December 23, 1985</date><text>The Midcon Corporation rejected yesterday an unfriendly bid for $2.71 billion made last week by a partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc. and offered to acquire up to 10 million shares of its own stock as a defensive measure. After an afternoon meeting, Midcon directors issued a statement that called the unsolicited bid ''a hostile, highly conditional tender offer'' that would be ''unfair and not in the best interests of Midcon or its shareholders.'' In the statement, Midcon, an oil and gas company based in Lombard, Ill., which recently completed a merger with United Energy Resources, said the takeover bid was too low and of ''questionable legality.'' Frederic Spar, a spokesman for a partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown of Midland, Tex., and Freeport-McMoran of New Orleans, said last night that the partnership would not comment on the Midcon action until it had reviewed the directors' statement.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Midcon Corporation rejected yesterday an unfriendly bid for $2.71 billion made last week by a partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown and Freeport-McMoran Inc. and offered to acquire up to 10 million shares of its own stock as a defensive measure. After an afternoon meeting, Midcon directors issued a statement that called the unsolicited bid ''a hostile, highly conditional tender offer'' that would be ''unfair and not in the best interests of Midcon or its shareholders.'' In the statement, Midcon, an oil and gas company based in Lombard, Ill., which recently completed a merger with United Energy Resources, said the takeover bid was too low and of ''questionable legality.'' Frederic Spar, a spokesman for a partnership formed by Wagner &amp; Brown of Midland, Tex., and Freeport-McMoran of New Orleans, said last night that the partnership would not comment on the Midcon action until it had reviewed the directors' statement.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/18/business/midcon-falls-1.50-a-share.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Midcon Falls $1.50 a Share<date>Published: December 18, 1985</date><text>Stock of the Midcon Corporation slipped $1.50 a share yesterday, to $61.875, on the New York Stock Exchange. Analysts said the drop reflected Wall Street's belief that the $62.50-a-share bid made for Midcon on Monday will fail. WB Partners, jointly owned by the Wagner &amp; Brown partnership of Midland, Tex., and Freeport-McMoran Inc. of New Orleans, made the offer, valued at $2.7 billion. But most analysts called that price low and said Midcon would resist it. Analysts also said opinions about the takeover had been affected by the Federal Reserve Board's proposed regulation to limit use of so-called junk bonds in takeover attempts. The regulations are to take effect Jan. 1. WB Partners said in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission that Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc., its financial adviser, intended to raise $1.25 billion of the proposed purchase price by offering junk bonds.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/10/21/business/sale-of-phillips-unit.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Sale of Phillips Unit<date>Published: October 21, 1985</date><text>NEW ORLEANS, Oct. 20— Freeport-McMoran Inc. said it had agreed to buy the Phillips Petroleum Company's Geysers Geothermal unit and other geothermal properties for $215 million. Freeport-McMoran said Friday that the acquisition strengthens its commitment to the natural resources industry. Geysers Geothermal produces geothermal steam air for electric power generation.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/03/21/business/freeport-britoil.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport-Britoil<date>Published: March 21, 1985</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. agreed to sell a 25 percent interest in some gas and oil reserves to Britoil Ventures Inc. for $73.5 million. The reserves were acquired by Freeport-McMoran when it bought the Midlands Energy Company in December. Britoil also acquired a 25 percent interest in 1.8 million acres of exploration land. Ian Clark, joint managing director of Britoil and chairman of Britoil's American subsidiary, said the acquisition concludes the company's search for specific production sites in the United States.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/01/08/business/business-and-the-law-setting-aside-uranium-pact.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">BUSINESS AND THE LAW; SETTING ASIDE URANIUM PACT<date>January 8, 1985</date><text>ONCE again, uranium is making lawyers glow. An extraordinary arbitration has concluded by setting aside a long-term supply contract for uranium, in part because the price collapsed soon after the contract was made. The case raises troubling questions on the frontiers of contract law: in particular, whether courts should set aside long-term contracts because of dramatic price changes in the market. The traditional view was that parties should be held to their bargains, because the very reason for entering long-term contracts was to lock in current prices.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] ONCE again, uranium is making lawyers glow. An extraordinary arbitration has concluded by setting aside a long-term supply contract for uranium, in part because the price collapsed soon after the contract was made. The case raises troubling questions on the frontiers of contract law: in particular, whether courts should set aside long-term contracts because of dramatic price changes in the market. The traditional view was that parties should be held to their bargains, because the very reason for entering long-term contracts was to lock in current prices.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/11/08/business/freeport-to-sell-minerals-unit.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Freeport to Sell Minerals Unit<date>Published: November 8, 1984</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. has agreed in principle to sell its performance minerals subsidiary, Freeport Kaolin, to the Engelhard Corporation for $100 million, the companies said. The sale requires a definitive agreement and approval by the directors of both companies, and may require approval of certain government agencies, Freeport-McMoran said. Orin R. Smith, president and chief executive of Engelhard, which is based in Edison, N.J., said the acquisition would provide Engelhard with additional manufacturing capacity and mineral reserves. Engelhard makes specialty chemical and metallurgical products, and has interests in precious metals dealing. Freeport- McMoran is an explorer, developer and producer of natural gas, oil, gold and other natural resources.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/11/03/business/sale-by-nu-west.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Sale by Nu-West<date>Published: November 3, 1984</date><text>Freeport-McMoran Inc. and the Transco Energy Company said they had completed a joint purchase of Canadian oil and gas interests from the Nu-West Group Inc. for $325 million (Canadian). The interests include proven reserves of about 316 billion cubic feet of gas and 3.3 million barrels of crude oil and condensate.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/10/17/business/midlands-tender-is-oversubscribed.html?ref=freeportmcmorancopperandgoldinc">Midlands Tender Is Oversubscribed<date>Published: October 17, 1984</date><text>The Midlands Energy Company's stock plunged after Freeport- McMoran Inc. said that about 8 million Midlands common shares - or nearly double the amount Freeport- McMoran was obligated to buy - had been tendered in response to an offer to acquire the company. Under an agreement announced Sept. 13, Freeport was to buy 4.5 million of the tendered shares at $30 each as part of a two-step transaction. Under the second part, the 4.2 million common shares remaining would each be converted into $27.50 principal amount of a new 10 1/2 percent convertible subordinated sinking fund debenture due 2014 of Freeport- McMoran. On the New York Stock Exchange today, Midlands dropped $3.50, to $22.625, making it the biggest percentage loser. Freeport-McMoran slipped 25 cents, to $16.</text></article></page><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
