<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="General Dynamics"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/03/business/03widmer.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Robert H. Widmer, Designer of Military Aircraft, Dies at 95<date>Published: July 2, 2011</date><text>The day the legendary test pilot Chuck Yeager shattered the sound barrier in 1947, Robert H. Widmer marched into his boss’s office at the Consolidated Vultee Aircraft Corporation in Fort Worth to say he wanted to design the world’s first supersonic bomber. He was told to stick to the contracts the company was already fulfilling.Mr. Widmer, an aeronautical engineer, nonetheless threw himself into designing the plane on his own time. Two years later, when the Air Force asked for bids to build a bomber that could fly at extreme altitudes and supersonic speeds, he had all but finished. Convair, as the company was called, won the contract for the bomber, the B-58, with Mr. Widmer’s design. He named the plane the Hustler. Able to fly as high as 15 miles and at a speed twice the speed of sound, it carried some of the most sophisticated military systems yet developed. The Russians had nothing that came close. Bomber pilots passed up transfers with pay raises and promotions just to fly it, Popular Science reported. Mr. Widmer, whose family said he died in Fort Worth on June 20 at the age of 95, would go on to lead the design and development of major aircraft like the F-111 “Aardvark” and the F-16 “Fighting Falcon” as well as the Tomahawk cruise missile, helping to enforce the cold war strategic balance known as mutual assured destruction. His daughter, Gail Widmer Landreth, said he saw lethal airplanes as instruments of peace. When the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics presented Mr. Widmer with its Reed Aeronautics Award for 1983, the organization said he had pioneered “the eras of supersonic cruise and fly-by-wire computerized flight control.” Well into his 80s, Mr. Widmer continued to go to the office every day as the company became General Dynamics, then Lockheed, then Lockheed Martin. In his later years he worked on the sort of unmanned aircraft that became integral to American warfare in Iraq and Afghanistan. A short man with a high-pitched voice, he also continued to display the salty personality for which he was known. “He swore like a sailor,” said Armand Chaput, who worked on advanced aircraft design at General Dynamics and now teaches at the University of Texas. “People were afraid of him, but they really respected him. He could shred you.” Robert Henry Widmer was born in Hawthorne, N.J., on May 17, 1916. Attending Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, he built a small racing biplane as his thesis project and was named the outstanding aeronautical engineer in his class. He earned a master’s degree at the California Institute of Technology but dropped his plans to earn a Ph.D. to join Convair at its headquarters in San Diego, where he first worked on marine aircraft. Transferred to the company’s main aircraft factory in Fort Worth, he honed the wing of the B-24 “Liberator,” the most-produced American military aircraft. When Convair moved on to the B-36 “Peacemaker,” Mr. Widmer presided over wind-tunnel tests. The B-36 went on to become the Air Force’s largest bomber ever and a strategic stalwart in the 1950s. But it experienced repeated problems, prompting Stuart Symington, secretary of the Air Force, to pay a visit to Fort Worth, as The Dallas Morning News recounted the episode in 1997. After being lobbied by Mr. Widmer, Mr. Symington decided that the program should continue and nervously phoned his decision to Defense Secretary James Forrestal. Mr. Symington then asked Mr. Widmer and two Air Force officers to stand and join hands. “If this damn airplane doesn’t make it,” Mr. Symington told them, “we’re going to walk either east or west until our hats float.” A decade later, similar mechanical problems dogged the F-111, a medium-range attack plane. For a time Mr. Widmer flew to Washington every Saturday to confer with Defense Secretary Robert S. McNamara about ironing out the flaws, Mr. Chaput said. Mr. Widmer later defied his bosses by secretly pushing ahead on the F-16, a lightweight fighter, even though there seemed to be no market for it, Mr. Chaput said. Mr. Widmer hid prototypes in hangars. Several years later, the Pentagon decided it wanted such a fighter, and General Dynamics, thanks to Mr. Widmer’s surreptitious efforts, was ready. Having been initially threatened with dismissal for insubordination, Mr. Widmer was instead promoted to vice president for science and engineering for all of General Dynamics. Among his later projects was the Tomahawk cruise missile, which was used extensively in the Persian Gulf war and the Iraq war, and a more fuel-efficient engine for automobiles that carmakers declined to buy. In addition to his daughter, Mr. Widmer is survived by his wife of 65 years, the former Jeanette Billing; his son, Robert; three grandchildren; and two great-grandchildren. Mr. Widmer often worked on highly classified projects, none more secret than his proposed spy plane “Fish” (the letters stood for First Invisible Super Hustler). In a 1999 television interview, Mr. Widmer said an early concept for the plane was to build it in the shape of a disc, a statement that has since reverberated on U.F.O. Web sites. Some of the stealth technology found its way into later airplanes. Mr. Widmer was so valuable to the government that for years the C.I.A. positioned agents in parked cars at each end of the Fort Worth street where he and his family lived, his son said. Mr. Widmer himself told of being instructed to keep a low profile — to make airline reservations under a fake name and to meet agents in half-finished buildings. The ultrasecret projects he worked on were called black projects. “I’m talking about the extreme black,” Mr. Widmer said. “I have lived the extreme black.”The day the legendary test pilot Chuck Yeager shattered the sound barrier in 1947, Robert H. Widmer marched into his boss’s office at the Consolidated Vultee Aircraft Corporation in Fort Worth to say he wanted to design the world’s first supersonic bomber. He was told to stick to the contracts the company was already fulfilling.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/24/us/24secret.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Secrets Prevent Supreme Court From Ruling in Aircraft Case<date>Published: May 23, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — The Supreme Court on Monday unanimously ruled that national security considerations made it impossible for it to take sides in a multibillion-dollar dispute between military contractors and the government.The decision came a week after the court refused to hear an appeal from men who said they had been kidnapped by the Central Intelligence Agency and sent abroad to be tortured as part of the Bush administration’s “extraordinary rendition” program. A federal appeals court had thrown out the lawsuit based on the “state secrets” privilege. The combination of the two developments at the Supreme Court amounts to “an unmistakable and loud signal that all nine of the justices are not about to change the rules of the game in cases in which the government claims that military, intelligence or diplomatic secrets may be revealed,” said David Rudenstine, an authority on the state secrets privilege at the Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law at Yeshiva University in New York. The case decided Monday arose from a 1988 contract between the Navy and two companies, General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas, to develop a stealth aircraft called the A-12 Avenger. Three years later, dissatisfied with the contractors’ progress, the Navy declared them in default and demanded the return of $1.35 billion. The contractors sued, asking to keep the money and seeking $1.2 billion more. They said their work had been frustrated by the government’s failure to share classified information about how to design and build stealth aircraft. The government disputed that, but it would not explain why, invoking the state secrets privilege. The case concerned “some of the government’s most closely guarded military secrets,” Justice Antonin Scalia wrote for the court on Monday. An appeals court had ruled against the companies, saying they had defaulted on their contracts and must return the $1.35 billion. The Supreme Court vacated that decision, ruling, in Justice Scalia’s words, that the better approach is to “leave the parties where they stood when they knocked on the courthouse door.” The contractors may keep what they have been paid but cannot recover more. That is, Justice Scalia wrote, “rough, very rough, equity.” Justice Scalia said the decision was not governed by the leading state secrets case, United States v. Reynolds. In the Reynolds decision, from 1953, the widows of men who died when a B-29 bomber crashed in Waycross, Ga., were denied access on state secrets grounds to information that could have proved their wrongful death claims. But Reynolds was only about given items of evidence, Justice Scalia wrote, and not about whether the case itself could proceed. The better analogies to the dispute before the court, he said, were two cases concerning what he called “alleged contracts to spy,” where the very subject matter of a claim or defense is secret. “Rather than tempt fate, we leave the parties to an espionage agreement where we found them the day they filed suit,” Justice Scalia wrote. “We think a similar situation obtains here.” That should come as no surprise, he said, to the contractors or to the government. Both sides, he said, “must have assumed the risk that state secrets would prevent the adjudication of claims of inadequate performance.” The case is not over, as Monday’s decision returned an important separate question to the lower courts. The government had argued that it had no obligation to share “highly classified information” with the contractors under the contract, even apart from national security concerns. The lower courts will now consider that question. Justice Scalia said Monday’s decision in two consolidated cases, in General Dynamics v. United States, No. 09-1298, and the Boeing Company v. United States, No. 09-1302, arose in an unusual setting. (Boeing is the corporate successor to McDonnell Douglas.) The state secrets privilege, he said, “is the option of last resort, available in a very narrow set of circumstances.”WASHINGTON — The Supreme Court on Monday unanimously ruled that national security considerations made it impossible for it to take sides in a multibillion-dollar dispute between military contractors and the government.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/12/business/12nocera.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">From the Pentagon, a Buy Rating on Contractors - Talking Business<date>Published: February 11, 2011</date><text>At the Cowen &amp; Company military industry investment conference on Wednesday, the breakfast speaker was a man named Ashton B. Carter. A former academic and industry consultant, Dr. Carter, as he likes to call himself — he has a doctorate in theoretical physics, in case you were wondering — is the Defense Department’s under secretary for acquisitions, technology and logistics. That is, he’s the Pentagon’s chief weapons buyer.Cowen is a small firm, but its military analyst, Cai von Rumohr, has been on the beat for more than 40 years. Companies tend not to turn him down when he invites them to his conference. W. James McNerney Jr., the chief executive of Boeing, would be making a presentation later in the day, as would executives from Northrop-Grumman and other contractors. Big institutional investors like T. Rowe Price were out in force. As was the Defense Department. In addition to Mr. Carter, a top Naval official was scheduled to present the next afternoon. If you’re wondering what high-ranking Pentagon officials were doing at an investment conference, well, suffice to say that this was not a question on the minds of the people in this room. They’ve gotten used to it. For the last few months, beginning with a secret meeting last October, Defense Department officials have been making the rounds of analysts and investors. Their main message, to put it bluntly, is that even in an era of tighter budgets, the Pentagon is going to make sure the military industry remains profitable. “Taxpayers and shareholders are aligned,” Mr. Carter intoned on Wednesday. Then he laid out a series of reforms that he said would both increase competition and maintain, as he put it, “profitability over the long term” — a phrase he repeated for emphasis. He told the assemblage that the Pentagon would frown on mergers among the five giant military contractors — the so-called primes: Lockheed Martin, General Dynamics, Raytheon, Northrop-Grumman and Boeing. However, he added, the Defense Department was going to encourage mergers among smaller military contractors. And, he said, “we will be attentive” to innovative smaller companies that provide services (as opposed to weapons systems) to the Pentagon. If you were an investor in the military industry, would you find this useful information? You bet — this is the stuff that can move markets. Although Mr. Carter made several references to “market forces,” the only market for the military industry is the government, which spends some $400 billion a year on weapons systems and other purchases. In economic terms, the Pentagon is a “ monopsony,” a single buyer with life-or-death power over its vendors. If the Pentagon wants the military industry to be healthy and profitable, it can pretty much ensure that outcome. Not being an industry insider, however, I found myself a little taken aback by Mr. Carter’s “guidance.” Monopsony or not, why should the Pentagon be talking up the stocks, even implicitly, of the companies it buys from? Why was Mr. Carter going out of his way to talk to investors and analysts? Didn’t he have more important things to do? The answer, I eventually learned, has to do with something that happened a very long time ago, and goes under the category of “Be careful what you wish for.” Let’s just say that banking isn’t the only industry where the government has allowed a handful of companies to become too big to fail.  The year was 1993. Bill Clinton was the new president, and Les Aspin was his defense secretary. As recounted later by Norman R. Augustine, then the chief executive of Martin Marietta, Mr. Aspin called together about 15 C.E.O.’s of the prime military contractors for a dinner at the Pentagon. Mr. Augustine would memorably label this dinner the Last Supper. Mr. Aspin and several other high-ranking Pentagon officials (including Mr. Carter, who was then an assistant secretary of defense) had brought the group together to send a tough message. With the Berlin Wall gone, the Soviet Union dissolved — and the Pentagon budget flat-lining — the Defense Department was no longer willing, as Mr. Augustine later recounted, “to pay the ballooning overhead” of all those contractors. In no uncertain terms, Mr. Aspin told the group that they needed to start merging. “The rest is history,” Mr. Augustine later wrote. “General Electric Aerospace merged with Martin Marietta, which combined with Lockheed. McDonnell Douglas joined Boeing. Grumman joined Northrop. When the dust had cleared, there were only a few firms left standing.” Five, to be exact. The Last Supper has become part of the lore of the military industry — though partly that’s because Mr. Aspin’s prediction about tighter Pentagon budgets turned out to be so wrong. “On the day George W. Bush took office,” said Loren B. Thompson, a well-known military consultant, “defense spending was around $300 billion.” Today it is more than double that amount, around $700 billion. The wars in Iraq and Afghanistan — not to mention the Pentagon’s voracious appetite for expensive weapons systems, and the lack of competition among the remaining contractors — have been a gold mine for the Big Five. Not surprisingly, for most of the first decade of the 21st century, the stocks of these companies soared. But after peaking in 2008, they came crashing back to earth. Which, for the Pentagon, has turned out to be a problem. These companies need access to the capital markets, which is more difficult when their stocks are down. And the Pentagon simply can’t allow them get into serious financial difficulty; there are just too few of them. “What we can’t afford from the defense perspective is a sick industry,” said Jacques S. Gansler, a former procurement official for the Pentagon who teaches at the University of Maryland. 1 2 Next Page »At the Cowen &amp; Company military industry investment conference on Wednesday, the breakfast speaker was a man named Ashton B. Carter. A former academic and industry consultant, Dr. Carter, as he likes to call himself — he has a doctorate in theoretical physics, in case you were wondering — is the Defense Department’s under secretary for acquisitions, technology and logistics. That is, he’s the Pentagon’s chief weapons buyer.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/25/opinion/25tue2.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Tactical Secrets<date>Published: January 24, 2011</date><text>At the Supreme Court last week, Justice Antonin Scalia summed up what he and other justices seemed to consider the least bad outcome in a difficult case: “It seems to me you call the game off.”The game in this case is a multibillion-dollar contract the government made in 1988 with General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas to build a stealth aircraft, the A-12 Avenger. The issue before the court in General Dynamics Corporation v. United States is whether the government can use the state-secrets privilege to avoid explaining why it wouldn’t share classified technology with them. Two weeks before the companies were supposed to deliver an initial A-12 prototype, they reported it would be delayed a year or more. Six months later, the government canceled the contract, saying the companies had defaulted. The contractors’ primary defense was that the government caused the delay by not sharing information with them, and they insist they should be paid for work done before the contract was ended. If the court favors the government’s argument, the government will collect $2.9 billion — $1.35 billion it claims it’s owed under the contract, plus 20 years of interest. If the contractors prevail, they will collect $2.6 billion — $1.2 billion to cover “actual costs” plus interest. It’s not hard to see why Justice Scalia sought what he called “a ‘go away’ principle of jurisprudence,” with no more money changing hands. But that would require ignoring the trouble with the state-secrets privilege. In the name of fighting terrorism, under President George W. Bush, it became a doctrine used far too frequently to cover up illegal and embarrassing acts. The Obama administration has adopted the Bush policies virtually wholesale, protecting the government from accounting for its misdeeds by denying even a day in court to their victims — like Maher Arar, the Canadian victim of mistaken identity who was arrested and flown to Syria to be tortured. It’s essential for the justices to address the privilege’s faults. In a 1953 ruling in United States v. Reynolds about the deaths of civilians in a military plane crash, the court first recognized and upheld the privilege, agreeing the government could withhold a report about the crash because there was “a reasonable danger” that information about secret electronic equipment would be disclosed. The privilege has since been broadened and overused. As a lower court said in the General Dynamics case, the government has used the privilege “for tactical purposes” and “an unfair advantage.” The court should narrow the privilege to what it was in Reynolds, a limited basis for the government not to disclose a piece of evidence so it can’t be invoked to dismiss entire claims or cases. The court should also rule that trial judges faced with claims of privilege must examine the evidence to ensure they are convinced about the risk to national security from disclosure. The evidence in the Reynolds case has since been declassified. We know that if the trial judge had looked at the “protected” report, he would have found proof only of Air Force negligence that caused the plane’s crash. There was no mention of military intelligence. In Reynolds, the government hoodwinked the Supreme Court. The court should honor the gravity of real state secrets by assuring that other kinds of information can’t be hidden behind this privilege.At the Supreme Court last week, Justice Antonin Scalia summed up what he and other justices seemed to consider the least bad outcome in a difficult case: “It seems to me you call the game off.”</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/19/us/19scotus.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Supreme Court Offers Little Guidance in State Secrets Case<date>Published: January 18, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — It has been almost 60 years since the Supreme Court last had a hard look at the state secrets privilege, which can allow the government to shut down litigation by invoking national security. In the years since the attacks on Sept. 11, 2001, the government has invoked the privilege frequently to scuttle cases, saying they would frustrate its efforts to combat terrorism.The privilege was at the center of an argument at the court on Tuesday. But the justices did not seem inclined to use the opportunity to give the lower courts guidance about its contours. The case arose from a 1988 contract between the Navy and two companies, General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas, to develop a stealth aircraft called the A-12 Avenger. Three years later, dissatisfied with the contractors’ progress, the Navy declared them in default and demanded the return of $1.35 billion. The contractors sued, asking to keep the money and seeking $1.2 billion more. They said their work had been frustrated by the government’s failure to share classified technology. The government disputed that, but would not explain why, invoking the state secrets privilege. An appeals court repeatedly ruled against the companies, saying at one point that national security interests trumped the companies’ rights under the Constitution’s due-process clause. There was no dispute during the argument on Tuesday that the government was entitled to invoke the privilege. The question was what should have happened when it did. The two sides also seemed to agree that the answer to that question could be found in a passage in the leading state-secrets decision, United States v. Reynolds. That decision, from 1953, dismissed a case brought by the widows of men who died when a B-29 bomber crashed in Waycross, Ga., during a secret mission. But the court in Reynolds said the case might have turned out differently if the government had been using the privilege as a litigation shield rather than as a sword. Writing for the majority, Chief Justice Fred M. Vinson said that in criminal cases, for instance, it would be unconscionable to allow the government “to undertake prosecution and then invoke its governmental privileges to deprive the accused of anything which might be material to his defense.” “Such rationale,” Justice Vinson continued, “has no application in a civil forum where the government is not the moving party.” At the argument on Tuesday, Neal K. Katyal, the acting United States solicitor general, said the government was not the moving party referred to in Reynolds here because of the way the contract was designed and the way claims against the government must be litigated. Chief Justice John G. Roberts Jr. told Mr. Katyal that the government’s proposed approach “is a pretty convenient rule for you.” Justice Elena Kagan agreed, saying “that really does sound like a tails you win, heads you win.” Carter G. Phillips, a lawyer for the contractors, said the passage in Reynolds meant that the government was not free both to demand money from his clients and to invoke the privilege when they sought to present a defense. But Justice Stephen G. Breyer said the statement in Reynolds did not fit the circumstances of the new case particularly well. “If we accept as a principle of law what was said in Reynolds, a criminal case or whatever, and apply it to government contracting, where sophisticated contractors are perfectly capable of negotiating their own contract, we are not just throwing a monkey wrench into the gears of government contracting,” Justice Breyer said. “We’re throwing the whole monkey.” Justice Antonin Scalia proposed to resolve the case based on what he called “the ‘go away’ principle of our jurisprudence.” That principle means, he explained, that the courts should do nothing when they cannot determine which side is right because of the state-secrets privilege. “So to say ‘go away’ means everybody keeps the money he has,” Justice Scalia said. Mr. Phillips, representing the contractors, seemed open to Justice Scalia’s approach. “Maybe to some extent you could say we’re sort of being a little greedy,” he said, in asking for $1.2 billion on top of the $1.35 billion his clients hope to keep. Justice Sonia Sotomayor seemed both intrigued by Justice Scalia’s proposal and uncertain about whether it represented a principled way to resolve the two consolidated cases, General Dynamics v. United States, No. 09-1298, and the Boeing Company v. United States, No. 09-1302. (Boeing has merged with and is the corporate successor to McDonnell Douglas.) “Mr. Phillips,” Justice Sotomayor said, “give us a way, a reasoned way, to reach the result Justice Scalia is suggesting, because you are being greedy. You admitted it.” He did not respond directly, but Justice Kagan expressed doubts about having multibillion-dollar disputes turn on the happenstance of which side was holding the other’s money.WASHINGTON — It has been almost 60 years since the Supreme Court last had a hard look at the state secrets privilege, which can allow the government to shut down litigation by invoking national security. In the years since the attacks on Sept. 11, 2001, the government has invoked the privilege frequently to scuttle cases, saying they would frustrate its efforts to combat terrorism.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/06/business/06marine.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Expeditionary Fighting Vehicle to Be Canceled, Officials Say<date>Published: January 5, 2011</date><text>It was supposed to be a tank that swims, a new way for the Marines to storm hostile beaches.But as military budgets come under pressure, the 38-ton landing craft that turns into an assault vehicle seems destined to be the next bit of high-tech wizardry to bite the dust. Pentagon and industry officials say the defense secretary, Robert M. Gates, is poised to cancel the long-delayed $14.4 billion program on Thursday, when he is expected to announce a new round of belt-tightening at the Pentagon. The hybrid vehicle, being built by General Dynamics, is the most expensive weapons system to be cut since Mr. Gates canceled or trimmed three dozen programs in April 2009. Mr. Gates is also likely on Thursday to approve a two-year delay in the Marine Corps version of the F-35 Joint Strike Fighter aircraft, the military’s largest program, and spell out how he plans to save up to $100 billion on the Pentagon’s operations. The military is facing intensifying political and economic pressures to restrain its budget, and Mr. Gates has sought to contain the demands by ending troubled weapons systems and squeezing more efficiency out of the Pentagon’s bureaucracy to pay for other programs. But Congress will have the final say on many of the decisions, including the fate of the hybrid Marine vehicle, and it remains hard to tell how it will balance the fiscal demands with concerns about jobs and military strength. The Marine landing craft, called the Expeditionary Fighting Vehicle, was conceived in the late 1980s, and each one was meant to carry 17 Marines ashore and roar inland without pausing on beaches raked by enemy fire. But difficulties in marrying the land and sea technology have led to billions in cost overruns and years of delay, with an early cost estimate of $9 billion for 1,000 vehicles ballooning to $14.4 billion for 574 of them. The government has so far spent about $3 billion on its development. Mr. Gates, moreover, has questioned whether amphibious assaults, which were crucial in World War II and the Korean War, make sense now that adversaries can fire missiles at ships and tanks from many miles away. As a result, a decision to cancel the vehicle would represent a shift in war-fighting strategy and could diminish the role of the Marines. Even though they have handled some of the toughest fighting in Iraq and Afghanistan, the Marines have been eager to get back to their traditional role as an amphibious fighting force. And to be effective, some say, they need a better means to force their way onto heavily defended islands and coastlines, even if infrequently. Current and former Marine officials said they would now extend the lives of their older landing vehicles, which must be released much closer to the beach, and see if they could come up with a less expensive version of the new vehicle. “We’ll just pray that we don’t have to go into harm’s way in the next 10 years,” said Gregory S. Newbold, a retired Marine lieutenant general who served as director of operations for the Joint Chiefs of Staff from 2000 to 2002. General Dynamics officials and some former Marine officials said they would appeal to Congress to consider buying a smaller number of the new vehicles — possibly 200 — to use in the most hazardous landings, while using other methods to conduct more routine operations. Company officials said the program could account for thousands of jobs in Michigan and Ohio. Mr. Gates’s decision comes after a series of extensive reviews of the future of the Marine Corps, which have left many Marines feeling under siege. Though the smallest service, the Marines have long been known for their outsize political strength, because of their gung-ho desire to be “first to fight” whenever trouble flares. The leaders of President Obama’s deficit reduction panel recommended in November that Mr. Gates cancel the fighting vehicle and also kill the Marine version of the F-35, which can take off and land almost vertically, and halt production of the V-22 Osprey, a combination of a winged plane and a helicopter that has also had a troubled history. But Mr. Gates is likely to give the Marines two more years to solve problems with parts failures that have caused the testing of their version of the F-35, a fighter designed to attack ground targets, to fall behind that of the more conventional Air Force and Navy models, industry officials said. Mr. Gates is not expected to reduce production of the V-22, which the Marines use to speed the delivery of their forces. Still, the Marines say they recognize that Pentagon spending is leveling off and is likely to decline over the next several years. Federal officials said Mr. Gates was seeking to increase the basic Pentagon budget, excluding war costs, to $566 billion for fiscal 2012, but had to push the White House to approve $554 billion, or just a slight increase over the $549 billion that the Pentagon sought for 2011. And even some Marines acknowledge that they made themselves vulnerable to the cost-cutting by becoming just as caught up in high-tech projects as the rest of the military. “The Marine Corps used to say, ‘Our weapons system is the Marine,’ and tout its affordability as a service,” said Dakota Wood, a retired Marine lieutenant colonel who is now a senior fellow at the Center for Strategic and Budgetary Assessments, a research group in Washington. “But they seem to have become enamored with the very high-end programs that in previous years they would have criticized the Army or the Air Force for pursuing.” The new fighting vehicle was supposed to replace the 40-year-old amphibious assault vehicle, which has less armor and can ferry the Marines only a couple of miles to shore. The new craft would have allowed Navy vessels to dispatch the Marines up to 25 miles from shore. It was also designed to travel three times as fast, which could have made it easier for the Marines to skirt the toughest defenses and land in more isolated spots. But during the two decades that the vehicle has been in development, the range of antiship missiles has shot up to 75 miles, making Navy vessels vulnerable if they tried to bring in Marines to attack more sophisticated adversaries. Mr. Gates has also said that a flat hull, needed for the vehicle to skim the surface of the water at 20 to 25 knots, would have exposed it to another threat — roadside bombs — once it came ashore. But after years of breakdowns and poor reliability in testing, program officials said new prototypes had finally seemed on the verge of meeting minimal reliability standards. Navy officials have suggested that Marines would only undertake assaults after enemy defenses had been largely subdued through weeks of bombing by ships and planes. But retired Marines say it is naïve to think that the military would always have such a luxury of time or that bombing works that well. Thom Shanker contributed reporting for this article.It was supposed to be a tank that swims, a new way for the Marines to storm hostile beaches.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/28/business/28arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics’ Profit Rises, Supported by Gulfstream Gains<date>Published: October 27, 2010</date><text>General Dynamics said Wednesday that its Gulfstream unit received orders for more business jets in the third quarter than in any comparable period since mid-2008, another indication of recovery in the market for corporate planes.Jay L. Johnson, the General Dynamics chief executive, told analysts that one-third of the orders came from Latin America and Asia, and the increase reflected demand for two high-speed models being tested. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., does not release quarterly order numbers. But in another measure of how its business is starting to bounce back, the company said it delivered 23 Gulfstream planes in the third quarter, up from 17 in the year-earlier period. Its deliveries had peaked at 41 just as the economy collapsed in the last three months of 2008. Buoyed by the improvement in its aerospace business, General Dynamics, which is also a large military contractor, said its overall profit rose by 13.6 percent in the third quarter. It also raised its forecast for full-year earnings. Northrop Grumman, another military contractor, also reported a gain in third-quarter profit on Wednesday and increased its forecast. Analysts watch the sales of business jets as an indicator of how willing corporations are to spend money as the economy rises and falls. Heidi Wood, an analyst at Morgan Stanley, said in a research note on Wednesday that business jet flights had increased since late last year, and that a recovery “appears under way.” She said earlier this week that there was consistent demand for large planes, while the market for midsize and smaller ones remained “painfully quiet.” She added that the consensus at a trade show last week was that 2012 would be the start of a new sales cycle for new planes, after a glut of used jets was purchased next year. General Dynamics said its deliveries in the third quarter included 17 large planes and six midsize ones. Mr. Johnson said Gulfstream now expected to deliver 75 large jets and nearly 30 midsize aircraft this year, compared with 156 planes in 2008. Textron, the owner of the Cessna Aircraft Company, said last week that its orders had picked up somewhat in September, though Cessna shipped only 26 business jets in the third quarter, compared with 68 a year earlier. Cessna cut 700 jobs in September and slowed production. But Scott C. Donnelly, Textron’s chief executive, told analysts last week that Cessna expected a significant increase in deliveries in the fourth quarter. Cessna also unveiled plans last week for a larger and more advanced version of its Citation X plane, which can seat nine passengers. It expects the first delivery in 2013. Mr. Johnson, the General Dynamics chief executive, said his company’s new and faster large jet, the G650, which seats eight people, should be ready for delivery in 2012. He said it had already attracted 200 orders. Mr. Johnson said orders were also coming in for Gulfstream’s new G250 jet, which has a midsize cabin, and should be ready by late next year. “Our timing relative to the recovery in the midcabin market looks pretty good,” he said. And as tighter military budgets slow the company’s growth in combat systems and warships, “our aerospace business will be the growth engine through the near and intermediate time frames,” Mr. Johnson said. General Dynamics said its net income increased to $650 million, or $1.70 a share, in the third quarter, from $572 million, or $1.47 a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 3.8 percent, to $8.01 billion. The company also increased its earnings forecast for the full year to $6.70 to $6.75 a share, from $6.60 to $6.65 a share. Northrop Grumman, based in Los Angeles, said its net income edged up to $497 million, or $1.67 a share, in the third quarter, from $490 million, or $1.53 a share, a year earlier. Sales increased 4 percent, to $8.71 billion. Northrop raised its full-year earnings guidance to $6.85 to $7 a share, from $6.60 to $6.80 a share. Northrop is exploring the sale of its $6 billion shipbuilding unit. It also might spin off the business to shareholders. Wesley G. Bush, Northrop’s chief executive, said the company was focused on improving its profit margins.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/06/us/politics/06charity.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Congressional Charities Pulling In Corporate Cash<date>Published: September 5, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTON — Representative Joe Baca has achieved near celebrity status in his suburban Los Angeles district, as much for his record of giveaways — Thanksgiving turkeys, college scholarships, spare boots for firefighters — as for anything he has done in Congress.That generosity is made possible by the Joe Baca Foundation, a charity his family set up three years ago to aid local organizations. It provides another benefit, too: helping the Democratic congressman run something akin to a permanent political campaign. Joe Baca T-shirts and caps are given out at the charity’s events, where banners display his name. Local newspapers mention the charity’s donations, and cable stations show appearances by Mr. Baca and his family at functions his foundation supports. “It’s great,” said Laura Goodloe, 36, as she watched her 8-year-old son, Jordan, play at the arena in San Bernardino, Calif., where the Baca Foundation offered a free basketball clinic last month. “He is giving back to the community.” But unlike most private foundations, Mr. Baca’s gets little of its money from its founders’ pockets. Instead, local companies and major corporations that have often turned to Mr. Baca’s Washington office for help, and usually succeed in getting it, are the chief donors. A review by The New York Times of federal tax records and House and Senate disclosure reports found at least two dozen charities that lawmakers or their families helped create or run that routinely accept donations from businesses seeking to influence them. The sponsors — AT&amp;T, Chevron, General Dynamics, Morgan Stanley, Eli Lilly and dozens of others — contribute millions of dollars annually in gifts ranging from token amounts to a check for $5 million. Since 2009, businesses have sent lobbyists and executives to the plush Boulders resort in Scottsdale, Ariz., for a fund-raiser for the scholarship fund of Representative Steve Buyer, Republican of Indiana; sponsored a skeet shooting competition in Florida to help the favorite food bank of Representative Allen Boyd, Democrat of Florida; and subsidized a spa and speedway outing in Las Vegas to aid the charity of Senator John Ensign, Republican of Nevada. Just last month, they touted their largess with flags bearing their names near the tees at a golf tournament benefiting the foundation of Representative James E. Clyburn, Democrat of South Carolina. Despite rules imposed in 2007 to curb the influence of special interests in Congress, corporate donations to lawmakers’ charities have continued, thanks to a provision that allows businesses to make unlimited gifts to them. And while business executives say they want to give to a good cause, their pattern of spending — contributions that often are not disclosed, in apparent violation of ethics rules — suggests another reason. Altria, the cigarette maker, for example, sent at least $45,000 in donations over a six-week period last fall to four charitable programs founded by House members — including Representative John A. Boehner of Ohio, the Republican leader, and Mr. Clyburn, the Democratic whip — just as the company was seeking approval of legislation intended to curb illegal Internet sales of its cigarettes. An Altria spokesman said the donations were not related to the measure, which all four congressmen backed. (The other two are Mr. Boyd and Representative Bart Stupak, Democrat of Michigan.) Tom Williams, a spokesman for Duke Energy, acknowledged that the company participates in lawmakers’ charitable events in part to get access to them and push its agenda. “We are not apologetic about it at all: it is part of our overall effort to work with policy makers,” he said. “Social settings are always a good way to get to know people.” Like Mr. Baca, other members of Congress benefit from the good will that their corporate-financed philanthropy generates among voters. The lawmakers defend the donations, saying they have no influence on the politicians’ positions on legislation or policy. They also say that they typically do not serve on the charities’ governing boards or solicit contributions themselves. “There is nothing improper here at all,” said Mark Hayes, a spokesman for Senator Richard G. Lugar, Republican of Indiana, who helped found two Indiana nonprofit groups that are supported by corporate contributions. “They are simply causes he believes in.” But some current and former lawmakers, as well as ethics officials on Capitol Hill, find the charitable donations troubling, calling them one of the last major unregulated fronts in the “pay to play” culture in Washington. The donations typically far exceed what companies are permitted to give to candidates in campaign contributions. The Office of Congressional Ethics, a House oversight group, twice last year investigated lawmakers’ charities, but took no action, in part because the House granted waivers exempting the congressmen from prohibitions against soliciting donations from companies with business before their committees.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/29/business/29arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Strong Results at 2 Military Contractors<date>Published: April 28, 2010</date><text>The military contractors General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman posted better-than-expected first-quarter earnings on Wednesday as segments that had been laggards showed signs of improvement.General Dynamics, which is having softer demand for armored vehicles after the war-related surge in previous years, said its Gulfstream business jet segment had the best quarter for new orders since mid-2008. That unit has experienced weak demand in the recession. The company said that the cancellation in 2009 of the ground vehicle portion of the Army’s Future Combat Systems modernization program hurt sales at its combat systems unit, which fell 17 percent from a year earlier. Still, first-quarter profit beat estimates, helped by lower operating costs. The business jet division had a 6.7 percent sales decline, but posted a 9 percent increase in operating earnings. Margins in that division improved to 16.1 percent from 13.7 percent a year earlier. General Dynamics reiterated a previous forecast for full-year profit of $6.40 to $6.50 a share. At Northrop Grumman, the shipbuilding division posted a 25 percent sales increase and a 26 percent rise in operating profit. Northrop has been working to turn around this operation, where quality issues have resulted in quarterly charges in the past. Northrop, which also had growth in its unmanned spy plane programs, said first-quarter earnings rose 21 percent, to $469 million. It cited decreases in its share count and pension expense. Profit of $1.53 a share beat the analysts’ average estimate by 21 cents, according to Thomson Reuters. Revenue was higher than expected, and Northrop Grumman raised its full-year outlook. General Dynamics shares rose 42 cents, or 0.55 percent, to close at $76.98, while Northrop Grumman shares climbed $1.49, or 2.2 percent, to $68.67.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/11/us/11evers.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">New Navy Ship to Be Named for Slain Civil Rights Pioneer<date>Published: October 10, 2009</date><text>JACKSON, Miss. (AP)  The widow of the slain civil rights pioneer Medgar Evers fought tears Friday as Navy Secretary Ray Mabus, a former Mississippi governor, announced that he was naming a new Navy supply ship for her husband. Skip to next paragraph Associated Press Medgar Evers was killed in Jackson, Miss., in 1963. Related Times Topics: Medgar Evers His widow, Myrlie Evers-Williams, said: “I think of those who will serve on this ship and those who will see it in different parts of the world. And perhaps they, too, will come to know who Medgar Evers was and what he stood for.” She spoke at Jackson State University, where Mr. Mabus made the announcement. Mr. Evers was Mississippi field secretary of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People when he was assassinated outside his Jackson home on June 12, 1963. He was 37. “He gave his life for his country,” Mr. Mabus told an audience of about 200. Mr. Mabus embraced Ms. Evers-Williams and Mr. Evers’s brother, Charles Evers, as they stood before a screen with a color likeness of the ship and a black-and-white photograph of Medgar Evers. The Medgar Evers will be built at General Dynamics in San Diego, and Mr. Mabus said construction of the 689-foot vessel would take up to two years. The ship will deliver food, ammunition and parts to other ships at sea. In the 1950s and early 1960s, Medgar Evers organized nonviolent protests, voter registration drives and boycotts in his home state. Mr. Mabus, who was a 14-year-old living in northern Mississippi when Mr. Evers was killed, served as governor from January 1988 to January 1992. He said he chose to name his first Navy ship after Mr. Evers because he was a pioneer. “He was committed to his fellow human beings and the dream of making America a nation for all its citizens,” Mr. Mabus said. Medgar Evers was born in tiny Decatur, Miss., about 60 miles east of Jackson. He served in the Army in World War II, fighting in France. After he returned to Mississippi, he earned a degree from what is now Alcorn State University and became involved in the civil rights movement. Mr. Evers’s assassination prompted President John F. Kennedy to ask Congress for a comprehensive civil rights bill. Mr. Evers is buried in Arlington National Cemetery. It was 1994 before his killer, the white supremacist Byron De La Beckwith, was convicted of murder. Ms. Evers-Williams  who lives in Los Angeles and Bend, Ore.  thanked Mr. Mabus for fulfilling a promise he made to her more than 20 years ago, that he would find an appropriate way to commemorate her late husband’s legacy. She said she flew to Mississippi for Friday’s ceremony without knowing why she had to be there. She joked that Navy officials and her friends in Mississippi who arranged the trip did a good job of keeping the information from her. “Mission accomplished,” she told Mr. Mabus with a smile. More Articles in US » A version of this article appeared in print on October 11, 2009, on page A30 of the New York edition.JACKSON, Miss. (AP)  The widow of the slain civil rights pioneer Medgar Evers fought tears Friday as Navy Secretary Ray Mabus, a former Mississippi governor, announced that he was naming a new Navy supply ship for her husband. Skip to next paragraph Associated Press Medgar Evers was killed in Jackson, Miss., in 1963. Related Times Topics: Medgar Evers His widow, Myrlie Evers-Williams, said: “I think of those who will serve on this ship and those who will see it in different parts of the world. And perhaps they, too, will come to know who Medgar Evers was and what he stood for.” She spoke at Jackson State University, where Mr. Mabus made the announcement. Mr. Evers was Mississippi field secretary of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People when he was assassinated outside his Jackson home on June 12, 1963. He was 37. “He gave his life for his country,” Mr. Mabus told an audience of about 200. Mr. Mabus embraced Ms. Evers-Williams and Mr. Evers’s brother, Charles Evers, as they stood before a screen with a color likeness of the ship and a black-and-white photograph of Medgar Evers. The Medgar Evers will be built at General Dynamics in San Diego, and Mr. Mabus said construction of the 689-foot vessel would take up to two years. The ship will deliver food, ammunition and parts to other ships at sea. In the 1950s and early 1960s, Medgar Evers organized nonviolent protests, voter registration drives and boycotts in his home state. Mr. Mabus, who was a 14-year-old living in northern Mississippi when Mr. Evers was killed, served as governor from January 1988 to January 1992. He said he chose to name his first Navy ship after Mr. Evers because he was a pioneer. “He was committed to his fellow human beings and the dream of making America a nation for all its citizens,” Mr. Mabus said. Medgar Evers was born in tiny Decatur, Miss., about 60 miles east of Jackson. He served in the Army in World War II, fighting in France. After he returned to Mississippi, he earned a degree from what is now Alcorn State University and became involved in the civil rights movement. Mr. Evers’s assassination prompted President John F. Kennedy to ask Congress for a comprehensive civil rights bill. Mr. Evers is buried in Arlington National Cemetery. It was 1994 before his killer, the white supremacist Byron De La Beckwith, was convicted of murder. Ms. Evers-Williams  who lives in Los Angeles and Bend, Ore.  thanked Mr. Mabus for fulfilling a promise he made to her more than 20 years ago, that he would find an appropriate way to commemorate her late husband’s legacy. She said she flew to Mississippi for Friday’s ceremony without knowing why she had to be there. She joked that Navy officials and her friends in Mississippi who arranged the trip did a good job of keeping the information from her. “Mission accomplished,” she told Mr. Mabus with a smile.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/20/business/20corner.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Fitting In, and Rising to the Top<date>Published: September 19, 2009</date><text>This interview with Linda Hudson, president of the land and armaments group for BAE Systems, a military contractor, was conducted, edited and condensed by Adam Bryant.Q. What are the most important leadership lessons you’ve learned? A. It was when I first became a company president, and it was the first job where I was truly responsible for the performance of a company. I had mastered the day-to-day mechanics of running organizations. But I don’t think the leadership part of it had settled in quite as profoundly as it did when I took over a company. I was the first female president of the General Dynamics Corporation, and I went out and bought my new fancy suits to wear to work and so on. And I’m at work on my very first day, and a lady at Nordstrom’s had showed me how to tie a scarf in a very unusual kind of way for my new suit. And I go to work and wear my suit, and I have my first day at work. And then I come back to work the next day, and I run into no fewer than a dozen women in the organization who have on scarves tied exactly like mine. And that’s when I realized that life was never going to be the way it had been before, that people were watching everything I did. And it wasn’t just going to be about how I dressed. It was about my behavior, the example I set, the tone I set, the way I carried myself, how confident I was — all those kinds of things. It really was now about me and the context of setting the tone for the organization. That was a lesson I have never forgotten — that as a leader, people are looking at you in a way that you could not have imagined in other roles. And I didn’t see that nearly as profoundly when I was leading a functional organization or a smaller enterprise. But to this day, not only the awareness of that, but the responsibility that goes along with it, is something that I think about virtually every day. Q. What else did you learn from that? A. Well, it gets back to the obligations that go with the position, or how do you parlay that position into something that is effective for the organization. And I think it’s all about clarity, where you’re going, how you’re going to get there, what you have to do to do it, communicating effectively and often, and being very accessible and open to the people around you. It’s trying to bring the human part of leadership into the day-to-day aspects of what you do. I’ve observed it too often: leaders, particularly of large organizations, isolate themselves from the people who work for them, and the personal relationships that often define who you are and what you’re trying to do tend to disappear. I work very hard for that not to be the way I do things or the way I interact with people. Q. Give me some specifics. What have you done to counteract that tendency? A. Well, just on a day-to-day basis. I have, what, 20,000 employees now, but I look for every opportunity, when I’m out visiting locations, just to sit down informally with a cross section of employees, from hourly workers to others, and say: “Anything’s on the table. What do you want to talk about?” I do that as frequently as I can find an opportunity to do it. I find that it’s extremely well received. My e-mail is open to anybody in the organization. Anybody can send me a message, and I answer it. And I find they don’t abuse that. I’m not a touchy-feely kind of leader. I tend to be very decisive and make decisions quickly. But I think it’s incredibly important to realize that relationships define everything that we do, and it’s all about the quality of those relationships that makes an organization work. Q. Are there any other lessons you learned that shaped your management and leadership style? A. I was a teenager in the ’60s and in college in the late ’60s and early ’70s. So I grew up in a very uncertain time, when the country was going through lots of difficulties, the Vietnam War, and riots because of civil rights issues. Women were just beginning to get active in the women’s rights movement. And that time very much defined who I am, along with the fact that I grew up in Central Florida at the peak of the space program. So I grew up wanting to fly airplanes and be an astronaut, and I was very technically inclined in an era when that was not an acceptable thing for women. I was the only female in my engineering class at the University of Florida. When I graduated from college, and I graduated near the top of my class, I was turned down for my first mortgage because I might get pregnant. Women were not entitled to their own credit. American Express turned me down for their college credit card program. In those early years, I was often told and treated like I didn’t count, I didn’t matter. I made more money than my husband, but they wouldn’t count my income. In the workplace, there were no laws at the time to protect women from sexual harassment. There were all kinds of evil and ugly things that happened in the workplace, and there was nothing you could do but find a way to cope and to find a way to make things happen.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/31/us/31cyber.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Contractors Vie for Plum Work, Hacking for U.S.<date>Published: May 30, 2009</date><text>MELBOURNE, Fla.  The government’s urgent push into cyberwarfare has set off a rush among the biggest military companies for billions of dollars in new defense contracts. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Gregg Matthews for The New York Times Terry Gillette, left, and Scott Chase run a Raytheon unit that finds flaws in Pentagon computers. Cyberwar The Digital Arms Race Computers, indispensable in peace, are becoming ever more important in political conflicts and open warfare. This series examines the growing use of computer power as a weapon. Previous Articles in the Series » Fending Off Attacks in Cyberspace What can the White House do to prepare for and fight cyberwars? Join the Discussion » The exotic nature of the work, coupled with the deep recession, is enabling the companies to attract top young talent that once would have gone to Silicon Valley. And the race to develop weapons that defend against, or initiate, computer attacks has given rise to thousands of “hacker soldiers” within the Pentagon who can blend the new capabilities into the nation’s war planning. Nearly all of the largest military companies  including Northrop Grumman, General Dynamics, Lockheed Martin and Raytheon  have major cyber contracts with the military and intelligence agencies. The companies have been moving quickly to lock up the relatively small number of experts with the training and creativity to block the attacks and design countermeasures. They have been buying smaller firms, financing academic research and running advertisements for “cyberninjas” at a time when other industries are shedding workers. The changes are manifesting themselves in highly classified laboratories, where computer geeks in their 20s like to joke that they are hackers with security clearances. At a Raytheon facility here south of the Kennedy Space Center, a hub of innovation in an earlier era, rock music blares and empty cans of Mountain Dew pile up as engineers create tools to protect the Pentagon’s computers and crack into the networks of countries that could become adversaries. Prizes like cappuccino machines and stacks of cash spur them on, and a gong heralds each major breakthrough. The young engineers represent the new face of a war that President Obama described Friday as “one of the most serious economic and national security challenges we face as a nation.” The president said he would appoint a senior White House official to oversee the nation’s cybersecurity strategies. Computer experts say the government is behind the curve in sealing off its networks from threats that are growing more persistent and sophisticated, with thousands of intrusions each day from organized criminals and legions of hackers for nations including Russia and China. “Everybody’s attacking everybody,” said Scott Chase, a 30-year-old computer engineer who helps run the Raytheon unit here. Mr. Chase, who wears his hair in a ponytail, and Terry Gillette, a 53-year-old former rocket engineer, ran SI Government Solutions before selling the company to Raytheon last year as the boom in the military’s cyberoperations accelerated. The operation  tucked into several unmarked buildings behind an insurance office and a dentist’s office  is doing some of the most cutting-edge work, both in identifying weaknesses in Pentagon networks and in creating weapons for potential attacks. Daniel D. Allen, who oversees work on intelligence systems for Northrop Grumman, estimated that federal spending on computer security now totals $10 billion each year, including classified programs. That is just a fraction of the government’s spending on weapons systems. But industry officials expect it to rise rapidly. The military contractors are now in the enviable position of turning what they learned out of necessity  protecting the sensitive Pentagon data that sits on their own computers  into a lucrative business that could replace some of the revenue lost from cancellations of conventional weapons systems. Executives at Lockheed Martin, which has long been the government’s largest information-technology contractor, also see the demand for greater computer security spreading to energy and health care agencies and the rest of the nation’s critical infrastructure. But for now, most companies remain focused on the national-security arena, where the hottest efforts involve anticipating how an enemy might attack and developing the resources to strike back. Though even the existence of research on cyberweapons was once highly classified, the Air Force plans this year to award the first publicly announced contract for developing tools to break into enemy computers. The companies are also teaming up to build a National Cyber Range, a model of the Internet for testing advanced techniques. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in US » A version of this article appeared in print on May 31, 2009, on page A1 of the New York edition.MELBOURNE, Fla.  The government’s urgent push into cyberwarfare has set off a rush among the biggest military companies for billions of dollars in new defense contracts. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Gregg Matthews for The New York Times Terry Gillette, left, and Scott Chase run a Raytheon unit that finds flaws in Pentagon computers. Cyberwar The Digital Arms Race Computers, indispensable in peace, are becoming ever more important in political conflicts and open warfare. This series examines the growing use of computer power as a weapon. Previous Articles in the Series » Fending Off Attacks in Cyberspace What can the White House do to prepare for and fight cyberwars? Join the Discussion » The exotic nature of the work, coupled with the deep recession, is enabling the companies to attract top young talent that once would have gone to Silicon Valley. And the race to develop weapons that defend against, or initiate, computer attacks has given rise to thousands of “hacker soldiers” within the Pentagon who can blend the new capabilities into the nation’s war planning. Nearly all of the largest military companies  including Northrop Grumman, General Dynamics, Lockheed Martin and Raytheon  have major cyber contracts with the military and intelligence agencies. The companies have been moving quickly to lock up the relatively small number of experts with the training and creativity to block the attacks and design countermeasures. They have been buying smaller firms, financing academic research and running advertisements for “cyberninjas” at a time when other industries are shedding workers. The changes are manifesting themselves in highly classified laboratories, where computer geeks in their 20s like to joke that they are hackers with security clearances. At a Raytheon facility here south of the Kennedy Space Center, a hub of innovation in an earlier era, rock music blares and empty cans of Mountain Dew pile up as engineers create tools to protect the Pentagon’s computers and crack into the networks of countries that could become adversaries. Prizes like cappuccino machines and stacks of cash spur them on, and a gong heralds each major breakthrough. The young engineers represent the new face of a war that President Obama described Friday as “one of the most serious economic and national security challenges we face as a nation.” The president said he would appoint a senior White House official to oversee the nation’s cybersecurity strategies. Computer experts say the government is behind the curve in sealing off its networks from threats that are growing more persistent and sophisticated, with thousands of intrusions each day from organized criminals and legions of hackers for nations including Russia and China. “Everybody’s attacking everybody,” said Scott Chase, a 30-year-old computer engineer who helps run the Raytheon unit here. Mr. Chase, who wears his hair in a ponytail, and Terry Gillette, a 53-year-old former rocket engineer, ran SI Government Solutions before selling the company to Raytheon last year as the boom in the military’s cyberoperations accelerated. The operation  tucked into several unmarked buildings behind an insurance office and a dentist’s office  is doing some of the most cutting-edge work, both in identifying weaknesses in Pentagon networks and in creating weapons for potential attacks. Daniel D. Allen, who oversees work on intelligence systems for Northrop Grumman, estimated that federal spending on computer security now totals $10 billion each year, including classified programs. That is just a fraction of the government’s spending on weapons systems. But industry officials expect it to rise rapidly. The military contractors are now in the enviable position of turning what they learned out of necessity  protecting the sensitive Pentagon data that sits on their own computers  into a lucrative business that could replace some of the revenue lost from cancellations of conventional weapons systems. Executives at Lockheed Martin, which has long been the government’s largest information-technology contractor, also see the demand for greater computer security spreading to energy and health care agencies and the rest of the nation’s critical infrastructure. But for now, most companies remain focused on the national-security arena, where the hottest efforts involve anticipating how an enemy might attack and developing the resources to strike back. Though even the existence of research on cyberweapons was once highly classified, the Air Force plans this year to award the first publicly announced contract for developing tools to break into enemy computers. The companies are also teaming up to build a National Cyber Range, a model of the Internet for testing advanced techniques. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/18/business/18ships.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics to Build New Destroyer<date>Published: April 17, 2009</date><text>WASHINGTON  General Dynamics has agreed to build the second ship in a new class of Navy destroyers under a fixed-priced contract as part of a shipbuilding swap arranged by Defense Department officials, the agency’s chief weapons buyer said Friday. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: General Dynamics Corporation John J. Young Jr., the under secretary of defense for acquisition, said the contract would replace a cost-plus-fee deal that had been made with another company, Northrop Grumman, in which the Pentagon would have borne all the risks of possible cost increases. Mr. Young told reporters that he had increasingly pushed for fixed-price contracts over the last year. President Obama has said he wants the Pentagon to expand the use of fixed-price contracts to reduce the huge cost overruns and delays that have plagued many high-tech weapons programs. Mr. Young said the final price was still being negotiated with General Dynamics, which will now build all three of the ships in the new class, the DDG-1000. But he said the shift in contract terms should help the government save money. Mr. Young said the first DDG-1000, which is being built by the General Dynamics shipyard in Bath, Me., was expected to cost $3.4 billion to $3.5 billion. That will include all the research and development costs for the program and the $200 million to $300 million of engineering costs that will be apportioned to each of the three vessels. He said the price for the second ship should drop to around $2.5 billion, and the third one could cost even less. The shift in contract terms came as part of a broader deal involving the two defense contractors that was proposed by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates when he announced a major reshaping in weapons programs this month. So as part of the deal, Northrop Grumman will, in essence, swap its rights to build the second DDG-1000 for contracts to build two older destroyers, the DDG-51, at its shipyard in Ingalls, Miss. The company will also continue to supply major components for the DDG-1000’s. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on April 18, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.WASHINGTON  General Dynamics has agreed to build the second ship in a new class of Navy destroyers under a fixed-priced contract as part of a shipbuilding swap arranged by Defense Department officials, the agency’s chief weapons buyer said Friday. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: General Dynamics Corporation John J. Young Jr., the under secretary of defense for acquisition, said the contract would replace a cost-plus-fee deal that had been made with another company, Northrop Grumman, in which the Pentagon would have borne all the risks of possible cost increases. Mr. Young told reporters that he had increasingly pushed for fixed-price contracts over the last year. President Obama has said he wants the Pentagon to expand the use of fixed-price contracts to reduce the huge cost overruns and delays that have plagued many high-tech weapons programs. Mr. Young said the final price was still being negotiated with General Dynamics, which will now build all three of the ships in the new class, the DDG-1000. But he said the shift in contract terms should help the government save money. Mr. Young said the first DDG-1000, which is being built by the General Dynamics shipyard in Bath, Me., was expected to cost $3.4 billion to $3.5 billion. That will include all the research and development costs for the program and the $200 million to $300 million of engineering costs that will be apportioned to each of the three vessels. He said the price for the second ship should drop to around $2.5 billion, and the third one could cost even less. The shift in contract terms came as part of a broader deal involving the two defense contractors that was proposed by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates when he announced a major reshaping in weapons programs this month. So as part of the deal, Northrop Grumman will, in essence, swap its rights to build the second DDG-1000 for contracts to build two older destroyers, the DDG-51, at its shipyard in Ingalls, Miss. The company will also continue to supply major components for the DDG-1000’s.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/09/business/09defense.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Contractors Agree on Deal to Build Stealth Destroyer<date>Published: April 8, 2009</date><text>Two military contractors, General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman, agreed on Wednesday to a Pentagon deal that will clear the way for all three of the Navy’s multibillion-dollar stealth destroyers to be built at General Dynamics’ shipyard in Maine, Pentagon and industry officials said. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Bath Iron Works A depiction of the Navys new Zumwalt-class destroyer, which will cost $3.3 billion and have stealth technology. Both General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman wanted to build the vessel. Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates, left, negotiated the deal. Also pictured is Gen. James E. Cartwright of the Marine Corps. Northrop Grumman, which had expected to build one of the DDG-1000 destroyers at its shipyard in Mississippi, will contribute major components for each of the vessels. It will also receive contracts for two other destroyers as the Navy restarts production of an earlier model. Stock analysts said the deal, pushed by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates, appeared to be a winning proposition for both contractors. “Mr. Gates delivered a gift to the shipbuilders,” said Loren B. Thompson, a military consultant and the chief operating officer of the Lexington Institute, a research group. Military officials said the precise financial arrangements still needed to be worked out. Pentagon officials had estimated that the first of the new destroyers, also known as the Zumwalt class, would cost $3.3 billion, with additional ships costing at least $2.5 billion each if the Navy had built the 10 that were originally planned. But given Mr. Gates’s decision to limit the program to three ships, independent analysts said, various economies of scale would be lost, and the average cost could rise to $5 billion or more. Still, in proposing a range of cuts in arms programs on Monday, Mr. Gates said he would build only one of the destroyers if General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman would not agree to have all three built at Bath Iron Works in Maine. Mr. Gates said it would have been far too costly and inefficient to have both shipyards gear up to be the lead contractor. Representative Gene Taylor, a Democrat from Mississippi and the chairman of a House armed services subcommittee, said the deal was good for Northrop Grumman because it ensured that the company was “aligned with where the Navy sees its future.” Under the plan, Northrop Grumman will restart production of the DDG-51, also known as the Arleigh Burke-class destroyer, at its Ingalls shipyard in Pascagoula, Miss., and build the first two ships. General Dynamics will build the third once it completes work on the DDG-1000s at the Bath Iron Works. Officials said it was likely that the companies would split any subsequent orders through some type of competitive bidding. Military analysts have estimated that the DDG-51s could cost an average of $1.5 billion to $2 billion each, depending on how many are eventually built. Navy officials had originally embraced the shift to the DDG-1000, in part because it would have new types of radars, designed by Raytheon, that allowed it to make precise scans in relatively cluttered areas near coastlines. That ability was designed to fit the Navy’s increasing emphasis on operating in shallower, coastal waters. But as the cost estimates rose last year, Navy officials began backing away, saying they could no longer afford the ship. Still, the DDG-1000 had substantial political support from Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the Democrat from Massachusetts, where Raytheon is based, and other legislators from New England who were concerned about losing jobs at the Maine shipyard, which employs 5,600. The yard, which began building the first ship in February, expects to deliver it in 2013. Analysts said that the Navy generally fared better than the Air Force and the Army in the Pentagon’s proposals. Mr. Gates said the Navy would gradually slow the production of aircraft carriers, with the total dropping to 10, from 11, after 2040. Northrop Grumman, which builds the carriers, said in a note to employees that it believed that proposal “requires a closer look.” Mr. Gates also said he would delay development of a new cruiser and amphibious ships. But he endorsed the Navy’s goal of buying 55 Littoral Combat Ships, a high-speed coastal combat vessel that has experienced huge cost overruns. His proposals included money for expanding construction of the Virginia-class submarines to two each year, starting in fiscal 2011, from one now. And he said the Navy could start planning a new generation of ballistic missile submarines. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on April 9, 2009, on page B3 of the New York edition.Two military contractors, General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman, agreed on Wednesday to a Pentagon deal that will clear the way for all three of the Navy’s multibillion-dollar stealth destroyers to be built at General Dynamics’ shipyard in Maine, Pentagon and industry officials said. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Bath Iron Works A depiction of the Navys new Zumwalt-class destroyer, which will cost $3.3 billion and have stealth technology. Both General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman wanted to build the vessel. Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates, left, negotiated the deal. Also pictured is Gen. James E. Cartwright of the Marine Corps. Northrop Grumman, which had expected to build one of the DDG-1000 destroyers at its shipyard in Mississippi, will contribute major components for each of the vessels. It will also receive contracts for two other destroyers as the Navy restarts production of an earlier model. Stock analysts said the deal, pushed by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates, appeared to be a winning proposition for both contractors. “Mr. Gates delivered a gift to the shipbuilders,” said Loren B. Thompson, a military consultant and the chief operating officer of the Lexington Institute, a research group. Military officials said the precise financial arrangements still needed to be worked out. Pentagon officials had estimated that the first of the new destroyers, also known as the Zumwalt class, would cost $3.3 billion, with additional ships costing at least $2.5 billion each if the Navy had built the 10 that were originally planned. But given Mr. Gates’s decision to limit the program to three ships, independent analysts said, various economies of scale would be lost, and the average cost could rise to $5 billion or more. Still, in proposing a range of cuts in arms programs on Monday, Mr. Gates said he would build only one of the destroyers if General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman would not agree to have all three built at Bath Iron Works in Maine. Mr. Gates said it would have been far too costly and inefficient to have both shipyards gear up to be the lead contractor. Representative Gene Taylor, a Democrat from Mississippi and the chairman of a House armed services subcommittee, said the deal was good for Northrop Grumman because it ensured that the company was “aligned with where the Navy sees its future.” Under the plan, Northrop Grumman will restart production of the DDG-51, also known as the Arleigh Burke-class destroyer, at its Ingalls shipyard in Pascagoula, Miss., and build the first two ships. General Dynamics will build the third once it completes work on the DDG-1000s at the Bath Iron Works. Officials said it was likely that the companies would split any subsequent orders through some type of competitive bidding. Military analysts have estimated that the DDG-51s could cost an average of $1.5 billion to $2 billion each, depending on how many are eventually built. Navy officials had originally embraced the shift to the DDG-1000, in part because it would have new types of radars, designed by Raytheon, that allowed it to make precise scans in relatively cluttered areas near coastlines. That ability was designed to fit the Navy’s increasing emphasis on operating in shallower, coastal waters. But as the cost estimates rose last year, Navy officials began backing away, saying they could no longer afford the ship. Still, the DDG-1000 had substantial political support from Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the Democrat from Massachusetts, where Raytheon is based, and other legislators from New England who were concerned about losing jobs at the Maine shipyard, which employs 5,600. The yard, which began building the first ship in February, expects to deliver it in 2013. Analysts said that the Navy generally fared better than the Air Force and the Army in the Pentagon’s proposals. Mr. Gates said the Navy would gradually slow the production of aircraft carriers, with the total dropping to 10, from 11, after 2040. Northrop Grumman, which builds the carriers, said in a note to employees that it believed that proposal “requires a closer look.” Mr. Gates also said he would delay development of a new cruiser and amphibious ships. But he endorsed the Navy’s goal of buying 55 Littoral Combat Ships, a high-speed coastal combat vessel that has experienced huge cost overruns. His proposals included money for expanding construction of the Virginia-class submarines to two each year, starting in fiscal 2011, from one now. And he said the Navy could start planning a new generation of ballistic missile submarines.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/20/business/worldbusiness/20jet.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics to Buy Jet Aviation<date>Published: August 19, 2008</date><text>General Dynamics, the military contractor, said Tuesday that it would acquire Jet Aviation, a privately held provider of business-aviation services based in Zurich, for about $2.25 billion in cash. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » General Dynamics said the deal, which would expand its flight support services, was expected to add to its earnings immediately. It expects the acquisition to close by year’s end. Jet Aviation, which is owned by the private equity firm Permira Funds, provides maintenance, repair and overhaul services for business jets. It also charters executive jets. After the acquisition, Jet Aviation will operate as a business unit within the General Dynamics Aerospace group under the Jet Aviation and Midcoast Aviation brands. General Dynamics, which makes Abrams tanks and Gulfstream aircraft, said the management of Jet Aviation would not change. The Swiss company has about 5,600 employees, General Dynamics said in a statement. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on August 20, 2008, on page C7 of the New York edition.General Dynamics, the military contractor, said Tuesday that it would acquire Jet Aviation, a privately held provider of business-aviation services based in Zurich, for about $2.25 billion in cash. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » General Dynamics said the deal, which would expand its flight support services, was expected to add to its earnings immediately. It expects the acquisition to close by year’s end. Jet Aviation, which is owned by the private equity firm Permira Funds, provides maintenance, repair and overhaul services for business jets. It also charters executive jets. After the acquisition, Jet Aviation will operate as a business unit within the General Dynamics Aerospace group under the Jet Aviation and Midcoast Aviation brands. General Dynamics, which makes Abrams tanks and Gulfstream aircraft, said the management of Jet Aviation would not change. The Swiss company has about 5,600 employees, General Dynamics said in a statement.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/24/business/24arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Profit at General Dynamics Increases 25%<date>Published: July 24, 2008</date><text>General Dynamics reported a 25 percent rise in quarterly profit on Wednesday, helped by strong sales of its combat systems and business jets. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » The military contractor has been buoyed by demand for its armored vehicles by American forces in Iraq and Afghanistan. It also issued a full-year forecast at the high end of Wall Street’s expectations. The company, which makes Abrams tanks, posted a second-quarter profit of $641 million, or $1.60 a share, compared with $513 million, or $1.26 a share, a year earlier. Quarterly revenue rose 10.8 percent, to $7.3 billion. Analysts’ average profit forecast was $1.44 a share, according to Reuters estimates. General Dynamics expects full-year earnings from continuing operations of $6 to $6.05 a share. More Articles in Business »General Dynamics reported a 25 percent rise in quarterly profit on Wednesday, helped by strong sales of its combat systems and business jets. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio General Dynamics Corp Go to your Portfolio » The military contractor has been buoyed by demand for its armored vehicles by American forces in Iraq and Afghanistan. It also issued a full-year forecast at the high end of Wall Street’s expectations. The company, which makes Abrams tanks, posted a second-quarter profit of $641 million, or $1.60 a share, compared with $513 million, or $1.26 a share, a year earlier. Quarterly revenue rose 10.8 percent, to $7.3 billion. Analysts’ average profit forecast was $1.44 a share, according to Reuters estimates. General Dynamics expects full-year earnings from continuing operations of $6 to $6.05 a share.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DF103AF93BA35756C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics Post<date>Published: May 8, 2008</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said Wednesday that the head of the power company Dominion Virginia Power, a unit of Dominion, will succeed the current chief executive, Nicholas D. Chabraja, when he retires next summer. The executive, Jay L. Johnson, is currently a member of the General Dynamics board. Under a succession plan, he will become vice chairman of the board and a General Dynamics executive on Sept. 2, then take over as chief executive on July 1, 2009, a day after Mr. Chabraja retires. Mr. Johnson, 61, has been a General Dynamics director since 2003 and is a former Navy admiral.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/25/us/25ship.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Lesson on How Not to Build a Navy Ship<date>Published: April 25, 2008</date><text>With the crack of a Champagne bottle against its bow, the newly minted Navy warship, bedecked with bunting, slid sideways into the Menominee River in Wisconsin with a titanic splash. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Erol Reyal for The New York Times Lockheed Martin held a launching ceremony for its combat ship prototype in 2006, but the ship, above in February, is still not finished. More Photos » Multimedia Slide Show How Not to Build a Ship Graphic A Shipbuilding Programs Troubles Moments before the launching on Sept. 23, 2006, Adm. Mike Mullen, the chief of naval operations, told the festive crowd of shipbuilders, politicians and Navy brass assembled at the Marinette Marine shipyard, “Just a little more than three years ago, she was just an idea; now Freedom stands before us.” Not quite. The ship  the first of a new class of versatile, high-speed combat vessels designed to operate in coastal waters  was indeed bobbing in the river, just four months after the promised launching date. But it was far from finished. In fact, the ship floats there still, work continuing day and night. A project heralded as the dawning of an innovative, low-cost era in Navy shipbuilding has turned into a case study of how not to build a combat ship. The bill for the ship, being built by Lockheed Martin, has soared to $531 million, more than double the original, and by some calculations could be $100 million more. With an alternate General Dynamics prototype similarly struggling at an Alabama shipyard, the Navy last year temporarily suspended the entire program. The program’s tribulations speak to what military experts say are profound shortcomings in the Pentagon’s acquisitions system. Even as spending on new projects has risen to its highest point since the Reagan years, being over budget and behind schedule have become the norm: a recent Government Accountability Office audit found that 95 projects  warships, helicopters and satellites  were delayed 21 months on average and cost 26 percent more than initially projected, a bill of $295 billion. In a narrow sense, the troubled birth of the coastal ships was rooted in the Navy’s misbegotten faith in a feat of maritime alchemy: building a hardened warship by adapting the design of a high-speed commercial ferry. As Representative Gene Taylor, the Mississippi Democrat who leads the House Armed Services Subcommittee on Seapower and Expeditionary Forces, put it, “Thinking these ships could be built to commercial specs was a dumb move.” Behind the numbers in the Accountability Office study, experts say, is a dynamic of mutually re-enforcing deficiencies: ever-changing Pentagon design requirements; unrealistic cost estimates and production schedules abetted by companies eager to win contracts, and a fondness for commercial technologies that often, as with the ferry concept, prove unsuitable for specialized military projects. At the same time, a policy of letting contractors take the lead in managing weapons programs has coincided with an acute shortage of government engineers trained to oversee these increasingly complex enterprises. The coastal ships  called littoral combat ships  are especially important to the Navy, which has struggled to retain a central role in American military operations after the cold war. In part, they are a response to the Navy’s own Sept. 11 moment, which came in October 2000, when two terrorists in a bomb-laden rubber dinghy rammed the destroyer Cole, killing 17 sailors and wounding 39 more. An examination of the littoral combat ships by The New York Times, including interviews with many of the principal Navy and industry officials involved, found that the project was hobbled from the outset by the Navy’s zeal to build the ships as fast and inexpensively as possible and the contractors’ desire  driven by competitive pressures  to stay on schedule, even as the ferry designs proved impractical and construction problems multiplied. In their haste to get the ships into the water, the Navy and contractors redesigned and built them at the same time  akin to building an office tower while reworking the blueprints. To meet its deadline, Lockheed abandoned the normal sequence of shipbuilding steps: instead of largely finishing sections and then assembling the ship, much of the work was left to be done after the ship was welded together. That slowed construction and vastly drove up costs. “It’s not good to be building as you’re designing,” said Vice Adm. Paul E. Sullivan, commander of the Navy branch that supervises shipbuilding. A Lockheed executive vice president, Christopher E. Kubasik, said, “We have acknowledged all along our shared responsibility for challenges encountered in the design and construction of the littoral combat ship, which are similar to those typically experienced with first-in-class vessels, including the competing LCS design.” Mr. Kubasik said the company was working toward “realistic cost goals for subsequent ships.” General Dynamics declined to comment. 1 2 3 4 Next Page » More Articles in US »With the crack of a Champagne bottle against its bow, the newly minted Navy warship, bedecked with bunting, slid sideways into the Menominee River in Wisconsin with a titanic splash. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Erol Reyal for The New York Times Lockheed Martin held a launching ceremony for its combat ship prototype in 2006, but the ship, above in February, is still not finished. More Photos » Multimedia Slide Show How Not to Build a Ship Graphic A Shipbuilding Programs Troubles Moments before the launching on Sept. 23, 2006, Adm. Mike Mullen, the chief of naval operations, told the festive crowd of shipbuilders, politicians and Navy brass assembled at the Marinette Marine shipyard, “Just a little more than three years ago, she was just an idea; now Freedom stands before us.” Not quite. The ship  the first of a new class of versatile, high-speed combat vessels designed to operate in coastal waters  was indeed bobbing in the river, just four months after the promised launching date. But it was far from finished. In fact, the ship floats there still, work continuing day and night. A project heralded as the dawning of an innovative, low-cost era in Navy shipbuilding has turned into a case study of how not to build a combat ship. The bill for the ship, being built by Lockheed Martin, has soared to $531 million, more than double the original, and by some calculations could be $100 million more. With an alternate General Dynamics prototype similarly struggling at an Alabama shipyard, the Navy last year temporarily suspended the entire program. The program’s tribulations speak to what military experts say are profound shortcomings in the Pentagon’s acquisitions system. Even as spending on new projects has risen to its highest point since the Reagan years, being over budget and behind schedule have become the norm: a recent Government Accountability Office audit found that 95 projects  warships, helicopters and satellites  were delayed 21 months on average and cost 26 percent more than initially projected, a bill of $295 billion. In a narrow sense, the troubled birth of the coastal ships was rooted in the Navy’s misbegotten faith in a feat of maritime alchemy: building a hardened warship by adapting the design of a high-speed commercial ferry. As Representative Gene Taylor, the Mississippi Democrat who leads the House Armed Services Subcommittee on Seapower and Expeditionary Forces, put it, “Thinking these ships could be built to commercial specs was a dumb move.” Behind the numbers in the Accountability Office study, experts say, is a dynamic of mutually re-enforcing deficiencies: ever-changing Pentagon design requirements; unrealistic cost estimates and production schedules abetted by companies eager to win contracts, and a fondness for commercial technologies that often, as with the ferry concept, prove unsuitable for specialized military projects. At the same time, a policy of letting contractors take the lead in managing weapons programs has coincided with an acute shortage of government engineers trained to oversee these increasingly complex enterprises. The coastal ships  called littoral combat ships  are especially important to the Navy, which has struggled to retain a central role in American military operations after the cold war. In part, they are a response to the Navy’s own Sept. 11 moment, which came in October 2000, when two terrorists in a bomb-laden rubber dinghy rammed the destroyer Cole, killing 17 sailors and wounding 39 more. An examination of the littoral combat ships by The New York Times, including interviews with many of the principal Navy and industry officials involved, found that the project was hobbled from the outset by the Navy’s zeal to build the ships as fast and inexpensively as possible and the contractors’ desire  driven by competitive pressures  to stay on schedule, even as the ferry designs proved impractical and construction problems multiplied. In their haste to get the ships into the water, the Navy and contractors redesigned and built them at the same time  akin to building an office tower while reworking the blueprints. To meet its deadline, Lockheed abandoned the normal sequence of shipbuilding steps: instead of largely finishing sections and then assembling the ship, much of the work was left to be done after the ship was welded together. That slowed construction and vastly drove up costs. “It’s not good to be building as you’re designing,” said Vice Adm. Paul E. Sullivan, commander of the Navy branch that supervises shipbuilding. A Lockheed executive vice president, Christopher E. Kubasik, said, “We have acknowledged all along our shared responsibility for challenges encountered in the design and construction of the littoral combat ship, which are similar to those typically experienced with first-in-class vessels, including the competing LCS design.” Mr. Kubasik said the company was working toward “realistic cost goals for subsequent ships.” General Dynamics declined to comment. 1 2 3 4 Next Page »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/25/business/25arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Higher Earnings for Military Contractors<date>Published: January 25, 2008</date><text>Two large military contractors, the Lockheed Martin Corporation and the Northrop Grumman Corporation, reported higher fourth-quarter profits on Thursday, both citing strong military and civil electronics business. The two companies both forecast higher profit for 2008. The results match the higher profit posted Wednesday by a rival, General Dynamics. Shares of Lockheed rose 4 percent, or $4.21, to $105.90. Shares of Northrop fell 88 cents, to $77.44. Lockheed reported a 10 percent rise in quarterly profit, to $799 million, or $1.89 a share, compared with $729 million, or $1.68 a share, in the period a year earlier. This year’s fourth-quarter results topped a forecast of $1.70 a share from Reuters Estimates. Revenue was flat at $10.84 billion. The company, based in Bethesda, Md., reported lower quarterly revenue from its F-16 fighter jet, which is now made only for overseas military forces, and also from its new F-35 fighter, which is still in the early stages of production. Those declines were offset by higher revenue at its electronics, information and space systems units, helped by sales of its technology services for military and civil use. Northrop Grumman, based in Los Angeles, reported fourth- quarter profit of $454 million, or $1.31 a share, compared with $453 million, or $1.28 a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales were up 10 percent, to $8.82 billion, ahead of analysts’ average forecast of $8.4 billion. Sales were higher across Northrop’s information, aerospace, electronics and shipbuilding units. But the increase in profit was slight because of a one-time gain of $111 million in the quarter a year ago from selling shares of the car parts maker TRW Automotive Holdings, which Northrop spun off. More Articles in Business »Two large military contractors, the Lockheed Martin Corporation and the Northrop Grumman Corporation, reported higher fourth-quarter profits on Thursday, both citing strong military and civil electronics business. The two companies both forecast higher profit for 2008. The results match the higher profit posted Wednesday by a rival, General Dynamics. Shares of Lockheed rose 4 percent, or $4.21, to $105.90. Shares of Northrop fell 88 cents, to $77.44. Lockheed reported a 10 percent rise in quarterly profit, to $799 million, or $1.89 a share, compared with $729 million, or $1.68 a share, in the period a year earlier. This year’s fourth-quarter results topped a forecast of $1.70 a share from Reuters Estimates. Revenue was flat at $10.84 billion. The company, based in Bethesda, Md., reported lower quarterly revenue from its F-16 fighter jet, which is now made only for overseas military forces, and also from its new F-35 fighter, which is still in the early stages of production. Those declines were offset by higher revenue at its electronics, information and space systems units, helped by sales of its technology services for military and civil use. Northrop Grumman, based in Los Angeles, reported fourth- quarter profit of $454 million, or $1.31 a share, compared with $453 million, or $1.28 a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales were up 10 percent, to $8.82 billion, ahead of analysts’ average forecast of $8.4 billion. Sales were higher across Northrop’s information, aerospace, electronics and shipbuilding units. But the increase in profit was slight because of a one-time gain of $111 million in the quarter a year ago from selling shares of the car parts maker TRW Automotive Holdings, which Northrop spun off.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/24/business/24arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics’ Profit Rose 42% in 4th Quarter<date>Published: January 24, 2008</date><text>WASHINGTON (AP)  The General Dynamics Corporation, the military contractor, said Wednesday that higher sales of combat vehicles to the Army and of corporate jets pushed fourth-quarter earnings up 42 percent. But the company’s outlook for 2008 was below Wall Street’s expectations. Net income rose to $579 million, or $1.42 a share, in the quarter, from $408 million, or $1 a share, in the period a year ago. The 2006 quarterly results included a charge of 13 cents a share, largely because of the company’s sale of a coal mining operation. Analysts had expected $1.41 a share in profit, according to Thomson Financial. Earnings estimates typically exclude one-time items. Sales rose 15 percent, to $7.52 billion from $6.51 billion last year, but fell short of Wall Street’s estimate of $7.55 billion. General Dynamics forecast a profit of $5.55 to $5.65 a share in 2008. That forecast is lower than the $5.73 a share expected by analysts. Analysts largely shrugged off the shortfall, noting that General Dynamics often makes cautious estimates early in the year, only to raise them later. “Given the firm’s history of starting the year with an element of conservatism, we remain confident in our estimate and do not believe that investors should take fright in this range,” wrote Robert Stallard, an analyst with Banc of America Securities, in a research note. Shares rose 20 cents, to $79.05. The company’s combat systems division, which makes military hardware, had a 46 percent sales increase to $2.6 billion in the quarter. The aerospace unit, composed of the Gulfstream private jet company, was up 17 percent, to $1.2 billion in sales. For all of 2007, General Dynamics had net earnings of $2.1 billion, or $5.08 a share, up 11 percent from $1.86 billion, or $4.56 a share, in 2006. More Articles in Business »WASHINGTON (AP)  The General Dynamics Corporation, the military contractor, said Wednesday that higher sales of combat vehicles to the Army and of corporate jets pushed fourth-quarter earnings up 42 percent. But the company’s outlook for 2008 was below Wall Street’s expectations. Net income rose to $579 million, or $1.42 a share, in the quarter, from $408 million, or $1 a share, in the period a year ago. The 2006 quarterly results included a charge of 13 cents a share, largely because of the company’s sale of a coal mining operation. Analysts had expected $1.41 a share in profit, according to Thomson Financial. Earnings estimates typically exclude one-time items. Sales rose 15 percent, to $7.52 billion from $6.51 billion last year, but fell short of Wall Street’s estimate of $7.55 billion. General Dynamics forecast a profit of $5.55 to $5.65 a share in 2008. That forecast is lower than the $5.73 a share expected by analysts. Analysts largely shrugged off the shortfall, noting that General Dynamics often makes cautious estimates early in the year, only to raise them later. “Given the firm’s history of starting the year with an element of conservatism, we remain confident in our estimate and do not believe that investors should take fright in this range,” wrote Robert Stallard, an analyst with Banc of America Securities, in a research note. Shares rose 20 cents, to $79.05. The company’s combat systems division, which makes military hardware, had a 46 percent sales increase to $2.6 billion in the quarter. The aerospace unit, composed of the Gulfstream private jet company, was up 17 percent, to $1.2 billion in sales. For all of 2007, General Dynamics had net earnings of $2.1 billion, or $5.08 a share, up 11 percent from $1.86 billion, or $4.56 a share, in 2006.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/25/business/25arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Profits Higher at Military Contractors<date>Published: October 25, 2007</date><text>The military contractors Northrop Grumman and General Dynamics posted higher third-quarter profit yesterday and raised their financial forecasts as a result of strong Pentagon spending. The broadly positive results come a day after Lockheed Martin, the world’s largest military contractor, beat Wall Street’s profit expectations and raised its full-year forecast on record Pentagon spending and demand for its jets. Northrop beat Wall Street’s quarterly profit forecasts and also raised its full-year profit forecast, helped by strong sales at its information technology and shipbuilding units. Northrop, like its rivals, is concentrating more on information technology and civil projects as a way of hedging the risk of a slowdown in the building of military hardware. The company, based in Los Angeles, made no financial projections for next year. Its shares rose $2.72, or 3.4 percent, to $82.25 on the New York Stock Exchange. General Dynamics also posted better-than-expected quarterly earnings and raised its full-year earnings forecast above Wall Street’s expectations based on strong demand for its military vehicles and business jets. The company, which makes Abrams tanks, Stryker fighting vehicles, and submarines and ships for the United States Navy, was bolstered by a 37 percent jump in sales at its military vehicles unit, which is seeing increased business supplying American forces in Iraq and Afghanistan. Shares of General Dynamics rose $2.90, or 3.3 percent, to $90. “The military side is turning a bit weak,” said an aerospace analyst, Paul Nisbet, at JSA Research. “If anything there’s less money for missile defense.” More Articles in Business »The military contractors Northrop Grumman and General Dynamics posted higher third-quarter profit yesterday and raised their financial forecasts as a result of strong Pentagon spending. The broadly positive results come a day after Lockheed Martin, the world’s largest military contractor, beat Wall Street’s profit expectations and raised its full-year forecast on record Pentagon spending and demand for its jets. Northrop beat Wall Street’s quarterly profit forecasts and also raised its full-year profit forecast, helped by strong sales at its information technology and shipbuilding units. Northrop, like its rivals, is concentrating more on information technology and civil projects as a way of hedging the risk of a slowdown in the building of military hardware. The company, based in Los Angeles, made no financial projections for next year. Its shares rose $2.72, or 3.4 percent, to $82.25 on the New York Stock Exchange. General Dynamics also posted better-than-expected quarterly earnings and raised its full-year earnings forecast above Wall Street’s expectations based on strong demand for its military vehicles and business jets. The company, which makes Abrams tanks, Stryker fighting vehicles, and submarines and ships for the United States Navy, was bolstered by a 37 percent jump in sales at its military vehicles unit, which is seeing increased business supplying American forces in Iraq and Afghanistan. Shares of General Dynamics rose $2.90, or 3.3 percent, to $90. “The military side is turning a bit weak,” said an aerospace analyst, Paul Nisbet, at JSA Research. “If anything there’s less money for missile defense.”</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/04/business/04boileau.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Oliver Boileau, 80, Aerospace Executive, Is Dead<date>Published: August 4, 2007</date><text>ST. LOUIS (AP), Aug. 3  Oliver C. Boileau, a retired aerospace executive who worked on projects from the lunar rover to the B-2 stealth bomber, died here on July 27. He was 80. The cause was complications of surgery, according to the Forever Bellerive Cemetery in Creve Coeur, Mo. Mr. Boileau, who was known as Ollie, held leadership positions at Boeing, General Dynamics and Northrup Grumman. He was born in Camden, N.J., and served in the Navy in World War II. Mr. Boileau began his career in national defense at RCA in Camden in 1951. A year later, he joined Boeing in Seattle, where he directed work on the lunar rover, the Minuteman missile program and other projects. He was later promoted to lead the Boeing Aerospace Company, which in the 1980s was the military and space arm of Boeing. Mr. Boileau left Boeing in 1980 to be president and vice chairman of General Dynamics in St. Louis. He held the post for nine years. After a brief retirement, Northrop in Southern California brought him back to lead the B-2 stealth bomber program. He retired in 1995 as president of Northrop Grumman. Among the survivors are his wife, Nan Eleze (Lee) Boileau; two daughters; two sons; and two grandchildren. More Articles in Business »ST. LOUIS (AP), Aug. 3  Oliver C. Boileau, a retired aerospace executive who worked on projects from the lunar rover to the B-2 stealth bomber, died here on July 27. He was 80. The cause was complications of surgery, according to the Forever Bellerive Cemetery in Creve Coeur, Mo. Mr. Boileau, who was known as Ollie, held leadership positions at Boeing, General Dynamics and Northrup Grumman. He was born in Camden, N.J., and served in the Navy in World War II. Mr. Boileau began his career in national defense at RCA in Camden in 1951. A year later, he joined Boeing in Seattle, where he directed work on the lunar rover, the Minuteman missile program and other projects. He was later promoted to lead the Boeing Aerospace Company, which in the 1980s was the military and space arm of Boeing. Mr. Boileau left Boeing in 1980 to be president and vice chairman of General Dynamics in St. Louis. He held the post for nine years. After a brief retirement, Northrop in Southern California brought him back to lead the B-2 stealth bomber program. He retired in 1995 as president of Northrop Grumman. Among the survivors are his wife, Nan Eleze (Lee) Boileau; two daughters; two sons; and two grandchildren.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/26/business/26arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics Beats Estimates<date>Published: July 26, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, July 25 (AP)  The military contractor General Dynamics said Wednesday that its second-quarter earnings slid 19 percent because of one-time items, but strength in its private jet and combat equipment units helped propel core earnings past Wall Street expectations. The company raised its 2007 outlook. Net income dropped to $513 million, or $1.26 a share, in the recent quarter, from $636 million, or $1.56 a share, in the year-earlier period, which included a gain of $220 million, or 54 cents a share, from the sale of the companys aggregate business. Profit from continuing operations rose to $518 million, or $1.27 a share, from $420 million, or $1.03 a share, in the year-ago quarter. The latest quarter included a tax benefit of $18 million, or 5 cents a share. Revenue rose 11 percent to $6.59 billion in the quarter from $5.93 billion in the 2006 period. General Dynamics, which makes tanks, submarines, warships and Gulfstream private jets, also raised its full-year goal for earnings from continuing operations. The chief executive, Nicholas D. Chabraja, predicted 2007 earnings of $4.85 to $4.95 a share on revenue of $27 billion. In January he had predicted earnings of $4.60 a share. He attributed the higher outlook to better-than-anticipated margins at Gulfstream, combined with growth in revenue in the companys shipbuilding unit and the combat systems division, which makes tanks, armored personnel carriers and other fighting equipment. General Dynamics shares rose $2.79, or about 3.5 percent, to $83.09. More Articles in Business »WASHINGTON, July 25 (AP)  The military contractor General Dynamics said Wednesday that its second-quarter earnings slid 19 percent because of one-time items, but strength in its private jet and combat equipment units helped propel core earnings past Wall Street expectations. The company raised its 2007 outlook. Net income dropped to $513 million, or $1.26 a share, in the recent quarter, from $636 million, or $1.56 a share, in the year-earlier period, which included a gain of $220 million, or 54 cents a share, from the sale of the companys aggregate business. Profit from continuing operations rose to $518 million, or $1.27 a share, from $420 million, or $1.03 a share, in the year-ago quarter. The latest quarter included a tax benefit of $18 million, or 5 cents a share. Revenue rose 11 percent to $6.59 billion in the quarter from $5.93 billion in the 2006 period. General Dynamics, which makes tanks, submarines, warships and Gulfstream private jets, also raised its full-year goal for earnings from continuing operations. The chief executive, Nicholas D. Chabraja, predicted 2007 earnings of $4.85 to $4.95 a share on revenue of $27 billion. In January he had predicted earnings of $4.60 a share. He attributed the higher outlook to better-than-anticipated margins at Gulfstream, combined with growth in revenue in the companys shipbuilding unit and the combat systems division, which makes tanks, armored personnel carriers and other fighting equipment. General Dynamics shares rose $2.79, or about 3.5 percent, to $83.09.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=generaldynamicscorporation">OPENERS: SUITS; PLEASE DON'T GO<date>Published: June 10, 2007</date><text>Nicholas D. Chabraja, chairman and chief executive of General Dynamics, now knows what a difference a year and two months can make. Mr. Chabraja, 64, was scheduled to retire in April 2008, and he had been promised two years' use of an office and assistant and 500 hours of flying time on the company's Gulfstream jets. In its proxy statement published in March, General Dynamics estimated the cost of those postretirement perquisites at about $3 million. But last week, the company agreed to pay Mr. Chabraja $8 million, plus interest, next year in lieu of the use of the planes and office, or well more than double what it said they were worth three months ago. A company spokesman said that for ''expedience,'' General Dynamics decided to give him enough to cover the cost of buying those services elsewhere. That is not the only special incentive for him to stay past his 65th birthday. He also would receive a bonus for all of 2009, despite working only four months of that year, that will be at least as big as his bonus for 2008. His bonus last year was $3.2 million. In addition, his retirement benefit will grow by more than $400,000 a year. PATRICK McGEEHAN</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/25/business/25arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Acquisitions Bolster General Dynamics<date>Published: January 25, 2007</date><text>General Dynamics, the largest maker of armored vehicles for the United States military, said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit rose on acquisitions. Sales missed analysts’ estimates. Profit from continuing operations climbed 16 percent, to $463 million, or $1.13 a share, from $398 million, or 98 cents, a year earlier, the company said in a statement. Revenue in the information systems and technology division was weaker than predicted as spending for the Iraq war shifted funds away from battlefield electronics to combat equipment like armored vehicles, according to Nicholas D. Chabraja, the chief executive. Acquisitions lifted sales of computer technology by 20 percent; such revenue would have grown just 2 percent without the deals. The company has benefited as the Iraq war increased demand for vehicles and support services. Sales grew 13 percent, to $6.51 billion, missing the average analyst estimate of $6.62 billion. Profit matched the average estimate of 18 analysts in a Bloomberg survey. More Articles in Business »General Dynamics, the largest maker of armored vehicles for the United States military, said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit rose on acquisitions. Sales missed analysts’ estimates. Profit from continuing operations climbed 16 percent, to $463 million, or $1.13 a share, from $398 million, or 98 cents, a year earlier, the company said in a statement. Revenue in the information systems and technology division was weaker than predicted as spending for the Iraq war shifted funds away from battlefield electronics to combat equipment like armored vehicles, according to Nicholas D. Chabraja, the chief executive. Acquisitions lifted sales of computer technology by 20 percent; such revenue would have grown just 2 percent without the deals. The company has benefited as the Iraq war increased demand for vehicles and support services. Sales grew 13 percent, to $6.51 billion, missing the average analyst estimate of $6.62 billion. Profit matched the average estimate of 18 analysts in a Bloomberg survey.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/12/business/worldbusiness/12arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Strict U.S. Rules Disqualify Some Canadian Arms Workers<date>Published: December 12, 2006</date><text>Correction Appended OTTAWA, Dec. 11  As a private in the Canadian army reserve, Marcos Henriquez drove light armored vehicles, sometimes while he was training with American soldiers. At the end of four years with the military, Mr. Henriquez found work inspecting similar vehicles as they rolled off an assembly line at a General Motors of Canada plant in London, Ontario. That is, until he was laid off with 172 co-workers in 2002. Mr. Henriquez said G.M. had told them that the United States government, one of the plants major customers, had decided that their dual citizenship made them security risks. This summer, Mr. Henriquez, a citizen of both El Salvador and Canada, reached a confidential settlement with G.M. over his dismissal. But the case involving him ripples far beyond the London plant. Arms makers who export to the United States are in a squeeze, thanks to a complex set of State Department rules known as the International Traffic in Arms Regulations or ITAR. The unusually strict rules that govern who can work on military projects for the United States government are in stark conflict with Canadian laws against discrimination. The rule that tripped up Mr. Henriquez bans nationals of about 20 countries from working on Pentagon contracts  period  or having any access to related plans and materials. Not only does it complicate management-employee relations, it makes it hard for American military contractors to bid competitively on Canadas military expansion program, which is worth about 15 billion Canadian dollars ($13 billion). Next month, General Motors will face an Ontario Human Rights Tribunal hearing over some of the London plant layoffs. That is a reminder for G.M. that to meet State Department rules, foreign-based military contractors often have to break, or at least challenge, local human rights and employment laws. Mr. Henriquez, who left El Salvador in 1989 to escape civil strife, said he never imagined himself in a civil rights dispute in North America. Im Canadian enough to fight for my fellow citizens but not Canadian enough to work for G.M., said Mr. Henriquez, 47, a father of two who has since found work at an auto parts supplier. They cant step on our laws just because they create jobs. Patty Faith, a spokeswoman for General Motors of Canada, which sold the London factory to General Dynamics in 2003, declined to comment. Ken Yamashita, a spokesman for General Dynamics in Canada, which is under separate investigation by the Ontario Human Rights Commission because of more recent citizenship-related complaints from the plant, also declined to respond. The ITAR citizenship rules affect all of the United States allies, but the conflict with local laws has become most public in Canada. By industry estimates, about half of the countrys seven billion Canadian dollars in annual military production involves contracts from the United States. Officials from the State Department and Canadas departments of foreign affairs and defense said the two governments were discussing the problem, which senior Canadian politicians have raised with their American counterparts. While these officials would not provide any details about those negotiations, Elizabeth Hodges, a spokeswoman for Canadas Department of National Defense, said Canada regards discrimination against workers based on citizenship or country of origin as a violation of the countrys charter of rights and freedoms. Although her colleagues in areas like procurement are required to follow ITAR guidelines, Ms. Hodges said Canadas defense department would never discriminate against a worker to meet the United States rules. As a government department, absolutely not, she said. We are obliged to uphold the law. Nevertheless, Ms. Hodges acknowledged that stance had led to conflicts with the United States. She said such cases were handled individually. While she declined to offer any details about how they are resolved, Ms. Hodges said that we havent run into any absolute roadblocks to date. The main purpose of the ITAR is to keep American military technology out of the hands of hostile nations. Ms. Hodges said the rules had been enforced more vigorously since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. G.M.s compliance, however, appears to be a more stringent approach than most. 1 2 Next Page » Heather Timmons contributed reporting from London. Correction: December 13, 2006 Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the strict rules that govern who can work on projects for the United States military, and the conflicts the rules pose with Canadian laws against discrimination, misstated the value in American dollars of the contracts in Canadas military expansion program, for which some American companies have had difficulty bidding. It is $13 billion, not million. More Articles in Business »Correction Appended OTTAWA, Dec. 11  As a private in the Canadian army reserve, Marcos Henriquez drove light armored vehicles, sometimes while he was training with American soldiers. At the end of four years with the military, Mr. Henriquez found work inspecting similar vehicles as they rolled off an assembly line at a General Motors of Canada plant in London, Ontario. That is, until he was laid off with 172 co-workers in 2002. Mr. Henriquez said G.M. had told them that the United States government, one of the plants major customers, had decided that their dual citizenship made them security risks. This summer, Mr. Henriquez, a citizen of both El Salvador and Canada, reached a confidential settlement with G.M. over his dismissal. But the case involving him ripples far beyond the London plant. Arms makers who export to the United States are in a squeeze, thanks to a complex set of State Department rules known as the International Traffic in Arms Regulations or ITAR. The unusually strict rules that govern who can work on military projects for the United States government are in stark conflict with Canadian laws against discrimination. The rule that tripped up Mr. Henriquez bans nationals of about 20 countries from working on Pentagon contracts  period  or having any access to related plans and materials. Not only does it complicate management-employee relations, it makes it hard for American military contractors to bid competitively on Canadas military expansion program, which is worth about 15 billion Canadian dollars ($13 billion). Next month, General Motors will face an Ontario Human Rights Tribunal hearing over some of the London plant layoffs. That is a reminder for G.M. that to meet State Department rules, foreign-based military contractors often have to break, or at least challenge, local human rights and employment laws. Mr. Henriquez, who left El Salvador in 1989 to escape civil strife, said he never imagined himself in a civil rights dispute in North America. Im Canadian enough to fight for my fellow citizens but not Canadian enough to work for G.M., said Mr. Henriquez, 47, a father of two who has since found work at an auto parts supplier. They cant step on our laws just because they create jobs. Patty Faith, a spokeswoman for General Motors of Canada, which sold the London factory to General Dynamics in 2003, declined to comment. Ken Yamashita, a spokesman for General Dynamics in Canada, which is under separate investigation by the Ontario Human Rights Commission because of more recent citizenship-related complaints from the plant, also declined to respond. The ITAR citizenship rules affect all of the United States allies, but the conflict with local laws has become most public in Canada. By industry estimates, about half of the countrys seven billion Canadian dollars in annual military production involves contracts from the United States. Officials from the State Department and Canadas departments of foreign affairs and defense said the two governments were discussing the problem, which senior Canadian politicians have raised with their American counterparts. While these officials would not provide any details about those negotiations, Elizabeth Hodges, a spokeswoman for Canadas Department of National Defense, said Canada regards discrimination against workers based on citizenship or country of origin as a violation of the countrys charter of rights and freedoms. Although her colleagues in areas like procurement are required to follow ITAR guidelines, Ms. Hodges said Canadas defense department would never discriminate against a worker to meet the United States rules. As a government department, absolutely not, she said. We are obliged to uphold the law. Nevertheless, Ms. Hodges acknowledged that stance had led to conflicts with the United States. She said such cases were handled individually. While she declined to offer any details about how they are resolved, Ms. Hodges said that we havent run into any absolute roadblocks to date. The main purpose of the ITAR is to keep American military technology out of the hands of hostile nations. Ms. Hodges said the rules had been enforced more vigorously since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. G.M.s compliance, however, appears to be a more stringent approach than most. 1 2 Next Page » Heather Timmons contributed reporting from London. Correction: December 13, 2006 Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the strict rules that govern who can work on projects for the United States military, and the conflicts the rules pose with Canadian laws against discrimination, misstated the value in American dollars of the contracts in Canadas military expansion program, for which some American companies have had difficulty bidding. It is $13 billion, not million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/19/business/19arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Contractor’s Net Rises<date>Published: October 19, 2006</date><text>COLLEGE PARK, Md., Oct. 18 (AP)  General Dynamics, the military contractor, reported a 17 percent increase in third-quarter earnings Wednesday as the company posted higher sales across its major business units. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., reported net income of $438 million, or $1.08 a share, compared with $374 million, or 93 cents a share, a year earlier. That was above the forecast of $1.06 a share among analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue rose almost 15 percent, to $6.07 billion, but Wall Street had expected revenue of $6.29 billion, and the shortfall caused its shares to fall $1.03, to close at $75.03. More Articles in Business »COLLEGE PARK, Md., Oct. 18 (AP)  General Dynamics, the military contractor, reported a 17 percent increase in third-quarter earnings Wednesday as the company posted higher sales across its major business units. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., reported net income of $438 million, or $1.08 a share, compared with $374 million, or 93 cents a share, a year earlier. That was above the forecast of $1.06 a share among analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue rose almost 15 percent, to $6.07 billion, but Wall Street had expected revenue of $6.29 billion, and the shortfall caused its shares to fall $1.03, to close at $75.03.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/22/business/22values.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Profit Margins Are Inducing Fear of Heights<date>Published: July 22, 2006</date><text>DESPITE what the adage says, what you dont know can hurt you when you put money in the stock market. Richard Berner, chief United States economist at Morgan Stanley, contends certain adverse developments are not factored into valuations, raising the chances of a decline. Investors are certainly aware that higher inflation and interest rates pose threats. But they may be missing other risks to earnings growth. The problem, Mr. Berner said in a research note, is profit margins  not that they are too low, but the opposite. Margins reached a 40-year peak in the first quarter as profits climbed to 12.3 percent of sales; when revenue and margins grow, profits grow even faster. He identified several factors to explain the margin expansion: higher productivity, lower interest costs and  heres one for the accountants  shrinking write-offs for depreciation, which reduce a companys costs with the stroke of a pen and inflate stated earnings. All three of these trends may be on the verge of reversing, he warned. That would narrow profit margins, as companies are forced to spread higher costs over a relatively stagnant revenue base. In this situation, earnings growth would drop, making for especially unflattering comparisons with robust recent quarters. Duncan W. Richardson, chief equity investment officer at the Eaton Vance funds, questioned Mr. Berners premise. Post-Enron improvements in corporate governance make earnings reports more trustworthy and less susceptible to cheap accounting tricks, he said, and he expects productivity gains to persist. When companies make progress on revenue growth, they can translate that into higher earnings, Mr. Richardson said. I would argue that the market looks very cheap based on the current level of earnings. How much progress companies make is anyones guess if the economy slows, however, and he said that investors could do worse than to focus on businesses that can maintain their margins in an uncomfortable climate. The first place he suggested looking was among critical consumer stocks. Some of his favorites include Comcast, Time Warner and other providers of cable television service. They are not exactly life-or-death consumer stocks, but the companies are critical enough to their customers. Its not as if people are going to turn off their cable if times are tough, Mr. Richardson said. ANOTHER resilient sector, he said, is upmarket retailing. Companies like Nordstrom are not going to lower prices just because things get a little soft, he predicted. A third industry he likes for its margin resilience really does involve matters of life and death: military contracting. His choices are United Technologies and General Dynamics. The sector has consolidated and unfortunately will have plenty of business going forward, he said. For the overall stock market, Robert Turner, chief investment officer of Turner Investment Partners, acknowledged that nothing, not even profit margin growth, lasts forever. At some point the rate of change slows, and we may be near that point now, he said. One possible way to avoid the reckoning is to stick with growth companies, which he said are able to keep margins higher because they can keep revenues higher. The stocks are cheap, too, he said, after six years of underperformance relative to value stocks. He favors Internet companies, including Yahoo; aQuantive, which deals in online advertising; and VistaPrint, an Internet-based printing business. He also likes shares of companies tied to gambling, notably Las Vegas Sands, International Game Technology and Station Casinos. Their margins are protected by human nature. One sector that he and Mr. Richardson consider a safe bet to maintain or raise margins is health care. Mr. Richardson recommended large drug makers, like Johnson &amp; Johnson, Novartis and Wyeth. Mr. Turner prefers biotechnology companies like Celgene, Genentech and Gilead Sciences. What investors dont know can hurt them, but sometimes it can help them, too, Mr. Richardson said. Some potential developments would improve earnings and margin growth, and they are certainly not factored into valuations. A decline in energy prices and an end to Federal Reserve credit tightening  and the easing that would follow eventually  would serve as levers pulling things up, enhancing results by fueling corporate investment, he said. Mr. Berners report is pointing out what can go wrong, Mr. Richardson said. I like to think about what can go right. More Articles in Business »DESPITE what the adage says, what you dont know can hurt you when you put money in the stock market. Richard Berner, chief United States economist at Morgan Stanley, contends certain adverse developments are not factored into valuations, raising the chances of a decline. Investors are certainly aware that higher inflation and interest rates pose threats. But they may be missing other risks to earnings growth. The problem, Mr. Berner said in a research note, is profit margins  not that they are too low, but the opposite. Margins reached a 40-year peak in the first quarter as profits climbed to 12.3 percent of sales; when revenue and margins grow, profits grow even faster. He identified several factors to explain the margin expansion: higher productivity, lower interest costs and  heres one for the accountants  shrinking write-offs for depreciation, which reduce a companys costs with the stroke of a pen and inflate stated earnings. All three of these trends may be on the verge of reversing, he warned. That would narrow profit margins, as companies are forced to spread higher costs over a relatively stagnant revenue base. In this situation, earnings growth would drop, making for especially unflattering comparisons with robust recent quarters. Duncan W. Richardson, chief equity investment officer at the Eaton Vance funds, questioned Mr. Berners premise. Post-Enron improvements in corporate governance make earnings reports more trustworthy and less susceptible to cheap accounting tricks, he said, and he expects productivity gains to persist. When companies make progress on revenue growth, they can translate that into higher earnings, Mr. Richardson said. I would argue that the market looks very cheap based on the current level of earnings. How much progress companies make is anyones guess if the economy slows, however, and he said that investors could do worse than to focus on businesses that can maintain their margins in an uncomfortable climate. The first place he suggested looking was among critical consumer stocks. Some of his favorites include Comcast, Time Warner and other providers of cable television service. They are not exactly life-or-death consumer stocks, but the companies are critical enough to their customers. Its not as if people are going to turn off their cable if times are tough, Mr. Richardson said. ANOTHER resilient sector, he said, is upmarket retailing. Companies like Nordstrom are not going to lower prices just because things get a little soft, he predicted. A third industry he likes for its margin resilience really does involve matters of life and death: military contracting. His choices are United Technologies and General Dynamics. The sector has consolidated and unfortunately will have plenty of business going forward, he said. For the overall stock market, Robert Turner, chief investment officer of Turner Investment Partners, acknowledged that nothing, not even profit margin growth, lasts forever. At some point the rate of change slows, and we may be near that point now, he said. One possible way to avoid the reckoning is to stick with growth companies, which he said are able to keep margins higher because they can keep revenues higher. The stocks are cheap, too, he said, after six years of underperformance relative to value stocks. He favors Internet companies, including Yahoo; aQuantive, which deals in online advertising; and VistaPrint, an Internet-based printing business. He also likes shares of companies tied to gambling, notably Las Vegas Sands, International Game Technology and Station Casinos. Their margins are protected by human nature. One sector that he and Mr. Richardson consider a safe bet to maintain or raise margins is health care. Mr. Richardson recommended large drug makers, like Johnson &amp; Johnson, Novartis and Wyeth. Mr. Turner prefers biotechnology companies like Celgene, Genentech and Gilead Sciences. What investors dont know can hurt them, but sometimes it can help them, too, Mr. Richardson said. Some potential developments would improve earnings and margin growth, and they are certainly not factored into valuations. A decline in energy prices and an end to Federal Reserve credit tightening  and the easing that would follow eventually  would serve as levers pulling things up, enhancing results by fueling corporate investment, he said. Mr. Berners report is pointing out what can go wrong, Mr. Richardson said. I like to think about what can go right.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/20/business/20arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Earnings at General Dynamics Rise 84%<date>Published: July 20, 2006</date><text>By Reuters General Dynamics said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 84 percent, led by strong sales in combat arms and aerospace. The company, a leading Pentagon supplier, reported a profit of $636 million, or $1.56 a share, compared with $345 million, or 85 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Earnings from continuing operations increased to $420 million, or $1.03 a share. Wall Street analysts, as tracked by Reuters Estimates, had expected earnings of $1 a share. Paul H. Nisbet, an aerospace specialist at JSA Research, said: “It was a very solid quarter. It was a little bit above consensus. Every segment did well.” Revenue increased 15.5 percent, to $5.9 billion, also exceeding estimates of $5.77 billion. The company, based in Falls Church, Va., estimated its full-year earnings from continuing operations around $4.15 a share. In trading yesterday, the stock, which rose early in the day, closed down 36 cents, at $67.99. General Dynamics shares, along with those of other military contractors, have more than doubled in price since the invasion of Iraq in March 2003. More Articles in Business »By Reuters General Dynamics said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 84 percent, led by strong sales in combat arms and aerospace. The company, a leading Pentagon supplier, reported a profit of $636 million, or $1.56 a share, compared with $345 million, or 85 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Earnings from continuing operations increased to $420 million, or $1.03 a share. Wall Street analysts, as tracked by Reuters Estimates, had expected earnings of $1 a share. Paul H. Nisbet, an aerospace specialist at JSA Research, said: “It was a very solid quarter. It was a little bit above consensus. Every segment did well.” Revenue increased 15.5 percent, to $5.9 billion, also exceeding estimates of $5.77 billion. The company, based in Falls Church, Va., estimated its full-year earnings from continuing operations around $4.15 a share. In trading yesterday, the stock, which rose early in the day, closed down 36 cents, at $67.99. General Dynamics shares, along with those of other military contractors, have more than doubled in price since the invasion of Iraq in March 2003.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/20/business/20arms.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">3 Companies Credit Military for Profit Gain<date>Published: April 20, 2006</date><text>By The Associated Press Three of the nation's largest diversified manufacturers said yesterday that their profits topped Wall Street forecasts in the first quarter, helped by strong spending in the military and aerospace sectors. The three companies  General Dynamics, Honeywell International and United Technologies  each reported that profit and revenue rose by more than 10 percent. General Dynamics, which is primarily a military contractor, said net income increased to $374 million, or 92 cents a share, on sales of $5.57 billion, from $336 million, or 83 cents a share, on sales of $4.80 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had estimated earnings of 84 cents a share. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., said all major business groups posted higher sales, led by a 30 percent gain in combat systems. Revenue at the aerospace unit, which makes Gulfstream aircraft, increased 23 percent, while sales at the informational systems and technology division rose 13 percent. Marine systems sales were up 5 percent. Honeywell said its profit rose to $436 million, or 52 cents a share, on sales of $7.24 billion, from $358 million, or 42 cents a share, on sales of $6.45 billion a year earlier. The results topped the 49 cents a share expected by Wall Street analysts. The company, based in Morris Township, N.J., posted growth in most segments, including a 5 percent gain in aerospace and a 19 percent rise in automation and control solutions, which include building security devices and thermostats. Sales in Honeywell's smaller specialty materials division, which includes refrigerants and electronic materials, increased 44 percent. United Technologies said it earned $768 million, or 76 cents a share, on sales of $10.62 billion, up from $651 million, or 64 cents a share, on sales of $9.41 billion. Analysts had expected earnings of 73 cents a share, according to Thomson Financial. Sales fell 15 percent at the Sikorsky helicopter unit, hurt by a strike. All other units delivered revenue gains. More Articles in Business »By The Associated Press Three of the nation's largest diversified manufacturers said yesterday that their profits topped Wall Street forecasts in the first quarter, helped by strong spending in the military and aerospace sectors. The three companies  General Dynamics, Honeywell International and United Technologies  each reported that profit and revenue rose by more than 10 percent. General Dynamics, which is primarily a military contractor, said net income increased to $374 million, or 92 cents a share, on sales of $5.57 billion, from $336 million, or 83 cents a share, on sales of $4.80 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had estimated earnings of 84 cents a share. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., said all major business groups posted higher sales, led by a 30 percent gain in combat systems. Revenue at the aerospace unit, which makes Gulfstream aircraft, increased 23 percent, while sales at the informational systems and technology division rose 13 percent. Marine systems sales were up 5 percent. Honeywell said its profit rose to $436 million, or 52 cents a share, on sales of $7.24 billion, from $358 million, or 42 cents a share, on sales of $6.45 billion a year earlier. The results topped the 49 cents a share expected by Wall Street analysts. The company, based in Morris Township, N.J., posted growth in most segments, including a 5 percent gain in aerospace and a 19 percent rise in automation and control solutions, which include building security devices and thermostats. Sales in Honeywell's smaller specialty materials division, which includes refrigerants and electronic materials, increased 44 percent. United Technologies said it earned $768 million, or 76 cents a share, on sales of $10.62 billion, up from $651 million, or 64 cents a share, on sales of $9.41 billion. Analysts had expected earnings of 73 cents a share, according to Thomson Financial. Sales fell 15 percent at the Sikorsky helicopter unit, hurt by a strike. All other units delivered revenue gains.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/15/business/15military.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics to Acquire Information Systems Concern<date>Published: December 15, 2005</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the military contractor, announced yesterday that it would acquire the Anteon International Corporation for $2.1 billion in a move by a company known for its warships and tanks to expand its technology services business. The deal reflects a shift in Pentagon spending and strategy away from heavy military equipment and toward more high-technology weapons and sophisticated electronic systems. The Pentagon recently announced that it wanted to cut $32 billion from coming budgets, and military contractors have responded by investing in the one growth area of the Pentagon budget, intelligence and technology. Under the deal, which is subject to approval by Anteon shareholders and regulators, General Dynamics would pay $55.50 a share and assume $100 million in Anteon debt. The deal was announced just before the market opened yesterday. Anteon shares closed at $40.77 on Tuesday, but yesterday rose 33 percent, to $54.02. Anteon, based in Fairfax, Va., is an information systems and engineering services company. It has forecast revenue in 2006 of $1.7 billion, mainly from Pentagon and Department of Homeland Security contracts. In a conference call with analysts, the chief executive of General Dynamics, Nicholas D. Chabraja, said the merger was a result of on-and-off discussions he had been having with Anteon for several years. General Dynamics was buying Anteon, Mr. Chabraja said, for its highly skilled work force and to enable it to enter new markets. More than 65 percent of Anteon's 9,500 employees have security clearances, which allow them to work on classified government projects. The company, which has a $6.6 billion backlog of orders, been competing with industry giants like Lockheed Martin and Northrop Grumman for federal computer system contracts. Loren Thompson, a military industry analyst with the Lexington Institute in Arlington, Va., said, "General Dynamics, which began as a shipbuilder, is following the rest of the defense industry out of hardware and into the direction of services." General Dynamics, which has annual 2004 revenue of $19.1 billion and 72,000 employees, is the second-largest military shipbuilder after Northrop Grumman. It makes tanks, the armored Stryker troop transport used in Iraq, munitions and gun systems and battlefield radios. But, as Pentagon budgets for military hardware are tightening and more money has been going toward computerized warfare systems, General Dynamics has followed. The company bought the government security and intelligence company Veridian in 2003, and made two other high-tech purchases this year: the Itronix Corporation and Maya Viz. General Dynamics said yesterday that its information systems and technology unit would have $2 billion in sales in the third quarter. The Pentagon "is pushing towards a broader technological capability and this acquisition gets General Dynamics there," said Howard Rubel, an military industry analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company. "Technology is where the world is going and the defense market is saying we need to provide a technological solution. General Dynamics was small in this business and this makes them larger." For Anteon, the takeover will allow it to compete for even bigger federal contracts, said Joseph Kampf, the company's chief executive. Referring to the larger military contractors, Mr. Kampf said that as a result of the deal "we will be able to look those companies in the eye." More Articles in Business &gt;The General Dynamics Corporation, the military contractor, announced yesterday that it would acquire the Anteon International Corporation for $2.1 billion in a move by a company known for its warships and tanks to expand its technology services business. The deal reflects a shift in Pentagon spending and strategy away from heavy military equipment and toward more high-technology weapons and sophisticated electronic systems. The Pentagon recently announced that it wanted to cut $32 billion from coming budgets, and military contractors have responded by investing in the one growth area of the Pentagon budget, intelligence and technology. Under the deal, which is subject to approval by Anteon shareholders and regulators, General Dynamics would pay $55.50 a share and assume $100 million in Anteon debt. The deal was announced just before the market opened yesterday. Anteon shares closed at $40.77 on Tuesday, but yesterday rose 33 percent, to $54.02. Anteon, based in Fairfax, Va., is an information systems and engineering services company. It has forecast revenue in 2006 of $1.7 billion, mainly from Pentagon and Department of Homeland Security contracts. In a conference call with analysts, the chief executive of General Dynamics, Nicholas D. Chabraja, said the merger was a result of on-and-off discussions he had been having with Anteon for several years. General Dynamics was buying Anteon, Mr. Chabraja said, for its highly skilled work force and to enable it to enter new markets. More than 65 percent of Anteon's 9,500 employees have security clearances, which allow them to work on classified government projects. The company, which has a $6.6 billion backlog of orders, been competing with industry giants like Lockheed Martin and Northrop Grumman for federal computer system contracts. Loren Thompson, a military industry analyst with the Lexington Institute in Arlington, Va., said, "General Dynamics, which began as a shipbuilder, is following the rest of the defense industry out of hardware and into the direction of services." General Dynamics, which has annual 2004 revenue of $19.1 billion and 72,000 employees, is the second-largest military shipbuilder after Northrop Grumman. It makes tanks, the armored Stryker troop transport used in Iraq, munitions and gun systems and battlefield radios. But, as Pentagon budgets for military hardware are tightening and more money has been going toward computerized warfare systems, General Dynamics has followed. The company bought the government security and intelligence company Veridian in 2003, and made two other high-tech purchases this year: the Itronix Corporation and Maya Viz. General Dynamics said yesterday that its information systems and technology unit would have $2 billion in sales in the third quarter. The Pentagon "is pushing towards a broader technological capability and this acquisition gets General Dynamics there," said Howard Rubel, an military industry analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company. "Technology is where the world is going and the defense market is saying we need to provide a technological solution. General Dynamics was small in this business and this makes them larger." For Anteon, the takeover will allow it to compete for even bigger federal contracts, said Joseph Kampf, the company's chief executive. Referring to the larger military contractors, Mr. Kampf said that as a result of the deal "we will be able to look those companies in the eye."</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/23/opinion/23sat1.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">The Ship That's Sinking the Navy<date>Published: April 23, 2005</date><text>iven the huge sums the Bush administration has lavished on the military, it is astonishing to learn that the Navy may not be able to buy all the new ships it needs. The Navy has no one to blame but itself, and its appetite for overequipped ships. The most glaring example of that is the DD(X) destroyer program. The DD(X) is a marvel of advanced technology. But its most costly features are not relevant to the battles the Navy is likely to fight, and its outsized price tag of well over $3 billion per ship leaves dangerously little for the aircraft carriers, submarines and fast coastal-combat vessels that will be needed in the years ahead. Advertisement In the post-9/11 world, the Navy must prepare for combat against terrorists who melt in and out of rivers and harbors and ram explosives-packed boats into sitting warships. This will require more light and cheap craft, suitable for fast pursuit and patrol missions, and fewer megaships, designed for traditional warfare. Earlier designs of the DD(X) might have served these needs, had the Navy not insisted on layers of technology that needlessly added to the ship's weight and cost. On average, the Navy can anticipate no more than about $10 billion a year for all of its shipbuilding needs. Much of that needs to go to renewing vital parts of the current fleet as they age. But that money simply won't be there if the Navy persists in spending $3 billion to $4 billion a year, as now planned, on the DD(X). Navy officials are aware of the problem but have not solved it. The only realistic answer is to jettison the DD(X) for a redesigned, more cost-effective large combat ship. Unfortunately, America's military contracting system is biased against such a sensible outcome. Like the other services, the Navy does not know how to say no to impressive technology, whether it's needed and affordable or not. In addition, consolidation in the defense industry has left only two main contractors capable of producing the Navy's ships - Northrop Grumman and General Dynamics - and they apportion the business between them. This absence of real competition significantly inflates costs, as does Congress's insistence on parceling out the work to as many of the six remaining major naval shipyards as possible. Lawmakers who represent these shipyards and their many subcontractors around the country constitute powerful Congressional constituencies for building prestigious but expensive ships that actually diminish national security by starving more vital programs. Nobody likes to see the shipbuilding jobs generated by the DD(X) put at risk. But weakening the Navy's future fighting strength is too high a price to pay for insulating a few thousand workers from the harsh realities of economic life.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/21/business/businessspecial3/21defense.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">3 Big Manufacturers Report Gains in Quarterly Earnings<date>Published: April 21, 2005</date><text>y Bloomberg News The United Technologies Corporation, Honeywell International Inc. and the General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that first-quarter earnings rose. United Technologies, which makes Sikorsky helicopters and Carrier air-conditioners, said first-quarter net income climbed 18 percent, to $651 million, or $1.28 a share, from $551 million, or $1.08, a year earlier. Sales increased 8.8 percent, to $9.41 billion. Advertisement The earnings beat analysts' expectations by 3 cents a share. The Otis elevator unit benefited from rising orders in Asia, while more airline travel helped Pratt &amp; Whitney sell spare parts for engines. Profit this year will climb to $5.90 to $6.15 a share, from $5.29 in 2004, George David, the chief executive, said. The previous forecast, given March 16, was $5.85 to $6.10. Mr. David also raised the revenue forecast to $43 billion from $41 billion to include the purchase of Kidde. Profit at Carrier, United Technologies' biggest business, more than doubled as sales rose 21 percent, to $2.71 billion. Profit at Otis jumped 40 percent on a 10 percent sales increase, while Pratt's profit soared 65 percent as sales rose 3.8 percent. At Honeywell, net income rose 22 percent, to $359 million, or 42 cents a share, up from $295 million, or 34 cents, a year ago. Sales were up 4.5 percent, to $6.45 billion. Analysts had expected profit of 40 cents a share. Sales increased 9 percent at the aerospace unit, the largest of the company's four main businesses, on orders from customers like Singapore Airlines and the United States Air Force. Operating profit rose by 15 percent as a result of reduced costs, while pension expenses declined 17 percent. Honeywell expects second-quarter profit of 49 cents to 51 cents a share. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call expect 50 cents. General Dynamics, which makes Gulfstream business jets, said quarterly profit rose 25 percent on higher sales of aircraft and a tax benefit. Net income increased to $336 million, or $1.66 a share, from $269 million, or $1.34, in the period a year earlier. General Dynamics' sales rose 3.7 percent, to $4.82 billion, the smallest increase in more than four years and less than analysts expected. Sales and profit rose at the business jet unit as corporations bought more planes. Resolution of a tax audit resulted in a tax that was $63 million less than the $132 million set aside a year earlier. Without that, the company would have missed its forecast, mainly because of rising costs for a commercial oil tanker program, said Eric Hugel, an analyst with Stephens Inc. in New York. "It looked like a pretty weak quarter," said Mr. Hugel, who rates the shares equal weight and does not own them. Other than the tax benefit, "they were pretty light, with weaker margins in the marine unit and combat systems." "People were looking for increasing sales and margins in combat systems and it's not clear why that didn't happen." General Dynamics was expected to earn $1.53 a share, the average estimate of 17 analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/19/business/19navy.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Navy of Tomorrow, Mired in Yesterday's Politics<date>Published: April 19, 2005</date><text>he Navy's new destroyer, the DD(X), is becoming so expensive that it may end up destroying itself. The Navy once wanted 24 of them. Now it thinks it can afford 5 - if that. The price of the Navy's new ships, driven upward by old-school politics and the rusty machinery of American shipbuilding, may scuttle the Pentagon's plans for a 21st-century armada of high-technology aircraft carriers, destroyers and submarines. Shipbuilding costs "have spiraled out of control," the Navy's top admiral, Vern Clark, told Congress last week, rising so high that "we can't build the Navy that we believe that we need in the 21st century." The first two DD(X)'s are now supposed to total $6.3 billion, according to confidential budget documents, up $1.5 billion. A new aircraft carrier, the CVN-21, is estimated at $13.7 billion, up $2 billion. The new Virginia-class submarine now costs $2.5 billion each, up $400 million. All these increases have materialized in the last six months. The Navy says it can make do with fewer big ships patrolling the oceans. It wants more fast boats and aircraft to fight offshore and upriver, a speedier force to counter terror. But Congress, seeking to sustain America's shipyards, wants as many big ships as possible. Admiral Clark, who plans to retire later this year, says both strategies could be sunk by soaring costs. Philip A. Dur, president of Northrop Grumman Ship Systems, the company primarily in charge of building the first DD(X) destroyer, defends the effort. "No question, the cost of the ship is an issue," Mr. Dur said, though its costs would be justified by state-of-the-art weaponry. Its sophisticated systems would require crews of as few as 125, one-third the size of today's destroyers, and stealth technology would make the 14,000-ton ship appear no larger than a fishing boat on an enemy's radar. But the $3.3 billion to build the first ship "is a big number," he said. The number became big, fast, because it was kept small at first. John J. Young Jr., the assistant Navy secretary in charge of buying new weapons, said that until recently Navy officials had knowingly "underestimated the price" of the DD(X) destroyer program. "There's a motivation in this building to birth programs," he said, referring to Pentagon proposals to create big new weapons systems. "People tend to understate their costs." Political haggling may also add to the price. The Navy wants a winner-take-all competition to build the destroyers. But Congress wants to give one to Northrop Grumman's shipyard in Mississippi, the next to General Dynamics' yard in Maine, to share the wealth and ensure more money for the yards. The dispute drags on. The Navy says the two-shipyard approach will add $300 million or more to the cost of each DD(X). The Navy now hopes to build five DD(X) destroyers, one a year, at a total cost of $20.6 billion, including research and development. But those plans are shaky. "There is doubt right now among people in the Navy and industry about whether a significant number of DD(X) will be procured," said Ronald O'Rourke, a Congressional Research Service analyst, who obtained the previously undisclosed cost figures for the new destroyers from the Navy. Unless the costs are controlled, some in the Navy and the shipbuilding industry say, the better alternative may be to finish none of them and skip to the next-generation destroyer. "The bottom line," Admiral Clark told lawmakers, "is you can't have the Navy of your dreams with the mechanisms that we're using." Military shipbuilding is a closed mechanism run by two contractors, Northrop Grumman and General Dynamics. Only they can produce the ships the Navy needs. Mr. Dur of Northrop Grumman calls military shipbuilding "a unique economy." Unique it is. Between them, the two contracting giants own the six remaining yards that can build American warships, in Maine, Connecticut, Virginia, Mississippi, Louisiana and California. They receive unstinting support from members of Congress representing those states; in turn, the contractors support thousands of smaller suppliers that are often the sole sources for what they make. Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/10/technology/circuits/10soon.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">When the Outlet's Out, a Way to Recharge Ravenous Devices<date>Published: March 10, 2005</date><text>uel cells, once the size of refrigerators and used for powering spaceships and submarines, have long been considered ripe for a radical retooling for earthbound applications, like powering cellphones and digital cameras. But until now, their flammable fuel and large size stymied developers. Next week Medis Technologies (medistechnologies.com), a company based in Manhattan, is scheduled to announce the creation of an inexpensive fuel cell for commercial use. The Medis Power Pack, which is about the size of a pager, will be a disposable power source designed to recharge common electronic devices like cellphones, iPods and personal organizers, said Robert K. Lifton, chief executive of Medis. "Our focus is providing power when the wall is not at hand, which in the wireless age is an ever-increasing experience," he said, emphasizing that the company's fuel cells are not intended to replace conventional batteries. Based on technology developed in Israel, the Power Pack uses a proprietary mix of sodium borohydride, alcohol, water and alkaline that Mr. Lifton says is harmless. The fuel is released into the cell by a built-in pump, giving the power pack enough juice to charge devices as if they were plugged into an outlet, he said. The Power Pack, expected to cost $12 to $20, should be ready for release early next year, Mr. Lifton said. Military versions of the fuel cells are being field tested by General Dynamics, which reports that results have been encouraging.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/19/business/19nuns.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Shareholders Who Answer to a Higher C.E.O.<date>Published: February 19, 2005</date><text>ecades ago, during a different war, many churches were at the forefront of antiwar efforts, whether it was the high-profile activism of the Berrigan brothers, the two Roman Catholic priests who splattered blood on draft records, or mainstream churches marching against nuclear weapons. While most of that activism has faded, a band of Catholic nuns has remained true to the cause of peace - though today's activism takes them to corporate boardrooms and shareholders' meetings. At the moment, nuns from dozens of orders are completing a series of resolutions to be introduced at shareholder meetings this spring. Companies like Lockheed Martin, General Dynamics or Raytheon are not about to lay down their arms, of course. But military companies, faced with the persistent nuns on their doorsteps, have begun to meet with them, and, in some cases, have begun to see their business in different ways. "We are raising questions that no one asks but us," said Valerie Heinonen, a Catholic nun and consultant on social responsibility in New York. "Part of what we are doing is planting seeds. These companies have an overwhelming influence wherever they operate, and I don't think religious bodies should be separate from that." The shareholder proposals to be offered by the nuns would make any military executive squirm. At the top of their agenda is limiting military sales in countries where the arms can fall into the hands of child soldiers or perpetuate long-running wars. The nuns are also promoting a code of conduct that holds arms makers accountable for the effect of their business on the environment, and on the political and social stability of countries where they operate. Raytheon is one company that has met with the nuns. In Boston last November a delegation of nuns talked to six Raytheon executives, including the director of the company's ethics and environmental division, several lawyers and other executives. The topic was the code of conduct proposal. Discussions between the nuns and the company are continuing, more recently by phone. "We didn't always agree, although it was all respectful," said Jack Kapples, Raytheon's corporate secretary, who attended the meeting. "The nuns had a lot of questions about our business, and there were a couple of questions that our guys thought were interesting. There were questions that led us to think that we hadn't looked at things that way." Sister Mary Ellen Gondeck of the Sisters of St. Joseph of Nazareth in suburban Detroit was at the Raytheon meeting, along with representatives of about half a dozen orders. "If we can dialogue seriously with these companies, that's part of the success," said Sister Mary Ellen, who is the coordinator of the office of peace and justice for her order. "If they are willing to talk to us on our issue, surely we are working toward something." To the nuns, success is measured in small ways - a new willingness of corporate executives to meet with them and a greater backing for the shareholder resolutions they submit each year. Dozens of religious groups, mainly Catholic orders but also some Protestant churches, have submitted shareholder resolutions to the Securities and Exchange Commission that will be put on the ballot of seven military companies this spring. Last year, shareholder proposals from religious orders gained 11 percent of the vote at Textron, nearly 9 percent at Raytheon and 5 percent at General Dynamics. Religious groups say this compares with 2 percent to 3 percent of the vote in years past. Moreover, this vote has come about without any shareholder solicitations or other politicking by the nuns or anyone else. The only way the nuns promote their ideas is when they speak on behalf of their proposals at annual shareholder meetings. "Our resolutions don't win or lose, although that's how a lot of people like to put the spin on it," said Gary Brouse, a program director at the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, a New York-based nonprofit group that promotes corporate social responsibility. "We are trying to illuminate these issues for other people and educate shareholders to these issues." Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DF1E3EF932A35751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; L-3 WILL BUY UNIT FROM GENERAL DYNAMICS FOR $185 MILLION<date>Published: December 1, 2004</date><text>L-3 Communications Holdings, a maker of bomb detectors and military electronics, agreed to buy the propulsion systems unit of the General Dynamics Corporation for $185 million to increase military sales. The acquisition -- expected to be completed in the first quarter of 2005 -- will contribute about $155 million to sales next year and add to earnings, L-3 said. The propulsion-systems unit designs and manufactures engines, transmissions and other parts for combat vehicles. The chief executive of General Dynamics, Nicholas D. Chabraja, told an investor conference in September that the company might sell businesses with as much as $500 million in revenue this year to dispose of unwanted portions of acquisitions. General Dynamics is based in Muskegon, Mich. L-3 is based in New York.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/19/business/19corptax.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">2 Shipbuilders Get Big Breaks in New Corporate Tax Bill<date>Published: October 19, 2004</date><text>For the Record WASHINGTON, Oct. 18 - A little-noticed provision in the sweeping corporate tax bill that passed Congress last week would reduce taxes at two major military contractors by nearly $500 million over the next 10 years. The provision, which primarily benefits General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman, would allow shipbuilders to postpone their taxes for years on profits from building ships and submarines for the Navy. Advertisement The new provision would benefit a handful of major shipyards, all owned by one of the two military conglomerates. They include the Bath Iron Works in Maine acquired by General Dynamics in 1995 and the company's Electric Boat division in Groton, Conn., as well as the Northrop-owned Newport News shipyard in Virginia. The new tax break would reverse a rule that Congress imposed as part of the sweeping tax overhaul of 1986, when lawmakers in both parties were incensed that major military companies often paid no income taxes despite earning billions of dollars providing major weapons systems to the military. Under the bill, Navy shipbuilders would be allowed to once again defer paying most federal income taxes on a project until the contract was completed. Because it takes about five years to build an aircraft carrier and three years to build a destroyer, the shipyards would be able to delay their tax bills for years, allowing more opportunity to offset taxes against future losses. The measure's primary sponsor was Senator Olympia J. Snowe, Republican of Maine, who said she was determined to protect Bath Iron Works, one of her state's largest employers. "This provision takes dramatic steps to remedy the inequity of how naval shipbuilders pay their taxes," Ms. Snowe said in a statement last week, just after House and Senate negotiators agreed to include the provision in a broader bill that would shower $140 billion in tax cuts across almost every segment of industry. But critics said the provision would not create jobs, the stated intention of the tax bill, because employment at naval shipyards is determined almost entirely by federal spending on ships and submarines rather than by tax incentives. "We're not going to buy any more war boats if we give them a tax incentive," said Robert S. McIntyre, director of Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal research group here that has long scrutinized corporate tax practices. "We're going to buy more boats if the government decides we need more boats." The shipbuilders' tax cut was typical of the furious scramble by lawmakers to include special provisions for their constituents in the bill. The final bill, which President Bush is expected to sign soon, includes tax breaks for oil companies, corn farmers, wine distributors and dozens of other highly specific industries. General Dynamics and Northrop Grumman, which will also benefit from many of the new bill's general tax cuts, are heavy contributors to political campaigns. Since January 2003, General Dynamics' employees and political action committees have contributed $1.3 million, about 64 percent to Republicans. Northrop contributed $1.24 million, about 58 percent to Republicans. Senator Snowe was among dozens of lawmakers whose support was needed to win final passage. She was also part of a bipartisan group that tried to tie a $10 billion buyout program for tobacco farmers, which is also part of the bill, to a new requirement that would allow the Food and Drug Administration to regulate cigarettes and other tobacco products. House Republicans rejected that provision, but Ms. Snowe voted for the overall bill in part because it included the shipbuilding tax break that she had proposed. She was hardly alone. Senator John Breaux, Democrat of Louisiana, opposed many parts of the overall bill but supported the shipbuilding tax break and numerous other tax cuts for oil companies that are big employers in his state. Few if any lawmakers publicly objected to the shipbuilding provision, which was tiny in comparison with sweeping tax cuts, worth $42 billion over 10 years, on foreign profits of American multinationals. The House and Senate passed the overall bill by overwhelming majorities. Under current law, shipbuilders have to pay income taxes on long-term Navy contracts based on the percentage of work they have finished. When that requirement was imposed in 1986, lawmakers were furious that top military contractors were deferring almost all of their taxes, even though they were getting progress payments throughout the term of their contracts. According to Mr. McIntyre, the top 12 Pentagon suppliers paid an effective tax rate of only 6.3 percent in the early 1980's, and some companies often paid none. Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DD1E30F936A2575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; TWO CONTRACTORS TO WORK ON ARMY PROGRAM<date>Published: September 15, 2004</date><text>General Dynamics and Lockheed Martin will stop competing on a program and instead work together on the $12 billion effort to design a communications network for the Army. The program, the Warfighter Information Network-Tactical, will link commanders at the Pentagon to troops in the field. Under the arrangement, General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., will lead the team and Lockheed, based in Bethesda, Md., will be the ''major subcontractor'' responsible for about 50 percent of the work, the Army and General Dynamics said yesterday.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/22/business/company-news-acquisitions-bolster-general-dynamics-profit.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Acquisitions Bolster General Dynamics Profit<date>Published: July 22, 2004</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the largest maker of armored vehicles for the Army, said yesterday that second-quarter earnings rose 24 percent, as acquisitions lifted sales and margins from business jets improved. The company, based in Falls Church, Va., also raised its 2004 forecast. Net income in the quarter climbed to $300 million, or $1.49 a share, compared with $242 million, or $1.22 a share, a year earlier, General Dynamics said. Sales increased 21 percent, to $4.76 billion from $3.94 billion. The company's information systems and technology unit, its largest, bolstered profit by 38 percent, as sales grew after the purchase in August of the sensor maker Veridian. General Dynamics had been expected to earn $1.40 a share, according to a survey by Thomson First Call.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/19/business/company-news-general-dynamics-will-hire-210-for-marine-corps-project.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS WILL HIRE 210 FOR MARINE CORPS PROJECT<date>Published: June 19, 2004</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said it would hire 210 workers at a plant in Lima, Ohio, to produce a new amphibious vehicle for the United States Marine Corps. The United States will invest $88 million to expand the plant, which is owned by the government but run by General Dynamics, to make the Expeditionary Fighting Vehicle, the company said. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., began developing the vehicles in June 1996 under a $200 million award. In July 2001 it got a $712 million contract to make and test nine prototypes. The program calls for the delivery of more than 1,000 vehicles, with production beginning in 2005 and continuing into 2018, the company said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/04/business/world-business-briefing-europe-britain-tank-builder-acquisition.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">World Business Briefing | Europe: Britain: Tank Builder Acquisition<date>Published: June 04, 2004</date><text>The European military contractor BAE Systems agreed to buy Alvis, maker of the Challenger II battle tank, for Â£355 million ($652 million), topping an offer from General Dynamics. BAE, based in London, offered 320 pence for each Alvis share, the companies said. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., bid Â£309 million, or 280 pence a share, for Alvis in March. BAE already owns 29 percent of Alvis, which makes all-terrain Viking and scouting vehicles.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/29/us/with-2-wars-us-need-of-munitions-is-soaring.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">With 2 Wars, U.S. Need Of Munitions Is Soaring<date>Published: May 29, 2004</date><text>With the United States fighting protracted wars in both Iraq and Afghanistan, its military faces a shortage of a basic necessity: ammunition.The Army Field Support Command in Rock Island, Ill., held an ''industry day'' last week to inform contractors of a vast increase in demand for small-caliber rounds, those for rifles and machine guns.Maj. Gary Tallman, an Army spokesman, said the armed services needed 300 million to 500 million rounds this year alone, beyond the 1.2 billion already being produced, to provide enough for a military whose active-duty force had increased because of the two wars.All production currently comes from a factory in Lake City, Mo., that is owned by the Army and managed by Alliant Techsystems, the nation's largest provider of munitions to the military. Alliant says it can expand that production, but it is not sure by how much.In the meantime, the Army has already arranged for two contractors -- Winchester, a division of the Olin Corporation, and the state-owned Israel Military Industries Ltd. -- to provide an additional supply this year.Further, in response to the Army's search for a ''systems integrator'' -- a general contractor -- to supplement its work, at least one military contractor, the General Dynamics Corporation, has proposed overseeing a consortium of small-caliber-ammunition producers to fit the service's needs. A formal request for bids from prospective general contractors is expected in August.Major Tallman, the Army spokesman, said the need for more ammunition had not affected troops fighting in Iraq and Afghanistan but instead stemmed primarily from an increase in necessary training.But Loren B. Thompson, a military analyst with the Lexington Institute, a policy research center in Arlington, Va., said the shortage was due not just to training.''The Army is reaching the outer limits of its ability to sustain the Iraqi operation,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''It simply can't sustain a large-scale protracted conflict.''Mr. Thompson said that while combat troops were not currently affected by the ammunition shortage, ''there could be serious shortfalls'' should a conflict arise on the Korean Peninsula, for example.Dan Carlson of the Army Field Support Command said the military ran no risk of being depleted. ''We're not going to let anybody run out of ammunition,'' he said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/22/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-hire-325-engineers-in-michigan.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO HIRE 325 ENGINEERS IN MICHIGAN<date>Published: May 22, 2004</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that it would hire 325 engineers in Michigan to do research for the Army's Future Combat Systems program of satellite-linked tanks and troops. The company will begin adding workers to its operations in Sterling Heights in August, a spokesman, Peter Keating, said. About $6.6 million will be invested in the expansion, he said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/19/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-maker-of-satellite-parts.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY MAKER OF SATELLITE PARTS<date>Published: March 19, 2004</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Spectrum Astro Inc., a closely held maker of satellite components, to gain business in missile defense and space technology. Terms were not disclosed. The purchase is expected to close in 60 days, General Dynamics said. Spectrum Astro, based in Gilbert, Ariz., sells equipment to the federal government and commercial customers and has 520 employees and an average annual sales growth rate of more than 46 percent, it said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/12/business/company-news-general-dynamics-is-buying-alvis-of-britain.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS IS BUYING ALVIS OF BRITAIN<date>Published: March 12, 2004</date><text>General Dynamics said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Alvis, the maker of the Challenger II battle tank, for Â£309 million ($556 million). General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., is offering 280 pence a share for Alvis, 33 percent more than the closing price on Wednesday. Alvis, based in London, will recommend the offer to shareholders, the chief executive, Nicholas Prest, said. Alvis, 29 percent owned by BAE Systems, also makes all-terrain mine-clearing and scouting vehicles. After the acquisition, General Dynamics, builder of the Abrams battle tank, expects to win combat vehicle orders from the United States, Britain and possibly Sweden. Alvis's shares rose 41 percent, to 296 pence.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/25/us/supreme-court-roundup-prosecutorial-misconduct-leads-justices-overturn-death.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Supreme Court Roundup; Prosecutorial Misconduct Leads Justices to Overturn Death Sentence in Texas<date>Published: February 25, 2004</date><text>The Supreme Court overturned a Texas inmate's death sentence on Tuesday on the ground that the prosecution deliberately withheld evidence that would have made jurors less likely to impose the death penalty had they been made aware of it.In a 7-to-2 decision, the court said that the undisclosed evidence would have allowed the defendant, Delma Banks, to discredit two of the state's most important witnesses. It would thus have allowed him to cast doubt on the prosecution's claim, essential for a death penalty under Texas law at the time, that he would pose a continuing danger to society if not executed.In her majority opinion, Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg directly rebuked the Texas prosecutors for concealing facts they had a legal obligation to disclose and for permitting the state's witnesses to testify untruthfully. Just as forcefully, if implicitly, the majority also rebuked the federal appeals court that in rejecting Mr. Banks's appeal in August 2002 blamed him for having failed earlier to uncover the evidence that the state had withheld.The justices have expressed increasing concern that the lower federal courts are too cursory in reviewing death row appeals. For example, almost exactly a year ago the court voted 8 to 1 to order a new hearing for another Texas death row inmate, Thomas Miller-El. Writing for the majority then, Justice Anthony M. Kennedy said that while Congress had recently instructed the federal courts to accord greater deference to state court decisions, ''deference does not imply abandonment or abdication of judicial review.''Mr. Banks, who was convicted in 1980 of killing a 16-year-old co-worker at a Texarkana steak house to steal his car, came within 10 minutes of execution last March before the Supreme Court granted a stay and agreed to hear his appeal.In 2000, a federal district judge in Texarkana granted Mr. Banks a writ of habeas corpus, but the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit overturned it, in part on the ground that Mr. Banks should have discovered the withheld evidence earlier and presented it to the Texas state courts.On Tuesday, noting that the prosecutors had asserted both at trial and in state court appeals that the state had given the defense all the evidence to which it was legally entitled, Justice Ginsburg called it ''appropriate for Banks to assume that his prosecutors would not stoop to improper litigation conduct to advance prospects for gaining a conviction.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/13/us/justices-mull-twist-in-law-on-age-bias.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Justices Mull Twist in Law On Age Bias<date>Published: November 13, 2003</date><text>When Congress made it illegal 36 years ago for employers to discriminate on the basis of age, it was clear that older workers were protected from discriminatory treatment that favored those who were younger. The question in a Supreme Court argument on Wednesday was whether the Age Discrimination in Employment Act also meant the reverse: if Congress in addition meant to prohibit policies that favor older workers over younger ones.The plain language of the statute suggests one interpretation, while the context in which the law was enacted in 1967 suggests the opposite. An employer shall not discriminate against someone ''because of such individual's age,'' the law reads, without specifying ''older age'' or ''younger age.'' The law's protection begins at age 40 and has no upper limit.''The real issue here is whether this court should add an additional element'' and treat the law as if it read ''because of their older age,'' Mark W. Biggerman, a lawyer for a group of younger workers at General Dynamics plants in Ohio and Pennsylvania, told the court. He urged the court to avoid a judicial rewriting of the statute. ''Congress's goal here was to make age a neutral factor in employment,'' Mr. Biggerman said.In 1997, General Dynamics negotiated an agreement with the United Automobile Workers eliminating medical benefits that current employees would have received in retirement. The agreement allowed an exception, though, for employees who turned 50 by July 1 of that year. Some 200 workers between the ages of 40 and 50 filed suit on the ground that the new plan, which they were too young to benefit from, discriminated against them because of age.The Federal District Court in Cleveland dismissed the suit, but the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, in Cincinnati, reinstated it on the ground that the law's protection ran in both directions. The Sixth Circuit was the first appeals court to interpret the law to permit a lawsuit of this kind.The company appealed to the Supreme Court, warning that the consequences of this new interpretation would prove highly unsettling to management and labor alike. Indeed, General Dynamics came to the court with the support of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. and several individual labor unions, as well as the United States Chamber of Commerce and other groups representing management.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/17/business/company-news-quarterly-earnings-fall-8-percent-at-general-dynamics.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; QUARTERLY EARNINGS FALL 8 PERCENT AT GENERAL DYNAMICS<date>Published: July 17, 2003</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that its earnings fell about 8 percent in the first quarter as sales in its aerospace division continued to lag. Net income for the military contractor and arms manufacturer totaled $242 million, or $1.22 a share, compared with $263 million, or $1.29 a share, in the same quarter last year. Shares of General Dynamics rose $3.49, to $77.49.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/10/business/company-news-general-dynamics-agrees-to-buy-veridian.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS AGREES TO BUY VERIDIAN<date>Published: June 10, 2003</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation plans to purchase the military contractor Veridian Corporation for $1.23 billion. The deal calls for General Dynamics to assume $270 million in debt. Veridian, which expects sales of $1.2 billion in 2003, draws 85 percent of its revenue from contracts with the Pentagon and intelligence agencies. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., will pay $35 for each share of Veridian's stock, a 28 percent premium over Friday's closing price. Veridian, based in Arlington, Va., was privately held for more than 50 years before going public in June 2002.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/22/business/so-much-for-the-plan-to-scrap-old-weapons.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">So Much for the Plan To Scrap Old Weapons<date>Published: December 22, 2002</date><text>OVER the past year, even as he hunted down terrorists, oversaw lingering operations in Afghanistan and made plans for a possible invasion of Iraq, Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld was also waging a battle much closer to home. On that front, pitted against American military contractors, he has more than met his match.This week, Mr. Rumsfeld will deliver to President Bush a $378 billion military budget that had been trumpeted as a new strategic vision -- one that was to have shaken the relics of cold-war weapons systems from the national arsenal and replaced them with new, lighter and more lethal fighting forces.Yet it now appears that the military contractors, united with allies in the Pentagon and Congress in a group known around Washington as the Iron Triangle, stood up to Mr. Rumsfeld -- and won. Weapons systems that had been on the chopping block have been saved, and others that many critics say should be consigned to the dustbin of history are about to receive millions, and in some cases billions, of taxpayers' dollars.''As far as the sweeping, let's-turn-the-place-inside-out changes that were being proposed, that's just not going to happen,'' said Byron K. Callan, a military industry analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''The most interesting thing about this administration and Pentagon is that there has been a lot of talk, but action only at the margin.''For two years now, the administration has wanted to make good on Mr. Bush's campaign promise to modernize the military, even if it meant skipping a generation of weapons in the works. Despite the attention the military receives for its high-technology weaponry, billions of dollars still flow into weapons systems designed to fight the battles of yesterday -- fighter jets built for aerial battles with the Soviets, warships designed for battles in the open seas.For companies like Lockheed Martin, Boeing, Northrop Grumman, General Dynamics and dozens of others, hundreds of millions of dollars were on the line every time Mr. Bush talked about modernization. He gave two major speeches on the subject at the Citadel, one as a candidate and one last year. His pronouncements were repeated even more forcefully by Mr. Rumsfeld, who, known for tough decisions, looked as if he could turn the tough talk into action.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/20/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-pay-1.1-billion-for-gm-unit.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO PAY $1.1 BILLION FOR G.M. UNIT<date>Published: December 20, 2002</date><text>The military contractor General Dynamics said yesterday that it would buy a military unit from General Motors for $1.1 billion, making it the leading maker of combat vehicles. The deal follows a recent Pentagon decision to include $1.5 billion in its 2004 budget for a fourth brigade of Stryker combat vehicles, which are being made by a joint venture of General Dynamics and the G.M. unit, G.M. Defense. The G.M. unit expects $950 million in revenue in 2002 and has an order backlog of more than $1.5 billion. General Dynamics, also a leading maker of combat ships and information systems, said it expected the deal to close in the first quarter of 2003.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/04/business/pentagon-to-dock-contractors-pay.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Pentagon to Dock Contractors' Pay<date>Published: December 04, 2002</date><text>The Pentagon said today that it would begin collecting $2.3 billion from General Dynamics and Boeing for what the government considers a debt owed on a canceled A-12 stealth aircraft project 11 years ago.Instead of asking the companies to turn over the $2.3 billion, the Pentagon will withhold about $128 million a month for 18 months on other government contracts of the companies.General Dynamics said it intended to ask a federal judge to block the deductions from the payments.''The Defense Department's entitlement to any payment in the A-12 matter is central to the issues that court is already scheduled to hear on Jan. 9, 2003,'' the company said.The A-12 was to be built for the Navy, but Dick Cheney, then secretary of defense, canceled the project in 1991, citing cost overruns and delays. The contractors and the Pentagon have been in court ever since.A Pentagon statement said the decision to start collecting was made because there was no sign that the case would be resolved soon.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/04/business/company-news-boeing-and-general-dynamics-face-navy-deadline.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; BOEING AND GENERAL DYNAMICS FACE NAVY DEADLINE<date>Published: September 04, 2002</date><text>The Navy yesterday gave General Dynamics and Boeing a deadline of Sept. 30 to return to the Treasury $2.3 billion paid during development of a fighter aircraft that was canceled. Dick Cheney, who was defense secretary at the time, canceled the A-12 program in January 1991. General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas sued, causing the largest military contract dispute ever. A federal court ruled against the companies in August 2001; talks have continued since with another session scheduled tomorrow. General Dynamics called the Navy's demand ''an unseemly negotiating tactic and an apparent effort to gain advantage during settlement talks'' and said the company would ask a federal appeals court to delay the collection if negotiations failed.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/27/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-sell-spacecraft-propulsion-unit.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO SELL SPACECRAFT-PROPULSION UNIT<date>Published: August 27, 2002</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the fifth-largest military contractor, agreed to sell its spacecraft-propulsion and fire-suppression businesses to GenCorp for about $90 million to focus on its main military businesses. The transaction, which will double the size of GenCorp's Aerojet-General unit, is expected to close in the fourth quarter, it said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/03/business/company-news-general-dynamics-agrees-to-buy-advanced-technical.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS AGREES TO BUY ADVANCED TECHNICAL<date>Published: May 03, 2002</date><text>General Dynamics, the military contractor, said yesterday that it was buying Advanced Technical Products, a maker of aircraft parts and chemical detection systems, for about $197 million. General Dynamics is also assuming debt of $36.2 million. General Dynamics said the deal, which is to be completed in two months, would immediately increase its earnings. General Dynamics is paying $33.50 for each share of Advanced Technical stock, which closed at $28.53 a share Wednesday on Nasdaq.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/20/business/internal-security-is-attracting-a-crowd-of-arms-contractors.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Internal Security Is Attracting a Crowd Of Arms Contractors<date>Published: March 20, 2002</date><text>Edmund B. Woollen, a vice president for integrated information systems at Raytheon, had just started a meeting in his office in northern Virginia when he heard a thunderous explosion and looked up to see the Pentagon burning. The date was Sept. 11.Mr. Woollen, a Vietnam veteran, quickly realized that the attacks that day did more than murder thousands of people, destroy the World Trade Center and damage the Pentagon. Shattered, too, was the assumption that the United States had to prepare for wars only on foreign soil. Now it also needed to protect against terrorist attacks at home.The next day, Raytheon's chairman, Daniel P. Burnham, asked Mr. Woollen to lead a team to prepare for the new security demands, and market possibilities, after the attacks of Sept. 11.''Neither of us doubted that this would change what we've done for the past 30 or 40 years,'' Mr. Woollen recalled.The entire arms industry seems to agree. Since Sept. 11, virtually every major military contractor has assigned senior executives to help reshape its marketing strategies, repackage its products and reorganize its bureaucracy to compete in the fast-growing business of domestic security.Wall Street analysts are less enthusiastic, noting that military contractors are accustomed to dealing with a well-defined budget being spent by a familiar and centralized bureaucracy at the Pentagon. Domestic security, by contrast, is divvied among many departments -- Justice, Interior, Treasury and Transportation, as well as Defense -- and the spending plan is not clear.Still, arms makers assume that the rapid build-up in spending on domestic defense -- President Bush has proposed that the federal government spend $37.7 billion next year, almost twice the $19.5 billion budgeted for this year -- will include opportunities too lucrative to ignore.Boeing, for example, is studying whether sensors designed to track enemy missiles could be used to identify hijacked airliners. Lockheed Martin is trying to adapt military simulators to train local emergency-response teams. General Dynamics hopes to sell armored personnel vehicles to police departments. And Northrop Grumman thinks its communications systems could help health authorities deal with bioterrorism threats.''A lot of the technologies that we developed for one purpose can be adapted to do other things,'' said Tom Davis, Northrop Grumman's corporate coordinator for homeland security. ''You've got a new mission that's emerging here.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/27/business/company-news-general-dynamics-ends-newport-news-merger-deal.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS ENDS NEWPORT NEWS MERGER DEAL<date>Published: October 27, 2001</date><text>General Dynamics officially canceled its $2.1 billion merger agreement with Newport News Shipbuilding yesterday, three days after the Justice Department sued to block the acquisition. Federal regulators stepped in because of concerns that General Dynamics would hold a monopoly on the construction of nuclear submarines. Norine Lyons, a spokeswoman for General Dynamics, which is based in Falls Church, Va., said that the company would not take legal or other steps to pursue the merger.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/24/business/us-moves-to-block-general-dynamics-bid-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">U.S. Moves to Block General Dynamics Bid for Shipbuilder<date>Published: October 24, 2001</date><text>The government moved yesterday to block the General Dynamics Corporation's $2.1 billion offer to acquire Newport News Shipbuilding, effectively endorsing a competing bid by Northrop Grumman. The action came in two steps -- a finding by the Pentagon that the General Dynamics bid would reduce competition in the construction of nuclear submarines and other military vessels, followed by an announcement that the Justice Department had filed an antitrust suit to block the deal. Vigorously contesting the General Dynamics offer, Northrop argued that the Pentagon would effectively be creating a monopoly if it allowed General Dynamics and Newport News to combine. The Navy, which considered and rejected competing bids for Newport News from General Dynamics and Litton Industries in 1999, has wanted to cut costs in its nuclear submarine program. Since 1997, Newport News and General Dynamics have evenly split the work on submarines. But competitive concerns turned out to be decisive. ''Either transaction would have reduced costs,'' a Pentagon spokesman, Glenn Flood, said. ''But in addition to cutting costs, General Dynamics would become a monopoly, hurting competition for not only nuclear submarines but also surface ships. We believe Northrop Grumman will preserve competition in the submarine building business.'' Northrop, mainly an aerospace company, gained shipbuilding expertise earlier this year with its purchase of Litton for $3.8 billion. The company, based in Los Angeles, said it was pleased with the Defense Department's decision. In a statement, it said it ''does not expect any issues with the Department of Justice on the closure of the acquisition.'' Executives of General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., declined to comment yesterday. In the past, the company has said that a Northrop-Newport News combination would have a virtual monopoly in the construction of aircraft carriers and other ships. Officials of Newport News Shipbuilding merely noted that any deal with Northrop would require its directors' approval. When it made its competing offer in May, Northrop Grumman offered to match General Dynamics' all-cash bid with a stock-and-cash offer that at the time was also worth $2.1 billion. Gains in Northrop Grumman's stock price since the attacks on Sept. 11 raised the value of its bid to the point that Newport News Shipbuilding three weeks ago opened talks about a possible deal. Northrop Grumman shares were trading for $91.50 when the company made its bid in May. Yesterday, they closed at $100, down $5.50; the announcements in Washington came after the close of trading. Analysts were divided about what effect, if any, last month's attacks had on the debate within the Pentagon about the two merger proposals. Byron K. Callan, an armaments industry analyst at Merrill Lynch, said: ''If Sept. 11 meant higher defense spending and more money for Navy ship construction programs, there was more room for competition and not just cost savings. The broader signal being sent is that competition is good, and monopoly is not good.'' Jacques Gansler, a former defense under secretary for acquisition, technology and logistics, said events flowing from the terrorist attacks probably had a limited effect on the Navy's thinking. ''The one thing you want to get is innovation and low cost and you need competition to do that,'' said Mr. Gansler, now a professor at the University of Maryland's School of Public Affairs. ''The Navy strongly argued for shorter-term cost savings. But I am sure the Justice Department had a pretty strong bias for maintaining competition.'' The Pentagon's decision to thwart the General Dynamics bid is a triumph for the Senate Republican leader, Trent Lott of Mississippi. Mr. Lott, whose state's largest employer is Litton Industries, invested considerable time and energy arguing that a General Dynamics-Newport News merger would be anticompetitive. General Dynamics shares closed at $81.76 yesterday, down $3.04. Newport News Shipbuilding fell 73 cents, to $69.11.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/23/business/company-news-general-dynamics-extends-bid-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS EXTENDS BID FOR SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: October 23, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, vying with the Northrop Grumman Corporation to buy Newport News Shipbuilding Inc., said yesterday that it had extended its tender offer for Newport's shares. General Dynamics said more than 12.7 million shares had been tendered as of Oct. 19, fewer than the 14.9 million shares it said had been tendered as of Oct. 5, a sign that some shareholders had withdrawn their backing. The General Dynamics offer, scheduled to expire last Friday was extended to this Friday. The Pentagon said on Friday it was still reviewing the matter.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/06/business/company-news-newport-news-agrees-to-talks-with-grumman.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NEWPORT NEWS AGREES TO TALKS WITH GRUMMAN<date>Published: October 6, 2001</date><text>Newport News Shipbuilding Inc., the target of a takeover battle between the General Dynamics Corporation and the Northrop Grumman Corporation, said yesterday that it would begin talks with Northrop Grumman. Newport News said it remained committed to its existing agreement to be acquired by General Dynamics but said the bid from Northrop Grumman might now be superior because of a recent rally in Northrop's stock price. Both companies bid $2.1 billion, or $67.50 a share, for Newport News, which designs and builds nuclear-powered aircraft carriers and submarines. General Dynamics' bid was all cash and Northrop's bid included a combination of cash and stock. Newport News said yesterday that Northrop's bid now appeared to be worth $72.67 a share, prompting it to agree to the talks. (Bloomberg News)</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/25/business/company-news-general-dynamics-again-extends-offer-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS AGAIN EXTENDS OFFER FOR SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: September 25, 2001</date><text>General Dynamics extended its tender offer for all outstanding shares of common stock of Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. to midnight this Friday, the company said yesterday. General Dynamics of Falls Church, Va., said about 22.8 million shares had been tendered by its earlier deadline of last Friday. General Dynamics is awaiting government approval to complete the acquisition. The proposed $2.1 billion merger, announced in April, has drawn scrutiny from the Defense and Justice Departments. Northrop Grumman of Los Angeles, General Dynamics' primary competitor for Navy shipbuilding contracts, has offered $2.1 billion for Newport News.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/22/business/nation-challenged-military-contractors-beneficiaries-military-buildup-await.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">A NATION CHALLENGED: THE MILITARY CONTRACTORS; Beneficiaries of the Military Buildup Await Their Orders<date>Published: September 22, 2001</date><text>WASHINGTON, Sept. 21— Early last week, Frank C. Lanza, the chief executive of L-3 Communications, an aerospace and communications company in New York, received a not-too-surprising telephone call from military officials. ''They asked us, 'Can you do the following things, and how long will it take you to do it,' '' Mr. Lanza said. ''They are in the planning process. And they need to know about our ability to deliver certain products.'' That planning process is about war: the Pentagon is preparing a shopping list for the global struggle against terrorism promised by President Bush. As a result, scores of military contractors, from giants like Lockheed Martin to smaller companies like L-3, could be among the corporate beneficiaries of the devastating attacks of Sept. 11. Even as those assaults have sent the stock market plummeting and caused havoc for much of American business, prospects for the military-industrial complex are looking stronger than they have in years. Overnight, political opposition in Congress to huge increases in Pentagon spending has vanished, along with concerns about dipping into surplus Social Security funds. Consequently, what had seemed to the industry like a disappointingly small military budget just two weeks ago is now climbing toward unanticipated heights, providing a lift for military contractors and a quick Keynesian stimulus for the economy. Beyond the buildup for war, winners and losers in the race for Pentagon money will also be determined by the outcome of Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld's efforts to transform the military. His goals have included improving intelligence, expanding long-strike capabilities and making the forces lighter, faster and more high-tech. But the process has faced stiff resistance from some commanders and lawmakers who fear Mr. Rumsfeld wants to starve programs for modernizing conventional ships, planes and howitzers to nurture untried products, like space planes or remotely piloted submarines. ''The services are going to want to try to use some money to address their modernization needs,'' said Jacques S. Gansler, an under secretary of defense in the Clinton administration who now teaches public policy at the University of Maryland. ''And that's where you get a conundrum over whether to buy a new tank, or equipment you'd like to have for 21st-century warfare against terrorists. You'll have a battle between those two options.'' The budget numbers tell the story. Three days after the attack, Congress overwhelmingly approved $40 billion in emergency funds, with $10 billion to $15 billion for the armed services. In the next few weeks, Congress is also expected to approve, with little dissent, a $33 billion increase in the Pentagon budget, raising it to $329 billion for the fiscal year beginning Oct. 1. And before final votes on the 2002 spending plan are even cast, the Pentagon is expected to ask for an additional $15 billion to $25 billion. There is bipartisan support for that, too. ''Capitol Hill is prepared to do whatever the Pentagon wants,'' said Gordon Adams, a budget official in the Clinton administration who is now director of security policy studies at the Elliot School of International Security Studies at George Washington University. Much of the initial wave of money will go toward rebuilding the smoldering hole left in the Pentagon by the hijacked airliner, paying for heightened security at military installations worldwide and preparing for retaliatory strikes. That will mean buying new bullets, cruise missiles, boots, reconnaissance equipment and spare parts. But many analysts and military officials say they expect there to be a significant amount of money left over after those basic needs are met. The service chiefs and senior lawmakers will probably want to spend those funds on favored weapons programs, like Boeing's F-18 E and F fighters, United Defense's Crusader artillery system, and Northrop Grumman and General Dynamic's DD-21 stealth destroyer. It will not matter if those systems are not clearly useful in the war on terrorism, the analysts say. ''There is a heightened sense of danger out there,'' said Loren Thompson, chief operating officer with the Lexington Institute, a military policy organization based in Arlington, Va.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/11/business/company-news-boeing-may-face-1.4-billion-charge-for-canceled-a-12.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; BOEING MAY FACE $1.4 BILLION CHARGE FOR CANCELED A-12<date>Published: September 11, 2001</date><text>The Boeing Company said it could take a $1.4 billion charge if it lost a legal appeal over the government's termination of a contract for the A-12 stealth fighter. The company also said it had decided to appeal the latest ruling in the decade-old legal battle, an Aug. 31 federal court decision that upheld the government's 1991 action. The court upheld the government's default termination on the grounds the contractor team of McDonnell Douglas, which Boeing has since purchased, and the General Dynamics Corporation could not meet the revised schedule. The two companies have been seeking reimbursement of $2.6 billion they spent developing the radar-evading A-12 for the Navy before it was canceled by Dick Cheney, who was then defense secretary.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/05/business/company-news-general-dynamics-again-extends-bid-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS AGAIN EXTENDS BID FOR SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: September 5, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation extended its $2.6 billion offer for Newport News Shipbuilding, the military contractor, for a sixth time because federal regulators need more time to review the proposal. The $67.50-a-share offer for Newport News, the only maker of nuclear aircraft carriers in the nation, expired Friday. About 22.5 million, or 76 percent of Newport News's shares have been tendered, General Dynamics said. The new offer expires Sept. 14. General Dynamics and the Northrop Grumman Corporation are competing to acquire Newport News. Northrop Grumman, which is based in Los Angeles, extended its offer Thursday, to Sept. 13.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/02/business/dogfight-for-dollars-on-capitol-hill.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Dogfight for Dollars On Capitol Hill<date>Published: September 2, 2001</date><text>WASHINGTON— THE video shows a flair for the dramatic. A crowd anxiously watches a pilot climb into a sleek, futuristic-looking jet. The engines whine, the plane rises slowly like a hulking prehistoric bird and the onlookers explode, cheering with joy and relief. The trailer for a new Tom Hanks film? Try the latest promotional video for Lockheed Martin's experimental plane, the X-35 -- better known as the Joint Strike Fighter. The video is part of an extravagant Lockheed promotional kit that includes CD-ROM images of test flights, glossy photographs and a videotape of the aircraft breaking the sound barrier. And that is just one piece of a multimillion-dollar lobbying, advertising and marketing campaign aimed at beating its competition, Boeing, for what could be the most lucrative military contract, worth more than $200 billion. ''This is the future for both Lockheed and Boeing,'' said Richard Aboulafia, an aerospace analyst at the Teal Group, a consulting firm in Fairfax, Va. ''The stakes are huge.'' Lockheed is hardly the only military contractor mounting an aggressive campaign here. The season for lobbying by the military industry is in full bloom, and contractors are inundating Congress with Power Point briefings, shuttling officials to test sites and factories, hiring top-drawer lobbyists and showering lawmakers with campaign contributions. The reason for all the activity is a confluence of major decisions expected this fall: * The Pentagon is scheduled to award contracts not only for the Joint Strike Fighter, but also for the DD-21 destroyer, which could be the most important shipbuilding program of the next two decades. * The Pentagon must decide whether to block either General Dynamics or Northrop Grumman from acquiring Newport News Shipbuilding, the nation's only builder of aircraft carriers. * As soon as Congress returns on Tuesday from its summer recess, it will begin what is expected to be a contentious debate on the size of the Pentagon budget for the 2002 fiscal year, which begins on Oct. 1. The first hearings are on Wednesday, and many Democrats are pushing to trim President Bush's proposed $33 billion increase. Though the increase would be the largest since the mid-1980's, many industry officials had hoped for more from a Republican president. * By the end of this month, Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld will complete the Quadrennial Defense Review, mandated by Congress, that will set the size and shape of the armed forces, provide a template for future budgets and help determine the fate of an array of billion-dollar programs. * Also this month, the armed services will begin outlining their budgets for the 2003 fiscal year, the year when Mr. Rumsfeld has vowed to make major decisions on weapons programs. And because of the rapidly declining federal surplus, he is expected to require the services to find cuts to help pay for their favorite systems. ''There is no question that we probably cannot afford every weapon system'' in development, President Bush said in late August. ''This administration is going to have to winnow them down.'' The outcome is vital to a host of major companies, including United Defense, Northrop Grumman, TRW and Raytheon. Not surprisingly, they have been furiously working the marble corridors of Capitol Hill and the pale yellow hallways of the Pentagon to keep their programs alive and well. Recent lobbying reports indicate that military contractors are likely to spend nearly $60 million on lobbying this year, less than the communications or banking industries but more than lawyers and labor unions combined. Of that total, Lockheed and Boeing together account for more than $10 million. In recent weeks, their work has ranged far and wide. One day in June, one of the Joint Strike Fighter prototypes at Lockheed passed a crucial test, lifting off and landing vertically. The company immediately dispatched a video of the event to CNN. Within 24 hours, Boeing completed a similarly complex maneuver with its prototype, the X-32: taking off on a shortened runway, then hovering and landing vertically. The company quickly sent a video to CNN, too.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/21/business/company-news-general-dynamics-extends-offer-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS EXTENDS OFFER FOR SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: August 21, 2001</date><text>General Dynamics extended its $2.1 billion tender offer yesterday for all outstanding shares of Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. until Aug. 31. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., said it made the extension because it was still waiting for government regulators to say whether they would approve the merger. As of Aug. 17, the previous deadline, more than a majority of Newport News shares had been tendered. The proposed merger, announced in April, has drawn scrutiny from the Defense and Justice Departments, which have expressed antitrust concerns.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/11/business/company-news-general-dynamics-and-northrop-delay-their-bids.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS AND NORTHROP DELAY THEIR BIDS<date>Published: August 11, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation and its rival military contractor, the Northrop Grumman Corporation, said yesterday that they had agreed to delay closing their competing bids for Newport News Shipbuilding to allow regulators more time to review the offers. The companies said they had signed an agreement with the Departments of Justice and Defense agreeing not to seek a final decision on their offers before Aug. 20. The agreement means the winning bidder will not be able to close the transaction until Sept. 4 at the earliest, General Dynamics said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/07/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-a-motorola-unit.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY A MOTOROLA UNIT<date>Published: August 07, 2001</date><text>The defense contractor General Dynamics said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire a division of Motorola for $825 million to strengthen its communications and information technology operations. The unit being purchased, Motorola's Integrated Information Systems Group, provides military and other government customers with technologies, products and systems for secure communications and communication systems. The group, based in Scottsdale, Ariz., has 3,000 employees. Separately, General Dynamics said it was extending its $2.1 billion bid for Newport News Shipbuilding as it awaits government approval for the deal.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/10/business/company-news-general-dynamics-extends-newport-news-tender-offer.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS EXTENDS NEWPORT NEWS TENDER OFFER<date>Published: July 10, 2001</date><text>General Dynamics said yesterday that it was extending its pending offer for shares of Newport News Shipbuilding common stock. General Dynamics, the military contractor based in Falls Church, Va., extended its offer until midnight, July 20, from the earlier deadline of July 6. About 20.3 million Newport News shares were tendered by July 6, General Dynamics said. The number of Newport News shares tendered is more than a majority of its 31.4 million shares outstanding, and General Dynamics said it was awaiting government approval to complete the acquisition. In a merger worth $2.1 billion, General Dynamics is offering $67.50 a share for Newport News Shipbuilding, which designs and builds nuclear-powered aircraft carriers for the Navy. Northrop Grumman has also offered $2.1 billion for Newport News.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/26/business/company-news-general-dynamics-extends-offer-for-newport-news.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS EXTENDS OFFER FOR NEWPORT NEWS<date>Published: June 26, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation extended a $2.6 billion cash offer for Newport News Shipbuilding to July 6 because federal antitrust regulators requested more information on the proposal. The $67.50-a-share offer for Newport News expired Friday. About 20.2 million, or 68 percent, of the Newport News shares had been tendered, General Dynamics said. General Dynamics, which is based in Falls Church, Va., and owns the Bath Iron Works and Electric Boat naval shipyards, and a rival, the Northrop Grumman Corporation, based in Los Angeles, are vying for Newport News, the only remaining independent naval shipbuilder. Newport News, based in the Virginia city of the same name, said it supported the bid from General Dynamics.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/07/business/company-news-newport-news-board-backs-bid-from-general-dynamics.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NEWPORT NEWS BOARD BACKS BID FROM GENERAL DYNAMICS<date>Published: June 07, 2001</date><text>The directors of Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. voted to support the General Dynamics Corporation's $2.1 billion acquisition offer but took no position on a similar counterbid by Northrop Grumman, Newport News said yesterday. The board unanimously reaffirmed its recommendation of the General Dynamics offer of $67.50 a share in cash for all outstanding shares of Newport News common stock, the company said. The board said it thought that the General Dynamics offer provided better and more certain value for Newport News stockholders, the company said. The Northrop offer contained a combination of cash and stock.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/30/business/us-study-questions-shipyard-acquisition.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">U.S. Study Questions Shipyard Acquisition<date>Published: May 30, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation's contested $2.1 billion plan to take over Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. could stifle competition in United States warship building, a Congressional analysis released today showed.The new company would acccount for about 70 percent of United States warship revenues and 82 percent of the corporate designers and engineers, the nonpartisan Congressional Research Service said in a report dated May 22.It would also get more than 95 percent of Navy research and development funds earmarked for the six private-sector shipyards that build major Navy ships, based on 1999 Defense Department figures, the analysis said.The all-cash merger plan, which has already been agreed upon by the companies, would ''reduce the potential for competition in submarine construction and, perhaps more significantly, submarine design and submarine technology development,'' wrote Ronald O'Rourke, the report's author.But General Dynamics, which is battling against a rival bid for Newport News from the Northrop Grumman Corporation, dismissed the Congressional study as wrongheaded and based on outdated data.''It doesn't reflect today, nor does it reflect the facts of competition,'' said Kendall Pease, a spokesman for General Dynamics, which is based in Falls Church, Va.But Mr. O'Rourke countered that the data on designers and engineers dated from this year and was provided by General Dynamics itself for his study. The share of the shipyards' revenues has been relatively stable for years and the makeup of the Navy's shipbuilding budget has not changed in a way that suggested that those shares would shift significantly, he added.The Justice Department and the Defense Department are studying the competing merger proposals.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/26/business/company-news-us-seeks-data-on-bid-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. SEEKS DATA ON BID FOR SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: May 26, 2001</date><text>Antitrust enforcers at the Justice Department are taking a closer look at the General Dynamics Corporation's proposed acquisition of Newport News Shipbuilding. General Dynamics said it had received a request from the department for information about the proposed deal, a sign that it intends to scrutinize its competitive impact closely. Newport News is the subject of rival bids from General Dynamics and the Northrop Grumman Corporation. Northrop has argued that the General Dynamics proposal would create a monopoly in nuclear shipbuilding.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/25/business/company-news-northrop-grumman-begins-offer-for-navy-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORTHROP GRUMMAN BEGINS OFFER FOR NAVY SHIPBUILDER<date>Published: May 25, 2001</date><text>The military contractor the Northrop Grumman Corporation said it had begun its offer for shares of Newport News Shipbuilding Inc., despite Newport's planned merger with a Northrop rival, the General Dynamics Corporation. Northrop said it would pay shareholders of Newport News $67.50 in cash or the equivalent in Northrop stock for each Newport News share, and that it was willing to negotiate the terms if Newport News would let Northrop review its financial records. A spokeswoman for Newport News, which makes ships for the Navy, said its board would review the offer. Northrop's bid matches an offer from General Dynamics, which had planned to acquire Newport News in a mutually negotiated $2.1 billion deal, announced in April. Newport News last week told shareholders that it would stick with the General Dynamics deal while waiting for details on Northrop's proposal.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/10/business/markets-market-place-northrop-grumman-short-details-but-long-defenses-its-bid.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">THE MARKETS: Market Place; Northrop Grumman is short of details but long on defenses of its bid for Newport News.<date>Published: May 10, 2001</date><text>EXECUTIVES from the Northrop Grumman Corporation began explaining and defending the company's hostile $2.1 billion bid for Newport News Shipbuilding yesterday. But as of the close of business, the company had yet to make details of the offer available to the company it intends to wrest away from the General Dynamics Corporation, which agreed last month to buy Newport News for the same price in cash.Early yesterday, Newport News said its board would meet to consider Northrop's offer once specifics, like the exchange ratio of the common stock portion of the offer, were provided. As outlined late Tuesday, Northrop Grumman said it would pay 25 percent of the $67.50-a-share price for Newport News in cash and the remaining 75 percent in stock. It would also assume $500 million in debt. If Newport News were ultimately to accept the Northrop bid, it would have to pay General Dynamics a $50 million breakup fee.During a conference call with securities analysts, Northrop Grumman executives tacitly acknowledged that their offer was inferior to the all-cash bid from General Dynamics.But they strenuously argued that antitrust concerns made it highly unlikely the General Dynamics bid would pass scrutiny with the Defense Department and federal regulators. In that context, their offer is superior, they said.''The critical issue is, 'Can this transaction close?' '' said Kent Kresa, Northrop Grumman's chairman and chief executive. ''I think the odds are higher with us than with General Dynamics.''Investors did not seem to have a clear sense of how the struggle would unfold. And former Defense Department officials were equally uncomfortable trying to handicap the outcome.''My guess is that the Northrop Grumman bid will add great complexity to the situation,'' said Jacques S. Gansler, a former under secretary for acquisition, technology and logistics at the Defense Department and now a professor at the School of Public Affairs at the University of Maryland.Shares of Northrop Grumman slipped $3.50, to $88. During the conference call, the company's executives said the deal would be dilutive to its earnings for the first year after completion. General Dynamics closed at $78.15, down 15 cents. And Newport News rose 4 cents, to $65.04.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/09/business/northrop-grumman-joins-bidding-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Northrop Grumman Joins Bidding for Shipbuilder<date>Published: May 09, 2001</date><text>The Northrop Grumman Corporation made an unsolicited bid yesterday to buy Newport News Shipbuilding Inc., an effort intended to undercut a deal struck last month between Newport News and the General Dynamics Corporation.Northrop's offer, which was summarized in a letter from Kent Kresa, the company's chairman and chief executive, to William P. Fricks, chairman and chief executive of Newport News, is for $2.1 billion, or $67.50 a share, the same price General Dynamics has offered.But unlike General Dynamics, Northrop is unwilling to pay all cash. Rather, its offer is only 25 percent cash; the remaining 75 percent would be in stock. And former Pentagon officials were skeptical that the Navy would view the deal favorably.A call to Northrop, based in Los Angeles, was not returned late yesterday.Earlier this year, Northrop acquired Litton Industries, which builds amphibious ships for the Navy.If approved by regulators and the Defense Department, a merger of General Dynamics and Newport News would combine the Navy's only two nuclear shipyards, leaving the company the only maker of submarines and aircraft carriers.A spokeswoman for Newport News confirmed the company had received Mr. Kresa's letter. A response will be released today, the spokeswoman said.''We are disappointed that Northrop Grumman has chosen to interfere in a proposed transaction agreed upon by the respective boards of directors of General Dynamics and Newport News Shipbuilding,'' Kendell Pease, a General Dynamics spokesman, said in a statement.''The combination of General Dynamics and Newport News is the only combination that can provide synergies necessary to achieve significant merger-related savings,'' the statement said. ''It is also the only combination that offers the Navy depth of experience in the safe management of nuclear shipbuilding.''When General Dynamics and Newport News announced their deal on April 25, analysts speculated that Northrop Grumman might try to thwart the combination, either by making a hostile bid or by lobbying against it in Congress. One of Litton's biggest shipyards is in Mississippi, home of Trent Lott, the Senate majority leader.If successful in its bid for Newport News, Northrop Grumman would have a monopoly on aircraft carriers, amphibious ships and large-deck amphibious ships, which are almost as large as aircraft carriers. Significantly, it would remain a partner with General Dynamics in the construction of nuclear submarines.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/02/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-galaxy-in-300-million-deal.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY GALAXY IN $300 MILLION DEAL<date>Published: May 02, 2001</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the maker of Gulfstream jets, agreed yesterday to buy the Galaxy Aerospace Company for $330 million in cash to add midsize planes to its line of commercial aircraft. The company also won an order that had a value of as much as $2 billion from Executive Jet Inc. for 50 Galaxy jets and options for 50 more aircraft over five years. Galaxy is a joint venture of the closely held Hyatt Corporation and Israel Aircraft Industries Ltd., which is owned by the Israeli government.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/26/business/general-dynamics-makes-2.1-billion-deal-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics Makes $2.1 Billion Deal for Shipbuilder<date>Published: April 26, 2001</date><text>In a bid to become the sole manufacturer of aircraft carriers and submarines for the Navy, the General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. for $2.1 billion in cash.The deal -- which is subject to approval by shareholders, the Pentagon and the Justice Department -- would not only give General Dynamics control over the manufacture and maintenance of all nuclear-powered military ships, analysts said, but it would also solidify its position in the construction of Navy destroyers, support ships and commercial oil tankers.On its surface, the deal would appear certain to raise antitrust concern. But analysts, former Defense Department officials and executives from the two companies said competition was already lacking in the construction of submarines and aircraft carriers. They predicted the deal would be approved.In a statement, the Navy said that it would examine the agreement between General Dynamics and Newport News ''to assess what effect the acquisition would have on the nation's private shipbuilding industrial base.''''Naturally, this assessment will include a focus on any changes that have occurred since General Dynamics' previous attempt to acquire Newport News in February 1999,'' the statement said.Investors seem to think the combination will ultimately be approved.On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, shares of Newport News jumped $9.05, to $64.10. General Dynamics closed at $72.73, down $1.38.Newport News is the sole builder of aircraft carriers and has been for decades. Under an agreement reached with the Navy in 1997, Newport News and General Dynamics have split the work evenly on submarines.The deal comes only weeks after Northrop Grumman completed its $3.8 billion acquisition of Litton Industries, the only other major American military shipbuilder.Deal making in the military industry was encouraged for several years during the Clinton administration to promote efficiency and lower costs as the nation's military needs shrank after the cold war. But the pace of consolidation has slowed over the last few years.''At the beginning of the Clinton administration, there were clearly too many firms and too much capacity, and the industry was encouraged to consolidate,'' said Jacques S. Gansler, a former under secretary for acquisition, technology and logistics at the Defense Department and now a professor at the School of Public Affairs at the University of Maryland.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/18/us/powell-s-wealth-now-over-28-million.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Powell's Wealth Now Over $28 Million<date>Published: January 18, 2001</date><text>Since his retirement from the military seven years ago, Gen. Colin L. Powell has become wealthy through high-priced speaking engagements, amassing an investment portfolio in excess of $28.2 million, according to his financial disclosure statement.General Powell, who began Senate hearings today as President-elect George W. Bush's choice for secretary of state, earned $6.7 million in speaking fees last year in 109 appearances around the country, the records show.In most cases, he charged $59,500 for his remarks to such diverse groups as Gallup, the polling organization; Petsmart, the pet supply company; Lucent Technologies; and Middlesex Community College. For a speech at Credit Suisse Financial Services, he received his highest fee for a single appearance: $127,500 on May 5.General Powell's wife, Alma, has also raised money on the speaker's circuit. For five appearances last year, Ms. Powell received $64,000 in fees from groups fighting child abuse and housing shortages, as well as from the United States Postal Service.General Powell formally disclosed the income to the Office of Government Ethics, as required by the confirmation process that, for him, is being held by the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. Several prominent public officials have moved quickly to capitalize on their celebrity on retirement, notably former President Ronald Reagan, who received $2 million from a Japanese company for two brief appearances.General Powell, who served as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff during the Persian Gulf War, received a $6 million advance for his 1995 autobiography, ''My American Journey,'' which became a best seller. Senator-elect Hillary Rodham Clinton surpassed that figure last month, netting an $8 million advance for her account of the White House years.General Powell's investments in various mutual funds are worth at least $9.9 million, and possibly much more. Rather than requiring specific amounts, the disclosure forms ask nominees to identify their holdings in a broad range, for example $5 million to $25 million, leaving analysts certain of only the most conservative figures.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/08/us/a-new-destroyer-may-force-choice-on-the-bush-team.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">A NEW DESTROYER MAY FORCE CHOICE ON THE BUSH TEAM<date>Published: January 08, 2001</date><text>Correction AppendedThey call it the DD-21 destroyer: an electric-powered stealth ship designed to attack enemies hundreds of miles inland from any of the world's oceans as well as fight at sea.It will carry more Tomahawk cruise missiles and bigger guns than any destroyer in existence, yet will need fewer than a third as many sailors and cost less to operate, say its advocates, who include the secretary of the Navy, Richard Danzig, and leading members of Congress.''It's like going from sail to steam,'' asserts Kendell Pease, a vice president of General Dynamics and a former rear admiral. General Dynamics will release its first public diagrams of the DD-21 at a Navy conference this week.Yet for all the hoopla over it, the DD-21 faces a gantlet of obstacles emblematic of the broader problems that the armed services and the administration of President-elect George W. Bush will confront as they struggle to balance modernizing the military with paying for the upkeep of aging equipment.During the campaign, Mr. Bush hammered home the need to rebuild the services, calling for an acquisition program that would ''propel America generations ahead in military technology.'' To its advocates, DD-21 fits that goal, and Mr. Bush is on record as promoting an earlier version of the DD-21 known as the arsenal ship. But Mr. Bush also never explained how he would pay for such leap-ahead technology, and therein lies the rub.Like the other services, the Navy is struggling just to pay for mundane things like fuel, spare parts and paint. And long before it can expect to sail its first DD-21, in 2010, the Navy says it must replace aging planes and rusting ships that are scheduled for retirement.The Congressional Budget Office has predicted that the Pentagon budget will have to grow by as much as $70 billion a year to maintain weapons systems while moving ahead with new ones like the DD-21. Some senior Pentagon officials say the shortfall is well over $100 billion a year. Yet Mr. Bush has called for increasing military spending by just $4.5 billion a year over the next decade.Correction: January 9, 2001, Tuesday A front-page article yesterday about decisions faced by the Bush administration over modernizing the military referred incorrectly to the price of the Air Force's F-22 fighter, which uses stealth technology. Expected to cost as much as $180 million per plane, the F-22 would be the most expensive jet fighter in history, but the most expensive jet is a bomber, the B-2.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/06/us/army-suspends-vehicle-award-after-a-protest.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Army Suspends Vehicle Award After a Protest<date>Published: December 06, 2000</date><text>The Army today suspended a contract it signed with great fanfare last month to build a new family of light armored vehicles after a company that lost the bid filed a formal protest of the contract award.The Army's move, which was required under the government's procurement laws, dealt another setback to what Army leaders call their ''transformation'' to a lighter, more agile force, raising the prospect of new delays in fielding the first of six new combat brigades.On Nov. 17, the Army announced that it had hired a consortium led by the General Motors Corporation and the General Dynamics Corporation to build 2,131 new light armored vehicles by 2008 at a cost of nearly $4 billion. But on Monday, one of three losing bidders, United Defense L.P., based in Arlington, Va., formally protested the Army's decision to the General Accounting Office, setting off a review that could last 100 days.United Defense executives complained that they had proposed building a cheaper vehicle, more quickly and that the Army had failed to consider the criteria it had laid out for contractors. A spokesman, Douglas Coffey, said today that the company's offer had met all the Army's criteria and cost less than $2 billion, or roughly half the winning bid.Protests, which are allowed under the Competition in Contracting Act of 1984, are not unusual, but the scale of the contract and its importance to the Army's transformation effort give this one added significance.Daniel I. Gordon, assistant general counsel for procurement law at the G.A.O., said the agency would focus on whether officials had properly followed contracting rules. In an extreme case, it could order the Army to put the contract out for bid again.But he said that in many cases protests were dropped before a conclusion was reached, either because they were withdrawn or were addressed by the contracting agency.Army officials declined to respond to the protest in detail, but said officials had selected the General Motors-General Dynamics consortium because it offered the best vehicle, even though it cost more. ''No one can say we didn't undergo a rigorous selection process,'' a spokesman, Maj. William F. Bigelow, said.Nevertheless, the protest could prove to be an embarrassment to the Army, which has made the vehicle a centerpiece of its move to more agile forces under its chief of staff, Gen. Eric K. Shinseki. General Dynamic's bid already left the Army 16 months behind General Shinseki's plans to field the first of the new combat brigades by the end of 2001.While the new family of vehicles is only meant as an interim step between today's heavy tank and tomorrow's futuristic weapons, it has generated considerable controversy even within the ranks, particularly among advocates of the service's heavy tanks. A fundamental difference between United Defense's vehicle and the one that ultimately won the contract is that it moves on tracks, not wheels.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/18/us/army-s-armored-vehicles-are-already-behind-schedule.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Army's Armored Vehicles Are Already Behind Schedule<date>Published: November 18, 2000</date><text>The Army today unveiled a new family of light armored vehicles that a senior officer called a step toward ''a new 21st century Army,'' and then announced that that step was nearly a year and a half behind schedule.The new ''interim armored vehicles,'' to be built at a cost of nearly $4 billion, are intended to equip six new brigades the Army is creating in hopes of fielding more agile combat units than today's heaviest forces. The first of those brigades was supposed to be ready to go next year, but today's announcement made it clear that deadline could be pushed well into 2003.The delay, which officials attributed to working out design and production schedules, could prove troubling for the ''transformation'' effort that the Army's Chief of Staff, Gen. Eric K. Shinseki, has made a signature of his tenure.In an interview last month, General Shinseki said it was important to build momentum for the transition to the future Army that he and others envisioned, one designed for new types of operations, from urban warfare to peacekeeping. A failure to do so, he suggested then, risked derailing the effort as his tenure ends in 2003.General Shinseki, who under government procurement rules was not involved in the contract decision, did not address the delay in fielding the new vehicle today.But in a rare admission of official displeasure, his senior assistant for acquisition, logistics and technology, Lt. Gen. Paul J. Kern, acknowledged it had not been received well.''The chief is not happy with the schedule that we are bringing in,'' General Kern said at the Pentagon today. ''He would like it to be much sooner than it is.''The delay is another indication of the challenges facing General Shinseki as he tries to move the Army from a cold-war mentality of preparing to fight the Soviet Union with tanks and other heavy weapons on the open plains of central Germany.Since General Shinseki unveiled it last fall, the transformation has prompted intense debate. Many in the Army have argued, largely internally, that equipping troops with lighter vehicles instead of today's heavier, more powerful tanks will leave them outgunned and vulnerable on the battlefield.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/17/us/an-army-contract-signals-a-shift-from-tanks-to-light-armor.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">An Army Contract Signals a Shift From Tanks to Light Armor<date>Published: November 17, 2000</date><text>In a move that represents an important shift in Army strategy, the Defense Department today announced a multibillion-dollar contract for the purchase of light armored vehicles that will increasingly replace tanks on the battlefield.The Army contract, which could be worth up to $4 billion, was awarded to General Dynamics Land Systems of Sterling Heights, Mich., a unit of the General Dynamics Corporation.Pentagon officials said the purchase of wheeled vehicles, which will be far easier to transport and maneuver than tanks, will allow the Army to respond quickly to small conflicts and peacekeeping missions where tanks are not appropriate.The decision follows an often-heated debate within the Army over the future of tanks and other large armored vehicles originally designed for use in the cold war. Tank commanders in the Army had argued that it was wrong to move away from buying tanks, given the protection of heavy armor plating and firepower they offer to soldiers.''This is one of the big steps toward the transformation of the Army into the 21st century,'' said Lt. Gen. Paul J. Kern, a specialist in Army acquisition and logistics. ''This is our first major acquisition of a wheeled vehicle for combat operations.''Pentagon officials said the vehicles could weigh no more than 19 tons, allowing them to be easily moved aboard standard C-130 military planes. Details of the contract are expected to released tomorrow.The Army's M-1A2 Abrams tank weighs almost 70 tons, which prevents easy or quick transport, often frustrating the Pentagon in planning smaller military and humanitarian operations like those in recent years in Somalia and the Balkans.General Kern said in an interview that the new vehicles would ''clearly provide less protection than an Abrams tank, but we're not giving up on those; we'll still have tanks.''The new vehicles will come in a variety of configurations, including mortar carrier, anti-tank guided missile vehicle, medical evacuation vehicle and a reconnaissance vehicle for the detection of nuclear, biological and chemical weapons.The Army said in a statement that all of the vehicles were to be delivered before September 2008. The statement did not say how many would be built.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/10/business/company-news-general-dynamics-in-cash-deal-for-primex.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS IN CASH DEAL FOR PRIMEX<date>Published: November 10, 2000</date><text>General Dynamics agreed yesterday to buy Primex Technologies for $334 million in cash, or $32.10 a share, and to assume $170 million in Primex debt. The addition of Primex's munitions and rocket engine business would make General Dynamics the largest supplier of large-caliber and self-propelled munitions to the Army, the company said; Alliant Techsystems leads the market for small-caliber munitions. Primex, which also makes rocket motors for satellites, was spun off from the Olin Corporation in 1996. Shares of General Dynamics rose 81 cents, to $70. They had gained 29 percent over the last year. Primex, which had risen by almost 50 percent in the last year, rose 44 cents, to $31.44.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-sell-20-planes-to-executive-jet.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO SELL 20 PLANES TO EXECUTIVE JET<date>Published: October 10, 2000</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation's Gulfstream Aerospace unit has brought out its GV-SP Gulfstream ultra-long-range business aircraft and has agreed to supply 20 of the new jets to Executive Jet Inc. in a contract worth about $800 million. General Dynamics said yesterday the contract with Executive Jet included long-term maintenance for the aircraft. Gulfstream Aerospace said the new GV-SP aircraft have more cabin space, greater range and an advanced avionics system. Executive Jet, a unit of Berkshire Hathaway , manages more than 300 aircraft.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/business/company-news-gulfstream-eliminates-2-of-its-workers-to-cut-costs.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GULFSTREAM ELIMINATES 2% OF ITS WORKERS TO CUT COSTS<date>Published: October 05, 2000</date><text>The Gulfstream business jet unit of the General Dynamics Corporation laid off about 200 employees, or 2 percent of the operation's work force, last month as part of a plan to cut costs and increase efficiency. Most of the workers were in management and administrative positions at Gulfstream's headquarters in Savannah, Ga., said Keith Mordoff, a Gulfstream spokesman. He declined to estimate the cost savings. The layoffs came as demand for business jets was declining from recent record levels and competition was increasing, said Paul Nisbet, an analyst with JSA Research Inc. in Newport, R.I.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/business/company-news-machinists-reach-an-agreement-with-general-dynamics.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; MACHINISTS REACH AN AGREEMENT WITH GENERAL DYNAMICS<date>Published: September 01, 2000</date><text>About 1,500 striking machinists at the Bath Ironworks shipyard in Maine, where Navy destroyers are built, reached a tentative settlement with the General Dynamics Corporation yesterday after a 20-hour negotiating session, union and company officials said. The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Local 6 agreed to allow General Dynamics to cross-train workers building complex ships like the $900 million Aegis destroyer, said Susan Pierter, a spokeswoman for the ironworks, in Bath, Me. In return, General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., agreed not to use the cross-training provision when layoffs are in effect, she said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/24/business/the-markets-maker-says-gulfstream-jet-orders-are-up.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">THE MARKETS; Maker Says Gulfstream Jet Orders Are Up<date>Published: June 24, 2000</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said second-quarter orders for its Gulfstream business jetliners rose to their highest level in the last five quarters.The company attributed the increase to a number of factors, including an increase in business being conducted internationally, and greater personal wealth.The Gulfstream is the best-selling business jet. General Dynamics re-entered the commercial-aircraft business it left in the early 1990's when it bought Gulfstream in July for $4.8 billion.Some analysts questioned the purchase as too expensive at a time when sales of commercial aircraft, which occur in multiyear cycles, may be subsiding.''Gulfstream Aerospace, which represents over 40 percent of our 2000 operating-profit estimate, is doing very well,'' Byron Callan, a Merrill Lynch analyst who has a ''near-term buy'' rating on the company, wrote in a research report today.General Dynamics gave the quarterly order outlook and other comments at a meeting with analysts and investors yesterday.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/14/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-spanish-combat-vehicle-maker.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY SPANISH COMBAT VEHICLE MAKER<date>Published: April 14, 2000</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire ENSB, a Spanish maker of combat vehicles and munitions. The price was not disclosed. ENSB, a unit of state holding company Sociedad Estatal de Participaciones Industriales, will become a part of the combat systems unit of General Dynamics. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., is a military contractor and manufacturer of business aircraft. It said it would invest $60 million in ENSB in the next five years.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/28/nyregion/metro-business-arsenal-takeover-offer.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Metro Business; Arsenal Takeover Offer<date>Published: January 28, 2000</date><text>Three major defense companies have made an offer to take over operation of the Watervliet Arsenal from the United States Army.General Dynamics, United Defense and British Aerospace made the unsolicited proposal earlier this month, said Steven Abney, a spokesman for the Army's Industrial Operations Command. The arsenal primarily makes cannons.Army officials will start negotiations with the companies to determine whether the proposal could benefit the arsenal and maintain critical job skills, Mr. Abney said.Cliff Bushey, vice president for strategic planning for General Dynamics, said it was too early to say what a deal could mean for the 670 workers at the arsenal, which is five miles north of Albany.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/23/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-businesses-from-gte.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY BUSINESSES FROM GTE<date>Published: June 23, 1999</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, a military contractor, continued a buying spree yesterday, agreeing to pay $1.05 billion for three businesses of the GTE Corporation a month after reaching a $4.8 billion stock deal for the Gulfstream Aerospace Corporation, an aircraft maker. The GTE units, parts of GTE's government systems organization, concentrate on communications systems, worldwide telecommunications services and electronic systems. General Dynamics, based in Falls Church, Va., said the three units employed about 6,200 people and were expected to record 1999 revenues of about $1.2 billion. For GTE, which is based in Stamford, Conn., the transaction is the latest in a plan to sell assets to generate more than $3 billion in after-tax proceeds.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/18/business/general-dynamics-to-acquire-gulfstream.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics to Acquire Gulfstream<date>Published: May 18, 1999</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, a military contractor that specializes in making nuclear submarines, surface ships and tanks, announced yesterday that it would acquire the Gulfstream Aerospace Corporation, a maker of corporate jets, for $5.3 billion in a deal that returns General Dynamics to a business it once shed.The Gulfstream acquisition, a one-for-one stock swap that would give General Dynamics shares to Gulfstream shareholders, would add a new and potentially cyclical business to the General Dynamics line, which is heavily laden with armaments that are steady cash generators.It would also move General Dynamics back to the aerospace industry, a business it stepped away from in the early 1990's when it sold Cessna Aircraft, a maker of business jets, to Textron and when it sold its F-16 fighter jet operations to Lockheed Martin as well as its missile division to Hughes Electronics.The deal for Gulfstream elicited a mixed reaction on Wall Street. General Dynamics tumbled nearly 10 percent, or $6.1875, to $65.25, after having traded as low as $63.25 by midday. Still, while many on Wall Street were skeptical about the deal, others said Gulfstream would add a strong cash generator to the company, even if it took General Dynamics in a new direction.''The deal makes a lot of sense from a financial perspective,'' said Pierre Chao, an analyst with Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''General Dynamics is adding a company with a solid background and great cash flow, which will allow them to fuel further defense acquisitions.'' He said the market was forgetting that General Dynamics used to be in the aerospace business.Nicholas D. Chabraja, General Dynamics's chief executive, said Gulfstream ''is well within our core competencies and one of the strategic areas where I said we would move.''He added that the company still had executives responsible for efficiencies in aircraft ''and can help Gulfstream with its internal plans.''''This company hit us right in the gut as a very nice opportunity and a very fine company,'' he said.Skeptics, however, wondered why General Dynamics would consider taking on a business-jet company at what may be the top of a decadelong business expansion. But, they acknowledged that a trend in the business-jet business toward fractional ownership, or a type of corporate time-share, should protect Gulfstream from the next economic downturn. Gulfstream currently has a $4 billion backlog of orders.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/07/business/litton-makes-bids-for-two-shipbuilders.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Litton Makes Bids for Two Shipbuilders<date>Published: May 07, 1999</date><text>Litton Industries made unsolicited offers today to buy both Newport News Shipbuilding and Avondale Industries, two shipbuilders that were already planning to merge. The two transactions would have a total value of $1.8 billion plus $600 million in assumed debt.A double acquisition by Litton, which already owns the Ingalls shipyard in Mississippi, would create the nation's largest shipbuilder, one with capacity to build nearly any kind of ship. But it would reduce the number of large shipbuilders serving the Defense Department to two from four, which could raise antitrust issues at a time when the Pentagon has become more wary about military consolidation than it used to be.Only last month, the Defense Department blocked at attempt by the General Dynamics Corporation to buy Newport News because it would leave the nation with only one builder of nuclear-powered warships.But Michael R. Brown, the chairman and chief executive of Litton, said in an interview that Litton's acquisition would not raise antitrust issues and would actually be good for the Pentagon because it would create a strong competitor to General Dynamics, which is now the only company that can build both nuclear and non-nuclear ships.He said Litton had not had any formal discussions with the Pentagon but was familiar with the Government's position based on the discussions that occurred relating to the General Dynamics bid for Newport News.The Government has already approved the merger of Newport News and Avondale.Litton offered to merge with Newport News in a stock transaction in which it would exchange 0.55 share for each share of Newport News. At today's closing price of $64.75, the offer would be valued at $35.61 a share of Newport, or $1.3 billion, plus the assumption of $600 million in debt. Shares of Newport News rose 12.5 cents, to $27.Litton offered to buy Avondale for $38 in cash, or about $500 million. Shares of Avondale fell 37.5 cents, to $31.75.The offer was announced after the close of the stock market.Litton, based in Woodland Hills, Calif., said either acquisition could go ahead without the other. Mr. Brown said the combined companies would have $7.4 billion in revenue and 58,000 employees. About $3.6 billion in revenue would come from shipbuilding.By contrast, General Dynamics had 1998 revenue of $5 billion, with shipbuilding accounting for $2.7 billion.William P. Fricks, the chairman and chief executive of Newport News, said in a statement that the company's board had authorized preliminary discussions with Litton to evaluate the offer. Avondale also said it would review the offer.The acquisitions would be the biggest for Litton, which until now has mainly done smaller deals to fill out product niches and to expand into the information-processing business. Mr. Brown said the company waited until now to make its offers because it was more confident that the Pentagon intended to expand its number of ships.Litton's Ingalls unit makes destroyers and cruisers. Newport, based in Newport News, Va., makes nuclear-powered aircraft carriers and submarines. Avondale, based in Avondale, La., makes amphibious assault vessels, as well as commercial tankers and container ships.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/15/business/us-blocks-hostile-bid-for-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">U.S. Blocks Hostile Bid For Shipbuilder<date>Published: April 15, 1999</date><text>Saying that the potential savings did not justify the deal, the Defense Department yesterday rejected an unsolicited $1.4 billion offer by the General Dynamics Corporation for Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. Within minutes of the Pentagon's announcement, General Dynamics withdrew its offer.These twin announcements, not unexpected, end General Dynamics' effort to create a shipbuilding giant that would have controlled all of the nation's nuclear warship construction and four of the nation's six military shipyards. Had General Dynamics' hostile bid succeeded, it would have also brought an end to a friendly $519 million takeover by Newport News of Avondale Industries of New Orleans, a smaller Navy ship supplier. The Pentagon has already approved that deal.In a statement, the Defense Department said that ''the savings projected by General Dynamics did not now outweigh potential competitive disadvantages from the proposed merger.'' The Pentagon specifically said that with only one supplier of nuclear submarines, ''there would be a reduction in the likelihood of future competition.'' Similarly, the proposed merger would have put more than 75 percent of all military shipyard engineering talent and more than 95 percent of Navy research and development investments in one company, the Pentagon said.While acknowledging that a General Dynamics-Newport News combination would have brought some savings, the Secretary of Defense, William S. Cohen, said the savings were ''not now so great as to override the management and competitive challenge we could face from the merger.''In announcing the withdrawal of his company's bid, Nicholas D. Chabraja, General Dynamics' chief executive, called the Pentagon's decision ''disappointing.'' Still, Mr. Chabraja said, ''We respect it and have withdrawn our offer.''''General Dynamics believes that its proposed acquisition of Newport News Shipbuilding would have meant significant savings for the U.S. Navy, enhanced value for the shareholders of both companies, and still preserved jobs,'' he added. ''We will pursue other acquisition opportunities.''The chief executive of Newport News, William P. Fricks, said that with the collapse of the General Dynamics-Newport News deal, his company would proceed with the Avondale takeover, a deal that ''we continue to believe makes sound strategic and financial sense.''</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/13/business/doubts-rise-on-takeover-of-shipbuilder.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Doubts Rise On Takeover Of Shipbuilder<date>Published: April 13, 1999</date><text>With the Pentagon saying it is only days away from deciding whether to permit a hostile $1.4 billion takeover of Newport News Shipbuilding Inc. by the General Dynamics Corporation, speculation over the fate of the deal increased yesterday after the chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee said it was ''less likely'' that the Government would approve the merger.Senator John W. Warner, a Virginia Republican who has criticized the deal, which would put 80 percent of the Navy's shipbuilding capacity in the merged company, said over the weekend that the ''case against it is growing stronger every day.'' Senator Warner declined to comment further yesterday, although the stock of Newport News fell $3.0625 a share, or almost 10 percent, to $27.6875, a sign that Wall Street had lowered its expectation that the takeover would be approved.Mr. Warner's weekend statement was taken seriously in a community that was already skeptical of a proposal that would leave the nation with only one supplier of nuclear-powered submarines and put four of the six military shipyards in the ownership of one company. Not only is Senator Warner chairman of the committee that reviews all Pentagon spending, but he is also considered to be close to the Secretary of Defense, William S. Cohen, formerly a Republican Senator from Maine, from the days when they served on the Senate committee together.''This deal may still have some life in it,'' said Charles A. Gabriel Jr., a Washington analyst for Prudential Securities. ''But certainly, there's a lot less room for optimism because Warner is the committee's chairman, and the fact that this emanated from his office shows he is still resistant to the marriage. Moreover, his pipeline to Cohen should be good. When Cohen was a senator, he and Warner dominated the location of shipbuilding resources.''Glenn Flood, a Pentagon spokesman, said yesterday that ''we're getting close, we're talking days away'' to a Pentagon announcement on the merger. ''We haven't made a final decision; the review and analysis continues,'' Mr. Flood added. A spokeswoman for Newport News said the company had not received any indication from the Pentagon of the deal's fate, and a spokeswoman for General Dynamics said the same thing.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/19/business/general-dynamics-makes-1.4-billion-bid-for-newport-news.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">General Dynamics Makes $1.4 Billion Bid for Newport News<date>Published: February 19, 1999</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the nation's largest military shipbuilder, stunned the defense industry yesterday by making an unsolicited $1.4 billion offer for the rival Newport News Shipbuilding Inc., in the face of a changing Government policy that has discouraged such consolidations.News of the offer began to leak out late yesterday and was made official by the two companies later in the day. The General Dyanmics bid had already come to Newport News on Feb. 10 in a letter. General Dynamics is offering $38.50 for every Newport News share, a premium of 35.4 percent over its closing price yesterday. It would also assume $600 million in Newport News debt.The deal was surprising for two reasons: First, the Government, in a reversal of policy, has been halting military industry mergers, and this deal would create only one supplier of nuclear-powered submarines and put four of the nation's six defense shipyards in the hands of one company. Second, it throws in question Newport News's $470 million friendly takeover of Avondale Industries, the nation's No. 4 military shipbuilder. That merger was announced last month and has not yet closed.Neither the Defense Department nor the Justice Department would comment on the offer yesterday. Late last year, the Government, after nearly a decade of encouraging military industry consolidations, stopped the $8.3 billion bid by the Lockheed Martin Corporation to buy the Northrop Grumman Corporation, signaling the start of a harsher attitude in Washington toward such combinations.''This certainly muddies the waters for Newport News in its plans to acquire Avondale,'' said Paul Nisbet, an analyst with JSA Research in Newport, R.I. ''And there are very possible problems with the Government on this one. Given the Government's view of the Lockheed-Northrop deal, the Government may find this unacceptable. But General Dynamics must think there's a fair chance they can do it.''In response to the bid, Newport News said that under its agreement with Avondale, it was not permitted to enter into any other merger unless the Newport News board determined it was superior financially and that it was reasonably capable of being completed. To that end, Newport News said it would not respond to the General Dynamics offer until it has received a signal from the Government that such a union would be permitted. It also said it had asked the Government to pre-review the deal for antitrust concerns.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/10/09/business/company-news-general-dynamics-to-buy-shipbuilder-for-415-million.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">COMPANY NEWS; GENERAL DYNAMICS TO BUY SHIPBUILDER FOR $415 MILLION<date>Published: October 09, 1998</date><text>The General Dynamics Corporation, the nation's fourth-largest military contractor, said yesterday that it would buy Nassco Holdings Inc. to strengthen its ship-repair business and to compete better for future commercial and Navy contracts. General Dynamics will pay $370 million in cash and assume $45 million in debt for Nassco, an employee-owned company based in San Diego that is the parent of the National Steel and Shipbuilding Company. General Dynamics already owns the Bath Iron Works in Maine, a destroyer builder for the Navy, and Electric Boat, in Groton, Conn., a submarine builder. Nassco specializes in smaller Navy vessels, like support ships, and also builds commercial ships.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/21/business/judge-orders-us-to-pay-1.2-billion-to-2-arms-contractors.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">Judge Orders U.S. to Pay $1.2 Billion to 2 Arms Contractors<date>Published: February 21, 1998</date><text>A United States Federal claims court judge has ruled that the General Dynamics Corporation and the Boeing Company are entitled to $1.2 billion from the Government for the improper 1991 termination of the Navy A-12 stealth attack aircraft.Judge Robert Hodges outlined in a 52-page final judgment, which was released today, that a combined $3.8 billion claim the contractor team filed in June 1991 was ''reasonable, allocable and allowable.''The contractors have previously been paid $2.6 billion in progress payments for work performed under what was a $4.3 billion fixed-price contract to design the aircraft. McDonnell Douglas was the initial team member. It was acquired by Boeing last year.Judge Hodges's judgment allows the contractor team to keep the $2.6 billion, in addition to receiving another $1.2 billion.Although the judgment was silent about additional payments, the contractor team is also entitled to receive about another $600 million in interest that has accrued at the rate of $250,000 a day since the complaint was filed in 1991. The Justice Department will appeal.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/29/business/2-military-suppliers-report-strong-4th-quarter-earnings.html?ref=generaldynamicscorporation">2 Military Suppliers Report Strong 4th-Quarter Earnings<date>Published: January 29, 1998</date><text>Two companies with big military businesses -- the General Dynamics Corporation and Allied Signal Inc. -- reported solid gains in quarterly earnings yesterday.General Dynamics said its earnings rose 19 percent in the fourth quarter because of strong growth in the company's armored vehicles division. Allied Signal reported a 16 percent increase in fourth-quarter profits, citing strong sales in its aerospace operations.Both companies' results were in line with analysts' expectations, but their stocks headed in different directions after the reports. General Dynamics shares fell $1.6875, to $85.625, while Allied Signal shares rose $2.50, to $39.3125.General Dynamics, which is based in Falls Church, Va., said its earnings for the quarter were $83 million, or $1.31 a diluted share, compared with $70 million, or $1.10 a share, a year earlier.Quarterly revenues rose 23 percent, to $1.1 billion from $896 million.The company's Combat Systems Group, which makes armored vehicles, saw fourth-quarter earnings jump to $54 million from $38 million. Sales for the unit rose to $422 million from $263 million.The company makes nuclear submarines and the Aegis class of nuclear destroyers for the Navy, and the M-1 Abrams battle tank for the Army.Allied Signal, which makes aerospace and automotive products, chemicals, fibers and plastics, earned $314 million, or 55 cents a diluted share, up from $270 million, or 46 cents a diluted share, a year earlier.Sales rose 12 percent, to $3.9 million from $3.5 billion.The aerospace division earned $177 million in the fourth quarter, up 40 percent from $126 million in 1996, on strong sales of aircraft spare parts and repair, landing systems, environmental controls and engine systems.</text></article></page></root>
