<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Gilead Sciences">
  <page index="1">
    <article index="1" href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/21/sharing-patents-to-wipe-out-aids/?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Sharing Patents to Wipe Out AIDS<date>July 21, 2011, 8:35 pm</date><text>Fixes looks at solutions to social problems and why they work. Tags: AIDS, antiretroviral drugs, HIV, Medicines Patent Pool, pharmaceutical industry Not since the announcement in 1996 that antiretroviral therapy could effectively control H.I.V. has there been a season of AIDS news as hopeful as this one.  Trials of a new microbicide have brought positive results; ongoing studies of circumcision are showing that it gives strong, lasting, protection; a man has been cured of H.I.V. infection and new animal and clinical trials are raising hopes that he won’t be alone. The research with the most immediate and dramatic impact, however, examines two novel ways to use those antiretroviral drugs.  People with H.I.V. who start their antiretroviral therapy as soon as they are diagnosed, instead of waiting for their immune systems to degrade, have a near-zero chance of passing the virus on to their sexual partners. This is the AIDS vaccine we’ve been waiting for — a 96 percent drop in infection rates is far better protection than any actual AIDS vaccine could  provide.  It has also now been shown that giving one antiretroviral pill a day to people who don’t have H.I.V. but are at very high risk for catching it can reduce their risk by two-thirds or more. Taken together, these two methods of using antiretroviral drugs not just to treat AIDS, but also to prevent its spread, offer real hope of ending the epidemic.  But there’s a catch:  they require providing these drugs to millions, perhaps tens of millions, more people than are getting them now.  Someone has to pay for all this. That’s why it matters that last week, Gilead Sciences, one of the most important manufacturers of AIDS drugs, became the first drug maker to join something called the Medicines Patent Pool, a two-year-old organization that was established by Unitaid, an international body dedicated to buying AIDS drugs. In joining the patent pool, Gilead agrees to let generic pharmaceutical companies copy four of its drugs for sale at very low prices in poor countries.  Gilead will get a small royalty for every copy sold. This development might seem like the most obscure of events.  But it is an important step towards solving the problem of paying for AIDS drugs for vast numbers of people.  Wealthy countries’ tolerance for spending money on medicine has already diminished to the point where we are not only denying drugs to people sick enough to be in desperate need of them, but also contemplating cutting off the supply to people already on them.  This is happening even in the United States — for example the state of Florida, which already has nearly 4,000 people with AIDS on a waiting list to get antiretroviral drugs, has proposed cutting off funding for about 1,600 people who now rely on them.  (A foolish plan: the cost of their emergency room visits will more than make up for any savings.) As budgets shrink, the fate of the AIDS epidemic will increasingly depend on our success in lowering the price of antiretroviral drugs.  In the past 10 years, as more and more poor countries have begun offering antiretroviral treatment, competition from generic drugs has brought down the price of AIDS medicines dramatically.   A year of the gold-standard triple therapy is now available for only $143 in some poor countries. Even that is far too expensive for most developing countries, so these drugs are largely paid for by the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria, and by the United States President’s Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief, or PEPFAR.  When the Bush administration began PEPFAR, it resisted the use of generic drugs, at the behest of the pharmaceutical industry.   But even under President Bush PEPFAR officials realized that the use of generics would allow the program to reach far more people — generics, one study showed, saved PEPFAR $323 million over four years. The Medicines Patent Pool is modeled on a patent pool created by aircraft manufacturers in World War I.   The idea of using it for AIDS drugs came from Jamie Love, a veteran campaigner for lower prices for essential medicines.  Love, who now leads a group called Knowledge Ecology International, first proposed the idea at an AIDS conference in 2002, and it became a reality in 2009.  Now the patent pool has left Unitaid and is a freestanding organization. Last year, in a show of support from the Obama administration, the U.S. National Institutes of Health became the first entity to donate intellectual property to the patent pool.  It gave the pool rights to an AIDS drug developed in N.I.H. labs.  Gilead, the first pharmaceutical company to join, has granted the patent pool licenses to four medicines for use in the developing world, and will supply all the data and information needed to make them.   The patent pool can then award sub-licenses to certain generic drug makers.  Gilead will receive royalties for sales of the copies of its drugs. The patent pool is designed to solve several important problems.  One is that poor countries — the countries where medicine is most desperately needed — usually have to wait a long time for affordable medicines. Under ordinary circumstances, medicines are not available in generic form until 20-year patents expire. But the patent pool can make drugs them available in generic form right away.  Two of Gilead’s covered AIDS drugs and one combination pill are still in development, not even yet on the market.  With the patent pool, they will likely be available in affordable form in poor countries the same time that people can get them in the United States and Europe. Another advantage of the patent pool is that it can overcome the intellectual property obstacles in the way of creating combination pills.   People are much more likely to take their medicines successfully when they are combined into a single pill, to be taken daily or twice-daily.  It can’t happen if each medicine is under patent by a different company, but it can with the patent pool’s licenses.  Generic manufacturers can also improve on the drugs in other ways — by inventing formulations that are heat-stable, for example, or made for children. (To encourage the development of pediatric formulations, which are in very short supply, Gilead says it will waive its royalties on these drugs.) The Medicines Patent Pool is also designed to drive down the price of drugs.  One way is by licensing various generic manufacturers to make them, creating competition.  The other path is by selling these generic medicines in middle-income countries as well — the larger markets will bring down prices. There are other ways to make medicines more affordable.  Companies can choose to slash prices or license their drugs to generic manufacturers for sale in poor countries; most AIDS drug makers have done some of this.  Or countries can legally make or buy the generics without the originator company’s consent, paying the originator company a royalty.  These strategies, however, have been piecemeal, in many cases temporary, legally complicated, politically difficult and slow.  Most countries don’t do them.  They are afraid to — such moves are often punished by the United States and the European Union, where pharmaceutical companies exert a heavy influence over trade policy. Related More From Fixes Read previous contributions to this series. It’s obvious how people with AIDS can benefit from the patent pool, but what’s in it for the drug companies?   Some royalties and economies of scale.  A lot of goodwill.  Over the past 10 years, drug companies have gradually moved from a “one planet, one price” dictum — or worse: they used to charge more in Kenya than in Britain — to acceptance of tiered pricing.  They have never wanted to give up their intellectual property rights by licensing generics, but they have been pushed into it by the public relations catastrophe caused by their aggressive defense of high prices everywhere. “A piece of their motivation is reputational benefits,” said Brook K. Baker, a professor at Northeastern University School of Law who has been a vocal supporter of increased access to medicines.  “They’ve faced their fair share of protest over the years.  And they are hoping it will take the pressure off for even more sweeping reform.  They are betting that by giving access to more countries and earlier access, it will take the pressure off demands for middle-income-country access.” This is a key point.  It is the patent pool’s most important draw for pharmaceutical companies — and its most serious potential weakness.  Gilead says its licensing agreements “focus on the countries with the greatest need and where the greatest number of people with H.I.V. live.”  But the agreement Gilead negotiated only covers very poor countries.    It leaves out Egypt, China, Brazil, plus dozens of other developing countries.  Current AIDS drug prices in these countries are six or seven times the price of drugs in sub-Saharan Africa.  Without help from the patent pool, these countries have little hope of expanding antiretroviral coverage. The patent pool reports that seven other drug companies are currently in negotiations.  They are likely to try to copy Gilead.  “The big worry is what will happen with middle income countries,” said Tido von Schoen-Angerer, executive director of Medecins Sans Frontieres’ campaign for access to essential medicines.  “What we have seen with Gilead should be the floor, not the ceiling.” This attempt to draw a line between the Malawis and Afghanistans of the world and the slightly-better off Egypts and Indonesias is not limited to the patent pool alone.  On Wednesday, I’ll respond to comments and look at how drug makers are now raising prices significantly  in these lower-middle-income countries.  And not just drug makers — for all its support of the patent pool and use of generic drugs in PEPFAR, the Obama administration is still negotiating trade deals that are likely to put lifesaving medicines out of reach for millions of people. Join Fixes on Facebook and follow updates on twitter.com/nytimesfixes. Tina Rosenberg won a Pulitzer Prize for her book “The Haunted Land: Facing Europe’s Ghosts After Communism.” She is a former editorial writer for The Times and now a contributing writer for the paper’s Sunday magazine. Her new book is “Join the Club: How Peer Pressure Can Transform the World.”</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/12/health/12global.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Gilead to Share 4 AIDS and Hepatitis Drugs With Patent Pool<date>Published: July 12, 2011</date><text>In the first agreement between a pharmaceutical company and the new international Medicines Patent Pool, Gilead Sciences announced Tuesday that it would license four of its AIDS and hepatitis B drugs to the pool.The move is particularly important because it includes tenofovir and emtricitabine, which have emerged as important components of AIDS therapy and new prophylaxis regimens, like vaginal microbicides for women and once-a-day pills protecting gay men. Many poor countries now have only older drugs, some of which have harsh side effects. Health advocates have long championed the idea of a pool: an independent agency that would hold patents on drugs and sub-license them to low-cost manufacturers for low or no royalties on the condition that they supply only poor countries. (In Uganda, above, cost cutting has set back anti-AIDS programs.) The pool was created last year, but drugmakers resisted it, wanting to control quality and protect rights to future profits from middle-income countries. Until this week, the only participant was the National Institutes of Health, which turned over a partial patent on an obscure AIDS drug. “This is a great achievement,” said James P. Love, a campaigner for lower drug prices who first proposed a pool in 2002. “The other drug companies didn’t want Gilead to sign anything, and this will put pressure on them.” The pool must negotiate which countries can get which drugs, and Mr. Love said he will watch that carefully. Gilead may benefit, he noted, because it may now get modest royalties from sales in countries where it never bothered to take out patents.In the first agreement between a pharmaceutical company and the new international Medicines Patent Pool, Gilead Sciences announced Tuesday that it would license four of its AIDS and hepatitis B drugs to the pool.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/11/business/11bizbriefs-GILEADMAKERO_BRF.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Gilead, Maker of H.I.V. Drugs, Discloses a Subpoena<date>Published: June 10, 2011</date><text>Gilead Sciences, the world’s largest maker of H.I.V. drugs, said it had received a subpoena for documents related to its manufacturing and quality and distribution practices. News of the subpoena, from the United States attorney’s office for the Northern District of California, sent the drug maker’s shares down 2.4 percent, to $39.25. Gilead said it was cooperating in the civil and criminal investigation.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://prescriptions.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/22/this-weeks-health-industry-news-29/?ref=gileadsciencesinc">This Week's Health Industry News<date>February 22, 2011, 2:17 pm</date><text>The effort by Congressional Republicans to undo the health care law and to cut the federal budget will shift out of Washington this week as members of Congress are in their home districts on a break. Having just announced its agreement to buy Genzyme for $20.1 billion, Sanofi-Aventis will get news this week on whether Genzyme’s flagship drug, Cerezyme, is about to face new, and potentially lower priced, competition. The Food and Drug Administration is expected to decide by Friday whether to approve a new treatment for Gaucher disease that was developed by Protalix Biotherapeutics of Israel and would be marketed by Pfizer. Both Protalix’s drug, called taliglucerase alfa, and Genzyme’s Cerezyme consist of the human enzyme that is lacking in people with Gaucher disease, a rare inherited condition. But while Cerezyme is manufactured in genetically engineered hamster ovary cells grown in stainless steel vats, Uplyso is made in genetically engineered carrot cells grown in plastic bags. That could give the Protalix drug a cost advantage. Only about 6,000 people in the world are being treated for Gaucher disease, which is marked by enlarged livers and spleens, low blood cell counts and destruction of bone. But Genzyme built Cerezyme into a billion-dollar drug by charging about $200,000 a year for each patient. Manufacturing problems at Genzyme’s factory in Boston in 2009 led to a shortage of Cerezyme and of Fabrazyme, a drug for Fabry disease, another rare condition. Genzyme’s stock fell, making the company vulnerable to Sanofi’s approach. Another competitor approved last year, Shire’s Vpriv, has a price about 15 percent lower than Cerezyme’s. Vpriv is manufactured in vats of genetically engineered human cells. Pharmaceutical industry boards were apparently working over the three-day weekend, with some acquisitions announced Tuesday morning. Forest Laboratories agreed to buy Clinical Data for $1.2 billion, or $30 a share to gain access to Clinical Data’s recently approved antidepressant, Viibryd. That will help Forest weather the loss of patent protection on its current antidepressant Lexapro. Forest will pay up to an additional $6 a share in the future if Viibryd does well. Gilead Sciences, which gets the bulk of its sales from a drug to treat H.I.V. infection and AIDS, announced it would buy privately held Calistoga Pharmaceuticals of Seattle, which is developing a cancer drug. Gilead, which has done a string of acquisitions in an effort to diversify, will pay $375 million in cash and up to $225 million more based on the performance of Calistoga. Earnings reports continue this week. Wellpoint, the insurer, which has already reported its earnings, will hold a four-hour investor conference on Wednesday.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/28/weekinreview/28mcneil.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">An AIDS Advance, Hiding in the Open<date>Published: November 27, 2010</date><text>In the war against AIDS, a new weapon has emerged.It wasn’t a secret weapon. It was a well-established treatment pill that has only now been shown to be effective as a prevention pill too. Which raises a question: What took so long? Last week, a clinical trial showed that taking Truvada, a pill combining two drugs, once a day would greatly reduce a gay man’s chances of getting infected with the dangerous virus. Although confirmatory studies are still needed, the practice — called “pre-exposure prophylaxis,” or “prep” — will, in theory, also protect sex workers, needle sharers, wives of infected men, prison inmates and anyone else at risk. But Truvada has been sold since 2004. And the world has known since 1995 that antiretroviral drugs, used in combination, can rescue people with AIDS. As far back as at least 1990, it also knew that “post-exposure prophylaxis” (“pep”) often works in humans — that is, that a victim of a needle stick or rape or unprotected sex who begins taking a short course of antiretrovirals within 72 hours can probably avoid infection. A few scientists even knew by 1995 that a drug in Truvada can protect monkeys from infection with the simian version of the AIDS virus. So couldn’t “prep” have been “discovered” earlier? Why did it take until 2010? The delay turns out to be a combination of scientific caution and the fiery politics of AIDS. While a medical advance can be made by a momentary flash of inspiration or luck — as legendarily happened with penicillin — proving that it works can take forever. And that is particularly true with AIDS, a disease surrounded by visceral fears, longstanding prejudices and the potential for huge profits. The chief reason this advance took so long, said Dr. Robert M. Grant, a virologist at the Gladstone Institutes in San Francisco and the study’s chief author, is that the two drugs in Truvada, tenofovir and emtricitabine, were not approved for use in humans until 2001 and 2002, respectively. Older drugs, like AZT, the first AIDS drug, adopted in 1987, were too toxic. Doctors once debated using nevirapine, approved in 1996. In poor countries, single doses for mother and baby are given at birth to prevent mother-child transmission. But taking nevirapine for even a few weeks can bring on brutal side effects. Over 10 percent of users get rashes. In rare cases, the drug can kill if not stopped in time. Giving powerful drugs to healthy people is different from giving them to the desperately ill. No doctor would give cancer drugs to a healthy person. Prophylaxis is common with, for example, malaria drugs for travelers making brief sojourns in the tropics. But a drug to be taken all one’s life — or at least for all of one’s sex life — must be very safe. Also, the drug must not prompt drug-resistance mutations in the virus. Tenofovir is unique that way, said Dr. Howard S. Jaffe, president of the Gilead Foundation, the philanthropic arm of Gilead Sciences, which makes Truvada. Structurally, it is so nearly identical to the bit of DNA it blocks that “the virus can’t easily outsmart it,” he said. Resistance to nevirapine, by contrast, can develop after a single dose. Another factor is that not every drug company wants to see its best treatment drugs, on which it earns billions of dollars, tested for prevention. Dying patients accept unpleasant side effects; healthy ones might sue. And any patient who gets infected, even if taking the drug improperly, could sue. Gilead Sciences was willing to let Truvada be tested, although it has not yet decided, Dr. Jaffe said, whether to apply for F.D.A. permission to sell it as prophylaxis. Also, several AIDS experts said, lab scientists were focused for years on the dream of an AIDS vaccine, while behaviorists assumed everyone would adopt condoms or abstinence. None of those hopes has been realized. The final delay was caused by political battling. Plans to test Truvada began in 2003, and sites were chosen not just in American cities with gay populations like San Francisco and Boston, but in countries where the virus was also killing prostitutes and clients: Nigeria, Cameroon, Ghana and Cambodia. Then, at the 2004 International AIDS Conference in Bangkok, the Paris chapter of the AIDS activist group Act-Up unexpectedly attacked Gilead Sciences’ booth, spraying it with fake blood and accusing the company of experimenting on poor people. As Dr. Jaffe tells it, French activists “played the anti-U.S. card in Francophone countries” and stirred up sex workers’ unions in Cambodia, eventually leading the Cameroonian and Cambodian governments to stop their trials. Nigeria’s stopped for other reasons, though many Nigerians were hostile to drug companies because of rumors that polio vaccine was an anti-Muslim plot and because Pfizer had tested a new antibiotic on children with meningitis. “If not for this misplaced activism, we might have had an answer five years earlier,” Dr. Jaffe said. Dr. Grant saw the same struggle differently. The activists were disruptive, he said, but also “raised significant questions” about whether participants would be protected from side effects and about who, if anyone, would pay for lifelong treatment if participants did eventually get AIDS. One result, he said, was that protocols were improved and more countries added: South Africa, Brazil, Peru, Ecuador, Thailand. But more important, he said, was the emergence of the two agencies that now pay for treatment in poor countries, the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria, and the President’s Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief. It took until about 2005 for most poor countries to take advantage of that aid. Enrollment finally began in 2007. While monkey trials are quick and vicious — give the drug, zap the caged animals with virus, wait a bit, and dissect a few — ethical human trials are complex. At a cost of $44 million, this one screened nearly 5,000 people to find 2,500 participants to follow for up to three years. Any approval process takes time and hits unexpected roadblocks, Dr. Grant said. “But,” he insisted, “we started working on prep the minute the right drugs became available.”</text></article>
    <article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/24/health/research/24aids.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">AIDS Risk Greatly Lowered by Daily Pill, Study Finds<date>Published: November 23, 2010</date><text>Healthy gay men who took an anti-AIDS pill every day were well protected against contracting H.I.V. in a study suggesting that a new weapon against the epidemic has emerged.In the study, published Tuesday by the New England Journal of Medicine, researchers found that the men taking Truvada, a common combination of two antiretroviral drugs, were 44 percent less likely to get infected with the virus that causes AIDS than an equal number taking a placebo. But when only the men whose blood tests showed that they had taken their pill faithfully every day were considered, the pill was more than 90 percent effective, said Dr. Anthony S. Fauci, head of the infectious diseases division of the National Institutes of Health, which paid for the study along with the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation. “That’s huge,” Dr. Fauci said. “That says it all for me.” The large study, nicknamed iPrEx, included nearly 2,500 men and was coordinated by the Gladstone Institutes of the University of California, San Francisco. The results are the best news in the AIDS field in years, even better than this summer’s revelation that a vaginal microbicide protected 39 percent of all the women testing it and 54 percent of those who used it faithfully. Also, Truvada, a combination of tenofovir and emtricitabine that prevents the virus from replicating, is available by prescription in many countries right now, while the microbicide gel is made in only small amounts for clinical trials. The protection, known as pre-exposure prophylaxis, is also the first new form available to men, especially men who cannot use condoms because they sell sex, are in danger of prison rape, are under pressure from partners or lose their inhibitions when drunk or high. It “does not involve getting permission from the other partner, and that’s important,” said Phill Wilson, president of the Black AIDS Institute, which focuses on the epidemic among blacks. Michel Sidibé, the head of the United Nations agency that fights AIDS, called it “a breakthrough that will accelerate the prevention revolution.” AIDS experts and the researchers issued several caveats about the study’s limitations, emphasizing that it looked only at gay men and Truvada. More studies, now under way, are needed to see whether the results can be duplicated, whether other antiretroviral drugs will work and whether they will protect heterosexual men and women, prostitutes and drug users who share needles. There is no medical reason to think the pill would not work in other groups, since it attacks the virus in the blood, not in the vaginal wall as a microbicide does. Pre-exposure prophylaxis became possible only in recent years as newer, less-toxic antiretroviral drugs were developed. Some scientists fear that putting more people on the drugs will speed the evolution of drug-resistant strains, though that did not occur in the study. Because Truvada is available now, some clinicians already prescribe it for prophylaxis, Dr. Fauci said, but whether doing so becomes official policy will depend on discussions by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Food and Drug Administration, medical societies and others, which could take months. Although the C.D.C. would prefer that doctors wait for further studies, more will probably prescribe the drugs now that this study is out, said Dr. Kevin Fenton, chief of the agency’s AIDS division, so the C.D.C. will soon release suggested guidelines. The agency will suggest that the drug be prescribed only with close medical supervision and used only with other safe-sex practices. “The results are encouraging, but it’s not time for gay men to throw away their condoms,” Dr. Fenton said. AIDS advocacy groups were very excited by the results. “If you comply with it, this works really well,” said Chris Collins, policy director of amfAR, the Foundation for AIDS Research. “This is too big to walk away from.” Mitchell Warren, executive director of AVAC, an organization that lobbies for AIDS prevention, called the study “a great day for the fight against AIDS” and said gay men and others at risk needed to be consulted on the next steps. In the study, 2,499 men in six countries — Brazil, Ecuador, Peru, South Africa, Thailand and the United States — were randomly assigned to take either Truvada or a placebo and were followed for up to three years. For ethical reasons, they were also given condoms, treatment for venereal diseases and advice on safe sex. There were 64 infections in the placebo group and 36 in the group that took Truvada, a 44 percent risk reduction. Two in the Truvada group turned out to have been infected before the study began. When the remaining 34 were tested, only 3 had any drug in their blood — suggesting that the other 31 had not taken their pills. Different regimens, like taking the pills not daily but only when sex is anticipated, also need testing. Also, many men in the study failed to take all of their pills, and some clearly lied about it. For example, some who claimed to take them 50 percent or 90 percent of the time had little or no drug in their bloodstreams. The pills caused no major side effects, though men who began to show signs of liver problems were taken off them quickly. Some men stopped taking the pills because they disliked relatively minor side effects like nausea and headaches. Also, some stopped bothering once they suspected that they might be taking a placebo. “People have their own reasons,” Mr. Collins said. “People don’t take their Lipitor every day either.” A major question now is who will pay for the drug. In the United States, Truvada, made by Gilead Sciences, costs $12,000 to $14,000 a year. In very poor countries, generic versions cost as little as 40 cents a pill. Globally, only about 5 million of the 33 million people infected with the AIDS virus are on antiretroviral drugs, and in an era of tight foreign-aid budgets, that number is not expected to rise quickly. Hundreds of millions of Africans, Eastern Europeans and Asians are at risk and could benefit from prophylaxis, but that would cost tens of billions of dollars. In this country, insurers and Medicare normally pay for the drugs, and the Ryan White Act covers the cost for the poor, but none of these payers yet have policies on supplying the drugs to healthy people. No participant in the study developed resistance to tenofovir. Three were found to have strains resistant to emtricitabine, but investigators believe that all three were infected before the study began at levels low enough to have been missed by their first H.I.V. tests. Another concern was that the participants would become so fearless that they would stop using condoms, but the opposite effect was seen — they used condoms more often and had fewer sex partners. But that can also be a result of simply being enrolled in a study and getting a steady diet of advice on safe sex and free condoms, the investigators said. Other trials of pre-exposure prophylaxis have about 20,000 volunteers enrolled around the world. Their results are expected over the next two years.</text></article>
    <article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/29/health/29glob.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">The Drug Industry: GlaxoSmithKline, Merck and Novartis Again Rank Highest on Access to Poor<date>Published: June 28, 2010</date><text>GlaxoSmithKline, Merck and Novartis have taken the top three spots again on the Access to Medicine Index, which ranks pharmaceutical companies on how readily they make their products available to the world’s poor. It was the second time the rankings, which were created in 2008, have been issued. This time, 95 percent of the brand-name companies approached by the Dutch foundation that started the index agreed to provide information; two years ago, only about half did. European companies slightly edged out American companies in the rankings, while the four Japanese companies ranked were at or near the bottom. The companies are graded on many factors, including whether they offer lower prices or donate drugs in poor countries, whether they license generic versions of their products or fight to prevent them, whether they donate expertise or money to struggling health systems and whether they do research on neglected diseases. Gilead Sciences and Pfizer rose several ranks from 2008. Those falling in rank were Novo Nordisk, Bayer, Bristol-Meyers Squibb and Merck KGaA (a German company no longer connected to the Merck based in New Jersey). The index, which is supported by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, the Dutch and British governments, Oxfam and other donors, also issued detailed “report cards” on 20 companies. For the first time, generic drug makers were ranked separately. Three Indian companies, Ranbaxy Laboratories, Cipla and Dr. Reddy’s, took the top three spots.</text></article>
    <article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/11/jobs/11boss.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">On the Discovery Trail<date>Published: October 10, 2009</date><text>I KNEW that I wanted to be a chemist by the time I was 8. Both of my parents were chemists. Skip to next paragraph JOHN C. MARTIN Chief executive, Gilead Sciences, Foster City, Calif. AGE 58 BIRTHPLACE Easton, Pa. FAVORITE SPORTS Football and basketball When I was 2, my father took a job at Mead Johnson in Evansville, Ind. Our house there was an old farmhouse. Our neighbors had a barn, and friends and I strung an incandescent light suspended from the rafters so we could play basketball every night. Evansville was a sports-crazy town. Everyone turned out for sports on Friday night. My first job, at age 8, was picking strawberries at a neighboring farm. We planted our own crops, too, including corn every three weeks in the spring. We had an acre of potatoes, lettuce and tomatoes and a half-acre of berries. I majored in chemical engineering at Purdue, where you could test out of college courses and get credit. I accumulated enough credits to graduate in two and a half years, but I stayed for the full four. The first semester I enrolled in two calculus courses and two chemistry courses. I also took English, physics and German. I was the only person in my accelerated English class who wasn’t an English major. After graduation, I applied for a summer job at the Amoco Oil Company on a project to reduce sulfur content and make fuel less polluting, but then I enrolled in graduate school at the University of Chicago, which had a reputation for multidisciplinary programs. Synthetic organic chemistry appealed to me. You are making a molecule that’s never been made before. You have a hypothesis, but more often than not, you’re wrong. My faculty adviser, Josef Fried, sent me to his brother John at Syntex Research, a division of the Syntex Corporation (now part of the Roche Group) to work with him. I worked there six years, and with Julien Verheyden, my supervisor, co-invented a molecule that became ganciclovir, a generic and antiviral drug that was initially developed for herpes. It was synthesized before I was 30. Only about 20 new molecules are approved for drugs by the Food and Drug Administration in a year. I had moved to another company by the time the drug was approved. I read about it in the newspaper. In this business, if you don’t innovate, someone else will. Working in the antiviral chemistry division at Bristol-Myers Squibb, I was in charge of overseeing the science for the drug stavudine for H.I.V., and when we developed tenofovir disoproxil fumarate it replaced stavudine. I joined Gilead Sciences in 1990, and by 1999 we were in the final stage of about five or six years of work in creating the drug adefovir dipivoxil to treat H.I.V. The drug wasn’t approved by the F.D.A. for H.I.V. because the data showed evidence of kidney toxicity. The company’s market cap went down. Still, the research generated a product, tenofovir, that had greater potential against H.I.V. Adefovir dipivoxil was later approved for treatment against hepatitis B at a lower dose. From 1997 to January 2001, Donald Rumsfeld, the former and future defense secretary, was chairman of Gilead while I was president and C.E.O. He had an exceptional attention to detail and understood the pharmaceutical industry. We got along famously. Tamiflu, invented by Gilead Sciences and developed by Gilead and Hoffmann La Roche as a treatment and preventative for seasonal influenza, was approved in October 1999. The time from clinical testing of humans to F.D.A. approval was about 30 months. With a new flu virus, you never know what you’re dealing with. Science is following the facts. There’s great concern about the second wave of H1N1, swine flu. What we say about pandemic flu is not if, but when. But the scientific community started investigating and now we’re going to work to control it. As told to Amy Zipkin. More Articles in Job Market » A version of this article appeared in print on October 11, 2009, on page BU8 of the New York edition.I KNEW that I wanted to be a chemist by the time I was 8. Both of my parents were chemists. Skip to next paragraph JOHN C. MARTIN Chief executive, Gilead Sciences, Foster City, Calif. AGE 58 BIRTHPLACE Easton, Pa. FAVORITE SPORTS Football and basketball When I was 2, my father took a job at Mead Johnson in Evansville, Ind. Our house there was an old farmhouse. Our neighbors had a barn, and friends and I strung an incandescent light suspended from the rafters so we could play basketball every night. Evansville was a sports-crazy town. Everyone turned out for sports on Friday night. My first job, at age 8, was picking strawberries at a neighboring farm. We planted our own crops, too, including corn every three weeks in the spring. We had an acre of potatoes, lettuce and tomatoes and a half-acre of berries. I majored in chemical engineering at Purdue, where you could test out of college courses and get credit. I accumulated enough credits to graduate in two and a half years, but I stayed for the full four. The first semester I enrolled in two calculus courses and two chemistry courses. I also took English, physics and German. I was the only person in my accelerated English class who wasn’t an English major. After graduation, I applied for a summer job at the Amoco Oil Company on a project to reduce sulfur content and make fuel less polluting, but then I enrolled in graduate school at the University of Chicago, which had a reputation for multidisciplinary programs. Synthetic organic chemistry appealed to me. You are making a molecule that’s never been made before. You have a hypothesis, but more often than not, you’re wrong. My faculty adviser, Josef Fried, sent me to his brother John at Syntex Research, a division of the Syntex Corporation (now part of the Roche Group) to work with him. I worked there six years, and with Julien Verheyden, my supervisor, co-invented a molecule that became ganciclovir, a generic and antiviral drug that was initially developed for herpes. It was synthesized before I was 30. Only about 20 new molecules are approved for drugs by the Food and Drug Administration in a year. I had moved to another company by the time the drug was approved. I read about it in the newspaper. In this business, if you don’t innovate, someone else will. Working in the antiviral chemistry division at Bristol-Myers Squibb, I was in charge of overseeing the science for the drug stavudine for H.I.V., and when we developed tenofovir disoproxil fumarate it replaced stavudine. I joined Gilead Sciences in 1990, and by 1999 we were in the final stage of about five or six years of work in creating the drug adefovir dipivoxil to treat H.I.V. The drug wasn’t approved by the F.D.A. for H.I.V. because the data showed evidence of kidney toxicity. The company’s market cap went down. Still, the research generated a product, tenofovir, that had greater potential against H.I.V. Adefovir dipivoxil was later approved for treatment against hepatitis B at a lower dose. From 1997 to January 2001, Donald Rumsfeld, the former and future defense secretary, was chairman of Gilead while I was president and C.E.O. He had an exceptional attention to detail and understood the pharmaceutical industry. We got along famously. Tamiflu, invented by Gilead Sciences and developed by Gilead and Hoffmann La Roche as a treatment and preventative for seasonal influenza, was approved in October 1999. The time from clinical testing of humans to F.D.A. approval was about 30 months. With a new flu virus, you never know what you’re dealing with. Science is following the facts. There’s great concern about the second wave of H1N1, swine flu. What we say about pandemic flu is not if, but when. But the scientific community started investigating and now we’re going to work to control it. As told to Amy Zipkin.</text></article>
    <article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/10/business/10aids.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">AIDS Activists Issue Grades to Drug Companies<date>Published: September 10, 2009</date><text>Merck won the highest grade and Abbott Laboratories flunked in a report card being issued Thursday by a prominent group of AIDS treatment activists after a yearlong study of the actions of nine major pharmaceutical companies to address the contagion in the United States. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Abbott Laboratories Go to your Portfolio » Although advances in drug regimens since the 1990s have added nearly 20 years to the average life expectancy of a person with H.I.V./AIDS, the report card graded the drug makers overall with a below-average C-minus and recommended improvements. “There’s an opportunity now to kick it up a notch,” said Bob Huff, antiretroviral treatment director of the Treatment Action Group in New York and a board member of the rating group. Twenty-one members of the AIDS Treatment Activists Coalition, a nonprofit group formed in 2001, researched the drug companies, interviewed executives and assigned grades assessing performance over the last quarter century, Mr. Huff said. The companies were scored on research and development, pricing, patient assistance programs, marketing, and community relations. More than one million people in the United States are infected with the human immunodeficiency virus, though only about half of them have been discovered and treated, the government says. Untreated, H.I.V./AIDS leaves people vulnerable to infections and cancers. While treatment reduces symptoms and extends life, there is no cure. The report gave its highest grade, a B, to Merck, for producing Isentress, the first of a new class of AIDS drugs called integrase inhibitors. It also praised Merck for freezing prices for lower income users. Isentress, approved in 2007, is already used by 11 percent of the more than 550,000 people treated in the United States, Michael S. Seggev, a spokesman for Merck, said Wednesday. “We’re very pleased to have achieved the highest grade on the report card,” he said. “They’re the most respected and most representative coalition of H.I.V. community groups in the U.S., so their opinion is very meaningful.” The group gave an F to Abbott for raising the wholesale price of Norvir, the first drug proved to increase survival in AIDS patients, by 400 percent in 2003. Norvir is a key ingredient in most AIDS treatment cocktails. The price increaes provoked an outcry by many patients and others. An Abbott spokesman, Dirk van Eeden, responded Wednesday, “The H.I.V. community is an important stakeholder for us, so yes, we do take notice of the comments they make.” He added, “We really believe we’ve discovered important medicines and played our part in making sure the patients who need it can get it.” Other grades included a B for Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, owned by Johnson and Johnson as a separate company focusing on infectious diseases; C-plus for Pfizer, which announced in April a joint venture with GlaxoSmithKline to spin off a company focused on H.I.V.; C-plus for Gilead Sciences; C-minus grades for Bristol-Myers Squibb and GlaxoSmithKline, both criticized for high prices; a D-plus for Boehringer Ingelheim; and a D for Hoffman LaRoche, which the coalition said has the most expensive drug on the market. Representatives for Pfizer, Gilead and Boehringer responded Wednesday that they valued the group’s opinion and continued their work in AIDS. Bristol-Myers Squibb and GlaxoSmithKline officials each said they were “disappointed” and deserved better grades. Other companies did not respond immediately to requests for comment. The coalition was to some degree biting the hand that feeds it. It receives all of its financing from drug companies, mostly for activists to travel to meetings with them. The executive director, Edward T. Rewolinski, disclosed specific amounts to The New York Times for the last two years. “None of our members has the wherewithal to afford this activity,” he said. “People like that would never be influenced by the flow of money,” Jennifer Flynn, managing director of an unrelated AIDS group, Health GAP, in New York, said. The top fund provider was Gilead with $100,000, followed by Pfizer, $63,000; Bristol-Myers Squibb, $50,000; Tibotec, $45,000; Merck, $15,000; and Boehringer, $5,000. Abbott gave no money. Mr. Huff said the grading group was insulated from financing requests. “There’s no sugarcoating,” he said. “The membership feels that the pharmaceutical industry can be doing a much better job, whether it’s innovation or pricing.” The coalition was formed in 2001 partly to coordinate contacts with drug companies instead of letting the industry decide whom to invite to meetings. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on September 10, 2009, on page B6 of the New York edition.Merck won the highest grade and Abbott Laboratories flunked in a report card being issued Thursday by a prominent group of AIDS treatment activists after a yearlong study of the actions of nine major pharmaceutical companies to address the contagion in the United States. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Abbott Laboratories Go to your Portfolio » Although advances in drug regimens since the 1990s have added nearly 20 years to the average life expectancy of a person with H.I.V./AIDS, the report card graded the drug makers overall with a below-average C-minus and recommended improvements. “There’s an opportunity now to kick it up a notch,” said Bob Huff, antiretroviral treatment director of the Treatment Action Group in New York and a board member of the rating group. Twenty-one members of the AIDS Treatment Activists Coalition, a nonprofit group formed in 2001, researched the drug companies, interviewed executives and assigned grades assessing performance over the last quarter century, Mr. Huff said. The companies were scored on research and development, pricing, patient assistance programs, marketing, and community relations. More than one million people in the United States are infected with the human immunodeficiency virus, though only about half of them have been discovered and treated, the government says. Untreated, H.I.V./AIDS leaves people vulnerable to infections and cancers. While treatment reduces symptoms and extends life, there is no cure. The report gave its highest grade, a B, to Merck, for producing Isentress, the first of a new class of AIDS drugs called integrase inhibitors. It also praised Merck for freezing prices for lower income users. Isentress, approved in 2007, is already used by 11 percent of the more than 550,000 people treated in the United States, Michael S. Seggev, a spokesman for Merck, said Wednesday. “We’re very pleased to have achieved the highest grade on the report card,” he said. “They’re the most respected and most representative coalition of H.I.V. community groups in the U.S., so their opinion is very meaningful.” The group gave an F to Abbott for raising the wholesale price of Norvir, the first drug proved to increase survival in AIDS patients, by 400 percent in 2003. Norvir is a key ingredient in most AIDS treatment cocktails. The price increaes provoked an outcry by many patients and others. An Abbott spokesman, Dirk van Eeden, responded Wednesday, “The H.I.V. community is an important stakeholder for us, so yes, we do take notice of the comments they make.” He added, “We really believe we’ve discovered important medicines and played our part in making sure the patients who need it can get it.” Other grades included a B for Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, owned by Johnson and Johnson as a separate company focusing on infectious diseases; C-plus for Pfizer, which announced in April a joint venture with GlaxoSmithKline to spin off a company focused on H.I.V.; C-plus for Gilead Sciences; C-minus grades for Bristol-Myers Squibb and GlaxoSmithKline, both criticized for high prices; a D-plus for Boehringer Ingelheim; and a D for Hoffman LaRoche, which the coalition said has the most expensive drug on the market. Representatives for Pfizer, Gilead and Boehringer responded Wednesday that they valued the group’s opinion and continued their work in AIDS. Bristol-Myers Squibb and GlaxoSmithKline officials each said they were “disappointed” and deserved better grades. Other companies did not respond immediately to requests for comment. The coalition was to some degree biting the hand that feeds it. It receives all of its financing from drug companies, mostly for activists to travel to meetings with them. The executive director, Edward T. Rewolinski, disclosed specific amounts to The New York Times for the last two years. “None of our members has the wherewithal to afford this activity,” he said. “People like that would never be influenced by the flow of money,” Jennifer Flynn, managing director of an unrelated AIDS group, Health GAP, in New York, said. The top fund provider was Gilead with $100,000, followed by Pfizer, $63,000; Bristol-Myers Squibb, $50,000; Tibotec, $45,000; Merck, $15,000; and Boehringer, $5,000. Abbott gave no money. Mr. Huff said the grading group was insulated from financing requests. “There’s no sugarcoating,” he said. “The membership feels that the pharmaceutical industry can be doing a much better job, whether it’s innovation or pricing.” The coalition was formed in 2001 partly to coordinate contacts with drug companies instead of letting the industry decide whom to invite to meetings.</text></article>
    <article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/13/business/13biotech.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Gilead, a White Knight, to Buy CV Therapeutics<date>Published: March 12, 2009</date><text>Gilead Sciences said on Thursday that it would acquire CV Therapeutics for about $1.4 billion. The deal, which tops a hostile takeover offer from Astellas Pharma of Japan, sent shares of CV Therapeutics up 31.5 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Gilead Sciences Incorporated CV Therapeutics Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » Gilead, which makes the H.I.V. drugs Truvada, Viread and Atriplia, said it had signed a definitive agreement to buy CV Therapeutics, which makes the cardiovascular drug Ranexa. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., offered $20 a share, higher than the $16-a-share offer from Astellas announced in January. Astellas turned hostile after the board of CV Therapeutics rejected the offer, saying it had undervalued the company. Representatives from Astellas were not immediately available for comment, but some analysts say they believe Astellas could come back with a higher offer. “We would not be surprised to see Astellas offer $22 to $24 per share to close a deal with CV Therapeutics,” said Joseph Schwartz, an analyst at Leerink Swann. “Astellas appears highly motivated to expand its cardiovascular sales presence in the U.S., and has sufficient flexibility to offer more to CV.” With CV, Gilead will gain Ranexa, a drug to treat chronic angina that generated $109.3 million in sales in the United States in 2008, up 64 percent in 2007. CV also makes Lexiscan, an injection used as a stress agent in cardiovascular procedures. The board of CV has approved the Gilead transaction, which will occur through a tender offer and second-step merger, and will recommend it to shareholders. Shares of Gilead jumped 39 cents, to $44.43 in trading on Nasdaq, while CV rose $5.04, or 31.5 percent, to $21.04. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on March 13, 2009, on page B6 of the New York edition.Gilead Sciences said on Thursday that it would acquire CV Therapeutics for about $1.4 billion. The deal, which tops a hostile takeover offer from Astellas Pharma of Japan, sent shares of CV Therapeutics up 31.5 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Gilead Sciences Incorporated CV Therapeutics Incorporated Go to your Portfolio » Gilead, which makes the H.I.V. drugs Truvada, Viread and Atriplia, said it had signed a definitive agreement to buy CV Therapeutics, which makes the cardiovascular drug Ranexa. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., offered $20 a share, higher than the $16-a-share offer from Astellas announced in January. Astellas turned hostile after the board of CV Therapeutics rejected the offer, saying it had undervalued the company. Representatives from Astellas were not immediately available for comment, but some analysts say they believe Astellas could come back with a higher offer. “We would not be surprised to see Astellas offer $22 to $24 per share to close a deal with CV Therapeutics,” said Joseph Schwartz, an analyst at Leerink Swann. “Astellas appears highly motivated to expand its cardiovascular sales presence in the U.S., and has sufficient flexibility to offer more to CV.” With CV, Gilead will gain Ranexa, a drug to treat chronic angina that generated $109.3 million in sales in the United States in 2008, up 64 percent in 2007. CV also makes Lexiscan, an injection used as a stress agent in cardiovascular procedures. The board of CV has approved the Gilead transaction, which will occur through a tender offer and second-step merger, and will recommend it to shareholders. Shares of Gilead jumped 39 cents, to $44.43 in trading on Nasdaq, while CV rose $5.04, or 31.5 percent, to $21.04.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="2">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/business/16gilead.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Gilead’s Drug Is Approved to Treat a Rare Disease<date>Published: June 16, 2007</date><text>Gilead Sciences won approval yesterday for a new drug to treat a life-threatening lung disease, stealing a march on another company, Encysive Pharmaceuticals, which learned yesterday that its similar drug would not be approved yet. The Gilead drug, Letairis, is a treatment for pulmonary arterial hypertension, which affects about 100,000 Americans, according to the Food and Drug Administration. It can cause severe shortness of breath and heart failure and, if untreated, leads to death in about three years, Gilead said. The approval of Letairis is a big step in an effort by Gilead, one of the largest biotechnology companies, to diversify beyond its successful drugs for H.I.V. and AIDS into drugs for heart and lung diseases. Its AIDS drugs accounted for about 70 percent of its $3 billion in revenues last year. Gilead obtained Letairis, also known as ambrisentan, by acquiring Myogen, a small Colorado biotech company, last year for $2.5 billion. Although pulmonary arterial hypertension is a fairly rare disease, there are already several treatments available for it, including Pfizer’s Revatio, which contains the same ingredient as its impotence pill, Viagra. Gilead’s Letairis is likely to compete most directly against Tracleer, a drug sold by the Swiss-based Actelion. Both drugs are so-called endothelin receptor antagonists, which work by relaxing blood vessels. The drug Thelin, developed by the Houston-based Encysive, works the same way. Late yesterday, Encysive said that the F.D.A. had declined to approve the drug, recommending instead another clinical trial to prove the drug’s efficacy. This is the third time the F.D.A. has declined to give the go-ahead to Thelin, which is approved in Europe and Canada. Because of the multiple delays, Encysive lost a big lead over Gilead in the race for approval. Gilead said its clinical trials showed that Letairis caused fewer cases of liver damage than Actelion’s drug. Nevertheless, the F.D.A., warning about liver damage and birth defects, is requiring Gilead to control carefully the distribution of the drug. Patients who use it are supposed to have blood tests for liver damage every month. Gilead said Letairis, a once-a-day pill, will cost $3,940 a month, about the same as Tracleer, which is also known as bosentan. The company said it was establishing programs to help uninsured or underinsured patients obtain the drug. Pulmonary arterial hypertension is marked by extremely high blood pressure in the arteries that supply blood to the lungs. That makes it hard for people to breathe or exert themselves. It also puts a strain on the heart that eventually leads to heart failure and death. The available drugs, including Letairis, can improve the ability of people to perform daily chores but do not restore normal health. In clinical trials Letairis improved the distance people could walk in six minutes by an average of 20 to 60 meters, or roughly 5 percent to 20 percent. The drug also slowed the disease. Geoffrey Meacham, an analyst with JPMorgan, estimated that worldwide sales could reach $1 billion by 2010. He wrote yesterday that the label for the drug captured its “first-class profile.” GlaxoSmithKline sells the drug outside the United States. Actelion’s Tracleer had sales in 2006 of about $722 million, up more than 40 percent from 2005. The approval of Letairis was announced after the close of trading. Gilead’s shares rose 19 cents, to $80.83, in regular trading and then more than $1.50 after hours. Encysive shares fell 50 cents, to $4.10, in regular trading and another 25 cents after hours. More Articles in Business »Gilead Sciences won approval yesterday for a new drug to treat a life-threatening lung disease, stealing a march on another company, Encysive Pharmaceuticals, which learned yesterday that its similar drug would not be approved yet. The Gilead drug, Letairis, is a treatment for pulmonary arterial hypertension, which affects about 100,000 Americans, according to the Food and Drug Administration. It can cause severe shortness of breath and heart failure and, if untreated, leads to death in about three years, Gilead said. The approval of Letairis is a big step in an effort by Gilead, one of the largest biotechnology companies, to diversify beyond its successful drugs for H.I.V. and AIDS into drugs for heart and lung diseases. Its AIDS drugs accounted for about 70 percent of its $3 billion in revenues last year. Gilead obtained Letairis, also known as ambrisentan, by acquiring Myogen, a small Colorado biotech company, last year for $2.5 billion. Although pulmonary arterial hypertension is a fairly rare disease, there are already several treatments available for it, including Pfizer’s Revatio, which contains the same ingredient as its impotence pill, Viagra. Gilead’s Letairis is likely to compete most directly against Tracleer, a drug sold by the Swiss-based Actelion. Both drugs are so-called endothelin receptor antagonists, which work by relaxing blood vessels. The drug Thelin, developed by the Houston-based Encysive, works the same way. Late yesterday, Encysive said that the F.D.A. had declined to approve the drug, recommending instead another clinical trial to prove the drug’s efficacy. This is the third time the F.D.A. has declined to give the go-ahead to Thelin, which is approved in Europe and Canada. Because of the multiple delays, Encysive lost a big lead over Gilead in the race for approval. Gilead said its clinical trials showed that Letairis caused fewer cases of liver damage than Actelion’s drug. Nevertheless, the F.D.A., warning about liver damage and birth defects, is requiring Gilead to control carefully the distribution of the drug. Patients who use it are supposed to have blood tests for liver damage every month. Gilead said Letairis, a once-a-day pill, will cost $3,940 a month, about the same as Tracleer, which is also known as bosentan. The company said it was establishing programs to help uninsured or underinsured patients obtain the drug. Pulmonary arterial hypertension is marked by extremely high blood pressure in the arteries that supply blood to the lungs. That makes it hard for people to breathe or exert themselves. It also puts a strain on the heart that eventually leads to heart failure and death. The available drugs, including Letairis, can improve the ability of people to perform daily chores but do not restore normal health. In clinical trials Letairis improved the distance people could walk in six minutes by an average of 20 to 60 meters, or roughly 5 percent to 20 percent. The drug also slowed the disease. Geoffrey Meacham, an analyst with JPMorgan, estimated that worldwide sales could reach $1 billion by 2010. He wrote yesterday that the label for the drug captured its “first-class profile.” GlaxoSmithKline sells the drug outside the United States. Actelion’s Tracleer had sales in 2006 of about $722 million, up more than 40 percent from 2005. The approval of Letairis was announced after the close of trading. Gilead’s shares rose 19 cents, to $80.83, in regular trading and then more than $1.50 after hours. Encysive shares fell 50 cents, to $4.10, in regular trading and another 25 cents after hours.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/03/business/03drugs.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Gilead Sciences Buys Myogen for $2.5 Billion<date>Published: October 3, 2006</date><text>DENVER, Oct. 2  Gilead Sciences, which makes drugs to treat H.I.V., announced plans on Monday to buy a rival, Myogen, for about $2.5 billion in cash, signaling its growing interest in developing pulmonary drugs. Gilead, which is based in Foster City, Calif., said that it would pay Myogen shareholders $52.50 a share, a premium of 50 percent over Fridays closing price of $35.08. The announcement caught many off-guard, not only for the acquisition price but because it represented a shift for Gilead out of its area of expertise in infectious diseases. An analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, Geoffrey Porges, said the offer indicated a possible bidding war for Myogen and reflected the scarcity of late-stage drugs in the pulmonary disease category. The president and chief executive of Gilead, John C. Martin, told analysts on Monday in a conference call that the acquisition would help the company build on its $365 million buyout of privately held Corus Pharma in August. Our planned acquisition of Myogen represents both a scientific and strategic step, Mr. Martin said. Myogen, which is based in the Denver suburb of Westminster, is developing a drug called ambrisentan to treat pulmonary arterial hypertension. It says it believes that information developed from two studies will support a drug application that it expects to file with the Food and Drug Administration by years end. An analyst at Argus Research, David Coleman, who has followed Myogen, said Gilead would probably be able to capitalize on the drug better than Myogen. Myogen also markets a drug called Flolan for treatment of primary pulmonary hypertension and has a study for a drug that could treat resistant hypertension. The deal is structured in two phases, with Myogen to become a wholly owned subsidiary of Gilead. Myogens board has approved the deal, which is expected to close by the end of the year, pending regulatory and other standard approvals. Gilead said the deal would increase earnings in 2007 and 2008. It does not expect Myogen to add to 2009 profit. Gilead, a biotechnology company, discovered Tamiflu for the treatment of flu and a range of drugs to treat life-threatening infectious diseases such as H.I.V. Gilead posted second-quarter net income of $265.2 million, or 56 cents a share, up 34 percent from $196 million, or 41 cents per share, in the previous second quarter. The company credited the jump to strong sales of its H.I.V. treatments. Myogen posted a net loss of $18.5 million, or 44 cents a share, in the second quarter compared with a net loss of 21.7 million, or 61 cents a share, in the second quarter of 2005. Myogen stock rose $16.36 a share yesterday, to $51.44. Shares of Gilead dropped $4.49, to $64.28 a share. More Articles in Business »DENVER, Oct. 2  Gilead Sciences, which makes drugs to treat H.I.V., announced plans on Monday to buy a rival, Myogen, for about $2.5 billion in cash, signaling its growing interest in developing pulmonary drugs. Gilead, which is based in Foster City, Calif., said that it would pay Myogen shareholders $52.50 a share, a premium of 50 percent over Fridays closing price of $35.08. The announcement caught many off-guard, not only for the acquisition price but because it represented a shift for Gilead out of its area of expertise in infectious diseases. An analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, Geoffrey Porges, said the offer indicated a possible bidding war for Myogen and reflected the scarcity of late-stage drugs in the pulmonary disease category. The president and chief executive of Gilead, John C. Martin, told analysts on Monday in a conference call that the acquisition would help the company build on its $365 million buyout of privately held Corus Pharma in August. Our planned acquisition of Myogen represents both a scientific and strategic step, Mr. Martin said. Myogen, which is based in the Denver suburb of Westminster, is developing a drug called ambrisentan to treat pulmonary arterial hypertension. It says it believes that information developed from two studies will support a drug application that it expects to file with the Food and Drug Administration by years end. An analyst at Argus Research, David Coleman, who has followed Myogen, said Gilead would probably be able to capitalize on the drug better than Myogen. Myogen also markets a drug called Flolan for treatment of primary pulmonary hypertension and has a study for a drug that could treat resistant hypertension. The deal is structured in two phases, with Myogen to become a wholly owned subsidiary of Gilead. Myogens board has approved the deal, which is expected to close by the end of the year, pending regulatory and other standard approvals. Gilead said the deal would increase earnings in 2007 and 2008. It does not expect Myogen to add to 2009 profit. Gilead, a biotechnology company, discovered Tamiflu for the treatment of flu and a range of drugs to treat life-threatening infectious diseases such as H.I.V. Gilead posted second-quarter net income of $265.2 million, or 56 cents a share, up 34 percent from $196 million, or 41 cents per share, in the previous second quarter. The company credited the jump to strong sales of its H.I.V. treatments. Myogen posted a net loss of $18.5 million, or 44 cents a share, in the second quarter compared with a net loss of 21.7 million, or 61 cents a share, in the second quarter of 2005. Myogen stock rose $16.36 a share yesterday, to $51.44. Shares of Gilead dropped $4.49, to $64.28 a share.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/13/business/13drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">F.D.A. Backs AIDS Pill to Be Taken Once a Day<date>Published: July 13, 2006</date><text>The first drug that allows AIDS to be treated by taking one pill a day won federal approval yesterday, a development that government officials said would both simplify and improve treatment of the disease. The drug, called Atripla, is a combination of three once-a-day drugs that are already on the market  Sustiva from Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Viread and Emtriva from Gilead Sciences. Only a decade ago, when cocktails of AIDS drugs began to be used, patients sometimes had to take two dozen or more pills a day. Atripla, which will be available this week or next, will have a wholesale price of $1,150 a month, equal to the sum of the prices of its components, James Loduca, a spokesman for Gilead, said. Both Gilead and Bristol-Myers will market the drug. The approval by the Food and Drug Administration yesterday, which was expected, came well before the October deadline for the agency to act. F.D.A. officials said they moved quickly because a once-a-day treatment would help people take their medicines faithfully. That would prevent the AIDS virus from gaining resistance to the drugs. “It’s one thing to have medicine available, but it will only be effective when people can indeed take it as they are supposed to,” Dr. Murray M. Lumpkin, an F.D.A. deputy commissioner, said at a news conference in Washington. Dr. Lumpkin said a once-a-day treatment would be particularly important for developing countries, where access to health care is more limited. Yet no announcement was made yesterday about when the drug would be available overseas and for what price. An agreement must first be reached with Merck &amp; Company, which sells Sustiva, also known as efavirenz, in developing countries under the name Stocrin. Jeffrey Sturchio, vice president for external affairs at Merck, said his company had “reached agreement on all the issues with Gilead.” He said it was now a matter of formalizing the agreement and then applying for approval in various countries. He predicted that Atripla would be available in some poor countries in the next several months at a price that would be roughly the sum of the heavily discounted prices at which the component drugs are now sold in those places. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., has become one of the most successful biotechnology companies, based on its AIDS drugs, which accounted for $1.4 billion of its $2 billion in revenue last year. One of its big sellers is Truvada, a once-a-day combination of Viread, also known as tenofovir, and Emtriva, also known as emtricitabine. Truvada is usually taken with another drug, like Bristol-Myers’s Sustiva. Yaron Werber, an analyst at Citigroup, which counts Gilead as a client, said that adding the Bristol-Myers drug into a three-drug combination pill would allow Gilead to take market share from GlaxoSmithKline, which sells a popular two-drug combination called Combivir. “I think the drug will do exceptionally well,” Mr. Werber said of Atripla. “The drug is now the most convenient on the market and it’s probably also the most potent.” More Articles in Business »The first drug that allows AIDS to be treated by taking one pill a day won federal approval yesterday, a development that government officials said would both simplify and improve treatment of the disease. The drug, called Atripla, is a combination of three once-a-day drugs that are already on the market  Sustiva from Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Viread and Emtriva from Gilead Sciences. Only a decade ago, when cocktails of AIDS drugs began to be used, patients sometimes had to take two dozen or more pills a day. Atripla, which will be available this week or next, will have a wholesale price of $1,150 a month, equal to the sum of the prices of its components, James Loduca, a spokesman for Gilead, said. Both Gilead and Bristol-Myers will market the drug. The approval by the Food and Drug Administration yesterday, which was expected, came well before the October deadline for the agency to act. F.D.A. officials said they moved quickly because a once-a-day treatment would help people take their medicines faithfully. That would prevent the AIDS virus from gaining resistance to the drugs. “It’s one thing to have medicine available, but it will only be effective when people can indeed take it as they are supposed to,” Dr. Murray M. Lumpkin, an F.D.A. deputy commissioner, said at a news conference in Washington. Dr. Lumpkin said a once-a-day treatment would be particularly important for developing countries, where access to health care is more limited. Yet no announcement was made yesterday about when the drug would be available overseas and for what price. An agreement must first be reached with Merck &amp; Company, which sells Sustiva, also known as efavirenz, in developing countries under the name Stocrin. Jeffrey Sturchio, vice president for external affairs at Merck, said his company had “reached agreement on all the issues with Gilead.” He said it was now a matter of formalizing the agreement and then applying for approval in various countries. He predicted that Atripla would be available in some poor countries in the next several months at a price that would be roughly the sum of the heavily discounted prices at which the component drugs are now sold in those places. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., has become one of the most successful biotechnology companies, based on its AIDS drugs, which accounted for $1.4 billion of its $2 billion in revenue last year. One of its big sellers is Truvada, a once-a-day combination of Viread, also known as tenofovir, and Emtriva, also known as emtricitabine. Truvada is usually taken with another drug, like Bristol-Myers’s Sustiva. Yaron Werber, an analyst at Citigroup, which counts Gilead as a client, said that adding the Bristol-Myers drug into a three-drug combination pill would allow Gilead to take market share from GlaxoSmithKline, which sells a popular two-drug combination called Combivir. “I think the drug will do exceptionally well,” Mr. Werber said of Atripla. “The drug is now the most convenient on the market and it’s probably also the most potent.”</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/health/09aids.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">New Medicine for AIDS Is One Pill, Once a Day<date>Published: July 9, 2006</date><text>The first complete treatment for AIDS that is taken once a day as a single pill is expected to be available soon. The pill, which combines three drugs made by two companies, would be a milestone in improving the simplicity of treatment for the disease, experts say. It should make it easier for people to take their medicine regularly, which is important for keeping the virus that causes the disease in check. Only a decade ago, when cocktails of AIDS drugs were first used, patients often had to take two or three dozen pills a day, some with food, some without, some so frequently patients had to get up in the middle of the night. Since then, the regimens have been whittled down to as few as two pills a day, and now, one. "Going down to one pill a day is amazing," said Keith Folger of Washington, who started on 36 pills a day about 11 years ago and expects to switch to the new pill when it becomes available. Mr. Folger, who is just leaving a job as director of community mobilization for the National Association of People With AIDS, said the pill would be "remarkable, especially for people who are starting on medication for the first time and are sort of freaked out that they will have to take pills for the rest of their lives." The new drug is a combination of drugs already on the market  Sustiva, sold by Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Truvada, sold by Gilead Sciences. Truvada is a combination of two Gilead drugs, Viread and Emtriva. The Food and Drug Administration is expected to approve the new drug as soon as this week. The agency has until October to act but is expected to do so much sooner, partly because the government has been encouraging companies to do just this sort of collaboration to come up with simpler AIDS drugs. The companies have not revealed the new drug's name or its price, though they have suggested it will cost roughly the same as Sustiva and Truvada bought separately, which is about $1,200 a month. There are already other AIDS pills that combine three drugs. One, made by a company in India, was recently approved by the F.D.A. for use in developing countries. But those other three-in-one pills generally contain older drugs and are taken twice a day. The drugs in the new pill already constitute the most widely prescribed regimen in the United States and one of the most effective. Doctors and securities analysts expect most people now taking Sustiva and Truvada separately to switch to the new pill. It is somewhat less certain how many people taking other drug combinations will switch. Some of them will not because the virus in their bodies is already resistant to one of the drugs in the new pill or because they cannot tolerate side effects. Sustiva, also known as efavirenz, can cause unsettlingly vivid dreams and birth defects. In addition, the new salmon-colored pill is about 1,500 milligrams, the size of a large vitamin pill, and some people may find it difficult to swallow. Going to a single pill could be especially important in poor countries, where patients have less access to medical care and more people are illiterate or uneducated. The vast majority of the nearly 40 million people in the world infected by H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, are in developing nations. In the United States there are about 1.1 million. Bristol-Myers and Gilead say they will make the new pill available at a sharply reduced price for developing nations, but details are still being worked out. They are negotiating with Merck &amp; Company, which sells efavirenz in those countries under the name stocrin. A once-daily treatment did not become feasible until a few years ago, with the development of individual drugs that needed to be taken only once a day. Still, no one company controlled all the drugs needed for an effective combination. It is rare for rivals to collaborate, though it has been done. Merck and Schering-Plough, for instance, have put two of their drugs into a combination cholesterol treatment called Vytorin. Executives at Bristol-Myers, discussing in 2003 how to increase sales of Sustiva, came up with the idea of approaching Gilead, which already had two once-a-day pills, Viread, also known as tenofovir, and Emtriva, or emtracitabine. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., is now the largest supplier of H.I.V. drugs. Talks were given further urgency when the F.D.A. summoned the two companies and Merck to a meeting in Washington in April 2004. The government was trying to encourage development of simpler pills as part of the president's plan to provide antiviral treatments to poor countries. The next month, the three companies announced their plan. But carrying it out was not easy. Simply combining the three chemicals produced a mixture that melted easily. 1 2Next Page » More Articles in Health »The first complete treatment for AIDS that is taken once a day as a single pill is expected to be available soon. The pill, which combines three drugs made by two companies, would be a milestone in improving the simplicity of treatment for the disease, experts say. It should make it easier for people to take their medicine regularly, which is important for keeping the virus that causes the disease in check. Only a decade ago, when cocktails of AIDS drugs were first used, patients often had to take two or three dozen pills a day, some with food, some without, some so frequently patients had to get up in the middle of the night. Since then, the regimens have been whittled down to as few as two pills a day, and now, one. "Going down to one pill a day is amazing," said Keith Folger of Washington, who started on 36 pills a day about 11 years ago and expects to switch to the new pill when it becomes available. Mr. Folger, who is just leaving a job as director of community mobilization for the National Association of People With AIDS, said the pill would be "remarkable, especially for people who are starting on medication for the first time and are sort of freaked out that they will have to take pills for the rest of their lives." The new drug is a combination of drugs already on the market  Sustiva, sold by Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Truvada, sold by Gilead Sciences. Truvada is a combination of two Gilead drugs, Viread and Emtriva. The Food and Drug Administration is expected to approve the new drug as soon as this week. The agency has until October to act but is expected to do so much sooner, partly because the government has been encouraging companies to do just this sort of collaboration to come up with simpler AIDS drugs. The companies have not revealed the new drug's name or its price, though they have suggested it will cost roughly the same as Sustiva and Truvada bought separately, which is about $1,200 a month. There are already other AIDS pills that combine three drugs. One, made by a company in India, was recently approved by the F.D.A. for use in developing countries. But those other three-in-one pills generally contain older drugs and are taken twice a day. The drugs in the new pill already constitute the most widely prescribed regimen in the United States and one of the most effective. Doctors and securities analysts expect most people now taking Sustiva and Truvada separately to switch to the new pill. It is somewhat less certain how many people taking other drug combinations will switch. Some of them will not because the virus in their bodies is already resistant to one of the drugs in the new pill or because they cannot tolerate side effects. Sustiva, also known as efavirenz, can cause unsettlingly vivid dreams and birth defects. In addition, the new salmon-colored pill is about 1,500 milligrams, the size of a large vitamin pill, and some people may find it difficult to swallow. Going to a single pill could be especially important in poor countries, where patients have less access to medical care and more people are illiterate or uneducated. The vast majority of the nearly 40 million people in the world infected by H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, are in developing nations. In the United States there are about 1.1 million. Bristol-Myers and Gilead say they will make the new pill available at a sharply reduced price for developing nations, but details are still being worked out. They are negotiating with Merck &amp; Company, which sells efavirenz in those countries under the name stocrin. A once-daily treatment did not become feasible until a few years ago, with the development of individual drugs that needed to be taken only once a day. Still, no one company controlled all the drugs needed for an effective combination. It is rare for rivals to collaborate, though it has been done. Merck and Schering-Plough, for instance, have put two of their drugs into a combination cholesterol treatment called Vytorin. Executives at Bristol-Myers, discussing in 2003 how to increase sales of Sustiva, came up with the idea of approaching Gilead, which already had two once-a-day pills, Viread, also known as tenofovir, and Emtriva, or emtracitabine. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., is now the largest supplier of H.I.V. drugs. Talks were given further urgency when the F.D.A. summoned the two companies and Merck to a meeting in Washington in April 2004. The government was trying to encourage development of simpler pills as part of the president's plan to provide antiviral treatments to poor countries. The next month, the three companies announced their plan. But carrying it out was not easy. Simply combining the three chemicals produced a mixture that melted easily. 1 2Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/12/world/asia/12aids.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">AIDS Groups in India Sue to Halt Patent for U.S. Drug<date>Published: May 12, 2006</date><text>NEW DELHI, May 11  AIDS groups this week brought an important test of India's new patent law, which restricts the ability of Indian companies to produce low-cost generic drugs. Skip to next paragraph China Rises Inside the New China A four-hour television series and interactive web site by The Times, The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation and the ZDF network of Germany. nytimes.com/chinarises » Two patients-rights groups asked Indian authorities to stop Gilead Sciences, a California biopharmaceutical company, from patenting the antiretroviral drug Viread  its brand-name version of tenofovir, which is available here as a generic drug. If it is patented, the groups contend, making the cheaper versions will become illegal, and the drug will become too costly for patients here and in other developing countries. "These generic drugs are not only consumed in India," said Leena Menghaney of Doctors Without Borders in New Delhi, which is working with the Indian groups on the issue. "People in Africa and the Caribbean are relying on India to produce these drugs," she said, later adding, "The quality matches that of U.S.-manufactured drugs, but the prices are affordable." The lawyers for the two groups  the Delhi Network of Positive People and the Indian Network for People Living with H.I.V./AIDS  presented arguments on Tuesday, contending that tenofovir is not a new drug, but a modified version of an earlier drug, and therefore not eligible for a new patent under India's new law. Those backing the legal challenge are hoping to gain a legal precedent for use in other patent applications. They say the recent rejection of a patent application by Novartis for a cancer drug, Gleevac, on the grounds of similar legal arguments, gave some cause for optimism. The World Health Organization recently recommended tenofovir for patients who are just starting treatment for AIDS and for those who have been receiving antiretroviral treatment therapy but who have become resistant to other treatments. In developed countries, Gilead's tenofovir costs $5,718 per patient per year. Cipla, one of the largest generic companies in India, is marketing a version called Tenvir, at a cost of $700 per person per year in India. Yusuf Hamied, chairman of Cipla, said the drug would eventually be made available in Africa for about half that price. But Tenvir would have to be withdrawn if Gilead were given a patent, which would be in effect for 12 years. Gilead Sciences said Thursday in an e-mail message, referring to its brand name for the drug: "We disagree with statements that Viread should not be patented; we believe that Viread represents innovation and is patentable under Indian law. We will use this patent responsibly, and will not block access to our medication in India or in other resource-limited countries where the H.I.V. epidemic has hit the hardest." The company, the message said, is "pursuing a broad policy of nonexclusive voluntary licensing under this patent to generic manufacturers in India for the local Indian market as well as provision for manufacturers to export product to the 97 developing-world countries included in Gilead's access program." More Articles in International »NEW DELHI, May 11  AIDS groups this week brought an important test of India's new patent law, which restricts the ability of Indian companies to produce low-cost generic drugs. Skip to next paragraph China Rises Inside the New China A four-hour television series and interactive web site by The Times, The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation and the ZDF network of Germany. nytimes.com/chinarises » Two patients-rights groups asked Indian authorities to stop Gilead Sciences, a California biopharmaceutical company, from patenting the antiretroviral drug Viread  its brand-name version of tenofovir, which is available here as a generic drug. If it is patented, the groups contend, making the cheaper versions will become illegal, and the drug will become too costly for patients here and in other developing countries. "These generic drugs are not only consumed in India," said Leena Menghaney of Doctors Without Borders in New Delhi, which is working with the Indian groups on the issue. "People in Africa and the Caribbean are relying on India to produce these drugs," she said, later adding, "The quality matches that of U.S.-manufactured drugs, but the prices are affordable." The lawyers for the two groups  the Delhi Network of Positive People and the Indian Network for People Living with H.I.V./AIDS  presented arguments on Tuesday, contending that tenofovir is not a new drug, but a modified version of an earlier drug, and therefore not eligible for a new patent under India's new law. Those backing the legal challenge are hoping to gain a legal precedent for use in other patent applications. They say the recent rejection of a patent application by Novartis for a cancer drug, Gleevac, on the grounds of similar legal arguments, gave some cause for optimism. The World Health Organization recently recommended tenofovir for patients who are just starting treatment for AIDS and for those who have been receiving antiretroviral treatment therapy but who have become resistant to other treatments. In developed countries, Gilead's tenofovir costs $5,718 per patient per year. Cipla, one of the largest generic companies in India, is marketing a version called Tenvir, at a cost of $700 per person per year in India. Yusuf Hamied, chairman of Cipla, said the drug would eventually be made available in Africa for about half that price. But Tenvir would have to be withdrawn if Gilead were given a patent, which would be in effect for 12 years. Gilead Sciences said Thursday in an e-mail message, referring to its brand name for the drug: "We disagree with statements that Viread should not be patented; we believe that Viread represents innovation and is patentable under Indian law. We will use this patent responsibly, and will not block access to our medication in India or in other resource-limited countries where the H.I.V. epidemic has hit the hardest." The company, the message said, is "pursuing a broad policy of nonexclusive voluntary licensing under this patent to generic manufacturers in India for the local Indian market as well as provision for manufacturers to export product to the 97 developing-world countries included in Gilead's access program."</text></article>
    <article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/17/business/17drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Accord on Sharing Flu Vaccine Production<date>Published: November 17, 2005</date><text>Correction Appended Under pressure to increase output of its flu drug Tamiflu, the Swiss pharmaceutical giant Roche agreed yesterday to share control of production and sales of the medicine with Gilead Sciences, the California biotechnology company that invented it. The agreement, which resolves a contract dispute, comes as governments around the world are trying to stockpile Tamiflu, in case the avian flu that is ravaging birds in Asia leads to a human epidemic. "Both Roche and Gilead recognized the urgent need to resolve our dispute and remove any distraction that might in any way impede Roche's ability to address an important global health need," John F. Milligan, Gilead's chief financial officer, said yesterday. Skip to next paragraph Noah Berger/Bloomberg News Gilead Sciences in Foster City, Calif., has resolved a contract dispute with Roche, allowing increased production of the flu drug Tamiflu. Gilead licensed exclusive rights to manufacture and sell Tamiflu, also known as oseltamivir, to Roche in 1996. But last June, Gilead demanded the rights back, accusing Roche of having breached the contract by failing to make and market the drug adequately. Roche denied that, saying there had simply been little interest in the drug from consumers or governments until the recent fears of a pandemic. "It became a drug which was difficult to commercialize," Franz Humer, chief executive of Roche, said in an interview yesterday. "We sat there with a drug in which we had invested a significant amount of development and where we had sales that were less than exciting." Under the agreement, Gilead said that it expected its royalty rate on Tamiflu sales for this year to increase to about 18 or 19 percent. Roche has previously estimated Tamiflu sales this year will triple to at least $755 million. Gilead's royalties would be up from an effective rate of about 10 percent until now, because the deal also means that Gilead will no longer have to contribute to Roche's manufacturing costs. Roche is paying Gilead $62.5 million to make that change retroactive to the beginning of 2004. Shares of Gilead rose nearly 8 percent, up $3.99 to close at $55.63. Shares of Roche fell 1.3 Swiss francs to 192.1 francs in Zurich. Tamiflu royalties are still small compared with the nearly $2 billion the company is expected to receive this year from drugs it sells by itself, particularly the AIDS drugs Viread and Truvada. John C. Martin, Gilead's chief executive, said in an interview that the companies had not been pressured to settle by government health authorities concerned about Tamiflu supplies. "No one has ever called me up to say we should resolve the dispute," he said. Under the new agreement, Roche will continue to produce and market the drug but committees with representatives from each company will oversee sales, manufacturing and overall strategy. That will give Gilead a say in which outside companies, if any, are allowed to produce Tamiflu. Roche said recently it would consider allowing other companies to make the drug and that it had received inquiries from about 150 companies or governments. Gilead will have the option of helping to promote Tamiflu to certain medical specialists in the United States. Roche has been unable to meet current demand for Tamiflu, which has shown effectiveness in animal studies at preventing death from avian flu. It has been used to treat some of the people in Southeast Asia infected with avian flu, with mixed results. So far more than 120 people in Southeast Asia have become infected by the H5N1 strain of avian flu and more than 60 have died. Roche said last week that it would vastly increase its production capacity, to a level of 300 million treatments annually in 2007. Gilead, which uses contract manufacturers to make its AIDS drugs, had been recruiting various contractors and raw material suppliers to make Tamiflu in the event it won back rights to the drug, Mr. Martin, the chief executive, said. The key raw material, shikimic acid, is extracted from star anise, a Chinese spice. Ching Shao, a businessman in Rockville, Md., said he had lined up 10,000 metric tons of star anise for Gilead. Now, he said, he hoped to deal with the joint Roche-Gilead committee. "Roche paid huge money to take Gilead away from production," he said. Correction: Nov. 18, 2005, Friday: A headline in Business Day yesterday about an agreement between Roche and Gilead Sciences to share production and sales of Tamiflu described the medicine incorrectly. It is a drug used to treat flu, not a vaccine to prevent it. More Articles in Business &gt;Correction Appended Under pressure to increase output of its flu drug Tamiflu, the Swiss pharmaceutical giant Roche agreed yesterday to share control of production and sales of the medicine with Gilead Sciences, the California biotechnology company that invented it. The agreement, which resolves a contract dispute, comes as governments around the world are trying to stockpile Tamiflu, in case the avian flu that is ravaging birds in Asia leads to a human epidemic. "Both Roche and Gilead recognized the urgent need to resolve our dispute and remove any distraction that might in any way impede Roche's ability to address an important global health need," John F. Milligan, Gilead's chief financial officer, said yesterday. Skip to next paragraph Noah Berger/Bloomberg News Gilead Sciences in Foster City, Calif., has resolved a contract dispute with Roche, allowing increased production of the flu drug Tamiflu. Gilead licensed exclusive rights to manufacture and sell Tamiflu, also known as oseltamivir, to Roche in 1996. But last June, Gilead demanded the rights back, accusing Roche of having breached the contract by failing to make and market the drug adequately. Roche denied that, saying there had simply been little interest in the drug from consumers or governments until the recent fears of a pandemic. "It became a drug which was difficult to commercialize," Franz Humer, chief executive of Roche, said in an interview yesterday. "We sat there with a drug in which we had invested a significant amount of development and where we had sales that were less than exciting." Under the agreement, Gilead said that it expected its royalty rate on Tamiflu sales for this year to increase to about 18 or 19 percent. Roche has previously estimated Tamiflu sales this year will triple to at least $755 million. Gilead's royalties would be up from an effective rate of about 10 percent until now, because the deal also means that Gilead will no longer have to contribute to Roche's manufacturing costs. Roche is paying Gilead $62.5 million to make that change retroactive to the beginning of 2004. Shares of Gilead rose nearly 8 percent, up $3.99 to close at $55.63. Shares of Roche fell 1.3 Swiss francs to 192.1 francs in Zurich. Tamiflu royalties are still small compared with the nearly $2 billion the company is expected to receive this year from drugs it sells by itself, particularly the AIDS drugs Viread and Truvada. John C. Martin, Gilead's chief executive, said in an interview that the companies had not been pressured to settle by government health authorities concerned about Tamiflu supplies. "No one has ever called me up to say we should resolve the dispute," he said. Under the new agreement, Roche will continue to produce and market the drug but committees with representatives from each company will oversee sales, manufacturing and overall strategy. That will give Gilead a say in which outside companies, if any, are allowed to produce Tamiflu. Roche said recently it would consider allowing other companies to make the drug and that it had received inquiries from about 150 companies or governments. Gilead will have the option of helping to promote Tamiflu to certain medical specialists in the United States. Roche has been unable to meet current demand for Tamiflu, which has shown effectiveness in animal studies at preventing death from avian flu. It has been used to treat some of the people in Southeast Asia infected with avian flu, with mixed results. So far more than 120 people in Southeast Asia have become infected by the H5N1 strain of avian flu and more than 60 have died. Roche said last week that it would vastly increase its production capacity, to a level of 300 million treatments annually in 2007. Gilead, which uses contract manufacturers to make its AIDS drugs, had been recruiting various contractors and raw material suppliers to make Tamiflu in the event it won back rights to the drug, Mr. Martin, the chief executive, said. The key raw material, shikimic acid, is extracted from star anise, a Chinese spice. Ching Shao, a businessman in Rockville, Md., said he had lined up 10,000 metric tons of star anise for Gilead. Now, he said, he hoped to deal with the joint Roche-Gilead committee. "Roche paid huge money to take Gilead away from production," he said. Correction: Nov. 18, 2005, Friday: A headline in Business Day yesterday about an agreement between Roche and Gilead Sciences to share production and sales of Tamiflu described the medicine incorrectly. It is a drug used to treat flu, not a vaccine to prevent it.</text></article>
    <article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/28/politics/28rummy.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Rumsfeld to Avoid Bird-Flu Drug Issues<date>Published: October 28, 2005</date><text>WASHINGTON, Oct. 27 - Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld has recused himself from government decisions concerning medications to prevent or treat avian flu, rather than sell his stock holdings in the company that patented the antiviral agent Tamiflu, according to a Pentagon memorandum issued Thursday. The memorandum, to Mr. Rumsfeld's staff from the Pentagon general counsel, said the defense secretary would not take part in decisions that may affect his financial interests in Gilead Sciences Inc. Before becoming defense secretary in January 2001, Mr. Rumsfeld was chairman of Gilead. On each of his annual financial disclosure statements, he has listed continued stock holdings in the company. Gilead holds the patent on Tamiflu, but contracts for it are signed with an American subsidiary of F. Hoffman-LaRoche Ltd., which holds marketing and manufacturing rights. Mr. Rumsfeld will remain involved in matters related to the Pentagon response to an outbreak, so long as none affect Gilead. More Articles in Washington &gt;WASHINGTON, Oct. 27 - Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld has recused himself from government decisions concerning medications to prevent or treat avian flu, rather than sell his stock holdings in the company that patented the antiviral agent Tamiflu, according to a Pentagon memorandum issued Thursday. The memorandum, to Mr. Rumsfeld's staff from the Pentagon general counsel, said the defense secretary would not take part in decisions that may affect his financial interests in Gilead Sciences Inc. Before becoming defense secretary in January 2001, Mr. Rumsfeld was chairman of Gilead. On each of his annual financial disclosure statements, he has listed continued stock holdings in the company. Gilead holds the patent on Tamiflu, but contracts for it are signed with an American subsidiary of F. Hoffman-LaRoche Ltd., which holds marketing and manufacturing rights. Mr. Rumsfeld will remain involved in matters related to the Pentagon response to an outbreak, so long as none affect Gilead.</text></article>
    <article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/19/business/19pharma.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Deal on H.I.V. Drug<date>Published: July 19, 2005</date><text>The biotechnology company Gilead Sciences said yesterday that it would pay about $341 million to acquire 65 percent of the royalty rights to its H.I.V. drug Emtriva, which are owned by Emory University. The other 35 percent will be bought by Royalty Pharma for about $184 million, making the deal worth $525 million. Under the agreement, Gilead will no longer owe Emory royalties on worldwide net sales of the product, but it will be obligated to make payments to Royalty Pharma based on future sales. Emtriva was first approved by United States regulators in 2003 and is a component of Gilead's Truvada, a pill that combines Emtriva with the H.I.V. drug Viread. More Articles in Business &gt;The biotechnology company Gilead Sciences said yesterday that it would pay about $341 million to acquire 65 percent of the royalty rights to its H.I.V. drug Emtriva, which are owned by Emory University. The other 35 percent will be bought by Royalty Pharma for about $184 million, making the deal worth $525 million. Under the agreement, Gilead will no longer owe Emory royalties on worldwide net sales of the product, but it will be obligated to make payments to Royalty Pharma based on future sales. Emtriva was first approved by United States regulators in 2003 and is a component of Gilead's Truvada, a pill that combines Emtriva with the H.I.V. drug Viread.</text></article>
    <article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/24/business/24tamiflu.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Partner Companies Fighting Over Rights to Avian Flu Drug<date>Published: June 24, 2005</date><text>Two drug companies are fighting over the rights to Tamiflu, an influenza drug that is viewed as the best hope for slowing a possible global pandemic of bird flu. Gilead Sciences, which invented the drug, said yesterday that it wanted to take back the rights to the drug from Roche, which makes and sells it. Gilead said Roche had not done enough to manufacture and promote the drug, thereby violating the 1996 contract between the companies. "We believe Roche has devoted only minimal effort to it," Gilead's chief financial officer, John F. Milligan, said in an interview. Mr. Milligan said that Roche had not started promoting the drug in 43 of the 64 countries in which it is approved. Roche's inadequate manufacturing efforts, he said, had led to shortages, and Gilead, after commissioning an audit, says that Roche owes it another $18 million in royalties. A spokesman for Roche, Terence Hurley, said his company was "deeply disappointed" at Gilead's action. "We strongly disagree with their decision but have every interest to resolve this issue with them." Mr. Hurley said Roche doubled production last year and planned to double it again this year. Under the contract, Roche can try to correct the perceived problems before losing its rights. It is also possible that the companies may renegotiate financial terms rather than switch manufacturing and sales. The dispute theoretically could affect the supply of Tamiflu. About 25 countries, including the United States, are stockpiling the drug as a first line of defense against a possible outbreak of avian influenza, or bird flu, which has no vaccine. While bird flu has affected only a small number of people in Asia so far, public health authorities fear that the virus will evolve into a form that can easily pass from person to person, which could lead to a global pandemic in which millions of people could die. Mr. Milligan of Gilead said he did not anticipate supply problems arising from the dispute. Roche said it would be "business as usual as our No. 1 commitment remains producing Tamiflu globally." Even if Gilead were to regain the rights, Roche would continue making the drug for two years. Bill Hall, a spokesman for the Department of Health and Human Services, said, "We do not have a concern about the supply of Tamiflu" stemming from the dispute. Tamiflu can reduce the duration of flu by one or two days if taken within the first 48 hours of symptoms. It can prevent flu if taken during a community outbreak . Gilead, a biotechnology company in Foster City, Calif., was a smaller company when it licensed Tamiflu to Roche, which is based in Basel, Switzerland. Now Gilead is one of the industry successes, mainly because of its H.I.V. drug Viread, which it sells itself. Tamiflu was approved in the United States in 1999. Since then, through the end of the first quarter of this year, Roche has sold $1.2 billion worth of the drug worldwide and paid Gilead royalties of $85.9 million, Mr. Milligan of Gilead said. More Articles in Business &gt;Two drug companies are fighting over the rights to Tamiflu, an influenza drug that is viewed as the best hope for slowing a possible global pandemic of bird flu. Gilead Sciences, which invented the drug, said yesterday that it wanted to take back the rights to the drug from Roche, which makes and sells it. Gilead said Roche had not done enough to manufacture and promote the drug, thereby violating the 1996 contract between the companies. "We believe Roche has devoted only minimal effort to it," Gilead's chief financial officer, John F. Milligan, said in an interview. Mr. Milligan said that Roche had not started promoting the drug in 43 of the 64 countries in which it is approved. Roche's inadequate manufacturing efforts, he said, had led to shortages, and Gilead, after commissioning an audit, says that Roche owes it another $18 million in royalties. A spokesman for Roche, Terence Hurley, said his company was "deeply disappointed" at Gilead's action. "We strongly disagree with their decision but have every interest to resolve this issue with them." Mr. Hurley said Roche doubled production last year and planned to double it again this year. Under the contract, Roche can try to correct the perceived problems before losing its rights. It is also possible that the companies may renegotiate financial terms rather than switch manufacturing and sales. The dispute theoretically could affect the supply of Tamiflu. About 25 countries, including the United States, are stockpiling the drug as a first line of defense against a possible outbreak of avian influenza, or bird flu, which has no vaccine. While bird flu has affected only a small number of people in Asia so far, public health authorities fear that the virus will evolve into a form that can easily pass from person to person, which could lead to a global pandemic in which millions of people could die. Mr. Milligan of Gilead said he did not anticipate supply problems arising from the dispute. Roche said it would be "business as usual as our No. 1 commitment remains producing Tamiflu globally." Even if Gilead were to regain the rights, Roche would continue making the drug for two years. Bill Hall, a spokesman for the Department of Health and Human Services, said, "We do not have a concern about the supply of Tamiflu" stemming from the dispute. Tamiflu can reduce the duration of flu by one or two days if taken within the first 48 hours of symptoms. It can prevent flu if taken during a community outbreak . Gilead, a biotechnology company in Foster City, Calif., was a smaller company when it licensed Tamiflu to Roche, which is based in Basel, Switzerland. Now Gilead is one of the industry successes, mainly because of its H.I.V. drug Viread, which it sells itself. Tamiflu was approved in the United States in 1999. Since then, through the end of the first quarter of this year, Roche has sold $1.2 billion worth of the drug worldwide and paid Gilead royalties of $85.9 million, Mr. Milligan of Gilead said.</text></article>
    <article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2D91330F932A15751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; JOINT VENTURE TO PRODUCE ONCE-A-DAY AIDS PILL<date>Published: December 21, 2004</date><text>The Bristol-Myers Squibb Company and Gilead Sciences have formed a joint venture to develop and market an H.I.V. treatment that combines three AIDS drugs in a once-a-day pill. The pill, which contains Bristol-Myers's Sustiva and Gilead's Viread and Emtriva drugs, would reduce the number of medicines AIDS patients take each day and help prevent doses from being missed. Bristol-Myers and Gilead said in May that they were discussing the joint venture. The companies plan to seek Food and Drug Administration approval for their new drug in the second half of 2005, a Gilead spokeswoman, Amy Flood, said yesterday. Gilead is based in Foster City, Calif. Bristol-Myers is based in New York.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="3">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/27/business/company-news-gilead-says-its-aids-treatment-is-better-than-glaxo-s.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; GILEAD SAYS ITS AIDS TREATMENT IS BETTER THAN GLAXO'S<date>Published: August 27, 2004</date><text>Gilead Sciences Inc. said early results from a study show that a combination of its AIDS drugs suppressed H.I.V. more effectively than a GlaxoSmithKline treatment. Researchers compared the effectiveness of Gilead's Viread and Emtriva medicines with Glaxo's Combivir after 24 weeks of a 48-week study. About 88 percent of patients getting the Gilead medicines had blood levels of H.I.V. below the target, compared with 80 percent of people on Combivir, Gilead said. A Glaxo spokeswoman, Mary Faye Dark, said it was too early in the study to draw conclusions. ''It's interesting to see what's happened at 24 weeks,'' she said in a telephone interview. ''Until you get to 48 weeks, you can't do too much with it.''</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/03/business/aids-medicines-are-approved.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">AIDS Medicines Are Approved<date>Published: August 03, 2004</date><text>Federal regulators said on Monday that they had approved two AIDS drug combinations designed to simplify treatment for patients in the United States and in poor countries.The makers, GlaxoSmithKline and Gilead Sciences, said they intended to provide the medicines at ''no-profit'' prices for needy nations. Glaxo also said it would give a free, 60-day supply of its combination drug, called Epzicom, to patients in the United States.The new combinations pair two medicines into one tablet, making treatment regimens easier to follow. Older therapies made patients juggle multiple pills and doses.Glaxo's Epzicom combines the company's H.I.V. medicines Epivir and Ziagen into a once-a-day pill. Gilead's once-a-day tablet, called Truvada, contains the AIDS-fighting drugs Viread and Emtriva.Proponents of aggressive treatment of AIDS around the world consider the easier-to-take combination pills vital to fighting the disease in Africa and the Caribbean.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/15/business/technology-briefing-biotechnology-gilead-sales-surge-on-aids-drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Technology Briefing | Biotechnology: Gilead Sales Surge On Aids Drug<date>Published: July 15, 2003</date><text>Gilead Sciences said yesterday that second-quarter sales soared as doctors wrote more prescriptions for its Viread AIDS drug. Shares rose as much as 15 percent. Revenue was $236 million to $239 million in the quarter, the company said in a statement. Analysts had expected $179 million, according to the average estimate from those surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sales of Viread were as much as $165 million, about $45 million higher than some analysts expected, and may mean that second-quarter earnings were also above forecasts, said Eric Schmidt, an analyst at SG Cowen Securities. Gilead already raised its forecast for 2003 sales of the drug by 18 percent to as much as $500 million in April. Before yesterday's announcement, analysts had expected the company, which reported a loss of $438.1 million, or $2.21 a share, in the first quarter, to earn 20 cents a share in the three months through June, according to a Thomson Financial survey. Shares rose $7.97, or 13.4 percent, to $67.25. after reaching $68.15, its highest price since it began trading in 1992.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/03/business/us-approves-new-once-a-day-aids-drug-from-glaxo-rival.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">U.S. Approves New Once-a-Day AIDS Drug From Glaxo Rival<date>Published: July 03, 2003</date><text>Gilead Sciences received approval yesterday from the Food and Drug Administration for a new once-a-day AIDS drug, Emtriva, setting the stage for competition with GlaxoSmithKline.Gilead obtained Emtriva by acquiring Triangle Pharmaceuticals, its developer, for $464 million a few months ago.People infected with H.I.V. generally take three drugs at a time and sometimes have to take many pills a day. Gilead hopes that its two AIDS drugs, both of which are taken once a day, will offer patients convenience.Emtriva appears to be aimed to compete directly with lamivudine, the most widely used AIDS drug, which is sold by GlaxoSmithKline as Epivir. Glaxo has had great success combining lamivudine with another drug, AZT, into a combination pill called Combivir.Gilead now hopes to take the same tack by combining Emtriva with its other H.I.V. drug, Viread, which is also taken once a day.''This provides the first real convenient alternative to Combivir,'' said John Milligan, chief financial officer of Gilead, which is based in Foster City, Calif.A single pill containing Emtriva and Viread could reach the market by 2005, he said. The company is planning a clinical trial to test the combination pill against Combivir.But even as two separate pills, he said, Viread and Emtriva could compete immediately against Combivir, which is taken twice a day. Gilead said the wholesale price of Emtriva would be about $250 a month.The market for AIDS drugs is crowded but patients often have to switch drugs because the virus develops resistance to the ones they are taking.Emtriva, which is known generically as emtricitabine, belongs to the most common category of H.I.V. drugs called nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors. They interfere with reverse transcriptase, an enzyme the virus needs to replicate.Emtriva is the third Gilead drug approved in the last two years, following Viread and Hepsera, for hepatitis B. The company, which focuses on antiviral drugs, has a market valuation of about $11 billion, the third largest in the biotech business behind Amgen and Genentech.Shares of Gilead rose $1.36, to $56.36.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/05/business/acquisition-by-gilead-to-expand-drug-line.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Acquisition by Gilead to Expand Drug Line<date>Published: December 05, 2002</date><text>Gilead Sciences said yesterday that it would buy Triangle Pharmaceuticals for $464 million in cash to expand its line of drugs to treat AIDS and hepatitis B.Gilead already sells an AIDS drug, called Viread. Triangle is seeking federal approval for its own AIDS drug, Coviracil, which would be its first product.Gilead executives said they hoped to market the two drugs together and to combine them into a single pill. That would allow the company to compete better with GlaxoSmithKline, which has had great success with Combivir, which combines two AIDS drugs into one pill.''Most of the sales Glaxo's generating are in combination form,'' said Mark L. Perry, Gilead's executive vice president for operations. The extra convenience is a significant marketing advantage because people infected with the virus that causes AIDS often have to take numerous pills each day. He said a combination of Viread and Coviracil would have an advantage because it would be taken once a day, whereas Glaxo's is taken twice daily.The acquisition could be one of a spree of mergers that analysts say might take place because many biotechnology companies are running out of cash at a time when low stock prices make raising money difficult. Triangle, based in Durham, N.C., had $60 million in cash, which would have lasted less than a year.The acquisition by Gilead ''solves a lot of problems in the type of market we're in,'' said Robert F. Amundsen Jr., Triangle's chief financial officer. ''It enables us to develop the drugs without the constant hangover of the strain of raising money.''Under the agreement, Gilead will make a tender offer for all of Triangle's stock for $6 a share, a third above Triangle's closing price on Tuesday. It would then pay $6 for any shares not tendered.Yesterday, shares of Triangle rose $1.32, or 29 percent, to $5.82. Shares of Gilead jumped 73 cents, to close at $37.61.Such an increase in stock price is rare for the acquiring company but seemed to reflect the opinion of investors that the deal made sense for Gilead because of the overlap of the companies.Coviracil, which could be approved to treat AIDS by next September, is also being tested in a late-stage clinical trial as a treatment for hepatitis B. Triangle has two other drugs in midstage clinical trials, one for AIDS and one for hepatitis B.Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., is expecting its first full year of profitability this year, based on sales of Viread, which was approved in October 2001, and Hepsera, a hepatitis B drug that was approved in September.Besides needing cash, Triangle, was searching for a marketing partner for Coviracil after the breakup of its alliance with Abbott Laboratories in July.</text></article>
    <article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/21/business/fda-approves-gilead-hepatitis-drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">F.D.A. Approves Gilead Hepatitis Drug<date>Published: September 21, 2002</date><text>The Food and Drug Administration said today that it approved the Hepsera drug from Gilead Sciences Inc. for treating infections with the hepatitis B virus, clearing the way for the company's second antiviral drug introduction in less than a year.Hepsera, known generically as adefovir dipivoxil, has been shown to be effective in treating patients with clinical evidence of the hepatitis B virus that is resistant to another approved antiviral therapy called lamivudine, the F.D.A. said.Hepsera is the second approved treatment for the hepatitis B virus, an F.D.A. spokesman said.Gilead said it would begin shipping the drug to wholesalers early next week.Gilead, which is based in Foster City, Calif., became a biotechnology power last year with the introduction of Viread, a promising H.I.V. treatment, which some analysts believe can eventually achieve blockbuster sales of more than $1 billion a year.United States and European sales of Hepsera are expected to reach $500 million a year, said David Bouchey, an analyst at C. E. Unterberg, Towbin. Gilead could reap up to another $100 million annually in royalties on sales of the drug in Asia and South America by its marketing partner GlaxoSmithKline, he added.In 1999, the F.D.A. turned down Gilead's application for adefovir as a treatment for H.I.V. infection, citing concerns about potential kidney damage.Gilead came back with a lower dose proposed for treating chronic hepatitis B, a blood-borne viral infection that can lead to cirrhosis, liver cancer and death. An estimated 1.25 million Americans have chronic hepatitis B.</text></article>
    <article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/11/business/company-news-shares-of-cubist-fall-after-venture-with-gilead-ends.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; SHARES OF CUBIST FALL AFTER VENTURE WITH GILEAD ENDS<date>Published: September 11, 2002</date><text>Shares of Cubist Pharmaceuticals fell 30 percent after the drug maker and Gilead Sciences ended a collaboration to market Cubist's experimental antibiotic Cidecin in Europe. Shares of Cubist fell $2.24, to $5.16. A study last month showed Cidecin was not effective in treating pneumonia. Cubist will file for Food and Drug Administration approval of Cidecin for treating skin infections later this year, the company said. Gilead will focus on virus-fighting drugs.</text></article>
    <article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/07/business/fda-panel-recommends-approval-of-hepatitis-b-drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">F.D.A. Panel Recommends Approval of Hepatitis B Drug<date>Published: August 07, 2002</date><text>A Food and Drug Administration advisory committee unanimously recommended approval yesterday for the Gilead Sciences drug adefovir for hepatitis B, a viral infection for which there are few good treatments.If the F.D.A. follows the panel's recommendation, as it usually does, the once-a-day pill could be on the market by September, said John Milligan, senior vice president at Gilead, a biotechnology company in Foster City, Calif.The panel's vote, 15 to 0, represents a comeback for adefovir, which a few years ago was rejected by the F.D.A. as a treatment for those who are H.I.V. positive because it could damage kidneys.For hepatitis B, Gilead tested a much lower dose, which seemed to largely eliminate that problem. Still, some members of the advisory committee cautioned that kidney damage might emerge when the drug was used longer than the 48 weeks for which patients were observed in Gilead's clinical trials.About 400 million people worldwide, including 1.25 million in the United States, are chronically infected with the hepatitis B virus, which can lead to cirrhosis of the liver or cancer, though often not for decades. About 30 percent of those chronically infected will eventually die from the disease, said Dr. Robert Gish, medical director of the liver transplant program at California Pacific Medical Center in San Francisco.Dr. Gish, who participated in the clinical trials of adefovir and is a consultant to Gilead, called the drug a major advance that ''could help hepatitis patients live years longer'' by suppressing the virus and reversing liver scarring. However, he said, it is not a cure.Among those testifying at the advisory panel meeting in Bethesda, Md., yesterday was Larry Kramer, the writer and advocate for AIDS patients who is often critical of drug companies. Mr. Kramer, who had a liver transplant last December because of hepatitis B, called adefovir a ''wonder drug.''There are now two drugs approved for hepatitis B, alpha interferon and lamivudine, also called 3TC, which is sold as the AIDS drug epivir. But the hepatitis B virus often develops resistance to lamivudine.Adefovir appears to work on the lamivudine-resistant virus, according to Gilead's data. Resistance has not been seen with adefovir, though some members of the F.D.A. advisory panel cautioned that it could eventually emerge with prolonged use of the drug.Adefovir could become the second drug approved within a year for Gilead, after the approval last October of Viread, a drug to treat those who are H.I.V. positive. The company, whose stock did not trade yesterday, turned profitable last quarter on sales of Viread.Kris Jenner, medical portfolio manager at T. Rowe Price, said adefovir might reach sales of $200 million to $300 million a year, making it less important to the company than Viread, which might reach $800 million to $1 billion in annual sales.Other drugs for hepatitis B are being tested by companies like Bristol-Myers Squibb and Triangle Pharmaceuticals, and the first of these might reach the market in 18 months, Dr. Gish said.GlaxoSmithKline has the rights to adefovir in Asia and Latin America, where hepatitis B rates are higher than in the United States. In this country, the number of new cases has dropped because of vaccinations.</text></article>
    <article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/27/business/company-news-osi-to-acquire-gilead-s-cancer-business.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; OSI TO ACQUIRE GILEAD'S CANCER BUSINESS<date>Published: November 27, 2001</date><text>OSI Pharmaceuticals will acquire the cancer business of Gilead Sciences for about $200 million in cash and stock to bolster its pipeline of experimental oncology products, the companies said yesterday. OSI will acquire Gilead's clinical candidates in oncology, the study of tumors, and all related intellectual property, as well as its operations in Boulder, Colo., including clinical research and drug development personnel, infrastructure and plants. OSI, which is based in Melville, N.Y., will pay Gilead $130 million in cash and $40 million in OSI common stock. Gilead, which is based in Foster City, Calif., said the deal would allow it to focus on its infectious diseases business. (Reuters)</text></article>
    <article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/04/business/company-news-fda-panel-supports-gilead-sciences-aids-drug.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; F.D.A. PANEL SUPPORTS GILEAD SCIENCES AIDS DRUG<date>Published: October 4, 2001</date><text>An advisory panel to the Food and Drug Administration gave its support yesterday to the Gilead Sciences experimental AIDS drug Viread which helps reduce levels of H.I.V. The committee urged approval for Viread, a once-a-day pill that has shown effectiveness against H.I.V. strains that resist other treatments. Nine members recommended restricting the approval to patients who have developed resistance to other therapies. Seven members voted in favor of clearing Viread for treating all adults with H.I.V. Viread would be added to other medicines as part of a multidrug mix. Approval is still needed from the full F.D.A. Gilead said it expected a final decision by Nov. 1.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="4">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/02/business/company-news-gilead-sciences-to-acquire-nexstar-pharmaceuticals.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; GILEAD SCIENCES TO ACQUIRE NEXSTAR PHARMACEUTICALS<date>Published: March 02, 1999</date><text>Gilead Sciences Inc. said yesterday that it planned to buy Nexstar Pharmaceuticals Inc. for $550 million in stock, bolstering its portfolio of drugs to treat infectious diseases and cancer. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., markets Vistide, which is used to treat an infection that harms the vision of people with AIDS. Nexstar, based in Boulder, Colo., sells Ambisome, used in the treatment of fungal infections, and Daunoxome, used to treat Kaposi's sarcoma, another condition often found in connection with AIDS. Shares of Nexstar rose $1.3125, to $15.125, while Gilead fell 50 cents, to $40.75.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/04/07/business/cephalon-falls-as-fda-meeting-is-canceled.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Cephalon Falls as F.D.A. Meeting Is Canceled<date>Published: April 07, 1998</date><text>Shares in Cephalon Inc. dropped 21 percent yesterday after the company said Federal regulators had canceled an advisory panel meeting to review its new treatment for Lou Gehrig's disease.The Food and Drug Administration panel meeting had been scheduled for Thursday. A similar panel recommended against approval of the drug, Myotrophin, last May, saying there was insufficient evidence that it helped sufferers of this fatal central nervous system disorder.A second big biotechnology stock was also making news yesterday, but it rose. Shares in Gilead Sciences Inc. gained about 20 percent after the company published better-than-expected results from clinical trials of a potential new AIDS drug. Preliminary data showed that the drug, Preveon, appears to increase the effectiveness of the multidrug ''cocktails'' typically given to AIDS patients.Cephalon shares closed at $12.1875, down $3.1875, while shares in the Chiron Corporation, its marketing and development partner in Myotrophin, closed at $20.875, down 68.75 cents, or 3.19 percent, both on the Nasdaq. Gilead shares gained $7.125 to close at $43.25 on the Nasdaq.Jason Rubin, a spokesman for Cephalon, said the F.D.A. gave no reason for canceling the meeting, except that it was not prepared to make a presentation to the advisory panel. He said the company was awaiting further word from the F.D.A. before determining how to proceed.Myotrophin's approval has been in doubt. While a study in the United States showed the drug could prolong the lives of patients, a study in Europe failed to confirm this result.Although investors assumed the canceled meeting was bad news for Cephalon, which is based in West Chester, Pa., Viren Mehta, an analyst with Mehta Partners, said he believed the F.D.A. had decided to approve the drug and had canceled the advisory panel meeting as unnecessary.''Most people want this drug to be available because there really is no alternative,'' he said.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/31/business/shares-in-maker-of-a-flu-drug-soar-but-competitor-has-edge.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Shares in maker of a flu drug soar, but competitor has edge.<date>Published: January 31, 1997</date><text>SHARES in Gilead Sciences Inc. soared earlier this week after the company announced that it would soon begin clinical trials of a drug to treat influenza. But a little-known Australian company, Biota Holdings Ltd., has a similar drug well advanced in human trials, and could beat Gilead to market by at least two years.Analysts like Gilead because it is one of the few biotechnology companies that has an approved drug -- Vistide, for CMV Retinitis, a condition that can cause blindness in AIDS patients -- and because it has a deep pipeline of anti-viral drugs. That may justify the company's $1 billion market capitalization, with or without the flu pill. Gilead also has other drugs in clinical trials for AIDS, herpes and genital warts, and $300 million in cash. Gilead shares closed yesterday at $31.875, up 12.5 cents, on the Nasdaq.Biota, on the other hand, is focused purely on influenza. The company's lead drug candidate, Zanamivir, recently completed the second of three phases of clinical trials typically required for approval by the Food and Drug Administration, and could, if the third trial goes well, reach market late in 1998. Zanamivir is to be produced and marketed by Glaxo Wellcome, with Biota receiving a 6 percent royalty on sales.In addition, Biota announced on Tuesday that Biostar Inc. of Boulder, Colo., would use Biota's technology to develop an influenza diagnostic kit for doctors' offices.So is Biota a good investment? That depends on the likelihood of its drug being approved, the potential size of the market and the likelihood of competition from Gilead, probably in that order. Biota, which is based in Melbourne, is listed on the Australian stock market, but its American depository receipts trade in the United States on the over-the-counter ''pink sheets'' at a ratio of three shares to each receipt. Biota A.D.R.'s closed yesterday at $6.875, giving the company a market valuation less than $150 million.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/29/us/in-animal-tests-new-pill-seems-to-stop-flu.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">In Animal Tests, New Pill Seems to Stop Flu<date>Published: January 29, 1997</date><text>A newly developed pill has been able to prevent or cure influenza infections in tests on animals, researchers said today.The scientists said the compound, which interferes with the reproduction of the flu virus, will be ready to test in people in several months. If the drug proves safe and effective, they said, it may be possible in a few years for people to cut flu infections short or to ward off flu each winter by taking a pill or two each day.A similar anti-flu drug licensed by Glaxo Wellcome, based in London, is already being tested on people, but that drug must be inhaled instead of being taken in pill form.Dr. Choung U. Kim and Dr. Norbert Bischofberger, researchers with Gilead Sciences of Foster City, Calif., said at a news conference here today that their oral compound, called GS 4104, had been tested on five animal species and appeared to block infections by all major flu strains while producing no adverse effects.''It's a big leap to jump from animals to humans, but we have every indication it will work in the same way,'' Dr. Bischofberger said. ''We think it will give people a new option for the control of influenza.''The company has petitioned the Food and Drug Administration for permission to begin limited human trials to address drug dosage and safety issues. Those trials would be run before more extensive tests to see if the compound staves off flu infections in healthy volunteers.In a paper appearing in the Jan. 29 issue of The Journal of the American Chemical Society, the Gilead researchers and colleagues at the Australian National University and the University of California at Berkeley describe how they developed a series of chemicals to inhibit the activity of neuraminidase, an enzyme on the surface of the flu virus. By studying the crystalline structure of the enzyme, they said, they created compounds that bound closely to the protein and blocked its activity.Dr. Kim said the flu virus infected cells in its host, reproduced inside these cells and then broke out to spread the infection to other cells. Neuraminidase on cell membranes allows the virus to escape, he said, so inhibiting the enzyme blocks the virus and checks the infection.GS 4104 is not the first neuraminidase inhibitor developed to attack flu, researchers said, but it is the first that can be taken orally. The drug primarily works on cells in the lungs, the primary infection site for the flu virus.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/09/business/pharmacia-upjohn-in-marketing-pact-with-gilead.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">PHARMACIA &amp; UPJOHN IN MARKETING PACT WITH GILEAD<date>Published: August 09, 1996</date><text>Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn Inc. said yesterday that it would pay Gilead Sciences Inc. $60 million for overseas rights to a drug that helps AIDS patients fight blindness. Pharmacia plans to pay Gilead an initial fee of $10 million for the drug, to be sold under the name Vistide. After receiving European marketing clearance, Pharmacia plans to pay an additional $10 million, and to acquire $40 million of newly issued Gilead preferred shares. Additional financial terms, including royalty payments, were not disclosed. Gilead shares closed at $19.125, up $1.50 in Nasdaq trading. Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., received Food and Drug Administration approval in June to sell Vistide.</text></article>
    <article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/19/business/panel-backs-retinitis-drug-gilead-stock-recovers-some.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Panel Backs Retinitis Drug; Gilead Stock Recovers Some<date>Published: March 19, 1996</date><text>Sometimes you have to stay to the end of the meeting.Shares in Gilead Sciences Inc. plunged $8, or more than 20 percent, on Friday, prompting a halt in trading, when it was disclosed that the company's drug Vistide, under review as a treatment to prevent blindness from cytomegalovirus retinitis in AIDS patients, had caused tumors in female laboratory rats.But by the end of the day, it was also disclosed that the drug had not caused corresponding cancers in monkeys or human beings, and a Food and Drug Administration advisory panel recommended that it be approved.Trading never resumed on Friday, but Gilead shares opened $8 higher today, and closed at $30, up $3.25, after hitting a high of $35.50 on extremely heavy Nasdaq volume."Vistide represents a significant advance in the treatment of CMV," John C. Martin, Gilead's chief operating officer, said in a statement. "Loss of sight remains one of the greatest fears of people with AIDS, and the data demonstrate that Vistide can help stave off blindness in these patients."Although the F.D.A. is not bound to follow the recommendations of its advisory panels, it usually does, and analysts said it was almost certain that Vistide would be approved later this year. If so, it would be the first approval for Gilead, based in Foster City, Calif., and the first for a new class of drugs called nucleotide analogs -- small molecules that mimic the shape of natural oligonucleotides, the strands of DNA that make up genes.Although the finding of cancer in rats seems to have been set aside, the approval recommendation for Vistide has been made despite some severe side effects, primarily kidney damage. It can be ameliorated by simultaneously dosing patients with the drug probenecid and increasing the water content in their bodies by intravenous hydration.Analysts said this kidney toxicity might ultimately limit the market for Vistide, although the two existing treatments for this kind of retinitis, ganciclovir, made by Hoffmann-LaRoche, a unit of Roche Holding, and foscarnet from Astra A.B. of Sweden, also have severe side effects."It's still a very toxic drug, and that will cause concern in the patient community," said Richard Vandenbrock of Hambrecht &amp; Quist.Perhaps the most important advantage for Vistide over the existing drugs is that a dose lasts longer, so that after an initial two doses, it requires intravenous infusions only every other week. Both ganciclovir and foscarnet are given in long infusions several times a week, which typically requires a catheter to be surgically implanted in the chest.Vistide also faces competition from Vitrasert, made by the Chiron Corporation, an implantable device that delivers ganciclovir directly to the eye. It received F.D.A. approval this month. In addition, Isis Pharmaceuticals has a drug in advanced clinical trials.</text></article>
    <article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/17/us/drug-appears-to-prevent-infection-by-an-aids-type-virus.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Drug Appears to Prevent Infection by an AIDS-Type Virus<date>Published: November 17, 1995</date><text>To the enormous surprise of researchers, an experimental drug completely prevented monkeys in one study from becoming infected with a virus that resembles the one that causes AIDS. Never before have scientists been able to prevent the transmission of the monkey virus, called S.I.V., for simian immunodeficiency virus.Researchers urged caution in jumping to conclusions about preventing infections with the AIDS virus itself or treating people who are already infected with the virus. Studies in humans, tentatively planned for next year, would be necessary to establish the drug's safety and efficacy in people.But researchers say that they are greatly encouraged by the work, and that the findings do offer hope that the same drug might protect health care workers who are accidentally exposed to H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS.In a paper being published today in the journal Science, investigators report that they gave the new drug, called PMPA, to 25 monkeys before or up to 24 hours after they inoculated the animals with S.I.V. None of the monkeys became infected with the virus. But when they gave 10 monkeys sham injections with salt water before inoculating them with S.I.V., every one became infected.PMPA, whose full name is (R)-9-(2)-Phosphonylmethoxypropyl)adenine, is made by Gilead Sciences of Foster City, Calif. A spokeswoman for Gilead, Lana Lauher, said the company hoped to conduct tests with humans in 1996.The research, by Dr. Che-Chung Tsai of the Regional Primate Research Center at the University of Washington in Seattle and his colleagues, has taken experts aback."It sounds almost too good to be true," said Dr. Marta Marthas, a virologist at the Regional Primate Research Center at the University of California at Davis. But, Dr. Marthas added, "You can't argue with that result."Dr. Ashley Haase, an expert on lentiviruses, the virus family that includes H.I.V. and S.I.V., said he was "surprised and pleased," by the finding. Dr. Haase added that the study was carefully done and that it was "if anything, more difficult" to protect against S.I.V. than it was to protect against H.I.V. infections.Dr. Anthony S. Fauci, the director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, said, "The results are very crisp and clear," but he cautioned against assuming that PMPA would cure people already infected with H.I.V."It is a majestic leap to go from the initial blocking of infection to the elimination of a virus," Dr. Fauci said.</text></article>
    <article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/12/business/company-news-gilead-in-deal-on-development-of-eyedrop-formula.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">COMPANY NEWS; GILEAD IN DEAL ON DEVELOPMENT OF EYEDROP FORMULA<date>Published: August 12, 1994</date><text>Gilead Sciences Inc., a drug research company, said yesterday that the American Cyanamid Company had agreed to develop and market an eyedrop form of its product to treat eye infections. Terms of the deal were not disclosed. Under the agreement, Cyanamid's ophthalmology unit, the Storz Instrument Company, has worldwide marketing rights and will develop and market Gilead's product. Gilead is based in Foster City, Calif.</text></article>
    <article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/06/08/health/search-advances-for-antisense-drugs.html?ref=gileadsciencesinc">Search Advances For 'Antisense' Drugs<date>Published: June 08, 1993</date><text>SCIENTISTS at a small biotechnology company have taken a significant step toward developing a new class of drugs designed to block the action of specific genes. Such drugs hold the potential to treat many viruses and cancers that elude current therapies.The drugs are an improved version of "antisense" agents, chemicals intended to target and impede messenger RNA, which mediates translation of the genetic information of DNA into specific proteins. The researchers, from Gilead Sciences Inc. of Foster City, Calif., report their findings in the current issue of Science.Antisense molecules have a sequence of bases that is opposite to that of the RNA molecules they target and therefore bind closely to them, since bases in nucleotide molecules attract their opposite pairs. Since messenger RNA is designed to function as a single stranded molecule, a double-stranded region caused by an antisense molecule will halt its operation and prevent the synthesis of whatever protein the messenger specifies. Chief New GainAlthough the theory of antisense is elegant, in practice antisense molecules have not proved particularly effective in the past, in part because they do not bind tightly enough to the target messenger RNA's. The principal advance described by the Gilead researchers is a method for modifying the component bases of the antisense molecule so that it grasps its target much more firmly. The method is to add to the base a small chemical group known as a propyne group."The difficulty with the whole antisense approach has been that it sounded great on paper but when you really tried to do it there were a lot of problems," said Fred Cohen, an associate professor of biochemistry and biophysics at the University of California at San Francisco. "They've made a real chemistry advance here, in a simple way, and in a way not likely to cause problems.""We made a modification to the base of the nucleotide -- a very simple modification -- which it turns out, increases their affinity tremendously to single strand DNA" and also RNA, said Brian C. Froehler, a principal scientist at Gilead. Binding affinity, a measure of potency, was increased by 10 to 100 times, according to the Science paper.The modifications made by the Gilead team only work with the T and C bases. The team is currently working on modifications of the A and G bases, which require different chemistry.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="5"/>
  <page index="6"/>
  <page index="7"/>
  <page index="8"/>
  <page index="9"/>
  <page index="10"/>
</root>
