<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="H. J. Heinz Company"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/26/business/media/ketchup-moves-upmarket-with-a-balsamic-tinge.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Ketchup Moves Upmarket, With a Balsamic Tinge<date>Published: October 25, 2011</date><text>TO emphasize its thickness, Heinz ketchup introduced a series of commercials in the 1970s that featured “Anticipation,” the Carly Simon song, which played as actors waited longingly for ketchup to pour onto burgers and fries.In the era of squeeze bottles, patience is no longer required, but to create anticipatory buzz for a new ketchup variety, Heinz initially will limit its availability. Heinz Tomato Ketchup Blended with Balsamic Vinegar, which substitutes balsamic for the traditional white vinegar, will first be available on Nov. 14 — but not in stores. Rather, consumers will be able to buy the ketchup only through the brand’s Facebook page until the product begins to appear in supermarkets in late December. Facebook visitors will be encouraged to “experience the richer, more sophisticated side of America’s Favorite Ketchup.” In photographs, the new condiment will be paired with a more genteel class of food, such as “Haute Dog,” “Hamburgeur” and “French Frites.” Heinz, which has no immediate plans to advertise the product, has more than 825,000 followers on Facebook, where it hopes enthusiasts will spread the word about the purchase. “We’re starting on Facebook first for our most avid fans,” said Noel Geoffroy, the vice president for United States retail brands at H. J. Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh. While 14-ounce glass Heinz bottles, which are still sold to restaurants, have not been widely available to consumers, the balsamic ketchup will only be sold in the bottles. The ketchup will carry a suggested retail price of $2.49 (plus a $2 shipping charge on Facebook), compared with $1.89 for the original in a plastic bottle of the same size. Labeled “limited edition,” the ketchup will be available in supermarkets through March, then offered permanently if it sells briskly. Ketchup, that most ubiquitous of condiments, is used in 97 percent of households, besting mustard, which is in 89 percent of homes, according to Mintel, the market research firm. Americans squirt ketchup on an average of 9.74 meals a week, and households on average consume 1.3 bottles a month. Heinz ketchup, first introduced in 1876 by Henry J. Heinz, is the dominant brand, with a 59 percent share of the market, dwarfing store brands, which account for 21.8 percent, and Hunt’s, with 15.1 percent, according to data for the 52 weeks ending Oct. 2 from SymphonyIRI Group, whose totals do not include Wal-Mart. For Heinz, in other words, there are not wide swaths of consumers unfamiliar with ketchup or loyal to a competing brand. But Ms. Geoffroy said that the new balsamic ketchup is unique enough that consumers will buy it in addition to the bottle already in their refrigerator door. “We think households who already use Heinz ketchup will use this in addition,” said Ms. Geoffroy. The tanginess of balsamic “does a nice job of adding a sophisticated spin” to ketchup, and the company will promote it as a complement to “center-of-the-plate proteins like chicken and pork,” she said. In a 2004 article in The New Yorker, “The Ketchup Conundrum,” Malcolm Gladwell examined why mustard varieties have proliferated while ketchup has remained comparatively constant in supermarket shelves, with Heinz’s original variety dominating. One thing that makes ketchup unique, Mr. Gladwell wrote, is that it simultaneously appeals to all fundamental human tastes: salty, sweet, sour, bitter, and umami, with umami being the full-bodied, savory flavor associated with meat, cheese and cooked tomatoes. In concocting ketchup that used riper tomatoes and more vinegar than its predecessors, Mr. Heinz “had come up with a condiment that pushed all five of the primal buttons,” Mr. Gladwell wrote. “How many things in the supermarket run the sensory spectrum like this?” Marketers at Heinz, like those at Coca-Cola, are loath to alter the original ketchup flavor, and are restrained about expanding the line. The last flavor variation, a hot and spicy ketchup that contains Tabasco sauce, was introduced in 2002. Other varieties address lifestyle or dietetic concerns while approximating the original flavor, such as versions that are organic, salt-free, or that use sugar rather than high fructose corn syrup. “One of the challenging things about it is people love it so much they don’t want you to touch it,” said Ms. Geoffroy. The brand has been less hesitant to tweak packaging. Heinz recently developed Dip and Squeeze, a successor to its ketchup packet that lets users either peel back the top for dunking fries or tear off the end for squirting. Along with appearing in fast-food chains, the single-serving pack, unlike the packets that preceded them, will be available in supermarkets, with a package of 10 having a suggested retail price of $2. In 2000, Heinz introduced green ketchup, followed by other colors such as purple, all tasting just like the original formula but meant to appeal to kids. Andrew F. Smith, author of “Pure Ketchup: A History of America’s National Condiment,” recently tried the new balsamic ketchup on a trip to Britain, where the variety was introduced in March. “Could I tell the difference? Yes,” said Mr. Smith, referring to the new ketchup. “But is it a significant difference? No.” Still, he said, like the green and purple varieties, which were discontinued in 2003, the new balsamic ketchup is bound to “get a lot of free publicity — in part it’s a P.R. move.” As for the new variety of ketchup spawning new uses for ketchup, Mr. Smith pointed out that consumers have historically shown little restraint in that regard, then cited a famous example. “There was the oddity of Richard Nixon putting ketchup on cottage cheese,” he said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/24/business/heinz-reports-strong-sales-growth-but-profit-slips.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Posts a Slip in Profit, but Sales Growth Is Strong<date>Published: August 23, 2011</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company reported on Tuesday that profit for its fiscal first quarter fell 6 percent as it closed factories and cut jobs. Excluding these cost-cutting measures, however, the results beat Wall Street estimates because of sales growth in emerging markets. Officials said the company’s performance exceeded expectations because of strong growth in places like China and Brazil. Heinz, along with most food and beverage companies, has been working to improve efficiency as commodity costs rise and American consumers spend cautiously. “We are off to a solid start to the year while continuing to adapt our strategies and tactics to meet the changing consumer dynamic,” Arthur B. Winkleblack, Heinz’s chief financial officer, told investors Tuesday. Heinz said it was raising prices and making other efficiency improvements to offset rising costs for tomatoes and other commodities. In May, the company announced that it would cut jobs, close plants and raise prices to improve its bottom line. Heinz plans to cut up to 1,000 jobs globally in its 2012 fiscal year. For its first fiscal quarter ending July 27, Heinz earned $226.1 million, or 70 cents a share, down from $240.4 million, or 75 cents a share, during the three-month period a year ago. After adjusting for costs associated with four factory closures, job reductions and other productivity initiatives, the company earned 78 cents a share. That beat the 76 cents a share analysts were expecting, according to data from FactSet. Revenue rose 15 percent to $2.85 billion, helped by sales growth in emerging markets and acquisitions. Wall Street had expected revenue of $2.79 billion. Heinz, the world’s largest maker of ketchup, earned about 32 percent of its revenue during the quarter in the United States, while emerging markets made up 23 percent of all sales, up from 18 percent in the period a year ago. Heinz reaffirmed its earnings for the 2012 fiscal year of $3.24 to $3.32 a share, which excludes productivity initiative costs. Analysts expect earnings of $3.35 a share. Shares of Heinz slipped 1.2 percent on Tuesday to $51.44.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/04/business/global/04heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Buys Stake in Industrias Alimenticias<date>Published: March 3, 2011</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company posted a 20 percent increase in quarterly profit on Thursday and announced a big step in its push into emerging markets with the purchase of an 80 percent stake in a Brazilian food company.Heinz has relied recently on emerging markets like China, India and Russia to fuel its growth. It said its plan to acquire the stake in the Brazilian company, Industrias Alimenticias, would eventually double its sales in Latin America. Alimenticias makes the Quero brand of tomato sauce and ketchup. Terms of the deal, which will also give Heinz a factory and distribution service that could be important to its future in the fast-growing region, were not disclosed. But the company said it would pay for the acquisition with cash on hand. “This is a major growth step under our emerging-market strategy,” Heinz’s chief executive, William R. Johnson, said. The deal will make Heinz one of a few United States consumer products companies with a major holding in the region. Heinz said the acquisition, which is expected to close in the next few months. would reduce earnings in fiscal 2012 but add to profit afterward. Heinz said it earned $273.8 million, or 84 cents a share, in its most recent quarter, an increase from $228.5 million, or 72 cents a share, a year earlier. The earnings beat analysts’ average forecast for earnings of 83 cents a share, according to FactSet. Revenue in the period, which ended Jan. 26 and was the third quarter of Heinz’s fiscal year, rose nearly 2 percent, to $2.72 billion, matching estimates. The company benefited from recent price increases it put in place to cope with higher commodity prices. Its sales rose in most markets around the globe outside Europe. Revenue in emerging markets rose 15 percent. Global volume edged up 0.5 percent, helped by the company’s acquisition of Foodstar in China in November. Stock in Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, rose 64 cents, or 1.3 percent, to $49.62.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/11/30/in-bogus-c-f-t-c-letters-an-arkansas-connection/?ref=hjheinzcompany">In Fake C.F.T.C. Letters, an Arkansas Connection<date>November 30, 2010, 7:40 pm</date><text>The case of the forged regulatory letters appears to be solved. Over the last month, the Commodities Futures Trading Commission received more than 150 letters about its proposal to limit conflicts of interest at derivatives clearinghouses. But some of the letters were fakes. The apparent source of the bogus letters: a grassroots advocate gone rogue. As Bloomberg News reported on Monday, nearly identical letters purportedly penned by an H.J. Heinz Company executive, a Burger King franchise and even some public officials were not actually written by these people. “This deceptive letter is not from Heinz or a Heinz executive and it does not represent the company’s views,” Michael Mullen, vice president of corporate and government affairs for Heinz, said in an e-mail to DealBook. Few clues pointed to the culprit of the forged letters, though there was one common thread: Arkansas. That’s right, each of the forged comment letters came from the state whose motto is “The People Rule.” The letters encouraged the C.F.T.C. to beef up its proposed derivatives rule, which the agency introduced as part of the Dodd-Frank financial overhaul law. “While the intent of the proposed rule is admirable, one provision contains a flaw” that would allow banks to control derivatives clearinghouses, many of the letters said. “It is likely that banks will try to exploit such a loophole to continue their cartel-like control of the derivatives market,” the letters said. The Securities and Exchange Commission received 18 similarly worded letters, according to an agency spokesman, although the S.E.C. did not receive any letters from Arkansas. A C.F.T.C. spokesman did not respond to requests for comment. DealBook traced the letters back to the Dewey Square Group, a Boston and Washington-based public affairs and lobbying firm known for steering grassroots public policy campaigns. Dewey Square, a spokeswoman confirmed, recently started a multistate campaign to toughen the C.F.T.C.’s derivatives rules. But Dewey Square contracted with lobbying firms in Rhode Island and Arkansas to spread the word, the spokeswoman, Ginny Terzano, said. The results were good in Rhode Island — elected officials, consumer advocates and corporate chieftains signed on to similar letters calling for tougher rules. Arkansas was a different story. Dewey Square’s contractor there outsourced the job to a local woman who forged several letters that she then sent to the C.F.T.C., according to a statement Ms. Terzano issued late Tuesday. That woman, who had no affiliation with Dewey Square, “no longer works” for the contractor, Ms. Terzano said. She did not know the woman’s name. “Dewey Square had no reason whatsoever to believe that the letters were not authentic and had no knowledge that they were in fact unauthorized until questions were raised in media accounts,” Ms. Terzano said in the statement. “We deeply regret that these misrepresentations were made in the course of work that our firm had requested.” The head of the Arkansas contracting firm, Miles M. Goggans, expressed regret as well in a statement. “This action was the sole doing of a subcontractor of mine who has worked for me only this past year,” said Mr. Goggans, a former Capitol Hill staffer who now lobbies for General Motors and Anheuser-Busch. “I deeply regret what this has done to these Arkansas businesses and individuals, and deeply regret that this inexcusable conduct occurred in the course of work I performed for Dewey Square, a firm that has the highest standards of professionalism and ethics.” Ms. Terzano declined to name the client that had hired Dewey Square to start the grassroots derivatives campaign. The group has lobbied on behalf of some half-dozen private companies this year, including health care and technology firms, lobbying disclosure records show. With the mystery seemingly solved, is it fair to say no harm, no foul? Not if you ask the Burger King franchise operator whose identity was stolen. “We were very upset,” said Terra Brace, treasurer of L.W. Clark Inc., which operates the Arkansas-based Burger King franchises. Ms. Brace told DealBook that she could not understand how her company got swept up in the controversy. “We’re a Burger King franchise,” she said, adding that derivatives are “not something as a company that we focus on.”</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/02/business/02heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Overseas Growth Helps Lift Revenue at Heinz<date>Published: September 1, 2010</date><text>The food company H. J. Heinz said first-quarter revenue rose 1.6 percent as sales in developing markets soared. It also said reductions in ketchup prices at Wal-Mart Stores helped demand.Sales rose to $2.48 billion, the company said Wednesday in a statement. Analysts had estimated $2.52 billion, the average of nine projections compiled by Bloomberg. Heinz said Tuesday that earnings rose to 75 cents a share, topping the average estimate. The company has increased marketing spending to lift sales of Heinz ketchup worldwide, soup and beans in Britain and children’s beverages in India. During the quarter, Wal-Mart, the world’s largest retailer, reduced the price of a 40-ounce bottle of Heinz ketchup to $1. Sales in the Asia-Pacific region increased 19 percent, helped by growth in India and Indonesia, the company said. North American sales rose 4.8 percent. In Europe, sales fell 7.7 percent, primarily because of unfavorable foreign-exchange rates. Net income rose 13 percent, to $240.4 million from $212.6 million, or 67 cents, a year earlier, Heinz said. The average of 13 analysts’ estimates was 73 cents. Shares of Heinz, which also makes Ore-Ida French fries and Lea &amp; Perrins sauces, rose 3 cents, to $46.27. The company agreed to buy Foodstar, a maker of soy sauce, from Transpac Industrial Holdings for $165 million in June, to expand in China. William Johnson, the Heinz chairman and chief executive, told investors on Tuesday that the company planned to generate 20 percent of sales from emerging markets by 2013, up from 18 percent in the first quarter. He told investors on Wednesday that Heinz might reach that goal earlier than expected.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/06/22/heinz-has-a-taste-for-chinese-soy-sauce/?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Has a Taste for Chinese Soy Sauce<date>June 22, 2010, 5:27 am</date><text>H.J. Heinz said Monday that it agreed to buy Foodstar, a private equity-backed Chinese food company that makes soy sauces and fermented bean curd, for $165 million, The Associated Press reported. The deal would give the U.S. ketchup maker a bigger foothold in China, boosting sales in that region to $300 million a year. It would also give the Pittsburgh company its first stake in fast-growing China’s $2 billion soy sauce market. The acquisition from the private equity firm Transpac Industrial Holdings also includes a possible extra payout in 2014 if Foodstar has strong performance as a Heinz brand. The deal for Foodstar, which has about 2,500 employees in China and four manufacturing sites, still requires regulatory approval in China. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Press Release from H.J. Heinz »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/28/business/28heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Raises Its Dividend as Sales Gain<date>Published: May 27, 2010</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said Thursday that its quarterly profit rose 10 percent, helped by sales in Asia and the Pacific.The company, which makes Ore-Ida potatoes, Classico pasta sauce and its signature ketchup said cutting costs and raising prices helped offset higher ingredient costs. Heinz raised its 2011 dividend 12 cents, to $1.80, and offered a forecast for the next year in line with Wall Street analysts’ estimates. The company said it earned $192.4 million, or 60 cents a share, in the quarter, up from $175.1 million, or 55 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended April 28 and was the fourth quarter of Heinz’s fiscal year, rose 8.3 percent, to $2.72 billion. Sales volume rose 1.6 percent, led by ketchup and sauces. Stock in Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, rose 54 cents, to $44.80 a share. The company said much of its growth resulted from a 63 percent increase on marketing spending. The chief executive, William R. Johnson, told investors in a conference call that the company would maintain current marketing levels, especially in emerging markets, where it wanted to position itself early to attract new shoppers to its brands. Mr. Johnson said it was likely that emerging markets like Russia, China, India and Indonesia would make up one-fourth of Heinz’s revenue in the next several years and 35 to 40 percent in the longer term. Asia and the Pacific now produce 20 percent of Heinz’s revenue, while North America and Europe produce 62 percent. In North America and Europe, revenue rose just under 7 percent each, while revenue in Asia and the Pacific jumped 27.3 percent.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/26/business/26heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Profit Falls 6% Despite Increasing Sales in Asia<date>Published: February 25, 2010</date><text>The food maker H. J. Heinz Company said rising sales in Asia’s emerging markets helped its third-quarter revenue rise 13 percent. But the cost of selling frozen food businesses in the United States and Britain cut into its profit, which fell 6 percent. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Daniel Acker/Bloomberg News Sales of Heinz products, which include ketchup and many other foods, increased more abroad than in the United States. Add to Portfolio Heinz, H J, Co Go to your Portfolio » Heinz, which makes Ore-Ida potatoes and Classico pasta sauce, as well as its namesake ketchup, benefited as consumers ate at home more often in the recession. But its sales in the United States fell for much of the last year, so it is marketing products more, developing new products and focusing on its emerging markets for growth. Its profit fell to $228.5 million, or 72 cents a share in the quarter, which ended Jan. 27, from $242.3 million, or 76 cents a share, a year earlier. But the company earned 83 cents a share excluding costs related to selling the two businesses. That is a penny more than the company forecast and 6 cents more than the average prediction of analysts polled by Thomson Reuters, who typically exclude such one-time items. On that basis, Heinz earned 76 cents a share last year. Heinz, which makes an array of products, sold a frozen hors d’oeuvres business in the United States and a private-label frozen desserts business in Britain. With sales rising 41 percent in Asia and 12 percent in Europe, the company’s third-quarter revenue rose to $2.68 billion, from $2.38 billion a year earlier. Analysts had expected revenue of $2.66 billion. The sales increase in Heinz’s Asia and South Pacific region was led by sales in Indonesia, China and India and offset by lower volume in Australia. The company’s North American consumer product sales rose 7 percent, to $815 million, and its sales to American food service businesses fell 3 percent, to $355 million. Heinz said its growth in emerging markets was driven by nutritional drinks Complan and Glucon-D in India, ABC brand sauces and drinks in Indonesia and Heinz ketchup in Russia. Heinz reiterated its full-year earnings outlook of $2.82 to $2.85 a share from continuing operations. Analysts expect a profit of $2.84 a share. Shares of Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, fell 26 cents, or 0.57 percent, to close at $45.66 on Thursday. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 26, 2010, on page B5 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D8103AF936A15752C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">Mixed Results for Heinz and Hormel<date>Published: November 25, 2009</date><text>H. J. Heinz and Hormel Foods reported on Tuesday mixed quarterly results, but said they expected sales to rise in the coming months. Heinz posted a smaller-than-expected decline in quarterly profit as overall sales rose despite a decline in North America. It earned $231.4 million, or 73 cents a share, in the quarter, down from $276.7 million, or 87 cents a share, a year earlier. Last year's results included a gain from currency hedging. Earnings of 76 cents a share from continuing operations topped analysts' average forecast of 69 cents. Hormel posted a bigger-than-expected increase in quarterly profit as a result of lower hog prices, but sales fell more than expected. It earned $103.9 million, or 77 cents a share, up from $67.8 million, or 50 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts had expected 68 cents a share.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/21/business/21food.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz and Hormel Exceed Forecasts<date>Published: August 20, 2009</date><text>H.J. Heinz Company and Hormel Foods both posted better-than-expected quarterly profits on Thursday, benefiting as consumers ate more meals at home to save money. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Heinz, H J, Co Hormel Foods Corporation Go to your Portfolio » Heinz, which makes Ore-Ida potatoes in addition to ketchup, said its results were helped by strength in emerging markets and by price increases. But the stronger dollar cut into sales outside the United States, causing net income to fall. Hormel, which makes Spam luncheon meat and Dinty Moore stews, said profits rose, in part, because of lower costs for feed in its Jennie-O turkey business. Most American food companies have benefited as consumers have tried to cut costs by eating more at home during the recession rather than at restaurants. Food companies also raised prices last year as costs for commodities like wheat, corn and oil soared. Even as many of those costs have fallen back, they have largely been able to maintain their pricing. Heinz profit fell to $219.1 million, or 67 cents a share, in the quarter ended July 29, but topped the average analyst forecast of 62 cents a share. Hormel’s earnings rose to $77.2 million, or 57 cents a share, in the third quarter ended July 26, beating the 52 cents a share that analysts were expecting. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on August 21, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/13/fashion/13iht-design13.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">An Icon, Despite Itself<date>Published: April 12, 2009</date><text>LONDON — What is the unbreakable rule of “good design”? It is not looking great, or being dazzlingly innovative. Nor is it reflecting changes in the way we see the world, or even scoring lots of environmental and ethical points. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image H. J. Heinz Company A Heinz Tomato Ketchup advertisement. More Photos » Multimedia Slide Show The Heinz Ketchup Bottle: Form vs. Function Great though all of those things are, design can still be “good” without them. The one thing design must do is fulfill its function efficiently. If not, it risks looking ridiculous, regardless of whatever else it has to offer. Yet there is one example of something that is generally considered to be “good design,” which does break the golden rule. It is part of our daily lives, and has been designed to similar specifications for more than a century — the glass Heinz Tomato Ketchup bottle. If you asked the millions of people who use that glass bottle whether it is well designed, they would probably say “yes.” If not they would be fools, because they could achieve exactly the same outcome — seasoning their food with fresh ketchup — by buying one of Heinz’s plastic bottles, which are not only cheaper, but do the job more efficiently. The job in question does not sound particularly challenging. It is to protect and preserve the ketchup, and to enable it to be extracted quickly and easily. The glass bottle executes the first part perfectly well, but not the second. Heinz Ketchup is what is called a “pseudoplastic” substance, which thickens when static, and thins again when moved. This means that it clogs up in the bottle, becoming too thick to pour. You can thin it again by shaking the bottle, but risk making the ketchup so runny, that it gushes out in a splodge. There are various ways around this. If you tap the neck of the bottle, it should release the ketchup. (Heinz has helpfully identified the best place to tap, with the number 57 on the American bottle and the royal crest on the British one.) You can also try plunging a knife into the ketchup, though that could get messy. An alternative is to use either the squeezable plastic bottle or upside down one that Heinz has devised to solve this problem. Some 75 percent of Heinz Tomato Ketchup is now sold in plastic bottles. So why do millions of people still choose to pay more for a glass bottle, which will not work as well? The obvious answer is because they like it. (I should come clean here by admitting that I like the glass bottle too, though not the taste of tomato ketchup — Heinz’s or anyone else’s.) What makes that glass bottle seem so special that we are willing to overlook its shortcomings? One reason is that it looks familiar. Heinz patented the original in 1882, and has refined its design over the years, although the basic shape of the gracefully curved neck and sturdy base has stayed the same, as has the geometric silhouette of the label. But familiarity is not necessarily attractive. It is just as likely to seem dull, as seductive. Heinz has succeeded in triggering fond childhood memories of its glass ketchup bottles and respect for its corporate heritage, without seeming to be stuck in the past. The subtle changes in the bottle’s design have helped, but so does its styling. There is nothing fussy or flamboyant about the glass or labels; instead they seem gentle, uncomplicated and reassuring. Critically, they look uncontrived, which is much more appealing than the truth: that every element of their design has been carefully planned and executed to create the illusion that the bottle has evolved organically. Take the glass. The shape is dictated by the bottle’s function, which gives it a pleasingly no-nonsense air. The smooth neck eases the flow of ketchup (once you’ve unclogged it) and the octagonal base ensures that the bottle nestles comfortably in your hand. The weight is just right — heavy enough to feel substantial, but not too much so — and there is no need for eco-neurosis, because the glass can be recycled. The only hint of decoration is the row of tiny 57s carved on to the neck as a reminder of Heinz’s “57 Varieties” slogan, which was coined by the founder Henry John Heinz to impress the public with the breadth of his product range. (The company made more than 60 products at the time, but he chose 57, because 5 was his lucky number and 7 his wife’s.) The labels are styled in the same spirit. The colors are restrained: just black, red, green and gold (a muted gold, not a blingy one) against a white background. The letters are printed in the bold strokes of hand-drawn typography with tiny traditional serifs at the ends to hint at Heinz’s heritage. The only decorative motif is an illustration of a tomato growing on a vine rendered in the style of early botanical drawings. It strikes another nostalgic note, but balances it with a contemporary one by soothing our eco-concerns with the gentle reminder that Heinz ketchup contains lots of natural ingredients. Last but not least, the glass bottle is a great example of democratic design. Like the Apple iPod, a Rawlings baseball and 3M’s Post-it Notes, Heinz Ketchup is a rare example of a best-selling brand that is also generally considered to be best in class. It would seem silly to splash out on a more expensive alternative, especially as the glass bottle affirms its stellar status. That is why Heinz Tomato Ketchup is one of the very few branded products you see in its original packaging in expensive restaurants. “Sometimes we have to accept that we can’t better something that already exists,” said Jeremy King, who co-owns The Wolseley in London and is now re-opening The Monkey Bar in New York. “When a customer asks for ketchup they generally want Heinz. The iconic glass bottle reassures them that they are getting it.” Quite a coup for something that does not really do its job properly. More Articles in Fashion &amp; Style »LONDON — What is the unbreakable rule of “good design”? It is not looking great, or being dazzlingly innovative. Nor is it reflecting changes in the way we see the world, or even scoring lots of environmental and ethical points. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image H. J. Heinz Company A Heinz Tomato Ketchup advertisement. More Photos » Multimedia Slide Show The Heinz Ketchup Bottle: Form vs. Function Great though all of those things are, design can still be “good” without them. The one thing design must do is fulfill its function efficiently. If not, it risks looking ridiculous, regardless of whatever else it has to offer. Yet there is one example of something that is generally considered to be “good design,” which does break the golden rule. It is part of our daily lives, and has been designed to similar specifications for more than a century — the glass Heinz Tomato Ketchup bottle. If you asked the millions of people who use that glass bottle whether it is well designed, they would probably say “yes.” If not they would be fools, because they could achieve exactly the same outcome — seasoning their food with fresh ketchup — by buying one of Heinz’s plastic bottles, which are not only cheaper, but do the job more efficiently. The job in question does not sound particularly challenging. It is to protect and preserve the ketchup, and to enable it to be extracted quickly and easily. The glass bottle executes the first part perfectly well, but not the second. Heinz Ketchup is what is called a “pseudoplastic” substance, which thickens when static, and thins again when moved. This means that it clogs up in the bottle, becoming too thick to pour. You can thin it again by shaking the bottle, but risk making the ketchup so runny, that it gushes out in a splodge. There are various ways around this. If you tap the neck of the bottle, it should release the ketchup. (Heinz has helpfully identified the best place to tap, with the number 57 on the American bottle and the royal crest on the British one.) You can also try plunging a knife into the ketchup, though that could get messy. An alternative is to use either the squeezable plastic bottle or upside down one that Heinz has devised to solve this problem. Some 75 percent of Heinz Tomato Ketchup is now sold in plastic bottles. So why do millions of people still choose to pay more for a glass bottle, which will not work as well? The obvious answer is because they like it. (I should come clean here by admitting that I like the glass bottle too, though not the taste of tomato ketchup — Heinz’s or anyone else’s.) What makes that glass bottle seem so special that we are willing to overlook its shortcomings? One reason is that it looks familiar. Heinz patented the original in 1882, and has refined its design over the years, although the basic shape of the gracefully curved neck and sturdy base has stayed the same, as has the geometric silhouette of the label. But familiarity is not necessarily attractive. It is just as likely to seem dull, as seductive. Heinz has succeeded in triggering fond childhood memories of its glass ketchup bottles and respect for its corporate heritage, without seeming to be stuck in the past. The subtle changes in the bottle’s design have helped, but so does its styling. There is nothing fussy or flamboyant about the glass or labels; instead they seem gentle, uncomplicated and reassuring. Critically, they look uncontrived, which is much more appealing than the truth: that every element of their design has been carefully planned and executed to create the illusion that the bottle has evolved organically. Take the glass. The shape is dictated by the bottle’s function, which gives it a pleasingly no-nonsense air. The smooth neck eases the flow of ketchup (once you’ve unclogged it) and the octagonal base ensures that the bottle nestles comfortably in your hand. The weight is just right — heavy enough to feel substantial, but not too much so — and there is no need for eco-neurosis, because the glass can be recycled. The only hint of decoration is the row of tiny 57s carved on to the neck as a reminder of Heinz’s “57 Varieties” slogan, which was coined by the founder Henry John Heinz to impress the public with the breadth of his product range. (The company made more than 60 products at the time, but he chose 57, because 5 was his lucky number and 7 his wife’s.) The labels are styled in the same spirit. The colors are restrained: just black, red, green and gold (a muted gold, not a blingy one) against a white background. The letters are printed in the bold strokes of hand-drawn typography with tiny traditional serifs at the ends to hint at Heinz’s heritage. The only decorative motif is an illustration of a tomato growing on a vine rendered in the style of early botanical drawings. It strikes another nostalgic note, but balances it with a contemporary one by soothing our eco-concerns with the gentle reminder that Heinz ketchup contains lots of natural ingredients. Last but not least, the glass bottle is a great example of democratic design. Like the Apple iPod, a Rawlings baseball and 3M’s Post-it Notes, Heinz Ketchup is a rare example of a best-selling brand that is also generally considered to be best in class. It would seem silly to splash out on a more expensive alternative, especially as the glass bottle affirms its stellar status. That is why Heinz Tomato Ketchup is one of the very few branded products you see in its original packaging in expensive restaurants. “Sometimes we have to accept that we can’t better something that already exists,” said Jeremy King, who co-owns The Wolseley in London and is now re-opening The Monkey Bar in New York. “When a customer asks for ketchup they generally want Heinz. The iconic glass bottle reassures them that they are getting it.” Quite a coup for something that does not really do its job properly.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D7163CF931A15752C1A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">Sales Increase for Heinz as More Americans Eat at Home<date>Published: November 22, 2008</date><text>PITTSBURGH (AP) -- The H. J. Heinz Company, the food products company, said Friday that strong sales of products like Ore-Ida frozen potatoes and frozen meals bolstered second-quarter profit by 22 percent as consumers cooked more meals at home. The company, based here, said it had benefited from hedging against currencies. The company reported a $92 million pretax currency benefit from the use of forward contracts to mitigate unfavorable exchange rates. Heinz said profit for the quarter ended Oct. 29 rose to $276.7 million, or 87 cents a share, from $227 million, or 71 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 4 percent to $2.61 billion, from $2.52 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters were expecting a profit of 76 cents a share on revenue of $2.7 billion. Heinz increased net prices by 8 percent to offset higher costs for ingredients like potatoes, meat and oil. Ketchup sales grew 12 percent, helped by new packaging formats in Europe and higher prices. In the United States, price increases and the start of Ore-Ida Steam 'n Mash potatoes drove up sales of the brand by a double-digit percentage. T.G.I. Friday's frozen meals were also strong sellers. The company's restaurant business was the only segment where sales fell, as customer traffic slowed.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D9133EF931A1575BC0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">Mixed Results For Hormel And Heinz<date>Published: August 22, 2008</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said Thursday that its quarterly profit rose 11 percent, fueled by sales growth of more than 10 percent in North America and Europe, while the Hormel Foods Corporation said profit fell 9 percent because of higher costs. Heinz, which makes Heinz Ketchup, Weight Watchers products and Ore-Ida frozen potatoes, said it earned $229 million, or 72 cents a share, up from $205.3 million, or 63 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended July 30 and was the first quarter of Heinz's fiscal year, rose 14 percent, to $2.58 billion, from $2.25 billion. Heinz said it raised prices by about 5.2 percent in the quarter to offset higher commodity costs. The price increases were largely for Heinz Ketchup, other condiments and tomato products. The profit was better than the 66 cents a share expected by analysts surveyed by ThomsonReuters, and Heinz's stock rose 28 cents, to $51.99 a share. Hormel, whose brands include Spam and Jennie-O turkey products, said it earned $51.9 million, or 38 cents a share, down from $57.4 million, or 41 cents a share. Revenue in the period, which ended July 27 and was the third quarter of Hormel's fiscal year, rose 10 percent, to $1.68 billion, from $1.52 billion. The profit fell short of the 39 cents expected by analysts, but Hormel's stock rose 30 cents, to $35.44 a share. The quarter was hurt by higher feed and fuel costs at its Jennie-O Turkey Store segment.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/26/dining/26ketchup.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">A Thicker, Sweeter, Spicier Ketchup, Just Right for Slathering<date>Published: March 26, 2008</date><text>Skip to next paragraph Tony Cenicola/The New York Times Good old-fashioned Heinz ketchup is the devil I know  and love  despite the high-fructose corn syrup in the recipe. Most fancy-pants ketchups do not quite measure up in terms of tangy-sweetness. But a new one, Katchkie Ketchup, made from Hudson Valley tomatoes by Katchkie Farm in Kinderhook, N.Y., has what it takes for me to slather it on my burger or meatloaf. All the qualities of ketchup are ramped up, making it more textured than Heinz, spicier and a bit sharper. Its distinctive homey sweetness comes from brown sugar. An 8-ounce jar is $6 at Zabar’s, the gift shop at Wave Hill, BLT Market and Market Table. More Articles in Dining &amp; Wine »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/27/business/27heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Profit Drops at Heinz, but Beats Expectations<date>Published: February 27, 2008</date><text>PITTSBURGH (AP)  H. J. Heinz, one of the world’s largest food companies, said Tuesday that its third-quarter profit edged slightly lower as a steeper tax rate and rising commodity costs offset sales growth fueled by increased marketing and higher prices. Heinz, which makes its namesake ketchup, Ore-Ida potatoes and Classico pasta sauces, reported earnings of $218.5 million, or 68 cents a share, for the three months that ended in January. In the period last year, when it had more shares outstanding, it earned $219 million, or 66 cents a share. Sales jumped 14 percent, to $2.61 billion, from $2.30 billion last year. The results exceeded Wall Street estimates. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial, on average, were looking for profit of 67 cents a share on sales of $2.58 billion. The company remains on track to achieve record full-year sales and growth of 9 to 10 percent in earnings per share for the fiscal year, William R. Johnson, Heinz’s chief executive, said in a statement. Heinz shares slipped 38 cents, to $45.60. Emerging markets accounted for 23 percent of Heinz’s sales growth. The Asia-Pacific region showed a 27.4 percent gain, and there were strong results in Australia, Indonesia, China and India. Sixty percent of Heinz’s revenue comes from outside the United States. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/22/business/22interview.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">At Heinz, Hoping to Leave a Legacy of Product Safety<date>Published: December 22, 2007</date><text>FOR wary consumers, 2007 may well be remembered as the year of the recall. Toys may have grabbed the spotlight, but pet food and food for humans ran a close second. One company  the Topps Meat Company in Elizabeth, N.J.  recalled more than 21 million pounds of frozen hamburger because of potential E. coli contamination. The company closed on Oct. 5 and declared bankruptcy late last month. Skip to next paragraph William R. Johnson Last spring, the Food and Drug Administration recalled millions of packages of pet food after finding evidence that tainted ingredients in the food, originating in China, had killed at least 16 cats and dogs and sickened thousands of other animals. And that does not count ConAgra’s recall of pot pies and Peter Pan peanut butter after salmonella outbreaks, and the recall by General Mills of thousands of Totino’s and Jeno’s frozen pizzas last month when the pepperoni topping was suspected in an E. coli outbreak. H. J. Heinz, the Pittsburgh food manufacturer, has had its own recalls in past years but has managed to stay off the hot seat this year. Recently the chief executive of Heinz, William R. Johnson, discussed product quality and recalls, what consumers have to look forward to and the shareholder activist who has taken a keen interest in the company. Excerpts from the interview follow: Q. Where does product quality fall in your top 10 concerns? A. Ensuring the quality of a product is the most important thing a company can do. Quality is to a product what integrity is to a human being. It’s the barometer of success for companies like ours. I’ve always told our people that Heinz brands are synonymous with quality and safety in an uncertain world, and we need to take every precaution so that we don’t have these kinds of problems. Quality is also a personal passion of mine. It’s one of the legacies I hope to leave in this company, an idea that Henry Heinz, the company founder, started. He was one of the few people in the industry who helped pass the Pure Food and Drug Act in 1906. Q. How does H.J. Heinz attempt to ensure that its products are safe and avoid recalls in the future? A. We established a quality council a couple of years ago that reports directly to me. I believe that’s unusual in the industry. I don’t want to speak for other companies, but the quality function sometimes reports to R.&amp;D. or operations or manufacturing. We’ve also upped our funding in the area of quality. Most recall issues are built around allergens and microbiological contamination. We haven’t had these problems in the last few years and have taken stringent action to counter them. We’ve added electronic scanners along our factory lines to eliminate what we refer to as “rogue” labels. In the case of beans, occasionally a supplier will violate our standards, but we’ve taken action in the last few years to follow up before there’s a problem. We’ve been implementing a comprehensive quality management system over the last few years that places controls on all aspects of our product sourcing and suppliers, as well as on operations in our factories. Q. What’s your opinion about the job the F.D.A. is doing in overseeing the food industry? A. I think the F.D.A. is the finest food agency in the world and has some of the most stringent processes and the finest people, but I believe they’re underresourced. Q. What’s the threshold for a recall at Heinz? A. We take immediate action on anything that has to do with consumer safety. One of our last quality issues, in 2006, involved a labeling error regarding milk in a frozen food product in the Northeast. It was a minor incident, but we immediately pulled all of the product off the shelves. Q. What advice do you have for consumers who may be nervous about the food they eat after the spinach recall last year, and this year’s recalls? A. I think consumers need to look at brands and understand the people they’re doing business with. Companies have to be stringent in their processes. Even without regulation, they have to insist on the highest standards. The annual survey by the University of Michigan on customer satisfaction rated the Heinz brand No. 1 again this year. The earnings we announced in November are testament to our quality. Earnings per share are up 20 percent for the quarter, sales are up 13 percent, and we’re doing well all over the world. Q. The shareholder activist Nelson Peltz and another member of his company, the Trian Group, won seats on your board in 2006. How has it been going? A. Very well. Nelson is obsessed with quality and we talk about it frequently. He’s an enthusiastic, energetic addition to the board. Nelson has offered a number of ideas, and I bounce things off him occasionally. He has been a positive influence on the company and we get along well. He’s all about us growing even faster. Q. Shoppers are none too happy about rising food prices. Do you see them dropping anytime soon? A. Unfortunately, American consumers are going to pay a little more for food as long as food is being converted to fuel. Ethanol is having an impact on the food supply in the United States, and the demand around the world for American commodities like grain is continuing to put pressure on commodity prices. Supply and demand need to equilibrate. But at the end of the day, you have to remember that food as a percentage of expenditures is relatively small, particularly in the United States. There may be some changes from eating out to eating at home more, which is good for our business. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4D61F3CF933A0575AC0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">CORRECTION; Correction: Business<date>Published: September 30, 2007</date><text>A book review on Sept. 2 of ''Supercapitalism,'' by Robert R. Reich, which examines how the economy is shaped by citizens acting as consumers and investors, included an incorrect statement based on the book's description of an effort by StarKist to sell dolphin-safe tuna. While Heinz U.S.A., the former owner of StarKist, found that consumers were not willing to pay additional money for dolphin-safe tuna, the company elected to sell only such tuna and never abandoned the practice.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE1D8133DF937A3575AC0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING; Zimbabwe: Heinz Sheds Its Interests<date>Published: September 4, 2007</date><text>The food giant H. J. Heinz, one of Zimbabwe's first major foreign investors, sold its Zimbabwe interests to Cottco, a government-controlled cotton company. Cottco paid $6.8 million for Heinz's 49 percent stake in Olivine Industries, a Zimbabwe company that makes fats, edible oils and soaps. The government previously shared ownership of Olivine with Heinz. Industry executives dismissed reports in the state media that called the Heinz deal the first in a much-publicized program by the government to take over white-controlled businesses. The executives said the deal was in negotiation months before plans were announced by President Robert G. Mugabe this year to force all businesses to yield 51 percent of their ownership to black Zimbabweans, a campaign the government calls ''indigenization.'' Heinz was one of the first major foreign investors after independence in 1980.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/business/01heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Earnings Rise Almost 8%<date>Published: June 1, 2007</date><text>H. J. Heinz posted a rise of almost 8 percent in quarterly profit yesterday as higher prices and increased marketing helped sales, and it raised its full-year 2008 forecast. The company, which makes ketchup, Ore-Ida potatoes and Smart Ones frozen meals, said earnings rose to $181 million, or 55 cents a share, in its fiscal fourth quarter, which ended May 2, from $167.9 million, or 50 cents a share, a year before. The results matched analysts average forecast, according to Reuters Estimates. Net quarterly sales rose 0.6 percent, to $2.4 billion. The latest quarter had one fewer week than the year-earlier period, which had a 7 percent impact on sales. Heinz said that it raised its fiscal 2008 earnings outlook to a range of $2.54 to $2.60 a share. Analysts on average have forecast $2.57. For all of fiscal 2007, Heinz earned $2.41 a share, before a 2 cent-a-share loss from discontinued operations. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/26/business/26content.ready.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">The High Price of Creating Free Ads<date>Published: May 26, 2007</date><text>From an advertisers perspective, it sounds so easy: invite the public to create commercials for your brand, hold a contest to pick the best one and sit back while average Americans do the creative work. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image AJ Mast for The New York Times Brushing his teeth with ketchup wasnt enough. Dan Burke sets up a camera while creating another video for the Heinz contest. But look at the videos H. J. Heinz is getting on YouTube. In one of them, a teenage boy rubs ketchup over his face like acne cream, then puts pickles on his eyes. One contestant chugs ketchup straight from the bottle, while another brushes his teeth, washes his hair and shaves his face with Heinzs product. Often the ketchup looks more like blood than a condiment. Heinz has said it will pick five of the entries and show them on television, though it has not committed itself to a channel or a time slot. One winner will get $57,000. But so far its safe to say that none of the entries have quite the resonance of, say, the classic Carly Simon Anticipation ad where the ketchup creeps oh so slowly out of the bottle. Heinz Top This TV Challenge Entry #138: Dan's Heinz Commercial Consumer brand companies have been busy introducing campaigns like Heinzs that rely on user-generated content, an approach that combines the populist appeal of reality television with the old-fashioned gimmick of a sweepstakes to select a new advertising jingle. Pepsi, Jeep, Dove and Sprint have all staged promotions of this sort, as has Doritos, which proudly publicized in February that the consumers who made one of its Super Bowl ad did so on a $12 budget. But these companies have found that inviting consumers to create their advertising is often more stressful, costly and time-consuming than just rolling up their sleeves and doing the work themselves. Many entries are mediocre, if not downright bad, and sifting through them requires full-time attention. And even the most well-known brands often spend millions of dollars upfront to get the word out to consumers. Some people, meanwhile, have been using the contests as an opportunity to scrawl digital graffiti on the sponsor and its brand. Rejected Heinz submissions have been showing up on YouTube anyway, and visitors to Heinzs page on the site have written that the ketchup maker is clearly looking for cheap labor and that Heinz is lazy to ask consumers to do its marketing work. Thats kind of a popular misnomer that, somehow, its cheaper to do this, said David Ciesinski, vice president for Heinz Ketchup. On the contrary, its at least as expensive, if not more. Heinz has hired an outside promotions firm to watch all the videos and forward questionable ones to Heinz employees in its Pittsburgh headquarters. So far, they have rejected more than 370 submissions (at least 320 remain posted on YouTube). The gross-out factor is not among their screening criteria  rather, most of the failed entries were longer than the 30-second time limit, entirely irrelevant to the contest or included songs protected by copyright. Some of the videos displayed brands other than Heinz (a big no-no) or were rejected because they wouldnt be appropriate to show mom, Mr. Ciesinski said. Heinz hopes to show more than five of them, if there are enough that convey a positive, appealing message about Heinz ketchup, he said. But advertising executives who have seen some of the entries say that Heinz may be hard pressed to find any that it is proud to run on television in September. These are just so bad, said Linda Kaplan Thaler, chief executive of the Kaplan Thaler Group, an advertising agency in New York that is not involved with Heinzs contest. One of the most viewed Heinz videos  seen, at last count, more than 12,800 times  ends with a close-up of a mouth with crooked, yellowed teeth. When Ms. Kaplan Thaler saw it, she wondered, Were his teeth the result of, maybe, too much Heinz? Heinz Top This TV Challenge Entry #4: My Entry For The Heinz Commercial Contest Scott Goodson, chief executive of StrawberryFrog, an advertising agency based in New York, said the shortcomings of contest entries  not just those for Heinz  refuted predictions that user-generated content might siphon work away from agencies. This Heinz campaign, much like the same ones done by Doritos, Converse and Dodge, only goes to show how hard it is to do great advertising, he said. In a traditional ad campaign, a client like Heinz will meet with its advertising agencies to come up with a central idea, often a tagline like MasterCards Priceless. The creative departments then design the ads while the media planners figure out where they should run. Except for the occasional focus group, consumers are largely on the receiving end. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/28/business/28heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Profit at Heinz Surges 90%<date>Published: February 28, 2007</date><text>H. J. Heinz said yesterday that quarterly profit soared nearly 90 percent, helped by new products, increased marketing and improvement in its international business. Heinz also stuck to its full-year earnings outlook from last week, when it said it expected earnings of $2.35 to $2.39 a share, in line with Wall Street estimates. The company also said that quarterly earnings were expected to rise about 30 percent from a year earlier. The company, whose products include its namesake ketchup, Heinz baked beans, Ore-Ida French fries and Smart Ones entrees, said profit was $219 million, or 66 cents a diluted share in the fiscal third quarter, up from $116.6 million, or 35 cents a share, a year earlier. Earnings beat the expectations of analysts, who on average forecast 61 cents a share, according to Reuters estimates. Despite strong results, shares of the company, based in Pittsburgh, fell. “Heinz beat our estimate by 6 cents, but did so on lower corporate expense, higher ‘other income’ and a lower tax rate,” a JPMorgan analyst, Pablo Zuanic, said in a research note. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/09/business/09heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">2 Dissidents Appear to Have Won Heinz Seats<date>Published: September 9, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Sept. 8  The investor Nelson Peltz and Michael Weinstein, the former chief executive of Snapple, learned on Friday that they most likely won seats on the board of the H. J. Heinz Company after a six-month proxy battle. Heinz released the preliminary results of the board vote on Friday, three weeks after shareholders voted at the companys annual meeting, where Mr. Peltz made his final push for up to 5 seats on the 12-member board. Both sides said at the time that they expected Mr. Peltz and his company, the Trian Group, to win some seats on the board, but they did not know how many. This is a big victory for all Heinz shareholders, Trian said in a statement after the announcement. Neither Mr. Peltz nor Mr. Weinstein could be reached for further comment. Heinz portrayed the outcome as a victory of its own, citing the fact that 10 of its 12 incumbent directors were re-elected. Peter Coors, vice chairman of the Molson Coors Brewing Company, and Mary Choksi, managing director of two investment firms, lost their seats. A Molson Coors spokeswoman said Mr. Coors had no comment. Ms. Choksi could not be reached for comment. The Heinz board will be focused on executing our plan, Heinzs chief executive, William R. Johnson, said in a statement. I look forward to moving ahead constructively and working closely with the board to enhance shareholder value. Mr. Peltz and Mr. Weinstein will officially join the board as soon as the votes are certified, which Heinz said could take place by Sept. 15. They will have their first chance to voice their opinions in an organizational conference call in early October, and then their first board meeting on Nov. 8, said Michael Mullen, a Heinz spokesman. Mr. Peltz began agitating for change in February, when he announced that Trian had acquired 5.5 percent of Heinzs outstanding stock and that he intended to shake up the company and force a proxy battle. For the next six months, he pushed his own plan to revitalize Heinzs performance, proposing to increase advertising and cut $575 million in expenses. Shares of Heinz had fallen from a high of $54.50 in 1998, when Mr. Johnson was appointed chief executive, to the $33 range just before Mr. Peltz announced his intentions this year. They closed on Friday at $41.74, down 33 cents. Heinz countered with its own plan to cut $355 million in expenses while citing its continuing efforts to refocus the company on core products, like its ketchup. Marvin Roffman, whose investment company, Roffman Miller Associates in Philadelphia, manages 145,000 Heinz shares, supported the Heinz board and he still says the proxy battle  which cost Heinz $14 million  was a waste of money forced by Mr. Peltz. I really think the company had righted itself very well before Mr. Peltz came around, he said. And now with Mr. Peltz and Mr. Weinstein on the board, he said, I dont think its going to be an amicable kind of relationship, but I think its a healthy experience to go through something like this. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/17/business/17heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Peltz Is Seen With 2 Seats at Heinz<date>Published: August 17, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Aug. 16  The investor Nelson Peltz won some seats on the board of the H. J. Heinz Company on Wednesday, securing a foothold in the company that may result in a showdown over its direction. The gains by Mr. Peltz, after a vitriolic proxy fight over several months, represents the latest success for a growing cadre of investors who call themselves shareholder activists and seek to bring about change at companies by publicly challenging them. More recently, some of their targets have been among the giants of corporate America, including General Motors, McDonalds, Time Warner and Knight Ridder. In the case of G.M., Kirk Kerkorian has injected himself into the battle over the companys future by pressing to put one of his representatives on the board and to consider an alliance with Nissan and Renault. Mr. Peltzs investment vehicle, the Trian Group, had sought to elect 5 directors to Heinzs 12-member board after the company rejected his proposed turnaround plan. It is unclear how many seats Mr. Peltz won on the Heinz board because all the votes have yet to be tallied. But based on an analysis of known votes after Wednesdays annual shareholder meeting, Mr. Peltz appeared to have won at least two seats. Its a great victory for all the Heinz shareholders, he said after the meeting, which attracted an overflow crowd of 1,000 to a ballroom in the Hilton Pittsburgh. This company needed this desperately. Yet the company, based here, also declared victory, contending that Mr. Peltz had lost because his entire slate was not elected. The fact that shareholders rejected the bloc of five suggests theres support for the Heinz plan to rejuvenate the company, said Ted Smyth, Heinzs chief administrative officer. With 330 million shares held by some 200,000 shareholders, official results will not be known for about a month. Heinz has also said that it plans to increase the size of the board to 14 from the 12 now. In trading Wednesday, shares of Heinz edged up 16 cents, to $41.13. Since Mr. Peltz initiated his board challenge in March, the stock has gained 10 percent. Its flagging price, down from a high of $54.40 when William R. Johnson became chief executive in 1998, was often cited by the Trian Group in its campaign. Still, shareholder activism does not always produce returns for shareholders. For example, another longtime activist, Carl C. Icahn, won three seats on the eight-member board of Blockbuster in May 2005 with the intention of achieving a company turnaround. At the time, Blockbuster shares sold for about $10. On Wednesday, they closed at $3.77. Heinz executives have promoted a five-year overhaul plan to focus the company on core products, citing recent results showing that the program, announced in June, was already working. Mr. Johnson said on Wednesday that he expected sales for the first fiscal quarter to rise 8 percent. On July 19 and again on Aug. 9, the company raised its estimates for the quarter, which ended Aug. 2. According to Mr. Peltz and Heinz executives, there was a last-ditch effort to avoid the battle that played out Wednesday. Last week, Thomas J. Usher, Heinzs presiding director, called Mr. Peltz at the urging of a major shareholder and asked him to come to Pittsburgh to discuss a settlement. The two met in Heinzs headquarters. Though they could not avert the showdown, they agreed that once the issue was resolved, they would smoke the peace pipe and work together, Mr. Peltz said. Mr. Peltz made his fortune through a string of acquisitions. He is probably best known for Snapple, the beverage company he bought for $300 million in 1997 and sold in 2000 for $1.45 billion. This week, he disclosed that he had accumulated a 1.2 percent stake in Tribune, the media company being pressed for change by its largest shareholder, the Chandler family. At the Hilton on Wednesday, the audience was clearly a hometown crowd  strongly in favor of the company that has called Pittsburgh home for 137 years. After Mr. Peltz spoke, citing Trians past successes, the crowd applauded quietly and politely. But after Mr. Usher of Heinz promised that the company was in fighting shape and that Heinz is not broken, there was a roar of applause and even a few whistles of support. The most enthusiastic applause was for Mervin Berkman, 72, a retired accountant, who declared: I dont want the Trian people coming in from out of state. This isnt Campbells Soup. This is Pittsburgh. Sean D. Hamill reported from Pittsburgh for this article and Andrew Ross Sorkin from New York. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/15/business/media/15paper.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Billionaire Investor Buys Tribune Stake<date>Published: August 15, 2006</date><text>Nelson Peltz, the billionaire investor who is in a proxy fight with the H. J. Heinz Company, has bought a stake in the Tribune Company, the newspaper publisher, according to a regulatory filing yesterday. Mr. Peltz bought about 2.8 million shares in Tribune in the second quarter, according to the filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. That is about 1.2 percent of the companys shares outstanding. Officials at Mr. Peltzs firm, the Trian Fund, and at Tribune were not immediately available for comment. Mr. Peltz, with Sandell Asset Management, holds a 5.5 percent stake in Heinz. He has engaged the company in a proxy battle for the last several months as Trian has sought to place several of its own choices on Heinzs board. Tribune is buying back shares and cutting costs at its properties, including The Los Angeles Times. Meanwhile, its largest shareholder, the Chandler Trusts, has called for the company to spin off its broadcasting division or find a buyer for the entire company. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/15/us/15pittsburgh.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Vote for Control of Heinz Keeps Pittsburgh on Edge<date>Published: August 15, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Aug. 10  It is election season here, but residents say a lot more is at stake than politics. Skip to next paragraph Lisa Kyle for The New York Times Special labels on ketchup bottles urged stockholders how to vote. Stockholders of the H. J. Heinz Company will cast their final ballots on Wednesday to decide whether an investment group will gain a near majority on the board. Many people here fear that if the investors win enough seats they will eventually move the companys headquarters from this city, where it has been for more than a century. I guess all of us remember the breakup of Gulf Oil, said Bill Lape, a retired employee of Heinz, referring to the former Pittsburgh-based company that merged and moved its offices out of town in 1983 after the corporate raider Boone Pickens tried to take it over. For this old steel city that lost its last steel mill two decades ago, the current fight is as much about pride as money and jobs. As we have said on numerous occasions, the Trian Group has no intention of either taking control of Heinzs board of directors or moving the company from Pittsburgh, said Carrie Bloom, a spokeswoman for the investment group. But no one around here seems to believe it. I never heard of anything good coming when a new company takes over, said Duane Buzzelli, 60, who retired from Heinz in 2002 and lives on his pension. Once a month, Mr. Buzzelli meets with other retirees to discuss shared concerns, like Medicare and investments. Lately, he said, the only thing anyone talks about is the board fight. We have this joke, he said. If we lose our pension and benefits, we will all go live under the 16th Street bridge together. Residents say they have reason to be jittery. Since 1970, the city and surrounding area have lost more than half of their manufacturing jobs and 14 percent of their population. Many are also skeptical about the Trian Groups director, Nelson Peltz, who is known as a quick flipper, an expert at buying companies, whipping them into shape and then selling them at sizable profits. That is good news for some investors. But it has the 1,200 Heinz employees here and the 10,000 Heinz pensioners in the city and surrounding area wondering whether promises made now by Trian will matter if the investment group sells its shares. If that corporation gets all mixed up and moves, Pittsburgh is going be lost, said Irene Sample, a retired nurse who lives in Mount Lebanon, just outside the city. Ms. Sample said that for the first time in her life she had found herself going straight to the business section when she opened her morning paper to follow the back and forth. As one of the few large companies that still have their headquarters in this former industrial hub, Heinz is everywhere. On the Ohio River, Heinz Field is home to the football Steelers. Downtown, Heinz Hall is where the citys world-class symphony plays. Four blocks from there, the Heinz History Center tells visitors the 250-year-old story of Pittsburgh. Ive been employed by five to six nonprofits here in my career, and all depend on Heinzs generosity, said Ambrose P. Murray, executive director of the Extra Mile Education Foundation, which supports underserved schools in the city, and receives more than $100,000 a year of its $2 million budget from Heinz. I think a lot of organizations are concerned about this fight. PNC, a local bank, has said it will vote for the Heinz directors, as has Calpers, the large California pension plan. All three of the major advisory services suggested supporting at least one of Mr. Peltzs nominees, but none supported his full slate of five nominees for the 12-member board. Senator John Kerrys wife, Teresa Heinz Kerry, who was married to the late grandson of the founder of the company, does not hold a significant percentage of shares. The incumbent board members are not going down without a fight. Since March, the company has spent $14 million on Project Steelers, as they have named their campaign, to pay for full-page advertisements in local and national newspapers and to call stockholders to urge them to reject the Trian nominees. The company has also sent employees and stockholders more than 1,000 bottles of ketchup labeled the White Card is the Right Card. (Each side has mailed proxy cards to the more than 200,000 shareholders for them to vote on the new board. White cards are for Heinz; gold cards are for the Trian Group). The editorial board at The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette has also made its views known. Unfortunately, corporate raiders are full of talk, and their aggression has often turned out to be another word for destruction, it said on July 21. It is time to pick sides. The H. J. Heinz Company is the side we choose. Local talk radio stations that normally fixate on the citys sports teams have been fielding calls from listeners wanting to voice concerns about the board fight. But for all of the local concern, in the end it is not clear how much say residents will have in the decision. Institutional investors hold more than 70 percent of the companys outstanding stock, and most of them are out of state. The only shareholder larger than Trian is an investment company in Los Angeles. That company has not said how it will vote. More Articles in National »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/21/business/21heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz, in Proxy Fight, Will Expand Board<date>Published: July 21, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, July 20  The H. J. Heinz Company announced plans on Thursday to add up to two seats to its board, bringing the total to 14 as well as other changes that it said would strengthen its corporate governance. The company, which is engaged in a proxy battle with a group led by the billionaire investor Nelson Peltz, said it had agreed in principle to adopt majority voting in the elections of directors, reduce supermajority shareholder voting provisions from 80 percent to 60 percent, and adopt a shareholder rights plan. Heinz also pledged to meet regularly with its independent directors and crucial board members. A Heinz spokesman, Michael Mullen, said that after meeting with many shareholders, Heinz is taking decisive action to further strengthen corporate governance and accountability. Heinz has faced criticism over its weak stock performance, and a dissident shareholder group led by Mr. Peltz has nominated 5 proposed members for the 12-member board as part of an effort to bolster returns. Mr. Peltz and his investment firm, the Trian Group, which owns 5.5 percent of Heinzs shares, want to put new members on the board to push an aggressive plan aimed at increasing shareholder returns. Heinz has dismissed the plan as flawed, charging that it would cripple the company, and it has announced a growth strategy of its own. The companys shares fell 25 cents yesterday, to $42.36. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/02/business/02heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Cutting Costs, Heinz Plans Fewer Plants<date>Published: June 2, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, June 1 (AP)  The H. J. Heinz Company, one of the world's largest food companies, said Thursday that its quarterly profit fell 19 percent and that it would cut 2,700 jobs and exit 15 plants as part of a plan to cut costs and increase profit. The company, best known for its namesake ketchup, has faced pressure from a billionaire investor, Nelson Peltz, to increase shareholder returns. It recently rejected a cost-cutting proposal by Mr. Peltz and his Trian Group. Bloomberg News reported yesterday that Mr. Peltz said the Heinz restructuring plan did not go far enough and he would continue to wage a proxy battle for five board seats. Heinz said profit declined to $167.9 million, or 50 cents a share, from $206.5 million, or 59 cents a share, a year earlier. The earnings were affected by charges linked to asset sales and a write-down of operations in Zimbabwe and gains from the sale of its European Seafood and Tegel poultry businesses, along with other noncore companies. Steeper interest costs and a higher quarterly tax rate also hurt results, the company said. Revenue in the period, which ended May 3 and was the fourth quarter of Heinz's fiscal year, grew nearly 8 percent, to $2.4 billion, from $2.23 billion, helped by growth in brands like Classico pasta sauce and Ore-Ida frozen potatoes William R. Johnson, chief executive of Heinz, said a four-year restructuring effort was complete, making it a "much leaner, more focused business." The efforts have focused on ramping up growth in three food categories: ketchup and sauces, meals and snacks, and infant nutrition. Heinz has been selling underperforming European businesses as part of the strategy. "With all of this now behind us, today's Heinz is structurally the company I envisioned four years ago," he said in a conference call Thursday. "We have made some of the most important people changes in this company's history." He also outlined plans for 2007 and 2008, saying the company would follow a three-part growth strategy to include cutting costs, developing core businesses and raising cash to increase shareholder returns. Heinz expects to save $355 million over the next two years through cost reductions including the layoffs and 15 plant exits this fiscal year, Mr. Johnson said. He did not identify the plants. The company is considering exiting five more plants in fiscal 2008. Michael Mullen, a Heinz spokesman, said the company "would be looking to sell or divest" the vast majority of the facilities, most of which are located outside the United States. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/25/business/25heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Investor's Demands Rebuffed by Heinz<date>Published: May 25, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News The H. J. Heinz Company, the food manufacturer, said yesterday that it had rejected a demand by the billionaire investor Nelson Peltz for representation on the board. Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, also said Mr. Peltz's demand to cut annual costs by $575 million was "unrealistic." The company said Mr. Peltz's nominees for five new directors did not meet company standards for qualifications or independence. Heinz next week will disclose its own plan to cut costs, increase sales and repurchase shares, the company said. A group of shareholders led by Mr. Peltz  including the investment firms Trian Fund Management, which he controls, and the Sandell Asset Management Corporation  outlined the proposal yesterday. They own about 5.4 percent of the company's stock. Mr. Peltz urged the company to sell assets, increase share repurchases and focus on its strongest brands. His push for change comes after the shares lost almost a quarter of their value in the five years through 2005. Heinz shares fell 37 cents yesterday, to $42.61. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/01/business/01heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Earnings Fall on Cost of Downsizing<date>Published: March 1, 2006</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Feb. 28 (AP)  The H. J. Heinz Company, one of the world's largest food producers, said on Tuesday that quarterly earnings fell 24 percent because of high costs related to downsizing and divestitures. Net income fell to $116.6 million, or 35 cents a share, for the three months that ended Jan. 25 from $152.4 million, or 43 cents a share, in the quarter last year. Revenue rose 6 percent, to $2.19 billion from $2.07 billion. Earnings from continuing operations totaled 39 cents a share. Earnings from continuing operations, excluding reorganization, impairment costs and other items, was 50 cents a share. Heinz said special items in the quarter for downsizing, integration, separation and preparation for sale totaled $27.9 million. The company also recorded a loss of $19.5 million related to potential sales. In addition to its flagship ketchup brand, Heinz owns Ore-Ida French fries, Boston Market and Smart Ones prepared meals and assorted Heinz sauces, soups and beans. For fiscal 2007, Heinz is projecting sales growth of 3 percent to 4 percent and earnings growth of 6 percent to 8 percent from a range of $2.10 to $2.16 a share anticipated for fiscal 2006. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/23/business/23heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Earnings Increase 2% at Heinz, Helped by a One-Time Gain<date>Published: November 23, 2005</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Nov. 22 (AP) - The H. J. Heinz Company reported Tuesday that its second-quarter earnings edged up 2 percent thanks to a one-time gain, and said that it was close to selling several underperforming European businesses. The company, whose brands include its namesake ketchup, Ore-Ida frozen potatoes and Smart Ones meals, said quarterly profit totaled $203.8 million, or 60 cents a share, up from about $199 million, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. The results included 9 cents a share from discontinued operations, related to resolved tax liabilities from businesses spun off to Del Monte Foods. Heinz officials told analysts that the company's efforts to streamline and focus on its core brands were paying off despite continuing struggles in Europe and the pressure of rising energy prices. "We're generally pleased as we posted good results in sales, earnings and cash flow," said William R. Johnson, president and chief executive. "We continue to gain momentum toward our goal of simplifying the company." Shares of Heinz rose 62 cents, or 1.8 percent, to $35.68 in afternoon trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Earnings from continuing operations fell to $171.8 million, or 50 cents a share, from $197.3 million, or 56 cents a share. The results exceeded analysts' estimates of 54 cents a share on $2.3 billion in revenue, according to Thomson Financial. Excluding reorganization charges, expenses for strategic reviews and other costs, Heinz earned $212 million, or 62 cents a share, and remains on course to report $2.35 to $2.45 in earnings a share by the end of the fiscal year, Mr. Johnson said. The company also expects to finish the year with $900 million to $1 billion in cash flow, Mr. Johnson said, giving it more flexibility in dealing with rising costs and debt. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/21/business/worldbusiness/21heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Hopes to Sell Overseas Food Units<date>Published: September 21, 2005</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it was hoping to sell its European seafood, vegetable and frozen food operations as it tried to focus on ketchup and other businesses to drive up earnings. The overhaul of the European portfolio would replicate steps Heinz took in recent years to jump-start its North American business. In a meeting with analysts, Heinz fleshed out plans that it telegraphed in May, when it said it was selling the HAK line of prepared foods and would review the seafood and frozen food businesses in Europe. The strategy, Heinz said, is to devote its resources to three food groups: ketchup, condiments and sauces; meals and snacks; and infant nutrition. The company, which makes its namesake ketchup, Bagel Bites snacks and other packaged foods, said its goal was to have a more focused organization that can increase revenue 3 percent to 4 percent a year, with earnings per share rising at the upper end of a 6 percent to 8 percent range. Heinz hired J. P. Morgan Chase &amp; Company to help sell the businesses. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/23/business/23food.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Quarterly Earnings Tumble at Two Big Food Makers<date>Published: August 23, 2005</date><text>The food makers H. J. Heinz and J. W. Smucker said first-quarter net income declined on higher costs. Heinz, the world's biggest ketchup maker, said in a statement yesterday that earnings dropped 19 percent as sales gained 5.3 percent. Profit excluding costs beat analysts' estimates. Skip to next paragraph Andrew Harrer/Bloomberg News Heinz was hurt by $24.5 million in costs to cut about 200 jobs. Forum: Markets and Industries Net income at Smucker, the nation's largest maker of jellies and jams, fell 8.9 percent while revenue climbed 23 percent. Profit at Heinz was hurt by $24.5 million in costs to cut about 200 jobs as the company loses market share to Nestlé and Unilever in Europe. Smucker's marketing spending jumped 15 percent, bolstered by promotions of the Pillsbury and Hungry Jack brands it bought last year. Net income at Heinz declined to $157.3 million, or 45 cents a share, from $194.8 million, or 55 cents, in the period a year earlier. Sales in the quarter ended July 27 increased to $2.11 billion. Excluding the costs of cutting jobs and reviewing businesses for sale, profit at Heinz would have been 52 cents a share. On that basis, which does not conform to generally accepted accounting principles, the company was expected to earn 49 cents. The food maker reiterated its forecast that fiscal 2006 earnings would rise to $2.35 to $2.45 a share, with sales gaining 4 percent to 6 percent. The company made $2.13 a share last year. Net income at Smucker declined to $29.9 million, or 51 cents a share, from $32.8 million, or 60 cents, a year earlier. Revenue for the first quarter ended July 31 rose to $510.3 million. Smucker said it earned 56 cents a share, excluding merger and revamping costs. On that basis, the company was expected by analysts to earn 63 cents. Last June, Smucker purchased International Multifoods, which brought the company the Pillsbury, Hungry Jack and Martha White brands, increasing interest costs 39 percent in the quarter. Shares of Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh and sells products in 200 countries, rose 39 cents, or 1 percent, to $36.69 in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. Smucker, which is based in Orrville, Ohio, plunged $2.01, or 4.2 percent, to $46.01. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E6DA133BF932A15755C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">World Business Briefing | Europe: France: Heinz to Buy Danone Sauces<date>Published: June 21, 2005</date><text>H.J. Heinz, the condiment company, said that it signed a deal with the French food company Groupe Danone to buy several of its sauce brands. Heinz will acquire Lea &amp; Perrins Worcestershire sauce, HP sauce and the Amoy line of Chinese sauces, for $855 million. The brands, which are marketed mainly in the United States, Britain and Canada, have annual sales of $300 million, Heinz said. Heather Timmons (NYT)</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/20/business/worldbusiness/20deal.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Is Said to Be Near a Deal to Acquire HP Foods of Britain<date>Published: June 20, 2005</date><text>LONDON, June 19 - The H. J. Heinz Company is close to a £470 million ($861.3 million) deal to buy HP Foods, the British condiment company, from Groupe Danone, according to three executives close to the negotiations. The all-cash deal is expected to be announced here on Monday morning, these executives said. Heinz already has a sizable presence in Britain, where it employs about 5,000 people. The company, which is based in Pittsburgh, has been focusing on its ketchup and condiment lines. HP Foods is famous in Britain for its namesake sauce, a spicy brown condiment often eaten with bacon sandwiches and "fry ups," a traditional English breakfast of eggs, sausages, bacon, beans, tomatoes and mushrooms. The ubiquitous sauce's name stands for Houses of Parliament, where it was supposedly served more than a century ago. The company's Lea &amp; Perrins Worcestershire sauce was first made by John Wheeley Lea and William Henry Perrins in the 1830's, and it earned an international following after its manufacturers paid stewards on ocean liners to serve it. HP Foods also owns Daddies, a line of ketchups and condiments; Rajah, an Indian spice line; and Amoy, a Chinese sauce brand. The London-based company has sales of about £180 million a year and employs 400 people. Groupe Danone, which owns HP Foods, is one of the world's largest food companies, with brands including Dannon yogurt and Evian water. The Paris-based company has been paring assets, and in May sold its stake in Mahou, the Spanish brewer of San Miguel beer. It purchased HP Foods in 1988 for £199 million. The company did not return a call on Sunday for comment. Heinz said in May that it was reviewing its international businesses. It is considering selling some units, including seafood and frozen foods businesses in Europe, the Weight Watchers products and the Linda McCartney vegetarian line. Heinz's chairman, chief executive and president, William R. Johnson, is under pressure to increase earnings per share, which were slightly less in 2004 than the year before. He said in May that the company would "place our focus and resources on our big brands with No. 1 and No. 2 market positions and in four large developing markets." Heinz also reorganized its management in May, adding a seven-member office of the chairman to the company. A Heinz spokeswoman had no comment on Sunday. Heather Timmons reported from London for this article and Andrew Ross Sorkin from New York. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DC1F30F935A25756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Cramer-Krasselt Assigned Additional Heinz Brands<date>Published: May 16, 2005</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company in Pittsburgh has consolidated advertising for its United States consumer products at Cramer-Krasselt in Chicago by awarding the agency the assignment for brands like Heinz ketchup and Classico pasta sauces. Total spending was not disclosed; the company has not advertised the brands widely in recent years. Leo Burnett USA in Chicago, part of the Leo Burnett Worldwide division of the Publicis Groupe, had handled ketchup, and Campbell Mithun in Minneapolis, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, had handled Classico. Cramer-Krasselt will also create campaigns for Heinz products like 57 Sauce, gravies, pickles and vinegar, which previously had no agency. Cramer-Krasselt joined the Heinz agency roster in August when it was awarded the Heinz frozen-foods account, for brands like Ore-Ida potatoes and Weight Watchers Smart Ones meals and desserts. Spending to advertise the frozen foods was estimated at $15 million.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/08/business/worldbusiness/08tax.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">European Tax Opinion Could Mean Huge Refunds<date>Published: April 8, 2005</date><text>RUSSELS, April 7 - A member of Europe's highest court offered a preliminary opinion Thursday that could lead to billions of euros in tax refunds to companies at a time when many European governments can least afford them. On Thursday, Miguel Poiares Maduro, an advocate general on the European Court of Justice, said that British tax authorities erred in denying the retail chain Marks &amp; Spencer the right to offset losses incurred in other European Union countries in its British tax filing. Advertisement If the judge's opinion is upheld, as often occurs, governments throughout Europe might face a threat to their already hard-pressed budgets. That possibility prompted Germany and six other countries to intervene in support of the British government at a court hearing last year. Their efforts apparently had little effect. "The advocate general rejects the German government's argument that the taking into account of foreign losses by the state concerned could not be permitted because it would lead to a reduction in tax revenue, and thus to major budgetary difficulties for the member state concerned," the court said in a statement Thursday. Marks &amp; Spencer has been seeking a tax refund of more than £30 million ($56.4 million), since 2001 from Inland Revenue, the British tax agency, to compensate it for losses in Belgium, Germany and France that it was not able to claim in those countries. Marks &amp; Spencer incurred the losses during a doomed foray into Continental Europe in the late 1990's. Adam Craig, head of the European tax practice of Deloitte Touche, commented, "Britain could face a bill of up to £1 billion." Sixty other companies have filed claims similar to Marks &amp; Spencer's in the British courts, and Thursday's opinion could become legal precedent for them. Those companies include British Telecom; the British subsidiary of BNP Paribas; and three American companies with large operations in Britain, the H. J. Heinz food company, PepsiCo and the construction equipment maker Caterpillar. "There are hundreds of others that have made similar claims in their tax returns," Mr. Craig noted. Analysts said Germany in particular had good reason to be worried about the Marks &amp; Spencer case. "If the final ruling permits retroactive claims, then the German government could face a bill of 30 billion euros," said Isabelle Kronawitter, an economist with the German bank HVB. That, she said, was her estimate of losses at German subsidiaries in other countries in the European Union from 1998 to 2002. The issue of retroactivity, however, has not yet been decided. The court will ultimately rule on whether companies are allowed to claim past losses, which will determine the impact on national treasuries across Europe. "It's 50-50," Ms. Kronawitter said of chances for retroactivity, adding that the court may decide not to allow it so that member states could have time to adjust their tax laws. Mr. Craig, however, felt sure the ruling would allow retroactive claims. "It would be surprising if the companies that have already made claims are unable to get their money back," he said. Mr. Maduro, the judge, stressed that a company should not be able to get a double tax advantage by registering the loss both at home and in the country where the losses occurred.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DA123DF932A35750C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ'S QUARTERLY PROFIT DROPS 25% ON WRITE-DOWN<date>Published: March 1, 2005</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company posted a 25 percent drop in quarterly profit yesterday because of a write-down of its investment in Hain Celestial Group, but frozen foods helped lead an increase in sales. Profit fell to $152.4 million, or 43 cents a share, in the third quarter, which ended Jan. 26, from $202.2 million, or 57 cents a share, a year earlier. Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, said that third-quarter sales rose 7.8 percent, to $2.26 billion, led by an 11 percent increase in North America. Higher prices in the United States and a lower-than-expected tax rate helped mitigate increases in costs for steel, fuel and other items, as well as lower prices in Europe, the company said. But third-quarter profit was hurt by $73.8 million in noncash charges, primarily from the write-down of Heinz's investment in the organic food maker Hain, based in Melville, N.Y. Heinz said in December that it would have to write down its 16 percent stake in Hain, which it bought at an average of $30 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB143EF937A15752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; PROFIT AT HEINZ RISES BUT IS BELOW EXPECTATIONS<date>Published: November 24, 2004</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company reported yesterday that it had higher earnings for the second quarter as revenue rose on strong sales of its Ore-Ida potatoes products in North America. But the profit fell short of Wall Street's projections. Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, reported a net income of $198.9 million, or 56 cents a share, for the three months ended Oct. 27, compared with $191.5 million, or 54 cents, for the period last year. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial had expected earnings of 59 cents a share. Shares of Heinz fell 61 cents, or 1.5 percent, to $37.78 yesterday.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/10/business/yourmoney/10sund.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Once and for All, It's Not Kerry Ketchup<date>Published: October 10, 2004</date><text>N the last year, no fewer than four major food companies have attributed weak earnings to low-carb diets. Interstate Bakeries, which makes Twinkies, even blamed the trend for forcing it into bankruptcy court. H. J. Heinz has escaped serious problems by adding low-carb alternatives to its lineup of ketchup, pickles and other foods. Still, while it has recently reported stronger earnings growth than its peers, Heinz has not been rewarded on Wall Street; its stock price has not reflected its earnings growth. The chairman and chief executive of Heinz, William R. Johnson, recently discussed what he called the "low-carb craze," the company's stock performance and the way it has been linked to Democratic Senator John Kerry, whose wife, Teresa Heinz Kerry, was married to the company heir H. John Heinz III before he died; she remains a shareholder. Following are excerpts from the interview: Advertisement Q. Interstate Bakeries, Krispy Kreme and others have been blaming changing consumer preference for low carbs for cutting into revenue and bringing down earnings. Do you think that's a legitimate claim? Have consumer tastes changed that much that quickly? A. I don't think consumer tastes have necessarily changed. We've been selling ketchup for over 100 years. People like it as much if not more today as they did 100 years ago. I think, particularly on the low-carb craze, we pretty much predicted almost a year ago that this would be a temporary phenomenon and that it would peak pretty quickly. So we addressed it as a tactical issue and not as a strategic issue. Q. Do you think there's any merit to the claims that the low-carb craze could significantly affect some companies' revenues? A. Well, I think there's certainly been a short-term impact, but I think the low-carb phenomenon speaks to the bigger issue, which is health and wellness and nutrition. Our view is this is just one edge of the leading trend, which is really health and wellness and nutrition. Q. You've recently made a bigger push behind Ore-Ida, the potato processor that is a Heinz brand. If people are interested in low carbs and health and wellness, how does that fit? French fries are not generally perceived as being high in nutrition and low in salt. A. Well, I think people want choice, and they want things that taste good. And, interestingly enough, the primary change in Ore-Ida with the new line is to greatly improve the taste and texture of our product. The other thing Ore-Ida brings, particularly with the new Easy Fries, is greater convenience. And convenience is a trend that mirrors that of nutrition. People are time-compressed, they lead busy lives, there are many dual-working families. They want things that taste good and are good for them, and at the same time are convenient and portable. Q. Are those the two biggest trends in the food business right now: health and wellness, and convenience? A. I certainly think they're the macro trends. I think convenience also plays into more away-from-home eating and more takeout. But I think those are the two big macro trends against which there are a lot of smaller subtrends. But ultimately food has to taste good. If food doesn't taste good, it can't meet the other two trends. So the trend that has been with us since the first processed food was introduced is good taste. Q. Heinz's profit has grown more than your stock price would suggest. Do you have any plans for trying to convince Wall Street that things are changing at Heinz? A. We talk continuously to Wall Street, and I think the best example of that is that since the spinoff of several of our businesses to Del Monte in 2002, which actually made us a smaller company, our shareholder return has been in the top tier of our peer group. So, again, it goes back to the need to be good. The market will eventually recognize us for what we are, which is a consistent, predictable, solidly performing company, and I think we'll be rewarded accordingly. Q. Where are you headed? Are you aiming to become a Unilever, or to position the company for sale? A. This is not about being big; this is about being good. We had an employee global meeting the other day with all our employees around the world via Webcast, and we talked about our vision of becoming the "good-food company" and the premier company in the industry. Q. The election has brought attention to the connection between Teresa Heinz Kerry and the company. Has it had any effect on your business? A. We don't believe the election rhetoric has had an impact on us one way or the other. We appeal to Republicans, Democrats, independents, just across a broad section of beliefs and views. That's our view. We have absolutely no connection at all with the family. The family has absolutely no connection with us. I think it's an unfortunate situation that's arisen out of some confusion and out of some misguided attempts to link us, but there is no linkage. Q. What about W Ketchup? Have you tried it? Have you seen it? A. I haven't tried W Ketchup because I know we make the best ketchup and our sales continue to grow, so I know it hasn't had an impact on us. Q. I understand you are a Republican. Is that correct? A. That is correct. Q. Does it bother you at all that there has been a perceived Democratic connection to the company? A. No. Q. It probably didn't help your business when James Tedisco, a Republican New York state assemblyman, said that buying Heinz ketchup was like giving to Democrats. A. As I said, the rhetoric has had no impact on us. Q. Has it diverted any attention away from your day-to-day business? A. No, it takes virtually no time for me. An extended version of this interview is at nytimes.com/yourmoney.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/08/dining/08KETC.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">A Ketchup Too Spicy for the G.O.P.<date>Published: September 8, 2004</date><text>AN a ketchup be too partisan? And what exactly does "conservative" taste like? Over the last five months, W Ketchup and Bush Country Ketchup have been marketed as a swipe at Teresa Heinz Kerry, the wife of Senator John Kerry, the Democratic nominee. Mrs. Kerry's first husband, Senator H. John Heinz III, a Republican and heir to the Heinz fortune, died in a plane crash. Bush Country Ketchup was first sold in April by two 26-year-old former college roommates. Two months later, a group of friends from the Upper East Side came out with W Ketchup, which has been more of the media darling of the two products. Advertisement In fact, W was sold at the Republican National Convention's G.O.P. Marketplace last week, while Bush Country Ketchup was banned. The reason? A labeling issue: Bush Country Ketchup's label sports an elephant trampling John Kerry. "I think the key words were respectful and positive," Dwight Williams, a convention spokesman, said of products approved for sale at the marketplace. "We offered the owner a chance to offer the product with a different label, but as it was, it didn't send the right message." The label for W is more subtle. "George Washington was selected for the label in order to avoid overt campaign advertising," said Bill Zachary, a managing director at an investment bank, who along with Dan Oliver helped come up with the product. "What does the W stand for?" Mr. Zachary said. "If people can't get the joke, then they can't get the joke." The founders of Bush Country Ketchup, Patrick Spero, a graduate student at the University of Pennsylvania, and Christopher Cylke, a junior staffer for the House Judiciary Committee, say they are more conservative entrepreneurs; but Mr. Zachary declined to engage in that kind of food fight. Mr. Spero said that when they were asked to change their label for the convention, "it would not only have been cost-prohibitive, but would have changed our whole message; trouncing is a common political metaphor." So far, the more moderate ketchup has sold more than 100,000 bottles (www.wketchup.com), while Bush Country has sold much of its initial run of 4,500. W, at $3 for a 24-ounce bottle, is also more moderately priced than Bush Country, which is $5.99 for a 13-ounce bottle; www.bushcountryketchup.com. The H. J. Heinz Company states on its Web site (www.heinz.com) that it is nonpartisan. A 24-ounce bottle is about $1.60. But recently, a nonscientific sampling of about 18 independent-minded ketchup lovers (at a late-night, nonpartisan Wendy's) consistently picked Heinz in blind taste tests. One tester (an independent voter from Washington State) initially liked the spicy sweetness of Bush Country, which has an almost barbecue flavor, but complained about the aftertaste. She, as others did, thought Heinz's vinegary taste was better for fattier, saltier foods like French fries. W, a lighter, sweeter version than Heinz, got few votes. Whichever image the Republican Party preferred in New York, away from the television cameras and back at the Capitol Hill Club in Washington, Bush Country is the ketchup of choice. Stan Lawson, general manager of the club, a prominent Republican hangout, said, "There's only so much room on the table."</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/02/business/media/02adco.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">The Branding of the Presidency<date>Published: September 2, 2004</date><text>HE race for the White House is turning into a brandapalooza for marketers as products and ad slogans assume increasingly prominent roles in the campaign - almost as if this were the first officially sponsored presidential election. Thanks to Teresa Heinz Kerry, the wife of the Democratic candidate, Senator John Kerry, the foremost campaign brand by far is Heinz ketchup, as typified by a question asked by Jon Stewart, the host of "The Daily Show," when Mr. Kerry appeared on the program Aug. 24: "Is it true that every time I use ketchup, your wife gets a nickel?" (Mr. Kerry's reply: "Would that it were.") Advertisement The Heinz mentions have become so frequent that some Republicans have started selling a brand of ketchup called W. Bill Zachary, a banker who co-founded the ketchup company in Eagle Bridge, N.Y., described W in an interview as "an alternative to Heinz, to give Republican voters a fun way to show their stripes." Ads on the W brand's Web site (wketchup.com) declare: "You don't support Democrats. Why should your ketchup?" The H. J. Heinz Company has even posted a statement on its own Web site (heinz.com) addressing the subject, describing its ketchup as "a nonpartisan condiment that simply stands for great taste." (Mrs. Kerry, as the widow of Senator John Heinz, is heir to the Heinz family fortune; according to the statement, the family trusts and endowments own less than 4 percent of the company's stock.) There have also been campaign cameo appearances by Diet Coke, a can of which is almost always within reach of Senator John Edwards, Mr. Kerry's running mate; the Wendy's fast-food chain, where Mr. Edwards and his wife, Elizabeth, celebrated their wedding anniversary at a Newburgh, N.Y., store on July 30, accompanied by the Kerrys; and Bush's baked beans, which is family-owned but not by that Bush family. Still, the Bushes have played their part in connecting Madison and Pennsylvania Avenues. For instance, when Laura Bush, the first lady, appeared on "The Tonight Show" on May 19, she responded to a question from Jay Leno about what she did during a recent visit to Las Vegas by echoing the popular slogan from the city's tourism ads, replying, "Jay, what happens in Vegas stays in Vegas." And during a speech on Tuesday at the Republican National Convention, the Bush daughters, Barbara and Jenna, said they could probably persuade their father and mother to "shake it like a Polaroid picture," citing a lyric from the OutKast song "Hey Ya." The new prevalence of brand names and themes is indicative of the growing role played by commercial culture in American society, even in the once-sacrosanct realm of politics, marketing and corporate identity, consultants say. "Americans are more familiar and comfortable navigating the world of product brands than they are the world of politics," said Allen Adamson, managing director of Landor Associates in New York, a consultant owned by the WPP Group, "so using brands to figure out what politicians are about is inevitable." The other side of the coin holds true as well, said Lucian James, president of Agenda, a brand strategy consultant in San Francisco. "Because brands are a huge part of the public consciousness, and are how we identify ourselves, mentioning brands serves as a useful shortcut for politicians to try to get closer to the people they represent," Mr. James said. That is particularly true as it becomes "impossible to divorce politics from pop culture," he added, citing the crossover into public life of celebrities like Arnold Schwarzenegger, the Republican governor of California, who also spoke at the convention on Tuesday. The branding of the 2004 election cycle may have begun in April, Mr. James said, with the extensive coverage of a passage from the book "Plan of Attack," in which the author, Bob Woodward, quoted Colin L. Powell, the secretary of state, as warning President Bush of the consequence of invading Iraq by citing "the Pottery Barn rule" of "you break it, you own it." The quote was so widely publicized that executives of Pottery Barn, the furnishings retail chain owned by Williams-Sonoma, took pains to tell reporters that the stores have no such policy. (In other words, what breaks at Pottery Barn stays at Pottery Barn.) Michael Watras, president of Straightline International in New York, a brand identity consultant, sees the Pottery Barn episode as a cautionary tale. "Ultimately, brands can be put at risk, high risk, from the fallout" surrounding politics, Mr. Watras said. "It's an area they need to stay away from because of the potential to polarize consumers," especially when polls show the electorate so closely divided. Mr. Watras drew a distinction between candidates mentioning or using products that have been part of their lives "before they decided to run," as Diet Coke and Wendy's have been for Mr. Edwards, and the marketers in question taking out ads to take advantage of the publicity and attention. "If Coke says, 'Edwards drinks Diet Coke and you should, too,' that's in bad taste," he added. Indeed, Heinz and the other companies behind the brands of the 2004 campaign say they will eschew exploiting their political exposure. The maker of Diet Coke, the Coca-Cola Company, is "delighted Senator Edwards is such an avid fan," said Mart Martin, a spokesman in Atlanta, "and we'll gladly accept his endorsement." But, he said, "there are no plans to capitalize on it." Bob Bertini, a spokesman for Wendy's International in Dublin, Ohio, said: "We appreciate our repeat customers, whether vice presidential candidates or visitors from the neighborhood. But we just didn't think it was appropriate to do anything with it. "We certainly made sure his order was correct," Mr. Bertini added, laughing. Wendy's has experience in the campaign arena, having enjoyed considerable publicity in 1984, when Vice President Walter F. Mondale, in a debate, quoted its ad slogan at the time: "Where's the beef?" Steve Harrison, a spokesman at Bush Brothers &amp; Company in Knoxville, Tenn., the maker of Bush's baked beans since 1908, recalled a campaign event in 2000 during which George W. Bush "visited the kitchen of a homeless shelter and held up a can of our beans." Asked about the coincidence of Heinz selling baked beans as well as ketchup, Mr. Harrison said: "They're better known for baked beans in Europe and we're better known for baked beans in the States. And we're happy with that."</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/25/business/heinz-profit-is-down-9-for-quarter.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Profit Is Down 9% For Quarter<date>Published: August 25, 2004</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company said yesterday that fiscal first-quarter profit fell 9 percent from a year earlier, when the company spun off businesses. Retail sales in North America rose for the first time in four quarters.Net income decreased to $194.8 million, or 55 cents a share, from $214 million, or 60 cents, in the year-earlier period, when earnings included 8 cents of profit from discontinued operations. Sales in the quarter rose 5.7 percent, to $2 billion, according to Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh.Profit in the quarter ended July 28 met the 55-cent average estimate of analysts polled by Thomson First Call.Retail sales in the United States and Canada rose 8.4 percent after the company increased marketing for Smart Ones low-carbohydrate frozen entrees and Ore-Ida Extra Crispy French Fries. The company raised ketchup prices to United States restaurants, muting the effect of higher commodity and transportation costs.''The new low-carb line they just introduced here and the new Ore-Ida brands are doing very well,'' said Marvin Roffman, president of Roffman Miller Associates, which is based in Philadelphia and owns Heinz shares.Heinz, which also makes Classico pasta sauces and Bagel Bites, repeated that it expected fiscal-year earnings to rise to $2.32 to $2.43 a share.Shares of Heinz rose $1.03, to $37.63, yesterday.Results a year earlier included $27.2 million in profit from discontinued operations. In December 2002, Heinz spun off its North American tuna, pet food, private-label soup and baby food businesses and then sold them to the Del Monte Foods Company for $2.9 billion.''The star of the quarter was North America,'' an analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston, David Nelson, wrote in a report. He has a neutral rating on the stock. ''This was the most top-line progress we've seen in a long time from Heinz.''</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/26/business/earnings-rise-in-quarter-for-heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Earnings Rise in Quarter for Heinz<date>Published: May 26, 2004</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company said yesterday that quarterly profit rose sharply, reflecting the benefit of the weak dollar and lower costs. Shipment volume, however, fell 1 percent on reduced marketing spending and a falloff in demand for some frozen foods, which have been hurt by the move toward low-carbohydrate diets.Heinz has been reducing unprofitable products and package sizes, cutting them by about 20 percent in the last year. It is also trying to revitalize frozen foods like Ore-Ida French fries with new crispy versions.The company, based in Pittsburgh, said it earned $196.5 million, or 55 cents a share, in the fourth quarter ended April 28, up from $102.6 million, or 29 cents, in the period a year ago.Quarterly sales rose 6.3 percent, to $2.33 billion, reflecting the benefit of the weak dollar.Earnings per share from continuing operations were 58 cents in the most recent quarter, matching the average of analysts polled by Reuters. That compares with 52 cents a year ago, excluding reorganization costs and the loss on the exit from nonstrategic businesses.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/21/business/company-news-hain-agrees-to-buy-2-food-businesses-from-heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HAIN AGREES TO BUY 2 FOOD BUSINESSES FROM HEINZ<date>Published: May 21, 2004</date><text>Hain Celestial Group, an organic foods maker, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Ethnic Gourmet and Rosetto lines from H.J. Heinz, expanding its offerings of low-carbohydrate foods. Hain also said it had reached an agreement with Sesame Workshop to create natural foods under the Earth's Best brand using Sesame Street characters. Terms of the two transactions were not disclosed. With the purchase of the Heinz businesses, Hain, based in Melville, N.Y., will increase its frozen-foods sales to about $50 million a year. The company plans to introduce low-carbohydrate frozen dinners and pastas under the CarbFit and Rosetto brands.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/04/business/company-news-heinz-is-seeking-to-replace-chief-who-will-resign.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ IS SEEKING TO REPLACE CHIEF WHO WILL RESIGN<date>Published: February 04, 2004</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company said Neil Harrison, the chief executive of Heinz North America, would leave the company to pursue other interests. A search for a successor for Mr. Harrison, who has been with the company since 1997, is under way, the company said. ''It's a career decision, not based on anything else,'' a spokesman, Jack Kennedy, said. Heinz is based in Pittsburgh.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/26/business/company-news-heinz-earnings-off-but-shares-rise.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ EARNINGS OFF BUT SHARES RISE<date>Published: November 26, 2003</date><text>The H.J. Heinz Company yesterday reported that its second-quarter earnings fell nearly 10 percent from the quarter last year, when the company was still reporting results from businesses that have since been spun off to the Del Monte Corporation. If the spinoffs, like Heinz's former pet food brands and Starkist tuna, are taken out of the mix, Heinz earnings were up more than 13 percent from last year. Heinz said that it earned $191.5 million, or 54 cents a share, in the three months that ended Oct. 29, compared with $212.1 million, or 60 cents a share, last fiscal year. Investors responded favorably to the report; Heinz shares were up 52 cents, to close at $36.19. But the latest earnings were a penny a share shy of analysts' expectations, according to Thomson First Call.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/04/business/heinz-sales-and-profit-surge.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Sales and Profit Surge<date>Published: September 04, 2003</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that first-quarter earnings more than doubled, as it sold more products like its namesake ketchup, got a sales lift from a weaker dollar and benefited from an accounting change that reduced results posted a year ago.Sales from continuing operations rose 3 percent, to $1.9 billion, helped by stronger exchange rates on the euro and the British pound. Heinz, which has been expanding throughout Asia and other overseas markets, gets more than 60 percent of its sales from outside the United States.Heinz said it earned $214 million, or 60 cents a share, in the first quarter ended July 30, compared with $100 million, or 28 cents a share, in the period a year ago.Excluding special items and a change in accounting rules for the treatment of good will in last year's quarter, Heinz reported earnings from continuing operations of $179.8 million, or 51 cents a share, compared with $166.0 million, or 47 cents, a year earlier.Those results were in line with analysts' expectations, before special items.Sales volume grew 2.2 percent, reflecting a stronger North American market for ketchup and Classico pasta sauces and higher sales to United States food service customers like restaurants and hotels. The Asia-Pacific region also posted strong results, helped by sales of poultry products, seasonal juices and soy sauce.Those factors helped offset weakness in frozen foods, which Heinz expects to revitalize with some new products in its Ore-Ida potatoes division in the second half of the fiscal year, executives told analysts during a conference call.Heinz shares rose 47 cents, to $33.46.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/31/business/l-pay-for-performance-113859.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Pay for Performance?<date>Published: August 31, 2003</date><text>To the Editor:As a recent purchaser of H. J. Heinz stock, I was not pleased to read about the substantial bonus and stock options for the chief executive during the most recent fiscal year (''At Heinz, a Novel Way to Say the Boss Is Worth It,'' Aug. 10).When the salary is only a small portion of the total pay package -- $1.05 million out of $8.8 million -- one might expect outstanding performance in the stock price. That did not occur.Unfortunately, the story is not unique to that company. Throughout the business community, stock options and bonuses are distributed without regard to performance -- and to the chagrin of the shareholder.Is there any chance that the system will be changed? Please, don't hold your breath.NELSON MARANSSilver Spring, Md., Aug. 11</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/10/business/business-at-heinz-a-novel-way-to-say-the-boss-is-worth-it.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Business; At Heinz, a Novel Way to Say the Boss Is Worth It<date>Published: August 10, 2003</date><text>TO help investors compare executive pay to performance, companies are required to include stock price charts in their annual proxy statements. But what does a company do if its chief executive gained while its shareholders lost?H. J. Heinz, the ketchup maker, has what seems to be a novel answer: It came up with a second chart that presents a much rosier picture of how shareholders fared -- not during the last fiscal year but over a more recent eight-month period. By that measure, Heinz has outperformed its competitors, an interpretation that might make it easier for shareholders to stomach the big raise the company gave to William R. Johnson, its chairman and chief executive.Mr. Johnson received a pay package valued at $8.8 million in the fiscal year that ended on April 30, according to the proxy statement Heinz released last week. That amounted to a 47 percent raise over the $6 million in cash, options and perquisites he received the year before.On top of his salary of $1.05 million, Mr. Johnson received a cash bonus of $1.53 million, stock worth $3.21 million and options worth $2.68 million. The company also paid for a life insurance policy and about $20,000 for his company car.In addition, Heinz enhanced the terms of Mr. Johnson's executive retirement plan at the beginning of the fiscal year to make it more competitive with those of other chief executives, said Ted Smyth, a spokesman at the company's headquarters in Pittsburgh. The upshot is this: If Mr. Johnson, 54, stays at Heinz for nine more years and earns as much in any four of them as he did last year, the company will pay him as much as $3.5 million a year after he retires.More than half of Mr. Johnson's 2003 package -- $4.74 million in cash and restricted shares -- was a bonus for last year. That reward did not reflect the performance of Heinz stock, whose price fell about 20 percent during the fiscal year, or about double the decline of its peer group of packaged-foods companies.''The bonus for management is tied to operational performance, not to the total shareholder return number,'' Mr. Smyth said.The compensation committee of the Heinz board said it had rewarded Mr. Johnson for other achievements, like increasing sales and cash flow and reducing debt, Mr. Smyth said. He added that the company's earnings had met analysts' expectations.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/13/business/heinz-s-earnings-decrease-54.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz's Earnings Decrease 54%<date>Published: June 13, 2003</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that fourth-quarter earnings slumped 54 percent after the company spun off businesses and higher marketing spending failed to increase sales of frozen foods.Net income dropped to $102.6 million, or 29 cents a share, from $223.5 million, or 63 cents, in the fourth-quarter of the year earlier, Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, said in a statement. Sales in the quarter ended April 30 rose 6 percent, to $2.19 billion, bolstered by rising European currencies and price increases.Frozen food sales fell 12 percent, the second consecutive quarterly drop, after disappointing introductions of products like multicolored Ore-Ida Funky Fries. William R. Johnson, the chief executive who spun off the pet food, soup and tuna businesses in December, increased marketing spending by $25 million in the quarter.Excluding $82.2 million in fourth-quarter expenses related to the spinoff and other restructuring costs, Heinz said it would have earned 52 cents a share. On that basis, profit was 1 cent less than the average forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Results from the year-earlier period include profit from discontinued operations of $43.6 million, or 12 cents. The businesses were merged with Del Monte Foods after being spun off to investors.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/04/business/sec-asks-3-food-makers-about-dealings-with-dutch-chain.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">S.E.C. Asks 3 Food Makers About Dealings With Dutch Chain<date>Published: April 04, 2003</date><text>The federal investigation into Royal Ahold, the Dutch grocer, appeared to broaden yesterday when three of the largest food manufacturers in the United States said that they had been contacted by regulators about their dealings with Ahold's distribution business.General Mills, H. J. Heinz and Kraft Foods said they had been asked by the Securities and Exchange Commission to furnish investigators with documents regarding their transactions with Ahold's U.S. Foodservice division. The companies said they were cooperating with investigators, but declined to provide any further details about what information regulators were examining or what they are seeking to learn.Royal Ahold said in February that it had overstated earnings by $500 million for the last two years because of accounting problems connected to payments made to U.S. Foodservice. The problems involved the inflation of promotional payments from suppliers, falsely increasing the unit's profit.Two top Ahold executives have resigned, and others from U.S. Foodservice have been suspended. The Justice Department and the S.E.C. are now investigating the company's accounting.The payments in question are paid by the manufacturers to distributors like U.S. Foodservice as incentives for putting their products on grocers' shelves.Last week, ConAgra Foods, Sara Lee and Tyson Foods acknowledged that they had been contacted by federal regulators regarding the investigation of Ahold and its subsidiaries.At a conference with industry analysts yesterday, Stephen W. Sanger, the chairman and chief executive of General Mills, said his company would continue to supply products to Fleming, the food distribution company that filed for bankruptcy protection on Tuesday after losing its biggest customer, Kmart.The S.E.C. is investigating how Fleming accounted for payments to suppliers and how it reported its revenue and earnings. Analysts and other industry experts are concerned that Fleming's suppliers will halt shipments or demand immediate payment.''We're working actively with Fleming to ensure that we can continue to supply products,'' Mr. Sanger said in a statement.Neither the troubles at Ahold nor Fleming are expected to affect General Mills' previously released financial statements or its 2003 earnings, Mr. Sanger added.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/12/business/3rd-quarter-profit-falls-25-at-heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">3rd-Quarter Profit Falls 25% at Heinz<date>Published: March 12, 2003</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its fiscal third-quarter earnings fell 25 percent, reduced by costs for spinning off some underperforming units to the Del Monte Foods Company in December, but its underlying profit beat expectations.Heinz posted net income of $151.6 million, or 43 cents a share, compared with $201.7 million, or 57 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.Excluding deal-related costs, earnings were $191.5 million, or 54 cents a share, compared with $161.2 million, or 46 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. On that basis, the results beat Wall Street estimates by 2 cents a share, according to Thomson First Call.Sales from continuing operations rose 9.1 percent, to $2.1 billion, helped by better pricing, improved foreign currency rates and acquisitions. But overall shipments fell 1.9 percent, hurt by inflation in some foreign markets and the elimination of some unprofitable product lines. More than half of Heinz's business is outside the United States.The company told analysts that it was also hurt by weakness in its food service business.Heinz said it still expected full-year earnings of $2 to $2.05 a share.In the quarter, Heinz took pretax charges of $81.5 million, primarily for costs related to the Del Monte deal, to reduce overhead in remaining businesses and for a loss on the divestiture of a Canadian fish and frozen vegetable business.Shares of Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, rose 26 cents, to $29.70.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/15/business/company-news-heinz-creates-consumer-and-business-units.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ CREATES CONSUMER AND BUSINESS UNITS<date>Published: January 15, 2003</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company is reorganizing its North American operations into two divisions, the company said yesterday. One will focus on products consumers use at home, like ketchup, condiments and frozen foods. The other one will cater to businesses like restaurants. The move comes less than a month after Heinz completed a $1.2 billion deal that sent StarKist tuna, and other brands to the Del Monte Foods Company, permitting Heinz to concentrate on its core products. Jeff Berger was named president of the ''away from home'' unit, while Dave Moran will lead the ''consumer products'' segment. Heinz is based in Pittsburgh.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/13/business/heinz-profit-edges-up-in-quarter.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Profit Edges Up in Quarter<date>Published: December 13, 2002</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that second-quarter earnings rose slightly, helped by higher sales, price increases in some markets and strong performance from new products like its Easy Squeeze upside-down ketchup bottle.Sales in the quarter ended Oct. 30 rose 6.4 percent, to $2.6 billion, Heinz said, as the company raised prices in some overseas markets and benefited from favorable foreign exchange rates.Heinz posted net earnings of $212.1 million, or 60 cents a share, for the quarter, up from $208.2 million, or 59 cents a share, a year earlier. Overall shipment volumes declined 1.7 percent, reflecting softness in Europe and some developing markets. Heinz said shipments were also hurt as the company trimmed lower-margin products.Despite the decline, shipments were better than analysts had expected and showed improvement from Heinz's first-quarter decline of 4.6 percent.The company also said that plans were on track to spin off StarKist tuna, private-label soup, pet food and some other underperforming units into a venture with Del Monte Foods, and that the deal could close as early as Dec. 20.Excluding costs for the Del Monte deal, Heinz earned $219 million, or 62 cents a diluted share, in the quarter. Analysts had expected 54 cents to 62 cents a share before special items, with an average estimate of 58 cents, according to Thomson First Call.After the spinoff, Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, plans to operate as a leaner company, relying on the sales of condiments, sauces and frozen foods. In addition, Heinz plans to continue to expand in developing markets overseas, particularly Asia, which posted higher quarterly sales.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/nyregion/c-corrections-042790.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Corrections<date>Published: November 22, 2002</date><text>A report in the Company News column of Business Day yesterday about the disclosure of a takeover offer made earlier this year for the Del Monte Foods Company, which rejected it, referred incorrectly to a transaction with the H. J. Heinz Company. Del Monte is merging into a new company controlled by Heinz shareholders; it is not being acquired by Heinz.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/21/business/company-news-del-monte-discloses-offer-received-before-bid-by-heinz.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; DEL MONTE DISCLOSES OFFER RECEIVED BEFORE BID BY HEINZ<date>Published: November 21, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedShares of the Del Monte Foods Company traded higher yesterday after the company, which has agreed to be acquired by the H. J. Heinz Company, disclosed that it had rejected an unsolicited takeover bid earlier this year. Analysts said Del Monte shareholders were heartened by news of the cash offer of up to $11 a share, which was received before the Heinz deal was struck. The offer was rejected in April, Del Monte said on Tuesday in a regulatory filing. ''It doesn't sound like that deal is at all doable anymore,'' said a Banc of America Securities analyst, William Leach. Heinz said early yesterday that its offer was on track. The deal, announced in June, is now valued at $1.37 billion, down from $1.83 billion, as Del Monte's shares have weakened. Shares of Del Monte rose $1.13, to $9.04, yesterday. Heinz rose 25 cents, to $34.68.Correction: November 22, 2002, Friday A report in the Company News column of Business Day yesterday about the disclosure of a takeover offer made earlier this year for the Del Monte Foods Company, which rejected it, referred incorrectly to a transaction with the H. J. Heinz Company. Del Monte is merging into a new company controlled by Heinz shareholders; it is not being acquired by Heinz.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/11/business/heinz-says-its-quarterly-profit-fell-11.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Says Its Quarterly Profit Fell 11%<date>Published: September 11, 2002</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its quarterly profit fell 11 percent because of higher marketing costs and expenses related to the spinoff of its tuna and pet-food businesses.Net income declined to $177.8 million, or 50 cents a share, from $200.5 million, or 57 cents, in the year-earlier period. Sales in the period, which ended June 31 and was the first quarter of Heinz's fiscal year, rose 6.1 percent, to $2.2 billion, the company said.Heinz spent $25 million more on marketing in the quarter, a jump of 45 percent, to promote products like Ore-Ida Funky Fries and Heinz Easy Squeeze upside-down ketchup. The chief executive, William Johnson, is jettisoning slower-growing businesses by turning them over to shareholders and to the Del Monte Food Company in a transaction valued at about $2.9 billion.Sales of StarKist seafood and products like 9-Lives pet food dropped 10 percent.Excluding certain costs, Heinz said, it would have earned 54 cents a share. The company, which also makes baby food and Smart Ones frozen entrees, was expected to have a profit of 53 cents a share, the average estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/06/business/company-briefs-271284.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: August 06, 2002</date><text>CENTENE CORP., St. Louis, a managed care provider, agreed to buy 80 percent of University Health Plans, Newark, a health care provider, in a cash transaction that would add about 50,000 Medicaid members. Terms were not disclosed.UNITED NATURAL FOODS INC., Dayville, Conn., the nation's largest distributor of natural foods, said it had agreed to acquire the Blooming Prairie Cooperative, Iowa City, a distributor of natural foods. Terms were not disclosed.ENERGIZER HOLDINGS INC., St. Louis, a maker of batteries, said it would pay $25.50 to $29 a share to buy back as many as six million common shares.H. J. HEINZ, Pittsburgh, reiterated its plan to trim its dividend 33 percent to help pay down debt and also said it planned to invest more than $100 million in incremental marketing spending.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/07/business/c-corrections-883026.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Corrections<date>Published: July 07, 2002</date><text>An article last Sunday about investing in H. J. Heinz stock misstated the amount of debt that the company has said it will repay by 2005; it is $1 billion, not $100 million.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/30/business/investing-can-a-leaner-heinz-fatten-profits.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Investing; Can a Leaner Heinz Fatten Profits?<date>Published: June 30, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedBY spinning off lagging brands, H. J. Heinz says it will build a revitalized, high-growth company on a foundation of ketchup and frozen foods.But investors are divided on whether Heinz, in its new incarnation, can increase earnings per share fast enough to justify a cut in the steady dividend yield that had been one of the stock's chief attractions.This month, Heinz announced plans to transfer several of its businesses, including StarKist Tuna, 9Lives cat food and Kibbles 'n Bits dog food, to Del Monte Foods. Del Monte would absorb the brands in a tax-free transaction worth $2.8 billion, making Heinz leaner.As a result, Heinz has said it expects that earnings per share, which declined 6.3 percent last year, will begin to grow 8 percent to 10 percent annually after 2003. Without the drag placed on earnings by businesses like the company's tuna brands, where expenses can swing wildly based on the price of raw fish, Heinz's profits will begin to rise, the company said.Heinz executives said that selling low performers will let the company concentrate on what made it most successful -- staples like ketchup, beans and frozen French fries. ''This is focusing on our core categories, which have grown strongly for us in the past,'' said Arthur Winkleblack, Heinz's chief financial officer. ''It is a much more efficient way for our shareholders to earn money on their investment.''But many analysts are withholding a verdict until Heinz can provide proof.''On paper it makes a lot of sense to get rid of a lot of the lagging business lines,'' said Patrick Schumann, a consumer product analyst at Edward Jones. ''But it all comes down to execution, and we just have not seen this company execute at a high-enough level in recent years, so we remain cautious on their ability to grow the company.''Christopher R. Growe, a food analyst at A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons, says the new Heinz has the potential for faster growth, but he continues to see the company as a ''perpetual restructurer.''''I need more confidence in sales and earnings,'' Mr. Growe said. ''It becomes to be a bit of a show-me story, truthfully.''Heinz's core product lines are mature, and new products like green and purple ketchup have not spurred sustained increases in profits.Correction: July 7, 2002, Sunday An article last Sunday about investing in H. J. Heinz stock misstated the amount of debt that the company has said it will repay by 2005; it is $1 billion, not $100 million.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/14/business/heinz-to-shed-some-brands-in-deal-with-del-monte.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz to Shed Some Brands in Deal With Del Monte<date>Published: June 14, 2002</date><text>The H. J. Heinz company said yesterday that it would spin off StarKist tuna, 9-Lives cat food and several other lagging brands to Del Monte Foods in a deal worth about $2.8 billion.Unlike the acquisitions that have transformed the food industry into a smattering of big players, this agreement will leave Heinz and Del Monte intact as two stand-alone companies.But a big part of Heinz's products in the United States, representing about $1.8 billion, or 20 percent, of its annual revenue, will be handed over to what both companies are calling the new Del Monte.Heinz has suffered from volatile swings in earnings, in part because of the weak performance of the brands it now plans to discard. The trimmed-down company expects its earnings per share to grow 8 percent to 10 percent annually after next year, a transformation that could make it a takeover target of its own.Under the deal, Heinz shareholders will virtually end up owning Del Monte. They will get 0.45 share of Del Monte stock for each of their Heinz shares, giving them 74.5 percent of the company. Del Monte will assume $1.1 billion in Heinz debt. By structuring the agreement in this way, the companies said, the transaction can be accomplished tax free.Del Monte's stock rose 90 cents, or 8.37 percent, to $11.65 yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, while shares of Heinz fell $2.05, or almost 5 percent, to $39.55.The deal brings together two companies that conspicuously sat out the consolidation craze that began coursing through the food industry two years ago. Yet, the deal also essentially sends them in opposite directions, as one grows and one shrinks.After posting roughly $1.5 billion in sales of canned fruits and vegetables last year, Del Monte will nearly double in size with the Heinz products. It says it needs such scale to haggle with ever-expanding retailers like Wal-Mart and to guard against encroachments by competitors.''We will be in every important grocery aisle, certainly every aisle that's important to us,'' said Richard G. Wolford, chairman and chief executive of Del Monte, which will remain based in San Francisco. Mr. Wolford will continue in his role, but the company's board will be reconfigured: Heinz will pick six directors; Del Monte will choose three.For Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, the exchange means slimming down, dropping the pet snacks, soups and baby food that it had long neglected in favor of the condiments and frozen dinners that drive much of the company's growth.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/02/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-spot-for-heinz-wins-grand-prize.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Spot for Heinz Wins Grand Prize<date>Published: May 02, 2002</date><text>A commercial by the London office of Leo Burnett Worldwide, for microwave soups sold by H. J. Heinz, won the grand prize last night at the 38th annual International Andy Awards ceremony, sponsored by the Advertising Club of New York.The award, known as the Grandy, comes with a $50,000 cash prize. The commercial gained attention in Britain for its provocative humor, which is rare in campaigns for prosaic packaged goods like soup; the spot, aimed at women, compares a husband's rushed lovemaking to the soup's selling point that it can be ''ready in two minutes.''The London and Paris offices of Burnett, part of the Bcom3 Group, won a total of three awards, second only to Wieden &amp; Kennedy in Portland, Ore., which won five, all for work it did for Nike.Another multiple winner, with two awards, was Bartle Bogle Hegarty, which is 49 percent owned by Bcom3. The London office won for work for Levi Strauss, and the New York office won for a public-service campaign to fight child hunger, which also won the Richard T. O'Reilly Award for public service ads. DDB Chicago and Tribal DDB Chicago, both part of the DDB Worldwide division of the Omnicom Group, each won an award for work for Anheuser-Busch; DDB Chicago won for radio commercials for Bud Light beer and Tribal DDB won for Web site work for Budweiser beer.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/15/business/heinz-s-earnings-drop-25-for-the-quarter.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz's Earnings Drop 25% for the Quarter<date>Published: March 15, 2002</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company reported today that the cost of putting new products on store shelves and into adverse foreign markets had led to a 25 percent decline in third-quarter earnings.Heinz, based here, reported earnings of $201.7 million, or 57 cents a share, compared with $270.5 million, or 77 cents a share, for the third quarter last year.Sales increased to $2.55 billion from $2.27 billion.The results for the quarter, which ended Jan. 30, met analysts' reduced expectations.Company executives revised their financial outlook for the quarter late last year, citing an economic slowdown in the wake of the Sept. 11 attacks and higher-than-expected foreign supply costs.William R. Johnson, Heinz's chief executive, said an emphasis on marketing new products and a simplified distribution system would allow the company to meet analysts' expectations for fiscal 2002.Leonard L. Teitelbaum, an analyst with Merrill Lynch, said that unfavorable foreign exchange rates would continue to be a hurdle for Heinz, an international company, in the foreseeable future.Heinz reported declines in its pet-products and seafood segments and its sales in Asia and the Pacific Rim.The company offset the sluggish foreign market somewhat with strong domestic sales of frozen foods.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/17/business/business-diary-when-french-fries-go-over-the-rainbow.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">BUSINESS: DIARY; When French Fries Go Over the Rainbow<date>Published: February 17, 2002</date><text>Perhaps the best way to create brand loyalty among customers is to start young. Few companies may understand that better than H. J. Heinz, which has a growing line of products geared toward young taste buds.Green or purple ketchup, anyone? The company, based in Pittsburgh, scored a hit with youngsters last year by producing its flagship product in different colors and packaging it in an easy-to-grip bottle.Its new offering is chocolate fries. Actually, chocolate is one of a few flavors of Funky Fries, a new line of Ore-Ida frozen potato products.Beginning in May, Heinz says it plans to sell Kool Blue, seasoned fries in sky blue; Sour Cream &amp; Jive, fries flavored with sour cream and chives; Cinna-Stiks, flavored with cinnamon and sugar; and Crunchy Rings, basically Tater Tots with a hole in the middle. The chocolate fries are called Cocoa Crispers.Leonard Teitelbaum, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, said he was optimistic about the new products. ''If you know your target market and can make the product fun and interesting, your chances of success at least initially are pretty good,'' he told The Associated Press last week.If the thought of blue fries covered in purple ketchup makes you cringe, consider that Heinz decided on its potato flavors after a year of testing 50 of them. A Fruit Loops flavor was among those rejected.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/14/business/heinz-reports-higher-earnings.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Reports Higher Earnings<date>Published: December 14, 2001</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Dec. 13— The H. J. Heinz Company announced today that quarterly earnings had risen 9.6 percent on strong sales of ketchup and frozen foods. Heinz said it had earned $208 million, or 59 cents a share, compared with $190 million, or 54 cents a share, in the comparable period a year ago. The results matched the estimates of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call. Sales in the period, which ended Oct. 31 and was the second quarter of Heinz's fiscal year, rose to $2.6 billion from $2.3 billion. Heinz, a food manufacturer based in Pittsburgh, revised its earnings downward last month because of expectations that fewer people would dine out, particularly at airports, hospitals and theme parks. The decline cost the company as much as 5 cents a share, said Leonard Teitelbaum, an analyst with Merrill Lynch. Since the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, restaurant meal purchases have fallen for the first time in a decade, Heinz said. ''A lot of restaurants traded away brand-name ketchup to private labels to lower costs quickly on or after Sept. 11,'' said John McMillin, an analyst with Prudential Securities. ''But I think they'll recover from it.'' Heinz warned that third-quarter results would be lower, but it said it expected profits to rebound in the fourth quarter. ''Heinz has a very strong brand focus with five megabrands driving almost 50 percent of global sales,'' said Heinz's chairman, William Johnson. Heinz acquired Classico pasta sauces, Delimex Mexican foods and Poppers and TGIF frozen snacks in the second quarter, and those moves helped sales, Mr. Johnson said. Tuna and pet food sales also increased, but profits were lower than last year.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/28/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-2-food-companies-hire-new-agencies.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; 2 Food Companies Hire New Agencies<date>Published: November 28, 2001</date><text>Two large marketers are expanding their agency rosters. The H. J. Heinz Company, based in Pittsburgh, named Campbell Mithun in Minneapolis to handle the account of the Classico line of pasta sauces, which Heinz recently acquired from the Borden Foods Corporation. Billings were estimated at more than $10 million. Campbell Mithun, which is part of the McCann-Erickson World Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies, has worked on Classico under the Borden ownership since 1998. Other Heinz roster agencies include Leo Burnett Worldwide in Chicago, part of the Bcom3 Group, and DDB Worldwide in San Francisco, part of the Omnicom Group. Also, Masterfoods USA, the new name of the United States operations of Mars Inc., named the Arnell Group in New York, part of Omnicom, to handle brand development strategy projects. Michelle Weese, a spokeswoman for Masterfoods in Hackettstown, N.J., confirmed a report of the assignment this week in Advertising Age. Spending was not disclosed. Arnell is working on Masterfoods brands like Twix candy and on new Masterfoods chocolate products. Arnell will work with the agencies that create campaigns for Masterfoods brands, including BBDO Worldwide, part of Omnicom; D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles, part of Bcom3; and Grey Worldwide, part of the Grey Global Group.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/10/business/company-news-shares-of-ketchup-maker-fall-on-earnings-outlook.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; SHARES OF KETCHUP MAKER FALL ON EARNINGS OUTLOOK<date>Published: November 10, 2001</date><text>Shares of the H. J. Heinz Company fell yesterday after the company, the biggest ketchup maker, said that its fiscal second-quarter earnings would miss forecasts and that its profit projections for the year would be lowered. Heinz said late Thursday that lower sales to restaurants and hotels and higher costs in Australia, New Zealand and Japan had reduced earnings in its second quarter, ended Oct. 31. Food service sales were $25 million to $30 million less than a year earlier because fewer people are eating out or traveling, Heinz said. Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, now expects second-quarter earnings of 59 cents to 60 cents a share, compared with an earlier forecast of 64 cents to 66 cents.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/12/business/heinz-posts-higher-income-but-warns-on-new-quarter.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Posts Higher Income But Warns on New Quarter<date>Published: September 12, 2001</date><text>PITTSBURGH, Sept. 11— The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its fiscal first-quarter net income rose 6.6 percent and that profit this quarter might be less than Wall Street expectations. Net income in the quarter, ended Aug. 1, rose to $200.5 million, or 57 cents a share, compared with $188 million, or 54 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales edged up to $2.19 billion from $2.17 billion. Excluding $13 million, or 4 cents a share, in restructuring charges that included closing a tuna plant in Puerto Rico, the company said it earned 61 cents. On that basis, Heinz matched the expectations of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/ First Call. William R. Johnson, the chairman and chief executive, said, ''New product successes, such as Heinz EZ Squirt condiments and StarKist pouch tuna, and strong sales for some of our big brands, contributed to our first-quarter performance.'' An increase in sales of frozen food in the United States helped Heinz overcome a 10 percent drop in pet food revenue, the company said. Pet food sales have declined in recent quarters because Heinz sells more wet, canned varieties than dry food, where sales are growing faster. The food-service business suffered as consumers dined out less often. And the weak euro reduced the value of Western European sales, also affecting first-quarter profit, A spokesman, John Runkel, said in a conference call that ''some of the elements that plagued us in the fourth quarter and moved into the first quarter are taking a little bit longer to unwind.'' This quarter, the company said, profit will be 3 cents to 5 cents higher than the first quarter's 61 cents, excluding special items. That is still less than the First Call analysts' average estimate of 69 cents. Heinz said its financial results should improve in the second half as foreign currencies stabilize and new products, including 9 Lives Gourmet, are introduced. It will also raise prices on about 90 percent of its products this year, the chief financial officer, Paul F. Renne, said. A senior vice president, Ted Smyth, said that Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, was ''on track'' to meet its earlier forecast for the fiscal year of $2.70 to $2.80 a share. Analysts were expecting $2.69 a share. In addition to an increase in the sales of frozen food, tuna sales rose 2 percent. Heinz's share of the United States tuna market has fallen in the last year because the company did not lower prices as competitors did. Separately, Heinz postponed its annual shareholder meeting, scheduled for today, because of the attacks on the World Trade Center, the Pentagon and airliners in flight. One of those, a United Airlines Boeing 757 with 45 on board, crashed southeast of Pittsburgh. Photo: William R. Johnson, Heinz's chairman, credited successful new products like the EZ Squirt line of condiments and StarKist pouch tuna, as well as strong sales of some established brands, for an improvement in the company's recent earnings. (Terry Clark for The New York Times)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/03/business/company-news-heinz-acquires-maker-of-mexican-convenience-foods.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ ACQUIRES MAKER OF MEXICAN CONVENIENCE FOODS<date>Published: August 03, 2001</date><text>H. J. Heinz said yesterday that it had bought Delimex, a maker of frozen tamales, quesadillas and other Mexican convenience foods, from Fenway Partners, the private investment firm. Terms were not disclosed. Delimex, based in San Diego, has sales of more than $150 million a year, Heinz said. The acquisition expands the number of items Heinz offers that people can heat and serve. Delimex frozen Mexican food products are sold in stores like Wal-Mart Stores, Albertson's and Safeway.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/01/business/company-news-latest-color-for-ketchup-from-heinz-is-purple.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; LATEST COLOR FOR KETCHUP FROM HEINZ IS PURPLE<date>Published: August 01, 2001</date><text>Hoping to build on last year's success with a ''Blastin' Green'' ketchup, the H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it would begin selling purple ketchup in September. In seven months, Heinz sold more than 10 million bottles of green ketchup, pushing total sales up 5.4 percent and helping the company increase its share of the United States ketchup market to 59 percent from 55 percent, a spokesman, Michael Mullen, said. Heinz said the purple ketchup would taste the same as red ketchup.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/26/business/media-business-advertising-heinz-putting-its-money-where-young-mouths-are.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING; Heinz is putting its money where the young mouths are to promote a line of frozen snacks.<date>Published: July 26, 2001</date><text>HEINZ is stepping up efforts to promote products to the intended eaters rather than to the intended buyers as the company begins an ambitious marketing campaign for a line of frozen snacks centered on Tony Hawk, the popular professional skateboarder.The campaign from the Heinz Frozen Food Company division of H. J. Heinz introduces Hot Bites, a line of frozen miniature pizza and potato snacks. The products are being aimed at so-called tweens, boys and girls ages 9 to 14, who will either buy them or nag -- er, encourage -- their parents to buy them. Elements of the campaign, by the San Francisco office of DDB Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, include television commercials and ''behind the scenes'' film from the spots being put up on a Web site.Hot Bites is the most recent Heinz brand to be aimed directly at younger consumers. Last year, marketing for the Bagel Bites line of frozen snacks, on which Hot Bites is based, was restaged to talk directly to the youngsters, and the result was a 21 percent increase in sales. The venerable Heinz ketchup brand has also been reinvigorated by campaigns aimed at teenagers along with product variations aimed at their younger siblings like green ketchup in squeezable bottles.Other marketers joining in the trend include Kellogg, for its Pop Tarts line of pastry; Procter &amp; Gamble, for Sunny Delight juice drinks; and the Frito-Lay division of PepsiCo, for various snack chips like Cheetos and Doritos.''In the world of 'tween'-consumed products, the marketing decision always is, 'Do you want to push it or do you want to pull it?' '' said Mary Moudry, chief operating officer at DDB San Francisco.''Pushing it through mom gets it into the pantry,'' she added, ''but if you want to create the pull demand on the end consumer, you've got to talk to the end consumer.''That is why Mr. Hawk, 33, was signed as the Bagel Bites spokesman last year and why he reappears in the Hot Bites campaign. The Hot Bites budget is estimated at $6 million.''Increasingly kids are saying 'I want something when I come home from school; I'm ravenous,' '' said John Carroll, managing director for North American potatoes and snacks at Heinz Frozen Food in Pittsburgh.''What we've actually seen is that there's evolved almost a fourth meal occasion -- there's breakfast, there's lunch and then there's this long spell between lunch and dinner,'' he added. ''Kids actually drive that. Mom plans it, and mom's looking for input.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/16/sports/plus-pro-football-heinz-and-steelers-agree-to-name-park.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">PLUS: PRO FOOTBALL; Heinz and Steelers Agree to Name Park<date>Published: June 16, 2001</date><text>H.J. Heinz Co., the company famous for its 57 varieties slogan, agreed to pay the Pittsburgh Steelers $57 million over 20 years to get its name on the team's new stadium.The condiment company and the Steelers announced the name of Heinz Field yesterday. A huge plastic ketchup bottle towered next to the new stadium, which opens this fall, and a Heinz banner was hanging from a scoreboard.The deal amounts to about $2.85 million a year for the Steelers, with the Pittsburgh company receiving exclusive rights to sell its products at the $281 million stadium. The deal makes the Steelers' new home the only stadium named for a food company. The deal should help the Steelers pay some of the $123 million they are contributing to the $281 million stadium.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/15/business/heinz-posts-4th-quarter-loss-saying-energy-costs-had-role.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Posts 4th-Quarter Loss, Saying Energy Costs Had Role<date>Published: June 15, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company posted a $170.5 million loss today for its fiscal fourth quarter, citing low tuna prices, higher energy costs and one-time items related to a revamping and asset sales and acquisitions.But its earnings excluding special items matched reduced expectations on Wall Street. The company had reduced its earnings outlook in March.Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, said it expected its first-quarter earnings to be 60 to 62 cents a share, slightly lower than the 65 cents expected by analysts, according to Thomson Financial/First Call.The company's loss for the quarter ended May 2 amounted to 49 cents a share, in contrast to a profit of $97.3 million, or 27 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $2.69 billion from $2.59 billion.Excluding special items, Heinz earned $185.7 million, or 53 cents a share, compared with $226.4 million, or 63 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.In the most recent quarter, Heinz took charges totaling $355.8 million, or $1.02 a share, for closing a Puerto Rican tuna plant and a loss on the sale of Budget Gourmet.Heinz's chairman, president and chief executive, William R. Johnson, said sales were up almost 6 percent in its ketchup, condiments and sauces business and 9 percent in frozen foods. But he said performance fell short in its tuna and European infant feeding businesses.He said steps had been taken to improve production efficiency and reduce costs, particularly in pet food and tuna.Among Heinz brands are Heinz ketchup, StarKist tuna, Bagel Bites, Ore-Ida frozen potatoes and 9-Lives pet food.Shares of Heinz fell 14 cents, to $42.49.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/07/business/company-news-heinz-is-buying-some-brands-from-borden-foods.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ IS BUYING SOME BRANDS FROM BORDEN FOODS<date>Published: June 07, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it would buy the pasta sauce, dry bouillon and soup businesses of the Borden Foods Corporation. Terms were not disclosed. The businesses' annual sales in the United States and Canada total more than $270 million. The brands involved include Classico pasta sauce, Aunt Millie's pasta sauce and Wyler's bouillons and soups. The products are made at plants in Pennsauken, N.J., and Northbrook, Ill. Borden officials said the 350 employees who work at the plants would be offered jobs with Heinz.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/09/business/heinz-to-offer-new-snack.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz to Offer New Snack<date>Published: May 09, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Frozen Food Company, an affiliate of the H. J. Heinz Company, said today that it would introduce bite-size pizza and potato snacks called Hot Bites as part of a plan to attract more pre-teen and teenage customers. Five varieties of Hot Bites, an extension of Heinz's Bagel Bites, will start selling in supermarkets this month, Heinz Frozen Food said. Heinz, which is the largest ketchup maker, will advertise Hot Bites with a television commercial starring Tony Hawk, a skateboarder.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/28/business/merger-blocked-for-makers-of-baby-food.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Merger Blocked For Makers Of Baby Food<date>Published: April 28, 2001</date><text>A federal appeals panel blocked the proposed acquisition of one large maker of baby food by another today in a challenge filed by the Federal Trade Commission during the Clinton administration.The challenge is based on a legal theory that has been criticized by President Bush's nominee to head the agency.Soon after the panel announced its decision to issue an injunction against the deal, which reversed a lower court order approving it, H. J. Heinz announced it would abandon its plans to buy the Milnot Holding Corporation, maker of Beech-Nut, for $185 million. While not among the larger corporate acquisitions under scrutiny by the government, the case illustrates the stark differences between the antitrust approaches of Clinton and Bush appointees.Robert Pitofsky, the departing chairman of the F.T.C., said the decision was one of the most important antitrust cases during his six years leading the agency.He said that had the decision gone the other way it would have encouraged other deals in highly concentrated industries.The Bush nominee to lead the F.T.C., Timothy J. Muris, a law professor at George Mason University, worked on behalf of the two companies. He has been critical of the government for failing to consider the economic benefits of such mergers, and he is expected to be confirmed soon as the next chairman of the Federal Trade Commission.In a speech late last year, Mr. Muris said that the case had presented the most powerful efficiencies he had ever seen, according to lawyers in the audience. He has told friends that several grounds even more compelling than the efficiency argument formed his conclusion that he would not have challenged the deal had he been at the F.T.C.Mr. Muris has said that Gerber Products, the largest player in the industry, objected to the deal, suggesting that it would increase and not decrease competition. But retailers also supported it.The proposed deal had been attacked on the ground that it would have reduced the industry to two dominant players from three. Heinz and Milnot together control nearly 33 percent of the retail baby food market; Gerber controls 65 percent.Heinz and Milnot defended the deal on the ground that the economic efficiencies created by the merger would benefit consumers far more than they would be harmed by any potential anticompetitive effects.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/16/business/company-news-heinz-says-it-plans-to-eliminate-1900-jobs.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ SAYS IT PLANS TO ELIMINATE 1,900 JOBS<date>Published: March 16, 2001</date><text>H. J. Heinz plans to eliminate 1,900 jobs, or about 4 percent of its global work force, with most of the cuts coming in its struggling tuna and pet food operations. Heinz's chief executive, William R. Johnson, said the job cuts were aimed at streamlining the tuna and pet food businesses and reducing overhead costs worldwide. A tuna processing plant in MayagÃ¼ez, P.R., will be closed, eliminating 1,300 jobs by the end of April, and 325 jobs will be lost with the closing of a pet food canning operation at Terminal Island, Calif. Heinz also said it earned $270.5 million, or 77 cents a share, in its third quarter, up from $171.1 million, or 47 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/08/business/company-news-heinz-is-buying-two-companies-in-costa-rica.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ IS BUYING TWO COMPANIES IN COSTA RICA<date>Published: March 08, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it had acquired the Banquete brand of ketchup as part of the purchase of two food companies in Costa Rica. Heinz, which makes the leading brand of ketchup in the United States, said it purchased Productos Columbia and Distribuidora Banquete, both of San JosÃ©, Costa Rica. Terms of the deal were not disclosed. Heinz said the Banquete brand made by the two companies has 16 percent of the ketchup market in Central America. ''Costa Rica enjoys Central America's most vibrant economy, and ketchups and sauces are an essential part of the local cuisine,'' Heinz's chairman, William R. Johnson, said. The companies also make Columbia, TÃ­pica, Salsitica and Emily Gyor sauces and condiments and have about $12 million in annual sales. Heinz has about $9 billion in sales.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/06/business/heinz-expects-lower-profits.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Expects Lower Profits<date>Published: March 06, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company warned yesterday that earnings for its third and fourth quarters and its 2001 and 2002 fiscal years would fall below Wall Street expectations, citing weakness in processed tuna prices and rising natural gas prices.Heinz, whose brands include its namesake ketchup, StarKist tuna and Ore-Ida French fries, said it expected earnings of 65 cents a share for the third quarter, which ended Jan. 31, excluding one-time items. Analysts were expecting the company to earn 70 cents a share, according to First Call/ Thomson Financial.The company, based in Pittsburgh, said it expected fourth-quarter earnings of 52 to 54 cents a share, well below Wall Street estimates of 69 cents a share.Heinz cut its outlook for core earnings to $2.54 to $2.56 a share for the 2001 fiscal year, which ends May 2, below analysts' estimates of $2.76 a share. Heinz earned $2.57 a share for its 2000 fiscal year.The company expects its third-quarter sales to rise about 4 percent on a constant currency basis and fall about 1 percent on a reported basis. It expects full-year sales to rise about 3 percent on a constant currency basis and decline about 1 percent on a reported basis. Heinz noted that fiscal 2001 is one week shorter than fiscal 2000.The company also said it expected to earn $2.70 to $2.80 a share in its 2002 fiscal year, while analysts expected the company to earn $3 a share for that period.Heinz will issue its third-quarter results on March 15.Shares of Heinz rose 5 cents, to $43.09.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/11/nyregion/briefing-science-prize-winner.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">BRIEFING: SCIENCE; PRIZE WINNER<date>Published: February 11, 2001</date><text>James E. Hansen, a NASA scientist credited with alerting the public to global warming, has been named a winner of of the Heinz Award, which honors people who enhance the lives of others. Mr. Hansen, 59, lives in Ridgewood and is director of the NASA's Goddard Institute of Space Studies in Manhattan. He gave the first warnings about how industrial pollution is changing the climate in testimony before a Congressional panel in 1988. The $250,000 award will be presented in Washington March 5. George James</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/10/business/company-news-heinz-sells-budget-gourmet-frozen-lines-to-luigino-s.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ SELLS BUDGET GOURMET FROZEN LINES TO LUIGINO'S<date>Published: February 10, 2001</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it had sold the All American Gourmet Company frozen-food business to the closely held Luigino's Inc. for undisclosed terms. The transaction will cut 2 cents a share from earnings for the year ending in April and 4 cents from next year because of lost sales, Heinz said. It will take a one-time charge this year of about $65 million. All American Gourmet makes the Budget Gourmet and Budget Gourmet Value Classics low-priced frozen entrees. Luigino's makes frozen entrees and snacks under the Michelina's brand.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/04/nyregion/briefing-business-vlasic-bankruptcy.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">BRIEFING: BUSINESS; VLASIC BANKRUPTCY<date>Published: February 04, 2001</date><text>Vlasic International, based in Cherry Hill, declared bankruptcy last week and said it planned to sell its pickle and barbecue sauce lines to Heinz for $195 million. Vlasic is the largest pickle-maker in the United States, with 24 percent of the market, but has had financial difficulties since being spun off from the Campbell Soup Company, based in Camden, in 1998. Vlasic also makes Open Pit barbecue sauce and Swanson frozen dinners, which is not part of the proposed sale. Mr. Lowery said the company was still exploring either selling the Swanson line or making a cash-for-equity swap with creditors for Vlasic to continue making the dinners. Robert Strauss</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/30/nyregion/metro-business-briefing-pickle-maker-is-bankrupt.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Metro Business Briefing; PICKLE MAKER IS BANKRUPT<date>Published: January 30, 2001</date><text>Vlasic Foods International, the pickle marketer based in Cherry Hill, N.J., that also owns Swanson frozen dinners and Open Pit barbecue sauce, sought bankruptcy protection yesterday and reached a deal to sell its pickle and barbecue sauce businesses to the H. J. Heinz Company of Pittsburgh. The sale is subject to approval by a federal bankruptcy court, which could consider any other offers that might be made. Heinz bid $195 million.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/28/business/private-sector-a-quest-for-irish-business-glory.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">PRIVATE SECTOR; A Quest for Irish Business Glory<date>Published: January 28, 2001</date><text>MARCHING toward middle age, his athletic career mostly behind him, a rugby-player-turned-entrepreneur named Anthony O'Reilly received the business offer of a lifetime in 1969. Come help run our company, urged the chief executive of H. J. Heinz, a corporation with more international influence than any for which he was likely to work in his Irish homeland. But Mr. O'Reilly was hesitant.''I don't want to go to America,'' he told Bert Gookin, Heinz's chief executive at the time.Still, he was eager to prove himself on the ''high altar'' of business, as he calls it, much as he had on rugby fields around the world as a star of the Irish national team. So he overcame his reluctance and agreed. But first, he struck an unusual deal with Mr. Gookin, and it governed the rest of his 30 years abroad.''Yes, I'll go, I'll work my butt off, but I'll always have interests in Ireland,'' said Sir Anthony O'Reilly, who was knighted by Queen Elizabeth II of Britain this month for promoting peace in Northern Ireland, recalling the agreement with Heinz. ''They allowed me this double life.''That double life is no more. Since stepping down as chairman of Heinz last September after 20 years as chief executive and, later, as chairman, Sir Anthony, now 64, has begun pouring his intellectual and capital resources into an unbridled effort to push his country to the front of the world business stage. Hunting for acquisitions that will expand the reach of his Irish enterprises, the broad-shouldered Sir Anthony has come full circle, almost as if he were back on the field, rallying the Irish team in its quest for international acclaim.''His heart was always in Ireland,'' said Ted Smyth, a Heinz spokesman who has known him for more than 30 years.Independent News and Media, Sir Anthony's Dublin-based network of 160 papers, has completed its takeover of the Belfast Telegraph, the largest newspaper in Northern Ireland. Now he has begun eyeing John Fairfax Holdings, one of the leading publishers in Australia, despite Australian laws restricting foreign ownership of domestic media.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/06/business/heinz-says-2nd-quarter-earnings-beat-estimates.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Says 2nd-Quarter Earnings Beat Estimates<date>Published: December 06, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its second-quarter earnings increased 5.8 percent because of rising sales of new products intended to be more convenient or to appeal to children.Profit from operations rose to $241.7 million, or 69 cents a share, compared with $228.4 million, or 63 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Sales in the quarter ended Nov. 1 fell 2 percent, to $2.3 billion from $2.34 billion. Excluding the Weight Watchers dieting business, sold in September 1999, sales rose 1.4 percent, the company said.Analysts had expected Heinz to earn 68 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.Heinz introduced products with wider profit margins, like green ketchup and StarKist tuna sold in pouches. The products helped Heinz's North American grocery profit rise 5.8 percent in the quarter.Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, also benefited from a cost-cutting program started in February 1999, when the company announced that it would cut thousands of jobs and close plants, mainly in Europe.Savings from that program are being used to introduce and market new products. The moves, expected to be completed this fiscal year, helped Heinz expand its operating profit margin to 20 percent from 18.5 percent in the quarter.Paul Renne, the chief financial officer, said at an investor conference in New York that Heinz expected to report profit this year of $2.79 a share. The forecast has come down from $2.83 in September.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/09/business/company-news-court-blocks-heinz-purchase-of-beech-nut.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; COURT BLOCKS HEINZ PURCHASE OF BEECH-NUT<date>Published: November 09, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company was barred by a federal appeals court from buying the owner of a rival maker of baby food, Beech-Nut, while antitrust authorities press their case to stop the merger. The decision could kill the transaction. Heinz and Beech-Nut together would have roughly 30 percent of the United States baby food market; Gerber Products, a unit of Novartis A.G., has nearly all the rest. The merger agreement between Heinz and the Milnot Holdings Company, the privately held owner of Beech-Nut, expires at the end of the month.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/08/business/can-healthier-foods-help-the-bottom-line-companies-find-gains-in-your-loss.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Can Healthier Foods Help the Bottom Line?; Companies Find Gains in Your Loss<date>Published: November 08, 2000</date><text>Andy and Rachel Berliner founded Amy's Kitchen, named for their newborn daughter, in 1988. Shocked by how much work caring for a baby could be, they decided there must be other people like them craving quick, convenient meals made from natural ingredients.They came up with products like frozen vegetable pot pie -- comfort food, Mr. Berliner calls it -- and pizza, as well as lasagna and shepherd's pie. Since then, despite minimal advertising and no marketing support, their company, based in Santa Rosa, Calif., has grown to $90 million in annual sales, much of that in high-quality grocery stores like the Florida-based Publix chain and D'Agostino in New York.Amy's Kitchen is dwarfed by big food companies like Kraft, a unit of Philip Morris, and ConAgra, with their billions of dollars in annual sales. Still, some of the largest food makers seem to believe that the formula Amy's Kitchen has adopted -- creating foods that are both healthy and convenient -- is a winner. ''The intersection of health and convenience is a very strong area of future growth for the entire food industry,'' said David Owens, senior vice president for strategy at Kraft North America.But while several big food companies are starting to offer more healthy convenience foods, change is coming slowly. A stroll through the typical supermarket today turns up relatively few packaged products that meet both criteria.Apart from the produce aisle, where items like prewashed lettuce and cut-up canteloupe are both healthy and convenient, traditional food makers have long made convenience the pivotal priority, judging by the fat, salt and sugar content spelled out on the food packages themselves, from canned soup to TV dinners, gravy mix, cold cereal and child-friendly yogurt. A package of Oscar Mayer Lean Turkey Breast Lunchables contains 360 calories, 9 grams of saturated fat -- 45 percent of the recommended daily amount -- and 1,470 milligrams of sodium.Shoppers say they are eager for a bigger choice in health-oriented convenience foods. Eleni Malatou, a full-time student and mother of a 16-month-old, buys ready-made pizza dough to make her own pizzas. ''It's not the best, I know, but it's convenient,'' she said, pushing her grocery cart through a Midtown Manhattan Food Emporium earlier this month. ''They could improve the ingredients, like the flour they use or the yeast they use, and I would feel better.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/business/responsible-party-casey-keller-so-far-it-s-easy-being-green.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">RESPONSIBLE PARTY: CASEY KELLER; So Far, It's Easy Being Green<date>Published: October 22, 2000</date><text>GREEN ketchup, announced with great fanfare months ago, is starting to arrive in stores. But it's not gathering dust. Store owners and their customers can't get it fast enough, said Casey Keller, managing director at H. J. Heinz for ketchup, condiments and sauces.''People have offered me $10 for a bottle,'' he said. ''Now I know what it must be like in the toy industry when they have a hit on their hands.'' Heinz now projects that a year's worth of the new ketchup will probably be sold in the first 90 days.The suggested retail price is $1.79 for 24 ounces.In development for nearly a year -- Mr. Keller would not reveal that cost -- the green ketchup comes in a new, softer, child-friendly bottle inspired by research among children 3 to 12.''Kids told us they had a hard time using the regular bottle,'' Mr. Keller said. ''They also suggested having ketchup in a different color. That threw us for a loop.''Green was the color they wanted. The new squeeze bottle will let them draw or write on their food, to decorate each French fry and make patterns on their burgers. Red ketchup is also being sold in the new bottle. ''It's the first step in making ketchup fun,'' said Mr. Keller, who did not rule out other colors in the future.The green ketchup tastes exactly like the red. The difference is the addition of food coloring -- blue No. 1 aluminum lake and yellow No. 5. Mr. Keller said Heinz had received no negative reactions from parents about the coloring.The new ketchup in the new bottles has also been bolstered with vitamin C. So with a green color and added nutrient value, does ketchup qualify as a vegetable after all, as the Agriculture Department once proposed during the Reagan administration? Probably not. When was the last time vegetables were fun? FLORENCE FABRICANT</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/business/company-news-judge-tells-heinz-to-put-off-beech-nut-acquisition.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; JUDGE TELLS HEINZ TO PUT OFF BEECH-NUT ACQUISITION<date>Published: October 20, 2000</date><text>A judge ordered the H. J. Heinz Company yesterday to hold off completing its $185 million buyout of a rival baby-food maker, Beech-Nut, while antitrust enforcers appeal the court's refusal to block the transaction. Under the order issued by Judge James Robertson of United States District Court in Washington, Heinz cannot complete its acquisition of the closely held Milnot Holdings Company, owner of Beech-Nut, while the Federal Trade Commission seeks an emergency injunction from an appeals court to block the merger. The judge gave the F.T.C. until Monday to seek an injunction.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/business/company-news-heinz-creates-new-division-to-offer-specialty-pet-food.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ CREATES NEW DIVISION TO OFFER SPECIALTY PET FOOD<date>Published: September 20, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said yesterday that it had created Heinz Specialty Pet Food, a new unit that will focus on selling Nature's Recipe, Techni-Cal and other specialty brands to veterinarians and pet stores. The new business will be separated from Heinz's grocery and mass merchandising pet food unit, which the company said should help increase sales and profit of its specialty pet food. Specialty pet food has generated about $150 million in sales for Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh. The market for specialty food has been rising 11 percent a year, while at grocery stores it has increased only 3 percent.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/business/heinz-shares-fall-on-profit-warning.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Shares Fall On Profit Warning<date>Published: September 07, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its second-quarter profit would be lower than analysts expected, and its shares fell nearly 5 percent.Profit in the quarter ending Nov. 1 will be about even with the 68 cents a share Heinz earned in its first quarter, Paul Renne, the company's chief financial officer, said in a conference call. Analysts had expected Heinz to earn 70 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.A 17 percent drop in the value of the euro compared with the dollar over the last year hurt Heinz, which derives a quarter of its sales from Europe. Costs to introduce StarKist tuna in a pouch also will cut profit. Heinz said it expected cost cutting in the second half to help it meet annual estimates. Shares of Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, fell $1.75, to $35.44.Heinz's second-quarter profit forecast excludes results from the Weight Watchers dieting-class business, sold in September 1999. Including the unit, Heinz earned 65 cents a share in the quarter a year earlier.Heinz expects profit for the year to rise 10 percent above last year's $2.57 a share, in line with analysts' forecasts.For its first quarter, ended Aug. 2, Heinz said today that its profit rose to $237.7 million, or 68 cents a share, compared with $223.8 million, or 61 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Sales fell 1.3 percent, to $2.15 billion from $2.18 billion. Excluding Weight Watchers, they rose 3.3 percent.Analysts had expected the company to earn 67 cents a share, according to First Call.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/19/business/company-news-food-services-unit-of-h-j-heinz-to-buy-a-distributor.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; FOOD SERVICES UNIT OF H. J. HEINZ TO BUY A DISTRIBUTOR<date>Published: July 19, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company, the maker of Heinz ketchup, Weight Watcher foods and Star-Kist tuna, said yesterday that its food-service unit had agreed to buy the privately held IDF Holdings Inc., the parent of food distributor International DiverseFoods Inc. The price was not disclosed. International DiverseFoods, based in Nashville, has more than $100 million in annual sales. It distributes sauces, condiments and pancake mix to restaurants, food distributors and food processors. Heinz, which is based in Pittsburgh, said it wanted to expand its business of providing food to places outside of homes.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/10/business/heinz-to-sell-a-green-ketchup.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz to Sell a Green Ketchup<date>Published: July 10, 2000</date><text>In a move to raise sales of its ketchup, H.J. Heinz plans to introduce a new version today that will be bright green and is intended to appeal to children.Numerous focus-group sessions with about 1,000 children led company executives to conclude that ketchup in a new color would encourage its more liberal use on food. In addition to the green ketchup, Heinz has also come up with a curvaceous bottle in plastic it says is softer and easier for children to squeeze. The nozzle emits a fine stream, compared with previous containers, enabling children to write their names on their food or play Jackson Pollock -- parents permitting.''It's empowered them in a way that they have always desired but haven't had an opportunity, until now,'' said Deb Magness, a Heinz spokeswoman. ''It's a ketchup they can call their own.''The ketchup, called EZ Squirt, is fortified with Vitamin C and will start appearing in stores in October, she said. Despite the color, the vitamins and the packaging, ''there is no taste difference,'' she added.With sales of packaged food showing little growth the last several years, companies are trying all sorts of strategies to help their businesses to grow. While new products can increase sales, at least in the short run, many analysts believe Heinz is likely to acquire another company so that it can become larger and more diversified. In addition to ketchup, Heinz also makes pet food, tuna fish, pickles, private-label soup and other products.A wave of consolidation the last three months has linked Bestfoods with Unilever and Nabisco with Philip Morris, increasing the pressure on smaller companies like Heinz to eventually combine forces with others so that they can be forceful players in the global supermarket business.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/08/business/company-news-us-challenges-heinz-bid-for-beech-nut.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. CHALLENGES HEINZ BID FOR BEECH-NUT<date>Published: July 08, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company's proposed $185 million purchase of the closely held Milnot Holdings Company, maker of Beech-Nut baby foods, was challenged yesterday by antitrust enforcers who said the transaction would hurt competition. The Federal Trade Commission voted 3 to 2 to challenge in court the combination of Heinz with the Beech-Nut Nutrition Corporation, the No. 2 United States baby food producer. The F.T.C. said the combination would mean just two companies, Heinz and the Gerber Products Company, a unit of Novartis, would control 98 percent of the United States market for prepared baby foods. Heinz closed yesterday on the Big Board up 31.25 cents, to $45.50.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/20/business/company-news-heinz-is-selling-us-can-making-operations.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">COMPANY NEWS; HEINZ IS SELLING U.S. CAN-MAKING OPERATIONS<date>Published: June 20, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company agreed to sell its can-making operations in the United States, American Samoa and Puerto Rico to the closely held Impress Metal Packaging Holdingsfor an undisclosed price. Impress, based in Amsterdam, will supply metal cans to Heinz's North American seafood and pet-products plants for 10 years. Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, makes a wide variety of food products. It has been closing plants to focus on new products.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/18/nyregion/c-corrections-824763.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Corrections<date>Published: June 18, 2000</date><text>A front-page article on June 4 about the quandary faced by American companies over genetically altered food included an industry analyst's imprecise reference to an ingredient in Heinz ketchup. A company spokesman said the product contained genetically modified corn syrup, not genetically modified tomatoes.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/16/business/heinz-profit-climbs-9.8-in-4th-quarter.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Profit Climbs 9.8% In 4th Quarter<date>Published: June 16, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company, maker of condiments, tuna fish and frozen goods, said today that its fiscal fourth-quarter profit rose 9.8 percent on lower manufacturing costs and increased sales.Profit from continuing operations in the quarter ended May 3 rose to $226.4 million, or 63 cents a share, from $206.1 million, or 56 cents, a year earlier. The year-earlier results were restated to exclude sales and profit from the Weight Watchers diet unit, sold in September. Sales rose 4.9 percent, to $2.59 billion.Heinz, based in Pittsburgh, was expected to earn 63 cents a share, the average estimate of analysts polled by First Call/Thomson Financial.William Johnson, the chief executive, has cut jobs and closed plants, using the savings to promote new products like frozen meals and side dishes under the Boston Market brand. Sales growth has been sluggish, so new products, including vacuum-sealed StarKist tuna packages introduced today, will be the key to a turnaround, analysts said.''Johnson has gone through a multistep process to get the company focused in the right direction,'' said Ebrahim Busheri, managing director at Manning &amp; Napier Advisors Inc., which owned 3.4 million Heinz shares as of March.Sales increased 13.5 percent, excluding sold businesses and the effect of foreign currencies, the company said. Ketchup, condiment and sauce sales rose 12 percent, to $669.1 million. Frozen food sales in North America rose 13 percent, helped by the new Boston Market products.In February 1999, Mr. Johnson said he would close as many as 20 plants and cut as many as 4,000 jobs to bolster profits. Over the last four years, similar moves have helped Heinz widen its operating margin -- how much the company earned after paying all the costs of doing business -- to 18.2 percent from 14.1 percent.Shares of Heinz rose 81.25 cents, to $40.4375.Heinz also said it would execute an option by Monday to buy enough shares in the Hain Celestial Group to restore its stake to 19.5 percent. The shares will be bought at a cost of $30.88 each, or about $80 million.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/16/business/business-diary-a-tempest-in-a-condiment-cap.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">BUSINESS: DIARY; A Tempest In a Condiment Cap<date>Published: April 16, 2000</date><text>H. J. Heinz and Del Monte Foods are trading barbs over a ketchup cap.Heinz, whose iconic ketchup has been the market leader seemingly forever, said early this month that it would introduce a cap for its plastic containers that is designed to capture the watery stuff that can hit your food after you start squeezing the bottle. (Water tends to collect atop pureed fruits and vegetables through a natural process called syneresis.)The new Heinz contraption has a reservoir and a small tube built inside a tall cap. When the bottle is turned upside down, syneresis fluid that may be present is trapped in the cap, while the thicker ketchup is sucked out through the tube.Nothing new about that, retorted Del Monte, the No. 3 ketchup marketer, behind Heinz and Hunt's. According to Maria Ruta, a spokeswoman, Del Monte introduced a patented syneresis cap with its plastic bottle six years ago, but did not promote it because its ketchup formulation does not create a significant syneresis problem.Heinz contends that its technology is a first and says it may seek a patent on its cap design.''Our point of view is, as category leader, we're upholding a rather long history of being first,'' said Deb Magness, a Heinz spokeswoman. ''We were first with the squeeze bottle and first with the recyclable bottle, and now we're first to solve the issue of the watery stuff.''But what of the Del Monte cap that Ms. Ruta said worked fine back in 1994?''We took a look at Del Monte's cap and found it ineffective against our standards,'' Ms. Magness said.Heinz plans to trumpet its syneresis cap in a big advertising and promotional campaign as the new ketchup bottles reach stores over the next 60 to 90 days.PATRICIA WINTERS LAURO</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/12/business/heinz-buys-sauce-brand.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Heinz Buys Sauce Brand<date>Published: April 12, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company has acquired the Yoshida's brand of Asian sauces in North America, including stir-fry, teriyaki and Hawaiian flavors. Terms of the deal were not disclosed, but Heinz said that sales for the brand exceed $20 million annually. Last year, Heinz acquired ABC Indonesia, the world's second-largest soy sauce company, and in March, it entered a joint agreement with Nutri Asia, the top producer of ketchup in the Philippines.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/10/business/third-quarter-profit-at-heinz-rose-by-3.5.html?ref=hjheinzcompany">Third-Quarter Profit at Heinz Rose by 3.5%<date>Published: March 10, 2000</date><text>The H. J. Heinz Company said today that its third-quarter profit rose 3.5 percent, the smallest gain in three and a half years, amid falling sales of baby foods, canned tuna and pet products.In the quarter that ended on Jan. 26, profit from operations at Heinz rose to $227.2 million, or 63 cents a diluted share, compared with $219.5 million, or 60 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales rose less than 1 percent, to $2.29 billion from $2.28 billion.Analysts had expected Heinz to earn 62 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks company earnings.Heinz took third-quarter pretax charges of $81.5 million, or 15 cents a share, to cover job cuts and plant closings. Those items made net income $171.1 million, or 47 cents a share.In the period a year earlier, the company had a reorganization charge and related costs of $141.7 million before taxes, or 27 cents a share, primarily for combining operations of its Ore-Ida Foods and Weight Watchers Gourmet Food units. That reduced net income to $120.6 million, or 33 cents a share.''The earnings gain isn't going to inspire anybody,'' said David Nelson, an analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston.William Johnson, Heinz's chief executive, has cut thousands of jobs and sold businesses like Weight Watchers classes and used the savings to increase marketing for ketchup and Ore-Ida potatoes. Competition, though, is cutting into sales of Star-Kist tuna, baby foods, and pet foods -- products that generate about a third of Heinz's sales.Earnings were also hurt because the year-earlier results include the Weight Watchers classes sold in September. Excluding that unit, operating profit rose 9.7 percent.Shares of Heinz rose 25 cents, to $34.50. The stock has fallen a third over the last 12 months.</text></article></page></root>
