<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Lowe's"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/16/business/lowes-posts-flat-income-in-quarter.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Posts Flat Income in Quarter<date>Published: August 15, 2011</date><text>The Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement retailer, posted flat quarterly income on Monday as volatile weather and consumers’ concerns about the economy muted demand during the company’s important summer selling season. Lowe’s lowered its sales forecast for the second half of its fiscal year as a result of consumers’ uncertainty, the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Mr. Niblock cited three factors likely to hurt spending: the debate in Washington this month over the debt ceiling, the subsequent downgrade by Standard &amp; Poor’s of the nation’s long-term credit rating and the recent stock market fluctuations. Shoppers continue to focus on repair and maintenance projects under $500, he added, rather than larger home renovation jobs. Lowe’s closed seven stores Sunday that it said were underperforming; the move eliminated 650 jobs. The company said it earned $830 million, or 64 cents a share. That compares with $832 million, or 58 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a charge related to the long-term value of the stores it closed, it earned 68 cents a share. Analysts expected adjusted earnings of 66 cents a share, according to FactSet. Revenue in the period, which ended July 29 and was the second quarter of the company’s fiscal year, rose 1 percent, to $14.54 billion. Analysts expected $14.77 billion. Mr. Niblock said in a statement that the performance fell short of the company’s expectations, despite some recovery in seasonal sales. Shares of Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., rose 17 cents, to $19.68 on Monday. The company said its revenue in stores open at least a year fell 0.3 percent. Lowe’s results were strongest in the North Central and Northeast regions of the country as customers made repairs after a winter of snow and ice storms. Results were weaker in the Gulf Coast, which has suffered heat and drought this summer.The Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement retailer, posted flat quarterly income on Monday as volatile weather and consumers’ concerns about the economy muted demand during the company’s important summer selling season. Lowe’s lowered its sales forecast for the second half of its fiscal year as a result of consumers’ uncertainty, the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Mr. Niblock cited three factors likely to hurt spending: the debate in Washington this month over the debt ceiling, the subsequent downgrade by Standard &amp; Poor’s of the nation’s long-term credit rating and the recent stock market fluctuations. Shoppers continue to focus on repair and maintenance projects under $500, he added, rather than larger home renovation jobs. Lowe’s closed seven stores Sunday that it said were underperforming; the move eliminated 650 jobs. The company said it earned $830 million, or 64 cents a share. That compares with $832 million, or 58 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a charge related to the long-term value of the stores it closed, it earned 68 cents a share. Analysts expected adjusted earnings of 66 cents a share, according to FactSet. Revenue in the period, which ended July 29 and was the second quarter of the company’s fiscal year, rose 1 percent, to $14.54 billion. Analysts expected $14.77 billion. Mr. Niblock said in a statement that the performance fell short of the company’s expectations, despite some recovery in seasonal sales. Shares of Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., rose 17 cents, to $19.68 on Monday. The company said its revenue in stores open at least a year fell 0.3 percent. Lowe’s results were strongest in the North Central and Northeast regions of the country as customers made repairs after a winter of snow and ice storms. Results were weaker in the Gulf Coast, which has suffered heat and drought this summer.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/17/business/17shop.html?ref=lowescompanies">Mixed Results From Two Major Retailers<date>Published: May 16, 2011</date><text>Two major retailers reported mixed quarterly results on Monday.Lowe’s, the home improvement chain, said its profit fell 6 percent, held down by economic conditions, while the department store chain J. C. Penney said its profit rose 6 percent, helped by cost cuts and a strong reception to its exclusive merchandise. Lowe’s said its results were also hurt by bad weather, and it cut its full-year forecast. The company’s results also fell short of Wall Street forecasts. Lowe’s reported net income of $461 million, or 34 cents a share, down from $489 million, or 34 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended April 29 and was the first quarter of Lowe’s fiscal year, dipped 2 percent to $12.19 billion, with revenue at stores open at least a year down 3.3 percent. Analysts surveyed by FactSet had expected earnings of 36 cents a share on revenue of $12.54 billion. Lowe’s cautioned in February that consumers were still holding back and its earnings were at the low end of its forecast of 34 to 38 cents a share for the quarter. The chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said in a statement that the company was also dealing with difficult comparison to a year ago, when federal rebates raised demand for appliances. For the full year, Lowe’s expects earnings of $1.56 to $1.64 a share and an approximately 4 percent revenue increase. The chain previously forecast earnings of $1.60 to $1.72 a share on a 5 percent revenue rise. Analysts predict full-year earnings of $1.70 a share on revenue of $50.9 billion. Stock in Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., fell 2.8 percent in early trading Monday. J. C. Penney said it earned $64 million, or 28 cents a share, up from $60 million, or 25 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended April 30 and was the first quarter of Penney’s fiscal year, edged up to $3.94 billion from $3.93 billion. Penney’s revenue at stores open at least a year rose 3.8 percent. Analysts predicted earnings of 26 cents on revenue of $3.94 billion, according to FactSet. “We are successfully implementing our merchandising initiatives, with strong gains in both our men’s and women’s apparel businesses,” the chief executive, Myron E. Ullman III, said in a statement. “Additionally, the steps we have taken to manage our expenses position us to increase the flow-through of sales to the bottom line.” Under pressure from shareholders, Penney has cut costs, including closing some stores, outlets and call centers. It is also finishing up closing its catalog business after announcing in November 2009 that it would stop publishing its twice-a-year “big book.” Mr. Ullman promised more cost-saving initiatives, including trimming marketing expenses and streamlining sourcing operations. The company expects to save about $25 million to $30 million by 2013, with about half of that in 2012. He expects the company to achieve an earnings target of $5 a share for 2014. Shares in Penney, which is based in Plano, Tex., fell 3.2 percent, to $37.21.Two major retailers reported mixed quarterly results on Monday.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/06/business/media/06adco.html?ref=lowescompanies">Big-Box Home Improvement Stores Offer Bar-Code Guides to Plants<date>Published: May 5, 2011</date><text>WHETHER it’s a piece of pipe or new kitchen cabinets, many Americans search for the right product in the aisles of home improvement stores like Home Depot or Lowe’s, trying to quickly identify what they need.The big-box stores are introducing some help to provide customers with immediate information for their buying decisions. They are adding bar codes to certain products that give potential buyers on-the-spot access to product reviews and ratings, how-to guides and videos. This will gradually expand across a greater range of products in the thousands of stores across the country as the huge home improvement retailers, which have been hit by the poor economy, seek to prompt consumers to undertake repairs or renovations they have been delaying. For now, garden plants sold at Home Depot and Lowe’s have bar codes on each plant tag that enable customers with smartphone scanners to check out whether the plant, for example, grows in low light or needs frequent watering. This is the season when stores sell millions of garden plants, which are an important segment of the business. At Lowe’s, for example, nursery sales, which also include trees and flowers, were 4 percent of the chain’s total $48.8 billion sales in the fiscal year ended Jan. 28.  Chris Gerhard, a home gardener and real estate broker in San Antonio, says mobile bar codes have greatly improved her gardening outcomes. “Those little plastic tags on plants always had minimal information,” she said of her purchases at her local Home Depot. “Now, with the bar codes, you can scan them and figure out immediately what is going to grow in the sun, when to plant and how far apart to place plants. “That’s great for me because in this climate you can fry things to a crisp, and I have. This helped me know exactly what would work on my front porch and back patio without wasting a lot of time and money.” Home Depot also has placed codes on its outdoor patio sets and is running a 30-second bar code commercial nationwide on cable and network television. It is also experimenting with newspaper circulars carrying bar codes that instantly link to a video about its new line, Martha Stewart Living Kitchens. In the video, Ms. Stewart discusses the various styles of kitchen cabinets, counters and other items that are available, and invites customers to make an in-store appointment with a Home Depot kitchen designer. Tom Sweeney, director of online strategy for homedepot.com, said the bar code pilots are about extending the company’s “anytime, anywhere” marketing strategy. “We are testing this out on specific product categories,” he said, of mobile bar codes, “but it’s too early to understand how, and whether, customers will use this technology.” “Large-ticket items, for example, require research, so there may not be an immediate purchase even with the information at the customer’s fingertips,” he said. Roger Marquis, a marketing expert who blogs about bar codes, questioned whether Home Depot or Lowe’s were giving their customers a useful experience that would prompt them to routinely scan codes and induce them to buy. “A lot of marketers look at bar-code technology as a silver bullet to engage customers,” he said. “There’s a disconnect. They are not giving enough information about what bar codes are, and not integrating the technology into their marketing strategies. If the user doesn’t have a worthwhile experience, then they aren’t going to scan codes, and the technology will die on the vine.” Lowe’s has taken steps, like building a mobile version of its Web site, to make information more accessible to customers, said Gihad Jawhar, vice president of lowes.com. The company introduced the readable tags last November for its poinsettias and fresh-cut trees, directing customers to its plant guide with instructions on care, including how much water, fertilizer and light to supply.  This spring, the trees in containers sold at Lowe’s garden centers began carrying tags that could be scanned to view a two-minute how-to video on the specifics of tree planting, including what soil to buy. One of the main reasons for container tree returns is unsuccessful planting, said a Lowe’s spokeswoman, Colleen Carbott. Lowe’s is using Microsoft tag technology — colorful squares — which looks different from the black-and-white checked quick-response codes at Home Depot. “We also have a star rating system on our product pages with user-generated content that is to be accessed by customers,” Mr. Jawhar noted. Lowe’s will not place the bar codes on items like a bag of cement, he said, but plans to place them on products that lend themselves to how-to information. Mike Wehrs, chief executive of Scanbuy, the mobile bar code platform that works with Home Depot, said more than 25 million people in the United States already had the ability to scan with their mobile phones. He expects the number to increase as more people acquire smartphones. “Mobile bar-code scanning experienced a 1,600 percent increase in traffic last year,” he said. Besides quick customer access, he said retailers can also choose to receive data on customer scans, including which products are scanned most and their geographical location. Customers like Keri Stevens, of Verona, Ky., already are convinced. While shopping with her three sons recently in Home Depot, one noticed a bar code on a potted cactus. An admitted “black thumb” gardener, Ms. Stevens bought it only after scanning the bar code to find out the care details. “Now we look for bar codes together,” said Ms. Stevens. “We make it a treasure hunt, and my kids see scanning bar codes as the new normal.”WHETHER it’s a piece of pipe or new kitchen cabinets, many Americans search for the right product in the aisles of home improvement stores like Home Depot or Lowe’s, trying to quickly identify what they need.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/18/business/media/18adco.html?ref=lowescompanies">Sears Challenges Garden Supply Rivals - Advertising<date>Published: March 17, 2011</date><text>A RETAILER struggling to fend off increasing competition is borrowing a page from the marketing playbook of products like soft drinks and soup by naming its rivals in aggressive advertising.Sears, in a campaign scheduled to begin on Sunday, will urge consumers to shop for lawn and garden products at Sears rather than Home Depot or Lowe’s. A description of the campaign on a section of the Sears Web site (sears.com/turfwars) underlines its tough-talking nature: “Sears Turf Wars, fighting the Home Depot and Lowe’s for the right to be on your lawn.” The campaign, being created by the Chicago office of Y&amp;R, has an extensive presence in new media, including Web video clips, social media and a mobile application that enables comparisons of products sold by those three retailers. “ ‘Turf Wars’ isn’t just an ad campaign,” said Martin Lee, vice president and chief marketing officer for lawn and garden products at Sears Holdings in Hoffman Estates, Ill. “It’s a marketing platform, an attitude, a statement of what we will do for our lawn and garden customers.” Sears, part of the Sears Holdings Corporation, is joining a lengthy list of marketers challenging competitors rather than using coy terms like “Brand X” or “another leading brand.” Such direct campaigns are known in the industry as comparative advertising, but they amount to the Madison Avenue equivalent of the negative advertising that is prevalent in politics. • Comparative ads typically become more commonplace when the economy is weak, on the theory that when times are tough it may pay to hit your rival harder. “We wanted to create disruptive advertising,” Mr. Lee said. “The brief to the agency was ‘shock and shatter.’ ” Among brands that have been naming names in pointed ads are Pepsi Max and Sierra Mist Natural sodas, citing, respectively, Coke Zero and Sprite; Campbell’s Select Harvest soups, tackling Progresso, which soon counterattacked; Dunkin’ Donuts, taking on the coffee sold by Starbucks; and the Chevrolet Cruze, proclaiming its superiority to the Honda Civic and the Toyota Corolla. Comparative advertising is not without its risks. One is that the intended audience may be turned off by the tactic, flagging the sponsor for unnecessary roughness. Another risk is that the novelty of hearing or seeing names of other products in ads may prevent consumers from recalling who the sponsor actually was. And comparative advertising requires “a high degree of believability about the message,” said Robert Passikoff, president of Brand Keys in New York, a brand and customer-loyalty consulting company. For instance, “if I tell you Kia is a match for Mercedes,” he added, “you’d be laughing your head off.” In the Brand Keys rankings of sellers of merchandise in the categories of garden care and home repair, Sears is fifth among five retailers, Mr. Passikoff said, trailing, in order, Ace, True Value, Home Depot and Lowe’s. However, the Craftsman brand, which is a focus of the new Sears campaign, does resonate with consumers on attributes like quality and value, he added. The initial television commercial in the campaign features an assertive, gravelly voiced actor named John Lacy, who has appeared in films like “Live Free or Die Hard” and “Zodiac.” He comes across more like a pitchman in a truck ad than a retail spot. Indeed, Mr. Lacy is first glimpsed inside the cab of a truck, part of a caravan delivering Sears lawn and garden products. The trucks drive past a Lowe’s store before setting up the merchandise in a parking lot near a Home Depot. “There’s a lot of home improvement centers out there,” he says, “but does paying more for less mower really improve anything? You deserve better.” Sears will “put our money where our mouth is,” Mr. Lacy says, by offering a lowest-price guarantee,” adding, “You won’t find a better deal there or there,” pointing to the Lowe’s and Home Depot stores. “It’s a turf war, ’cause your lawn is worth fighting for,” he concludes. The campaign is “purposely aggressive and provocative,” said Bob Winter, chief creative officer at Y&amp;R Chicago, part of the Y&amp;R unit of Young &amp; Rubicam Brands, owned by WPP. “It’s definitely got a little bit of bravado,” Mr. Winter said, because Sears executives “feel it’s time to show bravado.” But it does not go too far, he added: “It’s a war. But it’s a war waged with riding mowers that max out at seven miles an hour.” The tone should appeal to potential customers, Mr. Winter said, describing them as “middle-aged suburban dudes” for whom “their lawn is their ultimate form of self-expression.” The campaign is arriving as Y&amp;R Chicago takes part in a review for the Sears creative account, with spending last year, according to Kantar Media, of $459.4 million, of which $12.3 million was devoted to lawn and garden products. • Asked what it was like to produce the campaign at such a precarious time, Mr. Winter replied: “We’re focused on the future, and doing the right thing for our client, no matter what. The review aside, our challenge is to provide them with innovative creative solutions to their problems, and we’re going to continue to do that.” Mr. Lee declined to discuss the review but said, “Y&amp;R really did a great job for us on this.” The Turf Wars do not seem to be prompting Sears’s rivals to wave white flags. For example, Home Depot and a company called Scanbuy are introducing a print campaign using mobile bar codes, or QR codes, to provide information about Martha Stewart Living merchandise.A RETAILER struggling to fend off increasing competition is borrowing a page from the marketing playbook of products like soft drinks and soup by naming its rivals in aggressive advertising.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/28/business/media/28bookstores.html?ref=lowescompanies">Publishers Look Beyond Bookstores to Help Sales<date>Published: February 27, 2011</date><text>Kitson, a group of boutiques based in Los Angeles, is the kind of store that appears regularly in the tabloids for both its stylish clothes and its celebrity clientele like Sean Combs and Joe Jonas.But in a town that is all about flash, Kitson is finding a surprising source of revenue that is not from its fashionable shoes or accessories. It is from books. The company’s owner, Fraser Ross, estimates that Kitson sold 100,000 books in 2010, double what it had the previous year. Publishers turned aggressive about selling to Kitson, Mr. Ross said, as traditional bookstores switched focus or closed. That “has been good for us,” he said. “If there’s a good book, we’ll go deep into it.” And publishers, he said, “realize what a specialty store can do for their business, with the window and the table.” Publishers have stocked books in nonbook retailers for decades — a coffee-table book in the home department, a novelty book in Urban Outfitters. In the last year, though, some publishers have increased their efforts as the two largest bookstore chains have changed course. Barnes &amp; Noble has been devoting more floor space for displays of e-readers, games and educational toys. Borders, after filing for bankruptcy protection in February, has begun liquidating some 200 of its superstores. “The national bookstore chain has peaked as a sales channel, and the growth is not going to come from there,” said David Steinberger, chief executive of the Perseus Books Group. “But it doesn’t mean that all brick-and-mortar retailers are cutting back.” A wide range of stores better known for their apparel, food and fishing reels have been adding books. The fashion designer Marc Jacobs opened Bookmarc in Manhattan in the fall. Anthropologie has increased the number of titles it carries to 125, up from 25 in 2003. Coldwater Creek, Lowe’s, Bass Pro Shops and even Cracker Barrel are adding new books. Some mass retailers, too, are diversifying — Target, for instance, is moving away from male-centered best sellers and adding more women’s and children’s titles this year. Having a physical outlet for books is extraordinarily important, publishers say. While online and e-book sales are huge channels, lesser-known books can get lost in that world if they do not have a physical presence to spur interest. The ability to catch a shopper’s eye in a store is almost impossible to mimic online. So publishers are approaching just about anyone with a shelf. For Perseus, sales at nontraditional retailers in 2010 outpaced its sales at Borders, which were around 7 percent, for the first time. For Abrams, which publishes illustrated and art books, nontraditional retailers are seen as one way to offset the business lost by Borders, which has slowed especially in the last year, the Abrams president and chief executive, Michael Jacobs, said. “We’ve definitely cranked it up,” Mr. Jacobs said. Last year, executives realized that “so much of our backlist wasn’t being carried by bookstores. If we’re still doing these books, where are we going to sell them?” The nontraditional category has been growing for Abrams, making up more than 15 percent of its total business in 2010. Mr. Jacobs said he expected that it would grow to 25 percent in the next two to three years. Big publishers, too, like Houghton Mifflin Harcourt and Random House, say they have been seeking out specialty retailers. The attention from publishers comes as a welcome surprise to the stores. “The response has been dramatic. There are piles of book samples and catalogs dropped off in the shop every day,” Jennifer Baker, a book buyer for Marc Jacobs, said in an e-mail. “The assortment of rare and out-of-print books have been a challenge to keep in stock.” Placement in different stores can widen the audience for books, appealing to someone who would not spend time at a Barnes &amp; Noble. “A customer who might not often buy books but adores the brand can ease in to the Bookmarc selection,” Ms. Baker said. Beyond attracting new readers, book sales tend to be a good deal for both sides. Though sales to nonbook retailers can be more complicated and labor-intensive for publishers, books are generally sold on a nonreturnable basis. Bookstores, on the other hand, can return unsold books to publishers. “We know it’s a nice clean sale,” said John Duff, publisher of Perigee Books, an imprint of Penguin Group USA. The books tend to be profitable for the retailers, since they select them carefully and do not usually mark them down. More important, they can drive other purchases and help with branding. At Lowe’s, books on subjects like cooking and home projects are stacked at the front of the store, “inspiring and informing customers to purchase goods that will allow them to successfully complete home improvement projects,” Patti Price, the company’s senior vice president for merchandising, said in an e-mail. At Sam’s Club, which has long carried stacks of best sellers, more children’s books and cookbooks have been added lately. “Those are areas that don’t fit as well into the e-book story, like the best seller or mass-market or even romance books do,” said Phil Shellhammer, a Sam’s Club executive who oversaw the books category there until recently. Sam’s Club has been using its bricks-and-mortar advantage in other ways, too, like adding books from local writers, and bringing in authors for signings. If Anthropologie is selling ikat prints, it might feature books with ikat covers, or it will carry books about inspiration and poetry to get the customer in an escapist mood. “As we try to get them excited about different ideas as they walk in the door, books can be a tremendous way to narrate those stories,” said Aaron Hoey, head merchant for home and accessories at Anthropologie. “We do a very good job of selecting unique books, books you’re not going to find in a typical bookstore, and certainly not in a mass-market bookstore like Borders or Barnes &amp; Noble. And to stumble across it at Amazon, you have to really know what you’re looking for.” The specialty stores can be a boon for publishers selling quirky titles unlikely to get on Amazon’s home page. “Awkward Family Photos” is a hot item at Urban Outfitters, “Hello, Cupcake,” about cupcake design, has been selling strongly at the craft store Michaels, and Price Stern Sloan, another Penguin imprint, sold 42,000 copies of “Mad Libs” in January alone — at Cracker Barrel. At Bookmarc, where fashion titles sold predictably well, executives were surprised when “Erotic Poems” by E. E. Cummings started flying off shelves. At Kitson, too, the top sellers hardly mimic the best-seller list, including books like “How to Raise a Jewish Dog” and “The Official Dictionary of Sarcasm.” “We try to be different,” Mr. Ross said.Kitson, a group of boutiques based in Los Angeles, is the kind of store that appears regularly in the tabloids for both its stylish clothes and its celebrity clientele like Sean Combs and Joe Jonas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/24/business/24retail.html?ref=lowescompanies">Saks Sees Faster Sales Gains, but TJX Is More Wary<date>Published: February 23, 2011</date><text>Saks, the department store operator, said it expected sales to grow faster this year, while TJX Companies, a lower-price retailer, was more reserved in its predictions.Upscale Saks is coming off its best holiday season in years, as shoppers resumed spending on expensive dresses, handbags and shoes by top brands such as Marc Jacobs, Versace and Oscar de la Renta, lifting sales at established stores by 8.4 percent in its fourth quarter. Saks forecast that same-store sales, sales at stores open at least a year, would rise by a ”midsingle digit” percentage this year. In contrast, TJX, whose chains include Marshalls and T.J. Maxx in the United States and Winners in Canada, said same-store sales this fiscal year would rise by 1 to 2 percent, far below its gains in recent years. TJX shares were down 1.83 percent, to $48.81, while Saks shares fell 2.55 percent, to $11.86. TJX buys merchandise at below-wholesale prices and sells it at a discount. Many shoppers, feeling better about their finances, have begun trading back up to department stores, as the holiday sales results of Saks and Macy’s show. TJX has mitigated that by getting vendors to make products specifically for its chains. For fiscal 2012, which ends next January, TJX forecast adjusted earnings per share of $3.78 to $3.93 from continuing operations on same-store sales. Saks said overall sales rose 6.8 percent, to $866.3 million, in the quarter ended on Jan. 29. TJX said same-store sales rose 2 percent and reported a better-than-expected profit for the quarter, compared with a 12 percent increase the year before. TJX said it would raise its dividend to 19 cents a quarter, a 27 percent increase. Lowe’s Companies reported weaker same-store sales than Home Depot and issued a quarterly profit forecast below analyst expectations. The forecast overshadowed Lowe’s higher-than-expected fourth-quarter results and was made after Home Depot reported strong results and raised its profit forecast for the year. Lowe’s now expects first-quarter earnings of 34 to 38 cents a share. Analysts’ average estimate was 38 cents. It expects same-store sales to be about flat and operating margin to slide 0.1 to 0.2 percentage point. Lowe’s said net income rose to $285 million, or 21 cents a share, in the fourth quarter from $205 million, or 14 cents a share, a year ago. Analysts expected 18 cents a share, Thomson Reuters said. Sales rose 3.1 percent to $10.48 billion, more than analysts’ average estimate of $10.45 billion. Lowe’s said same-store sales rose 1.1 percent in the fourth quarter. Same-store sales at Home Depot rose 3.9 percent globally and 4.8 percent in the United States. New Chief at Sears Holdings Sears Holdings Corporation named a new chief executive on Wednesday, ending a three-year search. The company, which runs Sears and Kmart, said its board had elected Lou D’Ambrosio as its new chief executive and president. Mr. D’Ambrosio, 46, served as chief executive of telephone and computer software company Avaya from 2006 to 2008, before stepping down for medical reasons. Before joining Avaya, he held executive positions at I.B.M. For the last six months, Mr. D’Ambrosio has been working as a consultant to Sears’ board.Saks, the department store operator, said it expected sales to grow faster this year, while TJX Companies, a lower-price retailer, was more reserved in its predictions.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/17/business/17lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Profit Rises 9.6% to $832 Million<date>Published: August 16, 2010</date><text>Consumers bought more air-conditioners and grills at the home improvement retailer Lowe’s Companies in early summer, lifting second-quarter profit 9.6 percent, but overall spending was hurt by hot weather and the weak economy, the company said Monday.Lowe’s joined a long line of companies in sounding a cautious note about consumer spending and reduced its yearly revenue forecast as worries increased about a stalling economy. Robert A. Niblock, Lowe’s chief executive, said that Americans were responding to programs like federal cash-for-appliances rebates and sales, but he described 2010 as a “bouncing along the bottom” year. “We view 2010 as a year of transition for the home improvement industry, and we don’t expect consistent improvement in core demand until the fundamentals of the labor and housing markets improve,” Mr. Niblock in a call with analysts. Revenue from stores open at least a year, a crucial indicator of performance, rose 1.6 percent. But Americans remained cautious, spending on carpets or kitchen cabinets but not as much as they would have a few years ago, Larry D. Stone, the chief operating officer, said. “We do see some movement in kitchen cabinet sales, albeit not as strong as we would like to see it.” Carpet sales were strong, but not as strong as in previous years, Mr. Stone said. Home sales have declined recently after being helped early in the year by tax credits, which expired at the end of April. Recent home buyers tend to spend on items like appliances or paint. Lowe’s net income rose to $832 million, or 58 cents a share, in the quarter ended July 30. That was up from $759 million, or 51 cents a share. Revenue grew 3.7 percent to $14.36 billion, which fell short of the company’s expectations. Analysts had expected a profit of 59 cents a share and $14.52 billion in revenue, according to Thomson Reuters. Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., runs 1,724 stores in the United States, Canada and Mexico. The company predicted a profit of $1.38 to $1.45 a share this year, up from a previous estimate of $1.37 to $1.47 a share. But it now expects revenue to rise about 4 percent, rather than 5 to 7 percent. That suggests a total of about $49.11 billion in revenue, down from $49.58 billion to $50.53 billion. Analysts expect a profit of $1.42 a share and revenue of $49.57 billion on average. Lowe’s fiscal year ends Jan. 28. Revenue from stores open at least a year is expected to grow about 2 percent instead of 2 to 4 percent. The company forecast a profit of 28 cents to 32 cents a share in the third quarter, with revenue up 3 to 5 percent, to a range of $11.72 billion to $11.97 billion. Analysts expect a profit of 31 cents a share and $11.94 billion in revenue. Lowe’s shares rose 11 cents, or 0.56 percent Monday, to close at $19.70.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/18/business/18lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Posts 2.7% Increase in 1st-Quarter Profit<date>Published: May 17, 2010</date><text>The Lowe’s Companies said Monday its net income rose 2.7 percent in the first quarter as people spent more money on home improvement projects and bought more expensive items like gas grills and riding mowers.Lowe’s said it earned $489 million, or 34 cents a share, up from $476 million, or 32 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended April 30, rose 4.7 percent, to $12.39 billion. The results beat the expectations of analysts, who had predicted earnings of 31 cents a share on revenue of $12.24 billion, Thomson Reuters said. Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., also raised its outlook for the year, but the forecast fell short of analysts’ expectations. Lowe’s shares fell 81 cents, or 3.1 percent, to close at $25.26. The chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said people were again taking on projects and buying expensive items. Government stimulus programs and warmer weather also helped results, he said. He cautioned that those developments did not mean a full rebound was in sight. “We’re optimistic we’ll continue to see solid sales through the balance of the year with gradual improvement in core demand, but we still view 2010 as a year of transition for our industry, and it will likely be 2011 before we see significant growth,” he said. Revenue at stores open at least a year rose 2.4 percent in the quarter. At stores open at least a year, Lowe’s had a 1 percent increase in purchases of more than $500, but purchases of $50 or less grew faster at 3 percent.The Lowe’s Companies said Monday its net income rose 2.7 percent in the first quarter as people spent more money on home improvement projects and bought more expensive items like gas grills and riding mowers.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DD1238F932A35750C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">ADVERTISING; Lowe's Puts Its Focus on Knowing the Customer's Wants<date>Published: March 1, 2010</date><text>THE bar in ''Cheers'' was supposedly where everybody knew your name. A leading home-improvement retailer plans to present itself as the place where everybody knows which type of washer you need, which type of insect is infesting your garden or which shade of purple a teenage girl can paint her room without driving her mother crazy. In a campaign for spring, which will begin this week, Lowe's will celebrate its employees, whom the retailer calls associates, by giving the actors who play them as much screen time in the initial commercials as the actors who play customers. The associates are portrayed as knowledgeable, helpful and friendly -- the kind of sales staff needed by consumers who hope to save money by doing more household projects themselves. The campaign is indicative of the continued focus on value and service among major retailers as shoppers keep pinching pennies. Although Lowe's and its principal competitor, Home Depot, said last week that they saw signs of a recovery for the home-improvement industry, the monthly poll by the Conference Board of consumer confidence took a steep downturn in February. ''Everything we do in the campaign is grounded in service and value, because that's where the consumer lives right now,'' said Tom Lamb, senior vice president for marketing and advertising at the Lowe's Companies in Mooresville, N.C. Although ''we're seeing pockets of consumer re-engagement,'' he added, marketing messages must still make ''a clear promise we will deliver value back to them.'' The prominent role for employees in the campaign is among several changes by the brand's creative agency, BBDO New York. Others include replacing the actor Gene Hackman as the voice-over announcer for TV and radio commercials and adding the word ''experience'' to the longtime theme, ''Lowe's. Let's build something together.'' The new theme becomes ''Experience. Lowe's. Let's build something together.'' Or maybe it is ''Experience Lowe's. Let's build something together.'' Depending on your ear, it sounds as if Mr. Hackman's successor, an actor named Ben Yannette, says the slogan both ways. That is intentional, according to Wil Boudreau, executive vice president and senior creative director at BBDO New York, part of the BBDO Worldwide division of the Omnicom Group. ''We're hoping people take both meanings,'' Mr. Boudreau said. ''We've always talked about having a good shopping experience; the stores have wide aisles and they're brightly lit.'' ''What we wanted to add to it was to up the value proposition of what Lowe's is,'' he said, by focusing on the employees ''who will inform your shopping decisions and save you money in almost every case.'' ''This is the best expression of 'Let's build something together,' '' Mr. Boudreau said, because it is about ''a bond'' between the shopper and the associate. ''We don't want to overpromise,'' he added. ''It's not having the associates over for dinner. It's that Lowe's is a big store, but it can feel like a small-town hardware store.'' The first six commercials express those sentiments in breezy, fast-paced vignettes that use story-telling techniques from situation comedies like ''The Office'' and ''Modern Family.'' The spots are in a documentary style and the actors sometimes speak to the camera. The time lines are fluid; there are flashbacks and flash-forwards along with scenes in the present. For instance, in one commercial, a husband and wife recount sarcastically how much they ''really loved our old washer.'' Flash back to the washer causing a sudsy flood. Flash ahead to how a Lowe's associate ''hooked us up'' with a new one, the husband says. Flash back again, to the wife kicking the old washer as a Lowe's crew delivers the new one. Flash forward, again, to the couple and the associate in the store, kidding about missing ''that old thing.'' That pattern is followed in the other spots, in which, among other plot lines, a Lowe's employee identifies wood ants as the culprits in the garden infestation, another employee finds a paint named Rocker Girl as the perfect shade of purple to maintain domestic harmony and a third employee assists a woman with a bathroom renovation.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/24/business/economy/24home.html?ref=lowescompanies">Home Improvement Retailers See Glints of Rebound<date>Published: February 23, 2010</date><text>After more than a year of not spending money on their homes, consumers began refurbishing their kitchens and painting their living rooms in what appears to be the early stages of a comeback for the home improvement industry. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image David McNew/Getty Images A Home Depot in Burbank, Calif. Lowe's and Home Depot had better-than-expected profits. Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Lowe's Cos Go to your Portfolio » Home Depot and Lowe’s, the nation’s largest home improvement retailers, posted better-than-expected earnings this week. They said that they did not have to turn to discounts as much as they did last year, and that some customers splurged on higher-priced goods and services like carpet installations. Of Home Depot’s top 40 markets in the United States, all but two showed year-over-year improvement in the most recent reporting period. Some markets in California and Florida, among the states hit hard by the recession, even had sales growth at stores open at least a year, a barometer of retail health. Frank Blake, the company’s chairman and chief executive, said during a conference call on Tuesday that there was “cause for optimism in 2010,” though he described it as a transitional year, not a year of robust growth. “Calling the year ‘transitional’ doesn’t sound very exciting,” Mr. Blake said, “but we have been waiting for this transition for a long time.” For the three months that ended Jan. 31, Home Depot had a profit of $342 million, or 20 cents a share, in contrast to a loss of $54 million, or 3 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales fell 0.3 percent, to $14.6 billion, which executives attributed to store closings. Sales at stores open at least a year were up 1.2 percent  the first increase in years. Also, Home Depot increased its quarterly dividend for the first time since 2006. On Monday, Lowe’s posted a profit of $205 million for the three months that ended Jan. 29, or 14 cents a share, compared with $162 million, or 11 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales increased 1.8 percent, to $10.2 billion. Same-store sales declined 1.6 percent, but that was still the best performance in more than three years. Robert A. Niblock, the chairman and chief executive of Lowe’s, said during a conference call that the results suggested “that the worst of the economic cycle is likely behind us.” Yet while consumers appear to be taking on more discretionary home improvement projects, retailers are still under pressure. Mr. Blake underscored that the housing industry remained stressed, mortgage defaults continued to increase and unemployment was high. Mr. Niblock of Lowe’s noted that the industry was still contending with “the psychological impact of consumers wondering when home prices will finally bottom.” Indeed, Home Depot’s professional business  merchandise typically bought by builders and contractors  was weak, though the rate of decline was not as bad as in previous months. The company’s worst-performing categories included lumber, hardware, electrical goods and other high-priced construction-related categories. Lowe’s, too, said sales to its commercial business customers were soft. Both Home Depot and Lowe’s said that the average amount spent at their cash registers declined from figures in the period a year earlier, though that was not exactly bad news. “It’s still down, but down a lot less,” Carol Tomé, Home Depot’s chief financial officer, said in an interview on Tuesday. “We were very pleased with that.” Sales in Home Depot’s most recent reporting period were driven by the kitchen and bath, paint, flooring and plumbing categories as well as its international businesses. Sales in maintenance and do-it-yourself repair categories continued to be strong. So were simple décor-related categories like ceramic tile, carpet, paint, faucets and bath fixtures. Transactions of $900 or more, which represent about 20 percent of Home Depot’s sales in the United States, declined less than 1 percent. As Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, put it: that is “a significant improvement compared to double-digit declines in previous quarters in 2009.” He attributed the improvement to consumers snapping up values in Home Depot’s appliances, water heaters and windows categories. Lowe’s said sales of flooring, cabinets and countertops were strong, a sign that consumers were willing to take on more costly projects. Both companies said their results were also helped by cost cuts. Analysts who study the home improvement industry predict a slow recovery. Mike Baker, a research analyst with Deutsche Bank, noted in a research report that the biggest threat to the sector’s recovery “is another leg down in housing, particularly as government stimulus factors dissipate.” Both Home Depot and Lowe’s predicted business would pick up toward the end of the year. For 2010, Home Depot expects earnings of $1.79 a share, and a same-store sales increase of 2.5 percent. Lowe’s said that for the year it expects earnings of $1.30 to $1.42 a share, and a same-store increase of 1 to 3 percent. Shares of Home Depot rose 43 cents on Tuesday, to $30.75; Lowe’s fell 26 cents, to $22.81. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 24, 2010, on page B3 of the New York edition.After more than a year of not spending money on their homes, consumers began refurbishing their kitchens and painting their living rooms in what appears to be the early stages of a comeback for the home improvement industry. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image David McNew/Getty Images A Home Depot in Burbank, Calif. Lowe's and Home Depot had better-than-expected profits. Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Lowe's Cos Go to your Portfolio » Home Depot and Lowe’s, the nation’s largest home improvement retailers, posted better-than-expected earnings this week. They said that they did not have to turn to discounts as much as they did last year, and that some customers splurged on higher-priced goods and services like carpet installations. Of Home Depot’s top 40 markets in the United States, all but two showed year-over-year improvement in the most recent reporting period. Some markets in California and Florida, among the states hit hard by the recession, even had sales growth at stores open at least a year, a barometer of retail health. Frank Blake, the company’s chairman and chief executive, said during a conference call on Tuesday that there was “cause for optimism in 2010,” though he described it as a transitional year, not a year of robust growth. “Calling the year ‘transitional’ doesn’t sound very exciting,” Mr. Blake said, “but we have been waiting for this transition for a long time.” For the three months that ended Jan. 31, Home Depot had a profit of $342 million, or 20 cents a share, in contrast to a loss of $54 million, or 3 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales fell 0.3 percent, to $14.6 billion, which executives attributed to store closings. Sales at stores open at least a year were up 1.2 percent  the first increase in years. Also, Home Depot increased its quarterly dividend for the first time since 2006. On Monday, Lowe’s posted a profit of $205 million for the three months that ended Jan. 29, or 14 cents a share, compared with $162 million, or 11 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales increased 1.8 percent, to $10.2 billion. Same-store sales declined 1.6 percent, but that was still the best performance in more than three years. Robert A. Niblock, the chairman and chief executive of Lowe’s, said during a conference call that the results suggested “that the worst of the economic cycle is likely behind us.” Yet while consumers appear to be taking on more discretionary home improvement projects, retailers are still under pressure. Mr. Blake underscored that the housing industry remained stressed, mortgage defaults continued to increase and unemployment was high. Mr. Niblock of Lowe’s noted that the industry was still contending with “the psychological impact of consumers wondering when home prices will finally bottom.” Indeed, Home Depot’s professional business  merchandise typically bought by builders and contractors  was weak, though the rate of decline was not as bad as in previous months. The company’s worst-performing categories included lumber, hardware, electrical goods and other high-priced construction-related categories. Lowe’s, too, said sales to its commercial business customers were soft. Both Home Depot and Lowe’s said that the average amount spent at their cash registers declined from figures in the period a year earlier, though that was not exactly bad news. “It’s still down, but down a lot less,” Carol Tomé, Home Depot’s chief financial officer, said in an interview on Tuesday. “We were very pleased with that.” Sales in Home Depot’s most recent reporting period were driven by the kitchen and bath, paint, flooring and plumbing categories as well as its international businesses. Sales in maintenance and do-it-yourself repair categories continued to be strong. So were simple décor-related categories like ceramic tile, carpet, paint, faucets and bath fixtures. Transactions of $900 or more, which represent about 20 percent of Home Depot’s sales in the United States, declined less than 1 percent. As Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, put it: that is “a significant improvement compared to double-digit declines in previous quarters in 2009.” He attributed the improvement to consumers snapping up values in Home Depot’s appliances, water heaters and windows categories. Lowe’s said sales of flooring, cabinets and countertops were strong, a sign that consumers were willing to take on more costly projects. Both companies said their results were also helped by cost cuts. Analysts who study the home improvement industry predict a slow recovery. Mike Baker, a research analyst with Deutsche Bank, noted in a research report that the biggest threat to the sector’s recovery “is another leg down in housing, particularly as government stimulus factors dissipate.” Both Home Depot and Lowe’s predicted business would pick up toward the end of the year. For 2010, Home Depot expects earnings of $1.79 a share, and a same-store sales increase of 2.5 percent. Lowe’s said that for the year it expects earnings of $1.30 to $1.42 a share, and a same-store increase of 1 to 3 percent. Shares of Home Depot rose 43 cents on Tuesday, to $30.75; Lowe’s fell 26 cents, to $22.81.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6DB103AF930A15751C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">Results at Lowe's Top Expectations<date>Published: February 23, 2010</date><text>Lowe's, the home improvement chain, reported better-than-expected quarterly results on Monday and said sales would improve in 2010 as demand for remodeling projects picked up. The results suggest the worst of the economic cycle is over, said Robert A. Niblock, the chief executive of Lowe's. They also bode well for the company's larger rival, Home Depot, which reports quarterly earnings on Tuesday. Homeowners are gradually warming up to bigger renovation projects, including painting, new flooring, upgrading appliances and redoing their kitchens, Mr. Niblock said. But Lowe's, which plans to buy back up to $5 billion of its stock, also forecast current-quarter profit below Wall Street estimates as snowy weather across several markets kept many of its customers indoors and led to higher maintenance costs. Lowe's profit rose to $205 million, or 14 cents a share, in the fourth quarter, which ended Jan. 29, from $162 million, or 11 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts on average expected 12 cents a share, according to Thomson Reuters. Sales rose 2 percent, to $10.2 billion, from $10 billion in the fourth quarter a year ago, beating the average estimate of about $10.01 billion. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 1.6 percent. Lowe's expects same-store sales to range from a 2 percent decline to flat for the first quarter, with earnings of 27 cents to 29 cents a share. Analysts had forecast profit of 33 cents. For the full year, the company sees total sales rising 4 to 6 percent and same-store sales increasing 1 to 3 percent. It expects to earn $1.30 to $1.42 a share in the period. Lowe's stock fell 6 cents, to end at $23.07 a share on Monday. PHOTO: Lowe's said it benefited from a pickup in home renovation.(PHOTOGRAPH BY SHANNON STAPLETON/REUTERS)</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/22/business/22shop.html?ref=lowescompanies">D.I.Y. Chains Adjust to Smaller Projects<date>Published: August 21, 2009</date><text>In prerecession days, home improvement projects were usually grand, expensive overhauls of kitchens and bathrooms. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York Times Lowes has added more staff to popular do-it-yourself departments, like paint and hardware. Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Mark Lennihan/Associated Press Phyllis LeDosquet is repainting her kitchen to save money before she moves to a new apartment. She says she is saving $200. In this economy, home improvement projects consist of painting the walls and replacing the jiggly toilet handle. “I’m not doing any major projects anymore,” Steve Miller said as he shopped for putty knives this week at a Lowe’s in a suburb of Chicago, “but just fixing what I’ve got.” For months, Mr. Miller, 51, had been planning to give his kitchen and bathrooms a face-lift. “Then the economy got bad, and I don’t want to run up any more credit,” he said. While the recession has caused consumers to pull the plug on exorbitant renovations, it has ignited a resurgence of small, do-it-yourself repair and maintenance projects. The trend has been so noticeable at Lowe’s and Home Depot that those home-improvement chains are taking steps to adjust. Lowe’s has added more staff to popular do-it-yourself departments, like paint and hardware. Home Depot also beefed up its paint department, adding new products like an all-in-one paint and primer, and a Rust-Oleum paint variety that promises to cover more surface area for the money. Unwilling to part with their dollars for glossy new cabinets and granite countertops, consumers are buying only what they need to keep their homes in good condition: plumbing parts, paint, hardware, flooring. And they are buying garden and lawn goods  fertilizer, birdseed, lawn mower and grill repair parts  for their backyards, where many penny-pinchers have spent their summer vacations. “Certainly we’re seeing a shift away from the professional to the do-it-yourself,” said Michael Souers, a retailing analyst with Standard &amp; Poor’s Equity Research. He added that the renovations consumers were putting off today might be put off indefinitely, because homeowners are unable to refinance or get credit lines secured by their home equity. At Home Depot, participation in the company’s free weekly do-it-yourself workshops has spiked, especially sessions about tile, floors and paint. In May, registration for the chain’s quarterly “do-it-herself” workshop for women who want to be handier was up 30 percent compared with last year. Home Depot does not track attendance at its weekly workshops, “but anecdotally we have consistently heard from stores that participation has been way up,” said Jean Niemi, a spokeswoman for the company. These days, shoppers are not just walking out of stores with free pointers, they are walking out after spending less than the cost of a pizza. The other day, Phyllis LeDosquet, a professor in the education department of Northeastern Illinois University in Chicago, spent $9 in a Lowe’s store. “I’m painting my kitchen myself and saving $200,” said Ms. LeDosquet, 54, whose landlord asked her to paint her red walls white before moving out. “I also bought putty to fix the holes in the walls.” This wave of frugality has, of course, hurt sales at the nation’s home improvement chains. In the second quarter, sales at stores open at least a year fell 8.5 percent at Home Depot and 9.5 percent at Lowe’s compared with the period a year ago. Sales of costlier merchandise (checkout tickets above $900 at Home Depot, and above $500 at Lowe’s) declined by double digits. Even sales of home appliances are weak. On Thursday, Sears Holdings reported that same-store sales at its Sears operations in the United States sank 12.5 percent, much worse than analysts expected. The company said its results were hurt by lackluster sales of appliances amid a terrible housing market. Sales increased in the second quarter in only two of the 20 product categories at Lowe’s  nursery items and paint. Larry D. Stone, president and chief operating officer of Lowe’s, told investors in a conference call this week that those were the two most popular do-it-yourself categories. Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, expects the do-it-yourself trend to continue through the fall. “We are providing online tools to educate customers on the importance of weatherization and simple projects like caulking,” he told investors in a conference call this week, adding that Home Depot will offer “energy- and money-saving products along with fall project know-how.” Despite recent signs of stabilization in the housing market, including a jump reported Friday in the sales of used homes, the market is still quite soft by historical standards. A survey by Lowe’s found that 40 percent of consumers have a major home improvement project that they are postponing until the economy improves. “Most people are not spending money on home remodeling,” said Michael Beaulieu, a home builder and developer in Prospect Heights, Ill. “They will fix a leaky faucet, but that’s it.” More Articles in Business »In prerecession days, home improvement projects were usually grand, expensive overhauls of kitchens and bathrooms. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York Times Lowes has added more staff to popular do-it-yourself departments, like paint and hardware. Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Go to your Portfolio » Enlarge This Image Mark Lennihan/Associated Press Phyllis LeDosquet is repainting her kitchen to save money before she moves to a new apartment. She says she is saving $200. In this economy, home improvement projects consist of painting the walls and replacing the jiggly toilet handle. “I’m not doing any major projects anymore,” Steve Miller said as he shopped for putty knives this week at a Lowe’s in a suburb of Chicago, “but just fixing what I’ve got.” For months, Mr. Miller, 51, had been planning to give his kitchen and bathrooms a face-lift. “Then the economy got bad, and I don’t want to run up any more credit,” he said. While the recession has caused consumers to pull the plug on exorbitant renovations, it has ignited a resurgence of small, do-it-yourself repair and maintenance projects. The trend has been so noticeable at Lowe’s and Home Depot that those home-improvement chains are taking steps to adjust. Lowe’s has added more staff to popular do-it-yourself departments, like paint and hardware. Home Depot also beefed up its paint department, adding new products like an all-in-one paint and primer, and a Rust-Oleum paint variety that promises to cover more surface area for the money. Unwilling to part with their dollars for glossy new cabinets and granite countertops, consumers are buying only what they need to keep their homes in good condition: plumbing parts, paint, hardware, flooring. And they are buying garden and lawn goods  fertilizer, birdseed, lawn mower and grill repair parts  for their backyards, where many penny-pinchers have spent their summer vacations. “Certainly we’re seeing a shift away from the professional to the do-it-yourself,” said Michael Souers, a retailing analyst with Standard &amp; Poor’s Equity Research. He added that the renovations consumers were putting off today might be put off indefinitely, because homeowners are unable to refinance or get credit lines secured by their home equity. At Home Depot, participation in the company’s free weekly do-it-yourself workshops has spiked, especially sessions about tile, floors and paint. In May, registration for the chain’s quarterly “do-it-herself” workshop for women who want to be handier was up 30 percent compared with last year. Home Depot does not track attendance at its weekly workshops, “but anecdotally we have consistently heard from stores that participation has been way up,” said Jean Niemi, a spokeswoman for the company. These days, shoppers are not just walking out of stores with free pointers, they are walking out after spending less than the cost of a pizza. The other day, Phyllis LeDosquet, a professor in the education department of Northeastern Illinois University in Chicago, spent $9 in a Lowe’s store. “I’m painting my kitchen myself and saving $200,” said Ms. LeDosquet, 54, whose landlord asked her to paint her red walls white before moving out. “I also bought putty to fix the holes in the walls.” This wave of frugality has, of course, hurt sales at the nation’s home improvement chains. In the second quarter, sales at stores open at least a year fell 8.5 percent at Home Depot and 9.5 percent at Lowe’s compared with the period a year ago. Sales of costlier merchandise (checkout tickets above $900 at Home Depot, and above $500 at Lowe’s) declined by double digits. Even sales of home appliances are weak. On Thursday, Sears Holdings reported that same-store sales at its Sears operations in the United States sank 12.5 percent, much worse than analysts expected. The company said its results were hurt by lackluster sales of appliances amid a terrible housing market. Sales increased in the second quarter in only two of the 20 product categories at Lowe’s  nursery items and paint. Larry D. Stone, president and chief operating officer of Lowe’s, told investors in a conference call this week that those were the two most popular do-it-yourself categories. Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, expects the do-it-yourself trend to continue through the fall. “We are providing online tools to educate customers on the importance of weatherization and simple projects like caulking,” he told investors in a conference call this week, adding that Home Depot will offer “energy- and money-saving products along with fall project know-how.” Despite recent signs of stabilization in the housing market, including a jump reported Friday in the sales of used homes, the market is still quite soft by historical standards. A survey by Lowe’s found that 40 percent of consumers have a major home improvement project that they are postponing until the economy improves. “Most people are not spending money on home remodeling,” said Michael Beaulieu, a home builder and developer in Prospect Heights, Ill. “They will fix a leaky faucet, but that’s it.”</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/19/business/19shop.html?ref=lowescompanies">Profit Falls 22%, but Lowe’s Tops Expectations<date>Published: May 18, 2009</date><text>MOORESVILLE, N.C. (AP)  Lowe’s, the nation’s second-biggest home improvement chain after Home Depot, said Monday that its first-quarter profit fell 22 percent because of the housing market downturn. But the results were still above Wall Street’s expectations. Lowe’s said that consumers continued to stay away from bigger-ticket housing items as they tried to shore up their savings amid the recession. But it said smaller, outdoor purchases seemed to do well. Lowe’s remains optimistic. “In recent weeks we have seen consumer confidence improve, housing turnover show signs of a bottom in certain markets, and home prices slow their decline,” the chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said in a statement. Mr. Niblock noted that Lowe’s would still be keeping an eye on its expenses and would “continue to plan conservatively” since many of the variables affecting the housing market are still at or near historic lows. For the period ended May 1, earnings dropped to $476 million, or 32 cents a share, from $607 million, or 41 cents, a year ago. Analysts predicted net income of 25 cents a share, according to a Thomson Reuters poll. Analysts’ estimates normally exclude one-time items. Sales dipped 2 percent to $11.83 billion from $12.01 billion, but topped Wall Street’s estimate of $11.63 billion. For the year, Lowe’s forecast earnings of $1.13 to $1.15 a share. The retailer’s second-quarter guidance anticipates profit of 51 to 55 cents a share. The company expects a sales decline of 2 percent to an increase of 1 percent for both the full year and the second quarter. Analysts predict 2009 net income of $1.11 a share on revenue of $47.16 billion. Second-quarter profit is expected at 50 cents a share on sales of $14.12 billion. Lowe’s forecast a sales decline of 4 to 8 percent at stores open at least a year for both the second quarter and the year. More Articles in Business »MOORESVILLE, N.C. (AP)  Lowe’s, the nation’s second-biggest home improvement chain after Home Depot, said Monday that its first-quarter profit fell 22 percent because of the housing market downturn. But the results were still above Wall Street’s expectations. Lowe’s said that consumers continued to stay away from bigger-ticket housing items as they tried to shore up their savings amid the recession. But it said smaller, outdoor purchases seemed to do well. Lowe’s remains optimistic. “In recent weeks we have seen consumer confidence improve, housing turnover show signs of a bottom in certain markets, and home prices slow their decline,” the chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said in a statement. Mr. Niblock noted that Lowe’s would still be keeping an eye on its expenses and would “continue to plan conservatively” since many of the variables affecting the housing market are still at or near historic lows. For the period ended May 1, earnings dropped to $476 million, or 32 cents a share, from $607 million, or 41 cents, a year ago. Analysts predicted net income of 25 cents a share, according to a Thomson Reuters poll. Analysts’ estimates normally exclude one-time items. Sales dipped 2 percent to $11.83 billion from $12.01 billion, but topped Wall Street’s estimate of $11.63 billion. For the year, Lowe’s forecast earnings of $1.13 to $1.15 a share. The retailer’s second-quarter guidance anticipates profit of 51 to 55 cents a share. The company expects a sales decline of 2 percent to an increase of 1 percent for both the full year and the second quarter. Analysts predict 2009 net income of $1.11 a share on revenue of $47.16 billion. Second-quarter profit is expected at 50 cents a share on sales of $14.12 billion. Lowe’s forecast a sales decline of 4 to 8 percent at stores open at least a year for both the second quarter and the year.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/18/business/economy/18retail.html?ref=lowescompanies">Big Retailers Feeling Pain on the Web and Off It<date>Published: November 17, 2008</date><text>The retail industry continued to see signs of a sharp pullback in consumer spending, both online and in stores. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Target Corp Go to your Portfolio » Growth in online sales slowed to a near halt in October, comScore, a research firm, is expected to report on Tuesday. Separately, Lowe’s and Target reported Monday that third-quarter profit fell as consumers cut back on large home-improvement projects and discretionary purchases. Online spending grew by only 1 percent over October 2007, comScore said. That was the lowest monthly growth rate since comScore began tracking e-commerce in 2001, and was down from 5 percent in September. In the past, e-commerce has been somewhat protected from cutbacks in consumer spending that have affected retail stores, because online shopping was perceived as more convenient. Consumers also turned to online outlets to compare prices easily. But goods sold online are often discretionary, and as necessities like food and energy have become more expensive, people have less discretionary income, said Gian Fulgoni, chairman of comScore. “If people are stretched to basically make their budget, it just sucks the disposable income out of consumers’ wallets, and e-commerce is really driven by disposable income,” he said. Online sales had been the one bright spot for many retailers, growing as much as 28 percent in August 2007. In October, sales of music and movies online fell 38 percent from the year before. Sales of clothes, books, computer software, video games, flowers, toys and jewelry were also negative. “Those are troubling because those are categories that in the holiday season are very popular,” Mr. Fulgoni said. Only sales of computers and hand-held devices, consumer electronics and sports and fitness equipment rose over the year before. Households with income under $100,000, which have been hit hardest by the pullback in the economy, account for two-thirds of online spending. Those making less than $50,000 have led much of the recent decline, spending 3 percent less in the last three months than they did in the same period last year, comScore said. Lowe’s, meanwhile, said its net income in its third quarter dropped 24 percent to $488 million, from $643 million the same period a year earlier. Revenue rose slightly to $11.7 billion, up 1.4 percent from $11.57 billion in the same quarter a year ago. Profit at Target decreased 23.8 percent to $369 million, from $483 million. Earnings were 49 cents a share, which beat estimates by 1 cent. Sales for the quarter, which include revenue from credit card operations, were $15.1 billion, up 1.9 percent from $14.8 billion. Same-store sales, or sales at stores open at least a year, fell 3.3 percent. Target also said it would suspend its share-buyback program and cut capital spending by $1 billion. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on November 18, 2008, on page B11 of the New York edition.The retail industry continued to see signs of a sharp pullback in consumer spending, both online and in stores. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Target Corp Go to your Portfolio » Growth in online sales slowed to a near halt in October, comScore, a research firm, is expected to report on Tuesday. Separately, Lowe’s and Target reported Monday that third-quarter profit fell as consumers cut back on large home-improvement projects and discretionary purchases. Online spending grew by only 1 percent over October 2007, comScore said. That was the lowest monthly growth rate since comScore began tracking e-commerce in 2001, and was down from 5 percent in September. In the past, e-commerce has been somewhat protected from cutbacks in consumer spending that have affected retail stores, because online shopping was perceived as more convenient. Consumers also turned to online outlets to compare prices easily. But goods sold online are often discretionary, and as necessities like food and energy have become more expensive, people have less discretionary income, said Gian Fulgoni, chairman of comScore. “If people are stretched to basically make their budget, it just sucks the disposable income out of consumers’ wallets, and e-commerce is really driven by disposable income,” he said. Online sales had been the one bright spot for many retailers, growing as much as 28 percent in August 2007. In October, sales of music and movies online fell 38 percent from the year before. Sales of clothes, books, computer software, video games, flowers, toys and jewelry were also negative. “Those are troubling because those are categories that in the holiday season are very popular,” Mr. Fulgoni said. Only sales of computers and hand-held devices, consumer electronics and sports and fitness equipment rose over the year before. Households with income under $100,000, which have been hit hardest by the pullback in the economy, account for two-thirds of online spending. Those making less than $50,000 have led much of the recent decline, spending 3 percent less in the last three months than they did in the same period last year, comScore said. Lowe’s, meanwhile, said its net income in its third quarter dropped 24 percent to $488 million, from $643 million the same period a year earlier. Revenue rose slightly to $11.7 billion, up 1.4 percent from $11.57 billion in the same quarter a year ago. Profit at Target decreased 23.8 percent to $369 million, from $483 million. Earnings were 49 cents a share, which beat estimates by 1 cent. Sales for the quarter, which include revenue from credit card operations, were $15.1 billion, up 1.9 percent from $14.8 billion. Same-store sales, or sales at stores open at least a year, fell 3.3 percent. Target also said it would suspend its share-buyback program and cut capital spending by $1 billion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/20/business/20home.html?ref=lowescompanies">Home Repairs Become Focus as Consumers Feel Pinched<date>Published: August 19, 2008</date><text>Suddenly, the theme in home goods retailing is “in with the old.” Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Lowe's Companies Go to your Portfolio » With the housing market in the doldrums and inflation running at a pace unseen in nearly two decades, consumers are not buying new homes. Instead they are fixing up the ones they have, a trend that is beginning to show up in the financial reports of retailers. “Consumer’s wallets are being pinched,” said Carol B. Tomé, chief financial officer and executive vice president for corporate services at Home Depot. “Customers are moving away from discretionary projects and are spending money on small repair projects.” Home Depot, the world’s largest home improvement retailer and a bellwether for the industry, reported a 24 percent decline in profit in its second quarter on Tuesday, though it beat Wall Street estimates. Some of its best-performing categories were related to home repair, like plumbing and goods for the kitchen and bath. “Plumbing is as basic as it can get in terms of repair,” Ms. Tomé said. “It outperformed the company average.” Michael Souers, a specialty retail analyst with Standard &amp; Poor’s Equity Research, was not surprised that people were fixing toilets rather than remodeling. “It doesn’t cost as much,” he said, referring to repairs, “and consumers can afford those, and especially with the boost the stimulus checks brought.” Frank Blake, chairman and chief executive of Home Depot, said Tuesday in a conference call with investors that about $300 million in sales was probably related to the government stimulus package. Home Depot does not break out sales by category, though it said plumbing outperformed its overall same-store sales figure, or sales at stores open at least a year, an important measure of retail health. Home Depot’s same-store sales for the three months ending Aug. 3 fell 7.9 percent. (Adjusting for a shift in the company’s fiscal calendar this year would put that figure at a decline of 7.2 percent.) Both Home Depot and Lowe’s, the world’s second-largest home improvement retailer, acknowledged that consumers had shied away from costly discretionary items. “During the quarter we continued to see soft demand in cabinets and countertops, and fashion plumbing,” Larry D. Stone, president and chief operating officer of Lowe’s Companies, said in a conference call with investors on Monday. Sales of repair and maintenance products, on the other hand, were solid. Home goods retailers know all too well that getting a consumer to buy a new kitchen is nearly impossible these days. Instead Home Depot expanded its offering of low-priced items across the store, a tactic it said it thought made more sense than limited-time blowout sales. “We were less promotional over all compared to last year,” Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, said Tuesday in a conference call with investors, “and consciously focused on eliminating margin-eroding promotions.” Ms. Tomé said transactions for $25 and under were down “a lot less” than items over $600. David Strasser, a Banc of America Investment Services analyst, said this was an industrywide trend. “The bifurcation between low ticket and high ticket has become more dramatic,” he said. In addition to making necessary repairs, consumers  bracing for higher fuel prices this winter  are also trying to save money by making their homes more energy-efficient. “This is a trend we expect to continue into the third quarter,” Mr. Menear said. “Products such as weather stripping, caulk, CFL light bulbs, air circulation and pipe insulation all performed well. In the Northeast, we are already seeing strong sales in our fireplace category as customers are stocking up on pellet fuel before the cold weather arrives.” Home Depot plans to introduce more energy-efficient products like dimmable compact fluorescent light bulbs, water-saving faucets and toilets and a flush-mount programmable thermostat. The two biggest home improvement retailers are experiencing the same trends: same-store sales declines, a boost from stimulus checks, weakness in big-ticket item sales, even strong sales of pellet heaters. Home Depot reported Tuesday that profit for the three months ending Aug. 3 fell 24 percent, to $1.2 billion, or 71 cents a diluted share, compared with $1.6 billion, or 81 cents a diluted share, for the same period last year. Grim as the numbers may sound, they were better than analysts had expected. “I thought they were actually very strong,” said Mr. Souers of Standard &amp; Poor’s, “much stronger than my estimate of 63 cents a share. The Street was 61 cents.” Matthew J. Fassler, an analyst with Goldman Sachs, said he expected sales at Home Depot and Lowe’s to slow further based on the historical relationship between home sales and home improvement retail sales. “From Lowe’s on Monday and Home Depot today you can see that the home sector bucked the trend that you would typically expect in the middle of a shared housing downturn,” he said. Mitch Kaiser, senior research analyst for Piper Jaffray, also liked the earnings results but said declines in same-store sales at Home Depot and Lowe’s were likely to last at least another year. Every retailer is suffering in this economy, but “they’re hurt worst,” he said. “Their products are going into a declining price asset.” Lowe’s said its profit for the three months that ended Aug. 1 decreased 7.9 percent, to $938 million, or 64 cents a diluted share, compared with $1 billion, or 67 cents a diluted share, for the same period last year. Same-store sales declined 5.3 percent for the quarter. Home Depot and Lowe’s were cautious in their forecasts for the future. Even so, as the home improvement industry consolidates, analysts, including Mr. Kaiser, say Home Depot and Lowe’s are well positioned. It is smaller home improvement retailers that are in deeper trouble. “It’s not a Home Depot versus Lowe’s industry right now,” said Mr. Strasser of Banc of America Investment Services. “They both will come out of this very well. And the longer it lasts the better and stronger they’re going to be in some respects.” He added, “Other people can’t survive.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on August 20, 2008, on page C1 of the New York edition.Suddenly, the theme in home goods retailing is “in with the old.” Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Home Depot Inc Lowe's Companies Go to your Portfolio » With the housing market in the doldrums and inflation running at a pace unseen in nearly two decades, consumers are not buying new homes. Instead they are fixing up the ones they have, a trend that is beginning to show up in the financial reports of retailers. “Consumer’s wallets are being pinched,” said Carol B. Tomé, chief financial officer and executive vice president for corporate services at Home Depot. “Customers are moving away from discretionary projects and are spending money on small repair projects.” Home Depot, the world’s largest home improvement retailer and a bellwether for the industry, reported a 24 percent decline in profit in its second quarter on Tuesday, though it beat Wall Street estimates. Some of its best-performing categories were related to home repair, like plumbing and goods for the kitchen and bath. “Plumbing is as basic as it can get in terms of repair,” Ms. Tomé said. “It outperformed the company average.” Michael Souers, a specialty retail analyst with Standard &amp; Poor’s Equity Research, was not surprised that people were fixing toilets rather than remodeling. “It doesn’t cost as much,” he said, referring to repairs, “and consumers can afford those, and especially with the boost the stimulus checks brought.” Frank Blake, chairman and chief executive of Home Depot, said Tuesday in a conference call with investors that about $300 million in sales was probably related to the government stimulus package. Home Depot does not break out sales by category, though it said plumbing outperformed its overall same-store sales figure, or sales at stores open at least a year, an important measure of retail health. Home Depot’s same-store sales for the three months ending Aug. 3 fell 7.9 percent. (Adjusting for a shift in the company’s fiscal calendar this year would put that figure at a decline of 7.2 percent.) Both Home Depot and Lowe’s, the world’s second-largest home improvement retailer, acknowledged that consumers had shied away from costly discretionary items. “During the quarter we continued to see soft demand in cabinets and countertops, and fashion plumbing,” Larry D. Stone, president and chief operating officer of Lowe’s Companies, said in a conference call with investors on Monday. Sales of repair and maintenance products, on the other hand, were solid. Home goods retailers know all too well that getting a consumer to buy a new kitchen is nearly impossible these days. Instead Home Depot expanded its offering of low-priced items across the store, a tactic it said it thought made more sense than limited-time blowout sales. “We were less promotional over all compared to last year,” Craig Menear, Home Depot’s executive vice president for merchandising, said Tuesday in a conference call with investors, “and consciously focused on eliminating margin-eroding promotions.” Ms. Tomé said transactions for $25 and under were down “a lot less” than items over $600. David Strasser, a Banc of America Investment Services analyst, said this was an industrywide trend. “The bifurcation between low ticket and high ticket has become more dramatic,” he said. In addition to making necessary repairs, consumers  bracing for higher fuel prices this winter  are also trying to save money by making their homes more energy-efficient. “This is a trend we expect to continue into the third quarter,” Mr. Menear said. “Products such as weather stripping, caulk, CFL light bulbs, air circulation and pipe insulation all performed well. In the Northeast, we are already seeing strong sales in our fireplace category as customers are stocking up on pellet fuel before the cold weather arrives.” Home Depot plans to introduce more energy-efficient products like dimmable compact fluorescent light bulbs, water-saving faucets and toilets and a flush-mount programmable thermostat. The two biggest home improvement retailers are experiencing the same trends: same-store sales declines, a boost from stimulus checks, weakness in big-ticket item sales, even strong sales of pellet heaters. Home Depot reported Tuesday that profit for the three months ending Aug. 3 fell 24 percent, to $1.2 billion, or 71 cents a diluted share, compared with $1.6 billion, or 81 cents a diluted share, for the same period last year. Grim as the numbers may sound, they were better than analysts had expected. “I thought they were actually very strong,” said Mr. Souers of Standard &amp; Poor’s, “much stronger than my estimate of 63 cents a share. The Street was 61 cents.” Matthew J. Fassler, an analyst with Goldman Sachs, said he expected sales at Home Depot and Lowe’s to slow further based on the historical relationship between home sales and home improvement retail sales. “From Lowe’s on Monday and Home Depot today you can see that the home sector bucked the trend that you would typically expect in the middle of a shared housing downturn,” he said. Mitch Kaiser, senior research analyst for Piper Jaffray, also liked the earnings results but said declines in same-store sales at Home Depot and Lowe’s were likely to last at least another year. Every retailer is suffering in this economy, but “they’re hurt worst,” he said. “Their products are going into a declining price asset.” Lowe’s said its profit for the three months that ended Aug. 1 decreased 7.9 percent, to $938 million, or 64 cents a diluted share, compared with $1 billion, or 67 cents a diluted share, for the same period last year. Same-store sales declined 5.3 percent for the quarter. Home Depot and Lowe’s were cautious in their forecasts for the future. Even so, as the home improvement industry consolidates, analysts, including Mr. Kaiser, say Home Depot and Lowe’s are well positioned. It is smaller home improvement retailers that are in deeper trouble. “It’s not a Home Depot versus Lowe’s industry right now,” said Mr. Strasser of Banc of America Investment Services. “They both will come out of this very well. And the longer it lasts the better and stronger they’re going to be in some respects.” He added, “Other people can’t survive.”</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/19/business/19lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Profit Falls, but Beats Expectations<date>Published: August 18, 2008</date><text>The Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement chain, said Monday its profit fell nearly 8 percent in its most recent quarter but managed to top Wall Street expectations, helped by expense controls and better-than-expected sales, particularly in lawn and garden items. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Spencer Platt/Getty Images Customers at a Lowes store in Brooklyn Monday. The company raised its forecast for the year. Add to Portfolio Lowe's Companies Go to your Portfolio » The company said it expected to continue to suffer from a weak housing market and offered a weaker-than-expected outlook for the third quarter. It nonetheless raised its forecast for the full year. Lowe’s earned $938 million, or 64 cents a share, in the period, down from $1.02 billion, or 67 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended Aug. 1 and was the second quarter of Lowe’s fiscal year, rose 2.4 percent, to $14.5 billion, from $14.17 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters expected a smaller profit of 56 cents a share on revenue of $14.1 billion. Stock in the company, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., rose 4 cents, to $24.54. “It was a tough environment out there,” the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Lowe’s said seasonal lawn and garden and nursery sales were strong as homeowners restored their lawns and undertook other small outdoor projects to repair damage from last year’s drought. Mr. Niblock said the company benefited from the issuance of economic stimulus checks. Still, Lowe’s said sales of bigger-ticket items continued to fall, particularly in regions hurt most by the housing downturn. In the hardest-hit areas, like Florida and California, same-store sales fell by 10 percent or more. Over all, the company’s comparable store sales fell 5 percent. “All things considered, the quality of the second earnings was good,” a BMO Capital Markets analyst, Wayne Hood, told investors in a research note. For the fiscal year, the company raised its guidance for earnings per share to a range of $1.48 to $1.56, from $1.45 to $1.55. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on August 19, 2008, on page C5 of the New York edition.The Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement chain, said Monday its profit fell nearly 8 percent in its most recent quarter but managed to top Wall Street expectations, helped by expense controls and better-than-expected sales, particularly in lawn and garden items. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Spencer Platt/Getty Images Customers at a Lowes store in Brooklyn Monday. The company raised its forecast for the year. Add to Portfolio Lowe's Companies Go to your Portfolio » The company said it expected to continue to suffer from a weak housing market and offered a weaker-than-expected outlook for the third quarter. It nonetheless raised its forecast for the full year. Lowe’s earned $938 million, or 64 cents a share, in the period, down from $1.02 billion, or 67 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended Aug. 1 and was the second quarter of Lowe’s fiscal year, rose 2.4 percent, to $14.5 billion, from $14.17 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters expected a smaller profit of 56 cents a share on revenue of $14.1 billion. Stock in the company, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., rose 4 cents, to $24.54. “It was a tough environment out there,” the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Lowe’s said seasonal lawn and garden and nursery sales were strong as homeowners restored their lawns and undertook other small outdoor projects to repair damage from last year’s drought. Mr. Niblock said the company benefited from the issuance of economic stimulus checks. Still, Lowe’s said sales of bigger-ticket items continued to fall, particularly in regions hurt most by the housing downturn. In the hardest-hit areas, like Florida and California, same-store sales fell by 10 percent or more. Over all, the company’s comparable store sales fell 5 percent. “All things considered, the quality of the second earnings was good,” a BMO Capital Markets analyst, Wayne Hood, told investors in a research note. For the fiscal year, the company raised its guidance for earnings per share to a range of $1.48 to $1.56, from $1.45 to $1.55.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/20/business/20stox.html?ref=lowescompanies">Words of Caution Deflate Optimism<date>Published: May 20, 2008</date><text>Stocks ended mixed Monday after weakness in the technology sector punctured some of the market’s enthusiasm over a report that suggested the economy could still be growing. Comments about soft sales from the SanDisk Corporation, a maker of memory chips, helped pull stocks off their highs and sent tech shares lower. The Dow Jones industrial average, which had been up more than 100 points, finished well off its highs. The Conference Board’s report on leading economic indicators showed a 0.1 percent rise for April, following a similar increase in March. The index, intended to forecast economic activity in the next three to six months, bolstered investors’ belief that the nation’s economy, while weak, was positioned for recovery. After five months of declines in the leading indicators, some investors were concerned that March’s increase was an anomaly, so April’s advance was met with relief, said Hugh Johnson, chief investment officer of Johnson Illington Advisors. But technology shares tugged at the market after SanDisk issued cautious comments at a JPMorgan technology conference, said Neil Massa, senior trader at MFC Global Investment Management in Boston. SanDisk fell $2.42, or 7.5 percent, to $30.02. SanDisk’s remarks came on a day of light trading and dented but did not sink an upbeat mood on Wall Street. “Even though you’re up only 0.1 percent, it’s very good news that the declining trend may have been reversed,” Mr. Johnson said, referring to the leading indicators report. “That is important for this reason: It’s consistent with the message of the markets.” The Dow rose 41.36 points, or 0.32 percent, to 13,028.16. The blue chips had been up nearly 150 points at their highs of the session. Broader stock indicators finished mixed. The S.&amp; P. 500 advanced 1.28 points, or 0.09 percent, to 1,426.63, and the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index fell 12.76 points, or 0.50 percent, to 2,516.09. Government bonds rose as the rally in stocks cooled. The benchmark 10-year Treasury note rose 4/32, to 100 12/32, and its yield, which moves in the opposite direction from its price, fell to 3.83 percent, from 3.84 percent. The dollar rose against most other major currencies, while gold prices also climbed. One pressure point for the economy, rising energy prices, appeared relatively in check Monday. While many investors remain mindful of the rising price of oil and its effect on consumer spending, Wall Street seemed somewhat unfazed as oil advanced. Light crude rose 76 cents to settle at a record $127.05 a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange. Financial shares also pulled back after the market came off its highs. Merrill Lynch fell $1.14, or 2.3 percent, to $47.71, while Lehman Brothers Holdings fell 85 cents, to $42.79. The Lowe’s Companies posted a first-quarter profit decline and issued an outlook for the year that was below analysts’ estimates. The second-largest home improvement chain fell 64 cents, or 2.6 percent, to $24.25. Following are the results of Monday’s auctions of three-month and six-month Treasury bills and 30-day cash management bills: More Articles in Business »Stocks ended mixed Monday after weakness in the technology sector punctured some of the market’s enthusiasm over a report that suggested the economy could still be growing. Comments about soft sales from the SanDisk Corporation, a maker of memory chips, helped pull stocks off their highs and sent tech shares lower. The Dow Jones industrial average, which had been up more than 100 points, finished well off its highs. The Conference Board’s report on leading economic indicators showed a 0.1 percent rise for April, following a similar increase in March. The index, intended to forecast economic activity in the next three to six months, bolstered investors’ belief that the nation’s economy, while weak, was positioned for recovery. After five months of declines in the leading indicators, some investors were concerned that March’s increase was an anomaly, so April’s advance was met with relief, said Hugh Johnson, chief investment officer of Johnson Illington Advisors. But technology shares tugged at the market after SanDisk issued cautious comments at a JPMorgan technology conference, said Neil Massa, senior trader at MFC Global Investment Management in Boston. SanDisk fell $2.42, or 7.5 percent, to $30.02. SanDisk’s remarks came on a day of light trading and dented but did not sink an upbeat mood on Wall Street. “Even though you’re up only 0.1 percent, it’s very good news that the declining trend may have been reversed,” Mr. Johnson said, referring to the leading indicators report. “That is important for this reason: It’s consistent with the message of the markets.” The Dow rose 41.36 points, or 0.32 percent, to 13,028.16. The blue chips had been up nearly 150 points at their highs of the session. Broader stock indicators finished mixed. The S.&amp; P. 500 advanced 1.28 points, or 0.09 percent, to 1,426.63, and the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index fell 12.76 points, or 0.50 percent, to 2,516.09. Government bonds rose as the rally in stocks cooled. The benchmark 10-year Treasury note rose 4/32, to 100 12/32, and its yield, which moves in the opposite direction from its price, fell to 3.83 percent, from 3.84 percent. The dollar rose against most other major currencies, while gold prices also climbed. One pressure point for the economy, rising energy prices, appeared relatively in check Monday. While many investors remain mindful of the rising price of oil and its effect on consumer spending, Wall Street seemed somewhat unfazed as oil advanced. Light crude rose 76 cents to settle at a record $127.05 a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange. Financial shares also pulled back after the market came off its highs. Merrill Lynch fell $1.14, or 2.3 percent, to $47.71, while Lehman Brothers Holdings fell 85 cents, to $42.79. The Lowe’s Companies posted a first-quarter profit decline and issued an outlook for the year that was below analysts’ estimates. The second-largest home improvement chain fell 64 cents, or 2.6 percent, to $24.25. Following are the results of Monday’s auctions of three-month and six-month Treasury bills and 30-day cash management bills:</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/07/business/07adco.html?ref=lowescompanies">As the Snows Melt, Lowe’s Encourages Spring Thinking<date>Published: March 7, 2008</date><text>ANOTHER major advertiser is placing a big bet on its ability to cajole wary consumers into behaving as if gasoline prices were not climbing, housing values were not falling and the stock market was not gyrating. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Video Lowe's Aims to Jump Start Spring: Getting Shoppers Out of Hibernation Video Lowe's Aims to Jump Start Spring: Luring Shoppers with a Color Burst Lowe’s, the home improvement chain, is planning what may be its most ambitious annual spring marketing campaign, which gets under way on Sunday. The starting date is a couple of weeks earlier than usual this year, to take advantage of the earlier start to daylight saving time. The campaign, from several agencies owned by the Omnicom Group and an internal team at Lowe’s, is relentlessly upbeat, as shown by its cheerful theme, “Welcome back spring.” The centerpiece is a section of the Lowe’s Web site (lowes.com/spring), scheduled to begin on Monday, where computer users can visit a make-believe town, Sunnyville, whose inhabitants are gaga over activities like grilling, gardening and riding around on lawn mowers. The Web site, created by the Chicago office of Tribal DDB Worldwide, will offer new content that includes cellphone ring tones  called “spring tones”  that mimic seasonal sounds like birds, crickets and sprinklers. The site will also have a whimsical “meat calculator,” intended to help determine how much food to buy for barbecues, and a weather-data widget for iGoogle, the personalized home page service offered by Google. The site will later add a feature that is reminiscent of virtual worlds like Second Life: the ability for users to create a digital lawn, which will thrive provided it is watered and mowed. In addition to the online effort, the campaign includes commercials on television and radio, outdoor posters and ads in newspapers and magazines. Lowe’s spends considerably this time of year to stimulate sales because “for our business, spring is our Christmas,” said Bob Gfeller, senior vice president for marketing and advertising at the Lowe’s Companies in Mooresville, N.C. In the last two years, Lowe’s spent $85 million to $90 million in March and April, according to data from Nielsen Monitor-Plus. As for the budget for the spring 2008 campaign, “I couldn’t necessarily say it is the biggest in dollar investment,” Mr. Gfeller said, “but it’s the most integrated,” adding more digital elements to “make it more interactive than just Lowe’s talking to the customer.”  Madison Avenue is watching anxiously to see whether marketers like Lowe’s, which spends about $900 million each year to advertise in major media, will maintain their budgets or slash them because of the uncertain economic climate. The risk is that tough times can offer a company a chance to increase sales, particularly if competitors cut back their campaigns. But if consumers are not eager to spend, or are concentrating on necessities, large ad outlays can be wasteful. Pulling back “is certainly something you think about,” Mr. Gfeller said, but because Lowe’s has been gaining market share among sellers of home improvement merchandise, “we look at this as an opportunity.” “It’s not that investing in their homes is off the list for consumers; it’s a different level of investment based on the means they have here and now,” he added. “You can buy a large plant, or build a deck.” That attitude was echoed by executives at the Lowe’s agencies. “When we say, ‘Come in and get a grill,’ it doesn’t have to be the S.U.V. size,” said Steve Rutter, a senior vice president and creative director at the New York office of BBDO Worldwide who works on Lowe’s with Wil Boudreau, also a senior vice president and creative director. “If we were selling the $5,000 washer-dryer combo or a $25,000 kitchen remodel, it would be one thing,” Mr. Rutter said. “But everybody wants to spruce up the yard. We’re celebrating that it’s time to go to Lowe’s and live outside again.” The campaign manifests that attitude in several ways. Along with the beaming residents of Sunnyville, there is a couple transformed, by shopping at Lowe’s, from wintry black and white to springtime colors. There is also a bear named Mike, symbolic of what Mr. Rutter described as “coming out of hibernation, the moment you go from cabin fever to spring fever.” Lowe’s is the third prominent retailer to commit to a significant campaign in the last couple of weeks. The others are Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, part of Sears Holdings, which is teaming up with the Hearst Corporation for a campaign that urges shoppers to “Reimagine yourself,” and J. C. Penney, which is joining forces with Polo Ralph Lauren to introduce in Penney stores a merchandise line named American Living. Retail sales last month, reported on Thursday, were decidedly mixed. Chains like T. J. Maxx, Target and Wal-Mart, which play up discount prices, fared better than department stores and fashion-oriented stores. “As the economy we’re facing starts to turn down, people are scaling back their dreams,” said Kevin Flatt, executive creative director at Tribal DDB Chicago. “But they still have dreams, and it’s nice to be able to satisfy some of them.”  In addition to Tribal DDB and BBDO, the other Omnicom agencies working on the campaign include Cultura, for ads aimed at Spanish-speaking shoppers; OMD, for media planning and buying; and TPN, for promotions. Plans call for the campaign to run through mid-May, Mr. Gfeller said, then make way for ads with summer themes. If the economy keeps struggling, he added, Lowe’s has a strategy. It will encourage shoppers to “buy everything they need” during whatever store visits they are still making. For instance, if someone is planning to paint a house, the goal is to sell “not just paint,” Mr. Gfeller said, but also “the brushes, the rollers, the tape, the caulk.” More Articles in Business »ANOTHER major advertiser is placing a big bet on its ability to cajole wary consumers into behaving as if gasoline prices were not climbing, housing values were not falling and the stock market was not gyrating. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Video Lowe's Aims to Jump Start Spring: Getting Shoppers Out of Hibernation Video Lowe's Aims to Jump Start Spring: Luring Shoppers with a Color Burst Lowe’s, the home improvement chain, is planning what may be its most ambitious annual spring marketing campaign, which gets under way on Sunday. The starting date is a couple of weeks earlier than usual this year, to take advantage of the earlier start to daylight saving time. The campaign, from several agencies owned by the Omnicom Group and an internal team at Lowe’s, is relentlessly upbeat, as shown by its cheerful theme, “Welcome back spring.” The centerpiece is a section of the Lowe’s Web site (lowes.com/spring), scheduled to begin on Monday, where computer users can visit a make-believe town, Sunnyville, whose inhabitants are gaga over activities like grilling, gardening and riding around on lawn mowers. The Web site, created by the Chicago office of Tribal DDB Worldwide, will offer new content that includes cellphone ring tones  called “spring tones”  that mimic seasonal sounds like birds, crickets and sprinklers. The site will also have a whimsical “meat calculator,” intended to help determine how much food to buy for barbecues, and a weather-data widget for iGoogle, the personalized home page service offered by Google. The site will later add a feature that is reminiscent of virtual worlds like Second Life: the ability for users to create a digital lawn, which will thrive provided it is watered and mowed. In addition to the online effort, the campaign includes commercials on television and radio, outdoor posters and ads in newspapers and magazines. Lowe’s spends considerably this time of year to stimulate sales because “for our business, spring is our Christmas,” said Bob Gfeller, senior vice president for marketing and advertising at the Lowe’s Companies in Mooresville, N.C. In the last two years, Lowe’s spent $85 million to $90 million in March and April, according to data from Nielsen Monitor-Plus. As for the budget for the spring 2008 campaign, “I couldn’t necessarily say it is the biggest in dollar investment,” Mr. Gfeller said, “but it’s the most integrated,” adding more digital elements to “make it more interactive than just Lowe’s talking to the customer.”  Madison Avenue is watching anxiously to see whether marketers like Lowe’s, which spends about $900 million each year to advertise in major media, will maintain their budgets or slash them because of the uncertain economic climate. The risk is that tough times can offer a company a chance to increase sales, particularly if competitors cut back their campaigns. But if consumers are not eager to spend, or are concentrating on necessities, large ad outlays can be wasteful. Pulling back “is certainly something you think about,” Mr. Gfeller said, but because Lowe’s has been gaining market share among sellers of home improvement merchandise, “we look at this as an opportunity.” “It’s not that investing in their homes is off the list for consumers; it’s a different level of investment based on the means they have here and now,” he added. “You can buy a large plant, or build a deck.” That attitude was echoed by executives at the Lowe’s agencies. “When we say, ‘Come in and get a grill,’ it doesn’t have to be the S.U.V. size,” said Steve Rutter, a senior vice president and creative director at the New York office of BBDO Worldwide who works on Lowe’s with Wil Boudreau, also a senior vice president and creative director. “If we were selling the $5,000 washer-dryer combo or a $25,000 kitchen remodel, it would be one thing,” Mr. Rutter said. “But everybody wants to spruce up the yard. We’re celebrating that it’s time to go to Lowe’s and live outside again.” The campaign manifests that attitude in several ways. Along with the beaming residents of Sunnyville, there is a couple transformed, by shopping at Lowe’s, from wintry black and white to springtime colors. There is also a bear named Mike, symbolic of what Mr. Rutter described as “coming out of hibernation, the moment you go from cabin fever to spring fever.” Lowe’s is the third prominent retailer to commit to a significant campaign in the last couple of weeks. The others are Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, part of Sears Holdings, which is teaming up with the Hearst Corporation for a campaign that urges shoppers to “Reimagine yourself,” and J. C. Penney, which is joining forces with Polo Ralph Lauren to introduce in Penney stores a merchandise line named American Living. Retail sales last month, reported on Thursday, were decidedly mixed. Chains like T. J. Maxx, Target and Wal-Mart, which play up discount prices, fared better than department stores and fashion-oriented stores. “As the economy we’re facing starts to turn down, people are scaling back their dreams,” said Kevin Flatt, executive creative director at Tribal DDB Chicago. “But they still have dreams, and it’s nice to be able to satisfy some of them.”  In addition to Tribal DDB and BBDO, the other Omnicom agencies working on the campaign include Cultura, for ads aimed at Spanish-speaking shoppers; OMD, for media planning and buying; and TPN, for promotions. Plans call for the campaign to run through mid-May, Mr. Gfeller said, then make way for ads with summer themes. If the economy keeps struggling, he added, Lowe’s has a strategy. It will encourage shoppers to “buy everything they need” during whatever store visits they are still making. For instance, if someone is planning to paint a house, the goal is to sell “not just paint,” Mr. Gfeller said, but also “the brushes, the rollers, the tape, the caulk.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/27/business/27home.html?ref=lowescompanies">Home Depot Reports Profit Declined 27%<date>Published: February 27, 2008</date><text>ATLANTA (AP)  Fourth-quarter profit fell more than 27 percent at Home Depot, the home improvement chain, as a slowing housing market led to the company’s first annual sales decline. Home Depot, based in Atlanta, said on Tuesday that 2008 was expected to be worse in terms of sales and profits. The outlook was even gloomier than the one given Monday by a rival, the Lowe’s Companies, which predicted improving sales on the horizon. “We think we’ve still lost share to the market,” the chief executive of Home Depot, Frank S. Blake, told analysts during a conference call. The home improvement industry has suffered as consumers pulled back on renovations in the face of declining home values. Mr. Blake, noting that last year was among the most difficult financially for Home Depot, told analysts that the company was “still too often perceived as lagging in customer service.” Home Depot said it planned to add 55 stores this year, about half as many as last year. The results for the latest quarter fell short of Wall Street expectations, and shares rose a penny to $28.83. The company said it earned $671 million, or 40 cents a share, in the three months ended Feb. 3, compared with a profit of $925 million, or 46 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Earnings from continuing operations in the quarter were 40 cents a share, compared with 42 cents a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial were expecting earnings of 43 cents a share in the fourth quarter. With an extra sales week, revenue in the quarter rose 1.5 percent, to $17.66 billion, compared with $17.4 billion a year earlier. Excluding that additional week, fourth-quarter sales declined 4.7 percent compared with a year ago. Revenue for fiscal 2007 declined 2.1 percent, to $77.35 billion. A spokesman, Ron DeFeo, said that was the first annual sales decline for Home Depot. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 8.3 percent in the quarter. The company’s average sales ticket declined 2.3 percent, to $54.96 in the quarter, compared with $56.27 a year ago. For all of 2007, Home Depot said it earned $4.4 billion, or $2.37 a share, compared with a profit of $5.76 billion, or $2.79 a share, for 2006. Its $77.35 billion in sales for the year compared with $79.02 billion a year earlier. Lowe’s reported Monday that its fourth-quarter profit dropped by a third. But it predicted that sales  while still hurt by a soft housing market  would improve slightly in 2008. More Articles in Business »ATLANTA (AP)  Fourth-quarter profit fell more than 27 percent at Home Depot, the home improvement chain, as a slowing housing market led to the company’s first annual sales decline. Home Depot, based in Atlanta, said on Tuesday that 2008 was expected to be worse in terms of sales and profits. The outlook was even gloomier than the one given Monday by a rival, the Lowe’s Companies, which predicted improving sales on the horizon. “We think we’ve still lost share to the market,” the chief executive of Home Depot, Frank S. Blake, told analysts during a conference call. The home improvement industry has suffered as consumers pulled back on renovations in the face of declining home values. Mr. Blake, noting that last year was among the most difficult financially for Home Depot, told analysts that the company was “still too often perceived as lagging in customer service.” Home Depot said it planned to add 55 stores this year, about half as many as last year. The results for the latest quarter fell short of Wall Street expectations, and shares rose a penny to $28.83. The company said it earned $671 million, or 40 cents a share, in the three months ended Feb. 3, compared with a profit of $925 million, or 46 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Earnings from continuing operations in the quarter were 40 cents a share, compared with 42 cents a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial were expecting earnings of 43 cents a share in the fourth quarter. With an extra sales week, revenue in the quarter rose 1.5 percent, to $17.66 billion, compared with $17.4 billion a year earlier. Excluding that additional week, fourth-quarter sales declined 4.7 percent compared with a year ago. Revenue for fiscal 2007 declined 2.1 percent, to $77.35 billion. A spokesman, Ron DeFeo, said that was the first annual sales decline for Home Depot. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 8.3 percent in the quarter. The company’s average sales ticket declined 2.3 percent, to $54.96 in the quarter, compared with $56.27 a year ago. For all of 2007, Home Depot said it earned $4.4 billion, or $2.37 a share, compared with a profit of $5.76 billion, or $2.79 a share, for 2006. Its $77.35 billion in sales for the year compared with $79.02 billion a year earlier. Lowe’s reported Monday that its fourth-quarter profit dropped by a third. But it predicted that sales  while still hurt by a soft housing market  would improve slightly in 2008.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/26/business/26lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Soft Housing Market Sends Lowe’s Profit Down by a Third<date>Published: February 26, 2008</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies, the nation’s second-biggest home improvement retailer, said Monday that a softer housing market helped drive its fourth-quarter earnings down 33.4 percent. The company said it also expected sales to drop at least 5 percent in the current quarter and for the year. But that would be an improvement over the 7.6 percent decline in the fourth quarter. Lowe’s shares rose 91 cents, to $24.50. David S. Strasser, an analyst for Banc of America Securities, wrote in a client note, “These are bad numbers, but quite frankly, based on our conversations the last few weeks, they are not much worse than what we believe was the weak buy-side expectations.” In a conference call, Lowe’s chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said that slowing home sales, lower home prices and a tightening of credit standards had all combined to hurt consumer spending on big-ticket items. The fourth quarter is also seasonally the weakest for home-improvement retailers, Mr. Niblock said, as colder weather results in few building and renovation projects. Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., said profit in the period that ended Feb. 1 fell to $408 million, or 28 cents a share, from $613 million, or 40 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales remained virtually steady at just under $10.4 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 25 cents a share on revenue of $10.85 billion. Estimates usually exclude one-time items. Same-store sales  a closely watched gauge that measures sales at stores open at least a year  declined 7.6 percent for the fourth quarter. Mr. Niblock said the company would “remain focused on what we can control.” The company expects first-quarter sales to rise about 2 percent, with earnings of 38 cents to 42 cents a share. Analysts have forecast earnings of 43 cents a share. Lowe’s and its bigger rival, Home Depot, which is expected to post fourth-quarter numbers Tuesday, have experienced a slide in profits as a slump in the housing industry continues. For the year, Lowe’s reported earnings of $2.8 billion, or $1.86 a share, compared with $3.1 billion, or $1.99 a share, in 2007. Revenue rose to $48.3 billion from $46.9 billion a year ago. More Articles in Business »CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies, the nation’s second-biggest home improvement retailer, said Monday that a softer housing market helped drive its fourth-quarter earnings down 33.4 percent. The company said it also expected sales to drop at least 5 percent in the current quarter and for the year. But that would be an improvement over the 7.6 percent decline in the fourth quarter. Lowe’s shares rose 91 cents, to $24.50. David S. Strasser, an analyst for Banc of America Securities, wrote in a client note, “These are bad numbers, but quite frankly, based on our conversations the last few weeks, they are not much worse than what we believe was the weak buy-side expectations.” In a conference call, Lowe’s chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said that slowing home sales, lower home prices and a tightening of credit standards had all combined to hurt consumer spending on big-ticket items. The fourth quarter is also seasonally the weakest for home-improvement retailers, Mr. Niblock said, as colder weather results in few building and renovation projects. Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., said profit in the period that ended Feb. 1 fell to $408 million, or 28 cents a share, from $613 million, or 40 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales remained virtually steady at just under $10.4 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 25 cents a share on revenue of $10.85 billion. Estimates usually exclude one-time items. Same-store sales  a closely watched gauge that measures sales at stores open at least a year  declined 7.6 percent for the fourth quarter. Mr. Niblock said the company would “remain focused on what we can control.” The company expects first-quarter sales to rise about 2 percent, with earnings of 38 cents to 42 cents a share. Analysts have forecast earnings of 43 cents a share. Lowe’s and its bigger rival, Home Depot, which is expected to post fourth-quarter numbers Tuesday, have experienced a slide in profits as a slump in the housing industry continues. For the year, Lowe’s reported earnings of $2.8 billion, or $1.86 a share, compared with $3.1 billion, or $1.99 a share, in 2007. Revenue rose to $48.3 billion from $46.9 billion a year ago.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/20/business/20lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Home Slump Hurts Lowe’s as Earnings Decline 10%<date>Published: November 20, 2007</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 19 (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies, the nation’s second-largest home improvement chain, said Monday that its third-quarter profit fell 10.2 percent, citing a weak sales environment amid a continuing slump in the housing sector. The company suggested an industry recovery would not occur in early 2008, as it sharply cut its outlook for the fourth quarter and the full year. It has been a tough quarter for home-improvement retailers. Home Depot, the larger rival of Lowe’s, reported a 27 percent drop in third-quarter earnings last week and cut its full-year outlook, citing the persistent housing slump. In a conference call with analysts, Lowe’s chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, blamed slowing home sales, lower home prices and tightening of credit standards, all of which hurt consumer spending on big-ticket items. “Based on our results and the significant losses and write-downs announced this quarter in the banking and mortgage industries,” Mr. Niblock said, “it’s clear that the pressures on our industry and the home improvement consumer are greater than we previously anticipated and are likely to last longer than we expected.” Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., said it earned $643 million, or 43 cents a share, for the three months that ended Nov. 2, compared with $716 million, or 46 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $11.57 billion from $11.21 billion. Sales in stores open at least one year, a main measure of industry performance, fell 4.3 percent. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 41 cents a share on revenue of $12.4 billion. Lowe’s expects to earn 25 cents to 29 cents a share for the fourth quarter. Analysts were expecting earnings of 36 cents a share. Shares of Lowe’s declined $1.89, or 7.6 percent, to $23.12. More Articles in Business »CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 19 (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies, the nation’s second-largest home improvement chain, said Monday that its third-quarter profit fell 10.2 percent, citing a weak sales environment amid a continuing slump in the housing sector. The company suggested an industry recovery would not occur in early 2008, as it sharply cut its outlook for the fourth quarter and the full year. It has been a tough quarter for home-improvement retailers. Home Depot, the larger rival of Lowe’s, reported a 27 percent drop in third-quarter earnings last week and cut its full-year outlook, citing the persistent housing slump. In a conference call with analysts, Lowe’s chairman and chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, blamed slowing home sales, lower home prices and tightening of credit standards, all of which hurt consumer spending on big-ticket items. “Based on our results and the significant losses and write-downs announced this quarter in the banking and mortgage industries,” Mr. Niblock said, “it’s clear that the pressures on our industry and the home improvement consumer are greater than we previously anticipated and are likely to last longer than we expected.” Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., said it earned $643 million, or 43 cents a share, for the three months that ended Nov. 2, compared with $716 million, or 46 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $11.57 billion from $11.21 billion. Sales in stores open at least one year, a main measure of industry performance, fell 4.3 percent. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 41 cents a share on revenue of $12.4 billion. Lowe’s expects to earn 25 cents to 29 cents a share for the fourth quarter. Analysts were expecting earnings of 36 cents a share. Shares of Lowe’s declined $1.89, or 7.6 percent, to $23.12.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/25/business/25lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Tempers Its Profit Forecast<date>Published: September 25, 2007</date><text>ATLANTA, Sept. 24 (Reuters)  Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement chain, warned on Monday that its full-year profit could trail its previous forecast, saying dry conditions in some parts of the United States were hurting sales of outdoor products. The company’s shares fell as much as 5 percent in extended trading. Lowe’s, which is holding its analyst meeting on Tuesday, said current sales were trending below expectations because of drought in the mid-Atlantic, Southeastern and Western parts of the United States. As a result, Lowe’s, which is the second-largest home improvement chain after Home Depot, said it now expected profit for the year ending in February to be at the low end or below a forecast of $1.97 to $2.01 a share it gave in August. Analysts currently expect a profit of $1.99 a share for the current year, flat with earnings of $1.99 the year before, according to Reuters Estimates. Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., is expanding to big cities like New York and is set to open its first stores in Canada later this year. It expects average growth of 12 percent to 15 percent in profit per share each year from 2008 through 2010, while total sales rise 8 percent to 11 percent a year during that time. Lower home sales and less construction have hurt results at Lowe’s and Home Depot over the last year. More Articles in Business »ATLANTA, Sept. 24 (Reuters)  Lowe’s Companies, the home improvement chain, warned on Monday that its full-year profit could trail its previous forecast, saying dry conditions in some parts of the United States were hurting sales of outdoor products. The company’s shares fell as much as 5 percent in extended trading. Lowe’s, which is holding its analyst meeting on Tuesday, said current sales were trending below expectations because of drought in the mid-Atlantic, Southeastern and Western parts of the United States. As a result, Lowe’s, which is the second-largest home improvement chain after Home Depot, said it now expected profit for the year ending in February to be at the low end or below a forecast of $1.97 to $2.01 a share it gave in August. Analysts currently expect a profit of $1.99 a share for the current year, flat with earnings of $1.99 the year before, according to Reuters Estimates. Lowe’s, based in Mooresville, N.C., is expanding to big cities like New York and is set to open its first stores in Canada later this year. It expects average growth of 12 percent to 15 percent in profit per share each year from 2008 through 2010, while total sales rise 8 percent to 11 percent a year during that time. Lower home sales and less construction have hurt results at Lowe’s and Home Depot over the last year.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/21/business/21lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Reports Rise in Profit, Despite Woes in Housing<date>Published: August 21, 2007</date><text>ATLANTA, Aug. 20 (Reuters)  The Lowes Companies reported a higher-than-expected second-quarter profit and a gain in market share on Monday, saying that sales trends were improving in some regions despite the soft housing market. Lowes sees pockets of strength, and I think thats a bullish signal because lots of investors feared that nobody could pinpoint the bottom of this housing market, said Stephanie Hoff, senior retail analyst with Edward Jones in St. Louis. The company, which ranks second behind Home Depot in home improvement retailing, said it faced easier sales comparisons, but it still cut its full-year outlook. Earnings for the second quarter, which ended Aug. 3, rose 9 percent, to $1.02 billion, or 67 cents a share, from $935 million, or 60 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had expected 61 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Lowes said gross margin improved in the quarter on better management of imported products and distribution. Sales rose 5.8 percent, to $14.17 billion, aided by the opening of 26 stores. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 2.6 percent, in line with the companys expectations of a drop of as much as 3 percent. While falling sales and prices for homes and the troubles in the subprime mortgage market have pressured the home improvement sector, Lowes turned in better results than Home Depot, which said last week that quarterly earnings fell 15 percent on a 2 percent sales drop. Home Depot mentioned that they continue to lose market share but at a declining rate, said Sarah Henry, an analyst with MFC Global Investment Management in Berwyn, Pa., which owns stock in both chains. Lowes said that they have continued to gain market share. More Articles in Business »ATLANTA, Aug. 20 (Reuters)  The Lowes Companies reported a higher-than-expected second-quarter profit and a gain in market share on Monday, saying that sales trends were improving in some regions despite the soft housing market. Lowes sees pockets of strength, and I think thats a bullish signal because lots of investors feared that nobody could pinpoint the bottom of this housing market, said Stephanie Hoff, senior retail analyst with Edward Jones in St. Louis. The company, which ranks second behind Home Depot in home improvement retailing, said it faced easier sales comparisons, but it still cut its full-year outlook. Earnings for the second quarter, which ended Aug. 3, rose 9 percent, to $1.02 billion, or 67 cents a share, from $935 million, or 60 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had expected 61 cents a share, according to Reuters Estimates. Lowes said gross margin improved in the quarter on better management of imported products and distribution. Sales rose 5.8 percent, to $14.17 billion, aided by the opening of 26 stores. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 2.6 percent, in line with the companys expectations of a drop of as much as 3 percent. While falling sales and prices for homes and the troubles in the subprime mortgage market have pressured the home improvement sector, Lowes turned in better results than Home Depot, which said last week that quarterly earnings fell 15 percent on a 2 percent sales drop. Home Depot mentioned that they continue to lose market share but at a declining rate, said Sarah Henry, an analyst with MFC Global Investment Management in Berwyn, Pa., which owns stock in both chains. Lowes said that they have continued to gain market share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D8133EF93BA35754C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">The Week; Lowe's Completes Deal To Buy Catering Hall<date>Published: July 8, 2007</date><text>After months of delays, Lowe's Home Improvement has completed a deal for the Huntington Townhouse in Huntington Station and will open its fifth Long Island store on the site. Long Island Business News reported the sale price at $35 million. Chris Ahearn, a spokeswoman for Lowe's, would not confirm the price. The deal for the longtime catering hall was completed June 20. Rhona Silver, the owner, considered turning the catering hall into a development of condos before negotiations with Lowe's were fruitful. The 148,000-square-foot Huntington Townhouse, with its manicured grounds and waterfalls, was a popular site for weddings, bar and bat mitzvahs, sweet 16 parties and corporate and charity events. The last events at the Townhouse were held at the end of March. Ms. Ahearn said that Lowe's had been looking to expand on Long Island and that it identified the 18-acre site in Huntington Station as a good location. Its other stores on the Island are in Farmingdale, Bay Shore, Garden City and Medford. Ms. Ahearn said it typically took 18 months to open a store. The new Lowe's will be a 117,000-square-foot store, with about 175 employees, she said, and its size will be consistent with the company's other stores on the Island. Photo: New Owner Huntington Townhouse, a catering hall in Huntington Station, was bought by Lowe's, the home improvement retailer. (Photograph by Barton Silverman/The New York Times)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DD1F31F931A15756C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Rolls Back Its Annual Outlook After Profit Declines<date>Published: May 22, 2007</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the No. 2 home improvement chain, reported a lower-than-expected first-quarter profit and pared its full-year earnings forecast yesterday as the slower housing market pressured sales. Earnings came to $739 million, or 48 cents a share, down 12 percent from $841 million, or 53 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts expected Lowe's, which ranks behind Home Depot among home improvement chains, to earn 49 cents a share. ''While Lowe's still has more room to grow than Home Depot, it is increasingly competing for the same customer in a decelerating retail environment,'' said Jon Fisher, a portfolio manager for Fifth Third Asset Management. Sales in the period, which ended May 4, rose 2 percent, to $12.2 billion, helped by 15 store openings, but fell short of the $12.5 billion analysts had expected. Sales at stores open at least a year fell 6.3 percent, worse than Lowe's forecast of a 2 percent to 4 percent decline. In a statement, Lowe's said the weaker housing market, comparisons with year-earlier sales that were increased by hurricane rebuilding efforts and falling lumber prices hurt results. It also said cold and wet weather in April contributed to lower-than-anticipated sales. The company said consumers were taking on fewer high-ticket projects like kitchen remodeling, and said the weakest markets were in California, Florida and the Northeast. Stock in Lowe's, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., fell 79 cents, to $31.88 a share, in regular trading. Lowe's forecast full-year profit of $1.99 to $2.03 a share, down from its forecast made in February of $2.02 to $2.09 a share.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/24/business/24lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Profit and Sales Off at Lowe’s as Housing Slump Continues<date>Published: February 24, 2007</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., Feb. 23 (AP)  Profit at the Lowe’s Companies fell 11.5 percent in the fourth quarter, but beat analysts’ expectations. The company, based in Mooresville, N.C., said it earned $613 million, or 40 cents a share, down from $693 million, or 43 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended Feb. 2, fell 3.7 percent, to $10.4 billion from $10.8 billion a year earlier. Sales in stores open at least one year, known as same-store sales, fell 5.3 percent. The company, which opened 58 stores in the quarter, had expected same-store sales to decline 4 percent to 6 percent for the quarter. The drop in sales was a result of a slowing housing market, significant deflation in lumber and plywood prices and tough comparisons with last year, when rebuilding efforts were under way after a damaging hurricane season, the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. “There has been a slowdown in the major-renovation-type stuff,” Mr. Niblock said. “It’s nothing we haven’t seen before. People will start getting back to life as normal.” The profit was better than the 37 cents a share expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Shares of Lowe’s rose $1.30, to $34.93. Lowe’s said it planned to open 150 to 160 stores this year and expected its sales to increase 5 to 6 percent in the first quarter and 10 percent over the full year. Some analysts said Friday that Lowe’s might have borne the worst of a slowdown from the slumping housing sector. “Yes, it does appear that the worst is behind them,” said Stephanie Hoff, senior retail analyst with Edward Jones. “I think the question going forward though is how rapidly can we travel down that road to recovery.” A Banc of America Securities analyst, David S. Strasser, wrote in a research note: “Lowe’s indicated its sales trends appear to have bottomed. That is encouraging as our buy thesis has been predicated on a first-half bottoming and second-half recovery.” More Articles in Business »CHARLOTTE, N.C., Feb. 23 (AP)  Profit at the Lowe’s Companies fell 11.5 percent in the fourth quarter, but beat analysts’ expectations. The company, based in Mooresville, N.C., said it earned $613 million, or 40 cents a share, down from $693 million, or 43 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended Feb. 2, fell 3.7 percent, to $10.4 billion from $10.8 billion a year earlier. Sales in stores open at least one year, known as same-store sales, fell 5.3 percent. The company, which opened 58 stores in the quarter, had expected same-store sales to decline 4 percent to 6 percent for the quarter. The drop in sales was a result of a slowing housing market, significant deflation in lumber and plywood prices and tough comparisons with last year, when rebuilding efforts were under way after a damaging hurricane season, the chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. “There has been a slowdown in the major-renovation-type stuff,” Mr. Niblock said. “It’s nothing we haven’t seen before. People will start getting back to life as normal.” The profit was better than the 37 cents a share expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Shares of Lowe’s rose $1.30, to $34.93. Lowe’s said it planned to open 150 to 160 stores this year and expected its sales to increase 5 to 6 percent in the first quarter and 10 percent over the full year. Some analysts said Friday that Lowe’s might have borne the worst of a slowdown from the slumping housing sector. “Yes, it does appear that the worst is behind them,” said Stephanie Hoff, senior retail analyst with Edward Jones. “I think the question going forward though is how rapidly can we travel down that road to recovery.” A Banc of America Securities analyst, David S. Strasser, wrote in a research note: “Lowe’s indicated its sales trends appear to have bottomed. That is encouraging as our buy thesis has been predicated on a first-half bottoming and second-half recovery.”</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/13/business/13home.html?ref=lowescompanies">Home Depot May Shed Unit to Focus on Retail<date>Published: February 13, 2007</date><text>Shortly after Robert L. Nardelli was deposed as chief executive of Home Depot, several of the countrys biggest buyout firms welcomed the companys new leader, Frank Blake, with a tantalizing proposal, according to people briefed on the matter. Skip to next paragraph Related Home Depot Gets a Fresh Coat of Less-Glossy Paint (February 8, 2007) Shareholders Expect Big Changes After Ousting of C.E.O. (January 10, 2007) They would consider buying the retailers $12 billion wholesale supply business, which Wall Street thought was a poor fit for a home improvement chain, removing a liability from the Nardelli era and allowing Mr. Blake to focus on Home Depots 2,000 stores. It was an offer too good to refuse. Yesterday, Home Depot said it would consider selling the supply division, a network of companies that provides pipes, concrete and lumber to professional builders. Analysts estimate that it could fetch $9 billion. Now comes the hard part: reviving Home Depot without its fastest-growing business. Home Depot is running out of room to build new stores in the United States, which is why, in 2000, Mr. Nardelli began cobbling together Home Depot Supply. The new business never won over analysts or shareholders, who did not understand how it would help turn around slumping store sales, but the supply division provided $12 billion in revenue that will be hard to replace by selling more paint brushes and light bulbs. Now Home Depots future rests with its stores  where sales have been trailing those of its rival Lowes and customers routinely complain about a less than stellar shopping experience. It will definitely be a challenge, said Mark J. Rowen, an analyst at Prudential Securities. Part of the reason they created supply was because they did not know how to grow the retail business. The task for Home Depot executives now is to quickly improve employee morale, customer service and, eventually, store sales enough to lift the companys stock out of the doldrums. The stock, which traded at more than $50 in 2002, closed yesterday at $41.44, up 1 percent on news of the possible sale of the supply business. To overhaul its stores, Home Depot has set up five committees to study what it considers weak spots. One is called shopping environment, and another product availability. The associate engagement committee has already scored a victory with employees: a $3,000 fund for each store to be used to reward workers with holiday parties and spontaneous outings. But winning over workers will get Home Depot only so far. Lowes has snatched away customers, the housing market is weak and Home Depots reputation has suffered because of Mr. Nardellis decision to cut employee hours over the last six years. The supply business, for all its problems, gave Home Depot a soft cushion to fall back on. So why sell it? For one, it does not provide as high a profit margin as the retail business, and the cost savings expected from synergies  because the chain could order products like wood in bulk for its supply and retail divisions  did not materialize as quickly as executives had hoped. To exploit those cost savings, Home Depot would now have to start weaving together the supply and retail business, setting up one information technology system and rewriting supplier agreements to apply to both. Senior Home Depot executives have determined that integration could prove costly and distracting, dragging down the retail business even further, according to the people briefed on the matter who are not authorized to discuss it. It would be a lot of heavy lifting, said a person with direct knowledge of the internal debate over the future of the supply business. The company said it had hired Lehman Brothers to weigh whether it should sell Home Depot Supply, spin it off or take it public. For Mr. Blake, the prospect of selling the supply business had another attraction: it would serve as a strong declaration of independence from Mr. Nardelli, who spent $7 billion building the unit. Mr. Nardelli was ousted over his generous pay package and authoritarian management style  a legacy Mr. Blake is eager to distance himself from. In the last 40 days, since he was named chief executive, Mr. Blake has begun to quietly dismantle Mr. Nardellis Home Depot. He has nudged out several of Mr. Nardellis hand-picked deputies, eliminated perks like a free executive lunch and reached out to Home Depots revered founders, Arthur Blank and Bernard Marcus. In conversations with analysts and shareholders, Mr. Blake has said he wants to return Home Depot to its roots as a retailer  the Home Depot before Mr. Nardelli  a sentiment echoed in the chains statement yesterday about the potential sale of the supply business. We are undertaking this action, it said, because of our desire to increase our focus on our retail business. More Articles in Business »Shortly after Robert L. Nardelli was deposed as chief executive of Home Depot, several of the countrys biggest buyout firms welcomed the companys new leader, Frank Blake, with a tantalizing proposal, according to people briefed on the matter. Skip to next paragraph Related Home Depot Gets a Fresh Coat of Less-Glossy Paint (February 8, 2007) Shareholders Expect Big Changes After Ousting of C.E.O. (January 10, 2007) They would consider buying the retailers $12 billion wholesale supply business, which Wall Street thought was a poor fit for a home improvement chain, removing a liability from the Nardelli era and allowing Mr. Blake to focus on Home Depots 2,000 stores. It was an offer too good to refuse. Yesterday, Home Depot said it would consider selling the supply division, a network of companies that provides pipes, concrete and lumber to professional builders. Analysts estimate that it could fetch $9 billion. Now comes the hard part: reviving Home Depot without its fastest-growing business. Home Depot is running out of room to build new stores in the United States, which is why, in 2000, Mr. Nardelli began cobbling together Home Depot Supply. The new business never won over analysts or shareholders, who did not understand how it would help turn around slumping store sales, but the supply division provided $12 billion in revenue that will be hard to replace by selling more paint brushes and light bulbs. Now Home Depots future rests with its stores  where sales have been trailing those of its rival Lowes and customers routinely complain about a less than stellar shopping experience. It will definitely be a challenge, said Mark J. Rowen, an analyst at Prudential Securities. Part of the reason they created supply was because they did not know how to grow the retail business. The task for Home Depot executives now is to quickly improve employee morale, customer service and, eventually, store sales enough to lift the companys stock out of the doldrums. The stock, which traded at more than $50 in 2002, closed yesterday at $41.44, up 1 percent on news of the possible sale of the supply business. To overhaul its stores, Home Depot has set up five committees to study what it considers weak spots. One is called shopping environment, and another product availability. The associate engagement committee has already scored a victory with employees: a $3,000 fund for each store to be used to reward workers with holiday parties and spontaneous outings. But winning over workers will get Home Depot only so far. Lowes has snatched away customers, the housing market is weak and Home Depots reputation has suffered because of Mr. Nardellis decision to cut employee hours over the last six years. The supply business, for all its problems, gave Home Depot a soft cushion to fall back on. So why sell it? For one, it does not provide as high a profit margin as the retail business, and the cost savings expected from synergies  because the chain could order products like wood in bulk for its supply and retail divisions  did not materialize as quickly as executives had hoped. To exploit those cost savings, Home Depot would now have to start weaving together the supply and retail business, setting up one information technology system and rewriting supplier agreements to apply to both. Senior Home Depot executives have determined that integration could prove costly and distracting, dragging down the retail business even further, according to the people briefed on the matter who are not authorized to discuss it. It would be a lot of heavy lifting, said a person with direct knowledge of the internal debate over the future of the supply business. The company said it had hired Lehman Brothers to weigh whether it should sell Home Depot Supply, spin it off or take it public. For Mr. Blake, the prospect of selling the supply business had another attraction: it would serve as a strong declaration of independence from Mr. Nardelli, who spent $7 billion building the unit. Mr. Nardelli was ousted over his generous pay package and authoritarian management style  a legacy Mr. Blake is eager to distance himself from. In the last 40 days, since he was named chief executive, Mr. Blake has begun to quietly dismantle Mr. Nardellis Home Depot. He has nudged out several of Mr. Nardellis hand-picked deputies, eliminated perks like a free executive lunch and reached out to Home Depots revered founders, Arthur Blank and Bernard Marcus. In conversations with analysts and shareholders, Mr. Blake has said he wants to return Home Depot to its roots as a retailer  the Home Depot before Mr. Nardelli  a sentiment echoed in the chains statement yesterday about the potential sale of the supply business. We are undertaking this action, it said, because of our desire to increase our focus on our retail business.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/21/business/21lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Warning Taken in Stride<date>Published: November 21, 2006</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 20  Lowes, the nations second-largest home-improvement retailer, reported an increase in third-quarter profit of nearly 11 percent on Monday and warned that its fourth-quarter results would be weaker than expected. But investors sent the shares higher. One analyst said investors appeared to be looking beyond the slowing housing market. The point is, everyone knows about the economic bad news; now its time to look forward, a senior retail analyst with Edward Jones, Stephanie Hoff, said. This time next year we should see a rebound. Lowes shares rose 10 cents, to close at $30.58. The company said it earned $716 million, or 46 cents a share, for the three months that ended Nov. 3, up from $646 million, or 40 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $11.2 billion from $10.6 billion a year earlier. But sales in stores open at least one year, or same-store sales, a crucial indicator of industry performance, fell 4 percent. A UBS analyst, Brian Nagel, said in a research note, Much slower sales trends at Lowes lately do not bode well for prospects for the company over the next several quarters. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 43 cents a share on revenue of $11.49 billion. Still, net income was down from the $935 million reported in the second quarter as home improvement chains faced pressure from the weakening housing market. For the fourth quarter, Lowes expects a 4 percent decline in sales from last years $10.8 billion, implying sales of $10.37 billion and missing analysts revenue expectations of $10.8 billion. Lowes and its larger rival, Home Depot, benefited from strong American home sales and hurricane-related demand a year ago, but now face difficult comparisons as the housing market cools. More Articles in Business »CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 20  Lowes, the nations second-largest home-improvement retailer, reported an increase in third-quarter profit of nearly 11 percent on Monday and warned that its fourth-quarter results would be weaker than expected. But investors sent the shares higher. One analyst said investors appeared to be looking beyond the slowing housing market. The point is, everyone knows about the economic bad news; now its time to look forward, a senior retail analyst with Edward Jones, Stephanie Hoff, said. This time next year we should see a rebound. Lowes shares rose 10 cents, to close at $30.58. The company said it earned $716 million, or 46 cents a share, for the three months that ended Nov. 3, up from $646 million, or 40 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $11.2 billion from $10.6 billion a year earlier. But sales in stores open at least one year, or same-store sales, a crucial indicator of industry performance, fell 4 percent. A UBS analyst, Brian Nagel, said in a research note, Much slower sales trends at Lowes lately do not bode well for prospects for the company over the next several quarters. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had been looking for net income of 43 cents a share on revenue of $11.49 billion. Still, net income was down from the $935 million reported in the second quarter as home improvement chains faced pressure from the weakening housing market. For the fourth quarter, Lowes expects a 4 percent decline in sales from last years $10.8 billion, implying sales of $10.37 billion and missing analysts revenue expectations of $10.8 billion. Lowes and its larger rival, Home Depot, benefited from strong American home sales and hurricane-related demand a year ago, but now face difficult comparisons as the housing market cools.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/05/realestate/05habi.html?ref=lowescompanies">Living Small, but Living Well<date>Published: November 5, 2006</date><text>MARIANNE CUSATOS apartment is small (11 by 28 feet) and architecturally uninspired. But ask her where she lives, and shell light up as she describes the spot: the corner of Perry and West Fourth Streets, in what may well be the quaintest part of Greenwich Village. For what she pays in rent  $1,785 a month  she could have more space in another location, she said, but I would rather live here than in a bigger apartment somewhere else. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Marianne Cusato Lowes will sell two of her cottage designs as kits, including the salmon one. Because, if Ms. Cusato doesnt have great architecture, she feels as though she does. From her fifth-floor window, she looks out across the street at the cornices of two buildings, which, as a classically trained architect, she can describe in detail. This ones Doric; that ones Corinthian, she said, pointing to the architraves, metopes, triglyphs and other features derived from the parts of Greek temples. The proximity to classical architecture, and the promise of street life whenever she exits the building, keep Ms. Cusato feeling connected, both to history and to community, she said. Ms. Cusatos belief  that even a small space can feel expansive, if its part of something larger  has informed what has become her most important project thus far: designing a series of tiny houses for victims of Hurricane Katrina. Early next year, Lowes, the home improvement chain, is to begin selling two of her Katrina Cottages as kits. A buyer will be able to acquire everything needed to build a house, from the ceiling trusses down to the last can of paint, in a single transaction. Prices will begin at about $45 a square foot, or $27,000 for the smallest cottage, according to Jennifer Wilson, a spokeswoman for Lowes, which is based in Mooresville, N.C. The prices do not include the foundation or heating and cooling equipment, which vary too much from place to place to be included in the kits, according to David Steed, Lowes senior vice president for merchandising of building materials. Mr. Steed added: Marianne is the hero of the whole thing, going back to when the storm first hit. Now that Congress has appropriated $400 million for alternatives to the ubiquitous FEMA trailers, there is a possibility that her cottages will become as popular as the Levittown houses were after World War II. But unlike Levittown houses, which were largely unadorned, Ms. Cusatos cottages make an extra effort to incorporate historical detailing. More than 90 percent of residential architecture in this country is traditional, Ms. Cusato said, and that suits her fine. Growing up in Alaska in the 1980s, she disliked much of the development she saw. Around age 12, she recalled, she announced that I want to be architect, but I wont do strip malls. Ms. Cusato, now 32, studied architecture at the University of Notre Dame, where students learn, and draw, the components of classical architecture. After graduation, while working for an architecture firm in Charlotte, N.C., she formed a relationship with Andrés Duany, the designer of New Urbanist towns across the country. Through Mr. Duany, she met the British architect Leon Krier, with whom she has collaborated on a forthcoming book, Get Your House Right: How to Avoid Common Mistakes in Todays Traditional Architecture (Sterling Publishing). The volume is meant to show people how to design houses, of any size, with appropriately scaled details, Ms. Cusato said. In 1999, she moved to New York  a place she had always wanted to live, she said  and took a job at Fairfax &amp; Sammons, designers of expensive homes with classical detailing. That job, she said, gave her important experience she can now apply to creating affordable housing  her real lifes goal. As she puts it, You need to know the rules before you know which ones to break. Her chance came in 2005. Days after Katrina, Mr. Duany was drafted by Haley Barbour, the governor of Mississippi, to provide advice on how to rebuild devastated coastal cities. Mr. Duany invited a team of architects to spend part of October with him in Biloxi. During that time, Ms. Cusato sketched what became her first Katrina Cottage. Three months later, Mr. Duany got a chance to display a prototype at the International Builders Show in Orlando, Fla. Some of the New Urbanist proposals have been controversial, but the cottage was a hit. People fell in love with it, Mr. Duany said. One reason, he said, is that Ms. Cusatos cottages  unlike their prefabricated competitors  dont have to be designed to fit on trucks. Having to put a house on a truck pretty much guarantees bad proportions, Mr. Duany said. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Real Estate »MARIANNE CUSATOS apartment is small (11 by 28 feet) and architecturally uninspired. But ask her where she lives, and shell light up as she describes the spot: the corner of Perry and West Fourth Streets, in what may well be the quaintest part of Greenwich Village. For what she pays in rent  $1,785 a month  she could have more space in another location, she said, but I would rather live here than in a bigger apartment somewhere else. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Marianne Cusato Lowes will sell two of her cottage designs as kits, including the salmon one. Because, if Ms. Cusato doesnt have great architecture, she feels as though she does. From her fifth-floor window, she looks out across the street at the cornices of two buildings, which, as a classically trained architect, she can describe in detail. This ones Doric; that ones Corinthian, she said, pointing to the architraves, metopes, triglyphs and other features derived from the parts of Greek temples. The proximity to classical architecture, and the promise of street life whenever she exits the building, keep Ms. Cusato feeling connected, both to history and to community, she said. Ms. Cusatos belief  that even a small space can feel expansive, if its part of something larger  has informed what has become her most important project thus far: designing a series of tiny houses for victims of Hurricane Katrina. Early next year, Lowes, the home improvement chain, is to begin selling two of her Katrina Cottages as kits. A buyer will be able to acquire everything needed to build a house, from the ceiling trusses down to the last can of paint, in a single transaction. Prices will begin at about $45 a square foot, or $27,000 for the smallest cottage, according to Jennifer Wilson, a spokeswoman for Lowes, which is based in Mooresville, N.C. The prices do not include the foundation or heating and cooling equipment, which vary too much from place to place to be included in the kits, according to David Steed, Lowes senior vice president for merchandising of building materials. Mr. Steed added: Marianne is the hero of the whole thing, going back to when the storm first hit. Now that Congress has appropriated $400 million for alternatives to the ubiquitous FEMA trailers, there is a possibility that her cottages will become as popular as the Levittown houses were after World War II. But unlike Levittown houses, which were largely unadorned, Ms. Cusatos cottages make an extra effort to incorporate historical detailing. More than 90 percent of residential architecture in this country is traditional, Ms. Cusato said, and that suits her fine. Growing up in Alaska in the 1980s, she disliked much of the development she saw. Around age 12, she recalled, she announced that I want to be architect, but I wont do strip malls. Ms. Cusato, now 32, studied architecture at the University of Notre Dame, where students learn, and draw, the components of classical architecture. After graduation, while working for an architecture firm in Charlotte, N.C., she formed a relationship with Andrés Duany, the designer of New Urbanist towns across the country. Through Mr. Duany, she met the British architect Leon Krier, with whom she has collaborated on a forthcoming book, Get Your House Right: How to Avoid Common Mistakes in Todays Traditional Architecture (Sterling Publishing). The volume is meant to show people how to design houses, of any size, with appropriately scaled details, Ms. Cusato said. In 1999, she moved to New York  a place she had always wanted to live, she said  and took a job at Fairfax &amp; Sammons, designers of expensive homes with classical detailing. That job, she said, gave her important experience she can now apply to creating affordable housing  her real lifes goal. As she puts it, You need to know the rules before you know which ones to break. Her chance came in 2005. Days after Katrina, Mr. Duany was drafted by Haley Barbour, the governor of Mississippi, to provide advice on how to rebuild devastated coastal cities. Mr. Duany invited a team of architects to spend part of October with him in Biloxi. During that time, Ms. Cusato sketched what became her first Katrina Cottage. Three months later, Mr. Duany got a chance to display a prototype at the International Builders Show in Orlando, Fla. Some of the New Urbanist proposals have been controversial, but the cottage was a hit. People fell in love with it, Mr. Duany said. One reason, he said, is that Ms. Cusatos cottages  unlike their prefabricated competitors  dont have to be designed to fit on trucks. Having to put a house on a truck pretty much guarantees bad proportions, Mr. Duany said. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/29/business/yourmoney/29women.html?ref=lowescompanies">What Do Women Want? Just Ask<date>Published: October 29, 2006</date><text>FOR most of the 27 years it has been in business in Canada, Shane Homes has staked its claim as one of the countrys leading regional homebuilders the old-fashioned way: it devised and executed cookie-cutter designs for new houses just as fast as the orders came in. As the economy of its home base, Calgary, Alberta, soared on the back of oil and gas riches, it could have continued minting money by sticking with that tried-and-true approach. But two years ago, smack in the middle of a housing boom and heightened competition, Shane Homes dumped its old ways and adopted a new blueprint. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Women's Earnings Related Highlights of Womens Earnings in 2005 (PDF From the Department of Labor) Shane Homes AskPatty.com BeJane.com Boston Gal's Open Wallet My Open Wallet Crave Party Enlarge This Image Ken McCurdy for Shane Homes A focus group joined Shane Wenzel, third from right, of Shane Homes; Joanne Thomas Yaccato, a consultant; and Cal Wenzel, right, the companys chief executive, at a home in Calgary, Alberta. The groups suggestions were used in the homes design. The overhaul began at a real estate conference in 2003, when Shane Wenzel, the builders namesake and its head of sales and marketing, heard a speech about the tremendous buying power of women. That moment, Mr. Wenzel recalled, was an epiphany. He set up small listening groups of women to tap into the needs of people who actually lived in his companys homes. What Mr. Wenzel heard wasnt pretty. The ladies never held back once, he said. They were brutally honest. The kitchens in the companys homes, the women said, were all wrong. The pantries were tiny, and the sinks needed to overlook a window so kids in the backyard could be monitored. And the mudrooms! They shared space with laundry rooms, meaning that dirty floors might sit right beneath clean laundry. (Its called a mud/laundry room? one incredulous woman asked.) After that, Shane Homes subjected designs to similar grillings  before they were built  and adapted them accordingly. Shane Homes had the revolutionary idea of asking women what they wanted in a home, said Joanne Thomas Yaccato, a Toronto consultant and author who advised the company on female consumers. The revolutionary part is that they not only listened, they actually built the darn thing. Shane Homes is hardly alone. More companies, in the United States and elsewhere, have realized that they overlook women at their own financial peril. The companies are realigning their marketing and design practices, learning to court an increasingly female-centric consumer base that boasts more financial muscle and purchasing independence than ever before. We are perhaps on the first step to a matriarchal society; women will earn more money than men if current trends continue by 2028, said Michael J. Silverstein of the Boston Consulting Group. The trend has been escalating in the last 10 years as there has been a gradual, slow erosion of the power balance in the family, a psychic rebalancing. Women, Mr. Silverstein added, are controlling purchases and driving a shift in our economy. Retailers like Home Depot, Lowes, Sears, Best Buy and others recognize that women are running their households like purchasing managers. Some are identifying stores that have more female shoppers and offering additional services, including sales support, customized signs and special product displays, said Dana L. Telsey, who runs her own independent research firm. Travel companies, automakers, and other companies, meanwhile, have had to cater to the tastes of women who have careers outside the home and are pursuing hobbies and other pricey interests. The phenomenon is readily apparent on the Internet, where Web sites built around the needs and interests of such groups as female homeowners and car buyers have gained steady traction. Much of that shift has to do with education and pay. At American colleges and universities, women represent 57 percent of undergraduate classes and 58 percent of graduate classes, according to the American Council on Education. (They also hold a slight majority in the overall population.) And education, in turn, has helped to bolster salaries and income. In 2005, government data show, women who were full-time wage and salary workers had median weekly earnings of $585, or 81 percent of the $722 median for their male counterparts, up from about 63 percent in 1979. Women are making 70 percent of travel decisions, for the family, for their own getaways or for people at work, said Niki Leondakis, the chief operating officer of Kimpton Hotels and Restaurants in San Francisco. Its surprising that more people are not including women in their marketing. But some big retailers say they are, in fact, well aware of where purchasing power resides. 1 2 3 4 Next Page » More Articles in Business »FOR most of the 27 years it has been in business in Canada, Shane Homes has staked its claim as one of the countrys leading regional homebuilders the old-fashioned way: it devised and executed cookie-cutter designs for new houses just as fast as the orders came in. As the economy of its home base, Calgary, Alberta, soared on the back of oil and gas riches, it could have continued minting money by sticking with that tried-and-true approach. But two years ago, smack in the middle of a housing boom and heightened competition, Shane Homes dumped its old ways and adopted a new blueprint. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Women's Earnings Related Highlights of Womens Earnings in 2005 (PDF From the Department of Labor) Shane Homes AskPatty.com BeJane.com Boston Gal's Open Wallet My Open Wallet Crave Party Enlarge This Image Ken McCurdy for Shane Homes A focus group joined Shane Wenzel, third from right, of Shane Homes; Joanne Thomas Yaccato, a consultant; and Cal Wenzel, right, the companys chief executive, at a home in Calgary, Alberta. The groups suggestions were used in the homes design. The overhaul began at a real estate conference in 2003, when Shane Wenzel, the builders namesake and its head of sales and marketing, heard a speech about the tremendous buying power of women. That moment, Mr. Wenzel recalled, was an epiphany. He set up small listening groups of women to tap into the needs of people who actually lived in his companys homes. What Mr. Wenzel heard wasnt pretty. The ladies never held back once, he said. They were brutally honest. The kitchens in the companys homes, the women said, were all wrong. The pantries were tiny, and the sinks needed to overlook a window so kids in the backyard could be monitored. And the mudrooms! They shared space with laundry rooms, meaning that dirty floors might sit right beneath clean laundry. (Its called a mud/laundry room? one incredulous woman asked.) After that, Shane Homes subjected designs to similar grillings  before they were built  and adapted them accordingly. Shane Homes had the revolutionary idea of asking women what they wanted in a home, said Joanne Thomas Yaccato, a Toronto consultant and author who advised the company on female consumers. The revolutionary part is that they not only listened, they actually built the darn thing. Shane Homes is hardly alone. More companies, in the United States and elsewhere, have realized that they overlook women at their own financial peril. The companies are realigning their marketing and design practices, learning to court an increasingly female-centric consumer base that boasts more financial muscle and purchasing independence than ever before. We are perhaps on the first step to a matriarchal society; women will earn more money than men if current trends continue by 2028, said Michael J. Silverstein of the Boston Consulting Group. The trend has been escalating in the last 10 years as there has been a gradual, slow erosion of the power balance in the family, a psychic rebalancing. Women, Mr. Silverstein added, are controlling purchases and driving a shift in our economy. Retailers like Home Depot, Lowes, Sears, Best Buy and others recognize that women are running their households like purchasing managers. Some are identifying stores that have more female shoppers and offering additional services, including sales support, customized signs and special product displays, said Dana L. Telsey, who runs her own independent research firm. Travel companies, automakers, and other companies, meanwhile, have had to cater to the tastes of women who have careers outside the home and are pursuing hobbies and other pricey interests. The phenomenon is readily apparent on the Internet, where Web sites built around the needs and interests of such groups as female homeowners and car buyers have gained steady traction. Much of that shift has to do with education and pay. At American colleges and universities, women represent 57 percent of undergraduate classes and 58 percent of graduate classes, according to the American Council on Education. (They also hold a slight majority in the overall population.) And education, in turn, has helped to bolster salaries and income. In 2005, government data show, women who were full-time wage and salary workers had median weekly earnings of $585, or 81 percent of the $722 median for their male counterparts, up from about 63 percent in 1979. Women are making 70 percent of travel decisions, for the family, for their own getaways or for people at work, said Niki Leondakis, the chief operating officer of Kimpton Hotels and Restaurants in San Francisco. Its surprising that more people are not including women in their marketing. But some big retailers say they are, in fact, well aware of where purchasing power resides. 1 2 3 4 Next Page »</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/22/business/22lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe’s Profit Rises, but Warning Hurts Shares<date>Published: August 22, 2006</date><text>RALEIGH, N.C., Aug. 21 (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies reported an 11 percent increase in second-quarter profit on Monday but warned that a slowing housing market would hurt its earnings for the rest of the year, setting off a 4 percent decline in its stock price. Lowe’s reported income of $935 million, or 60 cents a share, up from $839 million, or 52 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended Aug. 4, rose more than 12 percent, to $13.39 billion, from $11.93 billion last year, slightly ahead of Wall Street estimates. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 3.3 percent. During the quarter Lowe’s gained market share for flooring, appliances, outdoor power equipment and cabinets, the company said, citing third-party estimates. But orders for new homes have slowed in recent periods and sales of existing houses are slowing from record levels, putting pressure on sales at Lowe’s and its larger rival, Home Depot. Increased gas prices have also affected business, Lowe’s chief executive, Robert Niblock, said. “Near-term pressures on the U.S. consumer have led to a more cautious outlook for the balance of the year,” Mr. Niblock said in a prepared statement. David S. Strasser, a Banc of America Securities analyst, wrote in a report about Lowe’s quarterly report: “We believe the home improvement sector is facing significant headwinds as housing turnover slows and interest rates rise.” Stock in Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., fell $1.17, to $28.35 a share. In a conference call with analysts, company officials said they were encouraged by continued low home mortgage rates and improving employment rates in the Midwest and elsewhere in the country. “We remain very optimistic about the long-term opportunities in these markets,” Mr. Niblock said. More Articles in Business »RALEIGH, N.C., Aug. 21 (AP)  The Lowe’s Companies reported an 11 percent increase in second-quarter profit on Monday but warned that a slowing housing market would hurt its earnings for the rest of the year, setting off a 4 percent decline in its stock price. Lowe’s reported income of $935 million, or 60 cents a share, up from $839 million, or 52 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended Aug. 4, rose more than 12 percent, to $13.39 billion, from $11.93 billion last year, slightly ahead of Wall Street estimates. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 3.3 percent. During the quarter Lowe’s gained market share for flooring, appliances, outdoor power equipment and cabinets, the company said, citing third-party estimates. But orders for new homes have slowed in recent periods and sales of existing houses are slowing from record levels, putting pressure on sales at Lowe’s and its larger rival, Home Depot. Increased gas prices have also affected business, Lowe’s chief executive, Robert Niblock, said. “Near-term pressures on the U.S. consumer have led to a more cautious outlook for the balance of the year,” Mr. Niblock said in a prepared statement. David S. Strasser, a Banc of America Securities analyst, wrote in a report about Lowe’s quarterly report: “We believe the home improvement sector is facing significant headwinds as housing turnover slows and interest rates rise.” Stock in Lowe’s, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., fell $1.17, to $28.35 a share. In a conference call with analysts, company officials said they were encouraged by continued low home mortgage rates and improving employment rates in the Midwest and elsewhere in the country. “We remain very optimistic about the long-term opportunities in these markets,” Mr. Niblock said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/23/business/23lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Profit Up 44%, but Outlook Is Lowered<date>Published: May 23, 2006</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the home-improvement retailer, said yesterday that first-quarter profit rose 44 percent on higher sales of appliances and lawn mowers, but the company cut its annual revenue forecast, setting off a 4 percent decline in its share price. Net income climbed to $841 million, or $1.06 a share, from $586 million, or 73 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of 94 cents a share. Sales increased 20 percent, to $11.92 billion. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 5.7 percent, less than some analysts projected. The chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said Lowe's cut its forecast for full-year sales gains because of higher fuel prices and trends in consumer spending. Investors are concerned that revenue growth will slow at Lowe's as interest rates climb. "If you look at the past few times we've had a rising interest rate cycle, they've had a slowdown" in comparable sales, said Bryan Keane, an analyst with the U.S. Trust Company in New York, referring to sales at stores open at least a year. Shares of Lowe's fell $2.82, or 4.5 percent, to $59.82. Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., lowered its full-year sales forecast to an increase of 13 percent from as much as 14 percent and its same-store sales growth forecast to 4 percent to 5 percent, from 5 percent to 6 percent. It raised its projection for profit in the year ending in January to $4.14 to $4.22 a share. Lowe's first-quarter sales were strong across most of the United States except the West Coast, where rain affected sales, and one north-central market, where layoffs and plant closings hurt revenue, Mr. Niblock said in a call with analysts. "The run-up in gas prices probably has hit disposable income for consumers a little, but the American consumer's pretty resilient," Mr. Niblock said in an interview. "They'll adjust to that." More Articles in Business »The Lowe's Companies, the home-improvement retailer, said yesterday that first-quarter profit rose 44 percent on higher sales of appliances and lawn mowers, but the company cut its annual revenue forecast, setting off a 4 percent decline in its share price. Net income climbed to $841 million, or $1.06 a share, from $586 million, or 73 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of 94 cents a share. Sales increased 20 percent, to $11.92 billion. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 5.7 percent, less than some analysts projected. The chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said Lowe's cut its forecast for full-year sales gains because of higher fuel prices and trends in consumer spending. Investors are concerned that revenue growth will slow at Lowe's as interest rates climb. "If you look at the past few times we've had a rising interest rate cycle, they've had a slowdown" in comparable sales, said Bryan Keane, an analyst with the U.S. Trust Company in New York, referring to sales at stores open at least a year. Shares of Lowe's fell $2.82, or 4.5 percent, to $59.82. Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., lowered its full-year sales forecast to an increase of 13 percent from as much as 14 percent and its same-store sales growth forecast to 4 percent to 5 percent, from 5 percent to 6 percent. It raised its projection for profit in the year ending in January to $4.14 to $4.22 a share. Lowe's first-quarter sales were strong across most of the United States except the West Coast, where rain affected sales, and one north-central market, where layoffs and plant closings hurt revenue, Mr. Niblock said in a call with analysts. "The run-up in gas prices probably has hit disposable income for consumers a little, but the American consumer's pretty resilient," Mr. Niblock said in an interview. "They'll adjust to that."</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/28/business/28lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Profit Jumped 37% in 4th Quarter<date>Published: February 28, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News The Lowe's Companies said yesterday that its fourth-quarter profit rose 37 percent, the biggest gain in three years, as Americans spent more on remodeling kitchens and bathrooms and as warmer-than-normal weather encouraged more construction projects. The company also forecast full-year profit above analysts' estimates. Lowe's, the second-largest home improvement retailer, said its net income jumped to $695 million, or 87 cents a share, in the quarter ended Feb. 3, from $508 million, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Revenue increased 26 percent, to $10.8 billion. Comparable-store sales gained 7.8 percent as customers bought cabinets and countertops and as hurricane damage forced homeowners to make repairs. Revenue growth at Lowe's is outpacing that of its larger rival, Home Depot, as it opens stores in metropolitan areas including Phoenix and Chicago. Lowe's, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., forecast that its profit for the 2007 fiscal year would rise to $4.03 to $4.13 a share. The consensus estimate from analysts for the year is $3.95, according to Thomson Financial. The company affirmed its sales forecast of a 13 percent to 14 percent gain. Shares of Lowe's surged $3.78, or 6 percent, to $69.30 in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. Sales at stores open at least a year increased in 19 of 20 product categories, Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said on a conference call with analysts and investors. Same-store sales of heating products declined because of the unusually warm winter weather, he said. Installation revenue grew more than 22 percent, to $2.6 billion, in the fiscal year, Nick Canter, executive vice president for store operations, said on the call. Gross margin, or the percentage of sales left after subtracting the cost of goods sold, widened to 35.14 percent, from 34.96 percent, the company said. Selling, general and administrative costs fell to 21.3 percent of sales from 21.5 percent. More Articles in Business &gt;By Bloomberg News The Lowe's Companies said yesterday that its fourth-quarter profit rose 37 percent, the biggest gain in three years, as Americans spent more on remodeling kitchens and bathrooms and as warmer-than-normal weather encouraged more construction projects. The company also forecast full-year profit above analysts' estimates. Lowe's, the second-largest home improvement retailer, said its net income jumped to $695 million, or 87 cents a share, in the quarter ended Feb. 3, from $508 million, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Revenue increased 26 percent, to $10.8 billion. Comparable-store sales gained 7.8 percent as customers bought cabinets and countertops and as hurricane damage forced homeowners to make repairs. Revenue growth at Lowe's is outpacing that of its larger rival, Home Depot, as it opens stores in metropolitan areas including Phoenix and Chicago. Lowe's, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., forecast that its profit for the 2007 fiscal year would rise to $4.03 to $4.13 a share. The consensus estimate from analysts for the year is $3.95, according to Thomson Financial. The company affirmed its sales forecast of a 13 percent to 14 percent gain. Shares of Lowe's surged $3.78, or 6 percent, to $69.30 in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. Sales at stores open at least a year increased in 19 of 20 product categories, Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said on a conference call with analysts and investors. Same-store sales of heating products declined because of the unusually warm winter weather, he said. Installation revenue grew more than 22 percent, to $2.6 billion, in the fiscal year, Nick Canter, executive vice president for store operations, said on the call. Gross margin, or the percentage of sales left after subtracting the cost of goods sold, widened to 35.14 percent, from 34.96 percent, the company said. Selling, general and administrative costs fell to 21.3 percent of sales from 21.5 percent.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/15/business/15lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Storm Repairs Help Increase Profit 26% at Lowe's<date>Published: November 15, 2005</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 14 (AP) - The Lowe's Companies, the home-improvement retailer, said Monday that earnings rose nearly 26 percent in its third fiscal quarter, surpassing Wall Street's forecast, as residents of the hurricane-ravaged Gulf Coast region and others improved or rebuilt their houses. The company, based in Mooresville, N.C., near here, earned $649 million, or 81 cents a share, compared with $516 million, or 65 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the quarter, ended Oct. 28, increased 16 percent, to $10.6 billion from $9.1 billion in 2004. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 6.2 percent. Lowe's earnings surpassed the 77 cents a share expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. In trading Monday, its shares advanced $2.92, or 4.7 percent, to $64.89. Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, cited a "lift in sales" after hurricanes devastated the Gulf Coast and areas of Florida. Hurricane damage drives up demand for items including generators, tarpaulin and plywood that homeowners need to secure dwellings. Beyond that, they commonly need several months for lasting repairs. At the same time, spikes in the price of gasoline and expected sharp rises in home heating fuels are cutting into discretionary spending. Mr. Niblock told analysts in a conference call: "Consumers are still shopping for products for home-improvement projects along with making repairs to their homes. Most of our customers are homeowners, and they are not willing to let their single biggest investment deteriorate." More Articles in Business &gt;CHARLOTTE, N.C., Nov. 14 (AP) - The Lowe's Companies, the home-improvement retailer, said Monday that earnings rose nearly 26 percent in its third fiscal quarter, surpassing Wall Street's forecast, as residents of the hurricane-ravaged Gulf Coast region and others improved or rebuilt their houses. The company, based in Mooresville, N.C., near here, earned $649 million, or 81 cents a share, compared with $516 million, or 65 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the quarter, ended Oct. 28, increased 16 percent, to $10.6 billion from $9.1 billion in 2004. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 6.2 percent. Lowe's earnings surpassed the 77 cents a share expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. In trading Monday, its shares advanced $2.92, or 4.7 percent, to $64.89. Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, cited a "lift in sales" after hurricanes devastated the Gulf Coast and areas of Florida. Hurricane damage drives up demand for items including generators, tarpaulin and plywood that homeowners need to secure dwellings. Beyond that, they commonly need several months for lasting repairs. At the same time, spikes in the price of gasoline and expected sharp rises in home heating fuels are cutting into discretionary spending. Mr. Niblock told analysts in a conference call: "Consumers are still shopping for products for home-improvement projects along with making repairs to their homes. Most of our customers are homeowners, and they are not willing to let their single biggest investment deteriorate."</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/17/business/17lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Despite Weather, Lowe's Profit Rises 31%<date>Published: May 17, 2005</date><text>CHARLOTTE, N.C., May 16 (AP) - The Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, posted a 31 percent increase in first-quarter profit Monday, and its stock rose more than 5 percent. The earnings fell short of Wall Street's expectations, but investors appeared to accept the company's explanation that poor weather in March in major markets like the Northeast was the chief culprit. Cold and rainy weather in March cut into sales of nursery products, lumber and seasonal living items, as consumers were prevented from working on their homes, Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Net income rose to $590 million, or 74 cents a share, from $452 million, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended April 29, rose 14 percent, to $9.91 billion, from $8.68 billion last year. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expected earnings of 76 cents a share on sales of $9.97 billion. Brian Postol, an analyst at A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons, said investors believed Lowe's explanation of the weather-related problems. Outside of the slowdown in March, Mr. Postol said, "They started out strong and ended strong." Stock in Lowe's, the No. 2 home improvement retailer behind Home Depot, rose $2.94, to $55.80 a share. Mr. Niblock said sales at stores that have been open at least a year increased 3.8 percent in the quarter. That compared with a rise of 9.9 percent in the first quarter of 2004. "While our comps fell short of our projections of 5 to 6 percent at the beginning of the quarter, we are not surprised by it because the weather affected our business in March," Mr. Niblock told analysts. Once the weather improved in April, Mr. Niblock said, Lowe's recorded the first $1 billion sales week in company history. More Articles in Business &gt;CHARLOTTE, N.C., May 16 (AP) - The Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, posted a 31 percent increase in first-quarter profit Monday, and its stock rose more than 5 percent. The earnings fell short of Wall Street's expectations, but investors appeared to accept the company's explanation that poor weather in March in major markets like the Northeast was the chief culprit. Cold and rainy weather in March cut into sales of nursery products, lumber and seasonal living items, as consumers were prevented from working on their homes, Lowe's chief executive, Robert A. Niblock, said. Net income rose to $590 million, or 74 cents a share, from $452 million, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended April 29, rose 14 percent, to $9.91 billion, from $8.68 billion last year. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expected earnings of 76 cents a share on sales of $9.97 billion. Brian Postol, an analyst at A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons, said investors believed Lowe's explanation of the weather-related problems. Outside of the slowdown in March, Mr. Postol said, "They started out strong and ended strong." Stock in Lowe's, the No. 2 home improvement retailer behind Home Depot, rose $2.94, to $55.80 a share. Mr. Niblock said sales at stores that have been open at least a year increased 3.8 percent in the quarter. That compared with a rise of 9.9 percent in the first quarter of 2004. "While our comps fell short of our projections of 5 to 6 percent at the beginning of the quarter, we are not surprised by it because the weather affected our business in March," Mr. Niblock told analysts. Once the weather improved in April, Mr. Niblock said, Lowe's recorded the first $1 billion sales week in company history.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6D91630F937A35756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Lowe's Sets Review, Incumbents Included<date>Published: May 4, 2005</date><text>The Lowe's Companies said yesterday that it had put in review the creative and media parts of the account of the Lowe's home-improvement retail chain, which have been handled since 1999 by two New York units of the McCann Worldgroup, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies. Lowe's spends an estimated $300 million a year on advertising. The creative duties are at McCann Erickson Worldwide and the media duties are at Universal McCann. Both agencies will take part in the review. Chris Ahearn, a spokeswoman at Lowe's, confirmed a report of the review that appeared on AdAge.com. Although ''we're happy with their work,'' Ms. Ahearn said of McCann Erickson and Universal McCann, ''as a normal course of business we like to review major relationships from time to time.'' Lowe's expects to consider 6 to 12 agencies, she said, with a decision expected in July. Universal McCann, which is replacing senior executives after a management shake-up, is involved in reviews for several large accounts. The campaign created by McCann Erickson is perhaps best known for having the actor Gene Hackman serve as the uncredited voice-over announcer in the commercials.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/24/business/24lowes.html?ref=lowescompanies">Earnings Rise 27% at Lowe's on Strong Sales of Appliances<date>Published: February 24, 2005</date><text>y Bloomberg News The Lowe's Companies said fourth-quarter profit rose 27 percent as it outperformed its bigger rival, Home Depot Inc. Net income increased to $508 million, or 64 cents a share, from $401 million, or 49 cents, in the period a year earlier. Sales climbed 18 percent, to $8.55 billion. Earnings in the fourth quarter were 5 cents more than the 59-cent average estimate of analysts polled by Thomson First Call. Sales at Lowe's stores open at least a year rose 6.9 percent, compared with 4.6 percent for Home Depot. Fourth-quarter earnings at Home Depot rose 9.5 percent, the smallest gain in almost two years.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDE1530F934A25751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=lowescompanies">National Briefing | South: North Carolina: Sentence In Computer Case<date>Published: December 17, 2004</date><text>One of three men who hacked into the national computer system of Lowe's hardware stores has been sentenced to nine years in federal prison. The government said the term was the longest ever handed down for a computer crime in the United States. Prosecutors said the defendant, Brian Salcedo of Whitmore Lake, Mich., and two other men tapped into the wireless network of a Lowe's store in Southfield, Mich., used that connection to enter the chain's central computer system in North Wilkesboro, N.C., and installed a program to capture customers' credit card information.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/07/business/businessspecial/07ODON.html?ref=lowescompanies">City May Never Sleep, but Most Stores Do<date>Published: December 7, 2004</date><text>HEN the sudden need for retail therapy strikes in New York City, you can rush to Fantasy World in Greenwich Village and lay down $89 for the red leather bondage bikini hanging over the cash register. You can buy it at 3 a.m. or 4 a.m. or 5 a.m., because Fantasy World never closes. Advertisement "Our sort of business, some people like to shop in the night," said the smiling salesclerk one recent night. He provided only his first name, Joe. (He is Roman Catholic, he said, and doesn't want it to be known where he works.) But Fantasy World is essentially it, as far as all-night shopping options for clothing go, even in the city that is said to never sleep. For those given to shopping in the wee hours, who never understood how friends could so easily turn to catalogs and the Internet, giving up the visceral thrill of hunting, handling and smelling merchandise, it may seem strangely unfair that few stores have rewarded your loyalty by staying open later. You could shop at L. L. Bean's flagship store 24 hours, 365 days a year. But not everyone lives within a short trip of Freeport, Me., or within striking distance of a 24-hour Wal-Mart. So you must learn to meld your late-night shopping needs to what is available. A trip to Lowe's home improvement store in Brooklyn one Friday night provided a glimpse of who, exactly, was out shopping late, making do with what was open and why. There was a small crowd at the paint counter. But, among the storage baskets, appliances and decorative lighting, there were even more shoppers who just wanted to browse. "I had no idea stores like this were open," said Georgia Kokolis, 37, as she surveyed rugs around 11 p.m. (This Lowe's is open 5 a.m. to midnight.) Ms. Kokolis, who is from Canada but lives in New York, said that she and her fiancé were driving by when they saw the Lowe's sign and decided to stop. Judy Alvarez, 52, who had stopped in with her husband, Ernesto, to get ideas for Christmas gifts, found the store manager to tell him that she had nearly stepped on a dead rat on the street outside the store. (A hazard of any nighttime venture in New York.) Mrs. Alvarez, in a trembling voice, said that she would become a daytime shopper. Most customers said that they worked until the evening on weekdays and loathed weekend crowds, leading them to shop in the late hours. "After I go home and cook dinner and come back out, you have less of the public to deal with," said Cheryl Darlington, 34, a social worker who lives in Brooklyn whose shopping cart included a shower-curtain rod and gardening supplies. Ms. Darlington said that sometimes on Friday nights she shops at Macy's as late as she can and then heads to a 24-hour supermarket to do her grocery shopping. Which was fine with her 9-year-old son, Roshawn Brooks, who was all too delighted to accompany her this night, delaying his bedtime. There are some things you must accept about night shopping, at any store. There will be clerks who are available to help you. If there is a parking lot, there will be plenty of parking. And despite a few boxes in the aisles as clerks restock the shelves, there will probably be ample room in which to maneuver. Once you get used to these luxuries, it's hard to return to the weekend afternoon crunch, said Jon Harris, 47, who lives in the Philadelphia suburbs, and was pushing his cart, unobstructed, through Lowe's shortly before closing. His girlfriend, Hope Menaker, 55, of Brooklyn, agreed. She described a date a few years back that ended at 2 a.m. with an impromptu dance in the aisles of the Brooklyn Home Depot, just because. But that was another boyfriend. And Home Depot now closes at midnight.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/16/business/16home.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Posts 15% Profit Rise but Shares Slump on Forecast<date>Published: November 16, 2004</date><text>y Reuters Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, reported a 15 percent rise in third-quarter profit yesterday, aided by its expansion to New York and other big United States markets, but its stock slumped on a disappointing outlook. The company said it expected fourth-quarter profit to be in line with or slightly below analysts' estimates, and its shares fell 1.7 percent. Analysts said many investors were hoping for a stronger forecast. Advertisement Analysts also focused on the company's gross margins, which were down when the effects of an accounting change were excluded. Third-quarter net income rose to $522 million, or 66 cents a diluted share, from $452 million, or 56 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Analysts had forecast 65 cents a share. Lowe's posted strong sales of outdoor power equipment, cabinets and countertops in the quarter but said gross margins were hurt by higher distribution expenses and freight costs and by damaged goods from recent hurricanes in the Southeast. The company's third-quarter sales rose 16 percent, to $9.06 billion. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 5.2 percent, compared with a rise of 12 percent a year earlier. Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., forecast fourth-quarter earnings of 58 cents to 60 cents a share. The average forecast of analysts is 60 cents. The company forecast that fourth-quarter same-store sales would rise by 4 percent to 5 percent. Though Lowe's has delivered solid earnings as it expands to big cities, it now faces tougher earnings and sales comparisons compared with a year ago, and stiff competition in some product categories. Alan Rifkin, a Lehman Brothers analyst, said rising interest rates also could limit earnings increases in 2005. For the year, Lowe's forecast profit of $2.69 to $2.71 a share, including the impact of an accounting change. Analysts expect $2.72 a share. Shares of Lowe's fell $1, to $59.25.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/17/business/lowe-s-profit-rises-by-18-outlook-up.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Profit Rises by 18%; Outlook Up<date>Published: August 17, 2004</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the world's No.2 home improvement retailer, said yesterday that its second-quarter profit rose 18 percent and that earnings for the rest of the year would top current estimates.Lowe's shares rose $2.49, or 5.3 percent, to $49.14 yesterday.Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., reported net income of $704 million, or 89 cents a share, for the quarter ended July 30, compared with $597 million, or 75 cents a share, a year earlier.Analysts on average were expecting a profit of 90 cents a share, according to Reuters estimates.Sales at stores open at least a year, an important retail performance gauge, rose 5.1 percent, below Lowe's forecast of 6 percent to 7 percent. Total sales for the quarter rose 17 percent, to $10.2 billion, helped by demand for lumber, outdoor power equipment and plumbing.Lowe's said higher-priced merchandise and new installation services and special-order programs were driving up its average purchase.The company said sales softened in June and early July as many factors, including poor weather, delayed the start of late-spring and summer projects. The retailer said sales rebounded later in July, and were currently running above forecasts for the third quarter.Both Lowe's and Home Depot, the industry leader, have benefited in recent years from a strong housing market. They face tougher conditions in the second half as consumers grapple with rising interest rates and higher oil prices.Lowe's predicted that sales at stores open at least a year would rise 3 percent to 4 percent in the third quarter, compared with a 12 percent rise in the 2003 period.The company said it expected third-quarter profit of 65 cents to 66 cents a share as sales rise 15 percent. For the full year, it forecast earnings of $2.69 to $2.71 a share, including the effect of an accounting change.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/04/business/driver-is-fined-for-nascar-ad-cover-up.html?ref=lowescompanies">Driver Is Fined for Nascar Ad Cover-Up<date>Published: August 04, 2004</date><text>A Nascar driver, Jimmie Johnson, who is sponsored by PepsiCo Inc., was fined $10,000 for covering a bottle of the Coca-Cola Company's Powerade sports drink with a sign after he won the Pennsylvania 500 on Sunday.Mr. Johnson climbed from his car on victory lane while surrounded by media and placed a sign for the Lowe's Companies, his primary sponsor, in front of a bottle of Powerade Nascar officials had placed on his car.Coca-Cola's Powerade is a sponsor of Nascar, stock-car racing's governing body.The fine comes a week after the organization's president, Mike Helton, ordered drivers to stop interfering with the placement of sponsors' products in victory lane. Mr. Johnson said that he was trying to follow Nascar's orders and protect a sponsor.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/18/business/lowe-s-earnings-are-up-8-kmart-rebounds-from-loss.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Earnings Are Up 8%; Kmart Rebounds From Loss<date>Published: May 18, 2004</date><text>The Lowe's Companies and the Kmart Holding Corporation both reported profits yesterday.Lowe's reported an 8 percent increase in first-quarter profit, helped by sales of higher-price items like kitchen cabinets and its expansion to big cities.But the company's stock fell about 2 percent, to $49.68, yesterday on concerns about higher energy prices and rising interest rates, analysts said.''What we don't know is what's going to be the effect on home-improvement spending in the next 12 months,'' Sarah Henry, an analyst with Sovereign Asset Management, said.Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., reported first-quarter net income of $455 million, or 57 cents a share, compared with $421 million, or 53 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts had expected 54 cents a share.Sales rose 22 percent, to $8.68 billion. Sales at stores open at least a year, an important retail measure, rose 9.9 percent, helped by higher lumber and building material prices.Excluding a 16-cents-a-share impact from an accounting change, Lowe's said, earnings for the 2004 quarter would have been $581 million, or 73 cents a diluted share.Kmart posted its second consecutive quarterly profit as it cut costs, driving its shares up nearly 10 percent even as sales tumbled after it closed hundreds of stores last year.The discount retailer, which emerged from bankruptcy protection last May with a new management team, fewer stores and lower debt, has been focusing on building profits, even at the expense of sales.The company, based in Troy, Mich., said it earned $93 million, or 94 cents a share, in the first quarter ended April 28. For the period a year ago, Kmart lost $862 million while it was still in bankruptcy.Kmart said quarterly sales tumbled 25.3 percent, to $4.62 billion, reflecting the closing of 316 stores in the first quarter last year. The company shut about 600 of its 2,100 stores while reorganizing.Sales at stores open at least a year fell 12.9 percent. Kmart attributed the decline to special promotions that increased sales last year and to reduced advertising this year.Kmart shares rose $4.32, to $48.62.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/28/nyregion/suburban-retailing-for-the-new-brooklyn.html?ref=lowescompanies">Suburban Retailing for the New Brooklyn<date>Published: April 28, 2004</date><text>In Dumbo, a high-concept exercise in nesting lust called Hadco, a demonstration center where customers can try out luxe appliances for purchase elsewhere, has opened near outposts of ABC Carpet and Home and West Elm. In Gowanus, within eyeshot of a fuel-oil depot and a bustling scrap-metal business, a gleaming new 136,000-square-foot Lowe's, the chain's first foray into New York City's urban market, is set to open this Friday. And in Red Hook, if Ikea has its way, an enormous yellow and blue box will draw shoppers to the Erie Basin.Even as the assorted factions with stakes in the future of Brooklyn haggle over the relative merits of housing versus industry, preservation versus economic development, and the needs of the affluent versus those of the working stiff, a quiet retail revolution has already come to the eastern shores of the East River. Responding to the pent-up desires of those living in the borough, as well as to the coming hordes foreshadowed by a new-housing boom, home renovation and furnishing stores -- some big-box, some just big -- are suddenly finding their way to Brooklyn and remaking its neighborhoods, albeit in fits and starts. While some say it means that the borough is the new Manhattan, others argue that it is becoming the new suburbs. Perhaps, in the end, it is simply the new Brooklyn.''The arrival of all of these home-furnishing stores follows the explosion in residential development,'' said Kenneth Adams, president of the Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce. ''Historically, there's been unmet consumer demand in this area, but that's really crescendoed,'' he added, as a ''wave of residential development continues to wash over Brooklyn.''According to census figures released in January, the borough leads the city in new home construction, a phenomenon that is visible in the neat rows of multifamily houses in East New York, in the 850-unit Oceana complex in Brighton Beach, and in the tall apartment buildings rising on Fourth Avenue in Park Slope and throughout Downtown Brooklyn.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/25/business/company-news-lawsuit-accuses-lowe-s-of-racial-discrimination.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LAWSUIT ACCUSES LOWE'S OF RACIAL DISCRIMINATION<date>Published: March 25, 2004</date><text>The Equal Employment Opportunity Commission said yesterday that it was suing Lowe's Companies Inc., the home-improvement retailer, for discrimination against black job applicants at a Lowe's distribution center. The commission's lawsuit, filed in United States District Court in Knoxville, Tenn., accuses Lowe's with failing to hire a class of qualified African-American applicants because of their race. The complaint says the discrimination occurred from 2002 to 2003 at a distribution facility in Vonore, about 15 miles south of Knoxville. A Lowe's spokeswoman said the company, which is based in Mooresville, N.C., had not seen the lawsuit but was aware of a news release from the commission. ''Lowe's does have a deep commitment to diversity,'' the Lowe's spokeswoman, Chris Ahearn, said. The commission said the lawsuit came after settlement efforts failed, and its seeks back pay with interest, compensatory damages and punitive damages.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/01/nyregion/metro-briefing-new-jersey-ocean-township-store-is-closed.html?ref=lowescompanies">Metro Briefing | New Jersey: Ocean Township: Store Is Closed<date>Published: March 01, 2004</date><text>A year-old Lowe's home-improvement store built on a former landfill and Superfund site has been closed indefinitely because of cracks in its floor, the company said. The 150,000-square-foot store closed at 6 p.m. Thursday. A statement by the company said the store was closed as a ''proactive measure'' after the landfill under the floor slab had settled, creating the cracks. The 123-acre landfill operated from 1941 to 1975. It was placed on the Superfund National Priorities list for potentially hazardous waste sites in 1983, then removed eight years later after the Environmental Protection Agency said there was no significant chemical contamination.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/29/business/business-yes-women-spend-and-saw-and-sand.html?ref=lowescompanies">Business; Yes, Women Spend (And Saw and Sand)<date>Published: February 29, 2004</date><text>SHEILA MILLER grips the black rubber handle of a circular saw, struggling to drive the blade through a tough piece of laminated wood flooring. Cheered on by her two daughters and three dozen women attending a Home Depot Do-It-Herself workshop here in late January, Ms. Miller finishes the job and shakily turns over the saw to Wendy Tijerina, the manager of the flooring department.''I just moved into a new house, and there's a lot of things to be done,'' Ms. Miller, 42, said, noting that she had already completed some of the easier home-improvement tasks.''But now I'm coming to the big tools,'' she added. ''They are my biggest fear, but I'm not paying somebody to do something I can do myself.''Her determination to tackle the toughest tasks -- like sanding and sealing a countertop in her kitchen -- is no surprise to executives at Home Depot, which is based nearby, in Atlanta. More than two years ago, under its relatively new chief executive, Robert L. Nardelli, the company embarked on an 18-month study of all its shoppers, paying particular attention to women. Home Depot executives pored over consumer data, and, with the ideas they gathered, the company is spending more than $1 billion to renovate many of its 1,700 stores.Home Depot's main rival, Lowe's, had already been marketing to women and had redesigned its stores to feature departments considered more appealing to them: lighting, accessories, paint and flooring. It even widened its aisles to help eliminate ''butt brush,'' the uncomfortable contact that can occur as consumers navigate the aisles, and something that women particularly disliked, the company found.''We're always looking to improve the stores, and many of the changes have made a real difference in the way women see Lowe's,'' said Julie Yenichek, a spokeswoman for the company.The moves have paid off for Lowe's. And now Home Depot, too, appears to be reaping rewards from its effort. While Lowe's had consistently outperformed Home Depot for several years in same-store sales, those for stores open at least a year, Home Depot outpaced its rival in its fourth quarter. On Tuesday, Home Depot announced that its same-store sales for that quarter, which ended on Feb. 1, were up 7.6 percent over the period a year earlier. That compared with a gain of 7.3 percent at Lowe's in its quarter ended Jan. 30. Home Depot also had a 39 percent gain in its fourth-quarter profit, versus 28 percent at Lowe's.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/11/business/company-news-lowe-s-realigns-to-aid-national-expansion-effort.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S REALIGNS TO AID NATIONAL EXPANSION EFFORT<date>Published: December 11, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, said yesterday that it would expand the number of operating divisions to five from three to allow for national growth. The company said it would add Northeast and Southeast divisions to its Southern, Central and Western ones. The changes will start on Jan. 1. Lowe's, based in Mooresville, N.C., said the new structure would allow the company to focus on customer service as it adds stores in major cities.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/09/business/company-news-lowe-s-to-buy-back-up-to-1-billion-in-stock.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S TO BUY BACK UP TO $1 BILLION IN STOCK<date>Published: December 09, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies said yesterday that it would buy back as much as $1 billion in stock, its first share repurchase. The amount that can be repurchased represents about 17.6 million shares, based on the closing price yesterday. The plan is effective immediately, the company said. Lowe's, the home improvement retailer, said improvements in earnings and cash flow would let it return more money to shareholders.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/24/business/company-news-lowe-s-raises-earnings-forecast-for-third-quarter.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S RAISES EARNINGS FORECAST FOR THIRD QUARTER<date>Published: September 24, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies raised its earnings forecast for the third quarter yesterday as demand for home-improvement products and its expansion in major cities led to better-than-expected sales. Lowe's, the No. 2 home improvement retailer behind Home Depot Inc., said it expected earnings of 52 cents to 53 cents a share for its fiscal third quarter, which ends Oct. 31. Last month, it forecast 50 cents to 51 cents. Lowe's also forecast profit of $2.27 to $2.28 a share for the fiscal year. Sales at stores open at least a year, or comparable-store sales, are running ahead of expectations for a 5 percent to 6 percent increase in the third quarter, Lowe's said. The company, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., said it expected earnings to rise 14 percent to 15 percent in fiscal 2004 and 25 percent to 26 percent in fiscal 2005.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/19/business/profits-rise-28-at-lowe-s-toys-r-us-narrows-loss.html?ref=lowescompanies">Profits Rise 28% at Lowe's; Toys 'R' Us Narrows Loss<date>Published: August 19, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the No. 2 home improvement chain behind Home Depot, reported a nearly 28 percent gain in its second-quarter earnings yesterday as homeowners caught up on spring projects delayed by cold and wet weather.Another retailer, Toys ''R'' Us Inc., which is No. 2 in toys behind Wal-Mart, said that it cut its second-quarter loss by a third. The company said that higher sales for its Internet, international and baby products divisions helped offset larger overhead expenses and slumping sales at its United States toy and children's apparel stores.Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., posted a profit of $597 million, or 75 cents a share, for the quarter ended Aug. 1, up from $467 million, or 59 cents a share, a year ago.Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had projected earnings of 69 cents.''Very impressive numbers,'' said Colin McGranahan, an analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein who follows Lowe's stock. ''Across the board, they showed strong momentum on things such as comparative store sales.''Sales at Lowe's increased 17 percent, to $8.77 billion, up from $7.49 billion in the year-ago quarter. Comparable store sales for the second quarter increased 6.9 percent.''As we had expected, Americans' passion for home improvement projects surged as the weather improved across most of the U.S.,'' Lowe's chairman and chief executive, Robert L. Tillman, said.Lowe's said it had sales strength in every product category, including the more expensive items as consumers returned to its stores to catch up on projects.Shares of Lowe's rose $3.06, to $51.96.Toys ''R'' Us, based in Wayne, N.J., said its net loss for the quarter that ended Aug. 2 was $11 million, or 5 cents a share. That matched the consensus forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call. In the year earlier, Toys ''R'' Us had a net loss of $17 million, or 8 cents a share.The company said that excluding an accounting change involving vendor credits and allowances for cooperative advertising, its second-quarter net loss would have been $5 million, or 2 cents.Total sales for the quarter reached $2.14 billion, up 3.3 percent from $2.07 billion a year earlier, despite the weak economy and tough competition. Excluding the effect of favorable currency exchange rates, revenue rose only 0.6 percent.Shares of Toys ''R'' Us rose 83 cents, to $12.71.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/09/business/commercial-real-estate-regional-market-connecticut-interstate-begets-home.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE: REGIONAL MARKET -- Connecticut; An Interstate Begets a Home Improvement Center<date>Published: July 09, 2003</date><text>Lowe's Home Improvement Centers is planning an $80 million, 1.4-million-square-foot distribution center on a 200-acre site here off Interstate 395, to serve its stores in the Northeast.Site plans submitted to town officials show a building that would cover almost 30 acres, and a similar expanse for parking 600 tractor-trailers and 600 cars. The development would straddle a portion of Lillibridge Road, which would be rerouted around the distribution center at a cost of $7 million.All local approvals are in place, and town officials said the only regulatory approval still to be obtained is from the Army Corps of Engineers, a requirement because of wetlands in the area. That approval is expected later this month.Chris Ahearn, a spokesman for Lowe's, based in North Wilkesboro, N.C., which operates almost 900 stores in 45 states, declined to comment on the proposal until all the permits were in place.Lowe's representatives have said at zoning hearings that the site's easy access to Interstate 395, less than a mile away, made it viable as a distribution-center site.Plainfield town officials are excited about the potential tax revenue, particularly this year, when a budget shortage has resulted in layoffs of employees and cuts in services. First Selectman David C. Allard estimates that after property-tax abatements -- the land is in a state-legislated enterprise zone -- and after paying off a loan for a new road, the town will net $14 million over the next 20 years, or $700,000 a year, a substantial figure for Plainfield, which has an operating budget of $34 million.Town and state officials said Lowe's had shown sensitivity to environmental concerns. When surveys discovered two species listed as endangered in the state, the Eastern spadefoot toad and the vesper sparrow, as well as a threatened species, the blue-spotted salamander, Lowe's redrew its plans.The Plainfield town planner, Louis J. Soja, said he expected the project to draw the attention of some small manufacturers that sell to Lowe's, which might see advantages to being near the distribution center. The town has an industrial park less than two miles away, with about 15 lots of two to three acres still available, and the new road the town is to build will provide access to more industrial-zoned land, in tracts ranging from a few acres to 20 acres.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/20/business/lowe-s-earnings-rise-22-but-shares-dip-on-weak-sales.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Earnings Rise 22%, but Shares Dip on Weak Sales<date>Published: May 20, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the second-largest home-improvement chain behind Home Depot, said today that its first-quarter earnings rose nearly 22 percent because of strong new-home construction and renovations of older ones.But sales fell short of projections because of bad weather, prompting investors to send the company's share price down sharply.Sales at stores open at least a year ''were up a disappointing 0.1 percent,'' the chairman and chief executive Robert L. Tillman told analysts. ''They were significantly affected by weather.''These sales are considered a crucial indicator of a retailer's health. Analysts polled by Thomson First Call expected a 2.6 percent gain in sales open at least a year.Shares of Lowe's dropped on the news, losing $4, -- more than 9 percent -- to close at $40.30.Lowe's reported net income of $421 million, or 53 cents a share, in the first quarter. That was up from $346 million, or 44 cents a share, in the same period last year.The results were a penny above the 52 cents predicted by analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Much of the income gain came from expansion into metropolitan markets, including New York and New Jersey. Winter storms in parts of the East Coast hurt sales in stores that have been open at least a year.Total sales were $7.2 billion, an increase of 11 percent.''We remain confident that home improvement consumers will continue to invest in their homes,'' Mr. Tillman said. ''There are many positive signs and the housing market is strong as mortgage rates remain at 40-year lows.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/04/business/so-which-man-will-sell-you-that-drywall.html?ref=lowescompanies">So, Which Man Will Sell You That Drywall?<date>Published: May 04, 2003</date><text>AT the beginning of spring, the nursery at the Home Depot in Kingston, N.Y., was barren, bordered by rows of dead or dying saplings left over from last fall. Less than a quarter-mile away, the garden center at its fierce competitor, Lowe's, was bursting with color, set off by a new line of pseudo-teak benches.To Wall Street analysts and the investors who have recently deemed Lowe's the new winner in the sweepstakes of home improvement chains, Home Depot's prospects may look as bleak as the row of dead trees. Lowe's stock price is near its all-time high; Home Depot's, on the other hand, has fallen by one-third over the last year. Lowe's same-store sales, those for stores open at least a year, have been rising for years; Home Depot's have been tumbling.The orange-bannered aisles at Home Depot, once at the forefront of warehouse retailing, have not changed much in the company's 24-year history. Its employees don't have the spring in their step they once did; in fact, they are often hard to find. Home Depot, still twice as big as Lowe's, has lost most of its mojo, critics say, and all of its pizazz.Stung by both bad numbers and bad reviews, Home Depot is battling back. The company plans to revamp all its old stores -- gutting 40 this year alone -- in an attempt to create an atmosphere that bears a remarkable resemblance to its rival's cleaner, better-illuminated stores. The changes are intended to appeal to women, increasingly the target customers for the home-improvement industry.To analysts, Home Depot's proposed turnaround is a strange new chapter in a rivalry that once seemed lopsided in Home Depot's favor. ''Home Depot is still the six-million-pound gorilla, and for the first time they are having to deal with viable competition,'' said Brian Postol, a retailing analyst at A. G. Edwards in St. Louis.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/02/business/business-home-depot-seeks-elbow-room-outside-cities.html?ref=lowescompanies">Business; Home Depot Seeks Elbow Room Outside Cities<date>Published: March 02, 2003</date><text>TIMOTHY AND ELIZABETH CAMPBELL'S last trip to Home Depot was sheer drudgery. To cart home the products they needed to remodel their house, they borrowed a friend's Chevy Suburban last week, then drove more than 100 miles from their home here, near Vail, Colo., to the closest Home Depot store, in Denver.Unable to find all the lighting fixtures they needed on the picked-over shelves at the first store, they said, they waited 15 minutes to speak to the lighting specialist before they were sent to a second location across town. ''We got everything we needed in the end,'' Mr. Campbell said. ''But it was a 12-hour ordeal.''The couple's next visit to a Home Depot may not be so miserable. That is because the company will soon open a 118,000-square-foot store here, just 10 minutes from their home. Avon was chosen, in part, by using ZIP code data from its stores' sales receipts to track long-distance customers like the Campbells. Based on that information, Home Depot, which is based in Atlanta, will also open two other stores in rural Colorado in the next three months.The chain is opening stores in places like Avon not only to serve loyal customers like the Campbells, but also to try to reignite sales growth and regain market share from its archrival, the Lowe's Companies. Home Depot, the country's largest home-improvement chain, has largely saturated the country's biggest cities, and it is increasingly turning to rural areas.''It's a reverse Wal-Mart strategy,'' said David M. Szymanski, director of the Center for Retailing Studies at Texas A&amp;M University, referring to that company's expansion beyond its original base in rural markets and into metropolitan areas. ''They've already picked most of the low-hanging fruit in metro areas, so now they're going into the secondary markets.''Even as Home Depot expands aggressively, sales at its 1,500 current outlets have slipped badly, in part, customers and industry analysts say, because the company's once-legendary customer service has slackened. Some problems can be traced to recent efforts by its chief executive, Robert L. Nardelli, to centralize the company's purchasing decisions, effectively removing control from individual stores, and to cut costs by trimming inventories and substituting part-time weekend workers for more experienced full-timers.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/25/business/lowe-s-earnings-climb-46-in-strong-market-for-housing.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Earnings Climb 46% In Strong Market for Housing<date>Published: February 25, 2003</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, a leading home improvement chain, capitalizing on a strong housing market, reported a 46 percent increase in its fourth-quarter earnings today, easily surpassing Wall Street's expectations.Lowe's also offered an upbeat profit outlook today, projecting that earnings for the year would beat current forecasts.Lowe's earned $319.4 million, or 40 cents a share, for the three months ended Jan. 31, up from $218.4 million, or 28 cents a share, a year ago. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call anticipated earnings of 33 cents a share.Revenue increased 16.5 percent, to $6.12 billion, from $5.25 billion in the quarter a year ago. Sales at stores opened at least a year, which are considered a strong gauge of a retailer's health, increased 4.1 percent.Shares of Lowe's rose $2.08, to $38.10.''The year ahead holds challenges, but many signs point to a strong home improvement market,'' the chief executive, Robert L. Tillman, said. ''Despite the uncertainties that remain in the broader economic and geopolitical environment, I'm optimistic that the home improvement consumer will remain resilient.''For 2002, net earnings grew 43.8 percent, to $1.47 billion, or $1.85 a share, from $1.02 billion, or $1.30 a share, in 2001. Sales increased 19.8 percent, to $26.5 billion, from $22.1 billion a year ago. Sales at stores open at least a year increased 5.6 percent for the year.Mr. Tillman called the home improvement market the ''sweet spot'' in the economy, helped by low mortgage rates and strong demand for refinancing. And he expects the current trends to continue well into 2003.For the current fiscal year, Lowe's forecast earnings of $2.16 to $2.20, above analyst projections of $2.11. The company projects that first-quarter earnings will be 51 cents to 53 cents a share. Analysts expect 51 cents a share.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/28/business/company-news-lowe-s-predicts-growth-near-20-over-next-two-years.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S PREDICTS GROWTH NEAR 20% OVER NEXT TWO YEARS<date>Published: September 28, 2002</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, said yesterday that it expected earnings to grow 19 percent to 20 percent annually over the next two years, with revenue up 18 percent to 19 percent, helped by its store expansion. The company said that it expected to add 130 stores in fiscal 2003 and 140 in fiscal year 2004. Lowe's currently has about 800 stores in the United States. Lowe's, which ranks behind the industry leader Home Depot, also said it expected to meet the upper end of its third-quarter earnings forecast of 39 cents to 40 cents a share and full-year forecast of $1.74 to $1.75 a share.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/25/business/company-news-lowe-s-to-open-60-stores-in-new-york-area.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S TO OPEN 60 STORES IN NEW YORK AREA<date>Published: September 25, 2002</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, a leading home-improvement retailer, said yesterday that it planned to open more than 60 stores in the New York metropolitan area and northern New Jersey in the next five years. The expansion is expected to cost about $1 billion and create more than 10,000 jobs, the company said. Lowe's will open stores this week in Roosevelt Field, New York, and Holmdel, N.J., and begin construction on its first outlet on Staten Island. Lowe's is expanding in major cities to compete head-on with its larger rival, Home Depot Inc. Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., plans to open 123 stores in the United States this year and 130 in 2003.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/22/business/investing-is-home-depot-a-fixer-upper.html?ref=lowescompanies">Investing; Is Home Depot a Fixer-Upper?<date>Published: September 22, 2002</date><text>LOW mortgage rates have fueled a housing boom, but that has not done much to help the shares of Home Depot, the nation's largest home-improvement chain.Instead, shares of the Lowe's Companies, Home Depot's biggest rival, are up substantially over the last 12 months -- 50.8 percent, versus a loss of 4.3 percent for Home Depot.The main difference between the two companies, analysts and portfolio managers say, is that Lowe's is growing rapidly while Home Depot has begun to cannibalize its sales when it opens American stores.''Home Depot has passed its best years in terms of square-footage growth,'' said David A. Schick of SunTrust Robinson Humphrey. ''It is now a Sears in this world.''In fact, Home Depot, which is based in Atlanta and has 1,437 stores in North America, is still growing, with 200 more stores planned for next year, but it has saturated most markets, Mr. Schick said.Lowe's, meanwhile, which is based in Wilkesboro, N.C., is rapidly opening stores outside its Southeast stronghold. It now has 806 in 43 states and plans to open 130 more next year. The design of its stores has attracted customers, especially women, who dislike the warehouse shopping layout of Home Depot, analysts said. Lowe's features wider aisles, brighter lighting and more signs, and it stocks a larger selection of products for home decorating, like lamps, window treatments and designer towels, than is found in traditional Home Depot stores.Sales in stores open at least a year rose 6.8 percent at Lowe's in the second quarter over the period a year earlier, compared with a 1 percent gain at Home Depot. Earnings per share grew 40 percent for Lowe's and 28 percent for Home Depot.Some investors hope that Home Depot, known for its orange-accented stores, finds a new format to reinvigorate itself. With $5.9 billion in cash, versus $1.5 billion at Lowe's, it can afford to experiment. It has opened 50 Expo Design Centers, featuring home decor; five Home Depot Supply stores, catering to contractors; and a Home Depot Landscape Supply store. It plans to expand its installation business.Despite such ventures, said Dan Wewer an analyst for CIBC World Markets, Home Depot's track record ''isn't great.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/20/business/company-news-lowe-s-posts-42-increase-in-quarterly-profit.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S POSTS 42% INCREASE IN QUARTERLY PROFIT<date>Published: August 20, 2002</date><text>The Lowe's Companies reported a 42 percent increase in its second-quarter earnings yesterday, helped in large part by its expansion into big cities. The company, the home improvement retail chain, reported that profit for the quarter was $467.1 million, or 59 cents a share, up from $329.1 million, or 42 cents a share. Wall Street analysts had expected Lowe's to earn 54 cents a share, according to Thomson First Call. Shares of Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., rose $4.21, to $41. Sales were $7.49 billion, up 22 percent from $6.13 billion. Sales in stores that have been open at least a year rose 6.8 percent, up significantly from the 1.7 percent increase in same-store sales a year ago.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/21/business/company-news-lowe-s-profit-for-first-quarter-increased-54-percent.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S PROFIT FOR FIRST QUARTER INCREASED 54 PERCENT<date>Published: May 21, 2002</date><text>The Lowe's Companies' first-quarter profit rose 54 percent from a year earlier, easily surpassing Wall Street expectations, the company said yesterday. Lowe's, the world's second-largest home improvement retailer, behind Home Depot, also raised its expectations for the second quarter and the rest of the year. Lowe's posted a profit of $345.8 million, or 44 cents a share, for the first quarter, up from $225.3 million, or 29 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call had expected 36 cents a share. Sales increased 23 percent, to $6.47 billion from $5.28 billion a year earlier.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/26/business/profit-at-lowe-s-rose-55-in-4th-quarter.html?ref=lowescompanies">Profit at Lowe's Rose 55% in 4th Quarter<date>Published: February 26, 2002</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the nation's second-biggest home improvement retailer after Home Depot, said today that its fourth-quarter profit rose 55 percent, fueled largely by the eagerness of American consumers to invest more money in their homes.Net earnings totaled $218.4 million, or 28 cents a share, for the quarter ended Feb. 1, up from $140.8 million, or 18 cents a share, a year earlier.Lowe's said fourth-quarter sales increased 16.7 percent, to $5.3 billion from $4.54 billion a year earlier.The profit topped the forecast of 25 cents a share by Wall Street analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call.Lowe's stock rose $1.44, to $47.49.Lowe's also benefited from the continued strength of the housing market. Some homeowners refinanced their mortgages and freed cash for home improvement, Robert Tillman, the chief executive, said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/05/business/company-news-lowe-s-say-fourth-quarter-results-will-beat-forecast.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S SAY FOURTH-QUARTER RESULTS WILL BEAT FORECAST<date>Published: February 05, 2002</date><text>The home improvement retailer Lowe's Companies said yesterday that its fourth-quarter earnings would top forecasts, as mild winter weather spurred higher-than-expected sales. Lowe's, the No. 2 home improvement retailer, after Home Depot, said earnings in the quarter ended Feb. 1 would exceed its forecast of 22 cents to 24 cents a share because of margin growth and sales that topped expectations. Lowe's, which is based in Wilkesboro, N.C., said sales at stores open at least a year would grow more than its forecast of 3 percent to 5 percent for the quarter.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/20/business/company-news-third-quarter-earnings-increase-24-at-lowe-s.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; THIRD-QUARTER EARNINGS INCREASE 24% AT LOWE'S<date>Published: November 20, 2001</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the No. 2 home-improvement retailer behind Home Depot, said yesterday that its fiscal third-quarter earnings had risen 24 percent, aided by healthy sales and cost controls. Lowe's, which cited increasing customer traffic after Sept. 11, also said that it expected to meet Wall Street estimates for its fourth quarter, which ends in February. For the quarter ended Nov. 2, Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., had net income of $250.5 million, or 32 cents a diluted share, up from $202 million, or 26 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts on average had expected earnings of 31 cents a share. Sales for the quarter rose 21 percent, to $5.45 billion, from $4.5 billion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/21/business/profit-rises-at-home-improvement-retailer.html?ref=lowescompanies">Profit Rises at Home-Improvement Retailer<date>Published: August 21, 2001</date><text>The Lowe's Companies said today that its fiscal second-quarter profit rose 18 percent as the company, the second-largest home-improvement retailer, sold more appliances and paint and added stores.Net income rose to $329.1 million, or 42 cents a share, compared with $279.6 million, or 36 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue in the quarter ended Aug. 3 rose 16 percent, to $6.13 billion from $5.26 billion.Analysts had expected the company to earn 41 cents a share, according to Thomson Financial/First Call.Lowe's sold more washers and dryers and decorating goods as it added 21 stores and advertised on television across the country. Lowe's has been expanding in large markets including the Northeast to win customers from its larger rival, Home Depot, and has been using its big size to negotiate from suppliers better prices on products, analysts said.Shares of Lowe's, which is based in Wilkesboro, rose $2.80, to $37.84.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/29/business/a-do-it-yourselfer-takes-on-home-depot.html?ref=lowescompanies">A Do-It-Yourselfer Takes On Home Depot<date>Published: July 29, 2001</date><text>WALK into a Home Depot during the day, and one thing may strike you by its inescapable presence, another by its conspicuous absence.There will probably be a big display of energy-efficient wares right up front, under a colorful sign urging you to buy the products to prevent soaring energy prices from siphoning off your tax refund. But there will probably not be many forklifts clogging the aisles, or employees restocking the shelves.Robert L. Nardelli, who left General Electric to become chief executive of Home Depot in December, has engineered both. He has also made sure that Home Depot's people are clear about his time frame.''He tells us, 'I'm not looking at the calendar; I'm looking at my watch,' '' said Bryant Scott, president of Home Depot's chain of Expo Design Centers. These days, Home Depot restocks at night.And it does seem that everything at the company is moving faster these days. Mr. Nardelli, who calls himself the ''consummate do-it-yourselfer,'' has spent the last seven months installing management systems that Home Depot had never before imagined, and pressing the fast-forward button on ones it had just begun to consider.Using news about oil prices and tax cuts to push products? His idea. The push to restock shelves at night? Home Depot had been trying it out in a couple of stores, but Mr. Nardelli insisted that every store do it, and by year-end.''We'd have done all this anyway, but Bob really shifted us into high gear,'' said Gary Harvin, a regional vice president for Home Depot's mid-South operations.The company may be hitting high gear just in time. It is facing a big challenge from Lowe's, a fast-growing home-improvement chain based in Wilkesboro, N.C.Changes at Home Depot's headquarters here are even more drastic. Mr. Nardelli has wiped out a swath of group presidencies and placed several deposed chiefs in charge of areas he wants to see move even faster.Home Depot had been shuffling toward Internet sales and purchases, but it is now barreling ahead, under the aegis of Rebecca Bass, a new vice president whom Mr. Nardelli hired from a local dot-com.And he is codifying procedures that were generally seat-of-the-pants under Bernard Marcus and Arthur M. Blank, Home Depot's revered co-founders. There are now formal councils, with members from all levels of the company, to assess and improve how Home Depot handles inventory control, accounts payable and vendor relations.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/27/business/investing-home-depot-is-no-1-but-investors-like-no-2.html?ref=lowescompanies">Investing; Home Depot Is No. 1, But Investors Like No. 2<date>Published: May 27, 2001</date><text>ITS major competitor has nearly twice as many stores and about double its share of the $400 billion market for home improvement products.But on Wall Street, Lowe's Companies has been doing better than Home Depot. The shares of each company made lows of about $34 on Oct. 12; Lowe's now trades at $71.82, Home Depot at $52.28.This is despite the fact that the operating environment for both has been essentially the same.Doubts about the near-term future deepened last fall, when the impact of the Federal Reserve's efforts to slow the economy began to surface. Lumber prices, which represent about 10 percent of the business, softened considerably. And higher energy prices were cutting into consumers' disposable income.''Before it became apparent there were a lot of risks in the economy, people were willing to pay a premium for the industry leader,'' said Danielle Fox, an analyst at J. P. Morgan. ''But by the second half of last year, people discovered there was earnings risk everywhere, so why pay a lot for the stock? At the time, Lowe's was very, very cheap.''As the economy weakened and revenues suffered, Lowe's was more aggressive in cutting costs than was Home Depot.''The reason Lowe's has survived and thrived as No. 2 is because of their efficient structure and distribution,'' David Strasser, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said. ''They can probably do a better job on the cost side of the equation, but Home Depot is huge. They are the 800-pound gorilla.''Many factors that dampened enthusiasm last year have improved markedly in recent months.The Fed, which spent the first half of 2000 raising short-term interest rates, has lopped 2.5 percentage points off the overnight federal funds rate since January. Lower market interest rates have sparked a surge in home-mortgage refinancings. Lumber prices are sharply higher. Sales of both new and existing homes remain healthy. And consumer confidence appears to be improving.Last week, when Lowe's reported its first-quarter earnings, those factors led Robert L. Tillman, the chairman and chief executive, to predict better times for his company in the second half.Lowe's had a 20 percent increase in earnings for the quarter despite tepid sales in stores open at least a year. More than half the gain reflected a calendar shift that stretched the quarter an additional week, into May. Earnings rose 8 percent after adjusting for the extra time. On Friday, the company announced a two-for-one stock split and a higher dividend.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/22/business/lowe-s-reports-20-profit-rise.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's Reports 20% Profit Rise<date>Published: May 22, 2001</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the nation's second-biggest home improvement retailer, reported a 20.4 percent gain in profits in its first quarter, surpassing Wall Street's expectations.The strong results, announced today, were achieved despite new store investments, a slowing economy and a competitive retail environment, the company said. Lowe's is second to Home Depot in home improvement retailing.For the three months ended May 4, Lowe's earned $225.3 million, or 58 cents a share, compared with $187.2 million, or 49 cents a share, a year earlier.Analysts polled by Thomson Financial/First Call had expected earnings of 54 cents a share in the latest period.Sales for the quarter increased 18.1 percent, to $5.3 billion from $4.7 billion.Sales at stores open at least a year, known as same-store sales, were down 3 percent. Results were hurt by deflation in lumber and building materials, the company said.During the first quarter, Lowe's opened 37 new stores, including 5 relocations of older, smaller stores. Two older, smaller stores were closed. At the end of the quarter, Lowe's operated 680 stores.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/06/business/lowe-s-to-test-appliances.html?ref=lowescompanies">Lowe's to Test Appliances<date>Published: March 06, 2001</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, which sells such appliance brands as Maytag and Whirlpool, said today that it would test sales of the Viking Range Corporation's high-priced stoves and refrigerators to attract more affluent customers. Lowe's will begin selling the appliances by special order at Lowe's stores in Las Vegas this month. They will be sold in conjunction with SunWest Appliance Distributing of Tempe, Ariz., Lowe's said. Viking stoves are sold for $2,700 to $8,500, said Dale Persons, Viking's vice president for market support. Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., trails Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company in United States retail appliance sales. Lowe's shares rose 5 cents, to $57.15.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/07/business/company-news-lowe-s-plans-to-build-75-stores-in-northeast.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S PLANS TO BUILD 75 STORES IN NORTHEAST<date>Published: February 07, 2001</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, the home improvement retailer, plans to build more than 75 stores from Philadelphia to Maine the next five years, including 25 in the Boston area. The $1.3 billion expansion will begin on Feb. 24 with a new store in Danvers, Mass., north of Boston. A second store in Brockton, south of Boston, is expected to open later this year. Also under construction in Massachusetts are Lowe's stores in Worcester and North Attleboro. Lowe's will open its first store in the New York City area this spring in North Bergen, N.J. It also plans to increase its presence in Philadelphia and Pittsburgh and to open its first store in the Providence, R.I., market later this year. Each outlet will employ about 175 people, creating over 13,000 jobs in the Northeast.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/business/company-news-lowe-s-same-store-sales-to-miss-forecasts.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S SAME-STORE SALES TO MISS FORECASTS<date>Published: October 07, 2000</date><text>The Lowe's Companies said fiscal third-quarter same-store sales would miss forecasts because of lower lumber and building materials prices and the integration of the Eagle Hardware and Garden Inc. chain. Lowe's said sales at stores open at least a year would rise at a ''low-single'' digit percentage rate in the quarter ending Oct. 27, less than the 4 percent to 6 percent gain it previously expected. Sales were hurt as Lowe's converted the Eagle chain into its own stores. Lowe's, based in Wilkesboro, N.C., bought Eagle last year for $1 billion in stock. Sluggish sales at Lowe's, the nation's No. 2 home-improvement chain after Home Depot, come as rising interest rates and gasoline prices push consumers to slow spending, analysts said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/13/business/who-s-minding-the-store-jdn-realty-is-in-disarray-after-a-series-of-disclosures.html?ref=lowescompanies">Who's Minding the Store?; JDN Realty Is in Disarray After a Series of Disclosures<date>Published: April 13, 2000</date><text>Correction AppendedFirst the founder was in charge. But then came an accounting scandal, and he stepped aside -- sort of. Replacing him were two other executives: his wife and the man who oversaw accounting. But then another accounting scandal became public yesterday, and they stepped aside, too -- sort of.Who's running the company this morning? A member of the board who has supposedly been overseeing the company's executives since the day it went public in 1994.This is JDN Realty, an Atlanta-based real estate investment trust that was one of the industry's most respected firms in the 1990's. It is also one of the prime developers for Wal-Mart Stores. But in the last two months, JDN disclosed that it had been making under-the-table payments to two of its own executives for years, that it improperly billed its two largest clients, that it defaulted on its main bank loan and that it would have to restate all of its earnings since 1994. Law firms across the country have filed class-action lawsuits. With the latest announcement yesterday, JDN's stock has dropped 43 percent since February.''The more you look into this, the stranger it gets,'' said Patrick S. McGurn, a vice president at Institutional Shareholder Services, which advises large investors on corporate governance issues. ''There is so much wrong with this that it's almost the plot for a satire.''More seriously, management experts say, JDN's travails offer a case study of the problems that can befall a public company that continues to operate like a private one. At a time when companies are going public at a record rate, and many are flouting widely accepted management guidelines, the lessons are particularly relevant. At the core of JDN's troubles, corporate governance specialists say, is a board that is too closely aligned with management to be an effective advocate for shareholders. The directors are a small inbred group -- mostly men who have business ties to JDN or personal ties to J. Donald Nichols, the founder, and his wife, Elizabeth. Most have been board members since the company went public in 1994. The board even lacks a nominating committee.JDN executives, through a spokesman, and board members declined to comment. A lawyer investigating the company's problems on behalf of the board said the directors had aggressively responded to the company's problems. ''The interests of the shareholders have been paramount in their minds,'' said John Latham, a partner at Alston &amp; Bird in Atlanta.Correction: April 15, 2000, Saturday An article in Business Day on Thursday about troubles at JDN Realty misattributed a statement made during a February conference call held by Elizabeth Nichols, the company's president, and William J. Kerley, a former executive. Mr. Kerley said that the company's former chairman, J. Donald Nichols, did not appear to have benefited personally from improper payments made to other employees. The statement was not made by Ms. Nichols, who is married to Mr. Nichols.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/10/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-lowe-s-awards-broadcast-account.html?ref=lowescompanies">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Lowe's Awards Broadcast Account<date>Published: May 10, 1999</date><text>The Lowe's Companies in North Wilkesboro, N.C., the national home-improvement retailer, has awarded its broadcast advertising account, effective July 1, to McCann-Erickson New York.The account, with billings estimated at $100 million, had been handled since 1990 by the Southfield, Mich., office of Doner.The decision came Friday after a 10-week review that began with 16 agencies. A list of six finalists announced in March was later pared to McCann-Erickson and the Playa del Rey, Calif., office of TBWA/Chiat/ Day, part of the TBWA Worldwide unit of Omnicom Group. Print campaigns continue to be handled in-house.McCann-Erickson, which will also handle strategic planning and media buying for Lowe's, will work on the assignments from offices in New York, Houston and Los Angeles and offices to be opened in North Wilkesboro and Tampa, Fla.The agency is part of the McCann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising unit of McCann-Erickson World Group, owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/10/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-6-finalists-named-in-review-by-lowe-s.html?ref=lowescompanies">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; 6 Finalists Named In Review by Lowe's<date>Published: March 10, 1999</date><text>The Lowe's Companies in North Wilkesboro, N.C., the home-improvement retail chain, said yesterday that it had narrowed a review for its broadcast advertising account to six finalists. Billings for the account, which has been handled by Doner in Southfield, Mich., since 1990, were estimated at $100 million.The finalists are Doner; the Leo Burnett Company in Chicago; D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles in New York, a unit of MacManus Group; McCann-Erickson New York, part of the McCann-Erickson World Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies; TBWA/Chiat/ Day in Playa del Rey, Calif., part of the TBWA Worldwide unit of Omnicom Group, and J. Walter Thompson Detroit, part of the J. Walter Thompson unit of WPP Group P.L.C. A decision is expected in the second quarter.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/26/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-lowe-s-sets-review-of-broadcast-account.html?ref=lowescompanies">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Lowe's Sets Review Of Broadcast Account<date>Published: February 26, 1999</date><text>Lowe's Companies, the home-improvement retail chain, said yesterday that it would begin a review for its broadcast advertising account, which has been at Doner in Southfield, Mich., since 1990. Billings were estimated at $100 million.Because Lowe's ''is in the midst of the most aggressive expansion program'' in its history, said Brian Peace, a spokesman in North Wilkesboro, N.C., the company thought ''it was a prudent time to move forward and explore'' its agency options. Doner has agreed to participate in the review, Mr. Peace said, adding that 15 agencies, which he declined to identify, had been invited to take part. A final decision is expected in the second quarter.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/01/01/business/company-news-request-from-ftc-delays-merger-of-lowe-s-and-eagle.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; REQUEST FROM F.T.C. DELAYS MERGER OF LOWE'S AND EAGLE<date>Published: January 01, 1999</date><text>Two hardware retailers -- the Lowe's Companies and Eagle Hardware and Garden Inc. -- pushed the closing date of their merger back to late in the first quarter of 1999 after regulators sought additional antitrust information, the companies said yesterday. Company officials declined to disclose details of the revised Federal Trade Commission filing. In the $1 billion stock deal, Lowe's is acquiring 35 Eagle Hardware stores in 10 Western states. Lowe's, based in North Wilkesboro, N.C., operates 473 stores in 26 states. The companies had expected the deal to close early in the first quarter before the F.T.C.'s request for a ''full review'' of proxy materials.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/29/business/business-diary-a-week-of-merging-exuberantly.html?ref=lowescompanies">BUSINESS: DIARY; A Week of Merging Exuberantly<date>Published: November 29, 1998</date><text>If you've grown a good bit bigger lately on account of heroic feats of ingestion, well, you might just be a corporation. The red button has not yet popped up on two big deals in the oven, Exxon-Mobil and Deutsche Bank-Bankers Trust, but last week yielded plenty of other done-to-a-turn merger and acquisition announcements.Among the $1 billion-plus highlights of the merger parade were these:America Online agreed to buy Netscape Communications for $4.2 billion, creating a company that, through a separate but related alliance with Sun Microsystems, might just become the first real threat to Microsoft in many a moon. International Paper said it would buy Union Camp for $5 billion in stock. AMP escaped a $9.7 billion hostile offer from Allied Signal when Tyco International rode in as a white knight to buy AMP for $11.3 billion.Two big disability insurers, Provident and UNUM, agreed to merge in a $4.8 billion deal. B. F. Goodrich said it would acquire Coltec, a leading aircraft-parts maker, for $2.2 billion. Lowe's, the No. 2 home improvement retailer, behind Home Depot, said it would buy Eagle Hardware and Garden in a $1 billion stock swap.In Britain, Siebe said it would acquire BTR, descendant of the old British Tire and Rubber, for $6.13 billion; the combined company would be the largest maker of industrial controls. Viag A.G., Germany's No. 3 utility, agreed to buy Algroup, a diversified Swiss manufacturer, in a stock swap worth $8.7 billion.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/24/business/company-news-lowe-s-to-acquire-eagle-hardware-and-garden.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S TO ACQUIRE EAGLE HARDWARE AND GARDEN<date>Published: November 24, 1998</date><text>The Lowe's Companies, a home-improvement store chain, will purchase Eagle Hardware and Garden Inc. in a $1 billion stock swap. Lowe's, the nation's second-largest do-it-yourself warehouse chain behind Home Depot, said late on Sunday that buying the 32-store chain in nine Western states would help it realize its expansion plans. Lowe's will issue shares to Eagle's shareholders valued at $29 per Eagle share. Eagle's shares rose 31.25 cents yesterday, to $27.8125, in Nasdaq trading, and Lowe's shares rose $1.6875, to $41.25, on the New York Stock Exchange. Eagle, based in Renton, Wash., operates warehouse home-improvement centers in nine Western states and employs more than 6,000 workers. Lowe's, based in North Wilkesboro, N.C., operates 465 stores in 26 states, with more than 65,000 employees.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/04/business/kmart-seeking-home-improvement-merger.html?ref=lowescompanies">Kmart Seeking Home Improvement Merger<date>Published: February 04, 1997</date><text>The Kmart Corporation and Waban Inc. said yesterday that they were negotiating to combine Kmart's Builders Square stores and Waban's Homebase chain, forming an independent company that would be the third-largest retail home improvement chain in the nation with 250 stores and annual revenue of $4 billion.The deal, the terms of which were not disclosed, is part of the trend toward consolidation in the retail home improvement industry. It would allow both companies to divest themselves of businesses that analysts say were not their forte. Kmart had hoped to shed the Builders Square chain by the end of last year as part of a strategy to focus on core operations.''There is opportunity here to create a large, financially liquid home improvement business which can be competitive on a national basis,'' said Marvin P. Rich, Kmart's executive vice president for strategic planning, finance and administration.Several analysts familiar with both Kmart and Waban said neither company had been particularly successful in the do-it-yourself retail business, making the proposed deal a smart strategic move for both. They also said they expected further consolidation in the mature and highly competitive market dominated by the Home Depot chain.''I think the competition proved to be real tough.'' said Sheldon Grodsky of Grodsky Associates Inc. ''There are a lot of also-rans in the world of home improvement centers and very few Home Depots.''For Waban, the transaction has the potential to better increase shareholder value than a previously announced plan to separate its BJ's Wholesale Club and Homebase divisions through a spinoff of BJ's, said Herbert J. Zarkin, the company's president and chief executive. ''Therefore, we have suspended activities related to the spinoff to allow time to consider this transaction.'' Waban is a warehouse merchandising company based in Natick, Mass.Leonard Green &amp; Partners, a private merchant-banking firm specializing in management buyouts, is negotiating with the two companies and would become majority owner of the new company, although the parent companies would not say how much of a stake they would retain. Nor would they comment on the value of the deal. It is also unclear if Kmart will receive anything for its chain.This would be Kmart's second deal with Leonard Green, which is based in Los Angeles.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/01/business/company-briefs-015830.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: May 01, 1996</date><text>STERLING HEALTHCARE GROUP INC., Coral Gables, Fla., a hospital and medical service company, said it had hired an investment bank to explore methods of growth, possibly through acquisitions or a merger.LOWE'S COS., North Wilkesboro, N.C., the nation's No. 2 home-improvement retailer, plans to add 60 stores this year, primarily in new markets. CAMERON ASHLEY BUILDING PRODUCTS INC., Dallas, a distributor of building materials, agreed to acquire California Roofers Supply, a unit of Star Inc., for undisclosed terms.SHERWIN-WILLIAMS CO., Cleveland, a paint manufacturer, bought Industria Quimica Elgin of Brazil, which sells paints under the brand name Colorgin. Terms were not disclosed.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/08/business/company-news-lowe-s-sets-2-for-1-stock-split-and-cash-dividend.html?ref=lowescompanies">COMPANY NEWS; LOWE'S SETS 2-FOR-1 STOCK SPLIT AND CASH DIVIDEND<date>Published: March 08, 1994</date><text>The Lowe's Companies said yesterday that its board had announced a 2-for-1 stock split and declared a dividend of 4 cents a share on the post-split shares. The cash payout equals the 8 cents a share paid on the shares before the split, Lowe's said. The company, based in North Wilkesboro, N.C., sells home-improvement products. The split is effective on March 31 for holders of record March 16, the company said. Its stock rose 37.5 cents yesterday, to $65.75, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/01/28/business/the-media-business-advertising-top-candidate-withdraws-in-levine-huntley-search.html?ref=lowescompanies">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING: Top Candidate Withdraws In Levine Huntley Search<date>Published: January 28, 1991</date><text>LEVINE HUNTLEY SCHMIDTBEAVER, a midsize New York agency whose clients include Subaru and Maidenform, was rocked earlier this month by the resignations of two top executives, Robert Schmidt and Tony DeGregorio. Now it has been dealt another blow.The anticipated replacement for Mr. Schmidt, who resigned as chairman two weeks ago, had been Andrew Langer, the chief executive of the Lowe Group. But Mr. Langer said in an internal memo released at his agency last Friday that he had decided not to defect to Levine Huntley.Industry executives were surprised that Mr. Langer had backed out. He had evidently been offered a good deal, which included equity in Levine Huntley, which has billings of about $250 million.Mr. Langer would not comment, but some executives said the negotiations were ambushed by articles in the trade press, The New York Times and The Wall Street Journal speculating that Mr. Langer would take charge of Levine Huntley. Because of the articles, some of the Lowe Group's biggest clients reportedly put pressure on Mr. Langer to make a decision on any moves before all the details in the Levine Huntley deal could be worked out.Harold Levine, the co-founder and acting chairman of Levine Huntley, would not comment on Mr. Langer's status. Mr. Levine said the agency was interviewing a number of well-qualified candidates and would make a choice late this week.At the moment, Levine Huntley does not appear to be looking for a replacement for Mr. DeGregorio, the creative director who left with Mr. Schmidt.With Mr. Langer out of the picture, one of the most likely candidates for the job is Edward Vick, the former president of AmmiratiPuris who is not now affiliated with any agency. Levine Huntley has reportedly been talking with Mr. Vick, but Mr. Levine said he would not comment on any possible candidates. Mr. Vick could not be reached for comment.Industry executives said Mr. Vick is an experienced account executive who would add the right balance at Levine Huntley, an agency largely driven by creative expertise. The executives also said Mr. Vick would be reassuring to clients because he had proved he could run a midsize agency in a well-organized way.That may be just what Levine Huntley is looking for. One reason for the agency's urgency in finding a new chairman -- this kind of search usually takes three months or more -- is concern that one of its leading clients, Subaru, may be stolen away.Since the resignation of Mr. Schmidt, who had close ties to Subaru, the car maker has been innudated with offers from other agencies. But Thomas R. Gibson, the president and chief operating officer of Subaru of America Inc., said there had been no trouble between Levine Huntley and Subaru.But he also said Subaru was paying close attention to Levine Huntley's executive search. "It is a concern for us," he said. "We are obviously very interested in who takes the job."</text></article></page><page index="10" /></root>
