<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="National Oilwell Varco Inc"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/18/business/18drill.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">Toolmaker for Oilfields Buys a Rival for $7 Billion<date>Published: December 18, 2007</date><text>HOUSTON (AP)  The oilfield services provider National Oilwell Varco said on Monday that it had agreed to buy the drilling-products maker Grant Prideco Inc. for about $7.37 billion, further consolidating the drilling sector. The two companies make and sell equipment and tools used in the production of oil and gas. Grant Prideco’s products include the pipe used to drill wells. “We believe Grant Prideco’s product range will add new, growing market segments to National Oilwell Varco and benefit our customers’ needs worldwide,” said Merrill A. Miller Jr., National Oilwell’s chairman and chief executive. National Oilwell reported sales of $2.58 billion in the third quarter; Grant Prideco posted sales of $539.9 million. National Oilwell is offering a combination of cash and stock currently valued at $58 a share, a 22.2 percent premium to Grant Prideco’s closing price of $47.46 on Friday. Grant Prideco had 127 million shares outstanding as of its last quarterly statement with regulators. Grant Prideco shareholders will receive $23.20 in cash and 0.4498 of a share of National Oilwell Varco for each Grant Prideco share. National Oilwell expects the deal to add to earnings and cash flow and save $40 million in costs next year. The transaction is not expected to affect Grant Prideco’s pending sale of its tubular businesses to Vallourec. Shares of Grant Prideco shares rose $6.45, to $53.91. Shares of National Oilwell Varco fell $6.68, to $70.69. Combined, the two companies will have a market capitalization of about $32 billion. Stockholders of National Oilwell Varco will own 86 percent of the combined company and stockholders of Grant Prideco will own 14 percent. The deal still requires approval by shareholders of Grant Prideco as well as regulatory approvals. The Grant Prideco stockholder meeting is expected to take place in the first quarter or early second quarter of 2008. More Articles in Business »HOUSTON (AP)  The oilfield services provider National Oilwell Varco said on Monday that it had agreed to buy the drilling-products maker Grant Prideco Inc. for about $7.37 billion, further consolidating the drilling sector. The two companies make and sell equipment and tools used in the production of oil and gas. Grant Prideco’s products include the pipe used to drill wells. “We believe Grant Prideco’s product range will add new, growing market segments to National Oilwell Varco and benefit our customers’ needs worldwide,” said Merrill A. Miller Jr., National Oilwell’s chairman and chief executive. National Oilwell reported sales of $2.58 billion in the third quarter; Grant Prideco posted sales of $539.9 million. National Oilwell is offering a combination of cash and stock currently valued at $58 a share, a 22.2 percent premium to Grant Prideco’s closing price of $47.46 on Friday. Grant Prideco had 127 million shares outstanding as of its last quarterly statement with regulators. Grant Prideco shareholders will receive $23.20 in cash and 0.4498 of a share of National Oilwell Varco for each Grant Prideco share. National Oilwell expects the deal to add to earnings and cash flow and save $40 million in costs next year. The transaction is not expected to affect Grant Prideco’s pending sale of its tubular businesses to Vallourec. Shares of Grant Prideco shares rose $6.45, to $53.91. Shares of National Oilwell Varco fell $6.68, to $70.69. Combined, the two companies will have a market capitalization of about $32 billion. Stockholders of National Oilwell Varco will own 86 percent of the combined company and stockholders of Grant Prideco will own 14 percent. The deal still requires approval by shareholders of Grant Prideco as well as regulatory approvals. The Grant Prideco stockholder meeting is expected to take place in the first quarter or early second quarter of 2008.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/13/business/company-news-national-oilwell-to-buy-varco-international.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL TO BUY VARCO INTERNATIONAL<date>Published: August 13, 2004</date><text>National-Oilwell, a maker of oil and gas drilling equipment, agreed to buy Varco International for about $2.4 billion in stock, extending a four-year expansion. Shareholders of Varco will receive 0.8363 share of National-Oilwell for each of their shares, the companies said. The transaction values Varco at $24.30 a share, above its closing price Wednesday of $23.62 a share. National-Oilwell has acquired 21 companies since 2000. The combination would create the nation's largest equipment maker for oil field services companies, surpassing FMC Technologies. Both companies are based in Houston.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/18/business/company-news-national-oilwell-acquires-halliburton-pumping-unit.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL ACQUIRES HALLIBURTON PUMPING UNIT<date>Published: January 18, 2003</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc., a maker of equipment for oil and natural gas drilling, said it had bought the Halliburton Company's pumping-equipment business for about $89.2 million in stock and cash to expand its product range. The company paid $22.7 million in cash and 3.2 million in newly issued shares for the unit, known as Monoflo Inc. in the United States and the Mono Group in Britain. The acquisition will increase operating profit by $18 million and add 5 cents a share to 2003 earnings, the company said. Both National-Oilwell and Halliburton are based in Houston.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/17/business/company-news-national-oilwell-is-buying-iri-for-320-million-in-stock.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL IS BUYING IRI FOR $320 MILLION IN STOCK<date>Published: March 17, 2000</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire the IRI International Corporation for $320 million, about $8.04 a share in stock. Both companies are based in Houston, and both make oil drilling equipment. IRI's stock rose $2.125, to $7.875; National-Oil rose $2.75, to $26.50. National-Oil said the two companies had complementary businesses. National-Oil focuses more on offshore drilling, while IRI concentrates more on land drilling. The companies also make different types of tools used in oil wells. National-Oil had $745.2 million in revenue in 1999, while IRI had $92.2 million in revenue.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/12/business/company-news-national-oilwell-to-buy-hitec-maker-of-drilling-gear.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL TO BUY HITEC, MAKER OF DRILLING GEAR<date>Published: October 12, 1999</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc. agreed yesterday to acquire Hitec A.S., a Norwegian maker of oil and gas drilling equipment, for $125 million in stock and cash. In the transaction, National-Oilwell will issue 8 million shares and pay about $20 million for Hitec's shares outstanding. National-Oilwell, based in Houston, makes machinery and equipment used in oil and gas drilling and production. It had revenue of $344.3 million in the six months ended June 30. Hitec specializes in automation and remote-control technologies used in drilling for oil and gas. It reported revenue of $180.4 million for fiscal 1998. Shares of National-Oilwell rose 62.5 cents to close at $13.125 on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/08/business/company-news-national-oilwell-acquires-ce-drilling-for-65-million.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL ACQUIRES CE DRILLING FOR $65 MILLION<date>Published: July 08, 1999</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc., an oil services provider, said yesterday that it had bought CE Drilling Products Inc. for about $65 million in cash. CE Drilling, with sales of about $100 million last year, makes Emsco drilling machinery and Wilson mobile rigs. National-Oilwell, with sales of $1.17 billion last year, designs, makes and distributes equipment used in oil and natural gas drilling. The Houston-based National-Oilwell said its sales would probably decline this year from 1998 as exploration companies struggle to recover from a slump in oil prices. National-Oilwell expects to increase profit by providing parts and services to current CE Drilling customers.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/10/business/company-news-national-oilwell-acquiring-a-business-from-westburne.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL ACQUIRING A BUSINESS FROM WESTBURNE<date>Published: November 10, 1998</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc. agreed yesterday to buy Westburne Inc.'s oil and natural-gas field-supply business for about $58.6 million in stock and debt securities to expand its services in Canada and to cut operating costs. National-Oilwell will give the Montreal-based Westburne three million shares of its common stock and will issue a short-term note for $6.5 million. The debt will be recouped through the sale of the Westburne division's excess inventory. National-Oilwell, based in Houston, makes equipment for oil and gas drilling and production. Its shares fell $1.4375, to $15.9375, on the New York Stock Exchange. Westburne's shares rose 5 cents, to $14 (Canadian), in Toronto.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/14/business/company-news-national-oilwell-in-deal-for-phoenix-energy-products.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; NATIONAL-OILWELL IN DEAL FOR PHOENIX ENERGY PRODUCTS<date>Published: May 14, 1998</date><text>National-Oilwell Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the privately held Phoenix Energy Products Inc. for $115 million plus $35 million in assumed debt. Phoenix Energy Products, based in Odessa, Tex., makes oilfield equipment. National-Oilwell, based in Houston, makes machinery, equipment and tools used in oil and gas drilling and production. It had revenue of $301.9 million in the quarter that ended March 31. Shares of National-Oilwell rose 12.5 cents yesterday, to $39.4375.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/24/business/company-briefs-842395.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: May 24, 1995</date><text>ARMCO INC., Parsippany, N.J., and USX Corp., Pittsburgh, said they planned to sell their joint venture, National-Oilwell, a supplier of oilfield pipe and equipment, to a group including Duff &amp; Phelps Corp., Chicago, and Bain Capital of Boston. Terms were not disclosed.W. R. GRACE &amp; CO., Boca Raton, Fla., said its Grace Dearborn unit would team up with Allied Colloids Group P.L.C., a British chemicals maker, to sell products to the water treatment and pulp and paper industries.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/11/04/business/company-news-usx-and-armco-cancel-accord-to-sell-unit.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; USX AND ARMCO CANCEL ACCORD TO SELL UNIT<date>Published: November 04, 1992</date><text>The USX Corporation and Armco Inc. said yesterday that they had terminated an agreement to sell their 50-50 partnership in a manufacturer of oilfield equipment to Empresas Lanzagorta, a Mexican company, because of slumping demand for the equipment and the weak performance of National-Oilwell, which lost $20.4 million in the first nine months of the year.Armco and USX will continue to operate Houston-based National-Oilwell, which employs about 3,000 people at plants around the world; a spokesman said the company was moving toward breaking even.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/09/17/business/company-news-usx-and-armco-agree-to-sell-oil-machinery-company.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; USX AND ARMCO AGREE TO SELL OIL MACHINERY COMPANY<date>Published: September 17, 1992</date><text>The USX Corporation and Armco Inc. said yesterday that they had agreed to sell their 50-50 partnership in a manufacturer of oil-field equipment to Empresas Lanzagorta, a Mexican company.USX, based in Pittsburgh, will receive $120 million in cash and notes for its interest in National-Oilwell, the Houston-based manufacturer. Armco, based in Parsippany, N.J., will receive $70 million in cash, as well as subordinated notes and a 15 percent equity interest in the new enterprise formed by Empresas. Armco said the transaction is expected to result in a loss to Armco of $25 million to $35 million. USX spokesman William Keslar said the company has not determined the financial impact of the sale.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/03/31/business/company-news-usx-and-armco-to-sell-venture.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; USX and Armco To Sell Venture<date>Published: March 31, 1992</date><text>The USX Corporation and Armco Inc. said they had agreed to sell their National-Oilwell joint venture to the Mexican company Empresas Lanzagorta S.A. for cash and notes in a deal worth more than $242.5 million. Under the agreement, USX will receive $110 million cash and $27.5 million in subordinated notes for its 50 percent ownership of National-Oilwell. Armco, based in Parsippany, N.J., will receive $90 million cash, $15 million in subordinated notes and a 15 percent equity stake in the new enterprise formed by the Mexican company.National-Oilwell is an oilfield machinery and equipment manufacturer formed when units of USX and Armco merged in 1986. Empresas Lanzagorta, based in Mexico City, manufactures a variety of equipment, including oilfield machinery.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/04/07/business/company-news-usx-armco-unit.html?ref=nationaloilwellvarcoinc">COMPANY NEWS; USX-Armco Unit<date>Published: April 07, 1987</date><text>The USX Corporation and Armco Inc. have merged their oilfield-equipment divisions, after failing to find buyers for the businesses last year. Armco said a new company, National-Oilwell, was being formed from Armco's National Supply Company and USX's Oilwell division. Its headquarters will be in Houston. Both units reported 1986 losses, but officials declined to disclose the amounts and predicted the new company would have a modest profit in 1987.</text></article></page><page index="3" /><page index="4" /><page index="5" /><page index="6" /><page index="7" /><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
