<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Norfolk Southern Corp"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/business/27surcharge.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Shippers May Raise Fuel Surcharges<date>Published: April 26, 2011</date><text>These should be good times for railroads and trucking companies. After all, an improving economy means that more goods and commodities need to be delivered to the nation’s ports and department stores.But rising fuel prices have taken a toll on their business. With diesel prices near their highest levels since 2008, the impact has started to appear in the first-quarter results of companies like Union Pacific railroad and the Arkansas Best Corporation, which has a trucking subsidiary. Some shippers said they expected to raise fuel surcharges. The timing, some economists say, could not be worse. Consumers are already paying steeper prices at the gas pump and may see prices climb in stores if diesel prices remain high. American manufacturers, meanwhile, are struggling to get back on their feet. “The manufacturing sector is hit disproportionately hard by higher diesel prices,” said Donald A. Norman, economist for the Manufacturers Alliance/MAPI, a public policy and economics research organization in Arlington, Va. “Simply to move all this stuff around, it is really hard to affect any cost savings. You have little in the way of alternatives.” Brandon Gale, the president of Retail Shipping Associates, said it was only a matter of time before the high fuel prices affected consumers. “It is a very straight-line relationship,” he said. “When you see fuel at the pump going up, it is going to go up at the package, too.” Crude oil prices started going up early this year as turmoil spread through the oil-producing regions of the Middle East and North Africa. Increased global demand for fuel has added to the pressure on prices. On Monday, the average price for a gallon of highway diesel was $4.09, according to the Energy Information Administration, which posts fuel prices every week based on a survey of outlets around the country. The current averages are in the highest range since 2008, when prices peaked at $4.76 on July 14, and more than a dollar higher than in 2010. The Energy Information Administration price functions as a reference point for trucking companies negotiating fuel surcharges with shippers. Railroads can use a less expensive type of diesel that does not reflect the highway taxes. While some railroad companies say their businesses can benefit from higher diesel prices because shippers may migrate to trains from trucks, they are still paying millions of dollars more for fuel. Last week, Union Pacific said in its report on the first quarter that it paid average diesel fuel prices of $2.88 a gallon, up 33 percent from the same period in 2010. The higher costs — the company said it paid about $200 million more for fuel in the quarter than the same period in 2010 — sliced 8 cents off the company’s $1.29 in earnings per share. Even so, the earnings were the company’s highest for any first quarter in its history. The company has already imposed fuel surcharges to recoup some of its higher costs. And while it did not say directly whether it would raise its surcharges, Tom Lange, a company spokesman, said, “It is how we are addressing it.” Another railroad company, the CSX Corporation, said in its first-quarter results report this month that higher fuel costs added $119 million to expenses in the year, bringing fuel costs to $402 million. Norfolk Southern reports its quarterly results on Wednesday. Railroad companies can benefit in some ways from higher oil prices. When oil prices rise, so do the prices of other commodities, a signal of brisk demand for what is a large component of train freight. “You can’t look at rising oil prices in a vacuum,” said H. Peter Nesvold, a managing director for research at Jefferies &amp; Company. “It actually helps the volumes at the rails.” In addition, some cargo usually moves to trains when diesel prices are high because they are more fuel efficient than trucks, industry officials said. “Fuel costs are an important factor for us; it costs us more money to do what we do,” said John T. Gray, a senior vice president for the Association of American Railroads. “Fortunately, it costs our competitors typically more money than it costs us.” He added, “If what we saw in 2008 happens now, there will probably be some customers that will seek out rail service that have not in the past.” 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/12/sports/football/12jets.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conductor Who Told Jets No Puts Family First<date>Published: December 11, 2010</date><text>HAMPTON, Ga. — Keith Fitzhugh, America’s most celebrated train conductor, rose for work at 4:30 on Friday morning. He drove roughly 120 miles north to Dalton, punched in at Norfolk Southern and donned his bright yellow safety vest and the orange hat that signified his trainee status.The three previous days felt like a dream. He held interviews with ABC’s Diane Sawyer, CNN and ESPN; took a congratulatory phone call from his company’s president; received an inquiry from a game show; and experienced several firsts, including wearing makeup, for the cameras. Late Thursday night, his living room here was a testament to the power of his story and the 24-hour news cycle. Tripods had left imprints on the blue carpet. Couches and chairs were pushed against the walls. All this stemmed from what Fitzhugh, 24, did not do: accept an offer to rejoin the Jets for an undetermined time. Because of the way he had conducted himself, choosing family over football, he became an overnight sensation, an example, in this economy, of values and virtue and, corny as it sounds, doing the right thing. “I had no idea any of this was coming,” Fitzhugh said. “I’m just a normal guy. I work on the railroad.” That was the point, right? Fitzhugh is a normal guy, a former safety with typical problems, struggles and a job in transportation. He lives with his parents: Keith Sr., a former truck driver who had two hip replacements and now uses a cane to get around the house, and Meltonia, an office supervisor for a freight company, the family rock. Fitzhugh loves trains. Really, really loves trains, so much so that in college, he paid a few hundred dollars to install a train horn in his Dodge Magnum. When the Jets called, Fitzhugh had about 30 minutes to decide. N.F.L. teams keep shortlists of available players in case of injury, but the summoned must leave immediately or teams move on. There is no sleeping on it. Later, Fitzhugh found out Norfolk Southern would have granted him a leave. Had he known that, he would have taken it. But he did not. Heart thumping, mind racing, Fitzhugh thought about the money, $5,200 a week on the practice squad, less expenses, taxed at a higher rate. He thought about the N.F.L. puppy mill that had discarded him three times. Mostly, he thought about his family. Thanks, but no thanks, he told the Jets. To the outside world, this was unusual. But to Fitzhugh’s fifth-grade teacher, it was simply Keith. “Didn’t surprise me one bit,” Diane Cameron, his former teacher, said. “That kid would be a success story if he was living on the street.” In school, Cameron continued, Fitzhugh challenged even teachers to footraces, excelled at math and declared he would play professional football. He also rambled on often about trains. His parents met in high school, and when Meltonia moved to Florida, Keith Sr. chased her, showed up unannounced and proposed. Thirty-four years later, they have raised three children on the tenets of faith and family. They had rules. Come home. Clean house. Do homework. Eat dinner, together, every night. Their youngest, Brittany, died at 14 from complications of the West Nile virus or another illness. The Fitzhughs are not sure. If the family was strong before her death, it was impenetrable afterward. Less than a mile from the family home, Norfolk Southern’s freight trains rumbled parallel to Tara Boulevard. Fitzhugh watched them while he ate at restaurants or sat at stoplights. Each time, he felt a familiar longing, a hope for conductors to blow the horn. If they did, he could hear it even at home. Early on, he played with train sets, the tracks snaking around the living room. Fitzhugh took his first passenger train trip from New York to Atlanta as a child. He sat for hours, silent, staring out the window, entranced by the animals and changing scenery. The feeling hooked him. Freedom is the best way he can describe it. Before the Jets re-signed and released him in August, Fitzhugh applied to several railroads, including the most familiar, Norfolk Southern. He entered the company’s training program in September, just as his N.F.L. money was running out. Fitzhugh works at least 40 hours a week, sometimes in 12-hour shifts, sometimes on trains, sometimes in the yard. He has helped transport a variety of shipments — he declined to say what — as far as from Atlanta to Chattanooga, Tenn. But nothing beats the engine room, with its two seats and hundreds of switches and dials, which transport him back to childhood. “There’s no feeling like it,” he said, his voice filled with excitement. “You’re in total control.” Fitzhugh finds parallels between his passions. A former safety, he lists safety as his most important job description. He takes copious notes on operations instead of game plans. He listens to the veterans, conductors of all ethnicities, some with more than 30 years’ experience, as they tell stories and discuss how much trains have changed. He works in tandem with an engineer, a relationship not unlike that of cornerback and safety. They receive instructions from dispatchers, who are like coaches.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/19/business/19fishwick.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">John Fishwick, 93, Paved Way for Norfolk Southern<date>Published: August 18, 2010</date><text>John P. Fishwick, a retired railroad executive who paved the way for a merger that created one of the nation’s top railroad companies, Norfolk Southern, died on Aug. 9 in Roanoke, Va. He was 93.The cause was congestive heart failure, his daughter Ellen Blair Martin said. Mr. Fishwick, whose career in the rail business spanned nearly four decades, was chief executive of the Norfolk and Western Railway from 1970 to 1981. Near the end of his tenure, he opened negotiations to merge with Southern Railway, which eventually led to the formation of the Norfolk Southern Corporation in 1982. John Palmer Fishwick was born Sept. 29, 1916. He graduated from Roanoke College and Harvard Law School. He went to work for the New York law firm of Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore as an associate in 1940 and then served in the Navy from 1942 to 1945, first as captain of a submarine chaser, then as commander of a destroyer. He joined Norfolk and Western in 1945 as assistant to the general solicitor, and rose through the ranks. In 1968 he was sent to manage two rail companies that Norfolk and Western had acquired, the Erie Lackawanna Railway and the Delaware and Hudson Railway Company. For decades, Norfolk and Western served as the lifeblood of much of the coal region in the Eastern United States. Mr. Fishwick was a strong proponent of consolidation in the fragmented rail industry, at the time a heavily regulated business that was also coming under pressure from other modes of transportation. In an interview in 1971, he said, “Our objectives are just as sublime in the railroad industry as in any other industry, but we have more difficulty getting there because we have somebody looking over our shoulder and sometimes putting glue on our feet.” As the government started to deregulate the rail industry at the end of the 1970s, it was the mergers of rivals — especially the Chessie System and Seaboard Coast Line Industries — that forced Mr. Fishwick to seek a defensive alliance. After several failed discussions with other companies, he spent six months negotiating a merger with Southern Railway. Those talks failed. But Mr. Fishwick was credited with laying the grounds for the alliance that was completed a year after he retired. Norfolk Southern’s routes now total 21,000 miles in 22 states. Mr. Fishwick’s first wife, Blair Wiley Fishwick, died in 1987. Besides his daughter Ellen, he is survived by his wife, Doreen Hamilton Fishwick; another daughter, Anne Palmer Posvar; a son, John Jr.; a stepdaughter, Patricia Doreen Hamilton; a stepson, H. David Hamilton; and six grandchildren.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0DA1039F933A25752C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Buying One, Buffett Aims To Sell Off 2 Railroads<date>Published: November 10, 2009</date><text>Warren E. Buffett is looking to sell off his stakes in two big railroad companies, even as he recently announced a takeover of Burlington Northern Santa Fe. Berkshire Hathaway, which Mr. Buffett controls, said it would sell its holdings in Union Pacific and Norfolk Southern before it completes its $26 billion deal for Burlington Northern. That deal, which would be the largest acquisition of Mr. Buffett's career, is expected to close within the first three months of next year. ''He will be disposing of both of those holdings between now and the transaction date,'' Matthew K. Rose, the Burlington Northern chief executive, told an employee during a conference call last week, a transcript of which was included in the regulatory filing made public on Monday. As of June 30, Berkshire held 9.5 million shares of Union Pacific and 1.9 million shares of Norfolk Southern, according to another regulatory filing. As of the companies' closing stock prices on Monday, the Union Pacific stake is worth $592.6 million and Norfolk Southern, $98.7 million. (Berkshire may have added to or sold some of those shares since June 30.) Mr. Buffett could not be reached for comment. When Mr. Buffett first bought shares of Burlington Northern in 2006, he added it to stakes he held in Union Pacific and Norfolk Southern. (At the end of the third quarter of 2006, Berkshire's stake in Burlington Northern was valued at $73 million; its holdings in Union Pacific were worth $278 million and its Norfolk Southern shares were valued at $142 million.) But Burlington Northern emerged as his choice, and he eventually built up a stake of about 76 million shares in the company. Mr. Buffett is not obligated to sell the railroad stakes. Analysts said last week that they expected the Burlington Northern deal to receive antitrust approval with little trouble, despite Berkshire's holdings in the other two railroad companies.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D9133CF937A35755C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">FREIGHT TRAIN DERAILS IN WESTERN ILLINOIS<date>Published: June 4, 2008</date><text>PHOTO: A Norfolk Southern freight train carrying coal and corn syrup derailed on Tuesday west of Barry, Ill., but no one was seriously injured. All in all, 32 cars of the 70-car train derailed. The cause of the accident, which happened on a bridge, is under investigation.(PHOTOGRAPH BY PHILIP CARLSON/THE QUINCY HERALD-WHIG, VIA ASSOCIATED PRESS)</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E7D61131F93AA25756C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">FIVE DAYS; A TRIO OF INVESTMENTS<date>Published: May 19, 2007</date><text>Billionaire investors helped drive the markets higher as they unveiled major stakes in a bevy of companies. On Wednesday, an affiliate company of Edward S. Lampert, the hedge fund manager, reported in a regulatory filing that it had bought more than 15 million shares in Citigroup, a purchase worth almost $800 million. That same day, Berkshire Hathaway, run by Warren E. Buffett, revealed in a filing that it had raised its railroad holdings, disclosing that it had acquired stakes in Norfolk Southern and Union Pacific worth a combined $1.4 billion. And on Thursday, an affiliate company of Carl C. Icahn, the activist investor, reported that as of March 31, he held a $122 million stake in another railroad company, CSX. While the antipodal investment philosophies of Mr. Buffett and Mr. Icahn are well known, Mr. Lampert's motivation in buying the Citigroup stake remains unknown. It is possible that he may simply find the troubled financial giant's stock undervalued or that he may agitate for change at the top. MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DC1731F93BA35751C1A9609C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Derailment Closes Bridge<date>Published: December 8, 2006</date><text>This item appeared in the paper as a stand alone photograph. Caption information is provided below. Photo: A Norfolk Southern train carrying lumber and chemicals derailed yesterday along the Susquehanna River in Catawissa, Pa., spilling a caustic material. Officials closed the East Bloomsburg Bridge on Route 487 during the cleanup. Four train cars overturned and several more left the tracks. (Photo by Robert Inglis/The Daily Item, via Associated Press)</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/29/business/29values.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Transportation Quietly Moves to New Highs<date>Published: April 29, 2006</date><text>TRANSPORTATION is a segment of the stock market that could use a good publicity agent. As investors cheer the recovery of more widely followed indexes, the Dow Jones transportation average excels in obscurity, up 11 percent this year and near a record high. The performance, which puts the index more than 21 percent above its peak of the previous bull market, is all the more remarkable against a backdrop of record energy prices, a big expense for companies that move things and people. Investment advisers say shares are soaring as a result of forces that remain largely unseen. Transportation may seem like yesterday's industry, but many businesses are using the latest technology and management methods to remake themselves and accelerate growth. That is so among railroad and trucking companies, and theirs are the more stellar performances. As for air carriers, it depends on what they carry; cargo haulers are doing better than airlines. Trucking went through a rough patch in the last recession. Times are no longer hard, even with oil at $70-plus a barrel, because the industry has greatly enhanced productivity and kept prices firm. Routes are managed in a way that limits turnaround time at destinations and maximizes the amount of cargo hauled. The best companies, said Barbara S. Walchli, manager of the Aquila Rocky Mountain Equity Fund, are able to insinuate themselves into their customers' manufacturing schedules, improving those companies' productivity as well. One concern in particular, Knight Transportation, based in Phoenix, exemplifies "this whole move by companies in supply-chain management, moving goods around as efficiently as possible," Ms. Walchli said. "They have added a layer of value to their trucking business by providing logistics." Tom Wadewitz, a transportation analyst for J. P. Morgan, says he thinks that added layer may be thinner than Ms. Walchli does. Logistics "may add a little more money and margin," Mr. Wadewitz said, "but the companies that do best are the ones that do best at their core business." He described Knight as "a high-quality company with good growth prospects over time" and "one of the best-run truckers," but he rates it only neutral because of doubts he has about the industry's prospects. "Capacity is coming in," he said, meaning that new operators are entering the market. "It's less clear that the pricing story and supply-demand dynamics will persist." A better investment, he said, is Swift Transportation, also of Phoenix, which has been thriving under new management. Mr. Wadewitz prefers railroads, a group for which everything has been moving, pardon the expression, on the right track since deregulation 25 years ago. The number of rail operators is actually shrinking, thanks to mergers, and so is the size of the crew needed to run a train. At the same time, trains are able to carry more and bigger cars because of the stronger construction materials. These developments reduce expenses, Mr. Wadewitz said, and on the other side of the ledger, railroads have been able to push up prices. They even benefit from higher oil and gas prices, which increase demand for, and shipments of, coal. Norfolk Southern, based in Norfolk, Va., benefits especially from the surge in coal use, he said, and from the rapid growth in global trade, which requires ever more goods to be shipped through seaports. He recommends its stock and that of CSX, a once wayward business that has righted itself. CSX "is enjoying strong pricing and cost control and utilizing equipment and labor more efficiently," he said. As much as he likes those two, he cautioned that some railroad stocks have moved too far, too fast. He is neutral on Burlington Northern Santa Fe largely because its share price has quadrupled in about three years. That caveat aside, Mr. Wadewitz says he expects the sector to continue to treat investors well, possibly into next year. "It's a long-term story for the rails," he said. "They have become very focused on productivity improvement and rationalizing some of the capacity out. It's a story that's more sustainable than for the truckers and air cargo companies." More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDA153FF930A15757C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">OPENERS: SUITS; RICH ADVICE<date>Published: April 23, 2006</date><text>In January, the Norfolk Southern Corporation told investors about a deal its directors had struck with the departing chairman and chief executive, David R. Goode. What it failed to tell shareholders was how much it would cost them. The directors wanted to continue tapping the expertise of Mr. Goode, 65, who was retiring after 40 years at Norfolk Southern, which operates a freight railway. So they asked him to serve as a consultant for five years. But rather than paying Mr. Goode an annual fee, they changed the terms of his pension and restricted stock. They waived the requirement that he forfeit his 135,000 unvested shares, then worth about $6 million. More creatively, the directors changed the formula for calculating his pension, basing it not on his five most highly compensated years, but on the top three years. How much was that switch worth? Norfolk Southern is not telling. ''There is no specific figure itemized in the proxy or the 8-K,'' said Susan Terpay, a company spokeswoman, referring to documents filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission. But the company's latest proxy statement indicates that Mr. Goode will collect about $1.6 million a year. A year earlier, the proxy showed him on track to get less than $1.3 million. Is it possible that in addition to the shares, Mr. Goode's payment for consulting with his successor will be $300,000 a year for life? Ms. Terpay would not say. PATRICK McGEEHAN</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/28/national/28train.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rail Line Agrees to Pay Some Crash Victims<date>Published: May 28, 2005</date><text>COLUMBIA, S.C., May 27 (AP) - A judge approved a tentative settlement on Friday to reimburse residents and businesses affected by a train wreck that killed 9 people and injured 250 on Jan. 6. The settlement of a class-action suit against the line, Norfolk Southern, covers 5,400 people forced to leave Graniteville after chemical fumes leaked from the wreck. The train ran onto a side track, smashing into parked railcars and rupturing one with chlorine. Federal investigators said the crew of the parked train had failed to flip a switch. Under the settlement, the rail line will pay $2,000 a household within one mile of the site for inconvenience, and $200 a day per person for people who left and were not hospitalized. The settlement does not cover the dead or hospitalized. Separate suits have been filed for them. At least one lawyer, Peter Borstell, has objected to the settlement, saying the 435 residents whom his firm represents deserve more money. The judge scheduled a hearing in August for formal objections. Norfolk Southern expects to spend $35 million for cleanup, legal claims and other expenses, a spokesman, Robin Chapman, has said. More Articles in National &gt;</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/06/national/06train.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Train Crew Is Dismissed After Crash<date>Published: February 6, 2005</date><text>OLUMBIA, S.C., Feb. 5 (AP) - A three-man crew suspected of failing to switch a railroad track back into position before a freight train crash that caused a deadly chlorine leak has been fired by the Norfolk Southern railroad. A spokesman for the railroad, Robin Chapman, said on Friday that the workers had been terminated because they had "failed to perform their duties properly." Advertisement Union officials said the three men, who each have at least 25 years of experience, would appeal. The Jan. 6 accident killed nine people, injured hundreds more and forced the evacuation of thousands of residents of Graniteville, S.C. Investigators have determined preliminarily that, after parking their train on a spur line, the crew members failed to switch the tracks back to the main line. This allowed an oncoming train to ram into the parked cars. The Federal Railroad Administration, in a safety advisory last month, said the likely cause of the crash was human error, rather than switch failure or sabotage. The crew members were not identified by the company. However, at least 15 lawsuits alleging negligence have been filed against Norfolk Southern, and at least six of them name as defendants the parked train's engineer, Benjamin Aiken, 50, its conductor, James Thornton, 56, and its brakeman, Mike Ford, 48.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2D81F38F936A15752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN TALLIES COST OF TRAIN WRECK<date>Published: January 25, 2005</date><text>The railway transportation company Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it expected expenses of $30 million to $40 million in the first quarter for a deadly train crash in Graniteville, S.C., on Jan. 6. Norfolk Southern, which is based in Norfolk, Va., said the figure did not include any fines or penalties that might be imposed. It also said that it expected its insurance coverage to cover potential claims or settlements. Nine people were killed and hundreds injured in the derailment. A chlorine leak from one of the train cars forced 5,400 people in the area to leave their homes for a week.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/08/national/08train.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Cloud Rising From Train Wreck, Then Death and a Ghost Town<date>Published: January 8, 2005</date><text>Correction Appended GRANITEVILLE, S.C., Jan. 7 - Michael Reed was working the graveyard shift at Avondale Mills here when a co-worker, John Laird, strode over to say that "he thought he heard a train crash," Mr. Reed recalled from his hospital bed on Friday. When another worker emerged from a restroom to say that he had seen "green stuff," and a third, Charles Shealey, echoed the concern, the group of mill workers, about 15 in all, ran to the parking lot. "We tried to unlock the gate to get to our vehicles," Mr. Reed said. "But by then the green stuff had come around the gate and got stronger, so we all put our heads to the ground." It was the wrong strategy. The "green stuff" was chlorine gas leaking from a tank car in the train wreck; heavier than air, it settles along the ground. But one of the men got his vehicle, a Dodge Durango, and Mr. Reed, 23, and a group of others climbed in and drove away. Mr. Laird and Mr. Shealey did not wait. They ran toward the woods, Mr. Reed said. Later, their bodies were found. Mr. Laird and Mr. Shealey were among eight people who died when the train carrying chlorine slammed into a train halted on a siding by the plant here early Thursday morning. The disaster has turned Graniteville into a ghost town, with investigators in hazardous-materials suits making occasional visits when chlorine levels permit. Gary Spires Sr., 60, was at a machine that dyes fabric when he and other workers noticed the chlorine. Two co-workers next to him began vomiting. "We were smelling it coming through the ducts into the building," Mr. Spires said in a telephone interview from his hospital bed in Aiken, S.C., on Friday. "It just kept intensifying. We didn't know what it was. We thought it was internal. But then we came to find out it was outside and that we were in immediate danger." Mr. Spires said he ran past the two co-workers, who were lying on the floor. "I had to try to save my own life," he said. "I was gasping for breath. I had only one thing in my mind: to save my life. I went up those steps to the parking lot two and three steps at a time. "When I got to my truck I drove straight out the parking lot. It looked like a stream of snow. I couldn't even see the road." Mr. Spires said he drove to a gas station. "The air there was cleaner but the smell was persistent," he said. "The lady at the gas station saw me, locked up the station and asked me to get in her car. She drove me to the hospital." Besides Mr. Laird and Mr. Shealey, the dead plant employees included Fred Rushton III, 41, of Warrenville; Allen Frazier, 58, of Ridge Spring; and Steven Bagby, 38, of Augusta, Ga., the Aiken County coroner's office said. A truck driver from Quebec, Joseph F. Stone, who was asleep in his cab, also died at the plant. The engineer of the moving train, Christopher Seeling, 28, of West Columbia, was killed, possibly from chlorine inhalation, as was a Graniteville resident, Tony DeLoach, 56, who was found dead in his home. Officials said there might be others, but they have not been able to conduct a thorough search. About 400 people work the graveyard shift at the mill, which operates 24 hours a day, said Stephen Felker Jr., manager of corporate development for Avondale Mills. "Yesterday was a dark day for the Avondale family," Mr. Felker said. "In spite of that, there were dozens of heroes who assisted people and helped them escape. People really pulled together." Five mill employees were killed last year in a grade-crossing accident about a tenth of a mile from the wreck on Thursday. One Avondale Mills worker was still missing Friday night, Lt. Michael Frank of the Aiken County sheriff's office said. Anybody in a low-lying area was vulnerable. Six hospitals in the area evaluated 234 people and admitted 58, about a dozen in serious or critical condition. Investigators were trying to determine why the 42-car Norfolk Southern train carrying chlorine left the main track and hit a Norfolk Southern train parked in a siding, and whether the crew that had parked the train a few hours earlier had left the switch in the wrong position. Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/29/business/profit-increases-55-at-norfolk-southern.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Profit Increases 55% At Norfolk Southern<date>Published: July 29, 2004</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said Wednesday that its profit rose 55 percent in the second quarter, beating Wall Street estimates, as volume increased.The company said it earned $213 million, or 54 cents a share, in the period, which ended June 30. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had expected earnings of 46 cents a share. The company earned $137 million, or 35 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 11 percent, to $1.8 billion.Revenue from hauling freight with a combination of trains and trucks rose 21 percent, to a record $364 million, because of traffic growth from new truck-competitive services, increased units handled with trucking partners and strong international shipments, the company said.General merchandise revenue rose 9 percent, reaching $1 billion. Coal revenue increased 9 percent, to $424 million, as demand for export coal increased.Railway operating expenses in the quarter were up $53 million, or 4 percent, over the same period in 2003.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/27/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-to-offer-incentives-to-quit.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN TO OFFER INCENTIVES TO QUIT<date>Published: September 27, 2003</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation will offer salaried employees with at least two years at the company incentives to quit in a bid to control labor costs. The severance program includes three weeks' pay per year of service and a year of paid health-care benefits. Employees who accept the offer will leave the company by Oct. 31 in most cases, said Susan Terpay, a spokeswoman for the company. Wage and benefit costs rose 4 percent at Norfolk Southern in the first half of this year. The company last offered managers incentives to leave the company in 2000, Ms. Terpay said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/15/us/derailment-brings-evacuation.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Derailment Brings Evacuation<date>Published: February 15, 2003</date><text>This item appeared in the paper as a stand alone photograph. Caption information is provided below.Photo: Eight cars of a 45-car Norfolk Southern freight train jumped the tracks in Delaware before dawn yesterday, causing the spill of a small amount of acid in powder form. The state police evacuated some 200 people from the town of Farmington, but there were no reports of injuries. (Associated Press)</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/11/nyregion/metro-briefing-new-jersey-linden-train-service-is-restored.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Metro Briefing | New Jersey: Linden: Train Service Is Restored<date>Published: February 11, 2002</date><text>Train service in New Jersey and along Amtrak's Northeast Corridor was nearly back to normal yesterday. On Saturday night, a freight train owned by Norfolk Southern and CSX Transportation knocked down wires near Linden, stranding some passengers in darkened trains for several hours. The accident caused travel delays for about 2,000 Amtrak passengers and an unknown number of New Jersey Transit riders. Power was restored to three of five affected tracks by 5:30 a.m. Sunday. New Jersey Transit did not expect problems today, but asked customers to allow a little extra time, just in case.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/24/business/railroad-s-earnings-rise.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Railroad's Earnings Rise<date>Published: January 24, 2002</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said today that cost control measures helped its fourth-quarter profit beat analysts' expectations despite the slow economy.The holding company, which owns the Norfolk Southern Railway Company freight railroad, earned $115 million, or 30 cents a share, in the three months ended Dec. 31.That compared with earnings in the fourth quarter of 2000 of $5 million, or 1 cent a share.Revenue increased to $1.53 billion, compared with $1.52 billion in the fourth quarter of 2000, despite a 1 percent, or 20,600-unit, decrease in carloads.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/16/business/major-railroads-win-ruling-to-block-strike.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Major Railroads Win Ruling to Block Strike<date>Published: January 16, 2002</date><text>The Union Pacific Corporation and other major railroads won a court order this week to block a strike by train engineers who protested a plan to assign freight-car switching work to a rival union.The Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers said their contract was violated when railroads selected the United Transportation Union to switch freight cars between trains by remote control instead of engineers. A strike could have shut railroads that carried more than 26 million shipments last year, disrupting manufacturing and food production.Judge Joan Gottschall of United States District Court granted an injunction sought by Union Pacific, the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Corporation, the CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation on Monday in Chicago. The railroads plan to use remote control this year to save as much as $250 million a year by eliminating jobs, analysts estimate.The engineers said in court proceedings they planned a strike when the other union's members began using remote-control switching, the ruling said. Railroads said the contract lets them make technology agreements with a union other than engineers.The rails' bargaining unit and the United Transport Union released a joint statement after the court ruling saying they have agreed to start using remote control in pilot projects while terms for wider use are set.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/27/business/rail-unions-to-merge-leader-of-one-says.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rail Unions to Merge, Leader of One Says<date>Published: June 27, 2001</date><text>Two unions representing about 70,000 train crew workers at the Union Pacific Corporation and other railroads will merge by the end of the year to increase their bargaining power, the head of one of them said today.Byron Boyd, president of the United Transportation Union, said his 45,000-member union expected to combine with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, which has about 25,000 active members. A merger of the unions two years ago fell through because of a financial dispute. The engineers' union could not be reached for comment.Both unions are in contract talks with Union Pacific, the CSX Corporation, the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation, which carry 90 percent of rail freight in the United States. The United Transportation Union and those railroads reached a tentative pact last year that has not been ratified because of a dispute over contract language.Talks continue with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and nine other unions.''As railroads grow larger and stronger, it has become increasingly difficult for fragmented unions to bargain effectively,'' Mr. Boyd said in a speech today at a union meeting in Greensboro, N.C.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/11/business/investing-all-aboard-for-the-recovery-maybe.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">INVESTING; All Aboard for the Recovery (Maybe)<date>Published: February 11, 2001</date><text>Correction AppendedAS signs of a downturn in the technology business become harder to ignore, some investors are looking to stocks of a bygone era.Since the beginning of the year, investors have pushed up the share prices of railroads, historically among the first groups of stocks to revive after recessions. And stock prices for producers of the aluminum, steel and coal historically borne on rail cars have gained recently at a rate similar to that of the Nasdaq's decline.But the apparent popularity of this classic investing strategy means that these investors face an unsettling possibility: that the so-called early-recovery stocks may have already recovered.Even some sales-oriented railroad analysts offer caveats about buying into the industry. And whether or not caution proves wise, market strategists' arguments against the rails show that these stocks, once predictable market pillars, now play a lesser role in an economy dominated by high technology. In a traditional recovery, these stocks could be expected to rebound strongly, but the current situation is different, strategists suggest.''This expansion has been unlike any other, both in longevity and in how little inflation it has engendered,'' said Charles Pradilla, chief investment strategist at SG Cowen. ''I don't think you can use traditional analysis.''The sales pitch for rail stocks is simple and seems fairly well founded. Industry analysts say the four major railroad companies -- Burlington Northern Santa Fe, CSX, Union Pacific and Norfolk Southern -- are in better shape than in a long time to reap the benefits of recovery. Union contracts negotiated since the 1991 recession have lowered labor costs, the wave of mergers that mired operations and slowed trains to a crawl seems to have ended, and soaring natural-gas prices have stimulated demand for coal, which is shipped by rail.From 1992 to 1998, railroad stocks nearly tripled, keeping up with the Dow Jones industrial average, despite the poorly integrated set of mergers that led to breakdowns in service. But then the technology-driven Nasdaq market siphoned huge amounts of money from old-economy stocks, and the growth of the Standard &amp; Poor's railroads index paled.Correction: February 18, 2001, Sunday An article last Sunday about the investment prospects for railroad stocks misstated the titles held by John Schreiber, a fund manager who plans to concentrate on other issues instead. He is an assistant portfolio manager of the Janus Fund, not its portfolio manager; he is portfolio manager of the Janus Fund 2.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/24/business/company-news-restructuring-at-norfolk-southern-includes-job-cuts.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; RESTRUCTURING AT NORFOLK SOUTHERN INCLUDES JOB CUTS<date>Published: January 24, 2001</date><text>One of the nation's largest railroads, the Norfolk Southern Corporation, said yesterday that it planned cut up to 6 percent of its work force, reduce its dividend and get rid of 12,000 freight cars as part of a restructuring plan. The company, based in Norfolk, Va., said it would eliminate 1,000 to 2,000 jobs over the next 12 months, noting that the cuts would be in addition to previously announced layoffs. Norfolk Southern has about 33,000 employees, a company spokesman said. The company said it would also reduce its quarterly dividend by 70 percent, to 6 cents a share from 20 cents.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/11/business/company-news-railroad-announces-accord-in-discrimination-lawsuit.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; RAILROAD ANNOUNCES ACCORD IN DISCRIMINATION LAWSUIT<date>Published: January 11, 2001</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation, one of the nation's largest railroads, has announced an agreement to settle a class-action discrimination lawsuit by paying $28 million and changing the way it promotes workers. About 7,700 current and former black employees are eligible to share in the settlement, which was disclosed late Tuesday. Along with measures to make its promotion methods fairer and more objective and to train and mentor new managers, the company agreed to name a major railroad center for a civil rights or railroad-industry figure who was black, and to celebrate African-American Railroader Month every February, beginning in 2002.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/20/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-to-cut-5-of-hourly-work-force.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN TO CUT 5% OF HOURLY WORK FORCE<date>Published: December 20, 2000</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it would eliminate more than 1,300 union jobs, or 5 percent of its hourly work force, and was considering laying off managers for the first time in 15 years. Norfolk Southern has been trying to cut costs in the 18 months since it divided Conrail with the CSX Corporation, leading to traffic snarls and delays. The high cost of fuel and the falling volume of freight made cost-cutting more urgent, the company said. Earlier eliminations of management jobs were carried out through voluntary early-retirement offers. Norfolk Southern shares rose 13 cents, to $13.44.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/04/business/railroad-taking-a-charge.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Railroad Taking a Charge<date>Published: April 04, 2000</date><text>Norfolk Southern, the fourth-largest United States railroad, said today that it would take a $100 million charge for the recently ended first quarter to pay severance costs for 919 workers who accepted an early-retirement plan announced in January. The company estimated the charge at 16 cents a share. Before the announcement, Norfolk Southern had been forecast to earn 6 cents share, according to securities analysts surveyed by First Call/Thomson Financial. The company had expected about 800 of the 1,180 eligible employees to accept the early-retirement terms.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/27/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-offers-managers-early-retirement.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN OFFERS MANAGERS EARLY RETIREMENT<date>Published: January 27, 2000</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it would offer early retirement to as many as 1,180 managers, a fifth of the total, as its fourth-quarter profit fell 81 percent on higher costs. The company, the fourth-largest United States railroad, said it expected about 800 people to accept the offer, made to nonunion workers older than 55 with more than 10 years of service. A spokeswoman, Susan Terpay, declined to discuss the severance costs. Norfolk Southern has been trying to cut costs since it began integrating part of the former Conrail Inc. system. The company, based in Norfolk, Va., and the CSX Corporation bought Conrail in 1998 for $10 billion. Norfolk Southern shares fell $1.0625 each, to $17.75, on the Big Board.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/12/business/the-media-business-railroad-may-enter-telecommunications.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS; Railroad May Enter Telecommunications<date>Published: October 12, 1999</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation, the fourth-largest United States railroad, is forming a unit to lease its telecommunications system to phone, Internet and cable service providers and may eventually enter that business.The railroad's new Thoroughbred Technology and Telecommunications Inc. unit is negotiating with long-distance and local telephone companies and cable providers to lease the rights of way along its 21,600 miles of railroad tracks for cables as well as its microwave network and other assets.''We have one of the largest private telecommunications systems in the world already set up and running and doing a good job of serving our needs, with plenty of capacity to handle others,'' said Bob Fort, spokesman for the railroad, based in Norfolk, Va.Cable-based Internet providers are expected to have 13.6 million subscribers by 2002, up from 700,000 last year, according to Forrester Research.Norfolk Southern stock fell 31.25 cents, to $22.1875.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/16/nyregion/metro-business-railroad-delays-continue.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Metro Business; Railroad Delays Continue<date>Published: June 16, 1999</date><text>Delivery delays and other rail-service problems continued to plague the new owners of Conrail as they began their third week of operations yesterday.Rail customers of the CSX and Norfolk Southern corporations, which carved up Conrail on June 1, reported late shipments of raw materials and trouble getting rail cars to pick up finished goods.Those problems interfered with production schedules nationwide and threatened to shut down some manufacturing plants.On Monday, United Parcel Service, one of the nation's largest rail customers, began moving some packages by truck, a more expensive option for longer-distance shipments. The company also had to pay its employees overtime to handle delayed shipments.The split of Conrail was the most complex transaction in modern railroading and followed a problematic merger of Union Pacific with Southern Pacific in 1996, a merger that led to severe congestion and delays in the West and the Midwest.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/10/business/disrupted-rail-service-draws-complaints.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Disrupted Rail Service Draws Complaints<date>Published: June 10, 1999</date><text>Some shippers have begun reporting major disruptions in service, including delayed trains and lost rail cars, since the CSX and Norfolk Southern railroads took over Conrail on June 1.Edward H. Rastatter, the director of policy at the National Industrial Transporation League, a trade group that represents many of the nation's largest shippers, said that he had received complaints about service on the Norfolk Southern part of Conrail from about six companies.He added that one major company, which he did not want to identify, had warned that it might face some plant closings because of delays in delivering materials.While most of the complaints have focused on Norfolk Southern, Norman Black, the manager of media relations for United Parcel Service, one of the largest shippers on the old Conrail system, said that many trains were not meeting their schedules on both the CSX and Norfolk Southern lines.''We have big time problems with both railroads,'' he said. ''We are very unhappy and it's not getting better. It's gotten worse each day.''The company has been forced to keep employees longer at sorting centers, which has caused substantial payments of overtime, he said.He added that the company was considering moving some of the trailers that are now carried on intermodal trains by truck instead.The company had to make such a switch back in 1997 at the height of the problems caused by Union Pacific's takeover of the Southern Pacific railroad.Michael Ward, an executive vice president at CSX Transportation Inc., the railroad subsidiary of CSX, which is based in Richmond, acknowledged the U.P.S. complaints.He said that the railroad hoped to be meeting its schedules in a couple of weeks.Both railroads took extensive measures to make sure the transition went smoothly. They worked closely with large shippers, bought extra locomotives, hired and trained extra crews and took more time before they took over operations of Conrail, which they bought jointly in April 1997.Don O'Brian, an assistant vice president at Norfolk Southern, acknowledged in an interview yesterday that some customers were not satisfied with service.He said, however, that special teams set up to deal with unexpected glitches had been working on problems as they arose.''We're not ready to declare victory yet,'' he added. ''We're seeing more progress every day.''Paulette Lauber, the rail operations manager for the Sauder Woodworking Company in Archbold, Ohio, said that for three days last week the company, which makes ready-to-assemble furniture, did not receive its normal eight or nine carloads of raw material.She also said that as Norfolk Southern merged its computer systems with Conrail, some cars were temporarily lost in transit.She said that her company had not had any disruptions in production because it had been able also to ship by truck.''I think it's clearing up,'' she added. ''But it's going to be longer than they thought it would be.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/06/nyregion/in-brief-agreement-issued-to-build-light-rail-line-in-south-jersey.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">IN BRIEF; Agreement Issued to Build Light Rail Line in South Jersey<date>Published: June 06, 1999</date><text>A long-delayed light rail commuter line between Trenton and Camden came closer to reality last week as New Jersey Transit agreed to award a contract to build the line and to pay for right of way on a stretch of track.The agency said it would pay $67.5 million to the Norfolk Southern and CSX Railroads to use 34 miles of track. Those railroads would run freight trains on the track between 10 P.M. and 6 A.M. and New Jersey Transit would operate light rail commuter trains the rest of the day.New Jersey Transit also issued a letter of intent that it would award a $604.5 million construction contract to a consortium led by Bectel Infrastructure, of Gaithersburg, Md., to build the rest of the line.State Transportation Secretary James Weinstein predicted that construction will begin within 90 days, with the first trains running in 2002. BILL KENT</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/02/business/freight-moves-on-schedule-in-takeover-of-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Freight Moves On Schedule In Takeover Of Conrail<date>Published: June 02, 1999</date><text>The CSX and Norfolk Southern railroads took over the Conrail system yesterday in one of the most complex handoffs in railroad history and for the first day, at least, trains throughout the Northeast ran close to schedule.The switchover began at 4:30 P.M. on Monday, when the computer systems of Conrail began to shut down. CSX computers had taken control of the CSX portion by 8 A.M. yesterday, according to Robert Haulter, the vice president for integration planning at CSX Transportation Inc., the railroad unit of the CSX Corporation, which is based in Richmond.The Norfolk Southern Corporation had some minor computer problems initially, but by noon yesterday it had taken control of its share of Conrail, according to Frank Brown, a spokesman for the railroad, which is based in Norfolk, Va..Norfolk operated 50 trains yesterday and expects to be running a full schedule of up to 225 trains by late today.The two railroads, which agreed to buy Conrail jointly for $10.3 billion in April 1997, have been planning the takeover for months. Conrail was created by Congress in 1976 out of the bankrupt Penn Central Railroad and five other struggling lines in the Northeast. Norfolk Southern has acquired 58 percent of Conrail, and CSX 42 percent.Jolene M. Molitoris, the administrator of the Federal Railroad Administration, which oversees the nation's railroads, visited the staffs of both railroads yesterday.''There have not been any glitches,'' she said in a telephone interview from Jacksonville, Fla., where the CSX railroad subsidiary has its headquarters. ''Today everything has been smooth.''The Eastern railroads have sought to avoid the disruptions in service that occurred throughout the Southwest and reached a crisis stage in 1997 when the Union Pacific, the nation's largest railroad, took over the Southern Pacific Rail Corporation.Major shippers awaited yesterday's switchover nervously because Conrail has been the rail backbone of the Northeast and helps run commuter lines in major cities.''I'm comforted so far,'' said Edward H. Rastatter, the director of policy for the National Industrial Transportation League, a trade group that represents many of the nation's largest rail shippers. He said that he had not heard of any complaints from major shippers.The long-awaited transition was particularly tricky since it involved handing over the dispatching of commuter service in some metropolitan areas.CSX, which took over the dispatching of numerous commuter trains in New Jersey, Boston and Chicago, has put senior employees in major dispatching centers in case there are snags. CSX kept 180 trains running while the transition was under way, executives said.Mr. Haulter said, however, that while yesterday was a major milestone, many more changes would be phased in over time.''It's gone very well,'' he said. ''But its just another milestone. We're keeping our eyes firmly focused on the tasks ahead.''The railroads are seeking to lure traffic from truck lines to the rails in the congested region by offering cheaper service.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/01/business/conrail-chugs-off-into-the-sunset-csx-and-norfolk-southern-take-over.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Chugs Off Into the Sunset; CSX and Norfolk Southern Take Over<date>Published: June 01, 1999</date><text>The companies about to divvy up the huge Conrail system have certainly tried to do their homework.They bought extra locomotives, laid hundreds of miles of new track, tested computer systems and settled with a multitude of unions. They hired thousands of Conrail workers and managers and spent long hours teaching them what the future would hold.That future arrives today, as Norfolk Southern and CSX, which already dominate commercial rail traffic in much of the East, take over chunks of Conrail. The switchover will herald the most sweeping change in a generation in the Northeast's commercial railroads -- especially in the New York area.If the transformation goes smoothly, the effects will be felt far and wide. With more competition, shipping costs should fall, a benefit that could ripple throughout the region's economy in the form of lower prices for all manner of goods. And increased rail traffic could take business from truckers, which would have a marked impact on traffic and pollution.Some of this bonanza, however, could well come at the expense of commuters. Many commuter lines in the Northeast share tracks with Conrail, and increased commercial traffic could put a squeeze on them -- and increase the risk of snags that would delay everyone. Both railroads have had extensive meetings with local transportation authorities to address these concerns.At the moment, though, the focus is on the long-awaited transition, and executives at the Norfolk Southern Corporation and the CSX Corporation say they are doing everything they can to make it go smoothly. For no one -- not the railroads, not the thousands of companies that rely on them to ship raw materials and finished products, not the consuming and traveling public -- wants a repeat of the nightmare that followed another recent railroad merger.After taking over Southern Pacific in 1996, Union Pacific, the nation's largest railroad, was mired in chaos for months, with thousands of rail cars lost or misrouted and its major rail lines clogged with traffic. Shippers faced such frustrating delays that some, in desperation, had to go to Union Pacific's rail yards themselves to search for their goods.At the height of the debacle, in late 1997, the extra cost to manufacturers, utilities and retailers along the Gulf Coast and on the West Coast ran to an estimated $100 million a month.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/19/nyregion/metro-business-a-railroad-gets-access-to-new-york.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Metro Business; A Railroad Gets Access to New York<date>Published: May 19, 1999</date><text>Norfolk Southern Corporation will have direct rail access to New York City by loading rail cars onto tug-propelled floats to cross New York Harbor, the company said yesterday.Direct access to New York and other points east of the Hudson River had been one of the major issues left unresolved when Federal regulators approved a split of Philadelphia-based Conrail last summer. Norfolk Southern and CSX Corporation, both Southeastern railroads, will carve up Conrail's Northeastern routes on June 1. The $10.3 billion transaction will restore competition to many Northeastern markets but keep a monopoly in place elsewhere.Most Conrail lines east of the Hudson will go to CSX after the split, leading to complaints that regulators were preserving a monopoly created in 1976 when Congress formed Conrail out of six bankrupt carriers.Norfolk Southern said it signed an agreement with New York Cross Harbor Railroad for the exclusive use of its floats between Jersey City and a new terminal in Brooklyn, allowing Norfolk Southern to get to lucrative New York markets, instead of having to stop in New Jersey.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/09/nyregion/us-backs-dividing-conrail-to-increase-competition.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">U.S. Backs Dividing Conrail to Increase Competition<date>Published: June 09, 1998</date><text>The Federal Government approved a sweeping plan today to restructure the nation's rail freight system east of the Mississippi River, a move officials said would take trucks off the road, reduce air pollution and lower the cost of goods for the New York City metropolitan region and much of the rest of the nation.Today's vote by the Surface Transportation Board gave final approval to a proposal by the CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation to divide Conrail's nearly 12,000 miles of track, stretching from Boston to St. Louis. CSX and Norfolk Southern jointly bought Conrail, which operated mainly in the Northeast, for $10.2 billion last year in one of the largest rail mergers in the nation's history.The plan approved today creates two railroad giants that will dominate rail freight shipping throughout the nation's eastern half, allowing direct competition between the two companies in several places, including much of New Jersey and parts of western New York State.''This carefully crafted, privately negotiated deal injects competition in the entire East like no merger before has ever done,'' said Linda J. Morgan, the chairwoman of the board. ''It will bring competition back to many areas that had lost options through the creation of Conrail.''Aides to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Gov. George E. Pataki hailed the decision, saying it would allow more than one major railroad company to ship goods in and out of New York City for the first time in decades and potentially provide new transportation routes for Long Island businesses that are solely dependent on trucks.''For the first time in a long time, businesses on the east side of the Hudson will have access to competitive freight rail services,'' said Bradford J. Race, Mr. Pataki's chief of staff. ''It's a significant step forward for Long Island, Manhattan and communities all along the river.''But some members of New York's Congressional delegation said the plan fell well short of what was needed to revitalize the region's rail freight industry, charging that the transportation board had squandered a chance to force much more competition for New York City's huge market. Less than 3 percent of all the goods shipped in and out of the city is carried by trains, compared with about 40 percent in other cities.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/13/business/company-news-clayton-dubilier-fund-to-buy-north-american-van-lines.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CLAYTON, DUBILIER FUND TO BUY NORTH AMERICAN VAN LINES<date>Published: January 13, 1998</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation agreed yesterday to sell its North American Van Lines unit for $200 million to a fund managed by the New York investment firm Clayton, Dubilier &amp; Rice Inc. North American Van Lines, based in Fort Wayne, Ind., runs household moving and specialized freight handling services in North America and Europe. Norfolk Southern, the holding company for the Norfolk Southern Railway Company freight railroad, said the sale would allow it to focus on efforts to improve rail service in the Eastern United States. Its shares rose 50 cents yesterday, to $30.50.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/23/business/conrail-proposal-raises-concerns.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Proposal Raises Concerns<date>Published: October 23, 1997</date><text>A proposed division of Conrail by two other railroads poses ''significant competitive problems'' for some electric utilities, the Justice Department said in newly filed documents.The deal would reduce competition in at least three markets for shipping more than $100 million worth of coal used to generate electricity, the department's antitrust division said.It did not ask the Surface Transportation Board to block the $10 billion transaction. But the concerns it raised could lead to changes into how Conrail's routes are divided.The department's position was explained in papers filed with the board on Tuesday, the deadline for objecting to a proposal by the CSX Corporation of Richmond, and the Norfolk Southern Corporation of Norfolk, Va., to take over the lines of Conrail, which is based in Philadelphia. The deal would give CSX and Norfolk Southern control of virtually all rail shipments east of Kansas City.A CSX spokeswoman, Kathy Burns, said today that the company was committed to resolving the concerns, but she said she could not comment on specifics because she had not seen the filing.Rick Harris, a Norfolk Southern spokesman, declined to comment.The Surface Transportation Board expects to rule on the transaction by June.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/09/10/business/stares-of-lawyerly-disbelief-at-a-huge-civil-award.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Stares of Lawyerly Disbelief at a Huge Civil Award<date>Published: September 10, 1997</date><text>Big civil-damages awards have become an increasingly common feature of the American legal landscape, but Monday's nearly $3.5 billion punitive-damages assessment in a 1987 Louisiana railway fire is being seen as a case unto itself.The accident that spawned the huge award was little noticed outside Louisiana and did not cause widespread injury or death. Questions were raised about the long-term health effects of the chemical fire, but no definitive studies have established lasting medical damage.The award has left legal experts shaking their heads. Advocates of tort reform say the case is a prime example of the need to limit or abolish punitive damages and to discourage the filing of class-action claims.Many of the case's specifics remained unclear today, including the potential for latent damage to the health of thousands of residents of the neighborhood near the fire and the culpability of the companies that shared blame for the accident.The size of the verdict may be partly explained by the residents' anger at the storage of highly flammable and toxic chemicals in rail cars in their poor, largely black neighborhood where citizens have little money or political influence. Lawyers for the residents said they were victims of ''environmental racism.''Still, the $3.5 billion judgment, representing seven times the ultimate payout in 1989 from the lethal chemical explosion at Bhopal, India, stunned participants and independent analysts alike. To be sure, India originally sought $3 billion in compensation for more than 3,000 deaths.Brent Barriere, one of a team of lawyers defending the five transportation companies in the case, called the verdict outrageous and said it was the result of a jury's riding a ''runaway train.''He said that the award bore no relationship to the actual damages borne by the 8,000 people temporarily evacuated from their homes 10 years ago when a tank car containing butadiene, a volatile chemical used to make synthetic rubber, began to leak and then burst into flames in a New Orleans rail yard.He noted that an earlier Federal court suit against the same companies, stemming from the same accident, had awarded several plaintiffs an average of $500 in compensatory damages. ''At most, they suffered 36 hours of inconvenience,'' Mr. Barriere said. ''These numbers are a stunning abuse of the system.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/08/12/business/norfolk-southern-and-csx-back-delaware-otsego-deal.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK SOUTHERN AND CSX BACK DELAWARE OTSEGO DEAL<date>Published: August 12, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation and the CSX Corporation disclosed yesterday that they planned to finance a management buyout of the Delaware Otsego Corporation. Under the deal proposed Friday, the two railroad companies and Walter G. Rich, Delaware Otsego's chief executive, would pay $40.43 million to acquire Delaware Otsego shares at $19 each, assume about $11 million of debt and repay $6.75 million of debt. Delaware Otsego is based in Cooperstown, N.Y., and owns the New York, Susquehanna &amp; Western Railway Corporation, which operates 300 miles of track including a direct route into the New York metropolitan area. Its shares closed yesterday down $2 at $21. Norfolk Southern shares were down 25 cents, to $107.75, while CSX shares were up 12.5 cents at $59.6875.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/09/business/rival-railroads-agree-on-conrail-s-assets.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rival Railroads Agree on Conrail's Assets<date>Published: April 09, 1997</date><text>The CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation announced an agreement yesterday that details how the two companies would split the assets of Conrail. A deal, which has been expected since Conrail abandoned its merger with CSX a month ago, will bring competition in freight rail service to New York for the first time in 29 years.Under the terms of the agreement, CSX and Norfolk Southern will jointly pay $115 cash a share, or $10.2 billion, for Conrail, the line that has had a virtual monopoly on freight traffic from Washington to Boston and west to Chicago. The two rival railroad companies will then divide Conrail, with CSX paying $4.3 billion for 42 percent of the assets and Norfolk Southern paying $5.9 billion for the remaining 58 percent.The deal formally brings to an end a bidding war for Conrail, which began in October with the announcement of an $8.4 billion merger between Conrail and CSX. Both railroads will now have access to major Eastern ports, including New York, and be able to provide single-line service between New York and Chicago, St. Louis and markets in the South and Southwest.Conrail shareholders, in turn, are to receive a 62 percent premium for a stock that was trading at $71 in October. CSX's current offer will be amended to include Norfolk Southern and will be extended to May 23, when the shares are to be placed in a voting trust, pending regulatory approval.''At this point, the major winners in this whole thing are the Conrail shareholders,'' said Brian Routledge, a transportation analyst with Prudential Securities. ''They ended up with more money than they ever could have hoped for. The other potential winners are the shippers, who only had one rail option in the past. We still don't know the details of exactly how they'll compete, but there will be major markets like Port Elizabeth, that for the first time in 30 years will have head-to-head competition.''CSX and Norfolk Southern may have paid more for Conrail than they expected six months ago, Mr. Routledge added, but the companies ''will get an adequate return; it just may be further out in the future.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/14/business/conrail-chairman-could-receive-22-million-severance-package.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Chairman Could Receive $22 Million Severance Package<date>Published: March 14, 1997</date><text>David M. LeVan, chairman of Conrail, will not get to lead one of the largest railroads in the country as he once planned. But he will get a $22 million golden parachute if Federal regulators approve a proposed deal to split Conrail between the CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation, a person close to the negotiations said yesterday.In what appears to be one of the more generous severance packages for outgoing management in the rapidly shrinking railroad industry, Mr. LeVan is to receive more than 40 times the $539,278 in salary and bonuses he received at Conrail in 1995. Top managers who are dismissed are also to receive hefty benefits.A spokesman for Conrail declined to answer questions about the severance packages.''From a financial standpoint, the consolation prize for Mr. LeVan is certainly enough to keep the wolf out of the kitchen and perhaps out of the living room,'' said John Spychalski, chairman of the department of business logistics at Pennsylvania State University and a former consultant to Conrail and other railroads.In October, Conrail and CSX announced a ''merger of equals'' that would have dominated rail freight east of the Mississippi. Eventually, Mr. LeVan was to become chairman of the combined company. But the rival Norfolk Southern also wanted Conrail and blocked the deal in a bitter four-month battle. To break the impasse, Conrail agreed last Friday to sell the company for $10.3 billion to CSX, which is negotiating to split the line with Norfolk Southern.CSX declined to comment on severance issues. Robert Libkind, a spokesman for Conrail, said that some of the issues were ''still under negotiation,'' although a news release from Conrail last Friday said that the company had taken action on bonuses for employees who stay with the company during the transition, and on severance packages.A person close to the negotiations who spoke on the condition of anonymity said that the severance numbers for Conrail's 2,926 nonunion employees might change slightly, but would total about $1.15 billion. ''Come payday, these numbers are not going to get significantly smaller or larger,'' the person said. ''This is the level of severance and benefits that will be provided for some 2,900 employees of Conrail.''The deal for Conrail is the latest in a string of mergers that cut the number of railroad employees in the United States by 59 percent, to 188,000, between 1980 and 1995.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/08/business/conrail-deal-focus-is-now-on-job-impact.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Deal: Focus Is Now On Job Impact<date>Published: March 08, 1997</date><text>As Conrail formally announced yesterday an agreement to sell the railroad to the CSX Corporation for $10.3 billion, the chairman of Conrail, David M. LeVan, was negotiating severance packages, bonuses and contract dates.CSX will now buy Conrail for $115 a share by June 2 and negotiate with the Norfolk Southern Corporation, which had tried a hostile takeover effort, to split Conrail's freight network.Mr. LeVan, meanwhile, has been negotiating the details of severance packages for 2,600 managers and nonunion employees and bonuses for those who stay with the company during the transition period before the deal gains regulatory approval.In a speech telecast to Conrail employees on Wednesday Mr. LeVan blamed CSX and its chairman, John Snow, for choosing ''not to fight'' Norfolk Southern and leaving Conrail no other choice but to agree to be split in two.But many people in the CSX camp contend that Mr. LeVan failed to realize that his goal of keeping Conrail intact was impossible in the face of opposition from shippers, Federal regulators and port and state officials who were determined to block any merger that left one railroad with a near-monopoly over rail freight in the Northeast.The exact value of Mr. LeVan's severance package has yet to be determined, although his five-year employment contract is worth an estimated $15 million, according to people familiar with the talks.Despite the prospect of severance packages and bonuses, the mood among Conrail employees was grim at Conrail's Philadelphia headquarters and at the company's locomotive and rail car shops.''While everybody's dancing in the streets at the south end of Manhattan, all of the employees are concerned about their future,'' said J. M. Brunkenfoefer, national legislative director of the United Transportation Union, which represents 10,000 Conrail employees. ''A few thousand people will probably lose everything they own.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/05/business/rail-systems-that-stretch-coast-to-coast-may-be-in-sight.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rail Systems That Stretch Coast to Coast May Be in Sight<date>Published: March 05, 1997</date><text>Robert D. Krebs -- chairman of Burlington Northern, the largest railroad in the country -- told stock analysts assembled at his Fort Worth headquarters last November that he would oppose a merger of Conrail and the CSX Corporation that left a single railroad in supreme control of the Eastern rail market.Mr. Krebs, whose 31,000 miles of track stretch from the West Coast as far east as St. Louis and Chicago, is hardly a proponent of small is beautiful. In 1995, he put together the Burlington Northern and the Atchison, Topeka &amp; Santa Fe railroads and set about realizing the dream of every rail baron for the past 165 years: a transcontinental railroad.With Conrail, CSX and the rival Norfolk Southern Corporation now negotiating a more or less equitable division of Conrail in the East, many rail experts see the creation of transcontinental railroads as the next step in the merger process that has swept the rail industry since deregulation in 1980. Mr. Krebs and others had worried that if one big carrier emerged from the Conrail merger the deal would not pass muster with regulators who opposed a competitive imbalance. Now, if all goes as planned, there will soon be two major railroads in the West, Burlington Northern and Union Pacific, and two in the East, CSX and Norfolk Southern.''The next step is for the two Western railroads to move toward combinations with their Eastern counterparts to form two major networks that bridge the nation,'' said John Spychalski, chairman of the department of business logistics at Pennsylvania State University and a rail expert. ''It is one dimension of the renaissance of the rail freight industry. But companies still have to find ways to provide service of such quality and price that it is competitive in relation to other forms of transportation.''In New York, port officials are hoping that the proposed division of Conrail between CSX and Norfolk Southern will result in competitive rail service that will enable New York to retain its status as the hub port on the East Coast, fending off challenges from both Norfolk, Va., and Halifax, Nova Scotia. The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey opposed any Conrail merger that would have left one railroad in control of the New York market, feeling it would result in higher shipping rates than in a competitive environment.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/04/business/rival-suitors-may-split-up-conrail-parts.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rival Suitors May Split Up Conrail Parts<date>Published: March 04, 1997</date><text>Conrail is close to a $10.3 billion agreement with the CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation that would split Conrail's railroad network between the two carriers, bringing to an end a bloody four-month battle for control of rail freight in the East, people familiar with the negotiations said yesterday.Under the tentative plan, CSX -- possibly with Norfolk Southern -- would buy Conrail for about $115 a share in cash and then sell about half of Conrail's rail lines to rival Norfolk Southern, giving both companies roughly equal freight routes throughout the Northeast and providing them each with access to New York, the largest market in the country.Norfolk Southern would pay CSX about $4.2 billion. CSX, in turn, would be required to sweeten its existing offer for Conrail by almost $1 billion, thereby matching Norfolk Southern's $10.3 billion hostile offer for Conrail and allowing both companies to claim victory.''All three sides came to the conclusion that a settlement was the only way to get this resolved in the near term,'' said Brian Routledge, an analyst with Prudential Securities. ''You'll now have two balanced rail freight systems in the East and the West.''Conrail's directors, who had been meeting all day yesterday, issued a statement last night that stopped short of endorsing the deal, although they appeared to have given up on their longstanding desire to keep the company intact. The statement said the directors had authorized Conrail management to ''negotiate an amendment'' to the CSX merger agreement ''that would assure that the Conrail shareholders receive $115 in cash per share at the earliest possible date.''Investors embraced the proposed agreement, driving shares of Conrail up $7.125 yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange to close at $111.625, less than the deal price but 57 percent higher than when the battle began last October. Norfolk Southern shares rose $2.75 to close at $93.875 and CSX rose $2.875, to $49. Word of the tentative agreement appeared on Sunday in The Washington Post.The apparent breakthrough in the railroad war was a victory for Norfolk Southern, which had sought to break up the CSX-Conrail merger, contending that it was anticompetitive in that it would give the combined company virtual control over rail freight in the Northeast.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/13/business/norfolk-southern-begins-tender-offer-for-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK SOUTHERN BEGINS TENDER OFFER FOR CONRAIL<date>Published: February 13, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it had begun a tender offer for the 90.1 percent of the common shares of Conrail Inc. it does not already own. Before Norfolk Southern, a hostile bidder based in Norfolk, Va., can buy additional shares, it must find a way to defeat Conrail's ''poison pill'' defenses, which are designed to make a hostile acquisition too expensive. Norfolk Southern and the CSX Corporation, based in Richmond, are battling for control of Conrail, based in Philadelphia. CSX has agreed to buy Conrail for $9.43 billion. Norfolk Southern has offered $115 a share, or $10.32 billion. Norfolk Southern said it intended to ''consummate a merger'' if enough Conrail shares were tendered by the offer's deadline of March 12.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/01/business/conrail-postpones-meeting-to-avoid-coup.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CONRAIL POSTPONES MEETING TO AVOID COUP<date>Published: February 01, 1997</date><text>Conrail Inc. said late yesterday that it would hold its annual shareholders meeting on Dec. 19, 1997, seven months later than normal. Pushing the meeting date back is seen as a defensive tactic should the Norfolk Southern Corporation, a hostile bidder for the railroad, and dissident shareholders, seek to win control of the board. Norfolk Southern's chief executive, David R. Goode, warned earlier this week that his company would try to replace Conrail's board if a friendly resolution to the three-month battle for Conrail could not be reached. The Conrail meeting would be held only if a friendly merger with a rival railroad company, the CSX Corporation, does not go through. The announcement by Conrail came after chief executives of the three companies ended a meeting without indicating whether any progress had been made. ''No further details on this meeting or timing of future meetings will be announced,'' a statement from the executives said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/31/business/lack-of-confidentiality-pact-could-stall-conrail-talks.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Lack of Confidentiality Pact Could Stall Conrail Talks<date>Published: January 31, 1997</date><text>For the first time since the takeover battle for Conrail began more than three months ago, the three companies involved are expected to meet today in Washington and discuss redrawing the rail freight map for the Eastern United States.But it remains to be seen whether a peaceful resolution is possible. Conrail and the Norfolk Southern Corporation, which has made a hostile bid for Conrail, wrangled yesterday over a confidentiality agreement for the talks. Executives of those companies and of the CSX Corporation, Conrail's preferred merger partner, opted to go ahead with the meeting, but absent an agreement shielding the content of the talks, it appears doubtful that they will discuss any substantive issues.''This makes it difficult for any meaningful talks to occur,'' said Anthony Hatch, a transportation analyst with NatWest Securities. ''I think we have to come to some resolution either before or after this gets to the regulators. Right now, Norfolk and CSX are both saying they're committed to owning Conrail. Somebody is going to have to back down. On the other hand, neither side is willing to break off the talks. The publicity would be horrendous.''The struggle between the competing railroads began in October when CSX and Conrail announced a friendly merger agreement. Norfolk Southern, fearing that it would become a weak competitor, quickly mounted its bid, eventually offering $10.5 billion. Using Pennsylvania's strict anti-takeover laws -- Conrail is based in Philadelphia -- Conrail and CSX were able to defend their $9.4 billion merger against Norfolk Southern. But Norfolk was able to persuade Conrail shareholders to block CSX from completing its purchase.Last week, Linda Morgan, chairwoman of the Surface Transportation Board, which regulates the railroad industry, urged the companies to negotiate a settlement that would provide ''competitive balance'' among railroads in the East. Two days later, the three railroads agreed to meet.''I'm not optimistic about a quick decision,'' said Douglas Rockel, an analyst with Furman Selz. ''There are still some bruised egos. Conrail doesn't want to be broken up; CSX is still seeking an edge, and Norfolk seems more willing to compromise.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/30/business/three-top-executives-to-discuss-conrail-impasse.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">THREE TOP EXECUTIVES TO DISCUSS CONRAIL IMPASSE<date>Published: January 30, 1997</date><text>The top executives of Conrail Inc., the CSX Corporation and the Norfolk Southern Corporation will meet tomorrow in a major step aimed a resolving a stalemate in the three-month takeover battle for Conrail. David Goode, the chief executive of Norfolk Southern, announced the meeting yesterday. Mr. Goode declined to disclose any details about the meeting with the chief executive of Conrail, David LeVan, and the chief executive of CSX, John Snow. Conrail, based in Philadelphia, and CSX, based in Richmond, could not be reached for comment on the meeting. Conrail has repeatedly said it is committed to its proposed $9.5 billion merger with CSX despite a rival $10.3 billion bid from Norfolk Southern, based in Norfolk, Va.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/18/business/norfolk-wins-a-big-round-in-the-battle-over-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Wins A Big Round In the Battle Over Conrail<date>Published: January 18, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation won a significant victory yesterday in the battle for control of rail freight in the East as Conrail shareholders rejected a measure that would have allowed the CSX Corporation to proceed with its $9.3 billion merger with the railroad.Norfolk Southern, which has made a hostile $10.5 billion bid for Conrail, said the vote at the special stockholders meeting in Philadelphia had sent a ''powerful message'' to Conrail's board that shareholders had endorsed its offer. Conrail's directors had asked shareholders to lift an anti-takeover provision and allow CSX to buy an additional 20 percent of Conrail. CSX already owns 19.9 percent.But the bidding war, already in its 102d day, is far from over. CSX and Conrail have signed an agreement that contains a $300 million breakup fee and bars either side from negotiating with another bidder until 1999.''It's an important symbolic victory,'' said Anthony Hatch, a transportation analyst with NatWest Securities. ''But it's not a rejection of the CSX-Conrail merger; it's a rejection of the merger at this price and under these conditions. Yet it was a vote to keep the game alive and that's good for Norfolk Southern.''Up until now, Norfolk has been unsuccessful in challenging the friendly merger legally. Its victory yesterday came about, in part, by its promise to pay shareholders $115 a share for 9.9 percent of Conrail shares if shareholders voted against the proposal. CSX is offering $110 a share for 40 percent of Conrail and a stock swap for the remaining 60 percent. The official outcome of the shareholder vote will not be known until tomorrow or Monday. But Conrail conceded defeat, however temporary. Norfolk Southern contended yesterday that shareholders with at least 53 percent of the company's stock outstanding had opposed the measure.''Our superior offer should be allowed to go forward and we're ready to have meaningful discussions with Conrail and CSX to that end,'' David R. Goode, chairman of Norfolk Southern, said. ''But whatever happens we will move forward.''Conrail remained unchanged yesterday, closing at $103.50 on the New York Stock Exchange. CSX climbed $1.75 to close at $46.75, while Norfolk was down 12.5 cents to finish at $88.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/16/business/intricate-suspense-at-conrail-as-shareholders-judge-two-suitors.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Intricate suspense at Conrail as shareholders judge two suitors.<date>Published: January 16, 1997</date><text>SHAREHOLDER meetings are almost always run by script. Even when there is a proxy fight, by the time of the actual meeting it is clear to the participants who will win.But tomorrow's Conrail meeting, at which shareholders will cast votes that will determine whether to accept less from the CSX Corporation in a takeover, or to hold on and hope that the Norfolk Southern Corporation will be able to pay more, is an exception. It appears that neither side is very confident.The vote, set for noon at the Academy of Music in Philadelphia, is formally on whether Conrail will waive a provision of the Pennsylvania takeover law. If it does, the way will be clear for Conrail's desired suitor, CSX, to proceed with a takeover, and CSX says it will do so promptly.If the shareholders vote against waiving the provision, then the game gets more interesting. Norfolk Southern, the other suitor, says it would then buy some stock, paying more than CSX is willing to pay and raising its stake to 9.9 percent. That offer to immediately buy some stock was made on Monday, and would seem to indicate that Norfolk Southern was not confident of victory in the vote.Even if Norfolk Southern did buy those shares, however, it would be prohibited by various laws and Conrail rules from buying more, perhaps for years. There would be more court fights and certainly more shareholder votes.On the other side, CSX and Conrail officials say they expect the vote to be close. That is an admission that most shareholders oppose their deal, because CSX and Conrail need only a majority of the votes cast. If owners representing 90 percent of the shares take part, that would require 45.1 percent of the shares. CSX has 19.9 percent, so that would mean it would need to get the votes only of 25.2 percent more.Forecasts of what will happen if the shareholders vote against the Conrail proposal have become the biggest issue in appealing for votes.''The alternative is needless delay and reduced value,'' Conrail warned in a full-page newspaper ad yesterday. Norfolk Southern, in its own ad, said the delay would be shorter than Conrail has said it would be.Whatever happens, Conrail shareholders are getting a much better deal than seemed likely in October, when Conrail spurned private talks with Norfolk Southern and agreed to a merger with CSX. That deal called for Conrail to be sold for cash and CSX stock then worth $92.50 a share.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/14/business/norfolk-southern-in-new-attack-on-conrail-merger.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK SOUTHERN IN NEW ATTACK ON CONRAIL MERGER<date>Published: January 14, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation, seeking to stop a planned $9.1 billion merger between Conrail Inc. and the CSX Corporation, proposed yesterday to buy a stake in Conrail even though its takeover bid had been rejected. Norfolk Southern said it would buy 9.9 percent of Conrail stock for $115 a share if investors defeated a key provision of the CSX merger plan, which is scheduled for a vote on Friday. Conrail is asking shareholders to waive a Pennsylvania law that effectively requires CSX, which already owns 19.9 percent of Conrail shares, to pay $110 per share in cash for the rest; a waiver would let CSX pay cash and stock. After buying the 9.9 percent stake, Norfolk Southern would begin a second offer for all remaining Conrail shares. The proposal came after the markets closed. Earlier, shares of Conrail rose $2.50, to $103.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/10/us/norfolk-southern-loses-2-rulings-in-attempt-to-take-over-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Southern Loses 2 Rulings In Attempt to Take Over Conrail<date>Published: January 10, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation lost a bid today to have a Federal court strike down an agreement that prevents Conrail Inc. from discussing a merger with anyone other than its friendly suitor, the CSX Corporation.Judge Donald Van Artsdalen of the United States District Court in Philadelphia declined to declare the provision in the merger agreement between CSX and Conrail invalid. Earlier today, the Surface Transportation Board, the Federal agency that oversees railroad mergers, also declined to strike down the provision.The decisions were blows to Norfolk Southern's hostile $10.32 billion bid for Conrail, making its richer offer, which Conrail has rejected, less likely to succeed. The CSX-Conrail lockout provision is effective until Dec. 31, 1998. Analysts have said that by preventing Conrail from merging with another company for more than two years, the lockout provision lowers the value of the Norfolk Southern offer by forcing investors to wait to get their money.A merger of Conrail with either CSX or Norfolk Southern would create the nation's third-largest freight rail line, behind Union Pacific and the Burlington Northern Santa Fe. It would also give CSX or Norfolk Southern access into the crucial New York market and track across the Eastern United States.Separately, the CSX chairman, John W. Snow, said his company was unwilling to raise its $9 billion cash and stock bid for Conrail.''We've exhausted our willingness to go higher,'' Mr. Snow said this morning at the court hearing.CSX has offered $110 in cash for each of the first 40 percent of Conrail shares that are tendered, plus 1.86 shares of CSX common stock and $16 in preferred stock for the remaining shares.Norfolk Southern is offering $115 a share in cash. However, the Norfolk Southern offer would presumably be taxable, while CSX has said the stock portion of its bid is expected to be a tax-free exchange.Conrail shareholders are scheduled to vote on Jan. 17 on whether to allow Conrail to opt out of a Pennsylvania law that prevents it from accepting CSX's two-tiered offer.Norfolk Southern says the lockout agreement gives Conrail shareholders little choice but to vote in favor of opting out of the state law, a move that would allow Conrail and CSX to proceed with their merger.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/09/business/norfolk-extends-its-hostile-bid-for-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Extends Its Hostile Bid for Conrail<date>Published: January 09, 1997</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation extended its $10.3 billion hostile takeover bid for the Conrail Corporation today until midnight Jan. 24.The railroad, based here, said 2.57 million Conrail shares, or about 2.9 percent of the almost 90 million outstanding, had been tendered by Tuesday's deadline.Norfolk Southern also said it had bank loan commitments that were more than enough to cover its $115-a-share cash offer.The move came one day before Norfolk was to ask a Federal judge to block the CSX Corporation's proposed $9.02 billion acquisition of Conrail.At issue is a so-called lockout provision that prevents the Philadelphia-based Conrail from discussing a merger with a company other than CSX until Dec. 31, 1998. On Dec. 27, Norfolk Southern asked the Surface Transportation Board, a Federal regulator, to strike down the provision.Conrail shareholders are scheduled to vote Jan. 17 on the proposed merger with CSX, based in Richmond.CSX has already acquired 19.9 percent of Conrail shares for $110 a share in the first phase of its offer, the most it can acquire under Pennsylvania law in a two-tiered offer. Its offer is for 40 percent cash and 60 percent stock.Conrail operates 11,000 miles of track in 12 Northeastern and Midwestern states, the District of Columbia and Quebec province in Canada.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/07/business/csx-sells-portion-of-conrail-stake.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CSX Sells Portion Of Conrail Stake<date>Published: January 07, 1997</date><text>The CSX Corporation last week sold 85,000 shares of Conrail Inc. CSX said it wanted to quash assertions that the size of its stake in Conrail meant that under Pennsylvania law it would have to pay cash for all Conrail shares.The contentions were made in court cases by the Norfolk Southern Corporation and a Conrail shareholders group.CSX agreed in December to pay $9.3 billion in stock and cash in a friendly merger with Conrail. After the merger partners revised terms of their deal, Norfolk Southern raised its all-cash offer by $500 million, to $10.5 billion.CSX said in documents filed with regulators that it had sold the shares on the New York Stock Exchange at prices from $98.875 to $99.125 a share.Norfolk Southern and the Conrail shareholders group have argued in court documents that shares held by Conrail directors should be counted together with a 19.9 percent Conrail stake, or 17.9 million shares, acquired by CSX in a tender offer, thus giving CSX control of more than 20 percent and putting the Pennsylvania law into force.CSX said it was selling the shares ''to moot certain contentions'' but that it still saw no merit in claims by Norfolk Southern and the shareholders group.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/30/business/rival-seeks-federal-action-against-conrail-csx-deal.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rival Seeks Federal Action Against Conrail-CSX Deal<date>Published: December 30, 1996</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation has asked a Federal agency to overrule a provision in Conrail's $9.3 billion merger deal with the CSX Corporation that prohibits Conrail from seeking another merger partner before 1999.Norfolk Southern, which has offered $10.5 billion for Conrail, said this weekend that it had asked the Surface Transportation Board, the Federal agency that oversees railroads, to rule that the provision ''constitutes unlawful control by one railroad over another.''A spokesman for Conrail, Bob Sullivan, said Norfolk Southern's petition to the board was ''completely without merit, and we will respond in due course.''Norfolk Southern has also sued in Federal court seeking to block the provision. A hearing on that motion is scheduled for Jan. 9 in the United States District Court in Philadelphia, where Conrail is based.Some analysts and investors said that if the exclusivity provision wasnot thrown out, a victory for CSX might be assured because shareholders would not want to wait two years for a deal with Norfolk Southern.Norfolk Southern has offered Conrail shareholders $115 a share, in cash and stock. CSX, based in Richmond, has offered a combination of cash and stock that is worth about $102 a share.Both companies raised their bids earlier this month. At the same time Conrail and CSX extended the exclusivity period to Dec. 31, 1998, from July 1997.Though Norfolk Southern's bid has been higher throughout the two-month takeover fight, Conrail contends that the union with CSX is a better strategic fit.Norfolk Southern, which is based here, lost a court fight last month in which it challenged previous terms of the deal, including the earlier exclusivity provision that ruled out other talks before July 1997.The latest court hearing is expected to hinge on whether Conrail's decision to grant the extended exclusivity period is within the broad discretion allowed a board under Pennsylvania law, legal experts say.Norfolk Southern said the amendment would prohibit Conrail, without the consent of CSX, from reaching or discussing a merger with any other company until 1999, even if Conrail shareholders or the Surface Transportation Board rejected the proposed Conrail-CSX merger.''The obvious and only intent of the amended lock-out provision'' is to delay Norfolk Southern's offer for so long that Conrail shareholders will feel that they are left with no other choice but to accept the CSX merger, Norfolk Southern said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/21/business/conrail-rejects-latest-norfolk-southern-offer.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CONRAIL REJECTS LATEST NORFOLK SOUTHERN OFFER<date>Published: December 21, 1996</date><text>Conrail Inc. said yesterday that its board had rejected a sweetened $10.5 billion takeover offer from the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Norfolk raised its hostile bid by $500 million Thursday even after the Conrail board agreed not to consider a takeover proposal from any company other than the CSX Corporation until 1999. Norfolk is challenging that provision in court. Conrail has agreed to a merger with CSX, which also raised its offer on Thursday, by $870 million, to $9.3 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/20/business/rival-bidders-raise-offers-for-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Rival Bidders Raise Offers For Conrail<date>Published: December 20, 1996</date><text>The CSX Corporation and its rival, the Norfolk Southern Corporation, traded body blows yesterday in an increasingly expensive battle for control of Conrail and rail freight traffic in the Northeast.CSX opened the day by raising its friendly stock-and-cash bid for Conrail by $870 million, to $9.3 billion, as Conrail directors agreed not to consider a takeover proposal from any other company until 1999.But last evening, Norfolk Southern, which is unwilling to give up its bitter two-month fight for the railroad that has a virtual monopoly over freight traffic in the Northeast, fired back with its own revised bid: $10.5 billion cash, or $115 share.Norfolk Southern also filed suit in United States District Court in Philadelphia, seeking to dismantle the lockup provision that binds Conrail to CSX for the next two years. A hearing is scheduled for Jan. 9, and the company said it was convinced the court would not approve the Conrail board's ''wholesale abrogation of its fiduciary duties to all of its constituencies.''Most analysts and investors say that Norfolk Southern must win the court battle, otherwise the monetary value of its offer will decline over the two years it must wait, making the bid less enticing for shareholders. In that case, CSX would most likely proceed to the next stage in the merger process: regulatory approval.''It makes a lot of sense for Norfolk to raise its bid in conjunction with trying to smash the lockup provision,'' Anthony Hatch, an analyst at NatWest Securities, said. ''Both tactics must work for this to succeed. But if they can't break the lockup provision, $115 a share is not enough for people to wait until 1999. I think we're finally coming to the end of the game.''Whatever the outcome, Conrail shares continued to climb, gaining $1.75 on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday to close at $100.75. The stock price for the once-troubled railroad has climbed a giddy $29.75, or 42 percent, since the bidding war began on Oct. 15 with the announcement of a friendly, $8.1 billion agreement between Conrail and CSX. CSX stock, however, fell $1.50 on the Big Board, closing at $43.75, while Norfolk, which did not announce its new offer until after the stock market had closed, gained $2.125, to $87.375.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/06/business/conrail-and-csx-file-lawsuit-against-norfolk-southern.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CONRAIL AND CSX FILE LAWSUIT AGAINST NORFOLK SOUTHERN<date>Published: December 06, 1996</date><text>Conrail Inc. and the CSX Corporation sued the Norfolk Southern Corporation yesterday, contending that Norfolk Southern illegally tried to break up their proposed $8.7 billion merger. The lawsuit, filed in Federal District Court in Philadelphia, requests a jury trial and seeks unspecified punitive damages. ''Norfolk Southern has flooded the marketplace with false and misleading information concerning both the CSX-Conrail merger and its conditional hostile tender offer,'' Conrail and CSX said in a joint statement. Norfolk Southern, which has made a $10 billion hostile bid for Conrail, called the lawsuit frivolous. ''If they really believe that Norfolk Southern is not serious about buying Conrail, then they should remove the barriers they put up,'' Bob Fort, a spokesman for Norfolk Southern, said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/23/business/fearing-a-rate-rise-shippers-await-2d-front-in-rail-merger.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Fearing a Rate Rise, Shippers Await 2d Front In Rail Merger<date>Published: November 23, 1996</date><text>Susann D. Felton was in the midst of negotiating railroad contracts last month to handle six million tons of coal a year for the Potomac Electric Power Company when the CSX Corporation disclosed an agreement to buy Conrail.Ms. Felton, vice president for materials at Potomac Electric, said she felt a sense of dread that only grew after CSX's rival, the Norfolk Southern Corporation, began its own hostile offer for Conrail, setting off a bidding war that continues to this day. No matter who wins the battle, Potomac Electric, which receives supplies for its four coal-fired power plants from all three of the rail carriers involved in the battle, is likely to end up entirely dependent on a single railroad for three of the generators. That will not leave Ms. Felton with a lot of negotiating room.''Was I thrilled?'' she said. ''No.''She added that any shipper could count on paying at least a 60 percent premium on captive routes above what it costs where competition exists. And then there is the worry that service may deteriorate as the merged railroad struggles to cut costs.Now on the sidelines, rail users all along the East Coast are waiting for the opening of a second front in the battle for Conrail: The winning bidder must take the proposed merger before the Federal Surface Transportation Board for public review and regulatory approval. Shippers, port operators and state officials hope to be more successful in keeping their options open than they were in their unsuccessful opposition to the giant mergers in the West, where the Union Pacific combined with the Southern Pacific and Burlington Northern swallowed the Atchison, Topeka &amp; Santa Fe to together control 90 percent of all rail traffic.Indeed, they have a better chance of extracting at least some concessions this time, in part because the merger is taking place in the East, where the political spotlight is brighter, and because it revolves around Conrail, the Government-subsidized amalgamation of several bankrupt railroads. The Consolidated Rail Corporation has a near monopoly on rail freight in the Northeast, especially in the Port of New York, the richest market in the nation.Still, opponents of a merger are fighting an uphill battle. The number of major railroads has already dropped to 10 from the 40 that existed in 1980 when the industry was deregulated. Most analysts believe that when the dust finally settles there will only be two or three transcontinental railroads.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/22/business/csx-says-its-offer-for-conrail-is-oversubscribed.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CSX SAYS ITS OFFER FOR CONRAIL IS OVERSUBSCRIBED<date>Published: November 22, 1996</date><text>The CSX Corporation said yesterday that its $110 cash tender offer for 19.9 percent of Conrail Inc. shares, which is the first part of its plan to buy Conrail for $8.8 billion, was oversubscribed. But the Norfolk Southern Corporation, which is battling with CSX for Conrail, extended its competing $10 billion offer yesterday until Dec. 16. Shareholders who would rather accept Norfolk Southern's hostile offer, which is more lucrative than CSX's friendly offer, could still vote to block CSX from buying more stock, despite the fact that the tender was oversubscribed. About 85 percent of Conrail's outstanding shares were tendered by the deadline of 12:01 A.M. yesterday, when the stock was worth $96.78. CSX will purchase 17,860,124 shares of the 76,629,202 tendered.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/21/business/court-clears-conrail-csx-deal-but-agrees-to-hear-an-appeal.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Court Clears Conrail-CSX Deal But Agrees to Hear an Appeal<date>Published: November 21, 1996</date><text>A Federal appeals panel kept alive the Norfolk Southern Corporation's attempt to thwart the planned merger of the CSX Corporation and Conrail Inc. today, but it declined to block the first step of the $8.5 billion deal.The three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit denied Norfolk Southern's request for an emergency injunction to block CSX's tender offer for 19.9 percent of Conrail's shares.The offer at $110 a share, the first step in the two companies' planned $8.5 billion cash-and-stock merger, was to expire at midnight.But the three judge panel also said that it would consider Norfolk Southern's motion for an expedited appeal of a Federal judge's rejection on Tuesday of the company's request to block the deal.The appeals panel asked the parties in the case to submit arguments by 2 P.M. on Thursday. CSX said, nevertheless, that it would proceed with the tender offer.CSX and Conrail said in a joint statement: ''We are pleased that the U.S. Court of Appeals has let stand yesterday's District Court ruling. Despite Norfolk Southern's continuing attempts to derail the merger of Conrail and CSX, we are committed to each other and to the great future of our combined companies.''Norfolk Southern is pursuing a hostile $10 billion cash offer for Conrail, and has sought in court to block Conrail's merger with CSX, contending that Conrail has improperly failed to consider the rival offer.On Tuesday, Federal District Judge Donald Van Artsdalen, who rejected Norfolk Southern's arguments, said Conrail's board had acted properly.Conrail shareholders are to vote on the deal in December. Norfolk Southern has asked the court to prevent CSX from voting any Conrail shares acquired in the tender.While the appeals panel denied Norfolk Southern's request for an emergency order blocking the tender offer, its willingness to hear arguments about an appeal means the court battle is not yet over, takeover specialists said.Takeover stock traders said the ruling raises the possibility that a later appellate decision could prevent CSX from voting the shares, or otherwise interfering with the merger and leave CSX holding some $2 billion worth of Conrail stock.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/20/business/judge-rejects-move-to-block-csx-conrail-merger-deal.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Judge Rejects Move to Block CSX-Conrail Merger Deal<date>Published: November 20, 1996</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation failed to thwart a giant railroad merger between its rival, the CSX Corporation, and Conrail yesterday, when a Federal judge in Philadelphia refused to grant a preliminary injunction blocking the $8.5 billion deal.The battle for Conrail and for supremacy of the rail freight industry east of the Mississippi is far from over, however.Norfolk Southern, which has offered $10 billion for Conrail, immediately appealed the decision by Federal District Judge Donald VanArtsdalen in Philadelphia. More important, CSX must still persuade Conrail shareholders next month to allow the railroad to acquire more than 20 percent of Conrail through its friendly, though less lucrative, offer.''The next battleground is going to be the proxy fight leading up to the shareholder meeting in December,'' said Barry Benzing, a lawyer at Wolf, Block, Schorr &amp; Solis-Cohen, whose firm is representing four arbitragers hoping that Conrail goes to the highest bidder. ''It looks as if CSX will have a headstart now, but Norfolk clearly has the superior economic offer.''With yesterday's ruling in hand, CSX is now expected to counter Norfolk Southern's advertising blitz with its own campaign promoting its offer. The CSX offer would give shareholders $110 cash a share for 40 percent of Conrail shares and, if the deal is approved, a stock swap worth $84.22 a share for the remaining 60 percent of the shares. Norfolk Southern is offering $110 a share for all Conrail stock.People close to the negotiations say that CSX will sweeten the offer for the remaining 60 percent of Conrail in early December to get the votes it needs.Barring a successful appeal by Norfolk Southern, CSX is expected to complete its tender at 12:01 A.M. tomorrow for 19.9 percent of Conrail, giving shareholders about $2 billion in cash for a merger that may not take place until 1998, if at all.Norfolk Southern had sought to block the friendly combination, contending in Federal court that Conrail's directors had abrogated their fiduciary responsibilities by agreeing to ''unprecedented'' merger terms that barred them from considering another richer offer for 270 days and prevented them from lifting the company's poison pill rights plan for any bidder other than CSX.Moreover, Norfolk said that CSX's coercive, two-tiered, cash-and-stock offer was an attempt to stampede shareholders into accepting CSX's lower offer.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/19/business/deadline-on-conrail-unfair-witness-says.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Deadline on Conrail Unfair, Witness Says<date>Published: November 19, 1996</date><text>CSX Corporation's proposal to acquire Conrail Inc. for $8.5 billion will succeed unless a deadline of Wednesday is removed, an expert witness for the Norfolk Southern Corporation said today in Federal court.Testifying at the opening of hearings on Norfolk Southern's lawsuit to block the acquisition, John Coffee, a Columbia University law professor, said frightened Conrail shareholders would tender their shares to avoid missing the cash portion of the two-tiered CSX offer.United States District Judge Donald W. Van Artsdalen said he would rule on the suit by 4 P.M. today.Norfolk Southern has offered $110 a share in cash, or $10 billion, in a hostile bid for Conrail. CSX is offering $110 a share in cash for the first 40 percent of Conrail and 1.856 CSX shares for the rest, or about $82.38 a share based on Friday's closing.In its lawsuit, Norfolk Southern charges that Conrail violated Federal securities laws by making misleading statements to coerce shareholders into tendering shares to CSX.CSX hopes to obtain at least 19.9 percent of Conrail shares by the time its tender offer expires on Wednesday. That would give it momentum for a December vote in which Conrail shareholders could opt out of a Pennsylvania law that says a company cannot accept a takeover bid with a second tier that is worth less than the first.If CSX gets the 19.9 percent of shares it wants, Professor Coffee said, the company is virtually assured of winning shareholder approval to opt out of the state law.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/16/business/conrail-fight-neither-side-can-afford-to-be-loser.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Fight: Neither Side Can Afford To Be Loser<date>Published: November 16, 1996</date><text>Forget Tyson and Holyfield. The next round in a much bigger heavyweight boxing match, pitting the transportation giants CSX and Norfolk Southernagainst each other in the battle for the Eastern railroad crown, opens in Federal District Court in Philadelphia on Monday. And crowding around the ring will be arbitragers, analysts, shareholders, railroad executives, lawyers and investment bankers with a stake in the outcome.Norfolk Southern has the financial edge. It has offered nearly $10 billion to buy Conrail, hoping to knock out the proposed $8.5 billion friendly merger between CSX and the Consolidated Rail Corporation. Norfolk asserts that Conrail directors abandoned their fiduciary duty, working with CSX ''to coerce, mislead and fraudulently manipulate Conrail's shareholders to swiftly deliver control of Conrail to CSX,'' denying shareholders the profit from Norfolk's richer offer.CSX may have the longer legal reach, though. Its deal with Conrail enjoys the advantages of Pennsylvania's rigorous anti-takeover statutes, and that, John W. Snow, chairman of CSX, argues, allows directors to act in the long-term interests of the company rather than the short-term interests of investors.''We are committed to our merger with Conrail because of the irresistible business logic of the combination,'' Mr. Snow said.This fight has become so bitter and bruising because neither company can afford to lose. The one that wins Conrail's virtual monopoly on rail traffic in the Northeast will emerge as the dominant freight carrier east of the Mississippi. The railroad that is forced to lick its wounds, Anthony Hatch, an analyst at NatWest Securities, said, ''potentially becomes a regional railroad.''The losing company, he added, ''faces an uncertain future.'' ''It's still viable, but the exciting phase of railroading will pass it by,'' he said. Ultimately, it could well be swallowed up by one of the two big Western railroads looking to form a coast-to-coast link.For a lot of Conrail shareholders, though, the battle mostly comes down to dollars and cents. There is a yawning gap between Norfolk Southern's offer of $110 a share cash and the current stock-and-cash bid from CSX that is valued at $93.42.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/14/business/conrail-steadfast-in-commitment-to-csx-takeover-bid.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CONRAIL STEADFAST IN COMMITMENT TO CSX TAKEOVER BID<date>Published: November 14, 1996</date><text>Conrail Inc., the Northeast railroad that is the target of two rivals, reiterated yesterday its agreement to an $8.5 billion takeover bid by the CSX Corporation and its rejection of a $10 billion hostile bid by the Norfolk Southern Corporation -- the second time Conrail has rejected a Norfolk Southern offer. Conrail has repeatedly said the CSX offer will provide more strategic benefits. Last week, the Richmond-based CSX had slightly sweetened its cash-and-stock bid for Conrail. The Philadelphia-based Conrail, which operates on 11,000 miles of track mostly in 12 Northeastern states, said its board had recommended that shareholders not tender their shares to Norfolk Southern.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/13/business/csx-puts-off-making-a-higher-offer-to-acquire-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CSX Puts Off Making a Higher Offer to Acquire Conrail<date>Published: November 13, 1996</date><text>Despite intense pressure to match a $10 billion all-cash bid from the rival Norfolk Southern Corporation, the CSX Corporation has decided for now not to raise its offer for Conrail.CSX concluded that it made no sense to fuel the bidding war with Norfolk Southern by sweetening the stock portion of its offer before it could reinforce its position by acquiring 19.9 percent of Conrail's shares later this month, according to two people familiar with the negotiations between Conrail and CSX.Directors from both Conrail and CSX, who had announced a merger agreement on Oct. 15, had been meeting Monday night and again on Tuesday to work out a response to Norfolk Southern's bid of $110 a share. CSX's latest offer is for cash and stock valued at $93.69 a share, based on yesterday's closing stock price.Conrail, which is based in Philadelphia, urged its partner to increase its bid and CSX submitted a new, tentative offer to the Conrail board, the two people familiar with the negotiations said. But the two sides were unable to agree on economic issues, as well as the timing of the new offer and related governance issues. CSX decided it did not have to respond so quickly.''We're still trying to come up with something that both sides can support enthusiastically,'' one person close to the negotiations said.After rising to almost $98 on expectations that CSX would raise its offer, Conrail closed at $96.875 yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, up 34.375 cents.Conrail is expected to reaffirm its commitment to its strategic merger with CSX today and to recommend that Conrail shareholders reject the latest, more lucrative offer from Norfolk Southern.Both Conrail and CSX declined to comment last night.CSX had cloaked its merger agreement with Conrail in protective armor: a $300 million break-up fee and more than $100 million in stock options granted to CSX by Conrail. More important, Conrail operates under anti-takeover statutes in Pennsylvania that permit companies to ignore richer, hostile offers.Many Conrail shareholders, however, have found Norfolk Southern's offer enticing, a sentiment many have conveyed to Conrail's directors.For its part, Norfolk Southern called on Wall Street and Conrail shareholders to support its offer for Conrail.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/09/business/norfolk-raises-bid-for-conrail-to-10-billion.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Raises Bid for Conrail To $10 Billion<date>Published: November 09, 1996</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation raised the ante yesterday for Conrail in the battle to control rail freight in the East by increasing its bid by 10 percent, to $10 billion cash, or about $1.5 billion more than the offer from its rival bidder, the CSX Corporation.Only three days ago, CSX sweetened its own cash-and-stock offer and Conrail reaffirmed its Oct. 15 merger agreement with CSX and strengthened the ties between the two railroads. CSX offered $110 a share in cash for 40 percent of Conrail's stock immediately. After the merger is approved by Federal regulators, CSX would acquire the remaining 60 percent through a stock swap. At yesterday's closing price, the entire offer is worth about $93 a share.Norfolk Southern now is offering $110 cash a share for all shares of the Consolidated Rail Corporation and the $17-a-share gap between the two offers may be too much for either CSX or Conrail to ignore. Some analysts expect that CSX will have to take some action, possibly before Conrail's board meets on Tuesday to issue a response to Norfolk Southern's hostile tender offer. In the meantime, Conrail, which is based in Philadelphia and controls nearly all freight traffic in the Northeast, has asked shareholders not to act on the offer from Norfolk Southern.''CSX's offer is of lesser economic value and it makes it harder for the Conrail board to forget their fiduciary responsiblity,'' said Douglas W. Rockel, an analyst at Furman Selz Inc. ''If they still want to acquire Conrail they have to consider revising their offer.''The latest move by Norfolk Southern sent Conrail's share price up by $3.375 to close at $96.375 on the New York Stock Exchange, while Norfolk Southern's shares closed down 37.5 cents at $86.625 and CSX was unchanged at $44.25.Norfolk's richer offer might have pushed Conrail's stock even higher, but the battle for Conrail is complicated by anti-takeover laws in Pennsylvania designed to protect companies from hostile acquisitions.Conrail shareholders have to approve the merger ultimately, but under state statutes, the company's directors can shun a higher offering price in the interests of the corporation and employees. In addition, the merger agreement between CSX and Conrail contains a $300 million breakup fee, more than $100 million in stock options for CSX and a freeze-out provision that bars Conrail from negotiating with another bidder until July.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/06/business/norfolk-southern-ends-talks-with-csx.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK SOUTHERN ENDS TALKS WITH CSX<date>Published: November 06, 1996</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said last night that it had terminated discussions with the CSX Corporation over their competitive bids to buy Conrail Inc. At the same time, Norfolk reaffirmed its all-cash $100-a-share offer for Conrail. On Oct. 23, Norfolk Southern announced a hostile offer intended at upending a friendly merger between CSX and Conrail. On Monday, CSX said it was discussing a post-merger sale of some of Conrail's assets to Norfolk. While confirming the talks, Norfolk insisted it was still pursuing its bid. CSX could not be reached for comment. The statement was released after the stock market closed. Shares of Norfolk Southern fell $1.75 yesterday, to $89, CSX slipped 87.5 cents, to $44, and Conrail fell $1.375, to $92.25.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/05/business/conrail-stock-shaken-by-suitors-conflicting-accounts-of-talks.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail Stock Shaken by Suitors' Conflicting Accounts of Talks<date>Published: November 05, 1996</date><text>Conflicting accounts of discussions between the Norfolk Southern Corporation and CSX Corporation over the fate of Conrail yesterday sent the stock of the railroad prized by both companies into a steep dive before it pulled out later in the day.Both CSX and Norfolk Southern are in a bitter struggle for control of Conrail, the railroad that dominates the Port of New York and much of the Northeast. Norfolk Southern initiated a rich counterbid for Conrail aimed at upending a friendly merger between CSX and Conrail that had been announced last month. The bidding war sent Conrail stock soaring on the expectation of further bidding.But stock of the Consolidated Rail Corporation opened sharply lower yesterday, down as much as $8.25 on early reports that Norfolk would abandon its competing offer for Conrail. The drop was prompted by a statement from CSX saying it was discussing a post-merger sale of some of Conrail's assets to Norfolk Southern. But Norfolk Southern promptly replied that it was still very much in the hunt, and Conrail recouped much of the early loss. It closed at $93.625, down $1.625.''We are still very much in the bidding for Conrail,'' said Robin Chapman, a spokesman for Norfolk Southern, based in Norfolk, Va. ''We agreed to discuss the competitive balance regardless of which railroad gets Conrail.''Both sides agreed that talks had taken place between them and indeed were continuing. But nearly everything else was in dispute. CSX contends that Norfolk initiated the talks over the weekend, while Norfolk counters that CSX was the instigator.Wall Street was rife with its own interpretations: Had Norfolk Southern blundered by agreeing to discussions about a post-merger distribution of track rights and assets that would gain regulatory approval, a move that seemed to indicate that it could not foil the CSX-Conrail merger? Or, as some analysts surmised, had CSX taken advantage of Norfolk's naivete in agreeing to the discussions in the first place by putting their own spin on the nature of the discussions?''It's really debatable who initiated these discussions,'' said Anthony Hatch, an analyst at the NatWest Securities Corporation. ''But whether Norfolk Southern blundered, or CSX took advantage of them, it's clear that Norfolk is not conceding the battle.''</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/24/business/norfolk-starts-bidding-war-for-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Starts Bidding War For Conrail<date>Published: October 24, 1996</date><text>Opening a multibillion-dollar bidding war to be the dominant rail freight company east of the Mississippi, the Norfolk Southern Corporation offered yesterday to pay $9.15 billion for Conrail Inc., topping last week's offer for the railroad from CSX Inc. by more than $1 billion.The prize in the battle between the rail giants is Conrail's virtual monopoly on Northeast rail lines and the ability to offer single-line service from Miami to Boston and east of the Mississippi. Norfolk would leap past CSX in size if it were to win Conrail, while CSX would obtain a strong advantage over its rival if it emerged as the victor. And each suitor appeared to be maneuvering to gain a piece of Conrail even if it lost the bid for control.Norfolk's all-cash offer generated excitement on Wall Street, sending Conrail's stock up sharply by nearly $11 a share, to $95.625. But the battle is far from over and it is not clear whether Norfolk will be able to overcome all the hurdles that CSX and Conrail have placed in its way. In signing their Oct. 15 merger agreement, the two railroads set up a number of deterrents to hostile offers, including a $300 million breakup fee and the cost of extensive stock options granted by Conrail to CSX.''Traditionally a low-profile, conservatively managed company, Norfolk has come out with all guns blazing,'' said Douglas W. Rockel, an analyst at Furman Selz Inc. ''CSX may come back with a counteroffer, but clearly Norfolk wants Conrail.''Under Norfolk's tender offer, Conrail shareholders would get $100 in cash for each share -- about 13 percent more than the offer from CSX, a mix of stock and cash that values Conrail at $87.70 a share.''This proposal is better on every point than the CSX-Conrail proposal announced last week,'' argued David R. Goode, chief executive of Norfolk, which has pursued Conrail for more than a decade. ''A combined Norfolk Southern-Conrail will create a more balanced Eastern rail system and will do so by increasing, rather than diminishing, competition.''Mr. Goode spoke to reporters yesterday at the Chase Manhattan Bank auditorium at 247 Park Avenue. Chase is one of four banks agreeing to provide CSX with a five-year, $4.8 billion loan to finance the merger with Conrail.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/16/business/conrail-accepts-8.4-billion-offer-by-eastern-rival.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">CONRAIL ACCEPTS $8.4 BILLION OFFER BY EASTERN RIVAL<date>Published: October 16, 1996</date><text>Correction AppendedConrail Inc., the freight railroad that dominates the Northeast, said yesterday that it had agreed to merge with the CSX Corporation, a far larger railroad that blankets the Southeast, Middle Atlantic and eastern Midwest.The merger, valued at $8.4 billion, would be the biggest yet in the cascade of deals that has been combining railroads since the deregulation of the industry in the 1980's, and it would leave most of the nation east of the Mississippi with just two big railroads that carry only freight.Conrail and CSX have routes extending nearly 30,000 miles, with about 54,000 miles of track, from Boston to New Orleans and from Chicago to Miami. The combined company would also control CSX's Sea-Land container shipping subsidiary and its inland barge company.Its only major rival would be the Norfolk Southern Corporation, which had itself often expressed interest in merging with Conrail and might yet try to top CSX's bid. At the very least, Norfolk Southern will demand and receive rights to run trains over its rival's tracks in some areas that would otherwise lose competitive freight service under the merger, according to Wall Street analysts. CSX and Conrail said they expected to seek Government approval of the merger early next year and to complete it by the end of 1997.''It's the right merger at the right time between the right people,'' said John W. Snow, chairman, chief executive and president of CSX. ''We are getting America's rail transportation infrastructure ready for the 21st century.''The merger would unite the oldest company in American railroading -- CSX is the descendant of the Baltimore &amp; Ohio Railroad, which built the first track from Washington northwest along the Potomac River -- with one of its youngest. Conrail, formally known as the Consolidated Rail Corporation, was created in a multibillion-dollar Government bailout of the bankrupt Penn Central and other Northeastern railroads two decades ago.The new company would have more than 50,000 employees and revenues of $14 billion, based on 1995's performance, making it the nation's largest railroad in terms of revenue.Anticipating criticism that the merger would reduce competition, CSX and Conrail contended that united they could offer many shippers a better alternative to trucking, especially on the crowded highways from the Northeast to Florida and other Southern states. Mr. Snow noted that trucking was roughly a $300 billion industry, 10 times the size of the American railroads.Correction: October 28, 1996, Monday A map in Business Day on Oct. 16 showing the principal rail lines owned by the CSX Corporation and Conrail Inc. included a track erroneously. The track that runs along Florida's eastern coast from Jacksonville to West Palm Beach is owned by the Florida East Coast Railway, not CSX.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/15/business/company-news-20-million-charge-to-be-taken-for-early-retirements.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS;$20 MILLION CHARGE TO BE TAKEN FOR EARLY RETIREMENTS<date>Published: November 15, 1995</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it would take a charge of $20 million, or 16 cents a share, against earnings in the fourth quarter to pay for early retirement packages. The company earlier had said that 272 salaried employees had accepted the retirement packages. That represented 57 percent of the 475 employees 55 and older who were eligible. Norfolk Southern, which is based in Norfolk, Va., operates rail service over about 14,500 miles in the Southeast and the Midwest. It has about 25,000 employees.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/03/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-increasing-capital-spending.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN INCREASING CAPITAL SPENDING<date>Published: December 03, 1994</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation, a railroad company, said yesterday that it planned to increase capital spending to $695 million next year from $634 million in 1994. The spending includes $220 million for the carrier's rail, crosstie and ballast programs; $148 million to purchase 125 six-axle locomotives; $57 million to rebody 3,500 coal cars and $9 million for Norfolk Southern's motor carrier subsidiary, North American Van Lines Inc. It is also spending $52 million to buy 414 multi-level racks to carry automobiles and 300 60-foot boxcars for use in automotive and aluminum service. It is also rebuilding 86-foot boxcars for automotive parts service.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/11/29/business/nc-rail-stock-slides-24.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">N.C. Rail Stock Slides 24%<date>Published: November 29, 1994</date><text>The shares of the North Carolina Railroad Company plummeted 24 percent today, after the state-controlled system agreed to extend its 99-year-old lease with the Norfolk Southern Corporation.N.C. Railroad, -- which is 75 percent-owned by the State of North Carolina, -- will receive at least $8 million a year to rent its 317 miles of track linking the port at Morehead City to Raleigh, Greensboro and Charlotte, under terms of the agreement struck last week.While that's more than 13 times the annual rent Norfolk Southern now pays, it is a puny 1.5 percent return on the railroad's assets, which are valued at $512 million, according to an independent appraisal."We're getting railroaded," said Walker Rucker, a shareholder who represents holders of about one-third of the railroad's publicly traded shares. "This lease extension satisfies the state's needs and Norfolk Southern's, but it's deficient to shareholders."N.C. Railroad shares, which rarely trade, plunged $8.50, to a 52-week low of $27, in over-the-counter trading of 5,000 shares. The stock traded as high as $40.50 in April, amid hopes that a new lease would raise the stock's value. Norfolk Southern shares fell 25 cents on the New York Stock Exchange to $59.875.The proposed agreement is the latest chapter in a century-old controversy spawned by the bargain-basement terms of the original lease. Norfolk Southern had been paying about $600,000 a year to use the tracks, an agreement that was dubbed "The Crime of the Century" in 1895 by a Raleigh newspaper.State officials have long maintained that more important than lease payments, the railroad generates jobs. North Carolina wants to keep the lease terms low, so it can use the rail network to lure more businesses and keep major state businesses -- such as the Philip Morris Companies, the RJR Nabisco Holdings Corporation and Fieldcrest Cannon Inc. -- on track with a major railroad.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/04/business/company-news-2-big-eastern-railroads-said-to-discuss-merger.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; 2 Big Eastern Railroads Said to Discuss Merger<date>Published: August 04, 1994</date><text>Two large Eastern railroads, the Norfolk Southern Corporation and Conrail Inc., are discussing a possible merger, according to people familiar with the companies' plans.The talks raise anew the possibility that the two railroads would join forces. Norfolk Southern, the fourth-largest railroad in terms of revenue, made its first offer to buy Conrail, currently the fifth-largest railroad, in 1984 for $1.2 billion, and pulled its final offer to buy the railroad for $1.9 billion in 1986 in part because of a six-month impasse in getting approval for its offer from the House of Representatives.The Federal Government, which owned Conrail at the time, eventually sold the railroad in an initial public offering. Consolidation TrendA merger of the two railroads, with combined revenues of $7.1 billion, would add to a consolidation trend that has reshaped the rail industry since it was deregulated in 1980. To cut costs, many railroads have merged to achieve economies of scale and more efficient operations.If an agreement is reached, the combined railroad would operate track that stretches from Boston to New Orleans, and from Chicago to Jacksonville, Fla.Spokesmen for Conrail and Norfolk Southern declined to comment on the talks, which were first reported yesterday in The Journal of Commerce.Stocks of both railroads surged early yesterday on the news, but after a day of heavy trading, shares of Conrail ended $2.25 higher at $56.50, while Norfolk Southern's stock fell 12.5 cents a share, to $63.625. 'Makes Sense'Scott Flower, a transportation analyst at Kidder, Peabody, said that if an agreement was reached, it would likely be a stock swap. As the on-again, off-again courtship of these railroads suggests, a merger "makes sense for all sorts of reasons," Mr. Flower added.Besides their extended geographic reach, both railroads are large carriers of coal and have big interests in "intermodalism," a rapidly growing part of the industry in which railroads carry truck trailers over long distances to destinations where they are then delivered by local drivers.Two large railroad mergers were announced in recent weeks. In late June, Burlington Northern Inc. and the Santa Fe Pacific Corporation announced a plan to merge in a stock swap valued at $2.7 billion. And two weeks ago, Kansas City Southern Industries said it was selling its railroad business to the Illinois Central Corporation in a stock swap worth about $1.6 billion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/12/29/business/company-news-north-american-van-lines-to-sell-freight-unit.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORTH AMERICAN VAN LINES TO SELL FREIGHT UNIT<date>Published: December 29, 1993</date><text>North American Van Lines Inc., a unit of the Norfolk Southern Corporation, said yesterday that it would sell North American Freight Systems to privately held DeBoer Inc. of Blenker, Wis. The terms were not disclosed. The sale would complete the departure of Norfolk Southern from the commercial trucking business. The assets in the sale include two terminals, 410 trailers and 1,500 trucks.North American Van Lines, based in Fort Wayne, Ind., has been selling its truck operations to concentrate on higher-margin services like shipping household goods, said Dennis Koziol, the vice president of corporate planning for the company.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/08/20/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-offers-voluntary-retirement-plan.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN OFFERS VOLUNTARY RETIREMENT PLAN<date>Published: August 20, 1993</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation has offered 600 nonunion employees a voluntary retirement program. Norfolk Southern, which owns the Norfolk Southern Railway, said about 13 percent of nonunion employees who are age 55 or older this year were eligible. A company spokesman would not speculate on how many employees would accept the offer. Shares of Norfolk Southern rose $2.125 yesterday, to a 52-week high of $69.625, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/07/06/us/4-injured-and-200-evacuated-as-train-derails-in-tennessee.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">4 Injured and 200 Evacuated As Train Derails in Tennessee<date>Published: July 06, 1993</date><text>At least four people were injured and more than 200 evacuated from their homes early today after a train derailed and one of its chemical tankers caught fire, officials said.The 29-car Norfolk Southern train derailed before dawn near Harriman, 36 miles west of Knoxville, and a car carrying highly flammable methyl ethyl ketone exploded, said Danny Pitchford, a spokesman for the Tennessee Emergency Management Agency.Residents of a nursing home and houses within a mile of the derailment were ordered to leave the area avoid poison gas from the fire and the danger of explosion of a propane tanker. But emergency workers were able to keep the flames contained and away from the propane tanker, Mr. Pitchford said.Four residents of Harriman were hospitalized with skin and eye irritations and breathing problems, he said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/06/26/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-to-sell-2-of-its-van-line-divisions.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; NORFOLK SOUTHERN TO SELL 2 OF ITS VAN LINE DIVISIONS<date>Published: June 26, 1993</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it would seek to sell two of North American Van Lines Inc.'s four divisions as part of a restructuring of the trucking unit. Norfolk said North American Van Lines, based in Fort Wayne, Ind., would seek a buyer for its commercial transport division and its Tran-Star Inc. subsidiary, which provides refrigerated transportation services. North American Van Lines accounted for $829.6 million, or 18 percent, of Norfolk Southern's 1993 revenue of $4.66 billion. In a statement, Norfolk Southern said the sale would improve the profitability of North American Van Lines by enabling it to focus on transporting household goods and specialized commodities in domestic and international markets.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/01/30/business/company-news-rail-concern-posts-loss.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Rail Concern Posts Loss<date>Published: January 30, 1992</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said today that it lost $354.6 million in the fourth quarter because of a special charge for job cuts and asset write-downs.The loss was in contrast to earnings of $117.1 million, or 75 cents a share, in 1990's fourth quarter.Excluding the special charge of $680 million, fourth-quarter earnings would have totaled $143.1 million. Sales were flat at $1.1 billion.Norfolk Southern, which operates the Norfolk &amp; Western Railway and the Southern Railway, said 1991 earnings totaled $29.7 million, or 20 cents a share, down 95 percent from $556.1 million, or $3.43 a share, in 1990.The company said its 1991 profits would have totaled $527.4 million without the charge. Revenue for the year was $4.45 billion, down 2 percent from $4.62 billion in 1990.Norfolk Southern stock rose 12.5 cents today, closing at $56.50.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/26/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-voluntary-layoffs.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Norfolk Southern Voluntary Layoffs<date>Published: November 26, 1991</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said it was offering its train service workers a voluntary layoff package that included a one-time compensation payment. It said employees whose applications were accepted would each receive a one-time $50,000 buyout. The offer covers employees who started working before Sept. 1, 1984.For employees 55 years of age and older who leave the company by Dec. 31, the program would also provide medical coverage and a $10,000 death benefit. Norfolk Southern said employees leaving the company under the program could also be eligible to receive an additional $60,000 each under a tentative agreement with union officials. Norfolk Southern said its offer would expire Dec. 6.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/07/26/business/norfolk-s-profit-falls-10.2.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk's Profit Falls 10.2%<date>Published: July 26, 1990</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said today that its second-quarter earnings fell 10.2 percent from a year earlier, when the company had a one-time $13.6 million gain.The transportation company said it earned $155.9 million, or 95 cents a share, down from $173.7 million, or 99 cents a share, in the 1989 quarter.Second-quarter revenue totaled $1.18 billion, up less than 1 percent from $1.17 billion in 1989.The drop in earnings was attributed in part to the $13.6 million after-tax gain that inflated Norfolk Southern's 1989 second-quarter earnings. The gain came from the sale of a portion of Norfolk Southern's trailer-train holdings.The company also said some of its divisions reported drops in revenue or increases in expenses, but it gave no other reasons for the income decline. A company spokesman said Norfolk Southern's earnings had been affected by fuel costs and other factors.Norfolk Southern's shares were unchanged today, at $44.875, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/04/26/business/profits-rise-at-norfolk.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Profits Rise At Norfolk<date>Published: April 26, 1990</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation reported today that its first-quarter net income rose 4.8 percent on a 2.7 percent increase in revenue.The company said it earned $140.2 million, or 84 cents a share, in the first three months of the year, up from $133.8 million, or 75 cents a share, a year earlier. First-quarter revenue rose to $1.14 billion, from $1.11 billion a year earlier.''Strong coal traffic has continued into 1990, with coal, coke and iron ore revenues up 11.1 percent over last year,'' the company's chairman and chief executive, Arnold B. McKinnon, said.The higher ore traffic more than offset a 1.3 percent drop in merchandise revenues and a 2.4 percent decline in revenues from the company's North American Van Lines subsidiary, Mr. McKinnon said. He said revenue rose 7 percent in agricultural commodities, 5.4 percent for chemicals and 2.6 percent for paper.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/10/28/business/company-news-norfolk-will-trim-5000-jobs-company-news.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Norfolk Will Trim 5,000 Jobs COMPANY NEWS<date>Published: October 28, 1987</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation is taking a $620 million special charge in connection with a cost-cutting restructuring that will eliminate 5,000 jobs and dispose of 15 percent of its rail track, the company said today.The railroad and transportation company said the charge resulted in a third-quarter net loss of $248.5 million, in contrast to a profit of $127.8 million, or 68 cents a share, after unusual gains a year earlier.Revenue rose slightly to $1.03 billion, from $1 billion a year earlier.Norfolk Southern said it planned to eliminate 5,000 jobs by 1990, which combined with earlier programs would bring to 6,000 the total number of job cuts expected to be made through voluntary early retirement and other means.The company also planned to sell or abandon about 2,700 miles of its 17,000 miles of track in 20 states.The cutbacks were expected to result in cost savings of $78 million next year and between $115 million and $143 million by 1990, said Rob Chapman, a spokesman.Without the special charge, Norfolk Southern would have posted a profit of $103.3 million, or 55 cents per share, down 19.2 percent from the previous year. Results from third quarter 1986 included an after-tax gain of $16.4 million in the sale of stock in Santa Fe Southern Pacific. Without the special charge, third quarter 1987 revenue would have been $350.5 million, or $1.85 a share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/09/11/business/bethlehem-order.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Bethlehem Order<date>Published: September 11, 1987</date><text>The Bethlehem Steel Corporation said its freight car division had received an order from the Norfolk Southern Corporation for 500 covered hopper railroad cars, used for the shipment of cement. The division said it was the largest single order received since it was formed in August 1983. Each steel hopper car would hold 3,000 cubic feet. Bethlehem said shipment would begin in the fourth quarter. The company's stock price jumped $1.375 today, to $17.75 a share, after the deal was announced.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/06/07/business/norfolk-southern-s-risky-one-track-strategy.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Southern's Risky One-Track Strategy<date>Published: June 07, 1987</date><text>THINGS are calmer now for Arnold B. McKinnon, the new chairman and chief executive of the Norfolk Southern Corporation.Mr. McKinnon spent the early part of the year recovering from triple-bypass heart surgery while somehow keeping tabs on the giant freight railroad's tangled takeover battle for Piedmont Airlines. Now, he said, ''I go out on the railroad a lot more, but I try to pace myself.''For different reasons, the pacing also extends to his long-term strategy for Norfolk. Sipping a glass of orange juice during a recent interview in his office here, Mr. McKinnon summed up his thinking with a line from Alexander Pope: ''Be not the first by whom the new are tried, nor yet the last to lay the old aside.''''I'm comfortable with that philosophy - it's not one where you stand still all the time,'' the 59-year-old Mr. McKinnon said in the slight drawl that recalls his native North Carolina.That kind of measured mix of change and continuity has served Mr. McKinnon well during his 36-year career at Norfolk and one of its predecessor companies, the Southern Railway System. But there are questions about whether that approach will work now for Norfolk.Spurred by deregulation and shifting market demands, many railroads have branched out into other forms of transportation and even adopted an international perspective. Yet Norfolk has remained mostly on the sidelines while its cash reserves have swelled, making it vulnerable to a takeover attempt, some analysts say.The freight carrier, the fifth-largest in the nation, has made only one acquisition - North American Van Lines, a medium-sized trucking company - since it was formed in 1982 from the merger of Southern and the Norfolk &amp; Western Railway. It failed in its ambitious bid to win Conrail, withdrawing its $1.9 billion offer for the Government-owned line last year in the face of Congressional pressure for a public sale. And many analysts say Norfolk was not unhappy to lose Piedmont to another bidder, USAir; Norfolk made a huge profit on its Piedmont stock.In short, Norfolk remains pretty much what it was when it was formed: a freight line that operates in 20 states in the East and South and the Canadian province of Ontario. By contrast, some of Norfolk's rivals, including the CSX Corporation and the Union Pacific Corporation, have diversified significantly, in ways that industry experts consider to be the wave of the future.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/23/business/business-people-a-reluctant-courtship-for-piedmont-president.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">BUSINESS PEOPLE; A RELUCTANT COURTSHIP FOR PIEDMONT PRESIDENT<date>Published: February 23, 1987</date><text>This is probably a time of mixed feelings for William R. Howard, the president and chief executive of Piedmont Aviation Inc., the parent of Piedmont Airlines.He can feel pride that he has groomed the consistently profitable carrier into a business attractive enough to lure at least two suitors. But the takeover offers come as Mr. Howard is still pursuing efforts to make North Carolina-based Piedmont a major force in American air travel.Last week, offers from the Norfolk Southern Corporation and the USAir Group apparently took the airline's future out of his hands.A sweetened offer from USAir led a special board committee of outside directors to withdraw its recommendation that the board accept the Norfolk Southern offer of $65 a share in cash. After deliberating for six hours on Thursday, the Piedmont board decided to open the bidding to anyone and await further offers.According to analysts, the recent runup in Piedmont's share price makes it likely that Norfolk Southern, which owns a 19.4 percent stake, will take its stock profits and abandon the acquisition effort. If no other bid comes in, that would mean Mr. Howard and the board have to contend with the USAir offer.Mr. Howard joined Piedmont in 1978 after a career at Eastern Airlines. He has helped develop a strategy to build Piedmont service and hubs in cities such as Dayton, Ohio, and Baltimore that had been neglected by the large carriers.A lawyer by training who learned how to fly when he was 16, Mr. Howard became president of Piedmont in May 1981, succeeding Thomas H. Davis, the founder of the airline, based in Winston-Salem, N.C.Piedmont has thrived under Mr. Howard, posting steady profits during an era when even the most stable carriers have had bad years.The 63-year-old executive has expanded the airline at a torrid pace, from 46 aircraft in 1978 to more than 150 this year. It has become the third-largest carrier in the New York area.When he is not on the job, Mr. Howard likes to fly his own plane to the Florida Keys, where he has a second home and yacht. He also collects motorcycles and antique cars.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/20/business/piedmont-aviation-board-invites-further-bidding.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">PIEDMONT AVIATION BOARD INVITES FURTHER BIDDING<date>Published: February 20, 1987</date><text>After deliberating for six hours yesterday on two competing takeover offers, the board of Piedmont Aviation Inc. opened the bidding to all interested parties.The company, which is the parent of Piedmont Airlines, said the move was spurred by the sweetened, $1.65 billion offer that the USAir Group made on Wednesday.Donald F. McGuire, a staff vice president at Piedmont, said that no new offers had been received as of late yesterday. Meanwhile, Piedmont's stock gained $3.875, to $69.75 a share, in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Norfolk Bid Loses SupportThe Piedmont board is also considering a bid for $65 a share, or $1.49 billion, from the Norfolk Southern Corporation, a major freight railroad in the East. A special committee of independent Piedmont directors had advised acceptance of the Norfolk Southern offer, but the panel said yesterday that it would withdraw the recommendation.A Piedmont spokesman said that Norfolk Southern, which already owns 19.4 percent of the airline, had not made any further proposals. Analysts have speculated that Norfolk Southern was more interested in bidding up the price of Piedmont to increase the value of its holdings than in actually acquiring the company.Thus, the USAir offer to pay $71 a share for half of Piedmont's 23 million shares, subject to a merger agreement, seemed to be the offer that the board would be discussing unless new bidders materialized.Under USAir's offer, Piedmont shares not acquired under a tender offer would be converted into shares of USAir common stock with an average market price of $73 a share. Piedmont's AttractionsPiedmont, which is based in Winston-Salem, N.C., has grown rapidly under deregulation and has been profitable for 10 years. One carrier that might find it particularly attractive is Delta Air Lines.Both Delta and Eastern Air Lines have major Atlanta hubs, and Delta is now facing heavy competition from the Texas Air Corporation because of that company's takeover of Eastern. Thus, Delta might want to offset that challenge with an acquisition.In addition, Piedmont has been competing with Delta in many other markets, so Delta might want to keep the carrier out of USAir's hands.James J. Hartigan, president and chief executive of United Air Lines Inc., said yesterday that his company was not interested in Piedmont.A merger of Piedmont with another airline must be approved by the Department of Transporation. Since both Piedmont and Pittsburgh-based USAir serve mostly markets in the the East, overlapping in some markets, such a merger could face tough scrutiny.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/19/business/usair-lifts-offer-for-piedmont.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">USAIR LIFTS OFFER FOR PIEDMONT<date>Published: February 19, 1987</date><text>The USAir Group raised the stakes yesterday in the struggle for Piedmont Aviation Inc. with a sweetened $1.65 billion merger offer.The new offer, analysts said, is expected to be studied by a special committee made up of independent directors advising the Piedmont board. The bid is conditional on Piedmont's entering into a merger agreement.Before USAir improved its bid, the committee had already recommended that an offer from the Norfolk Southern Corporation - of $65 a share in cash for all of Piedmont's stock - be approved by the Piedmont board, which is scheduled to meet today. That offer values Piedmont Aviation, the owner of Piedmont Airlines, at $1.49 billion. Terms of the Tender OfferUSAir offered to pay $71 a share in cash in a tender offer for up to half of Piedmont's common stock, which totals 23 million shares on a fully diluted basis. USAir said each share of Piedmont stock not acquired under the tender offer would be converted in the merger into USAir common shares for an average market price of $73.In its original plan, disclosed Tuesday, USAir made alternative offers: either $71 a share, all in stock, or $68 a share, half in stock and half in cash.Piedmont shares, listed on the New York Stock Exchange, closed at $65.875 yesterday, up 50 cents.One analyst said the new offer bears out the thinking of many investors who suspected that Norfolk Southern would rather sell out its holding at a high price than actually buy the rest of Piedmont, of which it already owns 19.4 percent. A Strong Combination SeenBut USAir, analysts agreed, seems eager to take over Piedmont, one of the fastest and most profitable carriers in the nation. Piedmont would strengthen USAir's ability to meet the challenge of huge carriers such as the Texas Air Corporation.One analyst, who did not want to be identified, said another reason USAir might be pressing to acquire Piedmont now would be to complete the deal before Congress, already concerned by the wave of mergers and growing concentration in the airline industry, could begin putting pressure on the Transportation Department to change its hands-off policy.The department would have to approve the acquisition by USAir. Since both carriers serve mostly markets in the East, overlapping in some cases, such a merger could face tougher scrutiny than others.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/18/business/norfolk-bid-backed-at-piedmont.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK BID BACKED AT PIEDMONT<date>Published: February 18, 1987</date><text>Piedmont Aviation Inc., the parent of Piedmont Airlines, announced yesterday that it had received takeover offers from two companies and that a committee of its board members had recommended approval of a $65-a-share all-cash bid by the Norfolk Southern Corporation.The panel of directors decided against recommending either of two alternatives proposed by the USAir Group. The Pittsburgh-based airline company offered $71 a share in stock or $68 a share divided evenly between stock and cash.Piedmont said that the recommendation by a special committee of independent directors favoring the Norfolk Southern bid, which would be worth $1.49 billion, was scheduled to be reviewed by the entire Piedmont board tomorrow. Stock Up $6.25, to $65.375Investors apparently believed yesterday either that another offer would materialize or that Norfolk Southern or USAir would sweeten its offer. Piedmont closed at $65.375, up $6.25 a share, in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange.Norfolk Southern, a major freight railroad on the East Coast, already owns 19.4 percent of Piedmont. On Jan. 27, it announced that it was considering acquiring the carrier, which has its headquarters in Winston-Salem, N.C., and primarily serves markets in the East. Analysts said at the time that they did not see a good potential fit between the two concerns.''I'm still puzzled,'' an airline analyst, who did not want to be identified, said about Norfolk's offer. He added that Norfolk could have made the bid to force up the bids of rivals, which would enhance its profits on its large block of Piedmont stock. Regarded as Well ManagedNevertheless, Piedmont is regarded as a well-managed airline that has had impressive growth since the airline business was deregulated in the late 1970's, and one that, even if its operations could not be easily integrated with Norfolk Southern's, could have a positive effect on the rail company's bottom line.Analysts found the bids by USAir were more understandable from a strategic point of view because USAir expects to feel more pressure from such major large carriers as Eastern, which has been taken over by the Texas Air Corporation. Texas Air is committed to reducing Eastern's costs and, if successful, could put great pressure on such higher-cost carriers as USAir.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/02/business/business-people-norfolk-southern-chief-extends-tour-of-duty.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">BUSINESS PEOPLE; Norfolk Southern Chief Extends Tour of Duty<date>Published: February 02, 1987</date><text>Robert B. Claytor was to have retired Dec. 31 as chairman and chief executive of the Norfolk Southern Corporation, one of the nation's largest railroads. But circumstances forced him to stay on for a while more, and his last days in command are proving to be busy ones.Mr. Claytor's successor, Arnold B. McKinnon, had heart surgery in early January after a problem was discovered during a physical examination late last year. Mr. Claytor, who turns 65 in February, agreed to fill in until the end of February while Mr. McKinnon, 59, recovers.Mr. Claytor's final month in office could be quite eventful, since Norfolk Southern announced on Tuesday that it was considering the acquisition of Piedmont Airlines. That would be the first merger between an American railroad and an airline.It was at a meeting of analysts in New York that Mr. Claytor made the announcement about Piedmont. He also told them that the railroad had record earnings last year, would split its stock three for one and increase its dividend.''It's been sort of hectic,'' said a company spokesman, Magda Ratajski. Mr. Claytor was unavailable for an interview, she said.Last year was also busy for the railroad. Norfolk Southern had bid $1.9 billion to buy Conrail, the Northeast freight line, from the Government. The deal would have created the largest rail system in the country, but Norfolk withdrew its bid, citing effects of the new tax law and delays in getting Congressional approval.Also last year, Mr. Claytor was driving a 23-car train carrying nearly 1,000 guests on a company outing when it derailed in the Great Dismal Swamp National Wildlife Refuge in Virginia, injuring more than 200 on the train. Engineer error was largely ruled out in a preliminary Federal report.Mr. Claytor did not start out as a railroad man, but as a lawyer with degrees from Princeton and Harvard Law School. He worked for the American Telephone and Telegraph Company from 1948 to 1951 and then joined the Norfolk and Western Railway Company, becoming president in 1980. That line merged with the Southern Railway in 1982 to create the Norfolk Southern, and Mr. Claytor was made chairman and chief executive of the combined operation.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/01/28/business/company-news-norfolk-considers-acquiring-piedmont.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Norfolk Considers Acquiring Piedmont<date>Published: January 28, 1987</date><text>In a disclosure that many analysts found puzzling, the Norfolk Southern Corporation said yesterday that it was considering the acquisition of Piedmont Airlines. Such a merger, if it occurred, would be the first between a railroad and an airline in the United States.Regardless of the historic implications, industry analysts were hard-pressed to find strategic reasons for such a union. ''You can't put a 727 on a rail car,'' said Burton M. Strauss Jr., the rail analyst for E. F. Hutton &amp; Company.Norfolk Southern, a major freight railroad on the East Coast, already owns 19.4 percent of Piedmont Aviation Inc., the nation's seventh-largest carrier and one of the fastest growing. Norfolk Southern acquired the stock over a five-year period at an average price of about $29.Yesterday's disclosure, made in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, sent Piedmont's stock surging in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange, where it closed at $58.25, up $8.75. Based on the closing price, the indicated total cost for Piedmont would be at least $1.08 billion. Norfolk Southern's stock lost $2 a share, closing at $90.50. Tactical Move SeenThe filing came one day after the expiration of a standstill agreement that had prohibited Norfolk Southern from buying more than 20.5 percent of Piedmont's shares.Most analysts interpreted the railroad's filing as a tactical move that would drive up the price of Piedmont's stock and flush out other potential bidders. A competitive offer would be likely to drive up the stock price further.Analysts said that, depending on the size of a rival bid, if one was made, Norfolk Southern would have the option of selling its holdings at a huge profit or of attempting to acquire the airline itself. Industry sources said that Norfolk Southern had hired Salomon Brothers to help it analyze its alternatives.Sources close to Norfolk Southern said that if the railroad ultimately sold its stake in Piedmont, it would be in a position to make an even larger acquisition in an industry more closely related to its own.Norfolk Southern was selected in 1985 by the Transportation Department to acquire Conrail, the Government-subsidized freight railroad system, for more than $1 billion. That deal was aborted last year by Congress, which now intends to sell Conrail in a public offering. No Proposal ReceivedPiedmont said in a statement that it had not received any proposal from Norfolk Southern, but did not throw cold water on such a prospect.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/14/business/company-news-norfolk-southern-acts-to-trim-staff.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Norfolk Southern Acts to Trim Staff<date>Published: October 14, 1986</date><text>NORFOLK, Va., Oct. 13— The Norfolk Southern Corporation said its railroad units are seekng to speed normal attrition among train and engine-service employees by offering them a one-time separation allowance. A spokesman would not say how many separations are sought nor estimate what the offer would cost the company. Under the offer, eligible engineers or firemen who entered service before Nov. 1, 1985, would receive a $35,000 allowance while conductors, train and yard workers would get $25,000. There would also be continued health insurance and other benefits for those employees over age 55. The company said the offer was open to employees in certain districts of its Norfolk &amp; Western unit and its Southern Railway unit.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/01/business/norfolk-purchase-challenged.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Norfolk Purchase Challenged<date>October 1, 1986</date><text>The Interstate Commerce Commission erred when it approved the acquisition of North American Van Lines, a large trucking company, by the Norfolk Southern Corporation, a leader in the railroad industry, a Federal appeals court ruled today. It returned the case to the I.C.C. for reconsideration.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Interstate Commerce Commission erred when it approved the acquisition of North American Van Lines, a large trucking company, by the Norfolk Southern Corporation, a leader in the railroad industry, a Federal appeals court ruled today. It returned the case to the I.C.C. for reconsideration.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/08/28/business/company-news-conrail-s-value-put-at-over-3-billion.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CONRAIL'S VALUE PUT AT OVER $3 BILLION<date>August 28, 1986</date><text>Conrail, the Federally owned freight railroad that the Government is trying to sell, should be worth more than $3 billion on the open market, the Congressional Budget Office said today. The amount tops by a wide margin the $1.9 billion offer for Conrail that the Norfolk Southern Corporation withdrew last Friday after winning approval from the Senate but running into opposition in the House.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Conrail, the Federally owned freight railroad that the Government is trying to sell, should be worth more than $3 billion on the open market, the Congressional Budget Office said today. The amount tops by a wide margin the $1.9 billion offer for Conrail that the Norfolk Southern Corporation withdrew last Friday after winning approval from the Senate but running into opposition in the House.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/08/26/opinion/conrail-s-proper-parents.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Conrail's Proper Parents<date>August 26, 1986</date><text>The corpse of the Reagan Administration's plan to merge Conrail with the giant Norfolk Southern rail system has finally been pronounced dead by its proponents. Elizabeth Dole, the Secretary of Transportation, now favors returning Conrail to private ownership by selling the Federal Government's 85 percent share of the stock. That's good news for Conrail, good news for private purchasers and good news for the public.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The corpse of the Reagan Administration's plan to merge Conrail with the giant Norfolk Southern rail system has finally been pronounced dead by its proponents. Elizabeth Dole, the Secretary of Transportation, now favors returning Conrail to private ownership by selling the Federal Government's 85 percent share of the stock. That's good news for Conrail, good news for private purchasers and good news for the public.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/08/23/business/norfolk-is-ending-1.9-billion-offer-to-us-on-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">NORFOLK IS ENDING $1.9 BILLION OFFER TO U.S. ON CONRAIL<date>August 23, 1986</date><text>The Norfolk Southern Corporation said today that it was withdrawing its $1.9 billion bid to buy Conrail, the big Northeast freight line in which the Government has an 85 percent stake. The merger would have created the largest railroad system in the country. Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Hanford Dole, who championed the proposed sale to Norfolk Southern, agreed today to consider a public stock offering as another way the Government could sell off its interest. The Government has long wanted to return Conrail to private hands and get back some of its $7 billion investment.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Norfolk Southern Corporation said today that it was withdrawing its $1.9 billion bid to buy Conrail, the big Northeast freight line in which the Government has an 85 percent stake. The merger would have created the largest railroad system in the country. Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Hanford Dole, who championed the proposed sale to Norfolk Southern, agreed today to consider a public stock offering as another way the Government could sell off its interest. The Government has long wanted to return Conrail to private hands and get back some of its $7 billion investment.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/28/business/washington-watch-effects-of-icc-merger-move.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Washington Watch; Effects of I.C.C. Merger Move<date>July 28, 1986</date><text>THE Interstate Commerce Commission's sobering punch to merger mania in rejecting the proposed merger of the Southern Pacific Railroad into the Santa Fe Railway is being viewed as having far-reaching implications for several other big merger plans subject to Government review. It appears to close yet another door to the Reagan Administration's faltering efforts to sell the Government-controlled Consolidated Rail Corporation to the Norfolk Southern Corporation, owner of the Norfolk &amp; Western and Southern Railways. It could also spell trouble for pending airline mergers.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] THE Interstate Commerce Commission's sobering punch to merger mania in rejecting the proposed merger of the Southern Pacific Railroad into the Santa Fe Railway is being viewed as having far-reaching implications for several other big merger plans subject to Government review. It appears to close yet another door to the Reagan Administration's faltering efforts to sell the Government-controlled Consolidated Rail Corporation to the Norfolk Southern Corporation, owner of the Norfolk &amp; Western and Southern Railways. It could also spell trouble for pending airline mergers.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/07/business/washington-watch-the-deadlock-over-conrail.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Washington Watch; The Deadlock Over Conrail<date>Published: July 7, 1986</date><text>The Heritage Foundation, hoping to succeed where others have failed, will soon try to break the stalemate on the sale of Conrail. The issue is caught between Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Hanford Dole and John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan and chairman of the House Committee on Energy and Commerce, which controls the sale legislation in the House. The research organization, which has been very influential with the Reagan Administration, will urge a public sale of the Government-controlled railroad. That would be a switch from the foundation's longtime support of Secretary Dole's position favoring a negotiated sale to the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Foundation insiders, who hope to make their case with Secretary Dole soon, note the growing consensus in the House for a public sale, based on increased readings from Wall Street investment bankers that such a sale is feasible. But without a shift in Secretary Dole's position, a top foundation official speculated that any sale of Conrail is doomed, damaging hopes for a broader program of selling Government assets to private companies.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/06/25/business/business-people-norfolk-southern-picks-its-next-chief.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">BUSINESS PEOPLE; Norfolk Southern Picks Its Next Chief<date>June 25, 1986</date><text>In a surprise move, the Norfolk Southern Corporation, the railroad giant, said yesterday that Arnold B. McKinnon, its executive vice president for marketing, would succeed Robert B. Claytor as chairman and chief executive. Norfolk Southern elected Mr. McKinnon, 58 years old, to the new position of vice chairman, effective next Tuesday, and said he would replace Mr. Claytor on Dec. 31, when Mr. Claytor retires. Wall Street had expected Mr. Claytor, 64, to retire by the end of the year. But several analysts - as well as some company executives - said that they had expected Harold H. Hall, the company's president and chief operating officer, to succeed Mr. Claytor. One company executive said, however, that Mr. McKinnon is well regarded within the company.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] In a surprise move, the Norfolk Southern Corporation, the railroad giant, said yesterday that Arnold B. McKinnon, its executive vice president for marketing, would succeed Robert B. Claytor as chairman and chief executive. Norfolk Southern elected Mr. McKinnon, 58 years old, to the new position of vice chairman, effective next Tuesday, and said he would replace Mr. Claytor on Dec. 31, when Mr. Claytor retires. Wall Street had expected Mr. Claytor, 64, to retire by the end of the year. But several analysts - as well as some company executives - said that they had expected Harold H. Hall, the company's president and chief operating officer, to succeed Mr. Claytor. One company executive said, however, that Mr. McKinnon is well regarded within the company.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/06/24/business/advertising-thompson-gets-north-american-van.html?ref=norfolksoutherncorporation">Advertising; Thompson Gets North American Van<date>Published: June 24, 1986</date><text>North American Van Lines, the household moving and trucking company based in Fort Wayne, Ind., has named J. Walter Thompson, Washington, to handle its advertising account of more than $1 million. The Norfolk Southern Corporation, which acquired North American a year ago, has used J. Walter Thompson for its railroad's advertising since 1978. There had been no active ad campaign for the van lines company since it was acquired from Pepsico. Pepsico had previously used several of its agencies on a project basis.</text></article></page></root>
