<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Occidental Petroleum Corp"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DC1E31F932A25751C1A9669D8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Adds to Its U.S. Oil Properties<date>Published: December 11, 2010</date><text>7:52 p.m. | Updated Occidental Petroleum agreed on Friday to buy oil properties in South Texas and North Dakota for $3.2 billion, further fueling the acquisition frenzy in the energy sector. The deal came the same day the China Petroleum and Chemical Corporation, or Sinopec, agreed to buy Occidental's Argentine oil and gas business for about $2.5 billion. Occidental also bought an additional 13 percent stake in Plains All-American, one of the largest pipeline operators in the United States, bringing its holdings to 35 percent. ''These properties, combined with acquisitions completed earlier this year, will more than replace the production from the sale of Argentina,'' Occidental's chief, Ray R. Irani, said in a statement. ''We expect that each of these new acquisitions together with future drilling, potential exploration and consolidation opportunities in these areas, over time, will grow to over 50,000 barrels of oil equivalent per day.'' With an expected increase in cash flow, Occidental said it would raise its quarterly dividend 21 percent. Shares in Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, rose more than 2 percent, to $93.04 a share. Energy companies, encouraged by high oil prices and cheap debt, are ramping up their deal-making around the world. ''Companies have more confidence that global oil demand is not going to continue to fall off a cliff,'' said Pavel Molchanov, an analyst at the investment bank Raymond James. The value of mergers and acquisitions in the sector has amounted to $464.5 billion so far this year, accounting for 21 percent of overall deals worldwide. The percentage of overall deals is up 32 percent over last year and is the highest on record, according to Thomson Reuters. Sinopec's purchase is part of a wider push by Chinese oil giants into Latin America and the rest of the world. Their deals for oil and gas assets globally have amounted to nearly $38.8 billion this year, with more than $13 billion in South America, according to Bloomberg data Two months ago, Sinopec agreed to pay $7.1 billon for a 40 percent stake in Repsol's business in Brazil, a country with huge offshore reserves. The China National Offshore Oil Corporation agreed in March to buy a 50 percent share of Bridas of Argentina for $3.1 billion. ''Large Chinese enterprises have been aggressively accumulating resources, particularly in places where Western companies are more reluctant to invest,'' Mr. Molchanov said. ''For China, it's not so much a commercial bargain, but rather a geopolitical strategy of locking up control over hydrocarbons, minerals and other resources.'' This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/15/business/15views.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Yahoo Needs to Look at Asian Holdings<date>Published: October 14, 2010</date><text>Asia Overlooked By Yahoo’s ChiefYahoo’s chief executive, Carol Bartz is losing her grip. With few signs that her plan to return the company’s core Internet business to relevancy is working, investors are restless. They have become increasingly focused on the company’s valuable Asian holdings, which Ms. Bartz has failed to monetize — or even make a persuasive case for keeping. A big value gap and growing impatience mean outsiders may do the job for her. It was clear when Ms. Bartz joined Yahoo in January 2009 she needed to address the company’s Asian assets, over which the company has little or no control. It was also already apparent that Yahoo’s Internet business was in danger of becoming an also-ran. Nearly two years later, Ms. Bartz has yet to answer these challenges. That is why AOL and private equity firms may be sniffing around. Unwinding Yahoo’s stake in Alibaba makes sense. Alibaba, the private company that owns China’s versions of eBay and PayPal, doesn’t really fit with the American Internet group. Alibaba’s executives are displeased with the relationship and want to buy back the stake. Ms. Bartz’s reluctance to budge is a mistake. Analysts value the 40 percent in Alibaba at $7.5 billion, and Yahoo Japan about the same. If the company can find a way to sell those stakes to minimize tax leakage — and Alibaba, for its part, has hinted that there is a way — it would unlock a big chunk of value for Yahoo’s long-suffering shareholders. Instead, it appears Ms. Bartz has focused more of her attention on fixing Yahoo’s core display advertising business. But as the dwindling fortunes of AOL show, it is tough to turn around a fading Internet operation. Yahoo’s revenue growth in the second quarter was largely stagnant while rivals reported growing Internet advertising sales. If the Asian operations are worth $15 billion, that implies that investors are valuing Yahoo’s core at less than $4 billion after adjusting for cash, or just five times estimated 2010 operating profit. Google was trading at 13 times before its impressive results were released on Thursday afternoon. Even with the prospect of having to pay taxes on any divestitures, the discount may be sufficient to tempt an outsider to try to wrap up what Ms. Bartz has failed even to begin. Occidental’s Activists Occidental Petroleum, the American oil group, is phasing out its $857 million man, the chief executive, Ray Irani. It is hard to begrudge him his handsome pay over the years, given the company’s performance. But his board allowed it to get too generous. Shareholders should thank the activists who helped cap Mr. Irani’s rewards. By any metric Mr. Irani has been lavishly rewarded. His almost $900 million haul over a decade made him the third-best paid American chief executive over the period, according to a Wall Street Journal analysis published in July. Occidental shareholders shouldn’t be overly upset. A $100 investment in the company 10 years ago would now be worth over $1,000 on a total return basis, compared with essentially no gain on the S.&amp; P. 500-stock index. Good fortune has played a part. About three-quarters of Occidental’s production is oil, a source of energy that sells at a big premium to natural gas, upon which many of Occidental’s rivals increasingly rely. In addition, most of the company’s reserves are in Texas and California, providing political stability and low royalty rates. Mr. Irani can take some credit, too. Occidental’s enviable position is the result of management judgment as well as historic luck. His contacts in the Middle East have helped the firm win lucrative business. Even so, Mr. Irani’s pay got out of hand. Over the decade considered in the newspaper analysis, Mr. Irani earned twice what the bosses at XTO Energy and Chesapeake Energy did, and their investors did better than Occidental’s. That is why two big Occidental shareholders, Relational Investors and the California State Teachers’ Retirement System, pushed to force the company’s board to pay out less. The outcome looks successful. Mr. Irani, 75, will be paid much less, but as executive chairman for several years the company will not lose his services. Meanwhile, the capable chief operating officer, Stephen Chazen, will take over as chief executive, with a lower pay scale. It is what can happen when a board, however belatedly, engages with activists for the good of all shareholders. ROBERT CYRAN and CHRISTOPHER SWANN</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/08/02/occidental-shares-unmoved-as-investors-plan-fight/?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Shares Unmoved as Investors Plan Fight<date>August 2, 2010, 8:52 pm</date><text>Shares in Occidental Petroleum changed little on Monday in response to news that two investors are organizing a proxy fight aimed at changing the oil company’s compensation and succession policies. Relational Investors, an activist hedge fund, and the California State Teachers Retirement System, a huge pension fund commonly known as Calstrs, sent a letter to Occidental last week after about a year of talks with management, representatives for both investors told DealBook. In particular, the two are taking aim at Occidental’s chairman and chief executive, Ray R. Irani. Having held both positions for about 20 years, Mr. Irani is among the nation’s highest-paid corporate chieftains. And at 75, he received a waiver to remain on the company’s board, since the retirement age for Occidental directors is 75. “The board is ossified and entrenched,” Ralph V. Whitworth, a founder of Relational, told DealBook in an interview. “And it reinforces the entrenchment of the C.E.O.” Mr. Whitworth said he and Calstrs were still determining who would be included in their slate of directors, though he would most likely be among the candidates. Earlier on Monday, Occidental said that it had named Stephen I. Chazen, its president and chief financial officer, as its chief operating officer. It also named James M. Lienert, an executive vice president for finance and planning, as Mr. Chazen’s successor as chief financial officer. “As we’ve said previously, the board has been deeply engaged in succession planning for some time, and today’s announcement is very clearly part of that process,” Richard S. Kline, an Occidental spokesman, told DealBook in a statement. But the announcement did little to appease either Relational or Calstrs. “Today’s appointment of Stephen Chazen is long overdue and a positive first step,” Ricardo Duran, a Calstrs spokesman, told DealBook on Monday. “However, we do feel it’s reactive to issues brought to them by shareholders.” Occidental shares closed on Monday at $80.19, up nearly 3 percent. But they did not move significantly after The Wall Street Journal reported the brewing proxy fight on its Web site at midday. One issue that neither Relational nor Calstrs has a problem with is Occidental’s stock price: shares in the company have climbed about 95 percent over the past five years. “It’s done well, and we give credit where credit is due,” Mr. Whitworth said, though he argued that Mr. Irani’s pay was at least three times larger than that of his peers. Occidental’s investors voted this year against its pay practices, in what is known as a nonbinding “say on pay” vote. Mr. Kline told DealBook that the company was expected to announce recommended changes within the next two months that it believes address investor concerns. But Mr. Whitworth said that he was unmoved: “There’s a palpable level of disgust among investor base here.” – Michael J. de la Merced</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/08/03/relational-and-calstrs-letter-to-occidental/?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Relational and Calstrs' Letter to Occidental<date>August 3, 2010, 1:07 pm</date><text>“Again, it is unfortunate that this process has led to this point, but we hope you understand and respect our position.” So ends the cordial but firm letter to the board of Occidental Petroleum by two big shareholders, Relational Investors and the California State Teachers Retirement System (commonly known as Calstrs), promising a proxy fight. (Read it after the jump.) As DealBook wrote on Monday, the two investors focus their ire on Occidental’s pay and chief executive succession policies. “These ongoing failings are patently inexcusable because each of them is readily within the board and central to the board’s most fundamental responsibilities.” Relational and Calstrs Letter to Occidental Petroleum Go to Previous Item from DealBook »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/08/02/two-funds-target-oxy-board-over-executive-pay/?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Two Funds Target Oxy Board Over Executive Pay<date>August 2, 2010, 4:46 am</date><text>Funds that own 1 percent of Occidental Petroleum are targeting board seats at the fourth-largest U.S. oil company because of their concern about how it pays executives, one of the funds said on Monday, Reuters reported. A spokesman for the California State Teachers’ Retirement System said in an email that his fund and Relational Investors aim to take at least four of the 13 board seats at the company’s annual general meeting next year. The move by the funds follows the rejection in May of Oxy’s pay policy by a majority of its shareholders. Chief Executive Ray Irani, whose compensation grew 40 percent in 2009 to $31.4 million, responded to that vote by saying the board would study what changes may have to be made. Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/15/opinion/15thu2.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">What $100 Million?<date>Published: October 14, 2009</date><text>Bankers will surely say “we told you so.” Citigroup’s sale of its profitable energy trading unit Phibro is exactly the kind of unintended consequence that the nation’s financiers warned us would happen when the Obama administration set out to limit their pay. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Citigroup Inc. | Andrew J. Hall We see it as a public policy success. Phibro is a high-risk, high-reward hedge fund. It has no place on the books of one of the nation’s too-big-to-fail banks. If a policy to cap bankers’ pay forces all banks to get rid of their hedge funds, it will be a winning policy. Citigroup sold Phibro to Occidental Petroleum only to rid itself of Andrew Hall, its most successful trader  or, more to the point, Mr. Hall’s promised $100 million compensation package. Kenneth Feinberg, who was hired by the White House to pass judgment on the compensation of top earners at the banks that benefited from public bailouts, probably could not have stopped Citigroup from paying the $100 million. That was determined by a contract signed before the bailout and not covered by the new rules. But the government does own 34 percent of the bank, and if Mr. Feinberg objected it would almost certainly have attracted unwanted attention from Congress. Mr. Feinberg has more direct leverage over compensation deals negotiated after the bailout. He is threatening to slash executive pay at the American International Group if the company does not reduce the $198 million in bonuses granted to executives at the trading unit that brought the company to ruin. This month he is slated to issue recommendations on the top pay of all bailed-out institutions. Meanwhile, he has done a good deed by getting Citigroup to sell Phibro. Compared with the havoc caused by investment banks like Bear Stearns, Lehman Brothers and Morgan Stanley, hedge funds played a relatively minor role in this financial crisis. But they are in an explosive business that can cause enormous damage. Mr. Hall’s unit generated about $200 million a year in earnings over the past decade. But it also posted a $100 million loss in a single day: Jan. 16, 1991, when the United States started bombing Iraq and oil prices wrong-footed Mr. Hall’s bets. These kinds of ups and downs are reasonable, perhaps, for a hedge fund playing with the money of sophisticated investors. One lesson from this crisis is that banks  which play with depositors’ money while covered by a big insurance policy financed by the taxpayer  shouldn’t be playing in any high-stakes investment games. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on October 15, 2009, on page A34 of the New York edition.Bankers will surely say “we told you so.” Citigroup’s sale of its profitable energy trading unit Phibro is exactly the kind of unintended consequence that the nation’s financiers warned us would happen when the Obama administration set out to limit their pay. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Citigroup Inc. | Andrew J. Hall We see it as a public policy success. Phibro is a high-risk, high-reward hedge fund. It has no place on the books of one of the nation’s too-big-to-fail banks. If a policy to cap bankers’ pay forces all banks to get rid of their hedge funds, it will be a winning policy. Citigroup sold Phibro to Occidental Petroleum only to rid itself of Andrew Hall, its most successful trader  or, more to the point, Mr. Hall’s promised $100 million compensation package. Kenneth Feinberg, who was hired by the White House to pass judgment on the compensation of top earners at the banks that benefited from public bailouts, probably could not have stopped Citigroup from paying the $100 million. That was determined by a contract signed before the bailout and not covered by the new rules. But the government does own 34 percent of the bank, and if Mr. Feinberg objected it would almost certainly have attracted unwanted attention from Congress. Mr. Feinberg has more direct leverage over compensation deals negotiated after the bailout. He is threatening to slash executive pay at the American International Group if the company does not reduce the $198 million in bonuses granted to executives at the trading unit that brought the company to ruin. This month he is slated to issue recommendations on the top pay of all bailed-out institutions. Meanwhile, he has done a good deed by getting Citigroup to sell Phibro. Compared with the havoc caused by investment banks like Bear Stearns, Lehman Brothers and Morgan Stanley, hedge funds played a relatively minor role in this financial crisis. But they are in an explosive business that can cause enormous damage. Mr. Hall’s unit generated about $200 million a year in earnings over the past decade. But it also posted a $100 million loss in a single day: Jan. 16, 1991, when the United States started bombing Iraq and oil prices wrong-footed Mr. Hall’s bets. These kinds of ups and downs are reasonable, perhaps, for a hedge fund playing with the money of sophisticated investors. One lesson from this crisis is that banks  which play with depositors’ money while covered by a big insurance policy financed by the taxpayer  shouldn’t be playing in any high-stakes investment games.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/10/business/10citi.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Citigroup Sheds Energy Unit and Its $100 Million Trader<date>Published: October 9, 2009</date><text>Citigroup is letting go of its $100 million man, Andrew J. Hall, and the lucrative energy trading business he ran, after Washington’s special compensation master threatened a public showdown over his nine-figure bonus. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Citigroup Inc Occidental Petroleum Corporation Go to your Portfolio » The bank handed its energy trading operation, Phibro, to Occidental Petroleum on Friday, averting one of the most closely watched clashes between a Wall Street firm and the Obama administration over executive pay. Mr. Hall’s $98 million bonus for 2008, and a $30 million bonus to another Phibro trader, had posed a problem for the Treasury Department’s pay czar, Kenneth R. Feinberg. Mr. Feinberg must approve the 25 largest pay packages this year at Citigroup and six other companies that received multiple government bailouts. The outsize bonuses have also been a political nightmare for Citigroup, in which the government took a nearly 34 percent stake after injecting $45 billion in taxpayer money. Citigroup officials maintained that bonuses pledged to Phibro employees should be exempt from Mr. Feinberg’s scrutiny because they stemmed from a pay agreement struck in 2008, before the current compensation rules took effect. Mr. Feinberg disagreed and put the bank on notice that he would issue an advisory opinion claiming the contracts promoted excessive risk-taking and ran counter to the public interest, according to people briefed on the talks. After several meetings with Mr. Feinberg, Citigroup officials concluded that their position was politically untenable and accelerated plans to sever the bank’s ties with Phibro, these people said. With Friday’s sale to Occidental, Mr. Hall and the compensation of the other Phibro trader will be removed from the pay czar’s review. Although Phibro was not one of Citigroup’s core operations, and had a fractious relationship with the bank’s leadership, it had been a big money maker for the bank since 1997. The unit brought in about $371 million in earnings for Citigroup in each of the last five years, profits that came even as huge losses elsewhere at Citigroup hobbled the banking giant. The scrutiny over Mr. Hall’s pay put Citigroup officials in a bind: face angry investors if they severed ties with Phibro and the rich revenue stream that the bank has leaned on as it seeks to repay its taxpayer lifeline, or face the public’s outrage if they kept Phibro and Mr. Hall’s pay. William B. Smith, a Citigroup shareholder who has been critical of the company for years, said the deal was the latest sign of Washington’s heavy hand. “The message is that Vikram Pandit is not the C.E.O. of the company,” he said. “You take the only division in the last 10 years that has consistently made money, and you give it away because you can’t take government backlash. Nobody in their right mind would do this deal.” Even before the furor over Mr. Hall’s bonus erupted, Citigroup officials had considered selling the business, reorganizing it as a joint venture or spinning it off. Mr. Hall had also considered Phibro and Citi a far-from-ideal marriage for years. He scarcely interacted with new management teams and did not seem to hold them in high regard, according to several people with knowledge of the situation. His discomfort only grew when the government took a stake in Citi, and he too began actively angling for a divorce in recent months. The ideal spouse, he had said, would be well capitalized and leave Phibro alone, these people said. Mr. Feinberg’s review accelerated the discussions. Although Mr. Feinberg never directed Citigroup to sever its ties with Phibro, he urged the bank’s executives to avoid a public confrontation, according the people briefed on the negotiations. Several aspects of Phibro’s pay arrangements raised eyebrows within the government, said a person briefed on the policy makers’ thinking. First, the outsize bonuses were based on a formula that allocated about 20 percent of Phibro’s profits  what some say is an unusually large portion  to a pool controlled by Mr. Hall. Second, the contract did not lay out a formula to determine the pay levels of his traders, leaving it up to Mr. Hall to decide. Citigroup officials ultimately concluded a sale was the best option. If the bank did a joint venture with Phibro, it would have required Citigroup to make a multibillion-dollar investment in the unit, or find outside investors, while still leaving Citigroup exposed to public anger over Mr. Hall’s compensation. “We didn’t just solve Obama’s problem,” one Citigroup executive said. “We had to think of the risks that the company would be under from an irritated administration or pay master.” Citigroup bankers pitched a sale of Phibro to at least seven potential buyers, including the billionaire investor Warren E. Buffett. After receiving three bids, the bank settled on Occidental about a month ago. Occidental paid slightly more than the book value of Phibro’s trading assets and agreed to invest $250 million into the firm. The deal is expected to close by the end of the year. Mr. Hall will still receive a large 2009 bonus  just not from Citigroup. Instead, Occidental, which faces no pay restrictions, will pay it after Phibro is sold. Mr. Hall will then put it back into Phibro to help finance its trading, and will do so with “significant portions” of future payouts. He is on track this year to make less than $98 million, but will still get an enormous payout. Mr. Hall may no longer be the richest employee at his new company. Ray R. Irani, Occidental’s chairman, has collected more than $884.8 million over the last 16 years, according to Equilar, an executive compensation research firm. David Segal contributed reporting. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 10, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.Citigroup is letting go of its $100 million man, Andrew J. Hall, and the lucrative energy trading business he ran, after Washington’s special compensation master threatened a public showdown over his nine-figure bonus. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Citigroup Inc Occidental Petroleum Corporation Go to your Portfolio » The bank handed its energy trading operation, Phibro, to Occidental Petroleum on Friday, averting one of the most closely watched clashes between a Wall Street firm and the Obama administration over executive pay. Mr. Hall’s $98 million bonus for 2008, and a $30 million bonus to another Phibro trader, had posed a problem for the Treasury Department’s pay czar, Kenneth R. Feinberg. Mr. Feinberg must approve the 25 largest pay packages this year at Citigroup and six other companies that received multiple government bailouts. The outsize bonuses have also been a political nightmare for Citigroup, in which the government took a nearly 34 percent stake after injecting $45 billion in taxpayer money. Citigroup officials maintained that bonuses pledged to Phibro employees should be exempt from Mr. Feinberg’s scrutiny because they stemmed from a pay agreement struck in 2008, before the current compensation rules took effect. Mr. Feinberg disagreed and put the bank on notice that he would issue an advisory opinion claiming the contracts promoted excessive risk-taking and ran counter to the public interest, according to people briefed on the talks. After several meetings with Mr. Feinberg, Citigroup officials concluded that their position was politically untenable and accelerated plans to sever the bank’s ties with Phibro, these people said. With Friday’s sale to Occidental, Mr. Hall and the compensation of the other Phibro trader will be removed from the pay czar’s review. Although Phibro was not one of Citigroup’s core operations, and had a fractious relationship with the bank’s leadership, it had been a big money maker for the bank since 1997. The unit brought in about $371 million in earnings for Citigroup in each of the last five years, profits that came even as huge losses elsewhere at Citigroup hobbled the banking giant. The scrutiny over Mr. Hall’s pay put Citigroup officials in a bind: face angry investors if they severed ties with Phibro and the rich revenue stream that the bank has leaned on as it seeks to repay its taxpayer lifeline, or face the public’s outrage if they kept Phibro and Mr. Hall’s pay. William B. Smith, a Citigroup shareholder who has been critical of the company for years, said the deal was the latest sign of Washington’s heavy hand. “The message is that Vikram Pandit is not the C.E.O. of the company,” he said. “You take the only division in the last 10 years that has consistently made money, and you give it away because you can’t take government backlash. Nobody in their right mind would do this deal.” Even before the furor over Mr. Hall’s bonus erupted, Citigroup officials had considered selling the business, reorganizing it as a joint venture or spinning it off. Mr. Hall had also considered Phibro and Citi a far-from-ideal marriage for years. He scarcely interacted with new management teams and did not seem to hold them in high regard, according to several people with knowledge of the situation. His discomfort only grew when the government took a stake in Citi, and he too began actively angling for a divorce in recent months. The ideal spouse, he had said, would be well capitalized and leave Phibro alone, these people said. Mr. Feinberg’s review accelerated the discussions. Although Mr. Feinberg never directed Citigroup to sever its ties with Phibro, he urged the bank’s executives to avoid a public confrontation, according the people briefed on the negotiations. Several aspects of Phibro’s pay arrangements raised eyebrows within the government, said a person briefed on the policy makers’ thinking. First, the outsize bonuses were based on a formula that allocated about 20 percent of Phibro’s profits  what some say is an unusually large portion  to a pool controlled by Mr. Hall. Second, the contract did not lay out a formula to determine the pay levels of his traders, leaving it up to Mr. Hall to decide. Citigroup officials ultimately concluded a sale was the best option. If the bank did a joint venture with Phibro, it would have required Citigroup to make a multibillion-dollar investment in the unit, or find outside investors, while still leaving Citigroup exposed to public anger over Mr. Hall’s compensation. “We didn’t just solve Obama’s problem,” one Citigroup executive said. “We had to think of the risks that the company would be under from an irritated administration or pay master.” Citigroup bankers pitched a sale of Phibro to at least seven potential buyers, including the billionaire investor Warren E. Buffett. After receiving three bids, the bank settled on Occidental about a month ago. Occidental paid slightly more than the book value of Phibro’s trading assets and agreed to invest $250 million into the firm. The deal is expected to close by the end of the year. Mr. Hall will still receive a large 2009 bonus  just not from Citigroup. Instead, Occidental, which faces no pay restrictions, will pay it after Phibro is sold. Mr. Hall will then put it back into Phibro to help finance its trading, and will do so with “significant portions” of future payouts. He is on track this year to make less than $98 million, but will still get an enormous payout. Mr. Hall may no longer be the richest employee at his new company. Ray R. Irani, Occidental’s chairman, has collected more than $884.8 million over the last 16 years, according to Equilar, an executive compensation research firm. David Segal contributed reporting.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/01/us/politics/01black.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">McCain Heads Today for Colombia, Where Adviser Has Long Had Ties<date>Published: July 1, 2008</date><text>At a time when the role of lobbyists and special interests are at issue in the presidential campaign, Senator John McCain leaves Tuesday on a trip to Colombia, where a senior adviser to him has long had business and political ties. Skip to next paragraph Jeff Chiu/Associated Press Charlie Black lobbied for years on behalf of Colombias leading foreign oil producer. Related Times Topics: Charles Black Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Election Guide More Politics News Since 1998, the lobbying firm headed until recently by Charlie Black, one of Mr. McCain’s closest confidants, has earned more than $1.8 million representing the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, the leading foreign producer of gas and oil in Colombia. The lobbying firm, BKSH &amp; Associates, has also represented Colombian textile and apparel manufacturers and a former foreign minister and presidential candidate who is also a prominent businesswoman. According to official filings, Mr. Black, who resigned as chairman of BKSH in March, lobbied Congress, the State Department and the White House on Occidental’s behalf regarding “general energy issues” and “general trade issues” involving Colombia. His list of activities also included winning “foreign assistance for Colombia” and efforts to block an economic embargo against the country, which has a questionable human rights record. “Though he did not have high visibility, we encountered his shadow often,” said Larry Birns, director of the Council on Hemispheric Affairs, an advocacy group that monitors Latin American human rights and political issues from Washington. Mr. McCain is making the trip in part to highlight his support for a free-trade agreement with Colombia that the Bush administration wants to see approved by Congress by year’s end. The senator, a strong free-trade advocate, has spoken in favor of the accord on the campaign trail. His presumed Democratic opponent, Senator Barack Obama, opposes the deal and frequently cites it in campaign speeches as an example of what he sees as the administration’s wrongheaded trade policies. Mr. Obama has expressed environmental and human rights concerns, including what he describes as the Colombian government’s repression of labor unions. Mr. Black has recently been at the center of campaign controversy over an interview, published in June by Fortune magazine, in which he said that another terrorist attack on the United States would benefit Mr. McCain’s candidacy. The McCain campaign declined to make him available to discuss his lobbying activities on behalf of Colombia for BKSH. “The campaign has no connection to that firm and therefore no connection to the questions you are asking,” said Tucker Bounds, a campaign spokesman. Occidental’s activities in Colombia have long been controversial, both within that country and among human-rights, indigenous-rights and environmental groups abroad. The groups have accused the company of complicity in the killing of peasants thought to be sympathetic to the left-wing guerrilla groups that operate in the area where Occidental has pipelines or drilling activities. They have also blamed Occidental for the polluting of rural areas and have accused it of intimidating Indian tribes seeking to prevent drilling on their ancestral lands. Occidental has long denied the accusations, maintaining that its practices are environmentally sound and describing its critics as unrepresentative. The most controversial episode dates from December 1998, when the Colombian Air Force dropped cluster bombs on Santo Domingo, a village near an Occidental pipeline, killing 18 people. Human rights groups and Colombian government officials say the bombing was a mistake that occurred because three employees of a Florida-based aerial security company employed by Occidental to monitor guerrilla movements had provided incorrect coordinates to the Colombian military pilots. The American employees of the security company dropped out of sight, and Colombian government efforts to have them handed over for questioning and perhaps trial were fruitless. Frustrated by what they consider the security company’s stonewalling, human rights groups filed suit in California in 2003 and 2004 against Occidental, whose headquarters is in Los Angeles. Occidental has denied any responsibility for the bombing of Santo Domingo, saying when the first suit was filed that it “has not and does not provide lethal aid to Colombia’s armed forces.” Even as the Santo Domingo attack became a cause célèbre among human rights groups in Washington, as well as some lawmakers there, Congress approved a special appropriation of nearly $100 million for the protection of oil pipelines in Colombia in 2003, when Mr. Black’s firm was lobbying on Occidental’s behalf. Atossa Soltani, executive director of Amazon Watch, a human rights group that works on behalf of Colombian Indian tribes opposed to oil drilling and pipelines on their lands, said Mr. Black was also “very active” while Congress was debating a $1.3 billion military assistance package to Colombia that became law in 2000. “We’d be making the rounds in Congress,” Ms. Soltani said, “and Oxy would be there making the rounds, too.” Occidental has come under fire as well in connection with the 2003 killing of three Colombian labor leaders who were initially and erroneously said to be affiliated with one of the guerrilla groups that regularly attack Occidental’s installations. Three Colombian soldiers, all of them members of a special unit that guards an Occidental pipeline, were charged with murder. Kitty Bennett contributed reporting. More Articles in US »At a time when the role of lobbyists and special interests are at issue in the presidential campaign, Senator John McCain leaves Tuesday on a trip to Colombia, where a senior adviser to him has long had business and political ties. Skip to next paragraph Jeff Chiu/Associated Press Charlie Black lobbied for years on behalf of Colombias leading foreign oil producer. Related Times Topics: Charles Black Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Election Guide More Politics News Since 1998, the lobbying firm headed until recently by Charlie Black, one of Mr. McCain’s closest confidants, has earned more than $1.8 million representing the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, the leading foreign producer of gas and oil in Colombia. The lobbying firm, BKSH &amp; Associates, has also represented Colombian textile and apparel manufacturers and a former foreign minister and presidential candidate who is also a prominent businesswoman. According to official filings, Mr. Black, who resigned as chairman of BKSH in March, lobbied Congress, the State Department and the White House on Occidental’s behalf regarding “general energy issues” and “general trade issues” involving Colombia. His list of activities also included winning “foreign assistance for Colombia” and efforts to block an economic embargo against the country, which has a questionable human rights record. “Though he did not have high visibility, we encountered his shadow often,” said Larry Birns, director of the Council on Hemispheric Affairs, an advocacy group that monitors Latin American human rights and political issues from Washington. Mr. McCain is making the trip in part to highlight his support for a free-trade agreement with Colombia that the Bush administration wants to see approved by Congress by year’s end. The senator, a strong free-trade advocate, has spoken in favor of the accord on the campaign trail. His presumed Democratic opponent, Senator Barack Obama, opposes the deal and frequently cites it in campaign speeches as an example of what he sees as the administration’s wrongheaded trade policies. Mr. Obama has expressed environmental and human rights concerns, including what he describes as the Colombian government’s repression of labor unions. Mr. Black has recently been at the center of campaign controversy over an interview, published in June by Fortune magazine, in which he said that another terrorist attack on the United States would benefit Mr. McCain’s candidacy. The McCain campaign declined to make him available to discuss his lobbying activities on behalf of Colombia for BKSH. “The campaign has no connection to that firm and therefore no connection to the questions you are asking,” said Tucker Bounds, a campaign spokesman. Occidental’s activities in Colombia have long been controversial, both within that country and among human-rights, indigenous-rights and environmental groups abroad. The groups have accused the company of complicity in the killing of peasants thought to be sympathetic to the left-wing guerrilla groups that operate in the area where Occidental has pipelines or drilling activities. They have also blamed Occidental for the polluting of rural areas and have accused it of intimidating Indian tribes seeking to prevent drilling on their ancestral lands. Occidental has long denied the accusations, maintaining that its practices are environmentally sound and describing its critics as unrepresentative. The most controversial episode dates from December 1998, when the Colombian Air Force dropped cluster bombs on Santo Domingo, a village near an Occidental pipeline, killing 18 people. Human rights groups and Colombian government officials say the bombing was a mistake that occurred because three employees of a Florida-based aerial security company employed by Occidental to monitor guerrilla movements had provided incorrect coordinates to the Colombian military pilots. The American employees of the security company dropped out of sight, and Colombian government efforts to have them handed over for questioning and perhaps trial were fruitless. Frustrated by what they consider the security company’s stonewalling, human rights groups filed suit in California in 2003 and 2004 against Occidental, whose headquarters is in Los Angeles. Occidental has denied any responsibility for the bombing of Santo Domingo, saying when the first suit was filed that it “has not and does not provide lethal aid to Colombia’s armed forces.” Even as the Santo Domingo attack became a cause célèbre among human rights groups in Washington, as well as some lawmakers there, Congress approved a special appropriation of nearly $100 million for the protection of oil pipelines in Colombia in 2003, when Mr. Black’s firm was lobbying on Occidental’s behalf. Atossa Soltani, executive director of Amazon Watch, a human rights group that works on behalf of Colombian Indian tribes opposed to oil drilling and pipelines on their lands, said Mr. Black was also “very active” while Congress was debating a $1.3 billion military assistance package to Colombia that became law in 2000. “We’d be making the rounds in Congress,” Ms. Soltani said, “and Oxy would be there making the rounds, too.” Occidental has come under fire as well in connection with the 2003 killing of three Colombian labor leaders who were initially and erroneously said to be affiliated with one of the guerrilla groups that regularly attack Occidental’s installations. Three Colombian soldiers, all of them members of a special unit that guards an Occidental pipeline, were charged with murder. Kitty Bennett contributed reporting.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/25/business/25conoco.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Smaller Profit at Conoco, but a Gain for Occidental<date>Published: October 25, 2007</date><text>ConocoPhillips reported a 5.2 percent decrease in third-quarter profit yesterday, while Occidental Petroleum said its third-quarter profit rose 13 percent. ConocoPhillips, which is based in Houston, said refined fuel prices failed to keep pace with gains by crude oil, narrowing profit margins on gasoline and diesel. The company, the third-largest United States oil producer, said profit fell to $3.67 billion, or $2.23 a share, from $3.88 billion, or $2.31 a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell 4.2 percent, to $46.1 billion. Margins are lower this year, said Bernard Picchi, an analyst at Wall Street Access in New York, because of higher crude oil prices and the inability of the marketers, for whatever reason, to be able to capture in their prices the cost of the raw material. ConocoPhillips has the second-largest United States refining capacity, behind Valero Energy. ConocoPhillipss output of oil and natural gas fell on downtime at fields from Alaska to the North Sea and a decision in June to exit Venezuela. The companys shares fell $1.57, or 1.9 percent, to $81.65. ConocoPhillips is the first of the three largest United States oil producers to report third-quarter earnings. Exxon Mobil plans to report on Nov. 1, and Chevron is scheduled for Nov. 2. Occidental, the nations fourth-largest oil company, said its results were helped by higher prices and production and gains from asset sales. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, said net income rose to $1.32 billion, or $1.58 a share, from $1.17 billion, or $1.36 a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 10 percent, to $4.84 billion. Occidental said it received an average of $67.81 a barrel for its oil, 9.7 percent more than a year earlier. Occidental shares rose $1.08, or 1.6 percent, to close at $67.83. More Articles in Business »ConocoPhillips reported a 5.2 percent decrease in third-quarter profit yesterday, while Occidental Petroleum said its third-quarter profit rose 13 percent. ConocoPhillips, which is based in Houston, said refined fuel prices failed to keep pace with gains by crude oil, narrowing profit margins on gasoline and diesel. The company, the third-largest United States oil producer, said profit fell to $3.67 billion, or $2.23 a share, from $3.88 billion, or $2.31 a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell 4.2 percent, to $46.1 billion. Margins are lower this year, said Bernard Picchi, an analyst at Wall Street Access in New York, because of higher crude oil prices and the inability of the marketers, for whatever reason, to be able to capture in their prices the cost of the raw material. ConocoPhillips has the second-largest United States refining capacity, behind Valero Energy. ConocoPhillipss output of oil and natural gas fell on downtime at fields from Alaska to the North Sea and a decision in June to exit Venezuela. The companys shares fell $1.57, or 1.9 percent, to $81.65. ConocoPhillips is the first of the three largest United States oil producers to report third-quarter earnings. Exxon Mobil plans to report on Nov. 1, and Chevron is scheduled for Nov. 2. Occidental, the nations fourth-largest oil company, said its results were helped by higher prices and production and gains from asset sales. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, said net income rose to $1.32 billion, or $1.58 a share, from $1.17 billion, or $1.36 a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 10 percent, to $4.84 billion. Occidental said it received an average of $67.81 a barrel for its oil, 9.7 percent more than a year earlier. Occidental shares rose $1.08, or 1.6 percent, to close at $67.83.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D71630F936A15756C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">HIGH &amp; LOW FINANCE; Risky Bets On Winning Tax Fights<date>Published: May 25, 2007</date><text>Death may still be certain, but taxes are something else entirely. Disclosures are now appearing in quarterly reports from American public companies, showing that companies are betting billions on tax breaks that may not work out. The disclosures also show that some companies keep fighting over taxes for decades. While most companies say they have cleaned up tax disputes from the 1990s and even up to 2002 or 2003, others are far slower. Some are still fighting over audits that began in the 1980s -- leaving the companies at risk of paying billions in taxes and penalties. Exxon Mobil may be the slowest of the settlers. It reports that it is still facing audits from the Internal Revenue Service for tax years back to 1989, and in Malaysia all the way back to 1983. All told, the company reports that $3.7 billion is being held in reserve to cover tax benefits the company claimed on its returns but deemed doubtful enough that it did not include them in profit reports to shareholders. The new rule from the Financial Accounting Standards Board is supposed to make all companies account for taxes in the same way, something that has not happened in the past, when accounting rules were vague and practices seem to have varied greatly. Getting into compliance now has caused some companies to cut their book values by hundreds of millions of dollars, and others to raise their values by similar amounts. The part of the rule that was perhaps most anticipated by investors and tax authorities was a requirement that companies warn shareholders of expected changes in tax reserves within the next year. The prospect of that warning scared a lot of companies, which worried that a statement that a company expected $100 million of reserves to be freed up when an audit was completed could spur the I.R.S. to get tougher in the audit. The companies begged the standards board to delay the effective date of the rule, but in vain. There have been some disclosures. Altria, the tobacco company, says ''it is reasonably possible that within the next 12 months certain U.S. state and foreign examinations will be resolved,'' providing $105 million in profits for the company. Those profits would come if the taxing authorities allowed tax benefits that the company claimed but did not report to investors, presumably because it thought there was a risk they would not be approved. But many companies found ways to talk without saying anything. ''The disclosures have been handed over to the lawyers,'' said Harvey L. Pitt, a former chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission (and a nonpracticing lawyer), ''and the lawyers are obfuscating.'' He spoke this week at a conference on the rule sponsored by Siegel &amp; Associates, a consulting firm. Consider a couple of disclosures. Here's one from JPMorgan Chase: ''It is difficult to project how unrecognized tax benefits will change over the next twelve months, but it is reasonably possible that they could change significantly.'' Here's another from Occidental Petroleum: ''It is reasonably possible that Occidental's existing liabilities for uncertain tax benefits may increase or decrease within the next twelve months primarily due to the progression of audits in process or the expiration of statutes of limitation. Occidental cannot reasonably estimate a range of potential changes in such benefits due to the unresolved nature of the various audits.'' Under the rule, companies are supposed to report in their profits any tax benefit claimed on tax returns if there is at least a 51 percent chance that the tax authorities will agree. That standard -- called ''more likely than not'' in tax jargon -- is a pretty generous one. Some companies previously posted tax benefits they thought would probably be approved, a higher standard. Book values for those companies actually increased under the new standard. But over all, more companies cut book values than raised them, said Sampriti Ganguli, managing director of the Tax Director Roundtable, a group of corporate executives. The leader in claiming tax benefits that it fears may not be accepted appears to be Merck, at $7.4 billion, according to a survey by David Zion, an analyst at Credit Suisse. General Electric and AT&amp;T also reported figures over $6 billion If those tax positions are ultimately upheld, reported profits will rise by those amounts. If they are rejected, profits will not suffer unless the tax authorities reject benefits that the companies expected to be approved and reported as profit. But cash flows will be hurt. A big question now for many companies is whether the I.R.S. will change its policies and ask to see more internal corporate documents on how the numbers were calculated, and then use the figures in audits. The I.R.S. has said it is thinking about changing its policy, Saul M. Rosen, Citigroup's tax director, said at the Siegel conference. ''Is it fair,'' he asked, ''for an agent to know what level of reserves a company has set up for a particular issue, or where a taxpayer thinks his position may have a weak point?'' If the I.R.S. finds itself embarrassed by companies reporting billions in profits after audits are settled in their favor, Mr. Rosen's question may become the next big battleground in tax policy. Chart: ''Exxon Mobil tax returns open to audit'' COUNTRY: Malaysia DATING BACK TO: 1983 COUNTRY: United States DATING BACK TO: 1989 COUNTRY: Canada DATING BACK TO: 1990 COUNTRY: Norway DATING BACK TO: 1993 COUNTRY: Equatorial Guinea DATING BACK TO: 1996 COUNTRY: Germany DATING BACK TO: 1998 COUNTRY: Nigeria DATING BACK TO: 1998 COUNTRY: Abu Dhabi DATING BACK TO: 2000 COUNTRY: Australia DATING BACK TO: 2000 COUNTRY: Angola DATING BACK TO: 2002 COUNTRY: Britain DATING BACK TO: 2002 COUNTRY: Japan DATING BACK TO: 2002 (Source by company report The New York Times)</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/09pay.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">More Nuggets on Pay From Proxy Filings<date>Published: April 9, 2007</date><text>Many of the most interesting nuggets on executive pay are buried so deep in the new corporate filings that it helps to bring along a calculator and a shovel. The Securities and Exchange Commissions new disclosure rules were supposed to make it easier for investors to understand how top managers were being paid. But piles of new data and proxy statements that are about as easy to parse as the federal tax code have even experts scratching their heads. There is an awful lot of stuff you have to wade through to get to the stuff that matters, said Jannice L. Koors, a compensation consultant at Pearl Meyer &amp; Partners. We are now in the business of data mining. Among the choice details recently unearthed in recent filings: ¶Ray R. Irani, Occidental Petroleums chairman and chief executive, is so far the highest paid corporate chief whose compensation package was tallied under the new rules. His total pay was about $52.1 million last year, according to an analysis by Equilar, the executive compensation research firm. But that was just the amount that Occidentals board awarded him last year. In fact, he took home a lot more. First, there was the $270.1 million in profit from stock options he cashed out in 2006. Then there was the $93.3 million that Mr. Irani withdrew from a huge deferred stock plan that was revealed for the first time this year under the new rules. (It is found in a table on Page 28 of the Occidental proxy statement, in the kind of fine print often used by credit card and insurance companies.) According to its proxy statement, the company ended the program late last year in light of the substantial liability and expense of the program. Of course, Mr. Irani can expect even more money down the road. Besides his annual pay, he still can tap at least four other deferred compensation plans, totaling at least $124 million. ¶International Business Machines will freeze this year an executive retention plan that helped bolster retirement benefits for Samuel J. Palmisano, its chairman and chief executive, to more than $33 million. On top of his $18.8 million pension, Mr. Palmisano is eligible to collect about $14.2 million through a special retention plan. In its proxy statement, I.B.M. said that it set up the program in 1995 to keep senior managers when the companys very existence was at risk, but that the original purpose had been met. I.B.M. closed the program in 2004 for new participants, and said that by the end of the year, it would freeze the payments earned by any existing managers. An I.B.M spokesman could not be reached for comment about the timing. ¶Buried in the proxy of the pharmaceutical giant Pfizer were details about more than the money it pays its board members and top executives. The company also took the unusual step of disclosing its independent compensation consultants compensation. The total amount of fees paid to Frederic W. Cook &amp; Co. for services to the committee in 2006 was $184,555, Pfizers proxy revealed. That works out to at least $15,000 a month just so the company can be certain that the wages and benefits of its top executives are well designed and competitive. Shareholders had asked about the information, said Bryant Haskins, a Pfizer spokesman. It was just an effort to be more transparent and go beyond what was asked for. ¶Other proxy statements appear to have been written by puzzle makers. Verizons long-term incentive plan is one notable example. Over the last three years, Verizon investor returns were slightly above the median for its industry, but two out of every three big companies in the Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index performed better. How much did Verizons performance program pay out? A handy chart would guide you to somewhere in the 41 percent range. But the text of the proxy leads the careful reader to a different conclusion: the payout is closer to 82 percent of the amount the company actually expects to award annually. The percentages in the table are based on the maximum amount payable under Verizons bonus plan  about twice the target level. Its a shell game, said Brian Foley, an independent compensation consultant in White Plains. They wrote it in a way that was most favorable to them. Here they have a setup that allows them to get paid out fairly well based on beating, only slightly, the median for the telecom group even though it is D level performance over all, he added. A Verizon spokesman was not available for comment. More Articles in Business »Many of the most interesting nuggets on executive pay are buried so deep in the new corporate filings that it helps to bring along a calculator and a shovel. The Securities and Exchange Commissions new disclosure rules were supposed to make it easier for investors to understand how top managers were being paid. But piles of new data and proxy statements that are about as easy to parse as the federal tax code have even experts scratching their heads. There is an awful lot of stuff you have to wade through to get to the stuff that matters, said Jannice L. Koors, a compensation consultant at Pearl Meyer &amp; Partners. We are now in the business of data mining. Among the choice details recently unearthed in recent filings: ¶Ray R. Irani, Occidental Petroleums chairman and chief executive, is so far the highest paid corporate chief whose compensation package was tallied under the new rules. His total pay was about $52.1 million last year, according to an analysis by Equilar, the executive compensation research firm. But that was just the amount that Occidentals board awarded him last year. In fact, he took home a lot more. First, there was the $270.1 million in profit from stock options he cashed out in 2006. Then there was the $93.3 million that Mr. Irani withdrew from a huge deferred stock plan that was revealed for the first time this year under the new rules. (It is found in a table on Page 28 of the Occidental proxy statement, in the kind of fine print often used by credit card and insurance companies.) According to its proxy statement, the company ended the program late last year in light of the substantial liability and expense of the program. Of course, Mr. Irani can expect even more money down the road. Besides his annual pay, he still can tap at least four other deferred compensation plans, totaling at least $124 million. ¶International Business Machines will freeze this year an executive retention plan that helped bolster retirement benefits for Samuel J. Palmisano, its chairman and chief executive, to more than $33 million. On top of his $18.8 million pension, Mr. Palmisano is eligible to collect about $14.2 million through a special retention plan. In its proxy statement, I.B.M. said that it set up the program in 1995 to keep senior managers when the companys very existence was at risk, but that the original purpose had been met. I.B.M. closed the program in 2004 for new participants, and said that by the end of the year, it would freeze the payments earned by any existing managers. An I.B.M spokesman could not be reached for comment about the timing. ¶Buried in the proxy of the pharmaceutical giant Pfizer were details about more than the money it pays its board members and top executives. The company also took the unusual step of disclosing its independent compensation consultants compensation. The total amount of fees paid to Frederic W. Cook &amp; Co. for services to the committee in 2006 was $184,555, Pfizers proxy revealed. That works out to at least $15,000 a month just so the company can be certain that the wages and benefits of its top executives are well designed and competitive. Shareholders had asked about the information, said Bryant Haskins, a Pfizer spokesman. It was just an effort to be more transparent and go beyond what was asked for. ¶Other proxy statements appear to have been written by puzzle makers. Verizons long-term incentive plan is one notable example. Over the last three years, Verizon investor returns were slightly above the median for its industry, but two out of every three big companies in the Standard &amp; Poors 500-stock index performed better. How much did Verizons performance program pay out? A handy chart would guide you to somewhere in the 41 percent range. But the text of the proxy leads the careful reader to a different conclusion: the payout is closer to 82 percent of the amount the company actually expects to award annually. The percentages in the table are based on the maximum amount payable under Verizons bonus plan  about twice the target level. Its a shell game, said Brian Foley, an independent compensation consultant in White Plains. They wrote it in a way that was most favorable to them. Here they have a setup that allows them to get paid out fairly well based on beating, only slightly, the median for the telecom group even though it is D level performance over all, he added. A Verizon spokesman was not available for comment.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0D6113FF936A3575BC0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Business Briefs | Occidental's Profit Falls<date>Published: August 5, 2006</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said second-quarter income fell 44 percent on losses from the seizure of a field in Ecuador and the reduced value of assets being sold. Net income fell to $857 million, or $1.97 a share, from $1.54 billion, or $3.77, a year earlier, Occidental said. Sales rose 36 percent, to $4.6 billion from $3.39 billion. The results included a loss of $347 million for the reduced value of a field that was seized by Ecuador's government in May and for assets of Vintage Petroleum, acquired in January, that the company is selling.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB1330F935A35754C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">World Business Briefing | Americas: Ecuador: Charge For Oil Field Seizure<date>Published: July 6, 2006</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said it would take an after-tax charge of $306 million as a result of the seizure by Ecuador of its oil fields there. The company, which is based in Los Angeles, said the charge would reduce first-quarter earnings from continuing operations to $2.67 a share from the previously disclosed $2.83 a share. Occidental Petroleum said that it expected earnings per share from continuing operations of $2.70 to $2.80 for the second quarter. Ecuador began seizing Occidental's oil fields in May after accusing the company of having illegally transferred oil assets.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/17/business/worldbusiness/17oil.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Ecuador Cancels an Oil Deal With Occidental Petroleum<date>Published: May 17, 2006</date><text>QUITO, Ecuador, May 16 (Reuters)  Ecuador began to take over operations of the United States oil giant Occidental Petroleum on Tuesday, the latest move in Latin America against foreign energy producers after nationalization in Bolivia and state intervention in Venezuela. Ecuador revoked Occidental's contract Monday after accusing it of transferring part of an oil field without authorization. Occidental says it has complied with its obligations and still hopes to settle. Occidental shares fell by 2.2 percent Tuesday, to $96.97. President Alfredo Palacio has been under pressure from Indian groups in the oil-rich Amazon to expel Occidental. The Indians accuse the company of exploiting natural resources with no benefit for Ecuadoreans. The surprise contract cancellation came a little more than two weeks after President Evo Morales, a leftist who is Bolivia's first indigenous president, nationalized the industry and ordered the military to occupy natural gas fields. Bolivia's move set off Wall Street fears that President Hugo Chávez of Venezuela, a self-styled revolutionary known for his anti-United States rhetoric, was pushing his neighbors in a campaign to tighten state control over natural resources. Ecuador ruled out any nationalization of the oil industry. Officials say the country will receive an extra $100 million a year in revenues because of the Occidental contract cancellation. Occidental is Ecuador's largest investor and extracts 100,000 barrels of oil a day, about 20 percent of Ecuador's total production. The Associated Press reported that the Bush administration had broken off talks on a free trade agreement with Ecuador because of the move on Occidental. In Bolivia, the head of a pension fund run by Zurich Financial Services said Tuesday that it had agreed to hand over shares in three energy companies to the government. The president of Futuro de Bolivia, Gonzalo Bedoya, said the fund had no choice but to comply. On Monday, the government gave two private pension funds three days to transfer the shares they hold in two energy firms  Andina, which is controlled by Repsol , and Chaco, run by BP  and in the gas transport company Transredes, controlled by Royal Dutch Shell. Higher Royalties in Venezuela CARACAS, Venezuela, May 16 (Bloomberg News)  Venezuela's congress approved higher royalties for oil companies like Exxon Mobil and Chevron that are shareholders in four heavy-oil ventures as President Hugo Chávez seeks a bigger share of industry profits. The law increases royalties to 33.3 percent from 16.67 percent on all oil companies operating in the country, including the four heavy-oil ventures, the state oil company Petroleos de Venezuela said on its Web site. More Articles in Business »QUITO, Ecuador, May 16 (Reuters)  Ecuador began to take over operations of the United States oil giant Occidental Petroleum on Tuesday, the latest move in Latin America against foreign energy producers after nationalization in Bolivia and state intervention in Venezuela. Ecuador revoked Occidental's contract Monday after accusing it of transferring part of an oil field without authorization. Occidental says it has complied with its obligations and still hopes to settle. Occidental shares fell by 2.2 percent Tuesday, to $96.97. President Alfredo Palacio has been under pressure from Indian groups in the oil-rich Amazon to expel Occidental. The Indians accuse the company of exploiting natural resources with no benefit for Ecuadoreans. The surprise contract cancellation came a little more than two weeks after President Evo Morales, a leftist who is Bolivia's first indigenous president, nationalized the industry and ordered the military to occupy natural gas fields. Bolivia's move set off Wall Street fears that President Hugo Chávez of Venezuela, a self-styled revolutionary known for his anti-United States rhetoric, was pushing his neighbors in a campaign to tighten state control over natural resources. Ecuador ruled out any nationalization of the oil industry. Officials say the country will receive an extra $100 million a year in revenues because of the Occidental contract cancellation. Occidental is Ecuador's largest investor and extracts 100,000 barrels of oil a day, about 20 percent of Ecuador's total production. The Associated Press reported that the Bush administration had broken off talks on a free trade agreement with Ecuador because of the move on Occidental. In Bolivia, the head of a pension fund run by Zurich Financial Services said Tuesday that it had agreed to hand over shares in three energy companies to the government. The president of Futuro de Bolivia, Gonzalo Bedoya, said the fund had no choice but to comply. On Monday, the government gave two private pension funds three days to transfer the shares they hold in two energy firms  Andina, which is controlled by Repsol , and Chaco, run by BP  and in the gas transport company Transredes, controlled by Royal Dutch Shell. Higher Royalties in Venezuela CARACAS, Venezuela, May 16 (Bloomberg News)  Venezuela's congress approved higher royalties for oil companies like Exxon Mobil and Chevron that are shareholders in four heavy-oil ventures as President Hugo Chávez seeks a bigger share of industry profits. The law increases royalties to 33.3 percent from 16.67 percent on all oil companies operating in the country, including the four heavy-oil ventures, the state oil company Petroleos de Venezuela said on its Web site.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/09/business/businessspecial/09oil.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Pay for Oil Chiefs Spiked Like Prices<date>Published: April 9, 2006</date><text>SUMMONED before a Senate subcommittee last fall to explain their industry's record profits, five chief executives of big energy companies were unanimous in explaining that they had no control over the prices set by global oil markets. Skip to next paragraph Mike Mergen/Bloomberg News John G. Drosdick, Sunoco's chief, was paid almost $23 million last year. Executive Pay: Proxy Season The New York Times spotlights the one season a year when shareholders can express their opinions on management. Go to the Section » Lee R. Raymond, then the chairman and chief executive of Exxon Mobil, even evoked a time in the 1990's when energy companies struggled with record-low oil prices. "People have to realize that we're in a commodity business, which has its ups and downs," he said. That was then. Now, as energy companies reveal the year-end bonuses they paid in December  just one month after the hearing  it is becoming evident that many top executives had no qualms about accepting record payouts, even if they were based on profits generated by the same high oil prices that they said they had nothing to do with. Mr. Raymond received 550,000 shares of restricted stock, which was worth $32 million when he received the grant on Nov. 29. He retired from Exxon on Dec. 31. Some compensation experts raise their eyebrows at the timing of the award, because restricted stock is widely considered a tool to retain crucial executives and to keep them focused on the long term. "It has such a forward look to it, it's hard to reconcile that with a five-week career," said Brian Foley, an executive compensation consultant in White Plains. Mr. Raymond already had a huge stake in Exxon's continued good fortune. Even before the 550,000-share grant, he owned 1.55 million restricted shares that would vest from 2007 to 2014. And then there are the 1.16 million restricted shares that vested when he retired, and the 4.15 million options to buy Exxon's stock. The shares would have been worth more than $70 million and the options about $90 million if Mr. Raymond still held them all last week, Mr. Foley said. But if certain one-time retirement items like his $80 million pension are excluded, then Mr. Raymond did not even have the biggest payday in the energy industry last year. Bonuses were up across the board, from those at big integrated energy companies to those at tiny oil services businesses. And some chief executives saw their pay rise substantially from 2004, another banner year for energy industry profits. Ray R. Irani, the chief executive of Occidental Petroleum, received about $63 million in total compensation last year, an increase of more than 50 percent from the year earlier. Over the last three years, Mr. Irani has reaped more than $135 million, mostly in options and restricted stock. "We've seen various energy C.E.O.'s dragged before Congress to explain the excessive price spikes in gasoline," said Patrick McGurn, special counsel for Institutional Shareholder Services, a corporate governance research group based in Rockville, Md. "And now it appears that a lot of the excess profits were going into Ray Irani's pockets." But Mr. Irani wasn't among the energy executives who testified before Congress recently. Occidental is much smaller than the companies represented there, with less than 5 percent of Exxon Mobil's revenue last year. "When you get a disconnect even on size, then that shows that nothing is driving compensation," Mr. McGurn said. Executive pay in the energy industry might not be tethered to any one measuring stick, like the company's size, but there does appear to be one constant: energy executives are usually paid much more than their peers at similar companies in other industries. John P. Surma Jr., the chief executive of U.S. Steel, for example, received total compensation of $6.7 million last year; Alain J. P. Belda, the chief executive of Alcoa, the aluminum manufacturer, received $7.5 million. But John G. Drosdick, the chief executive of Sunoco  an oil company that has revenue that is roughly in line with that of U.S. Steel and Alcoa  was paid nearly $23 million. David Swinford, a senior managing director at Pearl Meyer &amp; Partners, the compensation practice of Clark Consulting, said he would like to see pay packages in the oil patch reflect something more than the boom in industry profits. "They need to measure the achievement of long-term goals like improving operating margins and reducing the cost per gallon of a particular product," said Mr. Swinford, who advises several energy companies on executive pay. "I don't think very many boards are good about going back after the fact to determine if they actually got premium performance for premium pay." Paul Hodgson, a senior research associate at the Corporate Library, an investment research firm in Portland, Me., that specializes in corporate governance, said he did not think that energy executives' pay should be based on annual operational results at all. "The reason the C.E.O. got the job in the first place was to increase long-term revenue," he said. "The daily operational results are affected by executives much further down the chain." Mr. Hodgson added that energy companies often justify big pay and generous perks by saying that they could not possibly retain talented executives without them. But that's "illogical," he said, because companies like Kinder Morgan do "perfectly well" without them. Richard D. Kinder, the chairman and chief executive at Kinder Morgan, an oil products and natural gas pipeline company based in Houston, receives a $1 annual salary, no bonus, no options and no restricted stock. His payout comes from dividends on the Kinder stock he has accumulated as a co-founder and investor. (He owns nearly 20 percent of the company.) Mr. Kinder said ironclad bonuses and flashy perks would not suit the culture at Kinder Morgan, where salaries are capped at $200,000 a year. "Our senior executives could all walk across the street and get paid a lot more," he said. "But I think what's important is that they recognize the system here is fair." Kinder Morgan executives work without contracts. There is no separate retirement plan for senior executives. Every employee in the company, from the lowest paid on up, is eligible for a bonus. For the most part, commodity prices do not directly affect Kinder Morgan's profits. But even in the one unit that is affected by the market price of oil, Mr. Kinder said, he tries to keep bonuses commodity-price-neutral, because the executives have no control over the price. Yet there is no doubt that Kinder Morgan has enriched investors. Its shares have more than quadrupled in value since a merger in 1999 created the present company. Mr. McGurn of Institutional Shareholder Services referred to Mr. Kinder as an "enlightened founder," comparing him with Bill Gates, who has never accepted stock options from Microsoft. Mr. McGurn, however, was hard-pressed to come up with another example in the energy industry. More Articles in Business »SUMMONED before a Senate subcommittee last fall to explain their industry's record profits, five chief executives of big energy companies were unanimous in explaining that they had no control over the prices set by global oil markets. Skip to next paragraph Mike Mergen/Bloomberg News John G. Drosdick, Sunoco's chief, was paid almost $23 million last year. Executive Pay: Proxy Season The New York Times spotlights the one season a year when shareholders can express their opinions on management. Go to the Section » Lee R. Raymond, then the chairman and chief executive of Exxon Mobil, even evoked a time in the 1990's when energy companies struggled with record-low oil prices. "People have to realize that we're in a commodity business, which has its ups and downs," he said. That was then. Now, as energy companies reveal the year-end bonuses they paid in December  just one month after the hearing  it is becoming evident that many top executives had no qualms about accepting record payouts, even if they were based on profits generated by the same high oil prices that they said they had nothing to do with. Mr. Raymond received 550,000 shares of restricted stock, which was worth $32 million when he received the grant on Nov. 29. He retired from Exxon on Dec. 31. Some compensation experts raise their eyebrows at the timing of the award, because restricted stock is widely considered a tool to retain crucial executives and to keep them focused on the long term. "It has such a forward look to it, it's hard to reconcile that with a five-week career," said Brian Foley, an executive compensation consultant in White Plains. Mr. Raymond already had a huge stake in Exxon's continued good fortune. Even before the 550,000-share grant, he owned 1.55 million restricted shares that would vest from 2007 to 2014. And then there are the 1.16 million restricted shares that vested when he retired, and the 4.15 million options to buy Exxon's stock. The shares would have been worth more than $70 million and the options about $90 million if Mr. Raymond still held them all last week, Mr. Foley said. But if certain one-time retirement items like his $80 million pension are excluded, then Mr. Raymond did not even have the biggest payday in the energy industry last year. Bonuses were up across the board, from those at big integrated energy companies to those at tiny oil services businesses. And some chief executives saw their pay rise substantially from 2004, another banner year for energy industry profits. Ray R. Irani, the chief executive of Occidental Petroleum, received about $63 million in total compensation last year, an increase of more than 50 percent from the year earlier. Over the last three years, Mr. Irani has reaped more than $135 million, mostly in options and restricted stock. "We've seen various energy C.E.O.'s dragged before Congress to explain the excessive price spikes in gasoline," said Patrick McGurn, special counsel for Institutional Shareholder Services, a corporate governance research group based in Rockville, Md. "And now it appears that a lot of the excess profits were going into Ray Irani's pockets." But Mr. Irani wasn't among the energy executives who testified before Congress recently. Occidental is much smaller than the companies represented there, with less than 5 percent of Exxon Mobil's revenue last year. "When you get a disconnect even on size, then that shows that nothing is driving compensation," Mr. McGurn said. Executive pay in the energy industry might not be tethered to any one measuring stick, like the company's size, but there does appear to be one constant: energy executives are usually paid much more than their peers at similar companies in other industries. John P. Surma Jr., the chief executive of U.S. Steel, for example, received total compensation of $6.7 million last year; Alain J. P. Belda, the chief executive of Alcoa, the aluminum manufacturer, received $7.5 million. But John G. Drosdick, the chief executive of Sunoco  an oil company that has revenue that is roughly in line with that of U.S. Steel and Alcoa  was paid nearly $23 million. David Swinford, a senior managing director at Pearl Meyer &amp; Partners, the compensation practice of Clark Consulting, said he would like to see pay packages in the oil patch reflect something more than the boom in industry profits. "They need to measure the achievement of long-term goals like improving operating margins and reducing the cost per gallon of a particular product," said Mr. Swinford, who advises several energy companies on executive pay. "I don't think very many boards are good about going back after the fact to determine if they actually got premium performance for premium pay." Paul Hodgson, a senior research associate at the Corporate Library, an investment research firm in Portland, Me., that specializes in corporate governance, said he did not think that energy executives' pay should be based on annual operational results at all. "The reason the C.E.O. got the job in the first place was to increase long-term revenue," he said. "The daily operational results are affected by executives much further down the chain." Mr. Hodgson added that energy companies often justify big pay and generous perks by saying that they could not possibly retain talented executives without them. But that's "illogical," he said, because companies like Kinder Morgan do "perfectly well" without them. Richard D. Kinder, the chairman and chief executive at Kinder Morgan, an oil products and natural gas pipeline company based in Houston, receives a $1 annual salary, no bonus, no options and no restricted stock. His payout comes from dividends on the Kinder stock he has accumulated as a co-founder and investor. (He owns nearly 20 percent of the company.) Mr. Kinder said ironclad bonuses and flashy perks would not suit the culture at Kinder Morgan, where salaries are capped at $200,000 a year. "Our senior executives could all walk across the street and get paid a lot more," he said. "But I think what's important is that they recognize the system here is fair." Kinder Morgan executives work without contracts. There is no separate retirement plan for senior executives. Every employee in the company, from the lowest paid on up, is eligible for a bonus. For the most part, commodity prices do not directly affect Kinder Morgan's profits. But even in the one unit that is affected by the market price of oil, Mr. Kinder said, he tries to keep bonuses commodity-price-neutral, because the executives have no control over the price. Yet there is no doubt that Kinder Morgan has enriched investors. Its shares have more than quadrupled in value since a merger in 1999 created the present company. Mr. McGurn of Institutional Shareholder Services referred to Mr. Kinder as an "enlightened founder," comparing him with Bill Gates, who has never accepted stock options from Microsoft. Mr. McGurn, however, was hard-pressed to come up with another example in the energy industry.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/18/business/worldbusiness/18oil.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Offer Made to Settle Ecuador Oil Dispute<date>Published: March 18, 2006</date><text>QUITO, Ecuador, March 17 (Reuters)  The Occidental Petroleum Corporation is offering Ecuador up to $1 billion in disputed taxes, investments and extra revenue from its crude output to resolve a legal dispute. The Energy Ministry is studying whether to carry out a recommendation to revoke Occidental's contract over charges it transferred part of an oil block to EnCana, a Canadian company, in 2000 without government authorization. Occidental denies the charges and has proposed renegotiating the disputed oil field, investing to develop areas where it has operations and financing new projects for the state oil company, Petroecuador. Petroecuador said it had received the proposal and had until next week to respond to Occidental. Occidental's proposal foresees renegotiating the block to hand the state at least an extra $600 million in oil revenues over the next 13 years if Ecuador abandons its legal challenge and extends the contract life seven years, to 2019. The government would benefit from a mechanism that allows it part of any revenues Occidental earns above an agreed benchmark because of soaring crude prices. "Those would be revenues designated to the state," Occidental Ecuador's president, Gerald W. Ellis said, confirming the proposal's details. Occidental, an American company, would pay a $50 million bonus for contract changes, according to the proposal. The company would also invest $100 million in a fund for health and social development projects. It would offer $110 million for new projects with Petroecuador and $13 million for an Energy Ministry project to modernize its tax system. More Articles in Business &gt;QUITO, Ecuador, March 17 (Reuters)  The Occidental Petroleum Corporation is offering Ecuador up to $1 billion in disputed taxes, investments and extra revenue from its crude output to resolve a legal dispute. The Energy Ministry is studying whether to carry out a recommendation to revoke Occidental's contract over charges it transferred part of an oil block to EnCana, a Canadian company, in 2000 without government authorization. Occidental denies the charges and has proposed renegotiating the disputed oil field, investing to develop areas where it has operations and financing new projects for the state oil company, Petroecuador. Petroecuador said it had received the proposal and had until next week to respond to Occidental. Occidental's proposal foresees renegotiating the block to hand the state at least an extra $600 million in oil revenues over the next 13 years if Ecuador abandons its legal challenge and extends the contract life seven years, to 2019. The government would benefit from a mechanism that allows it part of any revenues Occidental earns above an agreed benchmark because of soaring crude prices. "Those would be revenues designated to the state," Occidental Ecuador's president, Gerald W. Ellis said, confirming the proposal's details. Occidental, an American company, would pay a $50 million bonus for contract changes, according to the proposal. The company would also invest $100 million in a fund for health and social development projects. It would offer $110 million for new projects with Petroecuador and $13 million for an Energy Ministry project to modernize its tax system.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/14/business/14vintage.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental to Buy Vintage<date>Published: October 14, 2005</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, the oil producer, agreed yesterday to acquire its smaller rival, Vintage Petroleum, for about $3.52 billion, as it seeks to expand in Latin America and California. Soaring crude oil and natural gas prices have increased cash levels at energy companies, spurring several acquisitions. Under the deal, Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, will pay $20 in cash plus 0.42 of an Occidental share for each Vintage share. Occidental will also assume $550 million in debt and $225 million in cash on Vintage's balance sheet at the end of the year. The terms value Vintage at $51.49 a share based on yesterday's closing prices, a 33 percent premium to its closing price of $38.59. Occidental also plans a program to buy back nine million Occidental shares as part of the deal. The deal is expected to close in the first quarter and is subject to approval by shareholders and regulators. Vintage has operations in Argentina, Yemen and California. More Articles in Business &gt;The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, the oil producer, agreed yesterday to acquire its smaller rival, Vintage Petroleum, for about $3.52 billion, as it seeks to expand in Latin America and California. Soaring crude oil and natural gas prices have increased cash levels at energy companies, spurring several acquisitions. Under the deal, Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, will pay $20 in cash plus 0.42 of an Occidental share for each Vintage share. Occidental will also assume $550 million in debt and $225 million in cash on Vintage's balance sheet at the end of the year. The terms value Vintage at $51.49 a share based on yesterday's closing prices, a 33 percent premium to its closing price of $38.59. Occidental also plans a program to buy back nine million Occidental shares as part of the deal. The deal is expected to close in the first quarter and is subject to approval by shareholders and regulators. Vintage has operations in Argentina, Yemen and California.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/02/business/worldbusiness/02oil.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Gains Rights to Oman Oil Field<date>Published: May 2, 2005</date><text>he Occidental Petroleum Corporation said that it would replace the Royal Dutch/Shell Group in developing an oil field in Oman at a cost of more than $2 billion. Occidental and its partner, Liwa Energy of Abu Dhabi, have committed to raising production from the Mukhaizna deposit to 150,000 barrels a day from the current 10,000 barrels within a few years, the parties to the agreement said yesterday. Advertisement Shell lost the right to develop the 2.4-billion-barrel field, Oman's sixth-largest, because of a disagreement with the Oman government over how best to tap the oil, officials familiar with the talks said last week. The Gulf state needs billions of dollars of investment to reverse a four-year decline in output. Petroleum Development Oman, in which Shell holds a 34 percent stake, controls 94 percent of Oman's oil production. The company, which had planned to spend $1.8 billion increasing output from the field to 100,000 barrels a day, will still be offered the chance to retain a reduced stake in the Mukhaizna field, with Occidental acting as the field's main operator, said Sheikh Ali al-Battashi, director general of planning at Oman's oil ministry. Mukhaizna holds crude oil that is too thick to pump without the use of steam or carbon dioxide, a process Occidental already uses elsewhere.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDE163AF93AA35751C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL REVISES QUARTERLY PROFIT UPWARD<date>Published: February 9, 2005</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit was 12 percent higher than previously reported because of the increased value of its stake in Lyondell Chemical. Fourth-quarter net income was $742 million, rather than the $665 million, or $1.64 a share, reported on Jan. 24, the company said. Profit almost doubled from $382 million a year earlier. The revised income report will be filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission, a spokesman, Larry Meriage, said. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, said Lyondell, based in Houston, reported fourth-quarter results last week.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/16/business/yourmoney/16refresh.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Leaving the Eye of the Storm<date>Published: January 16, 2005</date><text>ccustomed to stormy days in his long executive career, A. Robert Abboud nevertheless chafed at being snowbound at his suburban Chicago home early this month. "The driveway is about three-quarters of a mile long," he said, "and the snow is a foot deep today and drifting." Yielding to the weather - or almost anything else - wasn't Mr. Abboud's style when he was younger. He endured tough stints as chairman of the First National Bank of Chicago, from 1975 until he was fired in 1980; president of Occidental Petroleum, from 1980 until he resigned in 1984 after clashing with his chairman, Armand Hammer; and chairman and chief executive of the First City Bancorporation of Texas, from 1988 until he was fired in 1991. Advertisement Even now, at 75, he often drives to the downtown office of his investment firm, the A. Robert Abboud Company, which develops commercial and residential property, including the new Skyline on Brickell, a high-rise condominium in Miami. But Mr. Abboud, a former marine who served in Korea, says he is slowing down a bit. "I'm just an old codger now," he said with a laugh. The real estate investors he leads "let me do it because I'm older than any of them," he added. This self-deprecating version of Mr. Abboud is far mellower than the one who became known for harshly chastising senior officials in front of their subordinates when he was chairman of First National Bank of Chicago. In 1980, Fortune named him one of the 10 roughest bosses in the country, and he reveled in that persona, having once said, "People think the A in A. Robert Abboud stands for abrasive." (Actually, it stands for Alfred.) These days, when his real estate investments leave spare time, he is working for peace, not by calming directors in some corporate boardroom but by planning for a new era of Palestinian-Israeli relations. Mr. Abboud, the grandson of a Lebanese farmer, has helped to organize Manifesto for Peace, a group of Chicago-area business and civic leaders. "We're an organization of Christians, Jews and Muslims dedicated to coming together and agreeing on a plan for peace in the Middle East," he said. "If the formula we come up with is one that we all endorse, maybe it can help leaders over there to stop the violence." If that happens, Mr. Abboud will leave a legacy of diplomacy that few might have imagined during his tumultuous executive reigns. Robert Johnson</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/15/national/15reynolds.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">No Limits for Inaugural Fund-Raisers<date>Published: January 15, 2005</date><text>ASHINGTON, Jan. 14 - President Bush's top fund-raisers, who gathered a record sum in a marathon campaign, have shown that they can sprint, as well, collecting up to $40 million in six weeks for the inaugural celebrations. "We're about finished," said Mercer Reynolds, co-chairman of the Presidential Inaugural Committee, which has commitments for the money it needs and is now focused on collecting the checks. The list of contributors for the three-day celebration is freighted with wealthy Republicans loyal to the president and corporations that have regulatory and legislative interests in Washington like military contractors, energy companies and technology businesses. With so much money to raise in such a short time, Mr. Bush turned to his most prodigious fund-raisers. Chief among them is Mr. Reynolds, a longtime friend and supporter of the president who presided over the most effective money machine in presidential history. "Mercer is really his nickname," said Al Hoffman of Florida, an inaugural fund-raiser who also contributed $100,000. "His real name is Merciless. "He was the right guy to do the right job at the right time," Mr. Hoffman said. "He gets people excited to give, then goes in for the kill. Whatever arm twisting he does, he does it in a gentle way." Unlike the Bush election campaign, which could take only $2,000 from each contributor and gathered roughly $274 million from a vast number, the inauguration effort has focused on large donations of up to $250,000 from a shorter list of donors. Mr. Reynolds called the inauguration effort "a separate kind of sale." In early December, a small group of inaugural fund-raisers met here to carve up the duties. "We sat around the table with a huge list and said, 'Who wants to take this one, this one and this one?' " said Nancy Kinder of Texas, the finance chairwoman of the inauguration who gave $250,000. "You take who you know and who you feel comfortable calling." The committee took advantage of campaign finance laws that allowed companies, which are prevented from contributing to candidates during the election, to donate freely to the inauguration and offered packages that include premium tickets to the festivities and special events with the president. "Corporations do this as a matter of course," Mr. Reynolds said. "Many corporations had this in their budget for this year. Without knowing whether a Republican or Democrat was going to be elected, they had money already budgeted." Money poured in from major companies, which represented two-thirds of the contributors on the donors' list that the committee released voluntarily on Friday. The list, which lags the committee's actual fund-raising, showed almost $25 million from about 200 contributors. Many are heavily regulated by the government and spend millions each year to try to influence Congress and the administration. The inaugural contributions are simply part of a broader political program. "If you are playing in a sport, you've got to play in the sport," David F. Girard-diCarlo, chairman of a law firm in Philadelphia, Blank Rome, said. Mr. Girard-diCarlo gave $50,000, and his firm gave $200,000. Military contractors including Boeing, Lockheed Martin and Northrop Grumman, which have lobbyists working on a wide range of topics like government appropriations and weapons systems, each gave $100,000, records show. Energy firms like ChevronTexaco, ExxonMobile, Occidental Petroleum and the Southern Company, whose interests encompass environmental legislation and the energy bill that has been stalled in Congress, each gave $250,000. Technology firms including Microsoft and Oracle, with interests in patents, software licensing and cybersecurity, gave $100,000 each. Transportation companies, including Union Pacific, which gave $100,000, and the Burlington Northern and Santa Fe Railway, which gave $250,000, monitor issues like railway safety. Major Republican benefactors also responded like Alex Spanos, owner of the San Diego Chargers football team, and T. Boone Pickens, the Texas oil magnate. They supported Republicans heavily in the election and each gave $250,000 to the inauguration. "It is harder in many ways to raise money for the inauguration than it was for the campaign," Mr. Hoffman said. "People say they want to give money to make a difference. But they already got the president elected. Why give money for a party? You have to go to people who understand the importance of the ceremony." Of course, the sale is easier if you are friends with the president, as many inauguration fund-raisers are. Mr. Reynolds can trace his friendship back to a sweaty hug roughly 25 years ago, when Mr. Bush, fresh from jogging, greeted him exuberantly when they first met in a club in Texas to talk business. The two became friends and colleagues, working together in the oil industry and on the Texas Rangers baseball team. The president calls him Merce. Mr. Reynolds raised money for Mr. Bush's campaign in 2000 and the inaugural and was named ambassador to Switzerland, where he was sworn in on Sept. 11, 2001. He returned to work on Mr. Bush's campaign and, now, the inauguration. "He has a one agenda item on his list - George W. Bush," Karl Rove, the president's top political adviser, said. "That is exactly what the president appreciates about Mercer." Mr. Reynolds was widely seen as a potential nominee for commerce secretary, a position often held by presidential friends and fund-raisers. But Mr. Reynolds said he was planning to head home to Cincinnati after the inauguration. "I've been doing this for four years and I've loved working for this president," he said. "Obviously, if he asked me to do something that I thought and he thought was a good fit, I'm willing to serve. But my plan is to go home."</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD91039F935A35752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM CLOSES VINYL RESINS FACTORY<date>Published: January 6, 2005</date><text>Occidental Petroleum said that it had closed its vinyl resins factory in Pottstown, Pa., effective immediately. The closing reduced pretax profit in the fourth quarter by about $53 million. A write-off of production facilities that used mercury cell technology cut pretax profit by an additional $12 million, the company said. The unprofitable vinyl resins business employed 200 people and represented about 2.5 percent of Occidental's sales of chemicals, said Larry Meriage, a company spokesman. The chemicals unit, which accounts for about one-third of Occidental's total sales, more than doubled its profit in the third quarter, to $137 million. Occidental said it also would report pretax costs of about $76 million in the fourth quarter to increase its environmental remediation reserves, provide for litigation and raise self-insurance reserves.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/24/politics/24donate.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Energy Companies Help Lift Inaugural Fund to $8 Million<date>Published: December 24, 2004</date><text>ASHINGTON, Dec. 23 - Drawing support from the energy industry and other longtime backers of President Bush, the Presidential Inaugural Committee has raised almost $8 million since it began gathering money this month, according to a list it released Thursday. ExxonMobil, the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, ChevronTexaco and the Southern Company were among more than 20 donors to give the maximum $250,000, which entitles executives to attend the ceremonies, black-tie balls and events with the president. Many others gave smaller amounts in return for fewer perks, like the $100,000 contributed by the military contractors Boeing and Northrop Grumman. Advertisement The Presidential Inaugural Committee is seeking to raise as much as $40 million to kick off Mr. Bush's second term, with multiple events leading up to the Jan. 20 swearing-in, and has spent much of December soliciting donors across the country, despite the holidays and the exhaustion brought by an election that raised record amounts. "There is some donor fatigue," said Brad Freeman, a longtime Bush supporter and fund-raiser who is a co-chairman of the committee. "But they have had a nice rest." So far, the roster of donors is thick with people and companies loyal to Mr. Bush and the Republican Party, and fund-raisers expect it to grow substantially. For corporations, the inauguration represents a rare opportunity to write large checks. Though companies are forbidden to contribute directly to candidates or political parties during an election, campaign finance laws do not restrict them from donating to events like political conventions or inaugurations. Roughly half the 52 contributors identified so far are companies, including well-known names like International Paper, Union Pacific and Qualcomm. Several donors are individuals who also played a major role in this year's election. For example, T. Boone Pickens, a Texas oilman who contributed $250,000 for the inauguration, had given a total of about $5.5 million to the Progress for America Voter Fund and Swift Vets and P.O.W.'s for Truth, two groups that supported Mr. Bush. Ameriquest Capital Corporation also gave $250,000 to the inauguration. Dawn Arnall, who is co-chairwoman of the company along with her husband, Roland Arnall, gave $5 million to the Progress for America Voter Fund this year. The two were also $200,000 "ranger" fund-raisers for Mr. Bush's campaign. Another $250,000 donor for the inauguration is Richard Kinder, a former president of the Enron Corporation, who is now chief executive of the Kinder Morgan energy transportation companies. His wife, Nancy Kinder, was a ranger fund-raiser for Mr. Bush and both are members of the inauguration's finance committee. Though there is no legal limit to the amount donors can give to an inauguration, the committee has voluntarily capped donations at $250,000 per contributor. That apparently does not stop related organizations from each giving the maximum. For example, Ameriquest, which is a holding company for several financial services firms, gave $250,000, as did Argent Mortgage Company, Long Beach Acceptance Corporation and Town and County Credit, which are each part of Ameriquest. Collectively, the affiliated companies gave $1 million. Some advocates of tighter campaign finance restrictions say the lack of limits on inaugural fund-raising is a shortcoming in the McCain-Feingold campaign finance law, which was passed in 2002 to ban unlimited soft-money contributions to candidates and political parties. "It's a problem because the opportunity for wealthy donors to funnel huge sums of money to the president and receive recognition from the president could translate into access and influence," said Donald J. Simon, a lawyer who has worked to tighten campaign finance laws.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EED81E3BF930A25753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM TO BUY 4 CHEMICAL PLANTS<date>Published: October 13, 2004</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to buy four chemical plants from the Vulcan Materials Company for at least $214 million to increase production of chlorine and to cut costs. The plants are in Wichita, Kan.; Geismar, La.; and Port Edwards, Wis., Occidental said. Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, will gain a second plant in Geismar after Vulcan buys out a 49 percent stake in a venture with Mitsui &amp; Company of Japan for inclusion in the deal. Vulcan, based in Birmingham, Ala., is getting out of chemicals to focus on construction materials. The plants have an annual production capacity of a combined 815,000 tons of chlorine. Occidental will save at least $40 million a year in operating costs by combining Vulcan's operations with its own, the chief financial officer, Stephen I. Chazen, said.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/20/business/company-news-quarterly-income-up-55-at-occidental-petroleum.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; QUARTERLY INCOME UP 55% AT OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM<date>Published: July 20, 2004</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, a big oil and natural gas producer, said yesterday that second-quarter net income rose 55 percent as it sold more oil and chemicals at higher prices. Net income increased to $581 million, or $1.46 a diluted share, from $374 million, or 97 cents, a year ago, said Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles. Occidental also announced that its president, Dale Laurance, 59, would retire on Dec. 31 after 21 years. The chief executive, Ray Irani, 69, will take over the duties of president, the company said. Sales gained 21 percent, to $2.75 billion from $2.27 billion. Production of oil and gas rose 6 percent, to the equivalent of 574,000 barrels of oil a day.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/24/business/oil-giants-look-anew-at-libya.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Oil Giants Look Anew At Libya<date>Published: December 24, 2003</date><text>Libya's pledge to give up its weapons of mass destruction and the possibility that the United States may soon end its economic sanctions against Libya could be a boon for several American oil companies that once had extensive operations there, several energy executives said on Monday.ConocoPhillips and Marathon Oil, both based here; Amerada Hess of New York; and Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles operated in Libya for years before the United States imposed sanctions on the country in 1986. They all have contemplated a return to Libya for some time.''Listening to the news in the last few days was a mind-blowing experience,'' said Lawrence P. Meriage, a spokesman for Occidental. Libya was an important part of Occidental's past, as the site of its largest operations in the late 1960's and early 1970's after the company's founder, Armand Hammer, reached an accommodation with Libya's leader, Col. Muammar el-Qaddafi, to allow Occidental to expand its base there. Mr. Hammer died in 1990.The possibility that the United States could lift its sanctions was raised after President Bush and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain said on Friday that Colonel Qaddafi had admitted that his country tried to develop nuclear and other unconventional weapons, and he promised to dismantle them and submit to international inspections.Libya's foreign minister, Mohammed Abdelrahman Chalgam, stoked oil companies' hopes of a return to Libya when he told reporters in Algiers on Monday that Libya hoped to attract oil investment by American companies. Mr. Chalgam said that American companies could help Libya eventually double its oil output.''We currently produce 1.5 million barrels per day and we aim to increase the oil output to 3 million barrels per day in 2020,'' said Mr. Chalgam, who was in Algiers for a meeting of North African nations.Libya's oil production peaked about 30 years ago, at more than three million barrels a day, when investments by Occidental helped invigorate the nation's energy infrastructure and lift its importance within the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries. Since then, however, friction between Colonel Qaddafi and the United States has limited the growth of its oil industry and the role of American oil companies in Libya.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/25/business/company-news-human-rights-group-sues-occidental-over-98-bombing.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; HUMAN RIGHTS GROUP SUES OCCIDENTAL OVER '98 BOMBING<date>Published: April 25, 2003</date><text>Occidental Petroleum is being sued by a human rights group that contends the company participated in a 1998 bombing of a Colombian village that killed 19 civilians. The suit, in Federal District Court in Los Angeles, was filed under the Alien Tort Claims Act, which allows corporations to be held liable in United States courts for their conduct abroad. Occidental is accused of providing money and intelligence for the Colombian Air Force's raid on the village of Santo Domingo, the suit says. An Occidental spokesman, Lawrence Meriage, said he had not seen the suit and declined to comment.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/30/business/oil-pipeline-forges-ahead-in-ecuador.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Oil Pipeline Forges Ahead in Ecuador<date>Published: October 30, 2002</date><text>Environmentalists in this cloud forest of northern Ecuador still dream of halting construction of a new oil pipeline that the builders said could bring spectacular wealth to this poor Andean country. But with the 300-mile-long, privately financed pipeline now 70 percent complete, and long green tubes replacing the palm and canelo trees, even the most die-hard opponents acknowledge that stopping the construction is next to impossible.The announcement this month that the big DÃ¼sseldorf bank Westdeutsche Landesbank Girozentrale, or WestLB, would continue financing the project, despite an international campaign pressuring it to withdraw a $900 million loan, appeared to remove the last hurdle for the builders of the $1.3 billion pipeline.''Now, it's full speed ahead,'' said Ian Davidson, local director of Bird Life International, a conservation group that had opposed the project.After two years of acrimony by a strong, well-organized opposition that frequently disrupted construction, such admissions could not be more welcome for the consortium of multinational oil companies building the heavy-crude pipeline, known by its Spanish initials, O.C.P.But now, as the project enters its final stage, with the builders promising that the pipeline will be on tap next June, questions are being raised by oil analysts and economists over just how much economic impact it will have in Ecuador.Two years ago, when President Gustavo Noboa and the oil companies began talks for the O.C.P., it was billed as a mega-project that would, in time, help double national daily oil production to 850,000 barrels, and help gross domestic product grow as much as 2.3 percent a year over the next 20 years.But now, the government and the consortium -- made up of giants like Repsol YPF of Spain and Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles, and led by EnCana of Canada -- have scaled back the projections.The builders now say the pipeline will, for the foreseeable future, transport only 220,000 barrels a day, half of capacity. And nearly three-quarters of that crude is oil that is already in production and currently flowing through the country's only other major pipeline, the 30-year-old Trans-Ecuadorian tube known as SOTE, which runs nearly parallel to the new pipe.More exploration is expected to increase production, but the process is lengthy and expensive. This means that for at least a few years, only a few thousand more barrels of oil will be produced.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/04/world/new-role-for-us-in-colombia-protecting-a-vital-oil-pipeline.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">New Role for U.S. in Colombia: Protecting a Vital Oil Pipeline<date>Published: October 04, 2002</date><text>Casting a wary eye for rebel snipers, Lt. Felipe ZÃºÃ±iga and his counterinsurgency troops slog through the wet fields and patches of jungle here. Their mission has nothing to do with drugs -- until now, the defining issue in Colombia for American policy makers -- but instead with protecting a pipeline that carries crude to an oil-hungry America.The 500-mile pipeline, which snakes through eastern Colombia, transporting 100,000 barrels of oil a day for Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles, is emerging as a new front in the terror war. One of Colombia's most valuable assets, the pipeline has long been vulnerable to bombings by Colombia's guerrilla groups, which along with the country's paramilitary outfits are included on the Bush administration's list of terrorist organizations.Sometime in the next month, in a significant shift in American policy, United States Special Forces will arrive in Colombia to begin laying the groundwork for the training of Lieutenant ZÃºÃ±iga and his 35-man squad in the finer arts of counterinsurgency. Over the next two years, 10 American helicopters will bolster the Colombian counterinsurgency efforts, and some 4,000 more troops will receive American training, which will begin in earnest in January, Bush administration and American military officials said in interviews in recent days.The policy shift dovetails with the Bush administration's new, global emphasis on expanding and diversifying the sources of America's oil imports, with an eye to reducing dependence on Middle Eastern oil. That new approach, outlined in the administration's energy report issued last year, is gaining ever more importance with the threat to Persian Gulf oil supplies from the looming war with Iraq.The $94 million counterinsurgency program is also an important element in the offensive by Colombia's new government against two rebel groups and a paramilitary force that dominate much of the country.Pipeline bombings by the guerrillas cost the government nearly $500 million last year -- a blow in a country where oil accounts for 25 percent of revenues. The two main rebel groups, which view Occidental as a symbol of American imperialism, have bombed the pipeline 948 times since the 1980's, while extorting oil royalty payments from local government officials.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/03/business/occidental-in-venture.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental in Venture<date>Published: June 03, 2002</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation has paid $310 million to become the second partner of United Arab Emirates in Dolphin Energy, a natural gas venture, beating four other corporations, Dolphin said today.The Offsets Group, the investment arm of the United Arab Emirates that is the majority owner of the $3.5 billion project, selected Occidental, of Los Angeles, early in May. The deal was signed today.The venture is building a gas pipeline from Qatar to the United Arab Emirates. The deal gives Occidental a 24.5 percent share, equal to that of France's TotalFinaElf, while the state investment arm holds 51 percent of the project.The Enron Corporation previously held the stake and sold it to the state group a year ago, before the company's collapse.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/06/world/administration-shifts-focus-on-colombia-aid.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Administration Shifts Focus on Colombia Aid<date>Published: February 06, 2002</date><text>The Bush administration is proposing to expand military aid to this war-racked nation by training the Colombian Army to protect a 500-mile-long oil pipeline from leftist rebels, senior American officials visiting Colombia said today. Such a program would be a sharp departure from a policy that until now has focused on eradicating drugs.The administration is seeking Congressional approval of a $98 million request that would pay for helicopters, communications equipment and training for Colombian troops to guard the CaÃ±o LimÃ³n pipeline, which transports crude oil pumped by Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles from the country's eastern oil fields to a Caribbean port.''We are not saying this is counterdrug -- this is different,'' said a member of an American delegation here in a meeting with reporters in a BogotÃ¡ hotel. ''The proposition we are making to the government of Colombia and to our Congress is that we ought to take an additional step.''The administration is also asking Congress to provide financing for American training of a counternarcotics brigade that would operate in northern Colombia, a region under the influence of right-wing paramilitary groups, the officials said. The money for that would come from the $731 million the administration is requesting in anti-narcotics programs for the Andean region for 2003.Pipeline protection is crucial, American officials said, because oil is Colombia's largest money-making export and provides much-needed income for a country hobbled by a brutal 38-year rebel conflict.The pipeline has been the target of rebels who see Occidental as an exploiter of Colombian resources. It was bombed 170 times last year, costing Colombia and the company more than $500 million, Colombia's state-owned oil company, Ecopetrol, said today. Since 1986, when the first attack was recorded, more than 2.6 million barrels of oil have been spilled.Until now, American policy has focused on aerial spraying of coca and opium poppy fields, as well as programs aimed at encouraging farmers to shift to other crops. The money for those programs came through a $1.3 billion aid package allocated in 2000 for the Andean region, most for training and equipping a Colombian Army brigade of 3,000 men that now takes part in counterdrug operations in the south.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/01/business/company-news-lyondell-agrees-to-buy-occidental-s-stake-in-equistar.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; LYONDELL AGREES TO BUY OCCIDENTAL'S STAKE IN EQUISTAR<date>Published: February 01, 2002</date><text>Lyondell Chemical said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Occidental Petroleum's 29.5 percent stake in Equistar Chemicals, increasing Lyondell's interest to 70.5 percent. Equistar makes chemicals used in plastic film, bags and bottles. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, will get a 21 percent stake in Lyondell, a producer of petrochemicals used in plastic bags and packaging. Millennium Chemicals of Red Bank, N.J., holds the rest of Equistar. Lyondell, based in Houston, will pay Occidental 30 million to 34 million shares, give it five-year warrants to buy Lyondell stock for $25 a share, and make a contingent payment of as much as $35 million.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/16/world/arauquita-journal-pipeline-goes-boom-local-economies-go-bust.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Arauquita Journal; Pipeline Goes 'Boom!' Local Economies Go Bust<date>Published: August 16, 2001</date><text>The first thunderous blast came at 3:40 p.m. today, quickly followed by a second. A plume of acrid black smoke then rose to the sky, and everyone for miles around knew exactly what had happened: leftist rebels had once more bombed the oil pipeline that runs through this rich oil producing area.It is an all too common occurrence here in Colombia's eastern hinterlands, a region of swamps and rice paddies where Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles has pumped crude for 16 years.With today's bombing, 119 attacks on the pipeline have been recorded this year, up from 96 in all of 2000, a terror campaign that has destroyed farms and crippled local governments that depend on oil royalties to bankroll schools, hospitals and road repairs.''It happens so much -- 'boom!' is what you hear -- that you do not even pay attention anymore,'' said Espedito GutiÃ©rrez, 63, a farmer who spoke as the pipeline burned in the background just outside this town. ''But it makes you feel like you should just leave this place. It saps your morale. You do not want to work. All your work is suddenly sacrificed.''Just a month ago, rebels blew up the section of pipeline running behind Mr. GutiÃ©rrez's small farm, just half a mile from today's explosion. Trees were charred. Oil seeped out across 15 acres.With little grassland left for grazing, Mr. GutiÃ©rrez now has no alternative but to allow his cattle to continue feeding in the oily mess.He is one of many victims of a wave of bombings that since 1986, when the first attack was recorded, has resulted in the spilling of 2.6 million barrels of oil, nearly 11 times what was lost in the Exxon Valdez disaster in Alaska.The government has tried to guard the pipeline, but it is simply too long, stretching 500 miles from the CaÃ±o LimÃ³n oil field to the Caribbean port of Covenas.''To prevent them from blowing up the pipeline is almost impossible,'' said Brig. Gen. Carlos Lemus, commander of the local brigade. ''We can maybe control it, but it is hard to say we are going to stop it completely.''Two rebel groups are responsible for the attacks, the National Liberation Army and the much larger Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, both of which have said the bombings are strikes against multinational corporations that they accuse of exploiting Colombian resources.But here in this largely rural province, Arauca, people say the attacks have done nothing but sow misery for them.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/19/business/8-concerns-get-saudi-gas-project-role.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">8 Concerns Get Saudi Gas Project Role<date>Published: May 19, 2001</date><text>The Exxon Mobil Corporation and Royal Dutch/Shell led a group of eight oil companies that will take part in a $25 billion gas development program in Saudi Arabia, the country's biggest opening of its oil and gas industry to outsiders since the 1970's.The Western companies will help Saudi Arabia convert its utilities, which now burn oil, to natural gas. This would free more crude oil for export.The other companies selected are BP P.L.C., TotalFinaElf S.A., Conoco Inc., the Phillips Petroleum Company, the Occidental Petroleum Corporation and the Enron Corporation. Saudi Arabia's government-owned energy company, Saudi Aramco, will be an equity owner in the projects.Exxon Mobil, based in Irving, Tex., the world's largest publicly traded oil company; Shell; BP; and Phillips were picked to participate in the biggest of the projects, a $15 billion development in the South Ghawar region, according to the official Saudi Press Agency. The lead company was not announced.Exxon Mobil was also selected to lead a smaller Red Sea project that involves Enron and Occidental. Exxon Mobil said the combined investment in both projects would total $20 billion.Shell, TotalFinaElf and Conoco will help develop gas at Shaybah in southeast Saudi Arabia.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/18/world/rebel-group-in-colombia-kidnaps-100-but-frees-70.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Rebel Group In Colombia Kidnaps 100, But Frees 70<date>Published: April 18, 2001</date><text>A leftist rebel group that has bombed oil pipelines and played havoc with Colombia's oil industry struck again on Monday, abducting about 100 employees of an American oil company.By early today, at least 70 of the captives -- all Colombians working under contract for Occidental Petroleum of Los Angeles, -- had been released unharmed, the company said in a statement.But late today, 27 remained in the hands of the National Liberation Army, or E.L.N., which has long accused multinational companies like Occidental of exploiting Colombia's natural resources.Although the Liberation Army, Colombia's second-largest rebel group, did not offer detailed explanations for its actions, experts on Colombia's conflict saw the mass abduction as an effort by an ever-weakening rebel movement to gain recognition.The 37-year-old rebel group, which has been hit hard in recent years by illegal paramilitary groups, had been angling for the government to cede a Rhode-Island-sized swath of land in northern Colombia as a safe haven for peace negotiations. But the plans have instead been put on hold as conflict between invading paramilitary fighters and the rebels has escalated in the region of Bolivar Province earmarked for the demilitarized zone.''When nothing moves forward, these people try a harder line, and they try a harder line to get attention,'' said Manuel Ernesto Salamanca, a political scientist at the Javeriana University in Bogota. ''We have to keep in mind that the E.L.N. is in a process of complete debilitation, and these types of actions make waves, but in a very negative way.''The Liberation Army said in a communique read on a radio station that the kidnapping was part of ''our offensive against oil policy until such time as'' the company, ''together with the government, fixes a mechanism for dialogue with Colombia's rebels.''The kidnapping took place along a road in eastern Arauca Province, not far from the Venezuelan border, when the rebels stopped a convoy of vehicles carrying the workers. Occidental officials said the captives were blue-collar employees under contract with the company.This is not the first time the Liberation Army has carried out audacious mass kidnappings to get its point across. Since 1999, in the face of battlefield losses and government slights, the group has hijacked an airliner, kidnapped worshipers at a church and abducted dozens of diners from roadside restaurants outside Cali.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/17/business/private-sector-letter-from-a-surprise-visitor.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">PRIVATE SECTOR; Letter From a Surprise Visitor<date>Published: December 17, 2000</date><text>Investment bankers know they are not immune to protests by shareholder activists who sometimes see Wall Street as an accomplice to social wrongs. But last week, when Roberto Perez, chief of the Uwa Indian nation of Colombia, paid an unannounced visit to the the San Francisco headquarters of the Sanford C. Bernstein investment firm, it seemed caught unprepared.Mr. Perez delivered a letter demanding that Bernstein, a large shareholder in Occidental Petroleum, sell its stock as a gesture to help the 5,000-member Uwa nation in its eight-year struggle with Occidental over a jungle oil field. Occidental wants to drill in land the Uwa call sacred; it may contain 1.5 billion barrels of crude.Drilling, which could begin within months, will ''destroy the ancient culture of our ancestors,'' Mr. Perez said in the letter to Sanford C. Bernstein's chief operating officer, Roger Hertog, requesting that the firm divest its 53 million Occidental shares. Mr. Hertog and executives from Allied Capital, which recently acquired Bernstein, declined to comment.Fidelity Investments sold more than $400 million of Occidental stock in September, after Mr. Perez visited its offices. Fidelity says that there was no connection. William Santiago</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/05/world/colombia-oil-field-halts.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Colombia Oil Field Halts<date>Published: August 05, 2000</date><text>Occidental Petroleum halted production and declared force majeure at the second largest oil field in Colombia today after Marxist rebels had repeatedly bombed the pipeline that pumps crude oil from the field.The suspension is thought to be the first time in more than 18 months that the company has invoked force majeure at the Cano Limon complex in Arauca Province. Occidental operates the complex, which produces 105,000 barrels a day, with the state-run oil company, Ecopetrol. The declaration lets Occidental suspend contractual obligations.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/21/business/company-news-apache-is-buying-oil-and-gas-interests-from-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; APACHE IS BUYING OIL AND GAS INTERESTS FROM OCCIDENTAL<date>Published: July 21, 2000</date><text>The Apache Corporation agreed yesterday to buy offshore oil and gas interests in the Gulf of Mexico from a subsidiary of Occidental Petroleum for $385 million, part of which will be paid in future years. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, said it expected to record a pretax gain of about $65 million on the deal. Apache, based in Houston, said it expected the deal to add immediately to its earnings per share and cash flow. Shares of Apache were off $2.0625, to $51.125, while Occidental shares were up 6.25 cents at $20.125.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/19/us/2000-campaign-vice-president-gore-family-s-ties-oil-company-magnate-reap-big.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT; Gore Family's Ties to Oil Company Magnate Reap Big Rewards, and a Few Problems<date>Published: March 19, 2000</date><text>On the third page of Vice President Al Gore's most recent financial disclosure report, after routine listings for his salary and the value of his house in Washington and his small farm here, is an unlikely entry -- $20,000 for leasing land for zinc mining.Behind the yearly lease payment, which has earned Mr. Gore about $450,000 since 1974, is the story of a sweetheart land deal from long ago, and the ties between the vice president and his family and Armand Hammer and his oil company, Occidental Petroleum.While the origins of that relationship lie in these rolling hills of middle Tennessee and date back half a century, it has continued to bring both benefits and scrutiny for Mr. Gore as he has moved through Congress to the White House and finally toward his party's presidential nomination.For instance, Occidental gave $50,000 to the Democratic Party for the 1996 campaign after a telephone solicitation by Mr. Gore from his White House office and another $100,000 after its chief executive, Ray Irani, spent two nights in the Lincoln Bedroom in 1996.More recently, Occidental stock in the estate of Mr. Gore's father has made the vice president a target for environmental groups. They have demonstrated at about 30 Gore rallies, opposing the oil company's plans to drill on land in Colombia that Indians contend is theirs.The broad outlines of the Gore-Hammer-Occidental connection have been reported at various points in the vice president's career, with bits and pieces of it published in books and articles over the years. Mr. Gore's father, Albert Gore Sr., even described the ties in a memorandum for the Clinton campaign when aides were checking his son's background before picking him as the running mate in 1992.Now, as the pasts and legacies of both Mr. Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas come under scrutiny in a new presidential campaign, the relationship of the Gore family with Mr. Hammer is once again drawing attention.Essentially, Mr. Hammer sold the farmland to the elder Mr. Gore, then Mr. Gore turned around and sold it to his son, who was then a newspaper reporter in Nashville.On Tuesday, Mr. Gore said in Nashville that there had been nothing improper about his family's relationship with Occidental and that the company's mineral lease on the farmland had been the result of a free market negotiation.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/09/business/company-news-occidental-to-acquire-bp-amoco-shell-venture.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL TO ACQUIRE BP AMOCO-SHELL VENTURE<date>Published: March 09, 2000</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation agreed yesterday to buy Altura Energy Ltd., an oil and gas partnership owned by BP Amoco and Shell, in a $3.6 billion deal aimed at increasing its output and earnings. Los Angeles-based Occidental, which operates in the low-cost Permian Basin production area of Texas and New Mexico where Altura has its operations, said its global output would rise 36 percent immediately to 417,000 barrels a day from 1999's average. With the addition of Altura's reserves, Occidental's worldwide proven reserves will increase 63 percent. BP Amoco and Shell will retain a limited preferred interest in Altura and issue $2 billion in long-term notes to the partnership.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/02/business/world-business-briefing-americas-oxy-pete-sells-canadian-affiliate.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; OXY PETE SELLS CANADIAN AFFILIATE<date>Published: March 02, 2000</date><text>A seven-month standoff between the Occidental Petroleum Corporation of Los Angeles and its 29 percent-owned Canadian affiliate has been resolved through the sale of Occidental's stake for $822 million. The affiliate, Canadian Occidental Petroleum Ltd. of Calgary, will pay $592 million for 20 million of its own shares. The Ontario Teachers Pension Plan Board will pay $600 million for 20.2 million shares. Timothy Pritchard</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/14/world/colombian-indians-and-police-clash-over-oil-company-site.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Colombian Indians and Police Clash Over Oil Company Site<date>Published: February 14, 2000</date><text>Leaders of a Colombian Indian tribe say they will not give in to an American company's plans to drill for oil in their traditional lands, even after riot police clashed with protesters blocking a road to the area.''This is our land,'' Roberto Perez, head of the council of leaders for the tribe, the Uwa nation, said on Saturday. ''We will not leave it.''There were reports from tribal leaders that as many as five children fell into a fast-flowing river and might have drowned in the confusion after the clash on Friday. But the reports could not be confirmed. No bodies have been found, and the police have denied reports of deaths in Friday's violence.Members of the United States-based groups Amazon Watch and Rainforest Action Network, however, told reporters that three children had died during the clash.The confrontation between protesters and the police highlights the intensity of a long-running dispute over the Uwa tribe's claim to land it considers sacred. For weeks, members of the tribe have occupied land just outside their reservation on which Occidental de Colombia, an affiliate of Occidental Petroleum, wants to begin exploratory drilling.Although the drilling site lies outside tribal lands, the Uwa say they believe that exploration would bring violence and destroy their culture.On Friday, about 150 riot police flew by helicopter to Las Canoas, 210 miles northeast of Bogota, to disperse the hundreds of Indians who had blocked the dusty road leading to the Occidental drilling site.The police fired tear gas at the protesters, who were armed with wooden clubs and bows and arrows. Six Indians had cuts and bruises, while two police officers were slightly injured by metal-tipped arrows.The highway was reopened in the mountainous region near the Venezuelan border, and on Saturday construction trucks rolled past the scene of the violence, heading for the site where Occidental hopes to find up to two billion barrels of oil. The company could not immediately be reached for comment.Protesters lined the edge of the road facing a picket of riot police.''I'm not moving,'' said Pastor Bocota, who said his 4-month-old daughter died after riot police broke up the protest. ''This is my land, and nobody is taking it from me.''One Uwa girl, 9-year-old Kesiowia Bocota, told reporters through an interpreter that she had lost Mr. Bocota's baby while trying to cross the river. The girl, who is not related to the man or the baby, said the infant slipped from her arms.Col. Raul Cepeda, the regional police commander, said that the incident would be investigated.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/01/business/company-news-lyondell-and-occidental-won-t-buy-equistar-chemicals.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; LYONDELL AND OCCIDENTAL WON'T BUY EQUISTAR CHEMICALS<date>Published: February 01, 2000</date><text>The Lyondell Chemical Company and the Occidental Petroleum Corporation declined yesterday to buy out the 29.5 percent stake held by Millennium Chemicals Inc. in the companies' Equistar Chemicals L.P. joint venture, valued by Millennium at $800 million. Lyondell owns 41 percent and Los Angeles-based Occidental owns 29.5 percent of Equistar, a maker of basic chemicals like ethylene, polyethylene and propylene. Millennium, based in Red Bank, N.J., wants to sell to focus on more profitable specialty chemicals. Houston-based Lyondell said it had rejected the offer because it wanted to reduce debt. A spokesman at Los Angeles-based Occidental said the company told Millennium it was not interested in the offer.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/19/business/chevron-settles-suit-with-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Chevron Settles Suit With Occidental<date>Published: November 19, 1999</date><text>Chevron said today that it had agreed to pay an Occidental Petroleum unit $775 million to settle a lawsuit over a merger deal that fell apart 17 years ago between Gulf Oil and Cities Service.The case dates to 1982 when Cities Service sued Gulf after it terminated an agreement to merge with Cities. Cities Service was acquired by Occidental in 1982 and Gulf was bought in 1984 by Chevron.In 1996, an Oklahoma court sided with OXY USA, formerly Cities Service, in a $742.2 million judgment against Chevron. The Oklahoma Supreme Court affirmed the trial court judgment earlier this year, and Chevron then sought a review before the United States Supreme Court.The companies said they would ask the United States Supreme Court to dismiss Chevron's petition, which was due for review next week.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/14/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-plans-separate-chemical-unit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM PLANS SEPARATE CHEMICAL UNIT<date>Published: August 14, 1999</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, an oil, natural gas and chemical company, is forming a separate company for its specialty chemical operations, which expects to issue a new class of common stock to employees. The new company, the Occidental Industrial Specialty Chemicals Corporation, will have about $600 million in assets and 700 employees. While it will remain an Occidental unit, its operations will be ''separate and distinct'' from the parent's, Occidental said. Analysts say Occidental may eventually sell the specialty chemicals business to investors.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/04/business/occidental-upheld-on-award-vs-chevron.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Upheld on Award vs. Chevron<date>Published: March 04, 1999</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said today that the Oklahoma Supreme Court had upheld a $742.2 million judgment against the Chevron Corporation.The court affirmed a 1996 judgment favoring Occidental in a breach of a merger contract case that dates back more than 16 years. Interest on the award has brought its total value to $935 million, Occidental said.The suit challenged the Gulf Oil Corporation's decision in 1982 to back out of an agreement to buy the Cities Service Company, now a part of Occidental. Chevron inherited the lawsuit when it bought Gulf for $13.3 billion in 1984. Chevron said it would challenge the ruling, possibly by asking the court to reconsider it.''There were numerous errors in the trial proceedings, and those errors resulted in a miscarriage of justice,'' said Fred Gorell, Chevron spokesman.Gulf withdrew an offer of $4.9 billion in cash and stock for Cities Service in 1982, and Cities quickly filed suit, asking for $230 million in damages. Soon after, Occidental bought Cities Service for $4 billion and changed its name to Oxy USA.A district court in Tulsa, Okla., ordered Chevron to pay Oxy USA $742.2 million in 1996. Chevron appealed the award.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/20/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-cutting-1040-jobs-at-3-offices.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM CUTTING 1,040 JOBS AT 3 OFFICES<date>Published: November 20, 1998</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation is cutting 1,040 jobs, or 25 percent of the staff at its various headquarters, as part of a plan to reduce costs by $200 million by 2000. The cuts will affect the corporate headquarters in Los Angeles; oil and gas offices in Bakersfield, Calif., and its chemicals-business headquarters in Dallas. The company said yesterday that it had already cut 540 of the positions. Like other oil companies, Occidental has felt the pressure of depressed oil prices, which are down at least 25 percent from levels a year ago, and of a decline in the petrochemicals business.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/30/business/occidental-petroleum-to-sell-dutch-unit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Petroleum to Sell Dutch Unit<date>Published: June 30, 1998</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, the 13th-largest United States oil company, agreed today to sell its Occidental Netherlands Inc. unit to TransCanada Pipelines Ltd. for $275 million and unspecified contingent payments.Occidental Netherlands owns interests in eight natural-gas producing licenses in the Dutch North Sea and a 38.6 percent interest in Noordgastransport B.V., which owns the pipelines in the area.The wells produced 90 million cubic feet a day, accounting for 13 percent of the company's daily natural-gas production of 706 million cubic feet.The sale is part of Occidental Petroleum's strategy to concentrate its oil and natural-gas exploration and production in larger operations, like the Elk Hills field in California.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/07/world/74-are-missing-as-oil-plane-goes-down-in-the-amazon.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">74 Are Missing As Oil Plane Goes Down In the Amazon<date>Published: May 07, 1998</date><text>Rescuers battled mud and heavy rain today to pull 13 injured survivors from the wreckage of an Occidental Petroleum plane that crashed in the Amazon jungle and burst into flames with 87 people aboard.The survivors, some of whom were seriously injured, had to be carried three miles on stretchers because driving rain prevented their evacuation by helicopter.Despite mud that swallowed some bodies, the authorities held out hope that more survivors could be found among the dense grass and foliage. But they also declared the remaining 74 people missing and feared dead.''We still have hope,'' said Jose Diaz, a spokesman for Los Angeles-based Occidental Petroleum. ''There are so many places for the injured to be.''The Boeing 737, which Occidental chartered from the Peruvian Air Force to transport oil workers, plummeted into the swamp late Tuesday, three miles short of the airport at Andoas, an oil camp 650 miles north of Lima.Most of the 79 passengers on the plane, including an American and a Venezuelan, were oil workers employed either by Occidental or local contractors. The plane also carried a crew of eight, but there were no crew members among the survivors.The sole American aboard, Harold Whitehead, an engineer, was not among those rescued today, Occidental officials said. Mr. Whitehead worked for the Peruvian engineering company Grana y Montero, and his family lives in the Peruvian river port of Iquitos.Both the air force and Occidental said they had no information on bodies found.The plane was flying the workers from Iquitos to Andoas, an oil camp in a remote stretch of jungle near the Ecuadorean border.The cause of the accident was not known. A light rain was falling at the time of the crash, but it should not have affected the flight, Mr. Diaz said.Occidental has pumped oil around Andoas for 26 years and has a contract with Peru's air force to transport its workers, company officials said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/04/17/business/occidental-sells-assets.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Sells Assets<date>Published: April 17, 1998</date><text>Union Pacific Resources Group Inc. said today that it would purchase property, including four oil and gas fields, for $59 million from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation. The properties include 31 producing wells in the four fields in Wyoming and 23 producing wells in Louisiana. In addition, Union Pacific Resources will buy Occidental's 2.5 percent interest in the Masters Creek Gas Plant, complete ownership of the Occidental Central Facilities and nearly 127,000 acres of land in Louisiana. Union Pacific Resources, in Fort Worth, is a domestic oil and gas exploration and production company.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/04/03/business/company-news-mitchell-energy-agrees-to-buy-3-properties-in-texas.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; MITCHELL ENERGY AGREES TO BUY 3 PROPERTIES IN TEXAS<date>Published: April 03, 1998</date><text>The Mitchell Energy and Development Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to buy three oil- and gas-producing properties in Texas in separate transactions totaling $50 million. Mitchell is buying a 67 percent interest in the Columbus field unit in southeastern Texas from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation. It is also buying a 100 percent working interest in six gas units and a 25 percent interest in five units in the Personville field in eastern Texas from 22 sellers.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/21/business/company-news-occidental-in-deal-with-equistar-chemicals.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL IN DEAL WITH EQUISTAR CHEMICALS<date>Published: March 21, 1998</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation agreed yesterday to add its petrochemical business to Equistar Chemicals, a joint venture of the Lyondell Petrochemical Company and Millennium Chemicals Inc. The agreement creates one of the world's largest makers of ethylene and its derivatives, with assets of $7 billion and revenues of $6 billion. Under the agreement, Equistar will pay $425 million to Occidental and $75 million to Millennium. Lyondell will own 41 percent of the joint venture, while Occidental and Millennium will each own 29.5 percent. Previously, Lyondell held 57 percent and Millennium 43 percent.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/19/business/the-markets-market-place-at-occidental-so-so-results-but-big-pay-for-the-boss.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">THE MARKETS: Market Place; At Occidental, So-So Results But Big Pay For the Boss<date>Published: March 19, 1998</date><text>Last year, the directors of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation acknowledged that the employment contract of their chairman and chief executive, Ray R. Irani, needed an overhaul.So they paid Mr. Irani $95 million to ''extinguish'' the contract, which guaranteed lavish pay and contained an unusual automatic renewal feature, and gave him a new one that they said would tie his pay more to performance and would be more ''progressive.''Progress, though, appears to be in the eye of the beholder, not the shareholder.Some aspects of Mr. Irani's pay did decline last year. His base salary fell to $1.69 million from $1.9 million in 1996. And the value of his restricted stock awards dropped to $2.34 million from $2.61 million.Those declines, however, were more than offset by his bonus, which rose to $1.4 million from $872,000 in 1996. In all, the portion of his pay that was tied to company performance rose by $279,000.''I'm not sure that the performance of the company matches the magnitude of the money involved,'' said Judith Fischer, publisher of Executive Compensation Reports, a newsletter.At best, performance has been lackluster. Occidental, like its industry peers, was weighed down last year by falling oil prices and oversupply in the chemicals business. Occidental's revenue last year -- about $8 billion -- was roughly flat with the previous year after adjusting for the sale of the company's Midcon natural gas-transmission division.The company reported a net loss of $390 million in 1997, more than a $1 billion drop from its 1996 profit of $668 million. The sharp drop resulted from several one-time charges, including the cost of buying out Mr. Irani's previous contract and the sale of Midcon. Still, Mr. Irani received $101.4 million in cash compensation last year, according to the company's proxy statement filed on Tuesday. Mr. Irani also received his usual grant of 200,000 stock options, which the company valued at $1 million using the Black-Scholes method of valuing options.And in a departure from recent years, he was given 800,000 more stock options that vest only if certain performance targets are met -- for example, the stock has to trade at $30 a share or higher for 20 consecutive days within three years. The stock traded briefly above that mark in December, but has since fallen below it. Shares of Occidental closed yesterday at $28.25, up 56.25 cents. In its proxy, the company assigned a present value of just under $4 million to those options.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/06/business/company-news-chesapeake-energy-to-acquire-an-occidental-unit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CHESAPEAKE ENERGY TO ACQUIRE AN OCCIDENTAL UNIT<date>Published: March 06, 1998</date><text>The Chesapeake Energy Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire the Occidental Petroleum Corporation's MC Panhandle Corporation unit for $105 million. MC Panhandle has estimated proven reserves of 100 billion cubic feet of natural gas in the West Panhandle field in Carson, Gray, Hutchinson and Moore Counties of the Texas Panhandle. The wells produced about 13 billion cubic feet of natural gas a day in 1997. Discovered in 1918, the West Panhandle field has produced more than 3.3 trillion cubic feet of natural gas and is expected to produce for at least 50 years more. Chesapeake Energy is based in Oklahoma City. Occidental is based in Los Angeles.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/28/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-to-sell-some-properties.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM TO SELL SOME PROPERTIES<date>Published: February 28, 1998</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it would sell some natural gas properties in Oklahoma and Kansas to Oneok Inc. for $135 million to help pay for its purchase of a Federal petroleum reserve. Oneok, based in Tulsa, Okla., said the properties included more than 400 wells. The purchase will nearly double Oneok's oil and gas reserve base. Occidental's oil properties in the two states and holdings in the Hugoton field, which is North America's largest gas field, are not included in the sale. The Los Angeles-based Occidental said earlier that it would sell some properties to help finance its $3.65 billion purchase of the United States Naval Petroleum Reserve at Elk Hills, Calif., and to repurchase up to 40 million shares of stock.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/20/business/occidental-pipeline-unit-sale-realigns-natural-gas-industry.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Pipeline-Unit Sale Realigns Natural Gas Industry<date>Published: December 20, 1997</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation's agreement to sell its Midcon gas pipeline unit to KN Energy Inc. for $3.49 billion in cash will help move Occidental further into its core oil business and will quadruple KN's assets.Occidental announced Thursday night that KN was buying Micdon, which owns Natural Gas Pipeline of America, one of the largest transporters of natural gas into the Chicago area. It also owns other pipelines and gathers, processes and sells natural gas to utilities.Occidental said in October that it planned to sell the unit. It also announced then the planned purchase, for $3.65 billion, of the Federal Government's 78 percent share of the United States Naval Petroleum Reserve in California. Occidental expects Congress to approve the sale of the stake in the reserve, the Elk Hills field, by February.Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, will use proceeds from the sale of Midcon to help pay for the field's acquisition. ''This sale is a key step in the transformation of Occidental into a simpler, more profitable company,'' said Ray Irani, chairman and chief executive.Investors have called on Occidental to focus more on its main oil business, saying its diversification into chemicals, natural gas and pipelines made its stock hard to value. On the New York Stock Exchange today, Occidental fell 6.25 cents, to $29.1875, in a market that was down sharply over all.For KN, which will assume $400 million in debt as part of the transaction, the acquisition will more than quadruple its size in terms of assets. After the purchase, KN will have $7.8 billion in assets, 26,000 miles of pipelines in 15 states and annual operating revenue of $4.7 billion, based on the 12 months ended Sept. 30, the company said. It will transport or sell about 17 percent of all the natural gas in the United States.Occidental said that after taxes and other expenses related to the transaction, the proceeds would be $3.1 billion. Also, KN will pay Occidental an average of $30 million annually for the next 29 years for a lease of the Midcon Texas pipeline. Occidental will classify Midcon as a discontinued operation in its results for the fourth quarter and take a charge of $750 million.KN said it would finance the purchase with bank loans, then refinance it through sales of stock and debt. KN declined 87.5 cents, to $47.625, on the New York Stock Exchange today.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/19/business/kn-energy-seals-deal-for-midcon.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">KN Energy Seals Deal for MidCon<date>Published: December 19, 1997</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said today that it had agreed to sell its MidCon natural gas pipeline unit to KN Energy Inc. for about $4 billion in cash and assumed debt.MidCon owns the Natural Gas Pipeline of America, one of the largest natural gas transporters into the Chicago area. It also owns other pipelines and gathers, processes, and sells natural gas to utilities, KN Energy said.Occidental said in October that it planned to sell MidCon.KN Energy said that after the acquisition, its operations would account for about 17 percent of all natural gas transported or sold in the United States.Occidental said KN Energy would pay $3.49 billion in cash for MidCon and assume $500 million in debt.KN Energy said it would finance the purchase with bank loans, then refinance it through sales of stock and debt. The transaction is expected to close in early 1998.KN Energy had revenue of $1.84 billion in the year ended Sept. 30.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/21/business/company-news-occidental-is-planning-to-sell-1.6-billion-in-assets.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL IS PLANNING TO SELL $1.6 BILLION IN ASSETS<date>Published: November 21, 1997</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it planned to streamline its business by selling about $1.6 billion of exploration and production assets by the middle of 1998. The company plans to sell what it deems low-return properties, which generate a return on assets of 5 percent to 8 percent. The moves come in addition to Occidental's plan to sell its natural-gas pipeline unit, Midcon, to pay for the acquisition of a large Government-owned petroleum field, Elk Hills. Occidental officials said they had received interest in Midcon from 28 companies, including utilities, pipelines and gas marketers. They expect the sale to generate at least $3 billion in net proceeds. Occidental's stock rose 75 cents yesterday, to $29.6875.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/23/business/company-news-canadian-occidental-in-deal-with-pinnacle-resources.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; CANADIAN OCCIDENTAL IN DEAL WITH PINNACLE RESOURCES<date>Published: October 23, 1997</date><text>Canadian Occidental Petroleum Ltd. said yesterday that it would sell part of its Wascana Energy unit to Pinnacle Resources Ltd. for $308 million (Canadian), or $221.5 million (United States). Canadian Occidental said the sale included properties in southwest Saskatchewan that produce 11,200 barrels of oil equivalent a day and generate an annual cash flow of about $32 million (Canadian). The deal also includes about 788,000 acres of undeveloped land. Canadian Occidental acquired Wascana earlier this year for $1.7 billion (Canadian) after a bidding war with a rival, Talisman Energy Inc. Canadian Occidental, which is 30 percent owned by the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, and Pinnacle are both based in Calgary, Alberta.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/12/business/investing-it-occidental-makes-a-95-million-acquisition-the-boss-s-contract.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">INVESTING IT; Occidental Makes a $95 Million Acquisition: The Boss's Contract<date>Published: October 12, 1997</date><text>SO, it was not a misprint. On Monday, directors of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation announced that they were paying Ray R. Irani, the company's chairman and chief executive, $95 million to buy out his current contract so it could issue a new agreement that linked his pay more closely to the company's performance.Occidental officials declined to comment beyond a news release, in which George O. Nolley, chairman of the company's compensation committee, said that buying out the old contract would ''extinguish significant existing liabilities.''A contract given to Mr. Irani in 1991 paid him, among other things, $1.9 million in annual salary, at least 75,000 stock options every year, restricted stock worth at least 101 percent of his salary every year, and a bonus worth at least 60 percent of his salary every year. The contract was also automatically renewed daily for a new seven-year term. Such an ''evergreen'' feature was included in about 45 of 100 chief executives' contracts of the last two years that were analyzed by Executive Compensation Reports, a newsletter based in Springfield, Va.Because of the daily renewal of Mr. Irani's contract, it had to be bought out before the board could issue a new agreement. The company said it hired independent consultants and actuaries to arrive at the $95 million figure.The new contract lowers Mr. Irani's annual salary to $1.2 million and removes the evergreen provision by fixing the term of the contract at five years. It also gives the board full discretion over his bonuses -- a carrot, albeit for someone who has just consumed a $95 million feast.Stockholders may find the buyout a bit rich in light of Occidental's stock performance, which has lagged behind that of indexes tracking both the broad market and the oil industry since Mr. Irani took over.''Ray Irani's pay package has no relationship with the company's subpar performance, and it was designed to have no substantial relationship to performance,'' said Graef Crystal, a compensation expert.Occidental has a long tradition, started by the company's legendary founder and former chairman, Armand Hammer, of paying its top executives handsomely. For example, Mr. Hammer was among the first corporate leaders to get that paradoxical benefit, a guaranteed minimum bonus, Mr. Crystal said.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/07/business/us-oilfield-will-be-sold-to-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">U.S. Oilfield Will Be Sold To Occidental<date>Published: October 07, 1997</date><text>The Federal Government moved to get out of the oil business yesterday by accepting a bid of $3.65 billion in cash from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation for the Government's share of a huge oilfield in California that was acquired in the early 1900's to insure that the Navy had plenty of oil in reserve as it converted from coal.To help pay for the acquisition, Occidental said it would divest itself of some major assets, including Mid-Con, its natural gas pipeline subsidiary, which the company said would bring in about $3 billion. Though analysts said that Occidental was paying a steep price for the Government's 78 percent stake in the Elk Hills Naval Petroleum Reserve, as the field is known, the company's shares moved up sharply.Patricia Fry Godley, Assistant Secretary of the Department of Energy, which oversaw the sale of Elk Hills from 22 bids, said it was the largest sale ever of a Government asset to private industry. The largest sale was that of Conrail in 1987; the railroad was sold to the public in a stock offering that brought in $1.65 billion, the equivalent in today's dollars of $2.3 billion.''We're getting maximum value for this asset,'' Ms. Godley said. ''The Navy no longer needs Elk Hills and this sale helps get the Government out of the oil business.'' Several Federal agencies had put a value of about $1.5 billion to $2.4 billion on Elk Hills.Elk Hills played a major role in the Teapot Dome scandal during the Harding Administration in the early 1920's, when some oil companies won drilling rights on the reserve and paid off some top Government officials with cash and gifts.In recent years, the Navy has not relied on the field, because world oil supplies have been plentiful. For Occidental, however, there is a tantalizing aspect to Elk Hills, which is one of the largest producing fields in the United States. There have been indications from the Chevron Corporation -- which owns the other 22 percent of the field -- that major reserves might lie below the area that has already been explored and developed. Some critics of the plan to sell the field had raised the concern that the winning bidder could eventually end up with a windfall.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/07/business/occidental-chief-gets-95-million-contract-buyout-and-new-pact.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Occidental Chief Gets $95 Million Contract Buyout, and New Pact<date>Published: October 07, 1997</date><text>Ray R. Irani, the chairman of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, appears to have learned something about pay packages from his predecessor, Armand Hammer.The company said yesterday that it would give Mr. Irani $95 million to buy out his old contract, and that it would replace it with a new contract tied more directly to performance.Graef S. Crystal, a compensation consultant, said the payment to Mr. Irani was groundbreaking in its lavishness for a top executive whose performance had lagged behind the performance of broad stock market indexes. Since Mr. Irani took over in December 1990, for example, Occidental's return to shareholders has been one-half of the returns offered by the Standard &amp; Poor's 500.''Occidental is giving Ray Irani the best of all worlds, and he's a lousy performer,'' Mr. Crystal said. ''I've never seen a contract this outrageous before.''The previous chairman at Occidental, Dr. Hammer, had shown a similar knack for obtaining munificent rewards from his board. He was among the first corporate leaders to get a guaranteed minimum bonus. In addition, Dr. Hammer had a contract that lasted until next February. When he died in December 1990, the company paid $18.3 million to a foundation run by Dr. Hammer.Mr. Irani's previous contract had some unusual features, including a seven-year term that was renewed every day; a guaranteed bonus of not less than 60 percent of his salary; an annual grant of restricted stock worth at least as much as his annual salary of $1.9 million; a minimum of 75,000 stock options a year, and seven years' salary and payment of stock options if Occidental was acquired.Occidental said that buying out Mr. Irani's contract -- in addition to a $17 million contract buyout for Dale R. Laurance, its president -- would reduce third-quarter earnings by 16 cents a share, to 40 cents a share, a 29 percent drop.Investor reaction was obscured yesterday by announcement of Occidental's plan to buy the Federal Government's share in a huge California oilfield for $3.65 billion.The new contract for Mr. Irani is for a fixed five-year term, and reduces Mr. Irani's salary to $1.2 million from $1.9 million. Bonuses and incentives will no longer be paid according to guaranteed minimums, but instead will be determined at the board's discretion. The company also eliminated a lifetime retirement benefit for Mr. Irani and his surviving spouse, as well as the provision guaranteeing full payment of his contract if the company changes hands.George O. Nolley, chairman of the company's compensation committee, said in a statement: ''These revisions extinguish significant existing liabilities, as well as open-ended financial commitments, and implement contemporary incentive arrangements to replace those negotiated years ago.''A spokesman for Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, declined to comment further.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/16/business/pioneer-agrees-to-buy-chemical-plant-from-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">PIONEER AGREES TO BUY CHEMICAL PLANT FROM OCCIDENTAL<date>Published: May 16, 1997</date><text>The Pioneer Companies said yesterday that it had agreed to buy a chemical plant in Tacoma, Wash., from the Occidental Chemical Corporation for $102.5 million in cash and stock. Pioneer, a Houston-based chemical company, said the acquisition would add to its production of chlorine and caustic soda. Pioneer is to pay $97 million in cash and $5.5 million in preferred stock for the plant. The preferred stock is convertible into 440,000 shares of common stock. Pioneer also agreed to supply a portion of the Tacoma plant's chlorine production to Occidental Chemical for up to five years. Occidental Chemical is a subsidiary of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation of Los Angeles.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/13/business/rules-tightened-at-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Rules Tightened At Occidental<date>Published: May 13, 1997</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had adopted policies to strengthen its internal controls in its dealings with foreign governments and businessmen.The oil company was responding to an article in The Wall Street Journal, which reported that lawyers for the company were investigating whether it had overpaid some foreign middlemen or whether any funds might have been used for payoffs overseas.The article, which cited unnamed people it said were familiar with the matter, said that the company had curtailed some of its dealings with foreign middlemen, including Hany M. Salaam, a Lebanese businessman. Mr. Salaam's companies received about $100 million from Occidental from 1991 through 1996, the article said, about $14 million of which was for what were called advisory services.Mr. Salaam has been connected with Occidental since the days of its former chairman, Armand Hammer.In its statement, Occidental said the issues raised by the article were reviewed in the last year by the audit committee of the company's board.''As part of its review, the audit committee recommended that additional policies and procedures be adopted in order to strengthen internal controls,'' the company said. ''Those recommendations were carefully reviewed and accepted by the full board.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/04/10/business/canadian-occidental-wins-battle-for-wascana-energy.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">CANADIAN OCCIDENTAL WINS BATTLE FOR WASCANA ENERGY<date>Published: April 10, 1997</date><text>Canadian Occidental Petroleum Ltd., a unit of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, emerged as the winner yesterday in the battle for Wascana Energy Inc. after a rival bidder, Talisman Energy Inc., bowed out of the race. Talisman, based in Calgary, Alberta, opened the bidding for Wascana in February. The company said it would not increase its offer. Canadian Occidental, also based in Calgary, entered the bidding as white knight for Wascana, based in Regina, Saskatchewan, with an all-cash offer of $20.50 (Canadian) a share in March, and is now poised to become one of Canada's top three oil and gas producers.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/19/business/canadian-occidental-plans-to-bid-for-wascana-energy.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">CANADIAN OCCIDENTAL PLANS TO BID FOR WASCANA ENERGY<date>Published: March 19, 1997</date><text>Canadian Occidental Petroleum Ltd., a unit of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, said yesterday that it would offer $1.9 billion (Canadian), the equivalent of $1.39 billion (United States), for Wascana Energy Inc., topping a bid of $1.7 billion (Canadian) by Talisman Energy Inc. Canadian Occidental, which is based in Calgary, Alberta, has operations in western Canada, the United States and overseas. Wascana, based in Regina, Saskatchewan, had been speaking with suitors to ward off the hostile bid from Talisman, based in Calgary. The United States shares of Canadian Occidental rose $1.50 yesterday, to $18.625, on the American Stock Exchange. Shares of Wascana rose $1.05 (Canadian), to $20.40, on the Toronto Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/04/opinion/l-us-plays-partner-to-sudanese-abuses-472891.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">U.S. Plays Partner to Sudanese Abuses<date>Published: February 04, 1997</date><text>To the Editor:President Clinton should move to rescind the special waiver granted the Occidental Petroleum Corporation to do business with the Sudan (''Oil Deals and Arms Sales,'' editorial, Jan. 28). As you note, this loophole undermines United States anti-terrorism policy. Supplying the Sudan with oil wealth also insures that the Islamic fundamentalist Government will continue to murder, enslave and forcibly convert its black non-Muslim population with greater intensity.For more than a decade the human rights community has documented the ravages of the Sudan's self-declared jihad to Islamicize African Christians and animists in the south who dare to keep their faiths, languages and ethnic ways. More than a million black Africans have been killed, captured or displaced. The oil fields are in the south and should benefit the Africans under attack; extracting this wealth is grand larceny.What is at stake is not only the corrupting influence of large political donations (Occidental contributes to both Democrats and Republicans) and the crippling of efforts to guard ourselves against terror: the granting of this waiver makes America a partner to cultural cleansing, enslavement and murder. President Clinton must rescind the waiver.CHARLES JACOBSSomerville, Mass., Jan. 31, 1997The writer is research director for the American Anti-Slavery Group.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/28/opinion/oil-deals-and-arms-sales.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Oil Deals and Arms Sales<date>Published: January 28, 1997</date><text>The Clinton Administration's tendency to let commercial opportunities override sensible national security policies is troubling. Recent days brought word that last summer business considerations led the White House to waive a law prohibiting American companies from doing business with countries that sponsor terrorism. Specifically, officials gave approval to the Occidental Petroleum Corporation to take part in a $930 million oil project in Sudan.The Administration has also dropped a longstanding ban on sales of the Amraam air-to-air missile to countries outside NATO. The decision cripples efforts to negotiate limits on arms sales and increases the risk that this highly effective weapon may one day be used against America or its allies. The ban was dropped to allow American aerospace companies to gain a competitive edge over Russian and French rivals.The most effective way to fight terrorism or restrain arms sales is through international action. But with the world's biggest economy and its most technologically advanced arms industry, America can exert considerable influence on its own, provided it maintains strict and consistent standards. When Washington starts selectively enforcing its own rules, its policies become meaningless.Sudan's radical Islamic Government supports international terrorists. The Administration blames it for a 1995 assassination attempt against Egypt's President, Hosni Mubarak, and last year expelled a Sudanese diplomat for plotting to bomb the United Nations headquarters. Helping Sudan's oil industry does not serve American interests.A few months ago, the Administration judged Sudan's Government so threatening that it decided to provide military equipment to rebel groups based in three neighboring countries. When news of the American military deliveries became public, Sudan decided to exclude Occidental from the oil project.Washington's policy toward the Sudanese regime now seems hopelessly confused. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright did little to clarify it at her introductory news conference last Friday. Even as she called for new United Nations sanctions against Sudan, she endorsed the decision to let Occidental bid for the oil contract.The Amraam missile sales remain on track. In 1995 the Administration gave Lockheed permission to include the missiles along with 80 F-16 fighter planes the company was trying to sell to the United Arab Emirates. That gave Lockheed an edge over its French competitors. But it also set a damaging precedent. Soon Thailand also demanded Amraams as a sweetener for buying American jets. Thailand's bid has already been conditionally approved, making similar demands from other Southeast Asian countries certain.American efforts to combat terrorism and limit the sale of advanced weapons cannot be suspended every time an attractive business deal appears. Before long, the waivers and exceptions will become the policy, and Washington will be left with a set of hollow principles.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/14/books/armand-hammer-s-maze-of-skulduggery.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Armand Hammer's Maze of Skulduggery<date>Published: October 14, 1996</date><text>On a January day in 1979, shortly after admitting defeat in a bitter industrial war, the corporate mogul and art collector Armand Hammer brainstormed privately with his lawyer about some troublesome fallout. Several years earlier, he had passed off a $60,000 Goya painting as a million-dollar bequest to the Soviet Union. Suddenly, the transaction and a cash kitty it disguised threatened to become public, embarrassing him with his Soviet friends and entangling him with American investigators.Now, six years after the death of Hammer at age 92, the episode and much besides have emerged in a new book that casts a corrosive light on the often-preening supercapitalist who shook Lenin's hand, cultivated American Presidents, built a global oil and whisky empire and left a legacy of familial ruin and lawsuits against his multibillion-dollar Occidental Petroleum Corporation, as well as against the foundation and art galleries he controlled.The book, ''Dossier: The Secret History of Armand Hammer,'' by Edward Jay Epstein, published this month by Random House and excerpted last month in The New Yorker, ties Hammer to bizarre deceptions, from contriving a makeover and fake identity for an art adviser-mistress whom he was hiding from his third wife to serving as a conduit for dubious Russian artworks. Among other schemes, it says he trafficked in fake Imperial Faberge eggs that he authenticated as genuine with an official Faberge stamp.Documented in part by secret tape recordings made for Hammer by a member of his family and obtained by Mr. Epstein, the book also details bribery schemes said to have helped Hammer land lucrative oil drilling and mineral concessions in Venezuela and Libya. It is not clear why Hammer would have risked memorializing his chicanery.Samples of the documentation and access to sources were provided to The New York Times by Mr. Epstein, the author of previous investigative books on the spy craft and the John F. Kennedy assassination.From early on, Hammer's career diverged from his legend as an international philanthropist, which he later took pains to construct. After meeting Lenin in 1921, the book says, Hammer secretly distributed the equivalent of $600,000 in today's currency to agents of the Communist International in New York.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/06/world/land-clash-pits-indians-vs-oilmen-in-colombia.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Land Clash Pits Indians Vs. Oilmen In Colombia<date>Published: October 06, 1996</date><text>Late in the 17th century, a group of Spanish missionaries and tax collectors journeyed to a mountainous area about 30 miles southwest of here. Their goal was to establish control over a village of Uwa Indians.But rather than endure subjugation, the entire community, which had sought refuge atop a cliff, plunged to its collective death 1,800 feet below. The remains -- bones of men, women and children -- can still be found scattered at the bottom of what present-day Uwa, descended from other communities, call ''the Cliff of Glory.''Uwa also feel threatened today, this time by an oil company, Occidental de Colombia, an affiliate of Occidental Petroleum of Bakersfield, Calif.Occidental Petroleum has an agreement with the Colombian Government to explore here, and a spokesman for the Uwa said the Indians would rather die than let that happen. They say such exploration would damage the land, fill their territory with alien workers and destroy the world they know.''We have talked about collective suicide,'' said Roberto Cobaria, the chief spokesman. ''The Werhayas'' -- or spiritual leaders -- ''will decide how.''Occidental's agreement, signed in 1992, grants the company permission to explore for oil in parts of the Uwa reservation as well as surrounding territory. The dispute began when Occidental set out to obtain an environmental license to conduct seismic studies in the region. To secure such permits, companies whose work may affect native communities must first meet with the Indians to discuss the impact of the project.In January 1995, the last of several meetings between Occidental executives, officials from the Government and the state oil company, Ecopetrol, and Uwa leaders took place. In February the Environment Ministry awarded Occidental its license.Months later, while the company was conducting the field work here, the People's Defender's office, a Government human rights agency, sued the Environment Ministry on behalf of the Indians, arguing that the permit was invalid because the consultation process had not taken the Uwa point of view into account.Occidental and the Environment Ministry argued that the project did not, by law, require the approval of native communities, and a court is to rule on the matter. Occidental executives would not comment publicly.The suit has brought to the forefront the interests of the country's one million Indians versus those of oil exporting, Colombia's largest source of foreign revenue.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/04/business/occidental-petroleum-acquires-3-chemical-producers.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM ACQUIRES 3 CHEMICAL PRODUCERS<date>Published: September 04, 1996</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had acquired three chemical producers in separate transactions for a total of about $146 million, including $127 million in stock. The acquired entities are Laurel Industries of La Porte, Tex., which produces a chemical used as a flame retardant in plastics; Natural Gas Odorizing of Baytown, Tex., which produces chemicals for use in natural gas and propane production, and a plant in Augusta, Ga., that produces silicates used to make soap, detergents and paper. The Georgia plant was sold by Power Solicates Manufacturing Inc. Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, intends to increase its specialty chemicals business to $250 million in annual earnings by 2000, from $65 million now.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/31/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-sells-stake-in-oilfields-to-congo.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM SELLS STAKE IN OILFIELDS TO CONGO<date>Published: July 31, 1996</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had sold royalty stakes in three oilfields in Congo to the African nation for $215 million. Occidental, which is based in Los Angeles, acquired the interests in the offshore fields for $150 million in 1993. The interests entitled Occidental to a share of the Government's portion of oil from the developments. Occidental's net production in the Congo was 9,000 barrels a day in 1995, 3.2 percent of the company's total worldwide production of 278,000 barrels.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/23/business/oil-companies-report-strong-2d-quarter-earnings.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Oil Companies Report Strong 2d-Quarter Earnings<date>Published: July 23, 1996</date><text>Texaco, Mobil, Amoco and ARCO reported strong second-quarter earnings yesterday, as demand surged while oil and natural gas supplies shrank and prices soared.But Exxon's earnings edged lower as the company spent more on capital and exploration, and Occidental Petroleum's results were hurt by lower transport margins.Over all, the results were roughly in line with expectations, industry analysts said."Nothing exciting, but Mobil came through better than expected and Texaco was substantially better," said Rosario Ilacqua, an analyst with Rothschild Inc. "The big surprise is that chemical earnings continued to be the drag."Texaco Inc. said its earnings surged in the quarter to $689 million, or $2.59 a share, from $271 million, or 99 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. The most recent quarter includes a gain of $224 million from the sale of some Japanese interests by Caltex, a joint venture of Texaco and Chevron. But even excluding the one-time gain, Texaco's earnings were sharply higher, at $465 million, or $1.73 a share.The results exceeded Wall Street expectations of earnings of $1.55 a share, according to a survey of analysts by Zacks Investment Research."Improvements in nearly all sectors of our business were enhanced by strong crude and natural gas prices during the first half of 1996," said Peter I. Bijur, chairman of Texaco, which is based in White Plains.Crude oil prices on the New York Mercantile Exchange rose to more than $25 a barrel in early April, as inventories fell to 20-year lows as a result of a harsh winter, surprisingly strong Asian demand for oil and a slew of unexpected domestic refinery outages.The Mobil Corporation said its profits shot up more than four times, to $783 million, or $1.95 a share, in the quarter from $179 million, or 42 cents a share, in the period a year ago. Its operating income rose 15 percent, to a record $814 million from $706 million. Revenues rose to $19.5 billion from $18.8 billion.The latest results include a one-time charge of $31 million to restructure staff support services. A year ago, the company took $527 million in charges mainly to restructure worldwide staff support services and marketing and refining operations in the United States and Europe."Mobil's improvement this year reflected favorable industry fundamentals in the petroleum sector, partly offset by weaker margins in the chemical sector," Mobil's chairman, Lucio A. Noto, said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/20/business/chevron-settlement-put-at-700-million.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Chevron Settlement Put at $700 Million<date>Published: July 20, 1996</date><text>The Chevron Corporation has been ordered to pay an estimated $700 million in a lawsuit over the Gulf Oil Company's 1982 decision to call off its $5 billion acquisition of the Cities Service Company.Chevron, which bought Gulf two years later, said in a statement it would appeal the ruling in the breach-of-contract lawsuit.Jurors decided Thursday evening that Chevron should pay $228.9 million plus interest to the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, which bought Cities Service, another oil company, in 1982.Chevron put the interest at more than $500 million. The jury did not specify an amount.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/21/business/company-briefs-018376.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: March 21, 1996</date><text>MANPOWER INC., Milwaukee, agreed to acquire Teamwork Sverige A.B., an employment service concern in Sweden, for an undisclosed amount of cash.OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM CORP., Los Angeles, said it had added 43 percent more oil and natural gas to its reserve base than it produced last year.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/14/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-announces-layoffs.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM ANNOUNCES LAYOFFS<date>Published: February 14, 1996</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it would dismiss 450 workers at its Occidental Chemical Corporation subsidiary and eliminate the subsidiary's international division. The layoffs and reorganization are expected to result in annualized savings of about $100 million, Occidental said, and no charge against 1996 earnings is expected. The latest moves are part of Occidental's reorganization of worldwide oil and gas operations, announced in October. Last month, the company dismissed 400 workers at its Midcon Corporation subsidiary, to save about $50 million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/06/world/us-pesticide-kills-foreign-fruit-pickers-hopes.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">U.S. Pesticide Kills Foreign Fruit Pickers' Hopes<date>Published: December 06, 1995</date><text>Half a lifetime ago, when Mario Brito Dumas was a young man with a bride and a peasant's head of modest dreams, he tended the lush banana plantations outside Naranjal. If he had any plan, it was the common one that keeps a man toiling through his best years: to make enough money to raise a family.But a few years after his first son was born in 1972, Mr. Brito's plantation began using a pesticide both miraculous and terrible. It killed off a microscopic worm that would prevent the bananas' export to the United States, but it also killed pigs, frogs, birds and other creatures that drank water running from the field.What Mr. Brito and the other men who worked with this powerful new chemical could not guess was that it was also destroying their chances to have children.In 1977 the chemical, dibromo chloropropane, or DBCP, was found to cause sterility in men working at an Occidental Petroleum plant in Lathrop, Calif., prompting an immediate ban on its use in California, and sharply restricting its use elsewhere in the continental United States.But American-based food growers continued to use the fumigant in countries without the United States standard of environmental, legal and occupational protections. And now, emerging from the anger, the ruined marriages and childless houses across the globe, some 25,000 workers from 12 developing countries are suing manufacturers and fruit growers.No U.S. Law Prohibited Export of the ChemicalsContending that they were exposed to a known hazard without any warning that the pesticide could cause sterility and possibly birth defects and cancer, the workers are suing Dow Chemical, Shell Oil -- a unit of Royal Dutch/Shell -- and Occidental Petroleum, along with Del Monte Fruit, Chiquita Brands and Dole Food."Even though they knew the risk of the product -- they didn't use it in their own country," Mr. Brito said, "but they used it here in the third world, despite the damage to humans and animals. The ones who produced this chemical bear absolute responsibility for this disaster."The manufacturers deny that they sent the pesticide overseas after 1979. They also point out that they followed all United States laws governing the labeling, sale and use of DBCP, rated a probable human carcinogen by the Environmental Protection Agency.And that is perhaps the most unbearable element of all for people here, for no American law prohibits exporting chemicals that are banned from use in the United States.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/11/business/company-news-petroleum-concern-to-add-65-of-indspec-chemical.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;PETROLEUM CONCERN TO ADD 65% OF INDSPEC CHEMICAL<date>Published: November 11, 1995</date><text>Correction AppendedThe Occidental Petroleum Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire a 65 percent equity interest in the Indspec Chemical Corporation for $85 million. Occidental Petroleum said that Indspec's management and employees would retain voting control of the company. Occidental is buying the stake from Harlan Inc., a New York merchant bank, and an affiliated investment partnership. The investment partnership, Castle Harlan Partners II L.P., acquired Indspec in December 1993, along with Indspec management, employees and the employee stock option program. Indspec, with 1994 sales of $115 million, is the world's largest producer of resorcinol.Correction: November 14, 1995, Tuesday A brief report by Dow Jones in the Company News column of Business Day on Saturday about the purchase of 65 percent of the Indspec Chemical Corporation by the Occidental Petroleum Corporation misidentified the New York merchant bank that is selling the stake. It is Castle Harlan Inc., not Harlan Inc.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/07/business/company-news-clark-usa-agreements-to-reduce-parent-s-stake.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;CLARK USA AGREEMENTS TO REDUCE PARENT'S STAKE<date>Published: November 07, 1995</date><text>Clark USA Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to pay the Occidental Petroleum Corporation and the Gulf Resources Corporation $246.9 million in cash and Clark stock in exchange for proceeds from the sale of 21 million barrels of oil. The deals will give Occidental a 19 percent stake in Clark, the nation's No. 4 independent oil refiner and marketer, and give Gulf Resources, a privately held energy company, 4 percent of Clark. The stake of Clark's parent company, the Horsham Corporation, will be reduced to 46 percent from 60 percent. Horsham, based in Toronto, also has interests in gold mining and real estate.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/10/26/business/company-news-occidental-consolidating-its-oil-and-gas-operations.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;OCCIDENTAL CONSOLIDATING ITS OIL AND GAS OPERATIONS<date>Published: October 26, 1995</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it planned to consolidate its worldwide oil and gas operations into a single operating company, a move designed to save $100 million a year. Occidental could see 80 percent of the savings next year, with the full effect to be seen in 1997, according to the chief operating officer, Dale R. Laurance. Occidental, based in Los Angeles, plans to announce the full details of the move in January. The company said it would record a one-time expense against fourth-quarter earnings to reflect the changes, but Mr. Laurance declined to quantify the charge.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/12/business/company-news-potash-to-pay-280-million-for-occidental-unit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; POTASH TO PAY $280 MILLION FOR OCCIDENTAL UNIT<date>Published: September 12, 1995</date><text>The Potash Corporation of Saskatchewan Inc. said yesterday that it would buy a fertilizer production subsidiary from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation for $280 million. Potash would acquire White Springs Agricultural Chemicals Inc., which operates two mines and chemical plants. It also has a bulk terminal in Jacksonville, Fla. Other assets would include a feed plant in Davenport, Iowa, and ammonia terminals in Savannah, Ga., and in Houston. Potash, based in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, is the world's largest producer of potash, which is used to make fertilizer. Its shares were up $5.50 yesterday, at $62.50, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/19/business/company-news-912395.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;<date>Published: August 19, 1995</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that the United States Energy Department had formally accepted a $275 million settlement of an overcharging case against one of its subsidiaries. A tentative settlement was reached June 27. The settlement ends a case involving Energy Department allegations that between 1979 and 1981, Occidental's OXY USA Inc. unit violated Federal price controls on crude oil by overcharging some $254 million.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/21/business/3-oil-companies-report-strong-earnings.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">3 Oil Companies Report Strong Earnings<date>Published: July 21, 1995</date><text>Buoyed by almost every major segment of its business, particularly chemicals, the Exxon Corporation yesterday reported a surge in earnings in the second quarter.The Occidental Petroleum Corporation and the Sun Company also reported strong quarterly earnings yesterday.The oil industry has benefited this quarter from unexpectedly high demand for gasoline, causing refineries to run near full capacity. Gasoline prices have also surged from the quarter a year earlier, although recent surveys have shown prices falling by a few cents after rising for most of the year.Paul Ting, an oil industry analyst with Oppenheimer &amp; Company, noted that the profit margins of the nation's refineries were sharply higher from a year ago, in some cases as high as they have been since the Persian Gulf war in 1991.Exxon, based in Irving, Tex., said earnings rose 84 percent, to $1.63 billion, or $1.30 a share, compared with $885 million, or 70 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.The gain in profits was led by its chemicals business, whose earnings tripled in the quarter, to $571 million, from $190 million in the quarter a year earlier.Revenues rose to $31.7 billion, from $27.3 billion last year.Lee R. Raymond, the chairman of Exxon, attributed the gains to increased sales of gasoline and higher prices for crude oil, which were on the average $2 a barrel higher in the quarter than last year.Shares of Exxon rose 37.5 cents yesterday, to $73.125, on the New York Stock Exchange.Strong gains in chemicals also bolstered the second-quarter earnings of Occidental Petroleum.The company, based in Los Angeles, earned $187 million, or 51 cents a share, compared with a loss of $19 million in the quarter a year earlier. Earnings for its chemical division jumped to $354 million in the second quarter from $65 million a year earlier.Second-quarter earnings were reduced by $109 million in pretax charges to settle litigation with the Energy Department over violations of oil price and allocation regulations.Revenues rose to $2.7 billion in the second quarter from $2.2 billion.The Sun Company, which operates gas stations under the Sunoco brand, said earnings jumped in the second quarter, helped by an after-tax gain of $157 million from the sale of the company's remaining interest in Suncor, a Canadian petroleum company.The company, which is based in Philadelphia, earned $109 million, or $1.02 a share, compared with $12 million, or 11 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.Revenues rose to $2.92 billion from $2.25 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/21/business/sun-posts-loss-occidental-rebounds-for-a-gain.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Sun Posts Loss; Occidental Rebounds for a Gain<date>Published: April 21, 1995</date><text>The Sun Company posted a loss for the first quarter yesterday, while the Occidental Petroleum Corporation said it had swung to profitability.The results illustrated the current strengths and weaknesses in the energy industry. Sun, which reported its first loss since late 1992, was hurt by weak refining profits, while Occidental was aided by rising oil and chemical prices. Those trends are likely to be reflected next week, when the six biggest oil companies will be among those energy concerns that report earnings."All in all, when you average it all together you're going to have much better earnings than last year -- about 10 percent higher," said Fadel Gheit, an analyst with Fahnestock &amp; Company. "You have much better oil prices than last year."The Chevron Corporation, the Tosco Corporation and Ashland Oil Inc. have big refining operations and may post lackluster results, while the Amoco Corporation, the Exxon Corporation and the Phillips Petroleum Company are likely to have been aided by their big chemical operations. And companies with lots of oil production to sell, such as the Atlantic Richfield Company and Texaco Inc., stand to report improved results, as Occidental did.Hurt by low margins in its refining business, Sun posted its first quarterly loss since 1992, when it began a major restructuring program. Sun, based in Philadelphia, had a loss in the first quarter of $7 million, or 7 cents a share, in contrast to net income of $27 million, or 25 cents, in the 1994 quarter. Revenue rose 25 percent, to $2.59 billion from $2.07 billion, and reflected the purchase of a Chevron refinery in August.Sun shares were up 12.5 cents, at $28.125, on the New York Stock Exchange.Sun, the biggest independent petroleum refiner in the United States, said warm weather and an oversupply of gasoline and petroleum products crimped margins to record low levels in the quarter. Its results were $50 million less than what the company had projected, and Robert Campbell, Sun's chairman and chief executive, warned that if margins do not improve soon, it will be difficult to reach the operating income level of $250 million that Sun has forecast for this year.Occidental swung to a profit in the first quarter from a year ago, beating analysts' expectations, as demand for its chemicals soared. The Los Angeles oil and chemical concern posted net income of $178 million, or 49 cents a share, compared with a loss of $40 million, or 19 cents, a year ago. Revenue rose 28 percent, to $2.71 billion from $2.11 billion, as oil and natural gas production and chemical sales soared."We are pleased with the improved operating results in both our chemical and oil and gas divisions," said Ray R. Irani, chairman. "The higher cash flow from operations will enable us to accelerate our ongoing debt-reduction program."Its shares were up 37.5 cents, at $23.50, on the New York exchange.The chemical unit's operating profit soared to $307 million from $33 million before special items.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/01/12/business/bunker-hunt-files-lawsuit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Bunker Hunt Files Lawsuit<date>Published: January 12, 1995</date><text>Nelson Bunker Hunt has filed a lawsuit seeking the reversal of the sale of his family's oil company to Occidental Petroleum for $250 million.Mr. Hunt argues in his suit that the sale contradicted his parents' wishes to keep the Placid Oil Company in family hands. He also contends in the suit that the family trustees who approved the sale rejected higher offers.The suit was filed on Dec. 30 in Federal District Court in Shreveport, La.Founded by Mr. Hunt's father, the legendary Texas wildcatter, H. L. Hunt, Placid Oil was the centerpiece of the Hunt fortune. At the time of the sale, it was the last large chunk of the fortune left in family hands.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/11/30/business/company-news-occidental-purchasing-the-hunts-oil-company.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Occidental Purchasing the Hunts' Oil Company<date>Published: November 30, 1994</date><text>The Placid Oil Company, once the nucleus of the Hunt family's vast fortune, announced its sale today to the Occidental Petroleum Corporation for $250 million.The Dallas-based company, founded by H. L. Hunt in 1936 and later run by his sons, became one of the nation's largest independent oil companies. Despite depressed oil markets and a bankruptcy filing in the 1980's, it still has annual revenue of $450 million.Jerry R. Wright, Placid's president, said the trusts that owned the company for three Hunt brothers had decided a year ago to seek greater liquidity through a sale. Because of the trust structure, Mr. Wright said, the individual brothers -- William Herbert, Nelson Bunker and Lamar -- would not suddenly receive more than $80 million each.While it remained unclear whom the sale would directly benefit, a family spokesman said Herbert Hunt was leaving the money in his trust for his family.Placid filed for bankruptcy protection in 1986 as Herbert's and Bunker's silver, real estate and petroleum empires collapsed.Although Placid emerged from bankruptcy in 1988, other Hunt-related bankruptcy litigation has dragged on since. Only in recent months have the families of Herbert and Bunker, who filed for personal bankruptcy, agreed to hand over much of the property claimed by the brothers' creditors. The Hunt spokesman called the timing of the agreement with creditors and the company sale coincidental.Occidental Petroleum, having sold off many businesses after its founder, Dr. Armand Hammer, died in 1990, has been adding to its core oil and gas interests recently. The purchase, for $175 million in preferred stock and the rest in common stock, would not dilute the company's earnings, said Ray R. Irani, Occidental's chairman."It adds profitable current production, especially in the Gulf Coast area, where we already have significant oil and gas operations," he said in a prepared statement.Occidental picked up 17 other Gulf of Mexico properties from the AGIP Petroleum Company for $195 million in a deal announced earlier this year.Occidental's purchase appears to mark one more case where Hammer interests have come out ahead of Hunt interests. In 1973, after Libya nationalized Bunker Hunt's oil properties there, Hammer agreed to give the Libyans a 51 percent stake in Occidental's Libyan operations, apparently breaking an agreement pact among oil companies.In 1980, Hammer reported a gain of $119 million by betting on a decline in silver prices while the Hunts were losing billions betting on a rise.Occidental expects to complete the purchase by the end of the year Its shares closed at $19.50 today, down 12.5 cents, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/13/business/argentina-oil-venture.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Argentina Oil Venture<date>Published: July 13, 1994</date><text>The Argentine oil company Astra Capsa said today that it had completed its $83 million buyout of the remaining 80 percent of Occidental Exploration of Argentina Inc. from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation. The acquisition makes Astra the sole owner of the La Ventana oil and gas field in Mendoza, in western Argentina.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/30/business/company-news-occidental-plans-to-cut-150-million-in-costs.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PLANS TO CUT $150 MILLION IN COSTS<date>Published: April 30, 1994</date><text>Struggling with low oil prices and a weak chemical industry, the Occidental Petroleum Corporation plans to trim its costs by another $150 million this year, its chairman, Ray Irani, said yesterday at the company's annual meeting of shareholders. He said the new savings would come from streamlining the company's organizational structure and consolidating departments. He said the latest cuts would bring the total cost reductions Occidental has achieved since restructuring began in early 1991 to $750 million a year. Mr. Irani said that while the oil company's earnings had been "very disappointing," it had made steps toward the goal of strengthening long-term prospects.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/22/business/company-news-occidental-to-buy-oil-and-gas-properties.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL TO BUY OIL AND GAS PROPERTIES<date>Published: March 22, 1994</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it would pay $195 million in cash and stock to acquire interests in 17 well-established Gulf Coast oil and gas properties from AGIP, the Italian state-owned oil company. The properties, 15 in Federal waters and 2 onshore in Texas, contain the equivalent of about 204 billion cubic feet of natural gas. Half of the $195 million will be paid in cash and half in Occidental common stock.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/01/25/business/company-news-occidental-agrees-to-sell-2-plants.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL AGREES TO SELL 2 PLANTS<date>Published: January 25, 1994</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation has agreed to divest itself of two plants as a condition for its acquisition of certain assets of Tenneco Polymers Inc., the Federal Trade Commission said yesterday. The company will shed polyvinyl chloride plants in Addis, La., and Burlington, N.J., the commission said. The New Jersey plant was acquired from Tenneco. The divestitures must be completed within a year to a purchaser suitable to the F.T.C., and Occidental cannot acquire any interest in a United States polyvinyl chloride producer within the next 10 years without F.T.C. approval.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/12/28/business/company-news-energy-regulators-reverse-claim-against-occidental.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; ENERGY REGULATORS REVERSE CLAIM AGAINST OCCIDENTAL<date>Published: December 28, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that Federal regulators had reversed a 1988 Department of Energy claim for $935 million including interest. The department had accused a company that Occidental later bought, the City Service Oil and Gas Corporation, of violating Federal price-control laws in 1979 and 1980. Occidental renamed the company Oxy USA Inc. "We are gratified that the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission has upheld our position," Ray R. Irani, the chairman and chief executive of Occidental, said in a statement. Occidental is still defending separate proceedings brought by the Department of Energy's enforcement staff in 1992, alleging that the transaction violated other regulations.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/11/17/business/turkmenistan-oil-deal.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">Turkmenistan Oil Deal<date>Published: November 17, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation won a bid to explore and develop oil deposits in western Turkmenistan, the news agency Interfax said today. Occidental, which offered the former Soviet republic a bonus of more than $20 million, was granted rights to the Burun oil deposit with estimated recoverable reserves of 260 million barrels. Burun's output could reach 6,000 barrels a day, it said. A consortium consisting of another United States company, Oil Capital, and Lapis Holding of Turkey also won rights to explore and develop the Turkmen part of the Caspian Sea shelf after offering an initial bonus of $30 million.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/20/business/company-news-occidental-s-peru-plans.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Occidental's Peru Plans<date>Published: October 20, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said today that it planned to spend $40 million to drill for crude oil in the Amazon jungle in Peru. According to an Energy and Mines Ministry official, the company is expected to recover about 12 million barrels of light crude and 18 million barrels of heavy crude mixed with light. It will inject water in the Capahuari Sur reservior in the northeast jungle, the official said. The technology, which involves horizontal drilling, has been used successfully by Occidental in other parts of the jungle.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/08/03/business/company-news-occidental-to-sell-20-stake-in-argentine-unit.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL TO SELL 20% STAKE IN ARGENTINE UNIT<date>Published: August 03, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to sell 20 percent of Occidental Exploration of Argentina Inc. to Astra Compania Argentina de Petroleo for about $24 million. In addition, Los Angeles-based Occidental said, Astra had agreed to buy for $10 million an option, exercisable in July 1994, to acquire the remaining 80 percent. Occidental Exploration of Argentina owns Occidental's Argentine oil and gas operating interests. At the end of 1992, it had 35 million barrels of proven reserves.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/04/29/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-to-buy-oil-interests-in-congo.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM TO BUY OIL INTERESTS IN CONGO<date>Published: April 29, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had reached an agreement with the Republic of the Congo to buy interests in three offshore oil parcels for $150 million. Occidental also signed an agreement with Hydro Congo, the national oil company, to help upgrade production from the fields. The purchase would give Occidental its first oil output from the Congo, in west central Africa. Occidental's take would initially be 4,000 barrels of oil a day, increasing to 20,000 barrels by 1997.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/04/16/business/company-news-occidental-petroleum-sheds-its-last-coal-company.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL PETROLEUM SHEDS ITS LAST COAL COMPANY<date>Published: April 16, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation, based in Los Angeles, announced the sale yesterday of its last coal operation, completing two years of divesting itself of noncore businesses after the death of its former chairman, Armand Hammer. Occidental classified the company, Island Creek Coal of Lexington, Ky., as a discontinued operation in January. It reduced Island Creek's value on its books by $600 million. Consol Energy, a holding company owned in part by E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, has agreed to buy Island Creek, Occidental said. Financial details were not released.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/04/06/business/company-news-ftc-orders-occidental-to-sell-two-plastics-plants.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; F.T.C. ORDERS OCCIDENTAL TO SELL TWO PLASTICS PLANTS<date>Published: April 06, 1993</date><text>The Federal Trade Commission yesterday ordered the Occidental Petroleum Corporation to sell two plastics plants it had bought from Tenneco Polymers Inc., saying the acquisition was likely to hurt competition in the United States. Occidental bought the plants from Tenneco Polymers through its Occidental Chemical Corporation unit. The F.T.C. gave Occidental a year to sell the sites. The plants in Pasadena, Tex., and Burlington, N.J., produce a resin used to make plastic products, including pipe, packaging and floor tiles.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/03/09/business/company-news-occidental-sells-stake-in-natural-gas-company.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; OCCIDENTAL SELLS STAKE IN NATURAL GAS COMPANY<date>Published: March 09, 1993</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to sell its 45 percent stake in Trident NGL Inc., a private natural gas liquids company, to Trident for $121.5 million cash. The sale would complete the exit by Occidental, based in Los Angeles, from the natural gas liquids business. Trident plans to finance the purchase by issuing $30 million of equity to a group led by Hicks, Muse &amp; Company, a private investment firm, and $105 million of subordinated notes. Occidental stock closed up 25 cents yesterday, to $20.125 a share, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/02/12/business/company-news-a-top-officer-at-occidental-to-quit-posts.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; A Top Officer At Occidental To Quit Posts<date>Published: February 12, 1993</date><text>David A. Hentschel, a director and top executive of the Occidental Petroleum Corporation's oil and gas unit, told the company's directors today that he intends to retire and quit the board, effective April 30.He will be succeeded as chief executive of Occidental Oil and Gas by David R. Martin, 61, who has been president of the subsidiary since 1983 and who is currently heading its international operations.Kurt Wulff, an oil analyst for McDep Associates, said Mr. Martin "is a first-rate oil man with a good record of finding oil outside of the U.S.; he's one of Oxy's strengths."Last year, Mr. Martin's international unit increased oil reserves above industry averages. The unit was also responsible last year for a huge natural gas discovery off the coast of Malaysia.Mr. Martin's abilities are likely to be tested further as international exploration has been cited as the company's primary vehicle for growth by Occidental's chairman, Ray Irani. Even as Occidental has frozen salaries and hiring and has cut capital spending elsewhere, the company's international unit will see its capital expense budget rise by 30 percent this year. In 1992, the oil and gas unit, based in Tulsa, Okla., accounted for a fifth of the company's revenue and a quarter of the profits.Separately, the Los Angeles-based company said it intended to cut its debt $589.5 million by redeeming notes due in 1996 that pay 10 7/8 percent interest. The company's debt ratio will drop to 55 percent from 60 percent, lower than competitors like the Phillips Petroleum Company and the Unocal Corporation, said Eugene Nowak, an oil analyst for Dean Witter.In addition, the company is expected to lower its interest expenses soon by selling about $500 million in a private, convertible preferred stock issue that will pay 7 3/4 percent.In another development, the company announced plans to seek shareholder approval to cut its board to a maximum of 14 members from 17, a move that analysts said reflected Occidental's having become a smaller, more focused enterprise since the death of its founding chairman, Armand Hammer, in 1990. The board currently has 15 members, as a result of the death last year of C. Erwin Piper, a retired Los Angeles city administrator, and the retirement of Gerald Stern, the company's lawyer. When Mr. Hentschel retires, the board will be reduced to 14.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/11/20/business/company-news-occidental-to-cut-500-jobs-and-freeze-many-salaries.html?ref=occidentalpetroleumcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; Occidental to Cut 500 Jobs And Freeze Many Salaries<date>Published: November 20, 1992</date><text>The Occidental Petroleum Corporation said today that it would cut its operating costs by about $155 million next year by dismissing 500 workers and freezing the salaries of high-paid employees. The company also intends to reduce capital spending by $150 million.The planned cuts represent a second round of cost-cutting by Occidental since 1991 and should result in a $10 million charge against earnings in the fourth quarter.Analysts said Occidental's move was based on the expectation that slow economic growth would last another eight months or so. Economic lethargy has particularly hurt the profitability of the company's petrochemical business. Analysts said the moves should permit the company to channel more money to oil and gas exploration. Robin Shoemaker, an oil industry analyst with Lehman Brothers, said the potential benefits of Occidental's cost-cutting drive could be offset by soft business conditions. "Any fundamental improvement will be late in 1993, '94 or '95," he said.The salary freeze, which is effective immediately, will remain in place through 1993 for all salaried employees earning more than $40,000 a year; about a third of the company's work force of 24,700 people will be affected. These people represent 80 percent of the company's outlay for salaries, said Ray R. Irani, the chairman and chief executive.Salaried employees who earn less than $40,000 will receive a 3 percent increase on April 1 to offset inflation, compared with previous raises of about 5 percent. Unionized workers are not affected.The company expects to save $55 million from the salary freeze. Another $100 million is expected to be saved from 500 unspecified job cuts.Occidental, based in Los Angeles, began a restructuring in 1991 that has improved net income by an estimated $350 million. The company has reduced its revenue to $10 billion, from $21 billion, mostly from the sale of its stake in IBP Inc., a beef packer, and has cut debt by $3 billion.</text></article></page></root>
