<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Raytheon Co"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/18/us/stroke-victim-is-flown-from-south-pole.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Stroke Victim Is Flown From South Pole<date>Published: October 17, 2011</date><text>Renee Nicole Doucuer, who was serving as winter manager at the Amundsen-Scott research station at the South Pole when she suffered a stroke on Aug. 27, was airlifted from the isolated base on Monday. Ms. Doucuer was resting in New Zealand on Monday. She is expected to undergo tests on Tuesday to determine the severity of her stroke, and the results will determine when she flies home to Seabrook, N.H. Ms. Doucuer, 58, had been trying to leave the South Pole since her stroke. But Raytheon, which operates the station under contract from the National Science Foundation, determined that any rescue during Antarctica’s winter would unnecessarily put other lives at risk. Ms. Doucuer and her family pressured Raytheon and the National Science Foundation to have a plane on standby should the weather improve. The flight that ultimately retrieved Ms. Doucuer was the first scheduled one of the spring season. A C-17 cargo plane, which was not intended to carry passengers, made room for Ms. Doucuer and a doctor from the station.Renee Nicole Doucuer, who was serving as winter manager at the Amundsen-Scott research station at the South Pole when she suffered a stroke on Aug. 27, was airlifted from the isolated base on Monday. Ms. Doucuer was resting in New Zealand on Monday. She is expected to undergo tests on Tuesday to determine the severity of her stroke, and the results will determine when she flies home to Seabrook, N.H. Ms. Doucuer, 58, had been trying to leave the South Pole since her stroke. But Raytheon, which operates the station under contract from the National Science Foundation, determined that any rescue during Antarctica’s winter would unnecessarily put other lives at risk. Ms. Doucuer and her family pressured Raytheon and the National Science Foundation to have a plane on standby should the weather improve. The flight that ultimately retrieved Ms. Doucuer was the first scheduled one of the spring season. A C-17 cargo plane, which was not intended to carry passengers, made room for Ms. Doucuer and a doctor from the station.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/08/science/08southpole.html?ref=raytheoncompany">South Pole Worker Stranded After Stroke<date>Published: October 7, 2011</date><text>Renee-Nicole Douceur, the winter manager at the Amundsen-Scott research station at the South Pole, was sitting at her desk on Aug. 27 when she suffered a stroke.“I looked at the screen and was like, ‘Oh my God, half the screen is missing,’ ” she said Wednesday in a telephone interview. The station’s doctors quickly determined that Ms. Douceur should be removed as soon as possible from the isolated base, which has no M.R.I. or CT scan equipment, nor medicine to treat stroke victims, she said.  But that has not happened, and the situation has pitted Ms. Douceur and her family against Raytheon Polar Services, which manages the station through a contract with the National Science Foundation. Both Raytheon and the science foundation say that it would be too dangerous to send a rescue plane to the South Pole now and that Ms. Douceur’s condition is not life-threatening. “During the winter period, extremely cold temperatures and high winds make an extraction dangerous for all involved, passengers as well as crew,” said Jon Kasle, a Raytheon spokesman, “and such an extraction is considered only in life-threatening conditions.” Ms. Douceur, 58, of Seabrook, N.H., is in stable condition but said she had partial vision loss in both eyes. She is on medical leave from her job and spends part of every day on an oxygen therapy device that helps her breathe in the high altitude, she said.  The first cargo flight of the spring is to leave Oct. 17  — weather permitting — from the South Pole for McMurdo Station, on the Antarctic coast. From there, Ms. Douceur would fly to New Zealand for medical attention.  To Ms. Douceur and Sydney Raines, her niece, that is not soon enough. Last month, Ms. Raines started a campaign to put pressure on the National Science Foundation and Raytheon.  “My question back to them is, By what standard is a stroke considered a nonemergency?” said Ms. Raines, who was raised by Ms. Douceur.  Ms. Raines has set up a Web site, Saverenee.org, and a Facebook page that urge people to call officials at Raytheon and the National Science Foundation. A petition at Whitehouse.gov has more than 700 signatures. Ms. Raines has enlisted the help of Senator Jeanne Shaheen, Democrat of New Hampshire, who wrote to the foundation. “They’re saying the risk is too high,” said Ms. Douceur, who has worked at the South Pole on and off for three years. “But why aren’t you mobilizing and prepositioning planes so that when the weather breaks, you can come get me, instead of just saying, ‘No, you’re O.K., you’re going to wait’? It feels like they’re just stonewalling.” Treating a stroke victim without access to imaging technology is difficult, said Dr. Walter J. Koroshetz, deputy director at the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, because it is impossible to be sure what kind of stroke occurred. “If it’s a blockage of the blood vessel, the damage is done,” he said. But if the problem is a hemorrhaging vessel, more damage could still occur, “because that blood vessel is feeding brain that’s undamaged yet.” The most famous instance of a person being airlifted from the South Pole for medical reasons was that involving Jerri Nielsen FitzGerald, a doctor who treated herself for breast cancer for months while stationed at the American research station. When she departed, on Oct. 16, 1999, it was the earliest in the Antarctic spring that a plane had taken off, according to The Antarctic Sun, a newspaper put out by the United States Antarctic Program, which is run by the National Science Foundation. She died in 2009 of a recurrence of breast cancer. Temperatures must be higher than minus 50 degrees Fahrenheit for most planes to land at Amundsen-Scott or the fuel will turn to jelly. While that threshold has been crossed at the South Pole recently,  the temperature still regularly dips to 70 degrees below zero. “A risky rescue flight might not only jeopardize the health and safety of the patient but that of the flight crew and personnel on the ground at South Pole as well,” said Deborah Wing, a spokeswoman for the National Science Foundation. Ms. Douceur and Raytheon are also tussling over whether a medical attendant should be on the Oct. 17 flight. She says she is worried about the effects of flying on her already oxygen-deprived brain and wants a medical professional on board. Raytheon has offered to send an unspecified “attendant,” she said. The company declined to comment. Flying into Amundsen-Scott during the Antarctic winter, which runs from mid-February until late October, is indeed dangerous, said Col. Ronnie Smith, a former Air Force navigator who has flown there about 300 times.  “It’s like no other airfield in the U.S.,” Colonel Smith said. A pilot landing a plane there in winter, when it is dark 24 hours a day, would be flying blind “because you can’t install lights under the ice,” he said. “You need low wind conditions, because even a 15-mile-per-hour wind will blow the loose snow around 100 or 200 feet up in the air,” Colonel Smith said.Renee-Nicole Douceur, the winter manager at the Amundsen-Scott research station at the South Pole, was sitting at her desk on Aug. 27 when she suffered a stroke.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/09/business/some-companies-want-gays-to-wed-to-get-health-benefits.html?ref=raytheoncompany">As Same-Sex Marriage Becomes Legal, Some Choices May Be Lost<date>Published: July 8, 2011</date><text>Now that same-sex marriage has been legalized in New York, at least a few large companies are requiring their employees to tie the knot if they want their partners to qualify for health insurance.Corning, I.B.M. and Raytheon all provide domestic partner benefits to employees with same-sex partners in states where they cannot marry. But now that they can legally wed in New York, five other states and the District of Columbia, they will be required to do so if they want their partner to be covered for a routine checkup or a root canal. On the surface, this appears to put the couples on an even footing with heterosexual married couples. After all, this is precisely what they have been fighting for: being treated as a spouse. But some gay and lesbian advocates are arguing that the change may have come too soon: some couples may face complications, since their unions are not recognized by the federal government. “Even with the complications, many people will want to get married for the reasons people want to get married,” said Ross D. Levi, executive director of the Empire State Pride Agenda. “But from our perspective, to hinge something as important as insurance for your family to what is still a complicated legal matter for same-sex couples doesn’t seem to be a fair thing to do.” He said that there were a variety of reasons — legal, financial and personal — that companies should keep the domestic partnership option at least until gay marriage was recognized at the federal level. Legally speaking, getting married could create immigration issues or it could potentially muddy the process of adopting a child. In some instances, he added, an employee may work in a gay marriage state but live in a neighboring state that does not recognize the marriage. The couple may want to wait to marry until they can be legally wed in their home state. “There are certainly reasons why a couple may not wish to marry,” added Camilla Taylor, marriage project director at Lambda Legal. “People with certain immigration statuses might want to think very carefully before getting married. There are some types of visas that are meant to be temporary, and if you get married to someone who is a citizen, it could flag your renewal application and reflect your more permanent decision to stay.” When it comes to adopting a child, couples may run into trouble if they are trying to adopt from a place that restricts same-sex married couples from adopting. Having one parent adopt while still single may be easier. “If you want to be able to answer honestly in paperwork, multiple interviews and background checks, then you won’t want to get married,” Ms. Taylor said, adding that many foreign countries ban adoptions to same-sex couples. Marrying could also have serious implications for couples who relocate to a nonmarriage state, and ultimately decide to split up. Getting a divorce can be complicated, since one member of a couple may have to return to the gay marriage state and live there before their split can be completed. The employers making the changes said they spoke regularly with their gay and lesbian employee groups and planned to phase in the requirement. Corning, based in Corning, N.Y., said it would offer a reasonable grace period, though it had not completed the details. “After waiting so much time for that right, we want them to have the opportunity to enjoy that,” said Christy Pambianchi, a senior vice president for human resources at Corning, which put the policy into effect in New Hampshire and Massachusetts when gay marriage became legal there. She said employees did not raise concerns about the requirement. “They are delighted,” she said. Raytheon, based in Waltham, Mass. — another state where gay marriage is legal — said it would give employees several months to comply with its marriage requirement. Like Corning and I.B.M., the company said domestic partner benefits would remain in states where couples cannot marry (Raytheon also has an exemption for active members of the military, so they are covered for benefits without having to marry. Getting married violates the “don’t ask, don’t tell” policy, which is being phased out). I.B.M., based in Armonk, N.Y., said its workers would have up to a year to get married to maintain their current benefits. At least for now, these companies seem to be in the minority, though it is unclear whether more employers will follow their lead. Eastman Kodak, based in Rochester, said it would continue to offer domestic partner coverage to both same-sex and opposite-sex partners. “My impression is that there has been lots of discussion about dropping domestic partner coverage when marriage is first opened up to same-sex couples, but very few employers actually end up taking this step,” said Jennifer C. Pizer, legal director at the Williams Institute, which studies sexual orientation law and policy issues. “Some employers initially believe that it is fairer of them to impose the same marriage requirements on all employees, regardless of sexual orientation. But then employees and others explain that employees with a same-sex life partner remain in difficult circumstances due to the continuing federal discrimination.” Whether same-sex couples marry, they will still be responsible for paying federal income taxes on the value of their partner or spouse’s benefits since they are not recognized by the federal government as an economic unit, unless the person covered is considered a dependent. Couples will not owe those taxes at the state level in places like New York that recognize gay marriage. But it should become easier for gay employees who marry and live in New York to obtain insurance for their spouses. (There are an estimated 42,000 same-sex couples in New York, according to the Williams Institute.) Not only are the same-sex spouses of state workers eligible for spousal coverage, but the same goes for many people who work for private employers. There could be some exceptions, however. Employers who do not contract with an insurance company but instead pay for health benefits out of their own assets — so-called self-insured plans — are not subject to the state’s insurance laws but are governed by federal law. Most large employers have self-insured plans, said Helen Darling, president of the National Business Group on Health, a membership organization that focuses on health policies for large employers. That means they can choose to cover same-sex employees, but they do not have to. While virtually all large company plans cover legal spouses, she added, some companies offer domestic partner benefits only to gay employees who do not have the option to marry. (Some companies also extend the benefits to heterosexual unmarried couples.) “I am getting a lot of questions about what other employers are doing,” Ms. Darling said. “I see a movement coming where marriage will be a factor where marriage is possible.”Now that same-sex marriage has been legalized in New York, at least a few large companies are requiring their employees to tie the knot if they want their partners to qualify for health insurance.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/12/business/12nocera.html?ref=raytheoncompany">From the Pentagon, a Buy Rating on Contractors - Talking Business<date>Published: February 11, 2011</date><text>At the Cowen &amp; Company military industry investment conference on Wednesday, the breakfast speaker was a man named Ashton B. Carter. A former academic and industry consultant, Dr. Carter, as he likes to call himself — he has a doctorate in theoretical physics, in case you were wondering — is the Defense Department’s under secretary for acquisitions, technology and logistics. That is, he’s the Pentagon’s chief weapons buyer.Cowen is a small firm, but its military analyst, Cai von Rumohr, has been on the beat for more than 40 years. Companies tend not to turn him down when he invites them to his conference. W. James McNerney Jr., the chief executive of Boeing, would be making a presentation later in the day, as would executives from Northrop-Grumman and other contractors. Big institutional investors like T. Rowe Price were out in force. As was the Defense Department. In addition to Mr. Carter, a top Naval official was scheduled to present the next afternoon. If you’re wondering what high-ranking Pentagon officials were doing at an investment conference, well, suffice to say that this was not a question on the minds of the people in this room. They’ve gotten used to it. For the last few months, beginning with a secret meeting last October, Defense Department officials have been making the rounds of analysts and investors. Their main message, to put it bluntly, is that even in an era of tighter budgets, the Pentagon is going to make sure the military industry remains profitable. “Taxpayers and shareholders are aligned,” Mr. Carter intoned on Wednesday. Then he laid out a series of reforms that he said would both increase competition and maintain, as he put it, “profitability over the long term” — a phrase he repeated for emphasis. He told the assemblage that the Pentagon would frown on mergers among the five giant military contractors — the so-called primes: Lockheed Martin, General Dynamics, Raytheon, Northrop-Grumman and Boeing. However, he added, the Defense Department was going to encourage mergers among smaller military contractors. And, he said, “we will be attentive” to innovative smaller companies that provide services (as opposed to weapons systems) to the Pentagon. If you were an investor in the military industry, would you find this useful information? You bet — this is the stuff that can move markets. Although Mr. Carter made several references to “market forces,” the only market for the military industry is the government, which spends some $400 billion a year on weapons systems and other purchases. In economic terms, the Pentagon is a “ monopsony,” a single buyer with life-or-death power over its vendors. If the Pentagon wants the military industry to be healthy and profitable, it can pretty much ensure that outcome. Not being an industry insider, however, I found myself a little taken aback by Mr. Carter’s “guidance.” Monopsony or not, why should the Pentagon be talking up the stocks, even implicitly, of the companies it buys from? Why was Mr. Carter going out of his way to talk to investors and analysts? Didn’t he have more important things to do? The answer, I eventually learned, has to do with something that happened a very long time ago, and goes under the category of “Be careful what you wish for.” Let’s just say that banking isn’t the only industry where the government has allowed a handful of companies to become too big to fail.  The year was 1993. Bill Clinton was the new president, and Les Aspin was his defense secretary. As recounted later by Norman R. Augustine, then the chief executive of Martin Marietta, Mr. Aspin called together about 15 C.E.O.’s of the prime military contractors for a dinner at the Pentagon. Mr. Augustine would memorably label this dinner the Last Supper. Mr. Aspin and several other high-ranking Pentagon officials (including Mr. Carter, who was then an assistant secretary of defense) had brought the group together to send a tough message. With the Berlin Wall gone, the Soviet Union dissolved — and the Pentagon budget flat-lining — the Defense Department was no longer willing, as Mr. Augustine later recounted, “to pay the ballooning overhead” of all those contractors. In no uncertain terms, Mr. Aspin told the group that they needed to start merging. “The rest is history,” Mr. Augustine later wrote. “General Electric Aerospace merged with Martin Marietta, which combined with Lockheed. McDonnell Douglas joined Boeing. Grumman joined Northrop. When the dust had cleared, there were only a few firms left standing.” Five, to be exact. The Last Supper has become part of the lore of the military industry — though partly that’s because Mr. Aspin’s prediction about tighter Pentagon budgets turned out to be so wrong. “On the day George W. Bush took office,” said Loren B. Thompson, a well-known military consultant, “defense spending was around $300 billion.” Today it is more than double that amount, around $700 billion. The wars in Iraq and Afghanistan — not to mention the Pentagon’s voracious appetite for expensive weapons systems, and the lack of competition among the remaining contractors — have been a gold mine for the Big Five. Not surprisingly, for most of the first decade of the 21st century, the stocks of these companies soared. But after peaking in 2008, they came crashing back to earth. Which, for the Pentagon, has turned out to be a problem. These companies need access to the capital markets, which is more difficult when their stocks are down. And the Pentagon simply can’t allow them get into serious financial difficulty; there are just too few of them. “What we can’t afford from the defense perspective is a sick industry,” said Jacques S. Gansler, a former procurement official for the Pentagon who teaches at the University of Maryland. 1 2 Next Page »At the Cowen &amp; Company military industry investment conference on Wednesday, the breakfast speaker was a man named Ashton B. Carter. A former academic and industry consultant, Dr. Carter, as he likes to call himself — he has a doctorate in theoretical physics, in case you were wondering — is the Defense Department’s under secretary for acquisitions, technology and logistics. That is, he’s the Pentagon’s chief weapons buyer.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/24/opinion/24wed3.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Fixing Missile Defense<date>Published: March 23, 2010</date><text>It is always encouraging to see a commitment to the Sisyphean task of getting the most out of America’s gargantuan defense budget and reining in costs on expensive, badly managed or poorly performing programs. The Obama team killed the anachronistic F-22 combat jet and is cracking down on the way overbudget F-35 Joint Strike Fighter. Now it is looking at the long-troubled missile defense program. Lt. Gen. Patrick O’Reilly, the program’s chief, told a conference on Monday that some contractors continue to produce poor quality components for missile interceptors. That is not a good deal for American taxpayers, especially when there are huge and growing demands on the national budget. The missile defense agency is asking for a budget increase of $700 million, to $9.9 billion. General O’Reilly said he is withholding a portion of the profits from contractors responsible for the shoddy work. He neither identified the firms nor revealed the amount of the contract set aside, apparently because his decision is now subject to appeal. The Boeing Company, the Raytheon Company and the Lockheed Martin Corporation are the primary contractors for many weapons programs. In 2006, the Pentagon withheld some $108 million from Boeing because of shortcomings on a ground-based missile intercept. Penalizing contractors is sensible because profits are a strong motivator. But the penalty must be carefully structured so it does not boomerang. If contractors know profits will be reduced if a missile test is unsuccessful, experts say this could create a strong incentive for them to ensure the tests are (falsely) successful by conducting more scripted, less realistic tests. The Pentagon also needs to structure contracts more effectively. The Government Accountability Office said in 2009 that defense contractors typically get up to 84 percent of their promised profits just for “satisfactory” performance. That leaves only a small incentive for contractors to perform above-satisfactory work. General O’Reilly has urged defense companies to fire employees who fail to accept the need for more quality control. A hiring is also in order. To ensure the strongest team to address the program’s deficiencies, the Senate needs to overcome conservative opposition and confirm Philip Coyle, a leading advocate of reforming missile defense, as a White House science adviser. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on March 24, 2010, on page A26 of the New York edition.It is always encouraging to see a commitment to the Sisyphean task of getting the most out of America’s gargantuan defense budget and reining in costs on expensive, badly managed or poorly performing programs. The Obama team killed the anachronistic F-22 combat jet and is cracking down on the way overbudget F-35 Joint Strike Fighter. Now it is looking at the long-troubled missile defense program. Lt. Gen. Patrick O’Reilly, the program’s chief, told a conference on Monday that some contractors continue to produce poor quality components for missile interceptors. That is not a good deal for American taxpayers, especially when there are huge and growing demands on the national budget. The missile defense agency is asking for a budget increase of $700 million, to $9.9 billion. General O’Reilly said he is withholding a portion of the profits from contractors responsible for the shoddy work. He neither identified the firms nor revealed the amount of the contract set aside, apparently because his decision is now subject to appeal. The Boeing Company, the Raytheon Company and the Lockheed Martin Corporation are the primary contractors for many weapons programs. In 2006, the Pentagon withheld some $108 million from Boeing because of shortcomings on a ground-based missile intercept. Penalizing contractors is sensible because profits are a strong motivator. But the penalty must be carefully structured so it does not boomerang. If contractors know profits will be reduced if a missile test is unsuccessful, experts say this could create a strong incentive for them to ensure the tests are (falsely) successful by conducting more scripted, less realistic tests. The Pentagon also needs to structure contracts more effectively. The Government Accountability Office said in 2009 that defense contractors typically get up to 84 percent of their promised profits just for “satisfactory” performance. That leaves only a small incentive for contractors to perform above-satisfactory work. General O’Reilly has urged defense companies to fire employees who fail to accept the need for more quality control. A hiring is also in order. To ensure the strongest team to address the program’s deficiencies, the Senate needs to overcome conservative opposition and confirm Philip Coyle, a leading advocate of reforming missile defense, as a White House science adviser.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2DA1E38F932A15751C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">BITS; IPhone App For Battlefields<date>Published: December 21, 2009</date><text>Raytheon, the military contractor, announced an iPhone application that tracks soldiers -- friend and foe -- on the battlefield. Called the One Force Tracker, the Raytheon iPhone software can also be used by the police, firefighters and emergency medical technicians. The app works on a standard iPhone, said J Smart, chief technology officer for Raytheon's Intelligence and Information Systems. ''We are really delighted to be leveraging Apple's innovation,'' he said. The adaptation of the iPhone to military use is somewhat unusual, as technology more often trickles from the military to the consumer market. But this is a rare case of consumer hardware and software concepts being adapted for military use. For instance, crowdsourcing, in which volunteers use cellphones to report real-time traffic flow, could turn each soldier into a reporting unit, delivering real-time data about position and status. Live information could reduce tactical errors and friendly fire episodes. Maps with an overlay of points of interest are familiar to every GPS device user. The Raytheon app would use the same concept, but points of interest might be known sniper sites or safe fallback positions. Although the application that Raytheon has developed will work with an off-the-shelf iPhone, the company concedes the need for alterations for the battlefield. Because the iPhone doesn't have a replaceable battery, a fresh one can't be popped in when power gets low. Mr. Smart said Raytheon may add a stronger phone case that would accommodate a larger battery. ROY FURCHGOTT COMMENTWhat about the fact that I can't even make a call from the corner of 16th Street and 5th Avenue without getting my call dropped? I'd want a bit more reliability if I were a firefighter. brian b, Dec. 16 PHOTO</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/31/us/31cyber.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Contractors Vie for Plum Work, Hacking for U.S.<date>Published: May 30, 2009</date><text>MELBOURNE, Fla.  The government’s urgent push into cyberwarfare has set off a rush among the biggest military companies for billions of dollars in new defense contracts. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Gregg Matthews for The New York Times Terry Gillette, left, and Scott Chase run a Raytheon unit that finds flaws in Pentagon computers. Cyberwar The Digital Arms Race Computers, indispensable in peace, are becoming ever more important in political conflicts and open warfare. This series examines the growing use of computer power as a weapon. Previous Articles in the Series » Fending Off Attacks in Cyberspace What can the White House do to prepare for and fight cyberwars? Join the Discussion » The exotic nature of the work, coupled with the deep recession, is enabling the companies to attract top young talent that once would have gone to Silicon Valley. And the race to develop weapons that defend against, or initiate, computer attacks has given rise to thousands of “hacker soldiers” within the Pentagon who can blend the new capabilities into the nation’s war planning. Nearly all of the largest military companies  including Northrop Grumman, General Dynamics, Lockheed Martin and Raytheon  have major cyber contracts with the military and intelligence agencies. The companies have been moving quickly to lock up the relatively small number of experts with the training and creativity to block the attacks and design countermeasures. They have been buying smaller firms, financing academic research and running advertisements for “cyberninjas” at a time when other industries are shedding workers. The changes are manifesting themselves in highly classified laboratories, where computer geeks in their 20s like to joke that they are hackers with security clearances. At a Raytheon facility here south of the Kennedy Space Center, a hub of innovation in an earlier era, rock music blares and empty cans of Mountain Dew pile up as engineers create tools to protect the Pentagon’s computers and crack into the networks of countries that could become adversaries. Prizes like cappuccino machines and stacks of cash spur them on, and a gong heralds each major breakthrough. The young engineers represent the new face of a war that President Obama described Friday as “one of the most serious economic and national security challenges we face as a nation.” The president said he would appoint a senior White House official to oversee the nation’s cybersecurity strategies. Computer experts say the government is behind the curve in sealing off its networks from threats that are growing more persistent and sophisticated, with thousands of intrusions each day from organized criminals and legions of hackers for nations including Russia and China. “Everybody’s attacking everybody,” said Scott Chase, a 30-year-old computer engineer who helps run the Raytheon unit here. Mr. Chase, who wears his hair in a ponytail, and Terry Gillette, a 53-year-old former rocket engineer, ran SI Government Solutions before selling the company to Raytheon last year as the boom in the military’s cyberoperations accelerated. The operation  tucked into several unmarked buildings behind an insurance office and a dentist’s office  is doing some of the most cutting-edge work, both in identifying weaknesses in Pentagon networks and in creating weapons for potential attacks. Daniel D. Allen, who oversees work on intelligence systems for Northrop Grumman, estimated that federal spending on computer security now totals $10 billion each year, including classified programs. That is just a fraction of the government’s spending on weapons systems. But industry officials expect it to rise rapidly. The military contractors are now in the enviable position of turning what they learned out of necessity  protecting the sensitive Pentagon data that sits on their own computers  into a lucrative business that could replace some of the revenue lost from cancellations of conventional weapons systems. Executives at Lockheed Martin, which has long been the government’s largest information-technology contractor, also see the demand for greater computer security spreading to energy and health care agencies and the rest of the nation’s critical infrastructure. But for now, most companies remain focused on the national-security arena, where the hottest efforts involve anticipating how an enemy might attack and developing the resources to strike back. Though even the existence of research on cyberweapons was once highly classified, the Air Force plans this year to award the first publicly announced contract for developing tools to break into enemy computers. The companies are also teaming up to build a National Cyber Range, a model of the Internet for testing advanced techniques. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in US » A version of this article appeared in print on May 31, 2009, on page A1 of the New York edition.MELBOURNE, Fla.  The government’s urgent push into cyberwarfare has set off a rush among the biggest military companies for billions of dollars in new defense contracts. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Gregg Matthews for The New York Times Terry Gillette, left, and Scott Chase run a Raytheon unit that finds flaws in Pentagon computers. Cyberwar The Digital Arms Race Computers, indispensable in peace, are becoming ever more important in political conflicts and open warfare. This series examines the growing use of computer power as a weapon. Previous Articles in the Series » Fending Off Attacks in Cyberspace What can the White House do to prepare for and fight cyberwars? Join the Discussion » The exotic nature of the work, coupled with the deep recession, is enabling the companies to attract top young talent that once would have gone to Silicon Valley. And the race to develop weapons that defend against, or initiate, computer attacks has given rise to thousands of “hacker soldiers” within the Pentagon who can blend the new capabilities into the nation’s war planning. Nearly all of the largest military companies  including Northrop Grumman, General Dynamics, Lockheed Martin and Raytheon  have major cyber contracts with the military and intelligence agencies. The companies have been moving quickly to lock up the relatively small number of experts with the training and creativity to block the attacks and design countermeasures. They have been buying smaller firms, financing academic research and running advertisements for “cyberninjas” at a time when other industries are shedding workers. The changes are manifesting themselves in highly classified laboratories, where computer geeks in their 20s like to joke that they are hackers with security clearances. At a Raytheon facility here south of the Kennedy Space Center, a hub of innovation in an earlier era, rock music blares and empty cans of Mountain Dew pile up as engineers create tools to protect the Pentagon’s computers and crack into the networks of countries that could become adversaries. Prizes like cappuccino machines and stacks of cash spur them on, and a gong heralds each major breakthrough. The young engineers represent the new face of a war that President Obama described Friday as “one of the most serious economic and national security challenges we face as a nation.” The president said he would appoint a senior White House official to oversee the nation’s cybersecurity strategies. Computer experts say the government is behind the curve in sealing off its networks from threats that are growing more persistent and sophisticated, with thousands of intrusions each day from organized criminals and legions of hackers for nations including Russia and China. “Everybody’s attacking everybody,” said Scott Chase, a 30-year-old computer engineer who helps run the Raytheon unit here. Mr. Chase, who wears his hair in a ponytail, and Terry Gillette, a 53-year-old former rocket engineer, ran SI Government Solutions before selling the company to Raytheon last year as the boom in the military’s cyberoperations accelerated. The operation  tucked into several unmarked buildings behind an insurance office and a dentist’s office  is doing some of the most cutting-edge work, both in identifying weaknesses in Pentagon networks and in creating weapons for potential attacks. Daniel D. Allen, who oversees work on intelligence systems for Northrop Grumman, estimated that federal spending on computer security now totals $10 billion each year, including classified programs. That is just a fraction of the government’s spending on weapons systems. But industry officials expect it to rise rapidly. The military contractors are now in the enviable position of turning what they learned out of necessity  protecting the sensitive Pentagon data that sits on their own computers  into a lucrative business that could replace some of the revenue lost from cancellations of conventional weapons systems. Executives at Lockheed Martin, which has long been the government’s largest information-technology contractor, also see the demand for greater computer security spreading to energy and health care agencies and the rest of the nation’s critical infrastructure. But for now, most companies remain focused on the national-security arena, where the hottest efforts involve anticipating how an enemy might attack and developing the resources to strike back. Though even the existence of research on cyberweapons was once highly classified, the Air Force plans this year to award the first publicly announced contract for developing tools to break into enemy computers. The companies are also teaming up to build a National Cyber Range, a model of the Internet for testing advanced techniques. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/23/opinion/23thu3.html?ref=raytheoncompany">The Good Lobbyist<date>Published: April 22, 2009</date><text>It’s a cliché for a candidate to denounce the power of Washington insiders and the corruption of lobbyists’ wealth. So it was refreshing to see President Obama deliver on his campaign stand and refuse to hire registered lobbyists for jobs in their areas of special advocacy. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Lobbying and Lobbyists There also can be too much of a good thing. We think the White House is being overly rigid with its decision not to nominate Tom Malinowski, the Washington advocacy director for Human Rights Watch, to be the administration’s global human rights chief. By any fair judgment, Mr. Malinowski is ideally qualified, having worked ardently across the world  both outside government and in  on the gamut of rights issues, from torture to genocide. He is the antithesis of the deep-pocketed, back-slapping K Street insiders who gave the lobbying profession a black eye across the Capitol reign of Tom DeLay. White House officials agree on Mr. Malinowski’s virtues but nevertheless are making a show of insisting there must be no double standard for him as a registered lobbyist. What makes it especially puzzling is the Obama policy does allow for an occasional waiver. The president issued one for William Lynn, a lobbyist for the powerful defense contractor Raytheon who was his indispensable choice to be deputy secretary of defense. The White House said then that while Mr. Obama favored strict ethical rules, he also believed “any standard is not perfect,” and “a waiver process that allows people to serve their country is necessary.” The administration won its case for Mr. Lynn in Senate hearings. Mr. Malinowski should be nominated and given the same chance to argue that he is committed to promoting American values and serving the interests of all of the American people. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on April 23, 2009, on page A26 of the New York edition.It’s a cliché for a candidate to denounce the power of Washington insiders and the corruption of lobbyists’ wealth. So it was refreshing to see President Obama deliver on his campaign stand and refuse to hire registered lobbyists for jobs in their areas of special advocacy. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Lobbying and Lobbyists There also can be too much of a good thing. We think the White House is being overly rigid with its decision not to nominate Tom Malinowski, the Washington advocacy director for Human Rights Watch, to be the administration’s global human rights chief. By any fair judgment, Mr. Malinowski is ideally qualified, having worked ardently across the world  both outside government and in  on the gamut of rights issues, from torture to genocide. He is the antithesis of the deep-pocketed, back-slapping K Street insiders who gave the lobbying profession a black eye across the Capitol reign of Tom DeLay. White House officials agree on Mr. Malinowski’s virtues but nevertheless are making a show of insisting there must be no double standard for him as a registered lobbyist. What makes it especially puzzling is the Obama policy does allow for an occasional waiver. The president issued one for William Lynn, a lobbyist for the powerful defense contractor Raytheon who was his indispensable choice to be deputy secretary of defense. The White House said then that while Mr. Obama favored strict ethical rules, he also believed “any standard is not perfect,” and “a waiver process that allows people to serve their country is necessary.” The administration won its case for Mr. Lynn in Senate hearings. Mr. Malinowski should be nominated and given the same chance to argue that he is committed to promoting American values and serving the interests of all of the American people.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/23/opinion/23fri1.html?ref=raytheoncompany">The President Orders Transparency<date>Published: January 22, 2009</date><text>President Obama wasted no time in moving to roll back the Bush administration’s disgraceful strictures on open government. Skip to next paragraph The Board Blog Additional commentary, background information and other items by Times editorial writers. Go to The Board » In a welcome series of orders, Mr. Obama directed federal agencies to err on the side of transparency, not the Bush-era default of secrecy and delay, in releasing records to the public. He also undid the executive order signed by President George Bush that lets past presidents and vice presidents sit indefinitely on potentially embarrassing records that belong in the public domain. And Mr. Obama issued some of the toughest limitations yet on the power of lobbyists to influence government from within. Under the new rules, anyone who leaves the Obama administration will be barred from lobbying the executive branch for the remainder of Mr. Obama’s time in office, rather than the yearlong ban Mr. Bush employed. In addition, no one may serve in the Obama administration if he or she lobbied an executive agency in the preceding two years. The new president’s actions provided a burst of executive sunshine that Washington badly needs. Unfortunately, Mr. Obama already wants to make an exception for William Lynn, a former lobbyist for the defense contractor Raytheon, to become deputy secretary of defense. Mr. Lynn, a respected Pentagon official in the Clinton administration, has the right résumé  except that he was a lobbyist until last year. This clearly violates the mint-new standard, especially since the Pentagon job is so wide-ranging that recusal on specific issues is impossible. The White House is hoping for Senate approval nevertheless, arguing that while the president sought the firmest ethics rules, he also believes that “any standard is not perfect,” that “a waiver process that allows people to serve their country is necessary.” Maybe the Senate will concur that Mr. Lynn is “uniquely qualified” and a waiver is justified. But this is not an ideal first test of Mr. Obama’s exemplary rules. Voters who heeded the president’s campaign message of openness must demand any exceptions to be few and far between. This is particularly true for Mr. Obama’s order reversing a memo from Mr. Bush’s Department of Justice that hobbled agencies in fulfilling the Freedom of Information Act’s promise of accountability. A healthy democracy needs to know what is going on in its government. Small wonder historians instantly hailed Mr. Obama’s reversal of Mr. Bush’s order, which gave veto power to past presidents, vice presidents and their heirs over which executive archives are made public. President Obama’s new orders go well beyond the standards of his predecessors, particularly in shutting, not slowing, the revolving-door path from well-connected government veteran to high-salaried corporate lobbyist. The promise of transparency is heartening (though the Obama White House’s initial opening day action in crimping photographers’ traditional access to ceremonies was not). The president has vowed “a clean break from business as usual,” with transparency at the core. The nation welcomes this promise and will be tracking its fulfillment. More Articles in Opinion » A version of this article appeared in print on January 23, 2009, on page A22 of the New York edition.President Obama wasted no time in moving to roll back the Bush administration’s disgraceful strictures on open government. Skip to next paragraph The Board Blog Additional commentary, background information and other items by Times editorial writers. Go to The Board » In a welcome series of orders, Mr. Obama directed federal agencies to err on the side of transparency, not the Bush-era default of secrecy and delay, in releasing records to the public. He also undid the executive order signed by President George Bush that lets past presidents and vice presidents sit indefinitely on potentially embarrassing records that belong in the public domain. And Mr. Obama issued some of the toughest limitations yet on the power of lobbyists to influence government from within. Under the new rules, anyone who leaves the Obama administration will be barred from lobbying the executive branch for the remainder of Mr. Obama’s time in office, rather than the yearlong ban Mr. Bush employed. In addition, no one may serve in the Obama administration if he or she lobbied an executive agency in the preceding two years. The new president’s actions provided a burst of executive sunshine that Washington badly needs. Unfortunately, Mr. Obama already wants to make an exception for William Lynn, a former lobbyist for the defense contractor Raytheon, to become deputy secretary of defense. Mr. Lynn, a respected Pentagon official in the Clinton administration, has the right résumé  except that he was a lobbyist until last year. This clearly violates the mint-new standard, especially since the Pentagon job is so wide-ranging that recusal on specific issues is impossible. The White House is hoping for Senate approval nevertheless, arguing that while the president sought the firmest ethics rules, he also believes that “any standard is not perfect,” that “a waiver process that allows people to serve their country is necessary.” Maybe the Senate will concur that Mr. Lynn is “uniquely qualified” and a waiver is justified. But this is not an ideal first test of Mr. Obama’s exemplary rules. Voters who heeded the president’s campaign message of openness must demand any exceptions to be few and far between. This is particularly true for Mr. Obama’s order reversing a memo from Mr. Bush’s Department of Justice that hobbled agencies in fulfilling the Freedom of Information Act’s promise of accountability. A healthy democracy needs to know what is going on in its government. Small wonder historians instantly hailed Mr. Obama’s reversal of Mr. Bush’s order, which gave veto power to past presidents, vice presidents and their heirs over which executive archives are made public. President Obama’s new orders go well beyond the standards of his predecessors, particularly in shutting, not slowing, the revolving-door path from well-connected government veteran to high-salaried corporate lobbyist. The promise of transparency is heartening (though the Obama White House’s initial opening day action in crimping photographers’ traditional access to ceremonies was not). The president has vowed “a clean break from business as usual,” with transparency at the core. The nation welcomes this promise and will be tracking its fulfillment.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/25/business/25arms.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Missile Sales Help Profit at Raytheon<date>Published: July 25, 2008</date><text>The military contractor Raytheon said Thursday that lower pension expenses and higher missile sales raised second-quarter income from continuing operations 20 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Raytheon Co Go to your Portfolio » The company, based in Waltham, Mass., said it earned $426 million, or $1 a share, in the quarter, down from $1.33 billion, or $2.97 a share, in the year-earlier period. The 2007 second-quarter results were helped by $980 million from the sale of Raytheon’s aircraft division. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial had expected 94 cents a share this year in quarterly earnings from continuing operations. Raytheon also raised its outlook for 2008 by 15 cents, to $3.80 to $3.95 a share, on sales of $22.6 billion to $23.1 billion. Sales rose 11 percent, to $5.9 billion, helped by missiles and laser-guided bombs. More Articles in Business »The military contractor Raytheon said Thursday that lower pension expenses and higher missile sales raised second-quarter income from continuing operations 20 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Raytheon Co Go to your Portfolio » The company, based in Waltham, Mass., said it earned $426 million, or $1 a share, in the quarter, down from $1.33 billion, or $2.97 a share, in the year-earlier period. The 2007 second-quarter results were helped by $980 million from the sale of Raytheon’s aircraft division. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial had expected 94 cents a share this year in quarterly earnings from continuing operations. Raytheon also raised its outlook for 2008 by 15 cents, to $3.80 to $3.95 a share, on sales of $22.6 billion to $23.1 billion. Sales rose 11 percent, to $5.9 billion, helped by missiles and laser-guided bombs.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/18/us/politics/18fence.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Giuliani Had Ties to Company Trying to Sell Border Technology<date>Published: January 18, 2008</date><text>On the presidential campaign trail, former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani often promotes the installation of electronic monitoring devices at the border to stem illegal immigration, without mentioning that until a few months ago, he was partner in a company trying to market such technology. Skip to next paragraph Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Candidate Topic Pages More Politics News Mr. Giuliani and his consulting company were part owners of SkyWatch L.L.C., a closely held start-up company that says it has developed a sensor capable of monitoring illegal border crossings. SkyWatch, in collaboration with Raytheon, a large military contractor, is now looking to market the technology to the federal government and elsewhere. Mr. Giuliani’s company, Giuliani Partners, was invited to join the venture more than two years ago by Abdol Moabery, then the chief executive of SkyWatch’s parent company, who went on to help the Giuliani campaign raise money in Florida. As part of its work, an executive of Mr. Giuliani’s company met several times with development teams at Raytheon. But the financial relationship ended in September when Giuliani Partners gave up its ownership stake in SkyWatch without compensation. For nearly a year, Mr. Giuliani has extolled the benefits of a technological approach to border security. Among his efforts has been a radio advertisement, which went on the air in August, called “Fence,” in which he spoke of the need for a “technological fence” at the border. “You stop illegal immigration by building a fence, a physical fence and then a technological fence,” Mr. Giuliani said in the ad. “You then hire enough border patrol so they can respond in a timely way.” But neither in the ad, nor in other campaign settings where the issue has come up, has Mr. Giuliani mentioned his involvement with a company developing this technological fence. No one has suggested that Mr. Giuliani adopted his position because of his relationship with SkyWatch. He has continued to promote the concept since his relationship with the company ended, including during recent campaign discussions. A spokeswoman for his campaign said Mr. Giuliani’s longstanding support for a technological fence was not related to his involvement with SkyWatch. “It’s one part of Rudy’s comprehensive plan to end illegal immigration because it makes sense and is good policy,” the spokeswoman, Maria Comella, said. Last month, SkyWatch and Raytheon announced that the sensor, capable of monitoring more than 400 square miles from atop a tower, was available for sale. Industry analysts say the technology has a lucrative future, including a possible role in a multibillion-dollar federal program to help secure the nation’s borders. Gary Reese, the manager of SkyWatch, said the company ended its involvement with Giuliani Partners when it became clear the consulting company could not meet its contractual obligations. He said Giuliani Partners had essentially bartered for a 12.5 percent share of SkyWatch by committing to develop business and marketing plans and to raise $7 million in capital. But the companies amicably parted ways when those commitments were not reached, Mr. Reese said. Mr. Giuliani’s company was not paid for the work it performed, other than to receive a share of the company, which it has since relinquished, Mr. Reese said. Pasquale J. D’Amuro, the Giuliani Partners executive who oversaw the project, explained the split by saying that he had found the technology promising but did not feel it had progressed to a point where he could promote it to potential investors. Mr. Giuliani declined to be interviewed for this article. In response to a question last summer, he told an interviewer for The New Yorker that his role with the project would not give it any advantage in securing a federal contract were he to become president. Dennis F. Thompson, a professor at Harvard’s Kennedy School of Government who has written extensively on political ethics, said Mr. Giuliani should have mentioned his ties to SkyWatch when promoting the fence concept in his campaign. “We should know as citizens when a candidate makes a proposal of this sort who stands to benefit,” Professor Thompson said. “If the candidate himself is one of the beneficiaries, we want to take that into account.” Professor Thompson said the potential conflict is more acute when the candidate is an active partner in a closely held company, as opposed to a shareholder in a public corporation. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in National »On the presidential campaign trail, former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani often promotes the installation of electronic monitoring devices at the border to stem illegal immigration, without mentioning that until a few months ago, he was partner in a company trying to market such technology. Skip to next paragraph Blog The Caucus The latest political news from around the nation. Join the discussion. Candidate Topic Pages More Politics News Mr. Giuliani and his consulting company were part owners of SkyWatch L.L.C., a closely held start-up company that says it has developed a sensor capable of monitoring illegal border crossings. SkyWatch, in collaboration with Raytheon, a large military contractor, is now looking to market the technology to the federal government and elsewhere. Mr. Giuliani’s company, Giuliani Partners, was invited to join the venture more than two years ago by Abdol Moabery, then the chief executive of SkyWatch’s parent company, who went on to help the Giuliani campaign raise money in Florida. As part of its work, an executive of Mr. Giuliani’s company met several times with development teams at Raytheon. But the financial relationship ended in September when Giuliani Partners gave up its ownership stake in SkyWatch without compensation. For nearly a year, Mr. Giuliani has extolled the benefits of a technological approach to border security. Among his efforts has been a radio advertisement, which went on the air in August, called “Fence,” in which he spoke of the need for a “technological fence” at the border. “You stop illegal immigration by building a fence, a physical fence and then a technological fence,” Mr. Giuliani said in the ad. “You then hire enough border patrol so they can respond in a timely way.” But neither in the ad, nor in other campaign settings where the issue has come up, has Mr. Giuliani mentioned his involvement with a company developing this technological fence. No one has suggested that Mr. Giuliani adopted his position because of his relationship with SkyWatch. He has continued to promote the concept since his relationship with the company ended, including during recent campaign discussions. A spokeswoman for his campaign said Mr. Giuliani’s longstanding support for a technological fence was not related to his involvement with SkyWatch. “It’s one part of Rudy’s comprehensive plan to end illegal immigration because it makes sense and is good policy,” the spokeswoman, Maria Comella, said. Last month, SkyWatch and Raytheon announced that the sensor, capable of monitoring more than 400 square miles from atop a tower, was available for sale. Industry analysts say the technology has a lucrative future, including a possible role in a multibillion-dollar federal program to help secure the nation’s borders. Gary Reese, the manager of SkyWatch, said the company ended its involvement with Giuliani Partners when it became clear the consulting company could not meet its contractual obligations. He said Giuliani Partners had essentially bartered for a 12.5 percent share of SkyWatch by committing to develop business and marketing plans and to raise $7 million in capital. But the companies amicably parted ways when those commitments were not reached, Mr. Reese said. Mr. Giuliani’s company was not paid for the work it performed, other than to receive a share of the company, which it has since relinquished, Mr. Reese said. Pasquale J. D’Amuro, the Giuliani Partners executive who oversaw the project, explained the split by saying that he had found the technology promising but did not feel it had progressed to a point where he could promote it to potential investors. Mr. Giuliani declined to be interviewed for this article. In response to a question last summer, he told an interviewer for The New Yorker that his role with the project would not give it any advantage in securing a federal contract were he to become president. Dennis F. Thompson, a professor at Harvard’s Kennedy School of Government who has written extensively on political ethics, said Mr. Giuliani should have mentioned his ties to SkyWatch when promoting the fence concept in his campaign. “We should know as citizens when a candidate makes a proposal of this sort who stands to benefit,” Professor Thompson said. “If the candidate himself is one of the beneficiaries, we want to take that into account.” Professor Thompson said the potential conflict is more acute when the candidate is an active partner in a closely held company, as opposed to a shareholder in a public corporation. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/26/business/26raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon Reports a Decline in Earnings<date>Published: October 26, 2007</date><text>Raytheon reported slightly lower third-quarter profit yesterday, hurt by losses from a unit it is selling, and forecast next years profit would fall below Wall Streets average estimate. Raytheon, the military contractor that makes Patriot and Tomahawk missiles, reported higher sales of its military equipment, but those were offset by a one-time charge relating to the sale of its Flight Options private jet chartering unit to H.I.G. Capital, announced yesterday. The sale comes after the company sold its business jet unit, Raytheon Aircraft, this year. Raytheon, based in Waltham, Mass., reported a quarterly net profit of $299 million, or 68 cents a share, compared with $321 million, or 71 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding the Flight Options sale charge, worth $69 million after tax, Raytheon reported profit from continuing operations of 86 cents a share. On that basis, Wall Street was expecting 81 cents a share, on average, according to Reuters Estimates. Raytheons sales for the quarter rose 8 percent to $5.4 billion. Analysts were expecting $5.36 billion, on average. For 2008, it forecast earnings from continuing operations of $3.45 to $3.65 a share. Analysts are expecting $3.77 a share, on average. Raytheon shares fell 33 cents, to $65. More Articles in Business »Raytheon reported slightly lower third-quarter profit yesterday, hurt by losses from a unit it is selling, and forecast next years profit would fall below Wall Streets average estimate. Raytheon, the military contractor that makes Patriot and Tomahawk missiles, reported higher sales of its military equipment, but those were offset by a one-time charge relating to the sale of its Flight Options private jet chartering unit to H.I.G. Capital, announced yesterday. The sale comes after the company sold its business jet unit, Raytheon Aircraft, this year. Raytheon, based in Waltham, Mass., reported a quarterly net profit of $299 million, or 68 cents a share, compared with $321 million, or 71 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding the Flight Options sale charge, worth $69 million after tax, Raytheon reported profit from continuing operations of 86 cents a share. On that basis, Wall Street was expecting 81 cents a share, on average, according to Reuters Estimates. Raytheons sales for the quarter rose 8 percent to $5.4 billion. Analysts were expecting $5.36 billion, on average. For 2008, it forecast earnings from continuing operations of $3.45 to $3.65 a share. Analysts are expecting $3.77 a share, on average. Raytheon shares fell 33 cents, to $65.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3FF932A25751C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">OPENERS: SUITS; Unwritten Rule No. 1: Take Care of the Boss<date>Published: February 11, 2007</date><text>It seems that the Raytheon Company has decided that its chief executive, William H. Swanson, has been punished enough for his plagiarism. The company docked $1 million from his pay last year after he admitted to having taken large parts of his folksy book, ''Swanson's Unwritten Rules of Management,'' from a 1944 engineering classic written by a California professor. Only a few months have elapsed, but Raytheon recently said it raised Mr. Swanson's bonus to $2.8 million in 2006 -- even though, as The Boston Globe noted when it first reported the news, promoting ethical behavior is one criterion the board says it used in setting bonuses. Why did Mr. Swanson's bonus increase as his ethics decreased? Mac Jeffery, a Raytheon spokesman, said ethical behavior was just one factor the board considered. As if that's not enough, Mr. Swanson still has restricted shares valued at $25.7 million and received up to 240,000 more restricted shares -- worth $13.2 million at Friday's closing price -- with his 2006 cash bonus. LESLIE WAYNE Photo: William H. Swanson (Photo by Michael Springer/Bloomberg News)</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/22/business/worldbusiness/22onex.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Canadian Company Buys Raytheon Jet Unit<date>Published: December 22, 2006</date><text>OTTAWA, Dec. 21  Onex, a Toronto-based investment company, expanded its presence in the aerospace business Thursday by joining with the private equity arm of Goldman Sachs to buy Raytheons business jet division for about $3.3 billion. Raytheon had put the unit under review in July as part of a program to focus on government and military aerospace, where profit margins are generally higher. The business jet unit, which is based in Wichita, Kan., and has about 8,500 employees, will be renamed Hawker Beechcraft, after two of the units venerable brand names. The unit is Onexs third significant aerospace investment. Last year, Onex acquired a component division of Boeing for $1.2 billion; part of it was sold off last month in an initial public offering worth $1.4 billion. Onex is also a minority member of the consortium that successfully bid for Qantas Airways earlier this month. Like all business jet makers, Raytheons unit suffered as the market for its products dropped after the terrorist attacks on Sept. 11, 2001. But the unit has returned to profitability in the last three years, posting earnings of $142 million in 2005, up from $63 million a year earlier. The unit, which makes Hawker and Premier business jets and King Air turboprop planes, had revenue of $2.85 billion last year. Richard L. Aboulafia, an aerospace analyst with the Teal Group in Fairfax, Va., said that while the unit had made a strong comeback, it remained a laggard in its sector. Its an elite club, Mr. Aboulafia said. They are the weakest of the big five. Among Hawker Beechcrafts largest rivals will be another Canadian-owned company, Bombardier, which is based in Montreal. The Teal Group ranks Bombardier as the market leader, with a 25 percent share compared with Raytheons 10 percent. As with the purchase of the Boeing unit, it appears that Onex will be entering the business jet market at the beginning of a growth period. In an annual survey released in October, Honeywell estimated that shipments of business jets were up 26 percent in the first half of the year compared with the same period in 2005. For all of 2006, Honeywell estimates total shipments of 850 business aircraft, and for 2007 it forecasts 1,000 or more. Sales are still rebounding from 2003 lows in North America, and are rising in Asia and the Middle East. Like the Boeing operations acquired by Onex, Raytheons business jet unit was an early user of resin-reinforced carbon fiber composites as substitutes for metals. But Mr. Aboulafia said that it was not clear if that would enable cooperation between the operations. Because the unit produces a training jet for the American military and Onex is not an American company, the acquisition is subject to Pentagon approval. Onex and Goldman Sachs will own equal shares of the company. Onex said in a statement that it would retain the businesss current management, as it did with the Boeing unit. More Articles in Business »OTTAWA, Dec. 21  Onex, a Toronto-based investment company, expanded its presence in the aerospace business Thursday by joining with the private equity arm of Goldman Sachs to buy Raytheons business jet division for about $3.3 billion. Raytheon had put the unit under review in July as part of a program to focus on government and military aerospace, where profit margins are generally higher. The business jet unit, which is based in Wichita, Kan., and has about 8,500 employees, will be renamed Hawker Beechcraft, after two of the units venerable brand names. The unit is Onexs third significant aerospace investment. Last year, Onex acquired a component division of Boeing for $1.2 billion; part of it was sold off last month in an initial public offering worth $1.4 billion. Onex is also a minority member of the consortium that successfully bid for Qantas Airways earlier this month. Like all business jet makers, Raytheons unit suffered as the market for its products dropped after the terrorist attacks on Sept. 11, 2001. But the unit has returned to profitability in the last three years, posting earnings of $142 million in 2005, up from $63 million a year earlier. The unit, which makes Hawker and Premier business jets and King Air turboprop planes, had revenue of $2.85 billion last year. Richard L. Aboulafia, an aerospace analyst with the Teal Group in Fairfax, Va., said that while the unit had made a strong comeback, it remained a laggard in its sector. Its an elite club, Mr. Aboulafia said. They are the weakest of the big five. Among Hawker Beechcrafts largest rivals will be another Canadian-owned company, Bombardier, which is based in Montreal. The Teal Group ranks Bombardier as the market leader, with a 25 percent share compared with Raytheons 10 percent. As with the purchase of the Boeing unit, it appears that Onex will be entering the business jet market at the beginning of a growth period. In an annual survey released in October, Honeywell estimated that shipments of business jets were up 26 percent in the first half of the year compared with the same period in 2005. For all of 2006, Honeywell estimates total shipments of 850 business aircraft, and for 2007 it forecasts 1,000 or more. Sales are still rebounding from 2003 lows in North America, and are rising in Asia and the Middle East. Like the Boeing operations acquired by Onex, Raytheons business jet unit was an early user of resin-reinforced carbon fiber composites as substitutes for metals. But Mr. Aboulafia said that it was not clear if that would enable cooperation between the operations. Because the unit produces a training jet for the American military and Onex is not an American company, the acquisition is subject to Pentagon approval. Onex and Goldman Sachs will own equal shares of the company. Onex said in a statement that it would retain the businesss current management, as it did with the Boeing unit.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/08/business/08raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Three Bids Expected for Raytheon Unit<date>Published: December 8, 2006</date><text>Three bids are expected for a multibillion-dollar purchase of the aircraft division of the Raytheon Company, the military contractor, and the deal may be completed by year-end, according to several people involved in the transaction. The Carlyle Group of Washington, Cerberus Capital Management in New York and a team comprising Goldman Sachs and the Onex Corporation, which is based in Toronto, are probable bidders, according to Paul Nisbet, an analyst at JSA Research in Newport, R.I. Mr. Nisbet estimated that the company would get roughly $2.5 billion for the division. A person involved in the negotiations who asked not to be identified because the negotiations are confidential and continuing, confirmed the names of the bidders and the timing of the deal. Raytheon announced in July that it was considering selling its Raytheon Aircraft division, based in Wichita, Kan., to focus on its core military and technology businesses, said Mac Jeffery, a Raytheon spokesman. The aircraft division to be sold includes Beechcraft, which makes single-engine two- and four-seater planes, and Hawker, a maker of midsize twin-engine corporate jets that compete with foreign companies like Bombardier Aerospace of Canada and Embraer of Brazil. Representatives from Onex, the Carlyle Group and Goldman Sachs either declined to comment or did not return calls. More Articles in Business »Three bids are expected for a multibillion-dollar purchase of the aircraft division of the Raytheon Company, the military contractor, and the deal may be completed by year-end, according to several people involved in the transaction. The Carlyle Group of Washington, Cerberus Capital Management in New York and a team comprising Goldman Sachs and the Onex Corporation, which is based in Toronto, are probable bidders, according to Paul Nisbet, an analyst at JSA Research in Newport, R.I. Mr. Nisbet estimated that the company would get roughly $2.5 billion for the division. A person involved in the negotiations who asked not to be identified because the negotiations are confidential and continuing, confirmed the names of the bidders and the timing of the deal. Raytheon announced in July that it was considering selling its Raytheon Aircraft division, based in Wichita, Kan., to focus on its core military and technology businesses, said Mac Jeffery, a Raytheon spokesman. The aircraft division to be sold includes Beechcraft, which makes single-engine two- and four-seater planes, and Hawker, a maker of midsize twin-engine corporate jets that compete with foreign companies like Bombardier Aerospace of Canada and Embraer of Brazil. Representatives from Onex, the Carlyle Group and Goldman Sachs either declined to comment or did not return calls.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DC1030F93AA35754C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">OPENERS: SUITS; AND, BACK AT RAYTHEON<date>Published: July 9, 2006</date><text>Problems at Raytheon's commuter aircraft unit boiled to the surface again recently. Raytheon, the big military contractor, agreed last year to pay $12 million and discipline two people, including its former chief financial officer, Edward S. Pliner, to settle a Securities and Exchange Commission lawsuit accusing the company of fraud in the way it accounted for Beechcraft plane sales from 1997 to 2001. Now, it turns out, Raytheon's former chairman and chief executive, Daniel P. Burnham, and a former deputy finance chief, Aldo R. Servello, recently agreed to settle S.E.C. accusations of complicity in the fraud. Mr. Burnham, who stepped down as chief in July 2003 and quit as chairman the next January, agreed to pay $1,238,344. Mr. Servello agreed to pay $34,628. The S.E.C. said both men knew in advance about some misstatements. Neither man admitted or denied the findings. MARK A. STEIN</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDB133EF933A15756C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">Corrections<date>Published: May 20, 2006</date><text>A front-page article on Thursday about a federal plan to use contractors to help secure the borders of the United States misstated the amount that Lockheed Martin made in federal government sales in 2005. Of $37.2 billion in sales, more than $31 billion, not $6 billion, was in sales to the government.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/18/washington/18border.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Bush Turns to Big Military Contractors for Border Control<date>Published: May 18, 2006</date><text>Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic: New Technology on the Border Related 2 Immigration Provisions Easily Pass Senate (May 18, 2006) Bush Faces Resistance on Immigration (May 17, 2006) Bush Calls for Compromise on Immigration (May 16, 2006) Immigration Go to Complete Coverage » Readers’ Opinions Forum: Immigration Correction Appended WASHINGTON, May 17  The quick fix may involve sending in the National Guard. But to really patch up the broken border, President Bush is preparing to turn to a familiar administration partner: the nation's giant military contractors. Lockheed Martin, Raytheon and Northrop Grumman, three of the largest, are among the companies that said they would submit bids within two weeks for a multibillion-dollar federal contract to build what the administration calls a "virtual fence" along the nation's land borders. Using some of the same high-priced, high-tech tools these companies have already put to work in Iraq and Afghanistan  like unmanned aerial vehicles, ground surveillance satellites and motion-detection video equipment  the military contractors are zeroing in on the rivers, deserts, mountains and settled areas that separate Mexico and Canada from the United States. It is a humbling acknowledgment that despite more than a decade of initiatives with macho-sounding names, like Operation Hold the Line in El Paso or Operation Gate Keeper in San Diego, the federal government has repeatedly failed on its own to gain control of the land borders. Through its Secure Border Initiative, the Bush administration intends to not simply buy an amalgam of high-tech equipment to help it patrol the borders  a tactic it has also already tried, at a cost of hundreds of millions of dollars, with extremely limited success. It is also asking the contractors to devise and build a whole new border strategy that ties together the personnel, technology and physical barriers. "This is an unusual invitation," the deputy secretary of homeland security, Michael Jackson, told contractors this year at an industry briefing, just before the bidding period for this new contract started. "We're asking you to come back and tell us how to do our business." The effort comes as the Senate voted Wednesday to add hundreds of miles of fencing along the border with Mexico. The measure would also prohibit illegal immigrants convicted of a felony or three misdemeanors from any chance at citizenship. The high-tech plan being bid now has many skeptics, who say they have heard a similar refrain from the government before. "We've been presented with expensive proposals for elaborate border technology that eventually have proven to be ineffective and wasteful," Representative Harold Rogers, Republican of Kentucky, said at a hearing on the Secure Border Initiative program last month. "How is the S.B.I. not just another three-letter acronym for failure?" President Bush, among others, said he was convinced that the government could get it right this time. "We are launching the most technologically advanced border security initiative in American history," Mr. Bush said in his speech from the Oval Office on Monday. Under the initiative, the Department of Homeland Security and its Customs and Border Protection division will still be charged with patrolling the 6,000 miles of land borders. The equipment these Border Patrol agents use, how and when they are dispatched to spots along the border, where the agents assemble the captured immigrants, how they process them and transport them  all these steps will now be scripted by the winning contractor, who could earn an estimated $2 billion over the next three to six years on the Secure Border job. More Border Patrol agents are part of the answer. The Bush administration has committed to increasing the force from 11,500 to about 18,500 by the time the president leaves office in 2008. But simply spreading this army of agents out evenly along the border or extending fences in and around urban areas is not sufficient, officials said. "Boots on the ground is not really enough," Homeland Security Secretary Michael Chertoff said Tuesday at a news conference that followed Mr. Bush's announcement to send as many as 6,000 National Guard troops to the border. The tools of modern warfare must be brought to bear. That means devices like the Tethered Aerostat Radar, a helium-filled airship made for the Air Force by Lockheed Martin that is twice the size of the Goodyear Blimp. Attached to the ground by a cable, the airship can hover overhead and automatically monitor any movement night or day. (One downside: it cannot operate in high winds.) 1 2Next Page » Correction: May 20, 2006 A front-page article on Thursday about a federal plan to use contractors to help secure the borders of the United States misstated the amount that Lockheed Martin made in federal government sales in 2005. Of $37.2 billion in sales, more than $31 billion, not $6 billion, was in sales to the government. More Articles in Washington »Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic: New Technology on the Border Related 2 Immigration Provisions Easily Pass Senate (May 18, 2006) Bush Faces Resistance on Immigration (May 17, 2006) Bush Calls for Compromise on Immigration (May 16, 2006) Immigration Go to Complete Coverage » Readers’ Opinions Forum: Immigration Correction Appended WASHINGTON, May 17  The quick fix may involve sending in the National Guard. But to really patch up the broken border, President Bush is preparing to turn to a familiar administration partner: the nation's giant military contractors. Lockheed Martin, Raytheon and Northrop Grumman, three of the largest, are among the companies that said they would submit bids within two weeks for a multibillion-dollar federal contract to build what the administration calls a "virtual fence" along the nation's land borders. Using some of the same high-priced, high-tech tools these companies have already put to work in Iraq and Afghanistan  like unmanned aerial vehicles, ground surveillance satellites and motion-detection video equipment  the military contractors are zeroing in on the rivers, deserts, mountains and settled areas that separate Mexico and Canada from the United States. It is a humbling acknowledgment that despite more than a decade of initiatives with macho-sounding names, like Operation Hold the Line in El Paso or Operation Gate Keeper in San Diego, the federal government has repeatedly failed on its own to gain control of the land borders. Through its Secure Border Initiative, the Bush administration intends to not simply buy an amalgam of high-tech equipment to help it patrol the borders  a tactic it has also already tried, at a cost of hundreds of millions of dollars, with extremely limited success. It is also asking the contractors to devise and build a whole new border strategy that ties together the personnel, technology and physical barriers. "This is an unusual invitation," the deputy secretary of homeland security, Michael Jackson, told contractors this year at an industry briefing, just before the bidding period for this new contract started. "We're asking you to come back and tell us how to do our business." The effort comes as the Senate voted Wednesday to add hundreds of miles of fencing along the border with Mexico. The measure would also prohibit illegal immigrants convicted of a felony or three misdemeanors from any chance at citizenship. The high-tech plan being bid now has many skeptics, who say they have heard a similar refrain from the government before. "We've been presented with expensive proposals for elaborate border technology that eventually have proven to be ineffective and wasteful," Representative Harold Rogers, Republican of Kentucky, said at a hearing on the Secure Border Initiative program last month. "How is the S.B.I. not just another three-letter acronym for failure?" President Bush, among others, said he was convinced that the government could get it right this time. "We are launching the most technologically advanced border security initiative in American history," Mr. Bush said in his speech from the Oval Office on Monday. Under the initiative, the Department of Homeland Security and its Customs and Border Protection division will still be charged with patrolling the 6,000 miles of land borders. The equipment these Border Patrol agents use, how and when they are dispatched to spots along the border, where the agents assemble the captured immigrants, how they process them and transport them  all these steps will now be scripted by the winning contractor, who could earn an estimated $2 billion over the next three to six years on the Secure Border job. More Border Patrol agents are part of the answer. The Bush administration has committed to increasing the force from 11,500 to about 18,500 by the time the president leaves office in 2008. But simply spreading this army of agents out evenly along the border or extending fences in and around urban areas is not sufficient, officials said. "Boots on the ground is not really enough," Homeland Security Secretary Michael Chertoff said Tuesday at a news conference that followed Mr. Bush's announcement to send as many as 6,000 National Guard troops to the border. The tools of modern warfare must be brought to bear. That means devices like the Tethered Aerostat Radar, a helium-filled airship made for the Air Force by Lockheed Martin that is twice the size of the Goodyear Blimp. Attached to the ground by a cable, the airship can hover overhead and automatically monitor any movement night or day. (One downside: it cannot operate in high winds.) 1 2Next Page » Correction: May 20, 2006 A front-page article on Thursday about a federal plan to use contractors to help secure the borders of the United States misstated the amount that Lockheed Martin made in federal government sales in 2005. Of $37.2 billion in sales, more than $31 billion, not $6 billion, was in sales to the government.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/04/business/04raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Chief's Pay Is Docked by Raytheon<date>Published: May 4, 2006</date><text>Raytheon directors punished the chief executive, William H. Swanson, by taking away almost $1 million from his 2006 compensation yesterday because he failed to give credit for material that was in a management book he wrote. Skip to next paragraph Michael Springer/Bloomberg News William H. Swanson failed to give credit for material in his book. Related Comparison of the Books (May 2, 2006) David Leonhardt: Rule No. 35: Reread Rule on Integrity (May 3, 2006) Mr. Swanson's pay cut will come in two ways. His 2006 salary will be frozen at its 2005 level and his 2006 restricted stock award will be reduced 20 percent, Raytheon said. The cuts would come to nearly $1 million according to a person close to the board, who was granted anonymity because he was disclosing proprietary information. In 2005, Mr. Swanson received a salary of $1.12 million and restricted stock valued at $2.96 million. The board acted before the annual shareholders meeting yesterday afternoon in Arlington, Va. The punishment also comes as Raytheon has stopped circulating the book, "Swanson's Unwritten Rules of Management," a folksy book that turned Mr. Swanson into a management sage and earned him praise from business leaders like Jack Welch and Warren E. Buffett. Raytheon, a leading military contractor, had given away more than 300,000 copies of the book and had promoted it on its Web site. But many of the rules were later found to have been taken from a 1944 engineering classic, "The Unwritten Laws of Engineering," written by W. J. King, an engineering professor at the University of California, Los Angeles. Of Mr. Swanson's 33 rules, 17 were in the 1944 book, often word for word. In addition, The Boston Herald reported yesterday on its Web site that Mr. Swanson had lifted four rules  1 through 4  from a list of maxims collected by Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld and published in The Wall Street Journal in 2001 as Rumsfeld's Rules. The first rule in both Mr. Swanson's and Mr. Rumsfeld's list is the same: "Learn to say 'I don't know.' If used when appropriate, it will be used often." The Herald also found that Mr. Swanson's rule No. 32 was similar to a life lesson about rude treatment of waiters that was in the book "Dave Barry Turns 50," written by Mr. Barry, the humor columnist. A statement issued by Warren B. Rudman, Raytheon's departing lead director, and Michael C. Ruettgers, the company's incoming lead director, said the Raytheon board had "expressed to Mr. Swanson its deep concern over the disclosures involving 'The Unwritten Rules.' " The board "takes this matter very seriously" the statement said. But, it also praised Mr. Swanson for his "extraordinary vision" and said the board had "full confidence" in him. "The board noted that Mr. Swanson, appropriately, has taken full responsibility," the statement said, and has "sincerely apologized to all involved." In an interview yesterday, Mr. Rudman said "the board decided, and I think properly, that there is a great difference between an unintentional error, in which you have simple negligence, and an intentional act that breaches sound ethical conduct." "Based on the evidence, we decided that this was unintentional and not negligent. It was just poor judgment." The Boston Herald disclosure of additional copying came after the morning meeting of the Raytheon board. While cutting Mr. Swanson's salary and stock awards, the board did not touch other forms of compensation. These include his 2006 bonus  he received a $2.6 million bonus in 2005  along with personal use of corporate aircraft and a company-paid car. Raytheon also reimburses Mr. Swanson for his tax payments as well as covering his life insurance payments  neither of these items were reduced or withdrawn. Jay Lorsch a human relations professor at the Harvard Business School, said yesterday that he was "not sure whether the punishment was appropriate to what had happened." "This seems at best a very unusual way to deal with it," Mr. Lorsch said. "The real question is whether you want a guy like this as chief executive. A cut in pay is a little like a slap on the wrist. I suppose he is doing a good job in other ways and the company does not want to lose him. The board had to do something and maybe this is the best thing they could do." Mr. Lorsch said it remained to be seen how Raytheon employees would react and whether Mr. Swanson's failure to attribute his rules would undercut his credibility. A Raytheon spokeswoman, Pamela A. Wickham, said yesterday that disclosures of further copying did not change anything. She said that an apology issued by Mr. Swanson on Tuesday night, covered the material from the 1944 book, as well as material from any other newly disclosed sources. On Tuesday night, Raytheon issued a statement on Mr. Swanson's behalf that said the source for his book came from material he had collected over the years and had given to a member of his staff to prepare a presentation that he was to give to Raytheon engineers. "Bill knew that some of the material was from the things he had read and collected over the years," the Raytheon statement said. "Again, Bill apologizes to Raytheon's shareholders, directors and employees, as well as all involved for this misjudgment. He sincerely regrets the entire incident." At the annual meeting yesterday, Mr. Swanson issued another mea culpa. Bloomberg News said he told shareholders: "I did not properly check source material. I apologize to those whose material I wish I had treated with greater care." The similarities between many of the rules in Mr. Swanson's book and the 1944 text was uncovered by a San Diego engineer, Carl Durrenberger, who then posted his observations on a blog he maintains. More Articles in Business »Raytheon directors punished the chief executive, William H. Swanson, by taking away almost $1 million from his 2006 compensation yesterday because he failed to give credit for material that was in a management book he wrote. Skip to next paragraph Michael Springer/Bloomberg News William H. Swanson failed to give credit for material in his book. Related Comparison of the Books (May 2, 2006) David Leonhardt: Rule No. 35: Reread Rule on Integrity (May 3, 2006) Mr. Swanson's pay cut will come in two ways. His 2006 salary will be frozen at its 2005 level and his 2006 restricted stock award will be reduced 20 percent, Raytheon said. The cuts would come to nearly $1 million according to a person close to the board, who was granted anonymity because he was disclosing proprietary information. In 2005, Mr. Swanson received a salary of $1.12 million and restricted stock valued at $2.96 million. The board acted before the annual shareholders meeting yesterday afternoon in Arlington, Va. The punishment also comes as Raytheon has stopped circulating the book, "Swanson's Unwritten Rules of Management," a folksy book that turned Mr. Swanson into a management sage and earned him praise from business leaders like Jack Welch and Warren E. Buffett. Raytheon, a leading military contractor, had given away more than 300,000 copies of the book and had promoted it on its Web site. But many of the rules were later found to have been taken from a 1944 engineering classic, "The Unwritten Laws of Engineering," written by W. J. King, an engineering professor at the University of California, Los Angeles. Of Mr. Swanson's 33 rules, 17 were in the 1944 book, often word for word. In addition, The Boston Herald reported yesterday on its Web site that Mr. Swanson had lifted four rules  1 through 4  from a list of maxims collected by Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld and published in The Wall Street Journal in 2001 as Rumsfeld's Rules. The first rule in both Mr. Swanson's and Mr. Rumsfeld's list is the same: "Learn to say 'I don't know.' If used when appropriate, it will be used often." The Herald also found that Mr. Swanson's rule No. 32 was similar to a life lesson about rude treatment of waiters that was in the book "Dave Barry Turns 50," written by Mr. Barry, the humor columnist. A statement issued by Warren B. Rudman, Raytheon's departing lead director, and Michael C. Ruettgers, the company's incoming lead director, said the Raytheon board had "expressed to Mr. Swanson its deep concern over the disclosures involving 'The Unwritten Rules.' " The board "takes this matter very seriously" the statement said. But, it also praised Mr. Swanson for his "extraordinary vision" and said the board had "full confidence" in him. "The board noted that Mr. Swanson, appropriately, has taken full responsibility," the statement said, and has "sincerely apologized to all involved." In an interview yesterday, Mr. Rudman said "the board decided, and I think properly, that there is a great difference between an unintentional error, in which you have simple negligence, and an intentional act that breaches sound ethical conduct." "Based on the evidence, we decided that this was unintentional and not negligent. It was just poor judgment." The Boston Herald disclosure of additional copying came after the morning meeting of the Raytheon board. While cutting Mr. Swanson's salary and stock awards, the board did not touch other forms of compensation. These include his 2006 bonus  he received a $2.6 million bonus in 2005  along with personal use of corporate aircraft and a company-paid car. Raytheon also reimburses Mr. Swanson for his tax payments as well as covering his life insurance payments  neither of these items were reduced or withdrawn. Jay Lorsch a human relations professor at the Harvard Business School, said yesterday that he was "not sure whether the punishment was appropriate to what had happened." "This seems at best a very unusual way to deal with it," Mr. Lorsch said. "The real question is whether you want a guy like this as chief executive. A cut in pay is a little like a slap on the wrist. I suppose he is doing a good job in other ways and the company does not want to lose him. The board had to do something and maybe this is the best thing they could do." Mr. Lorsch said it remained to be seen how Raytheon employees would react and whether Mr. Swanson's failure to attribute his rules would undercut his credibility. A Raytheon spokeswoman, Pamela A. Wickham, said yesterday that disclosures of further copying did not change anything. She said that an apology issued by Mr. Swanson on Tuesday night, covered the material from the 1944 book, as well as material from any other newly disclosed sources. On Tuesday night, Raytheon issued a statement on Mr. Swanson's behalf that said the source for his book came from material he had collected over the years and had given to a member of his staff to prepare a presentation that he was to give to Raytheon engineers. "Bill knew that some of the material was from the things he had read and collected over the years," the Raytheon statement said. "Again, Bill apologizes to Raytheon's shareholders, directors and employees, as well as all involved for this misjudgment. He sincerely regrets the entire incident." At the annual meeting yesterday, Mr. Swanson issued another mea culpa. Bloomberg News said he told shareholders: "I did not properly check source material. I apologize to those whose material I wish I had treated with greater care." The similarities between many of the rules in Mr. Swanson's book and the 1944 text was uncovered by a San Diego engineer, Carl Durrenberger, who then posted his observations on a blog he maintains.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/25/business/media/25raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Executive Says His 'Rules' Didn't Properly Credit Another Text<date>Published: April 25, 2006</date><text>The chief executive of the Raytheon Company, William H. Swanson, acknowledged yesterday that he did "not properly credit" a 1944 engineering text when he wrote a book of management advice that included passages from the earlier text. Mr. Swanson said in a statement that the similarities between his book, "Swanson's Unwritten Rules of Management," and a 1944 text, "The Unwritten Laws of Engineering," were "beyond dispute." The engineering text was written by W. J. King, an engineering professor at the University of California, Los Angeles, and is a collection of folksy wisdom that later appeared in Mr. Swanson's book. "I regret that over the course of the years and in the process of compiling the 'Unwritten Rules', any reference to Professor King's work was not properly credited," Mr. Swanson said yesterday. His book, which contains 33 rules for management, has been distributed free by Raytheon, with over 250,000 in circulation. As a result of the book, Mr. Swanson has gained the reputation of a management guru and his rules have gained a wide following as pithy common-sense aphorisms. A total of 17 of Mr. Swanson's rules  rules No. 6 to 22  are also in the 1944 text, with either similar or identical language. As an example, Rule No. 16  "Don't overlook the fact you are working for your boss"  appears in both books. In his statement, Mr. Swanson said that in writing his book, he drew from many "unnamed" sources who "over the course of my life, contributed a thought or an idea relevant to the compiled work." "For me, the originality of the material was never the rules themselves," Mr. Swanson said, "but my expression of them in terms of my own experience over the years." The similarities between the books were discovered by a Hewlett-Packard engineer and blogger, Carl Durrenberger, who had posted his findings on the Internet. Mr. Durrenberger said he was struck by the similarities after USA Today mentioned Mr. Swanson's rules last week as part of an article on management and character. As a result of this experience, Mr. Swanson said he has a new rule, No. 34: "Regarding the truisms of human behavior, there are no original rules." More Articles in Business »The chief executive of the Raytheon Company, William H. Swanson, acknowledged yesterday that he did "not properly credit" a 1944 engineering text when he wrote a book of management advice that included passages from the earlier text. Mr. Swanson said in a statement that the similarities between his book, "Swanson's Unwritten Rules of Management," and a 1944 text, "The Unwritten Laws of Engineering," were "beyond dispute." The engineering text was written by W. J. King, an engineering professor at the University of California, Los Angeles, and is a collection of folksy wisdom that later appeared in Mr. Swanson's book. "I regret that over the course of the years and in the process of compiling the 'Unwritten Rules', any reference to Professor King's work was not properly credited," Mr. Swanson said yesterday. His book, which contains 33 rules for management, has been distributed free by Raytheon, with over 250,000 in circulation. As a result of the book, Mr. Swanson has gained the reputation of a management guru and his rules have gained a wide following as pithy common-sense aphorisms. A total of 17 of Mr. Swanson's rules  rules No. 6 to 22  are also in the 1944 text, with either similar or identical language. As an example, Rule No. 16  "Don't overlook the fact you are working for your boss"  appears in both books. In his statement, Mr. Swanson said that in writing his book, he drew from many "unnamed" sources who "over the course of my life, contributed a thought or an idea relevant to the compiled work." "For me, the originality of the material was never the rules themselves," Mr. Swanson said, "but my expression of them in terms of my own experience over the years." The similarities between the books were discovered by a Hewlett-Packard engineer and blogger, Carl Durrenberger, who had posted his findings on the Internet. Mr. Durrenberger said he was struck by the similarities after USA Today mentioned Mr. Swanson's rules last week as part of an article on management and character. As a result of this experience, Mr. Swanson said he has a new rule, No. 34: "Regarding the truisms of human behavior, there are no original rules."</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/28/business/28raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Ex-Raytheon Chief Agrees to Fine and Forfeit of Part of Bonus<date>Published: March 28, 2006</date><text>Correction Appended The former chief executive of the Raytheon Corporation, Daniel P. Burnham, has agreed to pay a fine and return part of a $1.75 million bonus to settle Securities and Exchange Commission accusations over improper accounting practices in 2000 and 2001. Disclosure of the arrangement came in a regulatory filing yesterday by the First Data Corporation, where Mr. Burnham, 59, is a director and chairman of the company's compensation committee. Mr. Burnham served as chairman and chief executive of Raytheon for five years until his resignation in July 2003. The alleged accounting irregularities took place in Raytheon's troubled commercial aircraft division from 1997 to 2001 and concerned the timing of losses recorded by the company. The S.E.C. said that the company had overstated its 2001 losses and that its aircraft subsidiary should have charged up to $240 million of a $693 million loss in 2000 instead. Raytheon, First Data and the S.E.C. would not comment on the settlement. The amount of the fine and the amount of the bonus that Mr. Burnham will return were not specified. Raytheon would not comment on whether directors' and officers' insurance would cover Mr. Burnham's costs. Mr. Burnham did not respond to a message left for him at First Data. Since January 2003, the S.E.C. has been investigating accounting practices at Raytheon's aircraft division, which had faced a deteriorating market. Last April, the company offered to settle the investigation and recorded a charge of $12 million in the first quarter of 2005 to cover potential settlement costs. Raytheon has neither admitted nor denied the charges and the offer has yet to be approved. The agreement with Mr. Burnham, who neither admitted nor denied the agency's charges, is still subject to approval by the S.E.C. In its regulatory filing, First Data expressed confidence in Mr. Burnham, whom the company is renominating as head of its compensation committee. After reviewing the S.E.C. charges, First Data said the company's board "determined that the allegations are not reflective of Mr. Burnham's conduct, judgment or integrity" as they relate to his First Data board activities and cited "Mr. Burnham's valuable service to the company over the past two years." First Data also praised Mr. Burnham for "the forthright manner in which Mr. Burnham brought the allegations" to the attention of the company and said the events at Raytheon were unrelated to his board work at First Data. Paul Nisbet, a military industry analyst with JSA Research in Newport, R.I., said Mr. Burnham's agreement was "somewhat unusual" but that it "doesn't mean much" for Raytheon. Mr. Nisbet said that Mr. Burnham's action might lead to a resolution of charges involving Edward Pliner, the company's former chief financial officer, who was put on leave last April in connection with the S.E.C. investigation into Raytheon's accounting. Raytheon has said that the S.E.C. is expected to "bring action" against Mr. Pliner. "This could very well lead to something similar involving Ed Pliner," Mr. Nisbet said. Mr. Burnham is not the only chief executive facing a giveback of some of his bonus. Last January, Nortel Networks announced that a dozen current executives would repay $8.6 million in bonuses over manipulated financial statements. Government regulators are seeking repayment of bonuses of two top executives at Fannie Mae as a result of its accounting scandal, and shareholder pressure caused FPL Group to announce it was recouping $22.5 million in bonuses to eight executives after a failed merger. Also, last January, an Alabama judge ruled that Richard M. Scrushy, the former executive of HealthSouth, must repay his company more than $47.8 million in bonuses. Dean L. Buntrock, former chief executive of Waste Management, agreed last August to pay $19.5 million, which included his bonus, to settle S.E.C. claims. The S.E.C. is also trying to obtain $100 million, including bonuses, from Henry Yuen, the former chief executive of Gemstar-TV Guide International after charges that Mr. Yuen inflated revenues to mislead the company's investors. Correction: March 30, 2006 An article in Business Day on Tuesday about a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission by the former chief executive of the Raytheon Corporation, Daniel P. Burnham, that will require him to return part of his annual bonus for 2000 included an erroneous example of executives who have faced pressure or agreed to give back bonuses. (The error also appeared in an article on Jan. 12, 2005.) While government regulators are considering requiring the repayment of bonuses from two former top executives at Fannie Mae, they have not yet decided to do so. More Articles in Business &gt;Correction Appended The former chief executive of the Raytheon Corporation, Daniel P. Burnham, has agreed to pay a fine and return part of a $1.75 million bonus to settle Securities and Exchange Commission accusations over improper accounting practices in 2000 and 2001. Disclosure of the arrangement came in a regulatory filing yesterday by the First Data Corporation, where Mr. Burnham, 59, is a director and chairman of the company's compensation committee. Mr. Burnham served as chairman and chief executive of Raytheon for five years until his resignation in July 2003. The alleged accounting irregularities took place in Raytheon's troubled commercial aircraft division from 1997 to 2001 and concerned the timing of losses recorded by the company. The S.E.C. said that the company had overstated its 2001 losses and that its aircraft subsidiary should have charged up to $240 million of a $693 million loss in 2000 instead. Raytheon, First Data and the S.E.C. would not comment on the settlement. The amount of the fine and the amount of the bonus that Mr. Burnham will return were not specified. Raytheon would not comment on whether directors' and officers' insurance would cover Mr. Burnham's costs. Mr. Burnham did not respond to a message left for him at First Data. Since January 2003, the S.E.C. has been investigating accounting practices at Raytheon's aircraft division, which had faced a deteriorating market. Last April, the company offered to settle the investigation and recorded a charge of $12 million in the first quarter of 2005 to cover potential settlement costs. Raytheon has neither admitted nor denied the charges and the offer has yet to be approved. The agreement with Mr. Burnham, who neither admitted nor denied the agency's charges, is still subject to approval by the S.E.C. In its regulatory filing, First Data expressed confidence in Mr. Burnham, whom the company is renominating as head of its compensation committee. After reviewing the S.E.C. charges, First Data said the company's board "determined that the allegations are not reflective of Mr. Burnham's conduct, judgment or integrity" as they relate to his First Data board activities and cited "Mr. Burnham's valuable service to the company over the past two years." First Data also praised Mr. Burnham for "the forthright manner in which Mr. Burnham brought the allegations" to the attention of the company and said the events at Raytheon were unrelated to his board work at First Data. Paul Nisbet, a military industry analyst with JSA Research in Newport, R.I., said Mr. Burnham's agreement was "somewhat unusual" but that it "doesn't mean much" for Raytheon. Mr. Nisbet said that Mr. Burnham's action might lead to a resolution of charges involving Edward Pliner, the company's former chief financial officer, who was put on leave last April in connection with the S.E.C. investigation into Raytheon's accounting. Raytheon has said that the S.E.C. is expected to "bring action" against Mr. Pliner. "This could very well lead to something similar involving Ed Pliner," Mr. Nisbet said. Mr. Burnham is not the only chief executive facing a giveback of some of his bonus. Last January, Nortel Networks announced that a dozen current executives would repay $8.6 million in bonuses over manipulated financial statements. Government regulators are seeking repayment of bonuses of two top executives at Fannie Mae as a result of its accounting scandal, and shareholder pressure caused FPL Group to announce it was recouping $22.5 million in bonuses to eight executives after a failed merger. Also, last January, an Alabama judge ruled that Richard M. Scrushy, the former executive of HealthSouth, must repay his company more than $47.8 million in bonuses. Dean L. Buntrock, former chief executive of Waste Management, agreed last August to pay $19.5 million, which included his bonus, to settle S.E.C. claims. The S.E.C. is also trying to obtain $100 million, including bonuses, from Henry Yuen, the former chief executive of Gemstar-TV Guide International after charges that Mr. Yuen inflated revenues to mislead the company's investors. Correction: March 30, 2006 An article in Business Day on Tuesday about a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission by the former chief executive of the Raytheon Corporation, Daniel P. Burnham, that will require him to return part of his annual bonus for 2000 included an erroneous example of executives who have faced pressure or agreed to give back bonuses. (The error also appeared in an article on Jan. 12, 2005.) While government regulators are considering requiring the repayment of bonuses from two former top executives at Fannie Mae, they have not yet decided to do so.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/17/business/17road.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Valet Parking, Comfy Seats, Nice Meal (This Is Flying?)<date>Published: May 17, 2005</date><text>THE morning rush-hour traffic was awful. My flight was scheduled for 7:58 a.m. I had just enough time to make it, assuming I could find the right terminal at the Westchester County Airport, which I couldn't. Skip to next paragraph Chris Gash Business Travel Minute: In-Flight Movies After frantically circling the little airport three times and then somehow ending up on a country lane, I called the terminal from my cellphone. A friendly woman answered and stayed on the line to give me directions as I sheepishly made my way back through the maze of roads. "O.K., I just passed the Quaker meeting house," I said. "Turn left at the next road and you'll be there," she said. "Just leave your car in front with the keys." Anxiously, I pulled the car in front of the Westair terminal. It was now 8:25. I tossed the car keys to a waiting attendant and was escorted onto the airport apron, where a sleek Lear 60 business jet sat, door open and engines revved. I was identified to the pilot, Capt. James Beller, and the first officer, Geoffrey McIntosh, both of whom amiably shook off my apology. On the plane, I buckled into a comfortable leather seat. Within five minutes we were climbing, steep in the sky. A fruit plate was placed before me, followed by bagels and lox. No, this is not the reverie of an oppressed business traveler who ordinarily considers himself lucky if he gets past security without being snarled at. This not only happened to me last week, it is the way things work for that lucky elite who fly to their destinations by private jet. Last week's column described the rebound in business jets after years of slump. So when a representative from Bombardier's Flexjet fractional business-jet subsidiary contacted me recently and asked if I wanted to take a flight to Flexjet's headquarters in Richardson, Tex. I said yes. When I boarded the plane last Tuesday, I was joining, for one day, a small but growing exodus of business travelers from the world of commercial flight and all its irritations. Companies in the United States own or operate more than 5,000 private jets. Also, manufacturing is rebounding sharply after a post-9/11 slump, with shipments up 21.1 percent in the first quarter of 2005. But let's face it, fellow working stiffs: the people who cruise the skies on company jets are different from you and me. They have more money. I am accustomed to flying, say, from Newark to Los Angeles on Continental Airlines at a round-trip coach fare of $350 or less. The numbers they are looking at are somewhat higher. Consider: Cessna, a unit of Textron, plans to introduce a new model, the Citation Mustang, the lowest-priced entry-level jet. The price is $2.4 million. But most other light jets start in the $4 million to $5 million range, while heavy jets are priced all the way up into the $40 million level and above. Here's a representative figure from NetJets, the leader in the fractional-share market: The cost for a one-eighth share in a midsize six- to eight-passenger, 2,961-mile-range Raytheon Hawker 800XP is $1,581,250. Add to that a $15,204 monthly management fee and an in-flight hourly operating cost of $1,969, and you've got yourself 100 hours a year of pretty swell transportation. NetJets, a unit of Berkshire Hathaway, increased fractional contracts by 28 percent and "earned a modest amount in the United States last year," Berkshire Hathaway's chairman, Warren E. Buffett, said in his company's 2004 annual report. That performance was affected by a shellacking NetJets took from its attempts to sell European business executives on the idea of private jets. Asked how much the company lost in Europe last year, Richard T. Santulli, the chief executive, would say only, "A lot." Yet he reaffirmed his confidence in the venture. "This may sound like one of those Internet economics deals or something like that, but I think we have to sell our way out of trouble in Europe," he said. NetJets actually increased its contracts in Europe by 90 percent last year, to 693, from 364 in 2003. Huge fleet-acquisition and early-stage operational costs account for the continuing losses. Flexjet, a major NetJets competitor, has about 600 fractional owners of its 80-plane fleet of Bombardier jets, and is planning to add 51 new aircraft over the next three years. Flexjet also made a small profit last year, but its expansion plans are deliberately more conservative than NetJets', Michael McQuay, the president of Bombardier Aircraft Services, said at the Flexjet headquarters. Because of intense competition, it is a business with "razor-thin margins" where "it's very difficult to make money," he said. I figured Mr. McQuay as a big-time business-jet flyer, but to my surprise he told me he uses a company jet only when he has to make trips to multiple cities in a day. Most of the time he flies commercial. Why? I asked. "Well, it's a lot cheaper," he replied. On the Road appears each Tuesday. E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com. More Articles in Business &gt;THE morning rush-hour traffic was awful. My flight was scheduled for 7:58 a.m. I had just enough time to make it, assuming I could find the right terminal at the Westchester County Airport, which I couldn't. Skip to next paragraph Chris Gash Business Travel Minute: In-Flight Movies After frantically circling the little airport three times and then somehow ending up on a country lane, I called the terminal from my cellphone. A friendly woman answered and stayed on the line to give me directions as I sheepishly made my way back through the maze of roads. "O.K., I just passed the Quaker meeting house," I said. "Turn left at the next road and you'll be there," she said. "Just leave your car in front with the keys." Anxiously, I pulled the car in front of the Westair terminal. It was now 8:25. I tossed the car keys to a waiting attendant and was escorted onto the airport apron, where a sleek Lear 60 business jet sat, door open and engines revved. I was identified to the pilot, Capt. James Beller, and the first officer, Geoffrey McIntosh, both of whom amiably shook off my apology. On the plane, I buckled into a comfortable leather seat. Within five minutes we were climbing, steep in the sky. A fruit plate was placed before me, followed by bagels and lox. No, this is not the reverie of an oppressed business traveler who ordinarily considers himself lucky if he gets past security without being snarled at. This not only happened to me last week, it is the way things work for that lucky elite who fly to their destinations by private jet. Last week's column described the rebound in business jets after years of slump. So when a representative from Bombardier's Flexjet fractional business-jet subsidiary contacted me recently and asked if I wanted to take a flight to Flexjet's headquarters in Richardson, Tex. I said yes. When I boarded the plane last Tuesday, I was joining, for one day, a small but growing exodus of business travelers from the world of commercial flight and all its irritations. Companies in the United States own or operate more than 5,000 private jets. Also, manufacturing is rebounding sharply after a post-9/11 slump, with shipments up 21.1 percent in the first quarter of 2005. But let's face it, fellow working stiffs: the people who cruise the skies on company jets are different from you and me. They have more money. I am accustomed to flying, say, from Newark to Los Angeles on Continental Airlines at a round-trip coach fare of $350 or less. The numbers they are looking at are somewhat higher. Consider: Cessna, a unit of Textron, plans to introduce a new model, the Citation Mustang, the lowest-priced entry-level jet. The price is $2.4 million. But most other light jets start in the $4 million to $5 million range, while heavy jets are priced all the way up into the $40 million level and above. Here's a representative figure from NetJets, the leader in the fractional-share market: The cost for a one-eighth share in a midsize six- to eight-passenger, 2,961-mile-range Raytheon Hawker 800XP is $1,581,250. Add to that a $15,204 monthly management fee and an in-flight hourly operating cost of $1,969, and you've got yourself 100 hours a year of pretty swell transportation. NetJets, a unit of Berkshire Hathaway, increased fractional contracts by 28 percent and "earned a modest amount in the United States last year," Berkshire Hathaway's chairman, Warren E. Buffett, said in his company's 2004 annual report. That performance was affected by a shellacking NetJets took from its attempts to sell European business executives on the idea of private jets. Asked how much the company lost in Europe last year, Richard T. Santulli, the chief executive, would say only, "A lot." Yet he reaffirmed his confidence in the venture. "This may sound like one of those Internet economics deals or something like that, but I think we have to sell our way out of trouble in Europe," he said. NetJets actually increased its contracts in Europe by 90 percent last year, to 693, from 364 in 2003. Huge fleet-acquisition and early-stage operational costs account for the continuing losses. Flexjet, a major NetJets competitor, has about 600 fractional owners of its 80-plane fleet of Bombardier jets, and is planning to add 51 new aircraft over the next three years. Flexjet also made a small profit last year, but its expansion plans are deliberately more conservative than NetJets', Michael McQuay, the president of Bombardier Aircraft Services, said at the Flexjet headquarters. Because of intense competition, it is a business with "razor-thin margins" where "it's very difficult to make money," he said. I figured Mr. McQuay as a big-time business-jet flyer, but to my surprise he told me he uses a company jet only when he has to make trips to multiple cities in a day. Most of the time he flies commercial. Why? I asked. "Well, it's a lot cheaper," he replied. On the Road appears each Tuesday. E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D81330F932A25756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; EADS AND RAYTHEON TO BID JOINTLY FOR ARMY CONTRACT<date>Published: May 11, 2005</date><text>The European Aeronautic Defense and Space Company, looking for ways to increase its presence in the world's largest military market, will team with the Raytheon Company to bid on a contract for United States Army transport planes. The companies said yesterday that Raytheon would be the prime contractor in the bid, overseeing the program's management, while EADS would assemble and deliver the planes. A Raytheon spokeswoman, Sabrina Steele, said Raytheon was working with EADS in part because no aircraft maker based in the United States is able to fulfill the military's requirements for a midsize transport. The contract would involve about 33 aircraft at a total cost of about $1 billion, Ms. Steele said. EADS North America, based in Arlington, Va., is a wholly owned subsidiary of EADS, but has considerable autonomy. Raytheon is based in Waltham, Mass.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/16/business/16raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon Offers $12 Million to Settle an S.E.C. Inquiry<date>Published: April 16, 2005</date><text>he Raytheon Company offered yesterday to pay $12 million to settle an investigation into its accounting practices by the Securities and Exchange Commission, and said it had reached an agreement to pay $39 million to settle a class-action lawsuit brought by shareholders over a sale of assets in 2000. The settlement, which is subject to S.E.C. approval, would resolve an inquiry into practices at Raytheon's commuter aircraft division from 1997-2001. Advertisement The investigation, which began in 2003, questioned the timing of revenue recognition at the division. Raytheon, primarily a military contractor, restated three years of results in 2000 after changing its policy to recognize aircraft sales at the date of delivery, rather than at the time of sale. The company also said yesterday that its chief financial officer, Edward S. Pliner, and a nonexecutive employee would be put on administrative leave. "The company understands that the S.E.C. staff has made a preliminary decision to recommend that the commission bring actions against two current employees," Raytheon said. Raytheon's vice president and controller, Biggs C. Porter, was named acting chief financial officer. Raytheon will take a $12 million charge in the first quarter for the S.E.C. payment, the company said. It also said the S.E.C. staff had agreed to recommend that commissioners accept its offer to resolve the matter. The company, which did not admit to wrongdoing, also agreed to a cease and desist order concerning violations of certain sections of securities law. The other settlement came over the 2000 sale of Raytheon's construction and engineering business to the Washington Group International. The lawsuit it settled was filed on behalf of investors who bought stock or bonds in the Washington Group, which is based in Boise, Idaho, from April 17, 2000, to March 2, 2001. The company said the settlement, which is subject to court approval, would reduce net earnings for 2005 by 6 cents a share. The Washington Group filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection after it bought the Raytheon unit for $503 million in July 2001. The Washington Group sued Raytheon, accusing it of hiding financial problems at the unit, and Raytheon countersued. Both companies agreed to drop their lawsuits in November 2001. The Washington Group emerged from Chapter 11 in 2002.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/19/business/19nuns.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Shareholders Who Answer to a Higher C.E.O.<date>Published: February 19, 2005</date><text>ecades ago, during a different war, many churches were at the forefront of antiwar efforts, whether it was the high-profile activism of the Berrigan brothers, the two Roman Catholic priests who splattered blood on draft records, or mainstream churches marching against nuclear weapons. While most of that activism has faded, a band of Catholic nuns has remained true to the cause of peace - though today's activism takes them to corporate boardrooms and shareholders' meetings. At the moment, nuns from dozens of orders are completing a series of resolutions to be introduced at shareholder meetings this spring. Companies like Lockheed Martin, General Dynamics or Raytheon are not about to lay down their arms, of course. But military companies, faced with the persistent nuns on their doorsteps, have begun to meet with them, and, in some cases, have begun to see their business in different ways. "We are raising questions that no one asks but us," said Valerie Heinonen, a Catholic nun and consultant on social responsibility in New York. "Part of what we are doing is planting seeds. These companies have an overwhelming influence wherever they operate, and I don't think religious bodies should be separate from that." The shareholder proposals to be offered by the nuns would make any military executive squirm. At the top of their agenda is limiting military sales in countries where the arms can fall into the hands of child soldiers or perpetuate long-running wars. The nuns are also promoting a code of conduct that holds arms makers accountable for the effect of their business on the environment, and on the political and social stability of countries where they operate. Raytheon is one company that has met with the nuns. In Boston last November a delegation of nuns talked to six Raytheon executives, including the director of the company's ethics and environmental division, several lawyers and other executives. The topic was the code of conduct proposal. Discussions between the nuns and the company are continuing, more recently by phone. "We didn't always agree, although it was all respectful," said Jack Kapples, Raytheon's corporate secretary, who attended the meeting. "The nuns had a lot of questions about our business, and there were a couple of questions that our guys thought were interesting. There were questions that led us to think that we hadn't looked at things that way." Sister Mary Ellen Gondeck of the Sisters of St. Joseph of Nazareth in suburban Detroit was at the Raytheon meeting, along with representatives of about half a dozen orders. "If we can dialogue seriously with these companies, that's part of the success," said Sister Mary Ellen, who is the coordinator of the office of peace and justice for her order. "If they are willing to talk to us on our issue, surely we are working toward something." To the nuns, success is measured in small ways - a new willingness of corporate executives to meet with them and a greater backing for the shareholder resolutions they submit each year. Dozens of religious groups, mainly Catholic orders but also some Protestant churches, have submitted shareholder resolutions to the Securities and Exchange Commission that will be put on the ballot of seven military companies this spring. Last year, shareholder proposals from religious orders gained 11 percent of the vote at Textron, nearly 9 percent at Raytheon and 5 percent at General Dynamics. Religious groups say this compares with 2 percent to 3 percent of the vote in years past. Moreover, this vote has come about without any shareholder solicitations or other politicking by the nuns or anyone else. The only way the nuns promote their ideas is when they speak on behalf of their proposals at annual shareholder meetings. "Our resolutions don't win or lose, although that's how a lot of people like to put the spin on it," said Gary Brouse, a program director at the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, a New York-based nonprofit group that promotes corporate social responsibility. "We are trying to illuminate these issues for other people and educate shareholders to these issues." Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3DF1F3CF932A25752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; L-3 PAID $42 MILLION FOR CAMERA DIVISION OF RAYTHEON<date>Published: November 11, 2004</date><text>L-3 Communications, a maker of bomb detectors and military electronics, said yesterday that it had paid $42 million to buy a Raytheon Company unit that makes infrared camera systems for use in public safety, fire, security and transportation markets. L-3 said it hoped to use the unit, which is in Dallas, to expand sales to law-enforcement and industrial customers. L-3, which is based in New York, said the acquisition should add about $50 million to 2005 sales. Raytheon, which is based in Waltham, Mass., said it would keep developing thermal-imaging systems for military customers. Raytheon has been selling commercial businesses to focus on its military operations.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DB163CF930A35752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON'S BOARD APPROVES PLAN FOR ANNUAL ELECTIONS<date>Published: November 3, 2004</date><text>The Raytheon Company, a manufacturer of missiles and industrial electronics, said its board had approved a plan to elect the company's directors annually and would submit the proposal to investors for a vote. Shareholders will decide the issue at the company's annual meeting in May 2005, Raytheon said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/21/nyregion/convention-boss-s-other-hat-lobbying-gop-for-defense-clients.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Convention Boss's Other Hat: Lobbying G.O.P. for Defense Clients<date>Published: August 21, 2004</date><text>For more than a year David Norcross has been a key player for the Bush-Cheney campaign in organizing the Republican National Convention. Mr. Norcross has hired the convention's chief executive, headed the committee responsible for guiding decisions on everything from transportation to entertainment and helped make arrangements for the delegations coming to New York.But Mr. Norcross wears more than one hat.At the same time that he has held this inside-the-party position with access to top government officials, he has also been lobbying the Bush administration on behalf of clients like Raytheon, the defense contractor. Mr. Norcross lobbied the Department of Defense, the Department of the Treasury, the Senate and the House, all on behalf of Raytheon, while he has been the chairman of the convention, according to records on file with the secretary of the Senate.There is nothing illegal about Mr. Norcross taking on both jobs at the same time, especially since his role at the convention is a party position, not a government one. In the past, party chairmen with far greater access to the White House than Mr. Norcross, including the former Republican National Committee chairman, Haley Barbour, and the onetime Democratic National Committee chairman, Ron Brown, have also simultaneously been affiliated with lobbying firms.But Mr. Norcross's dual roles come after Congress has sought to limit corporate influence in politics with stiffer campaign finance laws. But those laws have had the unintended effect of exaggerating the already considerable influence of corporate interests in the Democratic and Republican conventions.''Look, this is how this system works,'' said Fred Wertheimer, executive director of Democracy 21, a Washington-based group that helped push through changes to the campaign finance laws. ''These conventions are the oasis, the last remaining watering hole. They are the ultimate mixer for office holders, lobbyists, corporate and other special interests and big money guys.''And within that environment, Mr. Norcross works at the highest level as a lobbyist representing companies like Boeing and the biotechnology company 20/20 GeneSystems Inc., which is based in Rockville, Md. Mr. Norcross's employer, the Washington-based law firm Blank Rome and its lobbying subsidiary, highlights his party credential in Mr. Norcross's official biography posted on its Web site.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/14/business/company-news-raytheon-to-cut-earnings-by-335-million-to-settle-suit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON TO CUT EARNINGS BY $335 MILLION TO SETTLE SUIT<date>Published: May 14, 2004</date><text>The Raytheon Company said yesterday that it would reduce earnings by $335 million in the second quarter to settle a class-action lawsuit from 1999 that accused the company of misleading investors. The case, filed in the Federal District Court in Massachusetts, accused the company of failing to provide full information concerning its financial performance in a period when its shares fell 58 percent. In March 2002, the court certified the class as investors who bought Raytheon stock from Oct. 7, 1998 to Oct. 12, 1999. Raytheon, based in Waltham, Mass., suffered a series of delays and cost overruns on several defense and engineering contracts, and slowing sales of its products, which caused it to record $638 million of costs in the third quarter of 1999, and reduce its earnings forecasts for 1999 and 2000. The settlement includes a cash payment of $210 million, and warrants for Raytheon stock with a value of $200 million.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/07/business/company-news-raytheon-to-add-1500-jobs-mostly-in-engineering.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON TO ADD 1,500 JOBS, MOSTLY IN ENGINEERING<date>Published: May 07, 2004</date><text>Raytheon said yesterday that it planned to add about 1,500 workers this year, a 1.9 percent increase, to provide engineers for missile-defense and classified-intelligence programs it won recently. The company, based in Waltham, Mass., will have 79,500 workers by the end of this year, up from 78,000 last year, a spokesman said. About 200 of the new jobs will be in Massachusetts and the rest across the country, he said. About 80 percent of the workers hired this year will be engineers, Raytheon said.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/06/business/company-news-lockheed-wins-big-us-missile-contract.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; LOCKHEED WINS BIG U.S. MISSILE CONTRACT<date>Published: May 06, 2004</date><text>The Lockheed Martin Corporation has won an order to develop and build a common missile for the Army, Navy and Marine Corps, a program the company estimates could entail spending of as much as $5.5 billion over 20 years. Lockheed, which is based in Bethesda, Md., beat Boeing and Raytheon in the competition, which is initially worth as much as $1.6 billion, to develop the Joint Common Missile. The order also covers the first two production batches, or as many as 2,700 of 55,000 missiles, the Army said. The military wants to cut costs by fielding a common missile. The new 70-inch missiles would be launched from Army helicopters, Navy fighters and unmanned spy planes, and would replace Raytheon's Maverick and Lockheed's Hellfire missiles. Unlike the old missiles, the new ones would not have to be guided by pilots to their targets.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/28/business/2-military-contractors-report-higher-results.html?ref=raytheoncompany">2 Military Contractors Report Higher Results<date>Published: January 28, 2004</date><text>The Lockheed Martin Corporation and the Raytheon Company, both weapons contractors, said yesterday that fourth-quarter earnings gained because of increased military spending. Both companies said 2004 profit would be hurt by pension costs.Lockheed, based in Bethesda, Md., had a quarterly profit after a loss in the year-earlier period, as sales rose 15 percent. Profit at Raytheon, based in Waltham, Mass., increased 40 percent as sales climbed 9.4 percent.Sales at Lockheed benefited from rising federal spending to develop new jets like the Joint Strike Fighter, while Raytheon was helped as the United States replenished its inventory of missiles and satellite-guided bombs used during the war with Iraq.But the companies said that rising pension costs would counter the effect of higher military spending.Pension costs are likely to mean that 2004 profit at both companies will fall short of analysts' expectations, even as defense spending is set to rise for a seventh consecutive year.Lockheed had a fourth-quarter profit from continuing operations of $344 million, or 77 cents a share, compared with a loss from continuing operations of $342 million, or 76 cents, a year earlier. Sales rose to $8.98 billion from $7.78 billion.Raytheon's quarterly profit from continuing operations rose to $217 million, or 52 cents a share, from $155 million, or 38 cents, a year ago. Sales climbed to $5.1 billion, from $4.7 billion.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/06/business/business-travel-memo-pad.html?ref=raytheoncompany">BUSINESS TRAVEL; MEMO PAD<date>Published: January 06, 2004</date><text>Americans Traveling More This WinterEven with tightened security creating longer lines at domestic airports, Americans are planning to travel more this winter, according to the Travel Industry Association of America.Contributing to that trend has been ''a noticeable increase in business travel'' for the winter, the travel industry trade group said. From December 2003 through Feb. 2004, Americans will take 31.4 million separate business trips, an increase of 3.7 percent from last winter, according to an annual survey by the group. That represents the first growth in business trips since the winter of 1999-2000, when Americans took an estimated 39 million business travel trips.Leisure travel trips are expected to number about 164 million this winter, an increase of about 2 percent over the winter of 2002-3.Trips are defined as noncommuter travel exceeding 50 miles and/or including an overnight stay. About 75 percent of travel is done by automobile and 16 percent by airplane.United Suspends Some Rules in ChicagoO'Hare International Airport in Chicago was socked in with snow and ice Sunday, and weather delays continued yesterday. As a result, UAL's United Airlines has been using e-mail messages to reassure passengers with flights from, to or through O'Hare that ''all rules and restrictions regarding standard change fees, day or time applications, and/or minimum stay or Saturday night stay requirements have been waived'' through Jan. 12 for tickets purchased on or before last Sunday.Customers may rebook on any available flight in the same class of service; tickets must be reissued or revalidated by midnight on the day of the original scheduled departure.NetJets Orders 50 Hawker PlanesNetJets, the big fractional-share business jet company, has ordered 50 Hawker 400XP light jets and 8 Hawker 800XP midsize jets from the Raytheon Company. The total value of the order exceeds $360 million. The new 400XP aircraft -- which has a top speed in excess of 500 miles an hour -- will be offered as an entry-level jet, NetJets said.Some Visitors Facing New U.S. RequirementsNew requirements for fingerprinting and photographing foreign nationals from most countries will probably add "only seconds" to visitors' processing times at airports and seaports, the Department of Homeland Security said yesterday as the program went into effect.Citizens of the following countries belonging to the Visa Waiver Program are exempt from the new security measures for visits of up to 90 days: Andorra, Austria, Australia, Belgium, Britain, Brunei, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Liechtenstein, Luxembourg, Monaco, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Portugal, San Marino, Singapore, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, and Switzerland. JOE SHARKEY</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/04/business/us-contract-to-northrop.html?ref=raytheoncompany">U.S. Contract to Northrop<date>Published: December 04, 2003</date><text>The Defense Department awarded a $4.5 billion contract on Wednesday to a Northrop Grumman subsidiary to develop a weapon that will destroy enemy missiles shortly after they are launched.The eight-year contract for Northrop's space and mission systems subsidiary is for development of an interceptor to destroy a missile in its boost phase, before it reaches space.Raytheon, as a subcontractor, is expected to build the actual interceptor. Northrop Grumman beat Lockheed Martin for the project.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/03/us/knock-wait-15-seconds-then-break-in-justices-rule.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Knock, Wait 15 Seconds, Then Break In, Justices Rule<date>Published: December 03, 2003</date><text>The police need not wait more than 15 or 20 seconds after knocking before they break down a door to search a residence for drugs, the Supreme Court ruled unanimously on Tuesday.The decision overturned a ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco, which invalidated the search of a Las Vegas drug dealer's apartment on the ground that the brief interval between knocking and forcibly entering was constitutionally unreasonable.Justice David H. Souter said Tuesday that the reasonableness of a forced entry depended on the circumstances of each case, rather than on a particular formula or fixed time limit. In this case, he said, the Las Vegas police, who had a search warrant and were assisted by federal agents, knew that the suspect, LaShawn L. Banks, was likely to have drugs in his apartment.''We think that after 15 or 20 seconds without a response, police could fairly suspect that cocaine would be gone if they were reticent any longer,'' Justice Souter said.The decision added some content to recent Supreme Court rulings that referred in only general terms to the requirement that the police make their presence known before entering a residence to execute a search warrant. The question was ''how to go about applying the standard of reasonableness to the length of time police with a warrant must wait before entering without permission after knocking and announcing their intent,'' Justice Souter said.The answer was not one likely to provide much comfort to criminal suspects. Mr. Banks argued that he had not refused to open the door, but rather was in the shower and did not hear the police, making the officers' rapid entry all the more unreasonable in his view.But the fact of the shower was irrelevant, Justice Souter said. ''As for the shower, it is enough to say that the facts known to the police are what count in judging reasonable waiting time,'' he said.Most important, the decision said, was the fact that this was a drug search, and that drugs can disappear within seconds down a sink or toilet. ''It is imminent disposal, not travel time to the entrance, that governs when the police may reasonably enter,'' Justice Souter said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/04/business/company-news-raytheon-workers-accept-labor-contract.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON WORKERS ACCEPT LABOR CONTRACT<date>Published: November 04, 2003</date><text>Workers at a Raytheon Company plant in Tucson, Ariz., that makes Tomahawk cruise missiles voted to accept a revised labor contract, averting a strike that was to begin yesterday. The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Local 933, which represents about 2,100 of the plant's 10,000 employees, voted 50.3 percent to 49.7 percent to accept the contract, the union said. Union members had voted on Oct. 26 to strike, subject to a seven-day ''cooling off'' period, after rejecting a proposal that would have increased their share of health insurance premiums. Terms of the revised contract were not immediately available. Raytheon is based in Waltham, Mass.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/28/business/company-news-workers-plan-strike-at-raytheon-missile-plant.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; WORKERS PLAN STRIKE AT RAYTHEON MISSILE PLANT<date>Published: October 28, 2003</date><text>Workers at a Raytheon Company plant in Tucson that makes the Tomahawk cruise missile have voted to strike next Monday after rejecting a contract that would have raised their health care costs. The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Local 933 represents 2,100 of the 10,000 workers at the plant, said Robert Martinez, the union local's business manager. The contract would have increased workers' share of health insurance premiums to 15 percent from 8.2 percent, he said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/business/company-news-raytheon-swings-to-loss-and-trims-04-forecast.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON SWINGS TO LOSS AND TRIMS '04 FORECAST<date>Published: October 24, 2003</date><text>The military contractor Raytheon Company swung to a loss in the third quarter, cut its outlook for 2004 and disclosed significant problems in a unit that makes air-traffic control and communications equipment. The developments disclosed yesterday raise challenges for the chief executive, William H. Swanson, who is in his fourth month on the job. Raytheon reported a loss of $35 million, or 8 cents a share, in contrast to a profit of $147 million, or 36 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding one-time items, the company would have earned $21 million, or 5 cents a share, compared with $228 million, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts expected the company to earn 43 cents a share. Sales rose 7 percent, to $4.38 billion.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/14/world/the-struggle-for-iraq-weapons-iraqi-arms-caches-cited-in-attacks.html?ref=raytheoncompany">THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: WEAPONS; IRAQI ARMS CACHES CITED IN ATTACKS<date>Published: October 14, 2003</date><text>The two most recent suicide bombings here and virtually every other attack on American soldiers and Iraqis were carried out with explosives and matÃ©riel taken from Saddam Hussein's former weapons dumps, which are much larger than previously estimated and remain, for the most part, unguarded by American troops, allied officials said Monday.The problem of uncounted and unguarded weapons sites is considerably greater than has previously been stated, a senior allied official said.The American military now says that Iraq's army had nearly one million tons of weapons and ammunition, which is half again as much as the 650,000 tons that Gen. John P. Abizaid, the senior American commander in the Persian Gulf region, estimated only two weeks ago.In separate interviews, the officials, civilian and military and from different countries, expressed concern about the potential of attackers with access to the weapons dumps to nurture violence and insecurity.The officials said they were receiving intelligence about the attacks -- who is carrying them out and where they are getting their munitions -- from a variety of sources. Among the most fruitful, they said, have been would-be bombers who were stopped before carrying out their missions.The officials were deliberately vague about how many attacks had been thwarted, for fear of alarming an already jumpy populace here. But one of them said several car bombings had been prevented in recent weeks, suggesting that the number was more than just a handful.Officials also say that Mr. Hussein stockpiled at least 5,000 shoulder-fired missiles, and that fewer than a third have been recovered. They fear that many have been smuggled out of the country and may have fallen into the hands of terrorist organizations.There are not enough American soldiers here to do the job of finding the weapons and securing them until they can be destroyed, the officials said. A private American company, Raytheon, has been awarded a contract to destroy the weapons, but it will not begin work until December, one official said.''There are more sites than we can guard,'' an allied official said. ''We are destroying them as fast as we can, but we are finding more and more every day.''One of the largest in the country, covering more than 10 square miles, is near Al Musaiyib, 20 miles south of Baghdad, and is still not adequately guarded, an official said this week.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/02/us/man-rescued-at-south-pole-plans-to-stay-close-to-home.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Man Rescued At South Pole Plans to Stay Close to Home<date>Published: October 02, 2003</date><text>Correction AppendedThe ailing American worker whose evacuation from the South Pole was delayed for almost a week because of dangerous winds and snow said Tuesday that his medical ordeal had prompted him to stay closer to home, at least for a while.In the first interviews he has given since he was stranded at the Amundsen-Scott South Pole Station, Barry McCue, 51, recalled how he was stricken with such intense pain on Aug. 25 that he buckled and crawled to his bunker.''It just came right out of the clear blue sky and hit me like a two-by-four,'' Mr. McCue, an environmental safety and health coordinator for the Raytheon Polar Services Company based in Denver, said from his daughter's house in Braidwood, Ill., a Chicago suburb.''The doctor was pretty worried at first,'' Mr. McCue said. ''He thought I was having a heart attack because I was having chest pains.''After an examination, the lone doctor at the base gave Mr. McCue some medication, which diminished the pain for a few days.But a week later, Mr. McCue said, the pain returned, prompting a telemedical conference with doctors in Denver, Baltimore, Boston and Galveston, Tex.Eight doctors viewed Mr. McCue's ultrasounds online, and concluded that he had gallstones.Mr. McCue said he wanted the doctor to remove his gallbladder, ''but he couldn't, it was just him and his physician's assistant.''''They could've done mitigating things to help, but couldn't solve it.''The diagnosis set off a series of events that culminated in a perilous rescue mission in the total darkness of the Antarctic winter on Sept. 21.The effort had been delayed for days because of blowing snow and strong winds, but two turboprop planes finally arrived at the base and flew Mr. McCue to Rothera Air Station on the coast of Antarctica, then to Chile's southernmost city, Punta Arenas, where he was put on a Lear jet to Houston.His journey ended in Denver, where doctors performed two operations, one to take out his gallbladder one week ago and another to remove stones from his bile duct. He was released on Monday.''The doctors looking at it from the U.S. had to decide whether I could make it to the first week of November when it's safer to fly in,'' Mr. McCue said. ''By getting me out early, they put a lot of people at risk. You don't fly an airplane over the South Pole unless you have a good reason.''Correction: October 9, 2003, Thursday An article on Thursday about the medical ordeal and rescue of Barry McCue, an American worker at the South Pole, misstated the light conditions at the time of his evacuation, on Sept. 21. Visibility was low, but darkness was not total.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/16/us/national-briefing-science-and-health-weather-delays-rescue-in-antarctica.html?ref=raytheoncompany">National Briefing | Science And Health: Weather Delays Rescue In Antarctica<date>Published: September 16, 2003</date><text>Snow and winds gusting to more than 45 miles an hour grounded two planes and delayed the rescue of a seriously ill man working at the United States' South Pole research station. The Twin Otter planes, which are built to fly in rough weather, were flown over the weekend from the southern tip of Chile to the Rothera air station on Antarctica, where they were forced to wait because of bad weather, said Valerie Carroll, a spokeswoman for Raytheon Polar Services. The pilots expected the storm to ease and were hoping to fly to the South Pole today. The ill employee, whose name is being withheld, works for Raytheon, which manages the United States Antarctic research program.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/14/business/market-watch-greed-is-still-good-at-some-companies.html?ref=raytheoncompany">MARKET WATCH; Greed Is Still Good At Some Companies<date>Published: September 14, 2003</date><text>Correction AppendedEXECUTIVE greed has become so commonplace that it threatens to join death and taxes among life's grim inevitabilities. When set against the continued layoffs hitting employees across corporate America, however, the cupidity of some executives can take even the most jaded shareholder's breath away.A review of recent proxy materials by Equilar Inc., a compensation analysis firm in San Mateo, Calif., identified some of this year's top graspers. They include top brass at Raytheon, the Williams Companies and Hecla Mining.Not surprisingly, the deals involve stock options. As we all know, options provide a big incentive to bolster share prices and have turned many executives into stock promoters.Some civic-minded types have suggested that boards require options to be held for the long term, not cashed in immediately. On the other side of the fence are boards that allow option grants to be available for early vesting if the underlying stock price reaches a certain level within a specified time. Because of the potential for manipulation that surrounds such deals, most companies no longer offer such arrangements. But holdouts remain.Consider the grants made last year at Raytheon, the military contractor. A plan to reward ''key employees' performance'' at the company specified that when Raytheon's shares rose 21 percent and stayed at least that high for 20 consecutive trading days, one-third of the options vest.On Friday, Raytheon's stock closed at $31.91, below the exercise price of $32.15 on the date of the option grant in January 2002. Raytheon, however, had a period in spring 2002 when its stock stayed above $38.90, the level required to accelerate vesting. As a result, one-third of the options granted probably vested.A Raytheon spokesman said: ''That plan was adopted when executive retention was an issue. No value for executives is created unless shareholder value is equally enhanced.''At the Williams Companies, the pipeline owner, options granted in 2002 were subject to a vesting schedule of one-third of the grant each year. But they also had an acceleration clause based on the company's stock reaching an undisclosed target level. In the Williams case, the stock had only to trade at that level for 5 out of 10 business days.By March 2002, one month after the options were granted at a strike price of $15.86, Williams's stock had risen almost 55 percent. It is unclear how many options vested early.Correction: September 21, 2003, Sunday The Market Watch column last Sunday, about companies that allow executives to exercise stock options early if the price of the underlying shares rises enough, referred incorrectly to the status of a grant made last year by the Williams Companies. None of those options have vested; the number is not undetermined.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/10/business/company-news-sec-inquiry-on-raytheon-accounting-is-made-formal.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; S.E.C. INQUIRY ON RAYTHEON ACCOUNTING IS MADE FORMAL<date>Published: September 10, 2003</date><text>The Raytheon Company, a manufacturer of military equipment and commercial aircraft, said the Securities and Exchange Commission has made formal its investigation of a unit that makes Beech Jet and King Air aircraft. The S.E.C., which began an informal inquiry in January, is reviewing accounting at the company's commuter aircraft business from 1997 to 2001. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., said it was cooperating with the agency. A formal order allows the agency to subpoena documents and compel testimony from witnesses at the company and third parties, like customers. Raytheon announced the investigation after the close of market trading. Its stock fell 14 cents, to $32.46 a share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/06/business/technology-briefing-hardware-ibm-and-raytheon-in-chip-deal.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Technology Briefing | Hardware: I.B.M. and Raytheon In Chip Deal<date>Published: August 06, 2003</date><text>I.B.M. said yesterday that its custom chip and chip system design and engineering services group had signed a five-year deal with the Raytheon Company that could be worth up to $100 million. I.B.M., which is based in Armonk, N.Y., and Raytheon said in a joint statement that they would create a project office in Lexington, Mass., where Raytheon is based.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/27/business/company-news-delay-is-forcing-raytheon-to-take-90-million-charge.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; DELAY IS FORCING RAYTHEON TO TAKE $90 MILLION CHARGE<date>Published: June 27, 2003</date><text>The Raytheon Company, the defense contractor, will record costs of $90 million in the second quarter because completion of a power plant in Massachusetts will be delayed by as much as a month. Raytheon said it would not be able to complete the plant, the Fore River plant in Weymouth, Mass., by June 30 because of unspecified technical issues. The plant will be finished in July, Raytheon said. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., still expects to meet or exceed its second-quarter forecast for profit, excluding some costs, of 24 to 26 cents a share. Costs for the plant and another that was recently completed have more than quadrupled to more than $1.3 billion. Raytheon sold the unit that was building the plants to Washington Group International Inc. in 2000 and was forced to complete the projects itself when Washington Group declared bankruptcy a year later.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/17/business/company-news-lockheed-martin-and-raytheon-link-up-to-make-missiles.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; LOCKHEED MARTIN AND RAYTHEON LINK UP TO MAKE MISSILES<date>Published: May 17, 2003</date><text>The military contractors Lockheed Martin and Raytheon said yesterday that they had formed a joint venture to design and build missiles for the Army in an effort to cut costs and time. The joint venture, called NetFires, is expected to obtain contracts totaling as much as $2 billion over the next decade to develop attack missiles and a container launching system. ''The cost and time associated with development and production will be lower than if two companies were doing the work independently,'' said Jennifer Allen, a spokeswoman for Raytheon, which is based in Lexington, Mass. Lockheed is based in Bethesda, Md.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/24/business/company-news-raytheon-chief-says-he-is-leaving-his-post-on-july-1.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON CHIEF SAYS HE IS LEAVING HIS POST ON JULY 1<date>Published: April 24, 2003</date><text>Daniel Burnham, who has tried to return the Raytheon Corporation to its core military business during five years of leading the company, announced yesterday that he would resign effective July 1. He will be succeeded by William H. Swanson, 54, who is a 31-year veteran of the company and is its current president. ''It's time now for a new, more personal phase in my life,'' Mr. Burnham told shareholders at Raytheon's annual meeting at its Lexington, Mass., headquarters. Warren Rudman, Raytheon's lead director and a former United States senator, said the choice was Mr. Burnham's. Mr. Burnham, 56, arrived from AlliedSignal in 1998. Raytheon reduced its debt to less than $7 billion from $13 billion while Mr. Burnham was chief exectutive.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/23/business/2-military-contractors-post-gains-in-quarter.html?ref=raytheoncompany">2 Military Contractors Post Gains in Quarter<date>Published: April 23, 2003</date><text>Lockheed Martin and Raytheon reported increases in first-quarter sales yesterday, led by demand for fighter jets, missiles and radar products.Net income at Lockheed, which is based in Bethesda, Md., rose 15 percent because of increased revenue from work on the F/A-22 fighter jet and Joint Strike Fighter programs. Raytheon, the maker of Stinger and Tomahawk missiles, said profit in all military units rose.The war in Iraq increased the demand from the United States military for missiles, radar products and aircraft development, and that is leading to new and extended order contracts, analysts said. They added that the sales growth exceeded estimates.''The quality of earnings for this group is pretty high,'' said Keith Goddard, director of research at Capital Advisors Inc.Profit in Raytheon's missile systems unit rose 7.4 percent after gaining orders from the Navy for the new version of the Tomahawk, called the Tactical Tomahawk, and an order from the Air Force for Paveway guided bombs.Shares of Lockheed rose $3.30, or 7.3 percent, to $48.55 at 4 p.m. in New York Stock Exchange composite trading. Raytheon rose 92 cents, or 3.2 percent, to $29.75.Lockheed said net income rose to $250 million, or 55 cents a share, from $218 million, or 49 cents, a year earlier. Sales jumped 18 percent, to $7.05 billion, the company said.Raytheon said first-quarter profit from continuing operations fell 26 percent, to $111 million, or 27 cents a share, from $149 million, or 37 cents. Sales rose 7.7 percent, to $4.2 billion from $3.9 billion. Noncash pension expenses cut earnings by 14 cents a share, the company said.Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., had net income of $95 million, or 23 cents a share, in the first quarter in contrast to a net loss of $583 million, or $1.44 a share, in the year-earlier period.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/16/us/slump-in-plane-travel-grounds-wichita-world-s-air-capital.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Slump in Plane Travel Grounds Wichita, World's 'Air Capital'<date>Published: April 16, 2003</date><text>Correction AppendedTheir income from the aircraft industry has evaporated. Their split-level home of six years, in a neighborhood sliced from farmland, has a Coldwell Banker ''For Sale'' sign in front. Deborah Salter has sold her jewelry. Her husband, Jim, has sold his truck, guns, tools and lawn mower.The Salters are moving on, to what they do not know.Stunned by how their life has unraveled, Mrs. Salter looks to her husband for some solution. ''I'm trying to get answers out of him,'' she said. ''He doesn't have any answers.''Families all over Wichita share the Salters' plight. With its four commercial and general aviation plane makers, Boeing, Cessna, Raytheon and Bombardier Aerospace, the city calls itself the Air Capital of the World. One in four of its workers, about twice the national average, works in a factory, two-thirds making planes. The aircraft workers earn an average of $55,642 a year.But the plunge in air travel since Sept. 11, 2001 -- worsened in recent weeks by war -- has struck Wichita especially hard, coming on top of the general economic downturn and the periodic slowdowns normally experienced by the aircraft industry.Since the attacks, about 11,000 aircraft workers in Wichita have been laid off, leaving about 37,000. In March, Cessna, the last to order mass layoffs, said it would let 1,200 workers go in May. It will shut its plants for seven weeks in June and July, furloughing 6,000 more of the 8,000 still on the payroll. The unemployment rate, 6.8 percent in January, has doubled since the late 1990's.The aircraft business in Wichita has always been turbulent, sinking deeper than the economy in recessions, as in the early 1990's, and then rebounding. This time around, too, some jobs will come back. Cessna plans a 500-employee aircraft servicing plant. But more than in the past, the companies have moved their production abroad, and are reducing production space.''They're shrinking the footprint of several plants and selling off parts,'' said Bob Brewer, local manager of Boeing's engineers' union, the Society of Professional Engineering Employees in Aerospace. ''We've never seen anything like that before.''Correction: April 22, 2003, Tuesday An article on April 16 about the severity of the economic slump in Wichita, Kan., misstated the amount of food distributed there last year by the Living Word Outreach food pantry. It was 1.3 million pounds, not tons.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/10/business/competing-for-work-in-postwar-iraq.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Competing for Work in Postwar Iraq<date>Published: April 10, 2003</date><text>The roster of United States companies that have received potentially lucrative contracts for work in the Iraq region continues to grow despite a demand this week by Democrats in Congress for an independent review of the process for awarding such deals.The most recent winners, for work that could total as much as $300 million, are the Fluor Corporation, based in Aliso Viejo, Calif.; Washington Group International, in Boise, Idaho; and the Parini Corporation, in Framingham, Mass. Last week, each company received a contract from the Army Corps of Engineers to provide up to $100 million worth of work to the military in the region. The tasks could include repairing roads and bridges, replacing damaged windows and doors and building barracks for military personnel.According to unsuccessful bidders, the Raytheon Corporation in Lexington, Mass., and the Kellogg, Brown &amp; Root unit of the Halliburton Corporation in Houston have received a $30 million contract from the Defense Threat Reduction Agency to dismantle and neutralize any chemical or nuclear weapons found in the region. Neither Raytheon nor the agency would confirm any contract.But there is still no word on who will win the grand prize in the current round of bidding: a wide-ranging $600 million reconstruction contract that will be awarded by the United States Agency for International Development. The contract will cover early work on rebuilding Iraq's essential infrastructure, including airports, roads, water and power systems, schools and hospitals. The agency previously said it had narrowed the bidders to two finalists and would announce a decision by the end of last week.The Bechtel Group of San Francisco and Fluor have both been mentioned as finalists, although neither the companies nor the agency would confirm that status. But an executive of the Parsons Corporation in Pasadena, Calif., said that her company had not been eliminated from consideration.And although Halliburton announced publicly last week that it had not bid to be the lead contractor on the work, other bidders say that Halliburton is named in procurement documents as an integral subcontractor in the Parsons bid. Neither company would confirm that arrangement, but Halliburton's latest public statement on the contract noted that the company remained ''a potential subcontractor.''</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/10/technology/news-watch-hot-properties-inspiring-jealousy-by-day-lighting-the-road-by-night.html?ref=raytheoncompany">NEWS WATCH: HOT PROPERTIES; Inspiring Jealousy by Day, Lighting the Road by Night<date>Published: April 10, 2003</date><text>The Hummer H1 sports-utility vehicle resembles its military sibling, the Humvee, in many respects. But there's one feature that the civilian model lacks beyond, of course, weapons systems. AM General, which makes both versions of the vehicle, does not sell a night-vision system as a factory option on the civilian model.Now the commercial infrared division of Raytheon has developed NightDriver, a system for the Hummer H1 that it says will allow motorists to see three to five times farther down a dark road.Like a factory-option system that Raytheon makes for Cadillac, the system is based on an infrared camera mounted on the front of the vehicle. An electronic projector inside the camera beams an image of the camera's findings through a mirror onto a section of the windshield within the driver's field of vision.Chris Bade, president of Raytheon Commercial Infrared (www.raytheoninfrared.com), said that Raytheon did not work to hide the camera on the Hummer. ''It's almost a badge of honor,'' he said. The system costs $5,000, including installation by an authorized Hummer dealer. Ian Austen</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/03/business/factory-orders-fall-military-sales-rise.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Factory Orders Fall; Military Sales Rise<date>Published: April 03, 2003</date><text>Factory orders dropped 1.5 percent in February, the Commerce Department reported today, adding to suggestions that the approach of the Iraq war took a toll on manufacturing and the economy.The decrease, reflecting reduced demand for commercial aircraft, computers and chemicals, came after a 1.7 percent gain in January. Excluding transportation, orders fell 2 percent, the largest drop in a year. Bookings for military goods surged 27.1 percent, the third rise in four months.The drop in orders over all caused manufacturing to contract last month for the first time since October. Companies trimmed orders and factories reduced production as consumer purchases slowed in January and February.''There was a wait-and-see mentality among businesses'' as the threat of war approached, said Stuart Hoffman, chief economist at the PNC Financial Services Group in Pittsburgh.Manufacturing accounts for one-seventh of the economy and employs more than 16 million people. Economists had expected factory orders to fall 0.8 percent.The decline was the largest since a 2.4 percent drop in September.Factory inventories expanded 0.4 percent in February after a 0.1 percent gain in January. With shipments falling, the inventory-to-shipments ratio, a gauge of how long goods remain in warehouses, rose to 1.34 months from 1.32 months.The drop in February orders is probably ''setting the stage for a pullback in output in March, especially since inventories began to rise rapidly in February,'' said Jade Zelnik, chief economist at RBS Greenwich Capital in Greenwich, Conn.The decrease in orders was led by a 1.6 percent drop in bookings for durable goods, those intended to last at least three years. Orders for commercial aircraft fell 27 percent.Military capital goods were 23.3 percent higher in February than a year earlier. Raytheon said it would accelerate production of a new version of its Tomahawk cruise missile.Bookings for military communications equipment surged 14 percent after a 10.3 percent rise.Industrial machinery orders plummeted 29 percent, to $2.8 billion. Orders for computers dropped 17 percent, to $3.9 billion.Orders for nonmilitary capital goods excluding aircraft, a proxy for business investment in equipment and software, decreased 3.7 percent after a 5.2 percent rise the previous month. Shipments of capital goods, which are used in calculating the gross domestic product, declined 3.1 percent after gaining 3.1 percent.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/26/business/company-news-raytheon-might-have-to-reduce-backlog-of-orders.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON MIGHT HAVE TO REDUCE BACKLOG OF ORDERS<date>Published: March 26, 2003</date><text>The Raytheon Company said that it might be forced to reduce its backlog of aircraft orders by $1.75 billion because of a depressed market and delays in the introduction of new business aircraft. In its annual report to the Securities and Exchange Commission, Raytheon said on Monday that a $900 million order for its new business jet, the Hawker Horizon, could be reworked or canceled because of market conditions and developmental delays. It did not name the company that placed the order. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., also said it might have to take out of backlog $850 million in aircraft ordered by Flight Options, a joint venture based in Cleveland that arranges the shared use of business jets.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/12/business/company-news-maker-of-flight-displays-wants-refund-from-raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; MAKER OF FLIGHT DISPLAYS WANTS REFUND FROM RAYTHEON<date>Published: March 12, 2003</date><text>L-3 Communications Holdings, a maker of flight displays for the U-2 spy plane, wants a $100 million refund on its $1.2 billion purchase of a Raytheon Company unit to cover cost overruns at the business. L-3's audit of the unit, Aircraft Integration Systems, which it bought a year ago, found $86 million in extra costs to complete contracts because of circumstances that arose before the acquisition, L-3 said in its annual Securities and Exchange Commission filing. A Raytheon spokesman, Jim Fetig, said the company disputes L-3's claim. L-3 is based in New York and Raytheon is based in Lexington, Mass.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/07/business/shares-of-raytheon-fall-after-warning.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Shares of Raytheon Fall After Warning<date>Published: March 07, 2003</date><text>Shares of Raytheon fell today after the company, maker of Tomahawk and Patriot missiles, warned that its results would miss Wall Street forecasts.Raytheon warned after the close of trading on Wednesday that higher pension costs would cause 2004 earnings to miss average analyst forecasts by as much as 13 percent.''Certainly, it's a matter of concern for analysts and portfolio managers, particularly for larger, older companies that have established pension plans,'' said Dean Gulis, fund manager for Loomis Sayles &amp; Company. ''For some companies, it can be a multiyear issue.''Raytheon said higher estimated pension costs of 30 cents a share would push earnings from continuing operations in 2004 to $1.60 to $1.70 a diluted share, below the $1.83 a share forecast by analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Raytheon shares fell $1.49 yesterday, or 5.5 percent, to $25.42 a share.Raytheon has struggled with delays at two Massachusetts power plants. It said labor costs at the plants would increase a fourth-quarter 2002 charge by $65 million to $75 million. The previous charge, first announced in January, had been $197 million.Military stocks soared in 2002 as investors hoped a buildup for a possible war with Iraq would increase profits, but many of those stocks have erased gains as investors have taken profits.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/28/business/company-news-raytheon-to-pay-25-million-to-settle-export-claims.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON TO PAY $25 MILLION TO SETTLE EXPORT CLAIMS<date>Published: February 28, 2003</date><text>The military contractor Raytheon agreed yesterday to pay $25 million to settle accusations that it illegally tried to export communications equipment to Pakistan from 1990 to 1997. The allegations, dismissed as part of the settlement, concern Raytheon's attempts to sell its troposcatter radio system to Pakistan, which is prohibited from receiving United States arms exports under the 1990 Pressler Amendment. In the settlement, Raytheon ''acknowledges and regrets that it erred in failing to seek from the U.S. State Department a determination of whether the radio system was commercial or military.'' Raytheon said it denied that it intentionally violated any export laws.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/17/world/threats-responses-economy-military-towns-contractors-windfall-not-doing-much.html?ref=raytheoncompany">THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE ECONOMY; In Military Towns, Contractors' Windfall Is Not Doing Much Trickling Down<date>Published: February 17, 2003</date><text>Velma Maxson works 15 hours of overtime a week at Raytheon's four-square-mile complex here, molding fiberglass components for radar-packed air-to-air missiles. At Don Martin's precision machine shop, Competitive Engineering, bad memories of the dot-com crash have faded with orders trickling in from Raytheon, Honeywell and Boeing.But Steven Dreher had to shut down his Tucson butcher shop and deli in December. A few days after the terrorist attacks on Sept. 11, 2001, guards at the Davis-Monthan Air Force Base here turned away Mr. Dreher's truck, with 1,400 pounds of sausage for a pilots' cookout, and after that the catered-party business dried up.Outside the base, Mark Aldulaimi's used-car lot has no shoppers. ''Everybody's scared,'' Mr. Aldulaimi said. ''Nobody wants to spend their money.''In Washington and on Wall Street, the experts are speculating about what a war with Iraq might do to the nation's economy. But the effects are already being felt in cities where military bases and weapons plants are economic mainstays, and the news is grim.A wartime economy might be good for merchants of missiles and rockets, but it is putting a damper on everything else.Local businesses remain in the doldrums, with many fearing that war and the continuing threat of terrorism will only make things worse.In Tucson, for example, and in other military towns large and small, the march to battle has kept military contractors humming, but their windfall has not been widely shared. They are doing more without hiring many workers or spending more money locally.The military base and contractors in Tucson, with a population of 514,000, are busy cranking up. But they are islands in a sea of worry and indecision. The word for the Tucson economy, said Marshall J. Vest, the director of economic research at the University of Arizona's business school here, ''is 'hesitation.' ''Unemployment, normally about 3 percent here, is close to 5 percent. Shopping has fallen off, and with it the city's sales tax collections. The roads need work. Tucson's sunny and dry high season is well under way, but tourism -- as vital a part of the economy as the base and the military contractors -- is down.''They're all struggling -- premium restaurants, hotels, resorts,'' said Mayor Robert E. Walkup, a former aerospace executive.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/25/business/weapons-producers-report-strong-increases-in-sales.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Weapons Producers Report Strong Increases in Sales<date>Published: January 25, 2003</date><text>With war talk in the air and the United States increasing its military budget, the nation's largest weapons makers reported strong sales yesterday for the quarter and the year.The Lockheed Martin Corporation, the largest military contractor, reported an 11 percent increase in 2002 sales. The Raytheon Company, which makes Stinger and Tomahawk missiles, reported that its fourth-quarter operating profit doubled.While net earnings at both companies were hurt by one-time write-offs, their core product lines of armaments that have been used in Afghanistan and are being prepared for possible use in Iraq gave both companies solid cash flow and strong underlying growth.At Lockheed, revenue grew 11 percent in 2002, to $26.6 billion. Net income for 2002 was $500 million, or $1.11 a share, in contrast to a net loss of $1 billion, or $2.42 a share, in 2001. Without one-time charges, the company estimates, it would have earned $2.58 a share in 2002.For the quarter, Lockheed narrowed its loss to $347 million, or 77 cents a share, on revenue of $7.8 billion. That compares with a loss of $1.5 billion, or $3.49 a share, a year earlier. The latest results reflected some one-time charges, including a $504 million write-down on telecommunications investments and $200 million for space-related ventures.But the bright light at Lockheed came from many of its profitable bread-and-butter products, like the F-16 fighter jet. It benefited as well from increased spending on electronic surveillance and missile-control systems by the United States as it continues its crackdown on terrorism and prepares for a possible Iraqi invasion.''Our fourth quarter, like the entire year, was a solid one for the corporation,'' said Vance D. Coffman, the chief executive. These sentiments were echoed by analysts, who repeatedly praised the company for its strong showing in a conference call yesterday morning.Lockheed's ''underlying earnings growth looks on track,'' Nick Fothergill, an analyst with Banc of America Securities who is based in London, said in an interview. As far as future growth, Mr. Fothergill noted, ''they are going to be delivering a lot of combat aircraft over the next two years.''Some were more skeptical. Robert Friedman, an analyst for Standard &amp; Poor's, cautioned that investors ''should not get caught up in short-term results.'' Lockheed's current return on equity of about 8 percent is ''no great shakes,'' said Mr. Friedman, who said he thought Lockheed shares were overvalued.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/14/business/raytheon-discloses-inquiry-by-sec-into-its-accounting.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon Discloses Inquiry by S.E.C. Into Its Accounting<date>Published: January 14, 2003</date><text>Shares of the Raytheon Company fell sharply today after the military contractor disclosed that federal regulators had begun an informal investigation into accounting practices at its commuter aircraft business.Raytheon said the investigation, by the Securities and Exchange Commission, related to ''the timing of revenue recognition at its Raytheon Aircraft subsidiary in the period 1997 to 2001.''The company, which is based in Lexington, Mass., said that it considered the practices appropriate and that it would cooperate fully.The disclosure came as a federal prosecutor in Kansas announced that the same subsidiary, the Wichita Raytheon Aircraft Company, had paid $3.99 million to settle accusations that it incorrectly billed the cost of aircraft product liability insurance to the Department of Defense from 1988 to 1999.Raytheon shares fell $1.57, to $29.85.Paul Nisbet, an analyst at JSA Research, said the inquiry appeared to involve the same issues raised in 2000, when Raytheon changed its accounting procedures to report revenue only upon final delivery of aircraft and restated its financial results for 1997 to 2000. ''To me it was a tempest in a teapot when it happened and it didn't amount to much,'' he said. ''I'm at a loss as to what's happening this time and why it's come up again.''The insurance settlement concerned accusations that the Raytheon division overcharged the Pentagon from 1988 to 1999 by billing it for liability insurance using an allocation method that did not comply with accounting standards. Raytheon changed the practice on Jan. 1, 2000.Mr. Nisbet said the $3.99 million fine would have little effect on the company, which posted more than $4 billion in third-quarter revenue.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/10/us/crash-may-be-tied-to-servicing-mistake.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Crash May Be Tied to Servicing Mistake<date>Published: January 10, 2003</date><text>Federal investigators looking into the crash of a commuter plane here on Wednesday say they suspect that an error was made little more than 24 hours before in servicing the system that controlled the aircraft's pitch.The investigators said today that the plane's flight data recorder showed that it climbed soon after takeoff at a neck-straining angle of 52 degrees before it crashed, killing all 21 people on board.The data recorder also shows, they said, that the pitch-control system had been acting somewhat abnormally for eight flights after the maintenance work, although no one reported a problem before the plane crashed on the ninth.Investigators are also looking into the question of whether the plane was overloaded or, even if not, was carrying too much weight in the back, causing the nose to pitch up.According to the manifest, it was loaded to within 100 pounds or so of its maximum takeoff weight, 17,120 pounds. But with the approval of the Federal Aviation Administration, the practice of the airline, Air Midwest, was to assume that the average suitcase weighed 25 pounds; if the average was much higher, the investigators said, the plane would have been both tail-heavy and overweight.The abnormal pitch-control operation detected by the flight data recorder may have become progressively worse with each flight after the system was worked on, the investigators said, or it could have become suddenly worse if the plane was heavily loaded. ''If you have a light airplane, meaning not a lot of passengers, not a lot of fuel, not a lot of baggage, it behaves differently,'' said John Goglia, the member of the National Transportation Safety Board who is leading the inquiry.Among the long list of questions to be considered by the investigators, Mr. Goglia said, is whether the plane was carrying a heavy load on its doomed flight for the first time since the maintenance.But he also cautioned that the information from the flight data recorder was preliminary and that the investigators could not rule out the possibility that the abnormal movements were not that at all, but instead simply a problem with a tail-section sensor that fed the recorder.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/01/business/company-briefs-653551.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY BRIEFS<date>Published: January 01, 2003</date><text>DANA CORP., Toledo, Ohio, a maker of auto parts, sold real estate units that were part of Dana's equipment leasing and financing division to Goldman Sachs Group Inc., New York, the investment bank, for $73 million.RAYTHEON CO., Lexington, Mass., the military contractor, won three contracts with a combined value of $443 million for six ship-borne Aegis weapons systems and related equipment, including three sets for South Korea, two for the United States Navy and one for Japan.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/20/business/company-news-raytheon-to-take-a-charge-of-up-to-200-million.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON TO TAKE A CHARGE OF UP TO $200 MILLION<date>Published: December 20, 2002</date><text>Raytheon, the military contractor, said yesterday that it would take a fourth-quarter charge of up to $200 million to account for project costs related to its former construction business. Raytheon said higher-than-expected costs to complete two power plants in Massachusetts would force it to take the charges. The charges are not expected to affect any bank agreements, the company said, but will raise the total loss on the projects beyond its third-quarter estimate of $1.3 billion.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/12/business/company-news-raytheon-s-chief-financial-officer-resigns.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON'S CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER RESIGNS<date>Published: December 12, 2002</date><text>The Raytheon Company's chief financial officer, Frank Caine, has resigned and has been succeeded by the controller, Edward Pliner, the company said yesterday. The action comes two weeks after the Securities and Exchange Commission punished Mr. Caine for violating a rule barring selective disclosure of financial information. Mr. Pliner, 44, was a partner for PricewaterhouseCoopers, Raytheon's auditor, before he joined Raytheon in April 2000. Mr. Caine, 52, will remain with the company through the year to assist Mr. Pliner, a Raytheon spokesman, James Fetig, said. The S.E.C. asserted that Mr. Caine called individual analysts in February 2001 and told them their estimates for first-quarter earnings were ''too high,'' ''aggressive'' or ''very aggressive.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/26/business/market-place-sec-puts-data-disclosure-in-the-spotlight.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Market Place; S.E.C. Puts Data Disclosure In the Spotlight<date>Published: November 26, 2002</date><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission yesterday filed its first three cases against companies that it said had violated Regulation FD, which bars the selective release of important corporate information.The commission said it obtained cease-and-desist orders against three companies that had violated the rules. It took no action against a fourth, but issued a report saying the company had acted incorrectly. That company was spared further action because it had followed legal advice.Only one company, Siebel Systems, was forced to pay a penalty for the violation. Siebel, which the S.E.C. said had disclosed important information at a Goldman, Sachs technology conference that was not open to the public, agreed to pay $250,000.The other companies that accepted cease-and-desist orders, administrative proceedings that are at the lower end of S.E.C. legal sanctions, were Raytheon and Secure Computing. Motorola was let off with only a report, because it had secured legal advice that the S.E.C. said was wrong.In bringing the cases, the S.E.C. appeared to be trying to lay out clearly just what behavior was prohibited. At the same time, by letting Motorola off without any penalty, it was trying to reassure companies that they would not be penalized if they acted in good faith.The S.E.C. said Thomas N. Siebel, the chairman and chief executive of Siebel, told a Goldman technology conference on Nov. 5, 2001, that business was looking better than it had been a few weeks earlier. Siebel had told Goldman that the comments would be positive, and Goldman conveyed that information to its customers before trading began that day. The result was that the stock, which had closed the previous trading session at $17.29, opened at $18.60 and was up to $20.15, on very heavy volume, by the time news reports of the comments began to appear, the S.E.C. said.Those comments ignited a rise for Siebel that continued until Jan. 24, the day after it reported what Wall Street viewed as a good fourth quarter, and the stock hit $38.38. Since then, revenue has fallen in each quarter. Yesterday, Siebel shares fell 18 cents, to $8.57.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/09/business/company-news-raytheon-plans-to-lay-off-500-employees.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON PLANS TO LAY OFF 500 EMPLOYEES<date>Published: October 09, 2002</date><text>The Raytheon Company said yesterday that it planned to lay off about 500 workers in Massachusetts and California to adjust for the loss of a satellite contract and to improve organization. Headquarters staff and engineers will be eliminated in Marlborough, Mass., and El Segundo, Calif., starting next month, a spokeswoman, Amy Hosmer, said. They account for less than 1 percent of the company's work force of 77,500. Raytheon, which is based in Lexington, Mass., said last month that it would split its military and air-traffic control work into seven businesses.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/31/business/company-news-raytheon-to-reorganize-several-divisions-and-cut-jobs.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON TO REORGANIZE SEVERAL DIVISIONS AND CUT JOBS<date>Published: August 31, 2002</date><text>The Raytheon Company, the military contractor, said yesterday that it would split its military and air-traffic work into seven businesses. Raytheon, which is based in Lexington, Mass., will eliminate jobs after the reorganization, a spokesman, David Polk, said. The company will not know the exact number of jobs affected for a month, he said. The businesses include integrated military systems, intelligence and information systems, missile systems, network systems, space and airborne systems, technical services and homeland security.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/24/business/trw-wins-weather-satellite-contract.html?ref=raytheoncompany">TRW Wins Weather Satellite Contract<date>Published: August 24, 2002</date><text>TRW Space and Electronics, a unit of TRW Inc., won a $4.5 billion contract to build and deploy a new environmental satellite system for civil and military needs, the government said today.The project will merge military and civilian environmental satellite programs into a single system intended to improve weather forecasting and climate prediction.TRW and its chief partner, the Raytheon Company, beat a team led by Lockheed Martin, the nation's biggest defense contractor.Northrop Grumman reached a deal in July to acquire TRW, the military contractor and auto parts maker based in Cleveland, for $7.8 billion.The $4.5 billion figure includes all options in the contract, which is expected to run to 2018, said Daniel McClain, a TRW spokesman.As prime contractor, TRW will be responsible for overall system design and development, system engineering, system integration, acquisition of instruments and test of spacecraft.Raytheon will provide command, control and communications, mission-data processing and system engineering support.It said the project would provide increased capability at reduced overall cost.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/29/business/company-news-raytheon-and-lockheed-to-share-2-contracts.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON AND LOCKHEED TO SHARE 2 CONTRACTS<date>Published: June 29, 2002</date><text>The Raytheon Company and the Lockheed Martin Corporation will share two Federal Aviation Administration contracts with a combined value of $2.7 billion to settle a complaint over the handling of one of the project awards, company and government officials said. The agreement gives Raytheon a piece of a $1 billion project awarded to Lockheed to improve computer software in 20 F.A.A. centers that direct planes at high altitudes. Lockheed will be a subcontractor in a $1.7 billion upgrade of software and processors at 173 centers at or near airports that guide planes within 50 miles of takeoffs and landings.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/20/business/internal-security-is-attracting-a-crowd-of-arms-contractors.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Internal Security Is Attracting a Crowd Of Arms Contractors<date>Published: March 20, 2002</date><text>Edmund B. Woollen, a vice president for integrated information systems at Raytheon, had just started a meeting in his office in northern Virginia when he heard a thunderous explosion and looked up to see the Pentagon burning. The date was Sept. 11.Mr. Woollen, a Vietnam veteran, quickly realized that the attacks that day did more than murder thousands of people, destroy the World Trade Center and damage the Pentagon. Shattered, too, was the assumption that the United States had to prepare for wars only on foreign soil. Now it also needed to protect against terrorist attacks at home.The next day, Raytheon's chairman, Daniel P. Burnham, asked Mr. Woollen to lead a team to prepare for the new security demands, and market possibilities, after the attacks of Sept. 11.''Neither of us doubted that this would change what we've done for the past 30 or 40 years,'' Mr. Woollen recalled.The entire arms industry seems to agree. Since Sept. 11, virtually every major military contractor has assigned senior executives to help reshape its marketing strategies, repackage its products and reorganize its bureaucracy to compete in the fast-growing business of domestic security.Wall Street analysts are less enthusiastic, noting that military contractors are accustomed to dealing with a well-defined budget being spent by a familiar and centralized bureaucracy at the Pentagon. Domestic security, by contrast, is divvied among many departments -- Justice, Interior, Treasury and Transportation, as well as Defense -- and the spending plan is not clear.Still, arms makers assume that the rapid build-up in spending on domestic defense -- President Bush has proposed that the federal government spend $37.7 billion next year, almost twice the $19.5 billion budgeted for this year -- will include opportunities too lucrative to ignore.Boeing, for example, is studying whether sensors designed to track enemy missiles could be used to identify hijacked airliners. Lockheed Martin is trying to adapt military simulators to train local emergency-response teams. General Dynamics hopes to sell armored personnel vehicles to police departments. And Northrop Grumman thinks its communications systems could help health authorities deal with bioterrorism threats.''A lot of the technologies that we developed for one purpose can be adapted to do other things,'' said Tom Davis, Northrop Grumman's corporate coordinator for homeland security. ''You've got a new mission that's emerging here.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/16/business/company-news-delay-in-patriot-sales-leads-to-job-cuts-at-raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; DELAY IN PATRIOT SALES LEADS TO JOB CUTS AT RAYTHEON<date>Published: March 16, 2002</date><text>A delay in selling eight Patriot missile units to South Korea has contributed to the elimination of 490 Raytheon Company jobs at five Massachusetts plants, the company said yesterday. Raytheon, which is based in Lexington, Mass., said that the layoffs would affect about 210 manufacturing employees and 280 support and engineering employees at its Andover, Bedford, Lexington, Sudbury and Tewksbury operations. All are associated with Raytheon's Air/Missile Defense Systems unit.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/14/business/technology-briefing-research-mit-wins-nanomaterials-work.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Technology Briefing | Research: M.I.T. Wins Nanomaterials Work<date>Published: March 14, 2002</date><text>The Massachusetts Institute of Technology has been selected as the home for an Army-financed research center for molecular-scale materials science aimed at providing soldiers with uniforms and equipment that protect them against chemical and biological warfare. The new center will start with a five-year $50 million contract intended to support a research staff of 150 drawn from nine departments at M.I.T., DuPont and Raytheon, local hospitals and the Army. Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/09/us/inquiry-on-antimissile-contract-is-sought.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Inquiry on Antimissile Contract Is Sought<date>Published: February 09, 2002</date><text>Saying the competition to build the top weapon for the nation's antimissile effort was apparently decided not on technical merit but in the fallout over an incident of industrial spying, a California congressman is calling for an investigation into how the contract was awarded.The issue is important because some experts see the winning design, by the Raytheon Company, as technically weak. After two misses and three hits in costly flight tests, the prototype weapon is at the heart of the Bush administration's plan to erect an antimissile shield, whose cost was recently estimated at up to $238 billion.Representative Howard L. Berman, Democrat of California, asked the General Accounting Office last week to investigate a competition between the Boeing Company and Raytheon to build the weapon, called a kill vehicle. It is meant to fly into space atop an interceptor rocket and smash apart enemy warheads by force of impact.In a letter to the accounting office, the investigative arm of Congress, on Monday, Mr. Berman said Raytheon won the contract for the weapon in December 1998, after an internal Raytheon document about its weapon had been found in Boeing's hands. Mr. Berman's letter was provided to The New York Times by Congressional officials.Such spying breaks Pentagon regulations. Boeing quit the contest, Mr. Berman said, because it apparently feared that Raytheon would sue if Boeing tried to win the contract with purloined secrets. Mr. Berman said he learned of the incident from Congressional investigators who were pursuing a different antimissile case.''It is unimaginable that a decision of this magnitude with such enormous implications for our national security could have been made to protect the legal and financial interests of one contractor,'' Mr. Berman wrote David M. Walker, head of the General Accounting Office.Lt. Col. Richard Lehner of the Air Force, a spokesman for the Pentagon's Missile Defense Agency, said Boeing withdrew for other reasons. The company had an institutional conflict, Colonel Lehner said, because a larger Boeing team oversaw the whole antimissile effort and the kill-vehicle competition.A spokeswoman for Boeing, Monica Aloisio, said the company would not comment on the accusations about the document. A spokeswoman for Raytheon, Colleen Niccum, said the company won by virtue of the superiority of its design and added that the prototype had proved increasingly adept in flight tests.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/23/business/company-news-a-fraud-suit-brought-by-raytheon-is-dismissed.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; A FRAUD SUIT BROUGHT BY RAYTHEON IS DISMISSED<date>Published: January 23, 2002</date><text>A judge dismissed the Raytheon Company's lawsuit claiming Towers Perrin caused the military contractor to overpay in its $9.5 billion purchase of a Hughes Electronics Corporation unit. Judge Manuel Real of the United States District Court in Los Angeles issued his ruling from the bench without hearing oral arguments from either side. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., claimed it overpaid based on Towers Perrin's mistaken statement that Hughes's pension plan had a surplus of at least $1 billion at the end of 1996. A Raytheon spokesman, David Polk, said the company would appeal. Towers Perrin is based in New York.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/14/business/l-3-said-to-be-in-deal-for-unit-of-raytheon-for-1.1-billion.html?ref=raytheoncompany">L-3 Said to Be In Deal for Unit Of Raytheon For $1.1 Billion<date>Published: January 14, 2002</date><text>L-3 Communications plans to announce today that it has agreed to acquire a military equipment subsidiary of Raytheon for $1.13 billion in cash, beating out bigger rivals like Northrop Grumman and British Aerospace for control of one of the nation's largest suppliers of surveillance and reconnaissance equipment to the United States government.The deal would be L-3's largest acquisition since the company was formed in 1997 by cobbling together 10 languishing units of Lockheed Martin. The transaction gives L-3 a more unified set of military products, from devices that can track aircraft and ground troops to communication systems that can securely transmit data wirelessly back to base stations.For Raytheon, the sale of the business, Aircraft Integration Systems, which it put up for auction more than three months ago, will help it pay off a rising debt load. The sale is the second big deal between L-3 and Raytheon. In 2000, L-3 bought Link Simulation and Training, an unprofitable flight-simulation business for $160 million that L-3 recently turned profitable.Aircraft Integration Systems' technology has been used extensively by the United States in the war in Afghanistan. The unit, which is often referred to by it initials, A.I.S., makes systems that provide personnel on the ground and in the air with a real-time, three-dimensional view of the area in which they are fighting. A.I.S. also makes technology to collect, decode and analyze electronic signals.''A.I.S. is a national defense asset that for decades has had a special relationship with the U.S. intelligence community,'' said Frank C. Lanza, chairman and founder of L-3 Communications. ''A.I.S. has outfitted over 15,000 aircraft of more than 125 types.''''So as the nation's military forces continue to pursue our enemies,'' he added, and as the Defense Department upgrades its systems, ''A.I.S.'s capabilities in multi-intelligence and multiplatform operations are even more critical.''A.I.S. has contracts for about $800 million of work from the Defense Department and allies. It has operations in Greenville and Waco, Tex.; Lexington, Ky.; and Avalon, Australia. L-3 expects the deal to raise L-3's 2002 diluted earnings a share by 20 cents. The acquisition will be financed using cash on hand and short-term loans. L-3 then expects to sell about $1 billion of debt and equity securities during the first half of the year to help pay off those loans.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/03/business/company-news-raytheon-gets-military-order-worth-up-to-1.22-billion.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON GETS MILITARY ORDER WORTH UP TO $1.22 BILLION<date>Published: January 03, 2002</date><text>Raytheon Aircraft has won its largest military contract ever, a potential $1.22 billion deal that will maintain its work force but add no jobs, the company said yesterday. The one-year contract with four one-year options calls for the production of 234 T-6A Texan II aircraft. Military budgets are allocated and approved year by year, so the options are for anticipated orders in subsequent years. Raytheon Aircraft, a division of the Raytheon Company, will build 40 aircraft the first year, an order valued at $193 million, a spokesman, Tim Travis, said. If all the options are exercised, the contract could be worth $1.22 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/20/business/rosie-the-riveter-in-a-new-generation-military-industry-regains-self-respect.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Rosie the Riveter In a New Generation; Military Industry Regains Self-Respect<date>Published: October 20, 2001</date><text>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 19— In the heyday of the new economy, the Raytheon Company's military plant in the Southern California industrial town of Goleta was easy to ignore. Corporate mergers and cuts in military spending sliced the work force in half. There was little to keep employees loyal when Internet executives from nearby Santa Barbara came calling. ''Some of our brethren have gone to the dot-coms,'' said John Bowen, a senior manager at Raytheon's Infrared Operations, which makes the technology for, among other things, night-vision goggles. Indeed, said John Fennell, a manager of human resources, they could not compete with the fun-and-games work environment promised by the dot-coms. ''It became not a sexy place to work,'' he said, ''because we didn't have slides and beer on Fridays.'' Even though the Raytheon plant, which also makes decoys that lure enemy missiles away from American combat planes, is Santa Barbara County's sixth-largest employer, many people ignored its nondescript building and barely knew the company's name. But after Sept. 11, Raytheon workers in Goleta, about 100 miles up the coast from Los Angeles, are feeling a renewed sense of self-respect. Executives are almost surprised by their newfound relevance. While Internet stocks have nose-dived and many Americans are worried about layoffs, Raytheon's Goleta office hopes to fill 150 positions in the next few years. ''It's an ability once more to show we are a stable, vital company,'' said Jack Saunders, acting general manager of Raytheon's Electronic Warfare Operations. Something similar is being felt across Southern California, particularly in towns like Long Beach, where aircraft plants once dominated the landscape but have faded in importance in recent years. Many military contractors in the region scrambled over the last decade to transform themselves into anything else. Most notable was Hughes Electronics, which sold its military business to Raytheon in 1997 for $9.5 billion, and became a satellite and media company. But companies that stuck with the Pentagon are seeing virtues in their old businesses and a revived sense of being needed. Some analysts are even predicting that military contractors here will prosper. ''I would call these companies both the hidden and reluctant beneficiaries of what's going on,'' said Howard A. Rubel, an aerospace analyst at Goldman, Sachs in New York. ''It may not be in a lot of big stuff right away. It will be in parts and small stuff. But this elevates the prestige of the military back to where it should be.'' Some of those who joined the exodus have even come back. Kris Brawn, a San Diego-based project manager for Northrop Grumman who works on software for the B-2 bomber, left his job two years ago for a finance-related dot-com, but returned in January after just 13 months. ''Coming back to a defense company gives me the opportunity to proactively make a difference,'' said Mr. Brawn, who also hated the long hours and time away from his family. And during times like these, he added, ''at an Internet company you sit on the sidelines.'' But it will never again be like it once was. During and after World War II, Southern California suburbs blossomed to accommodate the hundreds of thousands of workers building and designing missiles, planes and other weapons. But when the cold war ended, many of those jobs withered away. Companies, in turn, became more streamlined. In Los Angeles County, 113,000 people now work in aerospace and military jobs, a far cry from the 290,000 of 15 years ago, said Jack Kyser, chief economist at the Los Angeles Economic Development Corporation. As a result, military contracting in this new era of terrorist warfare will rebuild only gradually as the military turns to companies that offer products that meet specific needs, particularly in information and technology. Among those expected to prosper is Northrop Grumman, which makes the Global Hawk, an unmanned surveillance aircraft being built in Palmdale, Calif. The company acquired the technology when it bought Ryan Aeronautical, based in San Diego, in 1999. The military has agreed to buy 60 Global Hawks in the next several years, and Northrop said it expected to hire 100 people to help with research and production.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/22/business/nation-challenged-military-contractors-beneficiaries-military-buildup-await.html?ref=raytheoncompany">A NATION CHALLENGED: THE MILITARY CONTRACTORS; Beneficiaries of the Military Buildup Await Their Orders<date>Published: September 22, 2001</date><text>WASHINGTON, Sept. 21— Early last week, Frank C. Lanza, the chief executive of L-3 Communications, an aerospace and communications company in New York, received a not-too-surprising telephone call from military officials. ''They asked us, 'Can you do the following things, and how long will it take you to do it,' '' Mr. Lanza said. ''They are in the planning process. And they need to know about our ability to deliver certain products.'' That planning process is about war: the Pentagon is preparing a shopping list for the global struggle against terrorism promised by President Bush. As a result, scores of military contractors, from giants like Lockheed Martin to smaller companies like L-3, could be among the corporate beneficiaries of the devastating attacks of Sept. 11. Even as those assaults have sent the stock market plummeting and caused havoc for much of American business, prospects for the military-industrial complex are looking stronger than they have in years. Overnight, political opposition in Congress to huge increases in Pentagon spending has vanished, along with concerns about dipping into surplus Social Security funds. Consequently, what had seemed to the industry like a disappointingly small military budget just two weeks ago is now climbing toward unanticipated heights, providing a lift for military contractors and a quick Keynesian stimulus for the economy. Beyond the buildup for war, winners and losers in the race for Pentagon money will also be determined by the outcome of Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld's efforts to transform the military. His goals have included improving intelligence, expanding long-strike capabilities and making the forces lighter, faster and more high-tech. But the process has faced stiff resistance from some commanders and lawmakers who fear Mr. Rumsfeld wants to starve programs for modernizing conventional ships, planes and howitzers to nurture untried products, like space planes or remotely piloted submarines. ''The services are going to want to try to use some money to address their modernization needs,'' said Jacques S. Gansler, an under secretary of defense in the Clinton administration who now teaches public policy at the University of Maryland. ''And that's where you get a conundrum over whether to buy a new tank, or equipment you'd like to have for 21st-century warfare against terrorists. You'll have a battle between those two options.'' The budget numbers tell the story. Three days after the attack, Congress overwhelmingly approved $40 billion in emergency funds, with $10 billion to $15 billion for the armed services. In the next few weeks, Congress is also expected to approve, with little dissent, a $33 billion increase in the Pentagon budget, raising it to $329 billion for the fiscal year beginning Oct. 1. And before final votes on the 2002 spending plan are even cast, the Pentagon is expected to ask for an additional $15 billion to $25 billion. There is bipartisan support for that, too. ''Capitol Hill is prepared to do whatever the Pentagon wants,'' said Gordon Adams, a budget official in the Clinton administration who is now director of security policy studies at the Elliot School of International Security Studies at George Washington University. Much of the initial wave of money will go toward rebuilding the smoldering hole left in the Pentagon by the hijacked airliner, paying for heightened security at military installations worldwide and preparing for retaliatory strikes. That will mean buying new bullets, cruise missiles, boots, reconnaissance equipment and spare parts. But many analysts and military officials say they expect there to be a significant amount of money left over after those basic needs are met. The service chiefs and senior lawmakers will probably want to spend those funds on favored weapons programs, like Boeing's F-18 E and F fighters, United Defense's Crusader artillery system, and Northrop Grumman and General Dynamic's DD-21 stealth destroyer. It will not matter if those systems are not clearly useful in the war on terrorism, the analysts say. ''There is a heightened sense of danger out there,'' said Loren Thompson, chief operating officer with the Lexington Institute, a military policy organization based in Arlington, Va.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/07/business/judge-rejects-sale-of-raytheon-unit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Judge Rejects Sale of Raytheon Unit<date>Published: September 7, 2001</date><text>BOISE, Idaho, Sept. 6— Washington Group International said today that a bankruptcy judge in Nevada had agreed to throw out a $503 million pact to buy a Raytheon construction unit because of accusations of hidden cost overruns. Washington Group agreed in July 2000 to acquire Raytheon Engineers and Constructors International and guarantee the completion of some projects started by the business. After the sale closed, Washington Group learned it was assuming liabilities of almost $650 million. Under federal law, executives of a company operating under Chapter 11 can recommend which agreements they think should be honored as part of the reorganization effort and ask a bankruptcy judge to reject all others.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/02/business/dogfight-for-dollars-on-capitol-hill.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Dogfight for Dollars On Capitol Hill<date>Published: September 2, 2001</date><text>WASHINGTON— THE video shows a flair for the dramatic. A crowd anxiously watches a pilot climb into a sleek, futuristic-looking jet. The engines whine, the plane rises slowly like a hulking prehistoric bird and the onlookers explode, cheering with joy and relief. The trailer for a new Tom Hanks film? Try the latest promotional video for Lockheed Martin's experimental plane, the X-35 -- better known as the Joint Strike Fighter. The video is part of an extravagant Lockheed promotional kit that includes CD-ROM images of test flights, glossy photographs and a videotape of the aircraft breaking the sound barrier. And that is just one piece of a multimillion-dollar lobbying, advertising and marketing campaign aimed at beating its competition, Boeing, for what could be the most lucrative military contract, worth more than $200 billion. ''This is the future for both Lockheed and Boeing,'' said Richard Aboulafia, an aerospace analyst at the Teal Group, a consulting firm in Fairfax, Va. ''The stakes are huge.'' Lockheed is hardly the only military contractor mounting an aggressive campaign here. The season for lobbying by the military industry is in full bloom, and contractors are inundating Congress with Power Point briefings, shuttling officials to test sites and factories, hiring top-drawer lobbyists and showering lawmakers with campaign contributions. The reason for all the activity is a confluence of major decisions expected this fall: * The Pentagon is scheduled to award contracts not only for the Joint Strike Fighter, but also for the DD-21 destroyer, which could be the most important shipbuilding program of the next two decades. * The Pentagon must decide whether to block either General Dynamics or Northrop Grumman from acquiring Newport News Shipbuilding, the nation's only builder of aircraft carriers. * As soon as Congress returns on Tuesday from its summer recess, it will begin what is expected to be a contentious debate on the size of the Pentagon budget for the 2002 fiscal year, which begins on Oct. 1. The first hearings are on Wednesday, and many Democrats are pushing to trim President Bush's proposed $33 billion increase. Though the increase would be the largest since the mid-1980's, many industry officials had hoped for more from a Republican president. * By the end of this month, Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld will complete the Quadrennial Defense Review, mandated by Congress, that will set the size and shape of the armed forces, provide a template for future budgets and help determine the fate of an array of billion-dollar programs. * Also this month, the armed services will begin outlining their budgets for the 2003 fiscal year, the year when Mr. Rumsfeld has vowed to make major decisions on weapons programs. And because of the rapidly declining federal surplus, he is expected to require the services to find cuts to help pay for their favorite systems. ''There is no question that we probably cannot afford every weapon system'' in development, President Bush said in late August. ''This administration is going to have to winnow them down.'' The outcome is vital to a host of major companies, including United Defense, Northrop Grumman, TRW and Raytheon. Not surprisingly, they have been furiously working the marble corridors of Capitol Hill and the pale yellow hallways of the Pentagon to keep their programs alive and well. Recent lobbying reports indicate that military contractors are likely to spend nearly $60 million on lobbying this year, less than the communications or banking industries but more than lawyers and labor unions combined. Of that total, Lockheed and Boeing together account for more than $10 million. In recent weeks, their work has ranged far and wide. One day in June, one of the Joint Strike Fighter prototypes at Lockheed passed a crucial test, lifting off and landing vertically. The company immediately dispatched a video of the event to CNN. Within 24 hours, Boeing completed a similarly complex maneuver with its prototype, the X-32: taking off on a shortened runway, then hovering and landing vertically. The company quickly sent a video to CNN, too.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/23/business/mesa-gets-loan-accord.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Mesa Gets Loan Accord<date>Published: August 23, 2001</date><text>The Mesa Air Group, which runs commuter flights for larger airlines, said today that it had reached an agreement with Raytheon that ends a default on aircraft loans.Mesa said Raytheon had also agreed to help reduce operating costs on the aircraft, the Beech 1900D. The airline primarily operates flights for America West Airlines and US Airways.Earlier this month, Mesa said it had stopped the payments as a way to get Raytheon to negotiate on restructuring debt on the Beech turboprop. Mesa has said it set aside money for the payments, although executives declined to say how much was owed. Mesa operates 55 Beech 1900D, 47 of them financed by Raytheon.The airline is trying to cut the number of the planes in its fleet, primarily because maintenance changes required by the Federal Aviation Administration have made the aircraft more expensive to operate.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/07/business/company-news-motion-filed-in-sale-of-raytheon-construction-unit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; MOTION FILED IN SALE OF RAYTHEON CONSTRUCTION UNIT<date>Published: August 07, 2001</date><text>The Washington Group International Inc. asked a federal bankruptcy judge in Nevada yesterday to throw out a $503 million agreement to buy the Raytheon Company's construction unit because of hidden cost overruns. The move comes less than a week after the Washington Group sued in bankruptcy court in Reno, Nev., to recover $822 million and avoid $700 million in indemnity payments to the military contractor in connection with the purchase. Washington Group sought Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection in May and hopes to emerge from its reorganization in October after shedding more than $300 million in debt and the Raytheon unit. Raytheon, which has denied wrongdoing, had expected Washington Group's move, company officials said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/04/business/company-news-raytheon-dismisses-suit-against-it-over-deal.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON DISMISSES SUIT AGAINST IT OVER DEAL<date>Published: August 04, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company said that a lawsuit filed against it by the Washington Group International was without merit and that it expected to prevail in court. The Washington Group, based in Boise, Idaho, has sued in connection with its purchase of Raytheon's construction unit, and is trying to recover $822 million and avoid repaying $700 million in indemnity to Raytheon. ''The claim appears to be nothing more than a ploy to keep Raytheon from exercising its rights as one of W.G.I.'s creditors,'' Neal E. Minahan, Raytheon's general counsel, said on Thursday.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/03/business/company-news-washington-group-files-lawsuit-against-raytheon.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; WASHINGTON GROUP FILES LAWSUIT AGAINST RAYTHEON<date>Published: August 03, 2001</date><text>Washington Group International said yesterday that it had sued the Raytheon Company over more than $1.5 billion in fees and payments in the purchase of Raytheon's construction unit. Officials of Washington Group, of Boise, Idaho, are seeking to recover $822 million and avoid repaying $700 million in indemnity payments to Raytheon, a spokesman said. The lawsuit was filed as part of a bankruptcy filing by Washington Group. The company filed for Chapter 11 protection from creditors in May after accusing Raytheon of hiding cost overruns in its engineering and construction unit, which Washington Group agreed to acquire last year for $503 million in cash and assumed debt. Officials with Raytheon were not immediately available for comment.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/28/business/raytheon-to-take-177-million-charge.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon to Take $177 Million Charge<date>Published: June 28, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company plans to take a $177 million second-quarter charge to cover added costs stemming from construction projects involving Washington Group International Inc. and Pohang Iron &amp; Steel of South Korea.Raytheon said Tuesday that the costs of completing two power plants it took over in March from the Washington Group may reach $700 million, more than double earlier estimates. Pohang is threatening legal action against Raytheon, claiming an iron-processing plant built by Raytheon in Venezuela is faulty.Raytheon sold its Engineers and Constructors unit to Washington Group last year for $53 million and $450 million in liabilities. Raytheon was obligated to take back projects it began before selling the unit after they were abandoned by the Washington Group.The problems are ''a persistent irritant,'' Raytheon's chief executive, Daniel Burnham, said today in a conference call with analysts.Washington Group, based in Boise, Idaho, filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection in March, blaming cost overruns at the unit it acquired. The purchase is also being investigated by the Securities and Exchange Commission. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass. has denied wrongdoing.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/26/business/job-to-raytheon-venture.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Job to Raytheon Venture<date>Published: June 26, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Technical Service Company, a unit of the Raytheon Company and JT3 L.L.C., in a joint venture with JT3 EG&amp;G Technical Services Inc., received an Air Force contract valued at up to $1.7 billion.In a news release yesterday, Raytheon said under the 15-year contract, JT3 would provide instrumented test and training-range support to the Air Force and Navy. Services include operations and maintenance, engineering and technical services for threats, instrumentation, communications and data systems, according to Raytheon, as well as hardware and software support, modeling, simulation and training and equipment modifications.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/23/business/raytheon-venture-gets-pentagon-work.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon Venture Gets Pentagon Work<date>Published: June 23, 2001</date><text>A joint venture by the Raytheon Company beat teams lead by the Computer Sciences Corporation and DynCorp Inc. for military work worth as much as $1.7 billion to support Air Force and Navy training ranges in Nevada, Utah and California.Raytheon's Technical Services Company of Reston, Va., and its partner, EG&amp;G Technical Services of Gaithersburg, Md., won an initial $96.7 million one-year cost-plus contract with the potential for $1.7 billion through 2016.The Raytheon and EG&amp;G team will provide technical services, maintenance and engineering for the Nevada Test and Training Range; the Utah Test and Training Range; the Air Force Flight Test Center at Edwards Air Force Base, Calif.; and the Navy's Electronic Combat Range at China Lake, Calif.The two companies beat a team led by Computer Sciences with the Lockheed Martin Corporation, Arcata Associates, Dynetics and the Metric Systems Corporation. It also beat a joint venture of DynCorp.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/20/business/company-news-raytheon-receives-200-million-in-orders-for-planes.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON RECEIVES $200 MILLION IN ORDERS FOR PLANES<date>Published: June 20, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company said it had received more than $200 million in orders for about 35 aircraft, including 10 of its new Premier I business jets. Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., said it received orders for 15 Hawker business jets, 7 Beech King Air turboprops and 2 Beach Barron airplanes at the Paris Air Show. The orders could help lift the performance of Raytheon's aircraft unit in Wichita, Kan., where sales fell 22 percent in the first quarter to $637 million.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/07/business/company-news-raytheon-plans-to-cut-470-more-jobs-at-aircraft-unit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON PLANS TO CUT 470 MORE JOBS AT AIRCRAFT UNIT<date>Published: June 07, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company plans to cut 470 more jobs at its commercial-aircraft unit in Kansas because of lower-than-expected deliveries of Beechjet and King Air planes. The cuts affect hourly workers and represent 4.8 percent of the unit's work force. The company said in April that it would cut 450 salaried employees at the unit, which makes business jets and turboprop planes. About 267 of those jobs will be eliminated by the end of the month, Raytheon said. Sales at the aircraft unit fell 22 percent last quarter. Raytheon expects to deliver 468 jets this year, 40 fewer than forecast.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/22/business/company-news-raytheon-ordered-to-provide-audit-to-rival-in-dispute.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON ORDERED TO PROVIDE AUDIT TO RIVAL IN DISPUTE<date>Published: May 22, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company has until next Tuesday to give Washington Group International an audited balance sheet of a business Raytheon sold to Washington Group, an Idaho judge ruled. The information is needed to help an arbitrator decide if Washington Group is entitled to a $400 million refund, a Washington Group spokesman, Brent Brandon, said. If Raytheon, a leading military contractor, or its auditor, PricewaterhouseCoopers, miss the deadline, the judge, Deborah Bail, will appoint an auditor. Washington Group of Boise, Idaho, filed for bankruptcy protection last week, about 10 months after it bought Raytheon's construction business for $53 million and assumed $450 million in liabilities. Washington Group filed suit in March, saying Raytheon, which is based in Lexington, Mass., committed fraud and seeking a cancellation of the purchase.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/15/business/a-leading-construction-company-files-for-chapter-11.html?ref=raytheoncompany">A Leading Construction Company Files for Chapter 11<date>Published: May 15, 2001</date><text>The Washington Group International, one of the nation's largest construction companies, filed for bankruptcy protection yesterday and settled in for a long fight with the Raytheon Company, which it has accused of misrepresenting the financial condition of a unit that Washington bought from it last year.Washington, which is based in Boise, Idaho, said it would continue to operate and pay its workers. The Chapter 11 bankruptcy filing, made in a Nevada federal court, included the parent company and 22 subsidiaries, which together employ around 17,000 people. As many as 70 other subsidiaries, joint ventures and partnerships, employing another 18,000 people, are not involved in the bankruptcy, the company said.The company, formerly known as Morrison Knudsen, said that its stockholders could expect to recover nothing and that its secured creditors would own the equity assets of the reassembled company. Unsecured creditors, the company said, would be paid either through the normal course of business or upon confirmation of the plan.Washington said it sought bankruptcy protection because of a cash-flow crisis resulting from cost overruns on some contracts and lower-than-expected profits on other contracts from the unit it acquired from Raytheon. The company has sued Raytheon, accusing it of fraud and is seeking to unwind its purchase of the unit. The deal did not include a breakup fee.''The wheels of justice just move slowly,'' Stephen G. Hanks, the company's president, said in a telephone interview. ''We are funding these undisclosed losses at the clip of $100 million a month, and we are simply out of cash.''In its filing, Washington listed assets of $3.8 billion and liabilities of approximately $3.3 billion.Mr. Hanks said that he expected that the reorganization would take four to six months to complete. In about two months, the company will disclose the specific conditions of the terms of the bankruptcy for unsecured creditors, who will most likely object, he said.Credit Suisse First Boston, which lent the company $1 billion to buy the Raytheon unit, agreed to lead a group of lenders that would supply the company with money while it reorganized under bankruptcy protection.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/04/business/sec-investigating-sale-of-raytheon-s-construction-unit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">S.E.C. Investigating Sale of Raytheon's Construction Unit<date>Published: May 04, 2001</date><text>Securities regulators are investigating the Raytheon Company's sale of its struggling construction business last year after the buyer, Washington Group International Inc., complained that it was defrauded by Raytheon.Raytheon confirmed today that it had received a subpoena from the Securities and Exchange Commission requesting information about its construction and engineering unit. Raytheon said the federal inquiry did not suggest it violated any law.Washington Group, based in Boise, Idaho, has accused Raytheon of withholding crucial financial information about construction projects it sold with the engineering business. Washington said the S.E.C. had contacted it, too.Washington Group, which was formerly known as the Morrison Knudsen Company, has also sued Raytheon to rescind its purchase of the operation, accusing Raytheon of fraud and misrepresentations about its construction and engineering business. Raytheon has denied the allegations.''We will respond to the S.E.C.'s questions and supply whatever information is requested,'' Daniel Burnham, Raytheon's chairman, said in a statement. ''We have made extensive disclosures regarding Raytheon Engineers and Constructors and its disposition to W.G.I. and believe that our policies and practices are in compliance with all regulations and laws.''Raytheon, the maker of Patriot missiles, business jets and radar systems, sold the engineering and construction business to Washington Group last July for $73 million in cash and assumed liabilities then estimated at $450 million. Raytheon subsequently has increased the loss on the sale to $415 million before taxes.A few months after buying the business, Washington Group reduced the carrying value of several contracts and increased estimated liabilities by about $700 million. Since then, Washington Group has walked off two construction jobs in Massachusetts, contending Raytheon withheld financial information about the projects.Washington Group is in a severe liquidity crisis and is seeking to have a judge compel Raytheon to produce an audit document needed to resolve purchase-price adjustments with Raytheon.The dispute has also taken a toll on Raytheon's financial results, contributing to first-quarter pretax charges of $325 million, or 61 cents a share, against earnings.The company has warned that the situation will hurt operating cash flow over the next four to six quarters.The S.E.C. would neither confirm nor deny the inquiry.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/10/business/company-news-raytheon-estimates-cost-of-completing-power-plants.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON ESTIMATES COST OF COMPLETING POWER PLANTS<date>Published: April 10, 2001</date><text>The military contractor Raytheon Company said yesterday that it expected to take a first-quarter charge of $275 million to $325 million to reflect the cost of completing two power plant projects in Massachusetts for which it had guaranteed performance before it sold its construction and engineering division. Raytheon retained liability for the plants when it sold its construction and engineering division to the Washington Group International last year. But the two companies have fought over a purchase price adjustment in the deal and the Washington Group, formerly known as Morrison Knudsen, abandoned the projects last month.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/04/business/company-news-raytheon-aircraft-to-eliminate-450-white-collar-jobs.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON AIRCRAFT TO ELIMINATE 450 WHITE-COLLAR JOBS<date>Published: April 04, 2001</date><text>Citing a softening economy, Raytheon Aircraft told its employees yesterday that it was eliminating about 450 administrative and managerial jobs, about 10 percent of the company's managerial work force in Kansas. ''I would characterize this move as pre-emptory in a soft economy, in the context of a weak stock market,'' said a Raytheon spokesman, Jim Gregory. The company employs 10,200 people in Kansas, most at its Wichita site where most of the cuts will be made.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/27/business/company-news-raytheon-business-jet-gets-faa-certification.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON BUSINESS JET GETS F.A.A. CERTIFICATION<date>Published: March 27, 2001</date><text>Raytheon has received certification from the Federal Aviation Administration for its Premier I business jet, the company said yesterday. Raytheon said it has more than 300 of the six-passenger, $5.3 million business jets on order and is preparing to deliver up to 60 a year. ''It was certainly a very important event,'' said Paul Nisbett, an aerospace analyst with JSA Research in Newport, R.I. ''They've been waiting for this for over a year.'' Mr. Nisbett said it is widely understood that Raytheon is trying to sell its aircraft division, based in Wichita, Kan., which had revenues of $3.2 billion last year, to reduce its $10 billion debt load. A Raytheon spokesman, David Polk, declined to comment on whether the unit is for sale.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/14/business/lockheed-is-seeking-work-on-air-traffic-system.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Lockheed Is Seeking Work on Air Traffic System<date>Published: March 14, 2001</date><text>Lockheed Martin began an effort today to try to replace Raytheon as the contractor modernizing the nation's air traffic control systems, telling federal regulators that it could do the job faster and cheaper.Raytheon's STARS modernization project is expected to be completed by 2002 at a cost of $1.4 billion -- almost $500 million over budget and three and a half years late. Raytheon has already been paid $406.9 million, said Fraser Jones, a Federal Aviation Administration spokesman.Lockheed said it could complete the project in three years for $500 million, saving the government about $400 million.Lockheed also asked the F.A.A. to do a cost-benefit analysis of its proposal versus Raytheon's.''We can begin the delivery of new technology to F.A.A. terminal facilities within 12 months and complete the deployment within three years,'' said Don Antonucci, president of Lockheed Martin Air Traffic Management. ''Our proposal will save hundreds of millions of dollars.''Raytheon won the STARS contract in 1996 to modernize the computer system for controlling air traffic approaching and leaving airports, beating Lockheed Martin and Boeing.The project, originally awarded for $940 million, was to have been completed by 1998.The Lockheed plan was announced a day before a Congressional hearing on air traffic control modernization before a subcommittee of the House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee. Lockheed officials are not scheduled to testify.Representatives of the F.A.A. and Raytheon said they had seen the Lockheed news release but not the full proposal.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/09/business/big-contractor-sues-raytheon-in-the-sale-of-a-unit.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Big Contractor Sues Raytheon in the Sale of a Unit<date>Published: March 09, 2001</date><text>Washington Group International, one of the nation's largest construction companies, said yesterday that it had sued the Raytheon Company, accusing it of misrepresenting the financial condition of a construction and engineering unit that Raytheon sold to Washington Group.In the suit, which was filed in a state district court in Idaho, the Washington Group said Raytheon had failed to comply with the terms of the sale, including the appointment of an independent accounting firm and an audit of the unit's financial statements.''These undisclosed problems from projects that were in trouble before we acquired them are threatening to destroy our company,'' said Stephen Hanks, president of Washington Group, which is based in Boise, Idaho. ''We will not stand by and let that happen.''The civil suit seeks the cancellation of the deal or unspecified damages. In its original form, filed last week, the complaint did not charge fraud or seek to dissolve the deal, said Brad P. Miller, a lawyer for Washington Group International.David Polk, a spokesman for Raytheon, said he had not seen the amended version of the complaint, which was filed today.''We deny any and all allegations of fraud or wrongdoing in connection with the sale,'' Mr. Polk said. ''The due diligence done by W.G.I. was long and extensive. We deny any claim that financial statements provided were in error.''Washington Group bought the unit, Raytheon Engineers and Constructors, for $53 million in cash in July, and assumed liabilities of $450 million.Last week, Washington Group said it might seek Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection because the unit had produced $700 million in unexpected losses. The company attributed those losses in part to cost overruns on some contracts and lower-than-expected profits on other contracts, and said they had created a cash-flow crisis and put it in default of debt agreements.Shares of Washington Group rose 11 cents yesterday, to close at $2.20.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/06/business/raytheon-is-sued-over-deal.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Raytheon Is Sued Over Deal<date>Published: March 06, 2001</date><text>Washington Group International, the large construction company formerly known as Morrison Knudsen, said that it is suing the Raytheon Company over losses and cost overruns at an engineering unit that Washington acquired last year.Washington filed the lawsuit last week in an Idaho state court seeking to compel Raytheon to release audited financial statements for the unit, said Brent D. Brandon, a spokesman. Washington is asking for $400 million from Raytheon, which has said it does not believe it owes a refund.On Friday, Washington said it may file for bankruptcy court protection from its creditors because of the losses and cost overruns. The company bought the unit in July for $53 million and assumed $450 million in liabilities.Raytheon, a leading defense contractor, retained responsibility on some projects and agreed to compensate Washington for cost overruns on another.Washington is facing a cash crunch, is in default of credit agreements and cannot secure performance bonds needed to start new projects. Washington will meet with lenders on Tuesday and on Friday, its president, Stephen G. Hanks, said during a conference call.The company's shares have tumbled 87 percent since Thursday, while its bonds dropped by more than half.Raytheon, based in Lexington, Mass., declined to comment because it hasn't seen the lawsuit, said David Polk, a spokesman.Washington Group plans to hold a conference call with its lenders on Tuesday. Credit Suisse First Boston arranged a $1 billion loan in June to help the company buy the Raytheon unit.The company is likely to consider debtor-in-possession financing, among other options, bankers said. This type of financing allows companies to continue operations under bankruptcy court protection.Bankruptcy law stipulates that debtor-in-possession lenders are the first to be repaid and will have a first priority lien on the assets of a company in bankruptcy.Shares of Washington, based here, fell 58 cents today to $1.07. The widely traded Class B shares of Raytheon rose 78 cents to $31.45.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/03/business/blaming-raytheon-deal-contractor-warns-of-bankruptcy.html?ref=raytheoncompany">Blaming Raytheon Deal, Contractor Warns of Bankruptcy<date>Published: March 03, 2001</date><text>Washington Group International, among the nation's largest construction companies, said yesterday that it might seek bankruptcy protection if the Raytheon Company did not refund a portion of the price that Washington paid for Raytheon's building and engineering unit.Washington said that since the acquisition it had faced about $700 million in unexpected losses because of cost overruns on some contracts, lower-than-expected profits on others and other liabilities, creating a cash-flow crisis and putting it in default of debt agreements. The company, once known as Morrison Knudsen, is considering selling assets, adding debt or issuing more shares, but it has lost substantial credibility on Wall Street. Its shares fell $6.35, or 79 percent, to $1.65 yesterday.Raytheon said it did not believe that it would owe a refund.The dispute involves Raytheon Engineers and Constructors International, a specialist in power plant construction that reported revenue of $2.7 billion in 1999. Washington paid $53 million in cash for the unit and assumed $450 million in debt.Now the company, which has delayed reporting its financial results, said that its outside accountants recommended seeking at least $400 million in cash from Raytheon because it guaranteed the performance of certain construction contracts that the unit had signed before the deal, a Washington spokesman said.Raytheon said it could not determine whether it owed a refund until Washington provided an itemized account of its unexpected costs, said David Polk, a Raytheon spokesman. Washington said, however, that it had already sent Raytheon that information. ''Why would we delay this?'' asked Brent Brandon, the company spokesman. ''This is money back to us.''Mr. Brandon said the deal was initially attractive because the power industry was on the verge of the current boom. He said Washington was denied the access it wanted for a detailed examination of the Raytheon unit's finances, but it moved quickly to complete the deal because it believed the unit's employees were leaving.Given that, he said, ''it was important that we reserved the right to adjust the purchase price.''But Raytheon said that Washington was given full access to all construction projects for 10 months. After that process, Raytheon agreed to retain responsibility for four large projects Washington deemed risky.''It may be that W.G.I. bit off more than it could chew, but we certainly aren't responsible for any failure by W.G.I. to manage projects properly after closing,'' Thomas D. Hyde, Raytheon's general counsel, said.Dennis R. Washington, the chairman of the Washington Group, has built his reputation and fortune acquiring troubled companies, first with a privately held business. Through the 1990's, Mr. Washington expanded the former Morrison Knudsen in an industry where mergers are uncommon because companies are reluctant to acquire contract backlogs. The terms of the deal between Washington and Raytheon did not include a breakup fee.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/08/business/company-news-raytheon-shares-fall-on-news-of-jet-approval-delay.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON SHARES FALL ON NEWS OF JET-APPROVAL DELAY<date>Published: February 08, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company, a leading military contractor, said yesterday that the federal government would not approve the design of its Premier business jet until the second quarter, later than investors had hoped. The Federal Aviation Administration held up certification because it was concerned that the wheels might burst under certain landing conditions. Testing has been scheduled, said Hansel Tookes, the aircraft division's chairman. He did not specify a date. Raytheon's Class B shares fell $1.58, to $33.81. It is based in Lexington, Mass.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/03/business/company-news-raytheon-plans-to-issue-a-single-class-of-stock.html?ref=raytheoncompany">COMPANY NEWS; RAYTHEON PLANS TO ISSUE A SINGLE CLASS OF STOCK<date>Published: February 03, 2001</date><text>The Raytheon Company said its board had approved a plan to combine its two separate classes of shares into a new, single class of common stock. The company, which makes Patriot missiles, business jets, radar and air traffic control systems, said consolidating its shares would probably increase the liquidity of its stock. The company, based in Lexington, Mass., said it had received a ruling from the Internal Revenue Service permitting the move. The current dual class structure was established to allow the 1997 merger of Raytheon and the defense business of the Hughes Electronics Corporation to be tax free to the General Motors Corporation and its shareholders, Raytheon said.</text></article></page></root>
