<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Regions Financial"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/01/business/01norris.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Europe’s Bank Plays Make-Believe With Greece<date>Published: June 30, 2011</date><text>If only C. David Ritter had been a central banker, rather than a commercial banker, he could be retiring with praise, rather than facing possible legal liability for following the time-dishonored practice of “extend and pretend,” in which bad loans are treated as if they were just fine.For that is precisely what Jean-Claude Trichet, the president of the European Central Bank, has successfully demanded be done about Greek national debt. As the tear gas cleared in Athens this week — and the Greek Parliament agreed to a new round of austerity that will raise unemployment and prolong a debilitating recession that almost certainly will ensure that the latest fiscal targets are missed — the critical concern seemed to be making sure that no financial institution will ever have to admit making a bad loan. Mr. Ritter was the chief executive of Regions Financial, a “super-regional” bank holding company based in Alabama, until he stepped down in 2010 after it became clear the bank was in deep trouble. It lives on, thanks to the bailout, but is the only major American bank not to have repaid the bailout money. Mr. Trichet will retire later this year after eight years at the helm of the E.C.B., at which time he will surely be praised for his leadership in dealing with the Greek crisis. Mr. Ritter is facing investigations by the Federal Reserve Board and his own bank’s audit committee over accusations — made by former bank officers — that he and other executives pretended loans were still performing as the financial crisis intensified in 2008. That enabled the bank to keep reporting profits while other banks suffered losses. As negotiations proceeded in Europe this spring over Greek Bailout II, Mr. Trichet laid down a line in the sand: Nothing must be done to force banks to take losses on the bad loans they have made to Greece. Just over a year ago, when Greek Bailout I was announced, the assumption was that by next year Greece would again be able to borrow from capital markets. Instead, the economy has continued to plunge, fiscal targets have not been met and rampant tax evasion continues as it always has. What has changed is the ownership of the debt. Certainly no one who owns Greek bonds now is under the impression they are safe investments, and many investors — banks and others — have taken losses and exited. In the spring of 2010, Mr. Trichet seemed surprised by a suggestion that the central bank should buy Greek bonds for its own account. Within days, the bank was doing just that. Add in the dubious collateral the central bank has taken on loans to banks in Greece and elsewhere, and its own balance sheet would not look good at all if Greece defaulted. But central banks can print money, and I don’t want to suggest it is only the bank’s self-interest that guides its policies. There is also great fear that many banks in Europe, still recovering from the last crisis, will have to seek another round of bailouts if Greece defaults. And it may be that the banks that still hold Greek debt include some institutions that are least able to bear the risk. Those that sold in the last year had to report losses, something troubled banks are reluctant to do. It may be worth it to ask for a moment what would have happened if there were no E.C.B. and no euro currency. Greece would probably have defaulted and there would have been a restructuring of its debts. The same would be true of Greek banks. The Greek currency would have plunged in value, impoverishing Greeks who could no longer afford imported goods, but some export businesses would have boomed as their costs collapsed. The economy would be growing by now. One recent possible precedent comes from, of all places, Kazakhstan. When two of its banks collapsed, there was no bailout available. The country changed its laws to allow bank restructuring, and the resulting negotiations caused lenders to the banks to take losses of more than half their money. In other words, those who lent money to irresponsible borrowers suffered. Francis Fitzherbert-Brockholes, a London-based partner in the law firm of White &amp; Case, worked on that restructuring, and he questions whether austerity alone can enable Greece to grow and service its enormous debts. He thinks that Greece must get “some sort of relief” on its debts or Europe and the International Monetary Fund will just have to keep putting up more money. There is a case for “extend and pretend,” also known as “delay and pray” to bankers who sometimes seem better at rhyming then lending. If the borrower’s distress is temporary, delay can provide time for recovery. That tactic was used by bank regulators when American banks got into trouble in the early 1990s, and seemed to work, although the fact they did not suffer may have helped encourage the banks to plunge into the new excesses that led to the recent crisis. 1 2 Next Page »If only C. David Ritter had been a central banker, rather than a commercial banker, he could be retiring with praise, rather than facing possible legal liability for following the time-dishonored practice of “extend and pretend,” in which bad loans are treated as if they were just fine.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDE103EF930A15755C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Regions Settles S.E.C. Action And Puts a Unit Up for Sale<date>Published: June 23, 2011</date><text>Lucas Jackson/Reuters Robert Khuzami, director of the S.E.C.'s enforcement division, in February.As regulators announced a settlement Wednesday with Morgan Keegan of charges that it defrauded customers during the financial crisis, its parent put the brokerage firm on the block. Morgan Keegan, a unit of Regions Financial, the big Alabama-based bank, agreed to pay $200 million to resolve a case brought by the Securities and Exchange Commission. It accused the brokerage firm and two former executives of mispricing risky mortgage-backed bonds in supposedly conservative mutual funds. One of those executives, the funds' portfolio manager, James C. Kelsoe Jr., agreed to a lifetime ban from the securities industry. ''The falsification of fund values misrepresented critical information exactly when investors needed it most - when the subprime mortgage meltdown was impacting the funds,'' Robert Khuzami, the director of enforcement at the S.E.C., said in a statement. ''Such misconduct does grievous harm to investors.'' Also Wednesday, Regions announced that it was putting Morgan Keegan up for sale in an effort to raise money to repay the $3.5 billion government loan it received during the financial crisis. ''The resolution of this legacy regulatory matter gives Regions great flexibility with respect to the Morgan Keegan franchise,'' said Grayson Hall, the chief executive of Regions, which sold the bond funds connected to this case in 2008 to another asset management company. Regions, which has owned Morgan Keegan since 2001, has retained Goldman Sachs to handle the sale of the brokerage firm. The firm, which is based in Memphis, could fetch as much as $1.5 billion, according to a person briefed on the business. The action against Morgan Keegan is just one of a spate of enforcement actions taken against firms related to their mispricing of mortgage securities in their mutual funds during the financial crisis. The S.E.C. has brought similar cases against the Charles Schwab Corporation, Evergreen Investments and the State Street Corporation. Federal authorities have recently stepped up actions against large banks related to their crisis-era conduct. On Tuesday, JPMorgan Chase agreed to pay about $150 million to settle civil accusations that it misled investors in a complex mortgage securities transaction in 2007. Last month, federal prosecutors in Manhattan filed a civil action against Deutsche Bank, accusing it of lying about the quality of home loans it handled for the Federal Housing Administration. The bank is fighting the case. Still, authorities continue to field questions about why they are not bringing criminal charges against bank executives and others who may have engaged in illegal practices during the mortgage boom. During a conference call with regulators on Wednesday, a reporter asked why the government did not bring criminal charges in the Morgan Keegan case. The government officials declined to comment. Investors in the five Morgan Keegan bond funds are said to have lost about $1.5 billion. These funds, which were marketed as relatively safe investment vehicles, lost more than half their value when the market for mortgage securities first seized up in 2007. Two former Morgan Keegan executives - Mr. Kelsoe and Joseph Thompson Weller, a controller - were accused in the case. Mr. Kelsoe, who started managing the Morgan Keegan funds in 1999, was a vocal booster of mortgage securities during the housing boom and became one of Wall Street's top-ranked mutual fund managers. Investors reaching for extra yield during last decade's persistently low-interest-rate environment flocked to Mr. Kelsoe's funds. But regulators said that Mr. Kelsoe ignored the funds' charter by investing predominantly in the risky structured products that became popular during the credit bubble, including pools of subprime mortgage-backed securities. The S.E.C. action also accused him of instructing Morgan Keegan's accounting department to make fake ''price adjustments'' to inflate the value of the funds' mortgage-backed securities holdings as the housing market began to sour. Mr. Kelsoe became an early, prominent casualty of the crisis in subprime mortgage bonds. ''What was an ocean of liquidity has quickly become a desert,'' wrote Mr. Kelsoe in a report to his investors in October 2007 as the fund was plummeting. He once compared his ''intoxication'' with low-grade mortgage securities to that of fund managers seduced by dot-com stocks. Mr. Kelsoe, 49 and a resident of Memphis, agreed to pay a $500,000 penalty and accept a permanent ban from the securities industry. Mr. Weller agreed to pay a $50,000 fine. Regulators from the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority, or Finra, as well as regulators from five Southern states were involved in the Morgan Keegan investigation and settlement. Federal and state authorities continue to pursue separate claims against Morgan Keegan related to its sale of auction-rate securities, another risky investment product that soured during the financial crisis. Although buffeted by the government's accusations, Morgan Keegan has performed well. Potential buyers could include a bank or brokerage firm looking to bolster its presence in the Southeast, or a private equity firm. A number of buyout shops have previously made successful investment in brokerage firms and asset managers, including Hellman &amp; Friedman, TA Associates and Lightyear Capital. This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print. PHOTO: James C. Kelsoe Jr. (B6)</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/22/morgan-keegan-settles-mortgage-securities-case-and-is-put-on-the-block/?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Morgan Keegan Settles Mortgage Securities Case and Is Put on the Block<date>June 22, 2011, 8:18 pm</date><text>Lucas Jackson/Reuters Robert Khuzami, director of the S.E.C.’s enforcement division, in February. As regulators announced a settlement Wednesday with Morgan Keegan of charges that it defrauded customers during the financial crisis, its parent put the brokerage firm on the block. Morgan Keegan, a unit of Regions Financial, the big Alabama-based bank, agreed to pay $200 million to resolve a case brought by the Securities and Exchange Commission. It accused the brokerage firm and two former executives of mispricing risky mortgage-backed bonds in supposedly conservative mutual funds. Morgan Keegan, via Bloomberg NewsJames C. Kelsoe Jr. One of those executives, the funds’ portfolio manager, James C. Kelsoe Jr., agreed to a lifetime ban from the securities industry. “The falsification of fund values misrepresented critical information exactly when investors needed it most — when the subprime mortgage meltdown was impacting the funds,” Robert Khuzami, the director of enforcement at the S.E.C., said in a statement. ”Such misconduct does grievous harm to investors.” Also Wednesday, Regions announced that it was putting Morgan Keegan up for sale in an effort to raise money to repay the $3.5 billion government loan it received during the financial crisis. “The resolution of this legacy regulatory matter gives Regions great flexibility with respect to the Morgan Keegan franchise,” said Grayson Hall, the chief executive of Regions, which sold the bond funds connected to this case in 2008 to another asset management company. Regions, which has owned Morgan Keegan since 2001, has retained Goldman Sachs to handle the sale of the brokerage firm. The firm, which is based in Memphis, could fetch as much as $1.5 billion, according to a person briefed on the business. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links S.E.C.'s order Regions Financial's statement Chart: Tracking Financial Crisis Cases The action against Morgan Keegan is just one of a spate of enforcement actions taken against firms related to their mispricing of mortgage securities in their mutual funds during the financial crisis. The S.E.C. has brought similar cases against the Charles Schwab Corporation, Evergreen Investments and the State Street Corporation. Federal authorities have recently stepped up actions against large banks related to their crisis-era conduct. On Tuesday, JPMorgan Chase agreed to pay about $150 million to settle civil accusations that it misled investors in a complex mortgage securities transaction in 2007. Last month, federal prosecutors in Manhattan filed a civil action against Deutsche Bank, accusing it of lying about the quality of home loans it handled for the Federal Housing Administration. The bank is fighting the case. Still, authorities continue to field questions about why they are not bringing criminal charges against bank executives and others who may have engaged in illegal practices during the mortgage boom. During a conference call with regulators on Wednesday, a reporter asked why the government did not bring criminal charges in the Morgan Keegan case. The government officials declined to comment. Investors in the five Morgan Keegan bond funds are said to have lost about $1.5 billion. These funds, which were marketed as relatively safe investment vehicles, lost more than half their value when the market for mortgage securities first seized up in 2007. Two former Morgan Keegan executives — Mr. Kelsoe and Joseph Thompson Weller, a controller — were accused in the case. Mr. Kelsoe, who started managing the Morgan Keegan funds in 1999, was a vocal booster of mortgage securities during the housing boom and became one of Wall Street’s top-ranked mutual fund managers. Investors reaching for extra yield during last decade’s persistently low-interest-rate environment flocked to Mr. Kelsoe’s funds. But regulators said that Mr. Kelsoe ignored the funds’ charter by investing predominantly in the risky structured products that became popular during the credit bubble, including pools of subprime mortgage-backed securities. The S.E.C. action also accused him of instructing Morgan Keegan’s accounting department to make fake “price adjustments” to inflate the value of the funds’ mortgage-backed securities holdings as the housing market began to sour. Mr. Kelsoe became an early, prominent casualty of the crisis in subprime mortgage bonds. “What was an ocean of liquidity has quickly become a desert,” wrote Mr. Kelsoe in a report to his investors in October 2007 as the fund was plummeting. He once compared his “intoxication” with low-grade mortgage securities to that of fund managers seduced by dot-com stocks. Mr. Kelsoe, 49 and a resident of Memphis, agreed to pay a $500,000 penalty and accept a permanent ban from the securities industry. Mr. Weller agreed to pay a $50,000 fine. Regulators from the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority, or Finra, as well as regulators from five Southern states were involved in the Morgan Keegan investigation and settlement. Federal and state authorities continue to pursue separate claims against Morgan Keegan related to its sale of auction-rate securities, another risky investment product that soured during the financial crisis. Although buffeted by the government’s accusations, Morgan Keegan has performed well. Potential buyers could include a bank or brokerage firm looking to bolster its presence in the Southeast, or a private equity firm. A number of buyout shops have previously made successful investment in brokerage firms and asset managers, including Hellman &amp; Friedman, TA Associates and Lightyear Capital.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/08/business/08views.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Tests May Spur Bank Mergers<date>Published: May 7, 2009</date><text>For America’s regional banks, it’s merger time. With the results of the stress tests now public, it’s clear that none of the country’s largest financial institutions will fail. Those that need capital will find it, even if it takes de facto nationalization. But that doesn’t mean the banking system is robust. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Regions Financial Corporation US Bancorp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » A handful of regional institutions received the equivalent of barely passing grades  including SunTrust, Regions Financial, KeyCorp and Fifth Third. These banks have more than $500 billion of assets among them. Even if they can raise the extra capital that regulators say they need, they may not be in a position to act as engines of credit creation  a requirement for their local economies to pull out of the recession. Moreover, if they can’t raise private money over the next six months, they may need to have the government take significant, or even majority, stakes in them. One risk is that they will stagger along, zombielike, for years. There’s an alternative: Let the strong eat the weak. A core group of relatively robust regional banks has also emerged from the Treasury’s examinations, including U.S. Bancorp and BB&amp;T, as well as PNC Financial, which has to raise a relatively modest $600 million. An alternative to propping up troubled banks with new capital is to actively encourage a wave of consolidation. This approach would make life simpler for the government should the banks fail to raise private capital. Rather than taking controlling positions in many midsize banks, the government could take smaller stakes (or none at all) in fewer, larger banks that in turn use the capital to buy troubled rivals. By encouraging, for instance, the acquisition of SunTrust by BB&amp;T, the takeover of KeyCorp by U.S. Bancorp and the purchase of Regions by PNC, the government would foster the creation of three new heavyweights better equipped to compete with JPMorgan Chase, Wells Fargo and Bank of America. These three went from big to megabanks by acquiring troubled rivals like Washington Mutual, Wachovia and Countrywide early in the banking crisis, in deals blessed by regulators. In theory, this approach would also streamline and improve regulation. Instead of scattering oversight among six institutions, the government could focus on three. By favoring more of the banks that fared best in the crisis and not just the very biggest, it rewards those executives whose teams proved better at risk management, like Richard Davis, chief of U.S. Bancorp. Finally, the enormous savings that would come from cutting overlapping operations, extra branches and redundant workers would accrue to shareholders and add to the capital cushions. Last year Fifth Third, SunTrust, KeyCorp and Regions had combined noninterest expenses of $18.5 billion. As a general rule of thumb, knowledgeable bank acquirers aim to save about one-third of these costs. Gentlemen, start your M.&amp; A. spreadsheets. Boon for Underwriters Banks must raise $75 billion of equity over the next six months. That sounds bad, but on Wall Street it may be cause for some celebration. That’s because the underwriters who sell all of that stock can charge fees of as much as $3 billion for doing so. In the grand scheme of a $75 billion capital shortfall, it’s a pittance. But on the equity capital markets desks of the big investment banks, it would be a bonanza. Dealogic estimates it could add up to 12 times the amount they’ve earned so far this year. Underemployed bankers at Merrill Lynch may finally have a reason to applaud their new bosses’ missteps. Merrill’s new owner, Bank of America, needs the biggest capital infusion of all  $34 billion. Of course, the lead manager on a bank’s stock offering is often the bank itself, which is motivated not to ratchet up fees. And many of the banks that the government has ordered to raise more capital may do so by swapping existing preferred shares for common stock. But with most bank stocks trading at decent premiums to the prices at which they would have to convert the government’s preferred stock, it’s a fair bet the next six months will be happier for the underwriters of Wall Street. ROB COX and DWIGHT CASS For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on May 8, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.For America’s regional banks, it’s merger time. With the results of the stress tests now public, it’s clear that none of the country’s largest financial institutions will fail. Those that need capital will find it, even if it takes de facto nationalization. But that doesn’t mean the banking system is robust. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Regions Financial Corporation US Bancorp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » A handful of regional institutions received the equivalent of barely passing grades  including SunTrust, Regions Financial, KeyCorp and Fifth Third. These banks have more than $500 billion of assets among them. Even if they can raise the extra capital that regulators say they need, they may not be in a position to act as engines of credit creation  a requirement for their local economies to pull out of the recession. Moreover, if they can’t raise private money over the next six months, they may need to have the government take significant, or even majority, stakes in them. One risk is that they will stagger along, zombielike, for years. There’s an alternative: Let the strong eat the weak. A core group of relatively robust regional banks has also emerged from the Treasury’s examinations, including U.S. Bancorp and BB&amp;T, as well as PNC Financial, which has to raise a relatively modest $600 million. An alternative to propping up troubled banks with new capital is to actively encourage a wave of consolidation. This approach would make life simpler for the government should the banks fail to raise private capital. Rather than taking controlling positions in many midsize banks, the government could take smaller stakes (or none at all) in fewer, larger banks that in turn use the capital to buy troubled rivals. By encouraging, for instance, the acquisition of SunTrust by BB&amp;T, the takeover of KeyCorp by U.S. Bancorp and the purchase of Regions by PNC, the government would foster the creation of three new heavyweights better equipped to compete with JPMorgan Chase, Wells Fargo and Bank of America. These three went from big to megabanks by acquiring troubled rivals like Washington Mutual, Wachovia and Countrywide early in the banking crisis, in deals blessed by regulators. In theory, this approach would also streamline and improve regulation. Instead of scattering oversight among six institutions, the government could focus on three. By favoring more of the banks that fared best in the crisis and not just the very biggest, it rewards those executives whose teams proved better at risk management, like Richard Davis, chief of U.S. Bancorp. Finally, the enormous savings that would come from cutting overlapping operations, extra branches and redundant workers would accrue to shareholders and add to the capital cushions. Last year Fifth Third, SunTrust, KeyCorp and Regions had combined noninterest expenses of $18.5 billion. As a general rule of thumb, knowledgeable bank acquirers aim to save about one-third of these costs. Gentlemen, start your M.&amp; A. spreadsheets. Boon for Underwriters Banks must raise $75 billion of equity over the next six months. That sounds bad, but on Wall Street it may be cause for some celebration. That’s because the underwriters who sell all of that stock can charge fees of as much as $3 billion for doing so. In the grand scheme of a $75 billion capital shortfall, it’s a pittance. But on the equity capital markets desks of the big investment banks, it would be a bonanza. Dealogic estimates it could add up to 12 times the amount they’ve earned so far this year. Underemployed bankers at Merrill Lynch may finally have a reason to applaud their new bosses’ missteps. Merrill’s new owner, Bank of America, needs the biggest capital infusion of all  $34 billion. Of course, the lead manager on a bank’s stock offering is often the bank itself, which is motivated not to ratchet up fees. And many of the banks that the government has ordered to raise more capital may do so by swapping existing preferred shares for common stock. But with most bank stocks trading at decent premiums to the prices at which they would have to convert the government’s preferred stock, it’s a fair bet the next six months will be happier for the underwriters of Wall Street. ROB COX and DWIGHT CASS For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DE163FF932A25751C0A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">New Plan, Old Doubts: Investors Register Disappointment, Sending Markets Into a Swoon<date>Published: February 11, 2009</date><text>Investors had been expecting the Obama administration to unveil a shock and awe solution on Tuesday for the nation's hobbled banking system. But the main reaction was disappointment as the new plan raised more questions than it answered, sending stock markets and the shares of banks assumed to be holding toxic assets sharply lower. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 381.99 points, or 4.6 percent, to close at 7,888.88, led by steep declines in Bank of America, Citigroup and large banks already leaning on taxpayers for support. Regions Bank, SunTrust, KeyCorp and Fifth Third fell even more as investors worried that regional banks could be vulnerable to a new ''stress test'' aimed at revealing the weakest links in the industry. ''The market was looking for a silver bullet,'' said David H. Ellison, the chief investment officer for FBR Funds, which specializes in the banking sector. ''They are getting the wake-up call again that it is going to take time. There is no quick fix here.'' Treasury Secretary Timothy F. Geithner laid out a $2 trillion financial stability plan, including an effort to entice private equity, hedge funds and other investors to buy hard-to-sell assets that have bogged down banks. Another involves a new round of capital injections for banks deemed to have enough resources to withstand a continued economic decline. David Burg, a financial analyst at Alpine Mutual Funds, said bank stocks plunged because the initiative would force many troubled financial institutions to take large amounts of new capital that would dilute the value of their outstanding shares. ''These guys are going to do a stress test on top banks and say, based on the results, 'You need X amount of new capital and you have to take it.' Common shareholders in these banks will get absolutely destroyed,'' he said. But that was about the only certainty investors took from hours of speeches and testimony by Mr. Geithner on Tuesday. Investors said his failure to publicly detail the mechanics of the plan forced them to make wild assumptions about various players in the industry. For example, the proposed ''stress test'' seems intended to allow regulators to better assess the depth of a bank's problems, and to convince taxpayers that they are not pouring money down an endless hole. The test automatically applies to the nation's 20 largest banks, and to any other bank applying for taxpayer support. Federal officials are expected to demand that banks maintain ultraconservative capital levels -- enough to weather the possibility of a further economic downturn, said a government official who was not authorized to speak publicly. The goal is for banks to have enough of a buffer to lend during the current downturn. That could mean that banks that normally would not need additional capital could require it if the economy worsened. Banks will be expected to assess their expected losses over the next two years. While Mr. Geithner did not say whether derivatives, or off-balance sheet exposures, would be included in the test, the government official said the test would be customized based on each bank's mix of loans and its history of losses. Regulators will also continue to look at a whether a bank is holding at least 6 percent of so-called Tier 1 capital, a well-known measure of its financial health, and whether at least half of that capital is held in common stock, the official said. But regulators will have leeway to allow a bank to continue operating if it falls slightly short of that standard. It is unclear how the test will apply to Citigroup and Bank of America. Investors are concerned that, unlike these banking giants, any number of regional banks are not considered too big to fail. That is worrisome in the current environment because many are sitting on commercial real estate loans whose value is eroding rapidly with the economy. If regulators impose loose standards for the test, banks that might not otherwise survive could receive a lifeline. If they take a stricter stance, it could lead to another wave of takeovers and failures.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/21/business/21markets.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Optimism in Washington, but Pessimism on Wall St.<date>Published: January 20, 2009</date><text>President Obama took office Tuesday urging Americans to choose hope over fear, but on Wall Street, fear was making a comeback. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Interactive Graphic Calculate Your Financial Comeback Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis -- The Essentials Add to Portfolio State Street Corporation Go to your Portfolio » Stock markets had one of their worst Inauguration Day losses in more than a century, skidding more than 4 percent. Financial companies plunged more than 15 percent, their biggest one-day drop in nearly two decades, as investors worried that the troubles facing the country’s biggest banks might be larger and deeper than anyone had thought. Even after record corporate write-downs and a $700 billion bailout to shore up the financial system, banks are still reporting huge losses, lining up for new government lifelines and cutting their profit outlooks. The State Street Corporation, one of the world’s largest institutional money managers, reported a 71 percent drop in fourth-quarter profit, sending its share price down 59 percent. The bigger economic picture is still a landscape of “gathering clouds and raging storms,” Mr. Obama said Tuesday. Housing values are falling faster, trade is shrinking and the unemployment rate, now at 7.2 percent, is expected to hit 9 percent or more. “At the end of the year, we saw some light at the end of the tunnel,” said Art Hogan, chief market strategist at Jefferies &amp; Company. “Unfortunately, we found out that the light at the end of the tunnel was a train.” Wall Street opened down and slid steadily lower throughout the day. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 332.13 points, or 4 percent, to 7,949.09. The Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index tumbled 5.28 percent, or 44.90 points, to 805.22. The Nasdaq composite index declined 5.78 percent, or 88.47 points, to 1,440.86. The losses erased all of Wall Street’s gains from the start of the year and brought stocks within reach of their lows of Nov. 20. Some analysts said they thought that Wall Street might now be headed there again. “It’s ugly,” said James W. Paulsen, chief investment strategist at Wells Capital Management. “It’s got all the makings of the late November panic.” Financial shares went into a free fall on Tuesday. Shares of Citigroup, once the largest American bank, fell 20 percent, or 70 cents, to $2.80 a share, and the bank cut its quarterly dividend to 1 cent. Bank of America fell 29 percent, or $2.08, to $5.10. Shares of JPMorgan Chase, Morgan Stanley, Wells Fargo and several other banks also dropped by double digits. State Street, which received $2 billion last year from the federal bailout fund, plunged 59 percent, or $21.46, to $14.89. Analysts said that the losses might force State Street to eventually raise more capital or sell itself. The drop in State Street’s shares also caused heavy selling in other so-called custody banks like Bank of New York Mellon and Northern Trust. Custody banks perform often mundane tasks for institutional investors, including recordkeeping, tracking performance and lending securities to hedge funds, mutual funds and pensions. Analysts and investors are worried that State Street’s continued losses on bond funds and other investments could cause credit agencies to lower their ratings, making it more costly for it to finance continuing operations. “The big question facing State Street and other banks is how much capital they need to satisfy investors, rating agencies and regulators,” said Mike Mayo, an analyst at Deutsche Bank. “The government needs to define what the minimum capital ratios should be for banks.” Regions Financial, which has banks in 16 states, reported a $6.2 billion loss for the fourth quarter. Its shares fell 24 percent, to $4.60. Investors took little solace from the latest measures by Britain and Canada to address the deepening recession. The Bank of Canada cut its benchmark interest rate by half a percentage point, to 1 percent, after Britain announced on Monday another bailout plan that included a measure to increase the government’s stake in the Royal Bank of Scotland to 70 percent. “It’s a growing lack of confidence, and almost panic, that’s traveling around the world right now,” said Michael Holland, chairman of Holland &amp; Company. As volatility rises and markets tumble lower, analysts said that Mr. Obama and Congress could not move fast enough to push an $825 billion stimulus package of tax cuts, public works projects and emergency benefits into law. “That fear that’s creeping back into Wall Street is spreading to the broader market,” said Ryan Larson, senior equity trader at Voyageur Asset Management. “We’re going to have to see some real action plans to get us out of this. We’re going to have to see the new administration step forward and announce some of these plans that are going to kick-start the market.” Crude oil prices settled at $38.74 a barrel, up $2.23 in New York trading. Oil prices have tumbled from their summer highs above $145 a barrel on weakening demand for gasoline and other petroleum products. The Treasury’s 10-year note fell 18/32, to 111 30/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 2.38 percent, from 2.32 percent late Friday. Following are the results of Tuesday’s Treasury auction of three- and six-month bills: More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 21, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.President Obama took office Tuesday urging Americans to choose hope over fear, but on Wall Street, fear was making a comeback. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Interactive Graphic Calculate Your Financial Comeback Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis -- The Essentials Add to Portfolio State Street Corporation Go to your Portfolio » Stock markets had one of their worst Inauguration Day losses in more than a century, skidding more than 4 percent. Financial companies plunged more than 15 percent, their biggest one-day drop in nearly two decades, as investors worried that the troubles facing the country’s biggest banks might be larger and deeper than anyone had thought. Even after record corporate write-downs and a $700 billion bailout to shore up the financial system, banks are still reporting huge losses, lining up for new government lifelines and cutting their profit outlooks. The State Street Corporation, one of the world’s largest institutional money managers, reported a 71 percent drop in fourth-quarter profit, sending its share price down 59 percent. The bigger economic picture is still a landscape of “gathering clouds and raging storms,” Mr. Obama said Tuesday. Housing values are falling faster, trade is shrinking and the unemployment rate, now at 7.2 percent, is expected to hit 9 percent or more. “At the end of the year, we saw some light at the end of the tunnel,” said Art Hogan, chief market strategist at Jefferies &amp; Company. “Unfortunately, we found out that the light at the end of the tunnel was a train.” Wall Street opened down and slid steadily lower throughout the day. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 332.13 points, or 4 percent, to 7,949.09. The Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index tumbled 5.28 percent, or 44.90 points, to 805.22. The Nasdaq composite index declined 5.78 percent, or 88.47 points, to 1,440.86. The losses erased all of Wall Street’s gains from the start of the year and brought stocks within reach of their lows of Nov. 20. Some analysts said they thought that Wall Street might now be headed there again. “It’s ugly,” said James W. Paulsen, chief investment strategist at Wells Capital Management. “It’s got all the makings of the late November panic.” Financial shares went into a free fall on Tuesday. Shares of Citigroup, once the largest American bank, fell 20 percent, or 70 cents, to $2.80 a share, and the bank cut its quarterly dividend to 1 cent. Bank of America fell 29 percent, or $2.08, to $5.10. Shares of JPMorgan Chase, Morgan Stanley, Wells Fargo and several other banks also dropped by double digits. State Street, which received $2 billion last year from the federal bailout fund, plunged 59 percent, or $21.46, to $14.89. Analysts said that the losses might force State Street to eventually raise more capital or sell itself. The drop in State Street’s shares also caused heavy selling in other so-called custody banks like Bank of New York Mellon and Northern Trust. Custody banks perform often mundane tasks for institutional investors, including recordkeeping, tracking performance and lending securities to hedge funds, mutual funds and pensions. Analysts and investors are worried that State Street’s continued losses on bond funds and other investments could cause credit agencies to lower their ratings, making it more costly for it to finance continuing operations. “The big question facing State Street and other banks is how much capital they need to satisfy investors, rating agencies and regulators,” said Mike Mayo, an analyst at Deutsche Bank. “The government needs to define what the minimum capital ratios should be for banks.” Regions Financial, which has banks in 16 states, reported a $6.2 billion loss for the fourth quarter. Its shares fell 24 percent, to $4.60. Investors took little solace from the latest measures by Britain and Canada to address the deepening recession. The Bank of Canada cut its benchmark interest rate by half a percentage point, to 1 percent, after Britain announced on Monday another bailout plan that included a measure to increase the government’s stake in the Royal Bank of Scotland to 70 percent. “It’s a growing lack of confidence, and almost panic, that’s traveling around the world right now,” said Michael Holland, chairman of Holland &amp; Company. As volatility rises and markets tumble lower, analysts said that Mr. Obama and Congress could not move fast enough to push an $825 billion stimulus package of tax cuts, public works projects and emergency benefits into law. “That fear that’s creeping back into Wall Street is spreading to the broader market,” said Ryan Larson, senior equity trader at Voyageur Asset Management. “We’re going to have to see some real action plans to get us out of this. We’re going to have to see the new administration step forward and announce some of these plans that are going to kick-start the market.” Crude oil prices settled at $38.74 a barrel, up $2.23 in New York trading. Oil prices have tumbled from their summer highs above $145 a barrel on weakening demand for gasoline and other petroleum products. The Treasury’s 10-year note fell 18/32, to 111 30/32. The yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 2.38 percent, from 2.32 percent late Friday. Following are the results of Tuesday’s Treasury auction of three- and six-month bills:</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/22/business/22bank.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Regional Banks Struggled Through 3rd Quarter<date>Published: October 21, 2008</date><text>In the Depression year of 1933, Cleveland suffered a citywide run on the banks. When the panic subsided, National City Bank was the first to reopen. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Aaron Josefczyk/Reuters National City, among regional banks feeling the strain of the credit squeeze, will lay off 4,000 employees as its losses surge. Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis  The Essentials Add to Portfolio National City Corporation US Bancorp Keycorp Fifth Third Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » But today that Ohio bank, now known as National City Corporation, has come to symbolize the crisis that is hobbling regional lenders across the nation. Many of these midsize institutions face uncertain futures, despite the government’s bank rescue plan. Five regional banks, National City among them, reported another round of painful results on Tuesday, and analysts say their business will worsen as the economy deteriorates. Several of these banks said they hoped to sell stock to the government to shore up their finances, as nine big national banks have done. But with losses mounting, it is unclear how many small and midsize lenders the government will choose to save. In some cases, analysts said, the Treasury will probably play kingmaker, nudging weak banks into the arms of stronger rivals. In others, banks could drag on, reporting disappointing results for at least the next four quarters. “We began over a year ago to try to configure the company for a difficult period,” Peter Raskind, National City’s chief executive, said in an interview Tuesday. “I don’t think anybody thought it would be this difficult.” For National City and many of the other regional banks, things are quickly moving from bad to worse. Mortgages and home equity losses continue to rise as housing prices have yet to find a bottom. Losses on auto and credit card loans have surged. New problem areas, like loans made to small corporations and commercial real estate developers, are starting to come under pressure. And that is with an unemployment rate that up until now has been unusually resilient. As the economy continues to slow and more jobs are lost, the banking industry’s problems could grow even bleaker. National City said it would cut 4,000 jobs as it reported a surge in losses to $729 million for the period, up from $19 million a year earlier. The bank had to increase the cushion it set aside for loan losses to $1.18 billion. Fifth Third, another Ohio-based bank, lost $56 million. KeyCorp of Cincinnati lost $36 million. Regions Financial of Alabama eked out a $79.5 million profit. Shares in the banks rose because their troubles were not as deep as expected, but other banks fell on concerns about their health. U.S. Bancorp of Minneapolis fell almost 3 percent, to $30.20, after reporting a drop in earnings tied to higher projected losses. Bank stocks generally are down about 42 percent in the last year. Investors are staring through a looking glass of diminished expectations, industry experts say. “You get to a point where it is not about the earnings,” said Brian R. Sterling, the co-head of investment banking at Sandler O’Neill and Partners. “It’s all about the book value” of assets and the strength of its balance sheet. They may also be looking to the future. “Historically, bank stocks have bottomed a full year before losses peaked,” said Jason Goldberg, a banking analyst at Barclays Capital. That, he said, is what happened during the recessions that followed the savings and loan crisis and the bursting of the technology bubble. The prospect of deeper losses at banks is setting the stage for a second round of consolidation in the industry, after the recent wave of blockbuster deals that occurred as the nation’s biggest banks swallowed troubled competitors. One regional bank, Sovereign Bancorp, was bought this month by a big Spanish bank amid signs that its finances were deteriorating. Citigroup is on the prowl for a deal that could bolster its relatively small domestic retail banking operations. While some regional banks had been reluctant to undertake or unable to complete such transactions, several regional lenders said Tuesday they would seek to take advantage of the government’s program of capital infusions to snap up weaker rivals. Regions Financial said it would seek to raise as much as $3.5 billion from the government; KeyCorp said it would seek $1.1 billion to $3.3 billion, and Zions Bancorporation of Utah said it would consider asking the government to take a stake of $500 million to $1.5 billion. Executives at BB&amp;T, PNC Financial and U.S. Bancorp also said in conference calls that they found the government’s offer quite attractive. “I am telegraphing that we’re more active and more interested than we might have been before” to pursue a deal, Richard Davis, U.S. Bancorp’s chief executive, said in a conference call Tuesday. Banks will have until Nov. 14 to apply for the Treasury program. Some are being encouraged by their regulators to apply. But others may be deemed too far gone to receive government funds. Indeed, analysts said they expected the government might use the money as an inducement to spur healthier banks to do a deal, or withhold it to urge weaker institutions to consider selling. Mr. Sterling said he would expect “deal dialogue to pick up” as it becomes clear who is getting financing and who is not. But other lenders may have fewer options. National City said that while it was interested in selling troubled assets into the government’s $700 billion bailout fund, it had not decided whether it would seek government capital. “There are a number of implications of taking advantage of it or not taking advantage of it,” Mr. Raskind said. “That is what we are thinking through right now.” Mr. Raskind said the company was cutting costs and had stockpiled enough funds to weather the worsening economy. “We pretty firmly believe we have more than adequate capital to see us through that,” he added. Still, there are more signs of trouble in other areas. Beyond worsening mortgages and consumer loans, analysts say that there are signs that loans made to small and midsize businesses appear to be souring across the country. This had been the bread-and-butter of regional banks, which took advantage of local ties after being elbowed out of the credit card and mortgage business by national players. First Horizon National of Tennessee, Capitol Bancorp of Michigan and Arizona and Sovereign Bancorp of Philadelphia had sharp increases in the percentage of bad loans in their commercial and industrial portfolio, according to an analysis by Friedman, Billings, Ramsey. “It is definitely a sign the economy is weakening,” said Paul Miller, one of its banking analysts. “You have another loan category coming down the road.” And analysts are beginning to see stress in loans to commercial real estate developers, especially in mall properties that are dependent on the retail sector. “There are lots of bank lines and loans out to developers and that type of commercial real estate,” said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. “We are beginning to see a few cracks in office space as well.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 22, 2008, on page B9 of the New York edition.In the Depression year of 1933, Cleveland suffered a citywide run on the banks. When the panic subsided, National City Bank was the first to reopen. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Aaron Josefczyk/Reuters National City, among regional banks feeling the strain of the credit squeeze, will lay off 4,000 employees as its losses surge. Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis  The Essentials Add to Portfolio National City Corporation US Bancorp Keycorp Fifth Third Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » But today that Ohio bank, now known as National City Corporation, has come to symbolize the crisis that is hobbling regional lenders across the nation. Many of these midsize institutions face uncertain futures, despite the government’s bank rescue plan. Five regional banks, National City among them, reported another round of painful results on Tuesday, and analysts say their business will worsen as the economy deteriorates. Several of these banks said they hoped to sell stock to the government to shore up their finances, as nine big national banks have done. But with losses mounting, it is unclear how many small and midsize lenders the government will choose to save. In some cases, analysts said, the Treasury will probably play kingmaker, nudging weak banks into the arms of stronger rivals. In others, banks could drag on, reporting disappointing results for at least the next four quarters. “We began over a year ago to try to configure the company for a difficult period,” Peter Raskind, National City’s chief executive, said in an interview Tuesday. “I don’t think anybody thought it would be this difficult.” For National City and many of the other regional banks, things are quickly moving from bad to worse. Mortgages and home equity losses continue to rise as housing prices have yet to find a bottom. Losses on auto and credit card loans have surged. New problem areas, like loans made to small corporations and commercial real estate developers, are starting to come under pressure. And that is with an unemployment rate that up until now has been unusually resilient. As the economy continues to slow and more jobs are lost, the banking industry’s problems could grow even bleaker. National City said it would cut 4,000 jobs as it reported a surge in losses to $729 million for the period, up from $19 million a year earlier. The bank had to increase the cushion it set aside for loan losses to $1.18 billion. Fifth Third, another Ohio-based bank, lost $56 million. KeyCorp of Cincinnati lost $36 million. Regions Financial of Alabama eked out a $79.5 million profit. Shares in the banks rose because their troubles were not as deep as expected, but other banks fell on concerns about their health. U.S. Bancorp of Minneapolis fell almost 3 percent, to $30.20, after reporting a drop in earnings tied to higher projected losses. Bank stocks generally are down about 42 percent in the last year. Investors are staring through a looking glass of diminished expectations, industry experts say. “You get to a point where it is not about the earnings,” said Brian R. Sterling, the co-head of investment banking at Sandler O’Neill and Partners. “It’s all about the book value” of assets and the strength of its balance sheet. They may also be looking to the future. “Historically, bank stocks have bottomed a full year before losses peaked,” said Jason Goldberg, a banking analyst at Barclays Capital. That, he said, is what happened during the recessions that followed the savings and loan crisis and the bursting of the technology bubble. The prospect of deeper losses at banks is setting the stage for a second round of consolidation in the industry, after the recent wave of blockbuster deals that occurred as the nation’s biggest banks swallowed troubled competitors. One regional bank, Sovereign Bancorp, was bought this month by a big Spanish bank amid signs that its finances were deteriorating. Citigroup is on the prowl for a deal that could bolster its relatively small domestic retail banking operations. While some regional banks had been reluctant to undertake or unable to complete such transactions, several regional lenders said Tuesday they would seek to take advantage of the government’s program of capital infusions to snap up weaker rivals. Regions Financial said it would seek to raise as much as $3.5 billion from the government; KeyCorp said it would seek $1.1 billion to $3.3 billion, and Zions Bancorporation of Utah said it would consider asking the government to take a stake of $500 million to $1.5 billion. Executives at BB&amp;T, PNC Financial and U.S. Bancorp also said in conference calls that they found the government’s offer quite attractive. “I am telegraphing that we’re more active and more interested than we might have been before” to pursue a deal, Richard Davis, U.S. Bancorp’s chief executive, said in a conference call Tuesday. Banks will have until Nov. 14 to apply for the Treasury program. Some are being encouraged by their regulators to apply. But others may be deemed too far gone to receive government funds. Indeed, analysts said they expected the government might use the money as an inducement to spur healthier banks to do a deal, or withhold it to urge weaker institutions to consider selling. Mr. Sterling said he would expect “deal dialogue to pick up” as it becomes clear who is getting financing and who is not. But other lenders may have fewer options. National City said that while it was interested in selling troubled assets into the government’s $700 billion bailout fund, it had not decided whether it would seek government capital. “There are a number of implications of taking advantage of it or not taking advantage of it,” Mr. Raskind said. “That is what we are thinking through right now.” Mr. Raskind said the company was cutting costs and had stockpiled enough funds to weather the worsening economy. “We pretty firmly believe we have more than adequate capital to see us through that,” he added. Still, there are more signs of trouble in other areas. Beyond worsening mortgages and consumer loans, analysts say that there are signs that loans made to small and midsize businesses appear to be souring across the country. This had been the bread-and-butter of regional banks, which took advantage of local ties after being elbowed out of the credit card and mortgage business by national players. First Horizon National of Tennessee, Capitol Bancorp of Michigan and Arizona and Sovereign Bancorp of Philadelphia had sharp increases in the percentage of bad loans in their commercial and industrial portfolio, according to an analysis by Friedman, Billings, Ramsey. “It is definitely a sign the economy is weakening,” said Paul Miller, one of its banking analysts. “You have another loan category coming down the road.” And analysts are beginning to see stress in loans to commercial real estate developers, especially in mall properties that are dependent on the retail sector. “There are lots of bank lines and loans out to developers and that type of commercial real estate,” said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. “We are beginning to see a few cracks in office space as well.”</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/17/business/17bank.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Earnings Are Disappointing at 3 Big Banks<date>Published: October 17, 2007</date><text>Three large banking companies  Wells Fargo, Regions Financial and KeyCorp  reported lower-than-estimated third-quarter profits yesterday and said rising loan losses might hurt future earnings. Wells Fargo, based in San Francisco, said an increase in bad home equity and consumer loans held earnings growth to 4 percent. Net income at Regions, of Birmingham, Ala., rose 12 percent, and profit at KeyCorp, in Cleveland, dropped 33 percent. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, beat estimates with a 2.2 percent drop. The worsening housing slump caused borrowers to miss payments, with Wells Fargo and KeyCorp reporting higher loan losses. Regions said it expected charge-offs for bad loans to rise gradually in coming quarters. Wells Fargos chief financial officer, Howard I. Atkins, said weakness linked to housing market problems would continue to affect results this quarter. Mortgage cycles last years, not quarters, said Fred Cannon, an analyst at KBW. The issues in the mortgage markets are going to cause pressure for some time. Fallout from reduced home loan values and tighter lending standards in the quarter just concluded would take 90 days or more to show up in earnings reports, he said. Wells Fargo earned a penny a share less than analyst estimates compiled by Bloomberg. Regions earned 64 cents a share, excluding acquisition-related costs, or 5 cents under estimates. KeyCorps income from continuing operations of 57 cents was well short of a 73 cent average estimate. Profit of 67 cents a share at U.S. Bancorp was a penny better than predicted. Net income advanced at Wells Fargo to $2.28 billion, or 68 cents a share, from $2.19 billion, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Wells Fargo has turned in the best stock performance this year among the nations five biggest banking companies, having succeeded so far in containing losses tied to troubled mortgages. Yesterdays report may signal that the bank cannot meet its target of 10 percent annual earnings growth, Mr. Cannon at KBW said. More Articles in Business »Three large banking companies  Wells Fargo, Regions Financial and KeyCorp  reported lower-than-estimated third-quarter profits yesterday and said rising loan losses might hurt future earnings. Wells Fargo, based in San Francisco, said an increase in bad home equity and consumer loans held earnings growth to 4 percent. Net income at Regions, of Birmingham, Ala., rose 12 percent, and profit at KeyCorp, in Cleveland, dropped 33 percent. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, beat estimates with a 2.2 percent drop. The worsening housing slump caused borrowers to miss payments, with Wells Fargo and KeyCorp reporting higher loan losses. Regions said it expected charge-offs for bad loans to rise gradually in coming quarters. Wells Fargos chief financial officer, Howard I. Atkins, said weakness linked to housing market problems would continue to affect results this quarter. Mortgage cycles last years, not quarters, said Fred Cannon, an analyst at KBW. The issues in the mortgage markets are going to cause pressure for some time. Fallout from reduced home loan values and tighter lending standards in the quarter just concluded would take 90 days or more to show up in earnings reports, he said. Wells Fargo earned a penny a share less than analyst estimates compiled by Bloomberg. Regions earned 64 cents a share, excluding acquisition-related costs, or 5 cents under estimates. KeyCorps income from continuing operations of 57 cents was well short of a 73 cent average estimate. Profit of 67 cents a share at U.S. Bancorp was a penny better than predicted. Net income advanced at Wells Fargo to $2.28 billion, or 68 cents a share, from $2.19 billion, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Wells Fargo has turned in the best stock performance this year among the nations five biggest banking companies, having succeeded so far in containing losses tied to troubled mortgages. Yesterdays report may signal that the bank cannot meet its target of 10 percent annual earnings growth, Mr. Cannon at KBW said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D71E30F933A15752C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Today In Business | Barclays To Buy Subprime Lender<date>Published: January 20, 2007</date><text>Barclays Bank announced that it would buy the Equifirst Corporation, the subprime mortgage lending unit of Regions Financial, for $225 million. The sale is expected to be completed in the first half of the year. Equifirst is the 12th-largest sub-prime mortgage originator in the United States, Barclays said. Subprime mortgages are made to borrowers with low credit ratings and have higher risk of default. The mortgage business continued ''to experience a challenging environment,'' Regions said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DB1E3EF934A15756C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">FIVE DAYS; From Top of the Corporate World to Appeals Court<date>Published: May 27, 2006</date><text>JUDGMENT day arrived for the two top executives at Enron, and the jury found both men guilty of fraud and deceit. The case was perhaps the most closely watched corporate crime trial of the decade. GUILTY, GUILTY, GUILTY -- Kenneth L. Lay and Jeffrey K. Skilling did in fact deceive investors about the real financial straits at Enron, the once-highflying energy company that imploded in a wave of accounting scandals, as a midlevel executive once predicted. After hearing four months of testimony and deliberating for five days, jurors convicted Mr. Lay, Enron's chairman and for many years its chief executive, on six counts of conspiracy and fraud. He is 64 and could be sentenced to as much as 45 years in federal prison. The jury also convicted Mr. Skilling, who was an important adviser to Mr. Lay and was briefly Enron's chief executive, on 19 counts of conspiracy, fraud, insider trading and making false statements; it found him not guilty on nine counts, mostly insider trading. Mr. Skilling, 52, faces a maximum term of 185 years. Separately, in a nonjury trial, Federal District Judge Simeon T. Lake found Mr. Lay guilty of bank fraud for not telling Bank of America that he intended to use $75 million in personal loans to buy stock. Judge Lake said he would sentence Mr. Lay and Mr. Skilling on Sept. 11. Both men were released on $5 million bond until then. FEEDING FRENZY -- Having been outflanked in its effort to acquire the London Stock Exchange, the NYSE Group, which operates the New York Stock Exchange, turned its attention to Euronext, the pan-European exchange, which it offered to buy for as much as $10.2 billion. If successful, the takeover would create the first trans-Atlantic stock exchange. Almost as soon as the NYSE offer was broached, another exchange, Deutsche Börse of Germany, stepped up and offered to buy Euronext for about $10.6 billion. Euronext, which runs stock exchanges in Paris, Amsterdam, Brussels and Portugal, as well as a derivatives exchange in London, dismissed the German offer because it is partly payable in Deutsche Börse stock. Exchanges are interested in merging because that gives them access to more investors, which makes the exchanges more attractive to companies with stock to sell. NYSE's move may encourage the Nasdaq Stock Market to accelerate its incremental takeover of the London Stock Exchange. In a series of transaction, Nasdaq has amassed a 25 percent stake in the London market. TIMING IS EVERYTHING -- Federal investigators expanded their inquiry into how some companies granted stock options to their senior executives, suspecting that they may have been backdated to guarantee the executives the biggest possible gains. More than 20 companies have received subpoenas from the Justice Department seeking information on their executive stock option plans going back as far as a decade. The UnitedHealth Group is the biggest company to acknowledge receiving a subpoena so far. Many others are technology companies, including Juniper Networks and the KLA-Tencor Corporation. Legal experts say it is unclear whether backdating option awards is illegal, but several groups of investors have filed class-action lawsuits against companies suspected of the practice. UnitedHealth has told its shareholders that it may have to restate its results for the last three years, acknowledging a ''significant deficiency'' in its options program. SUSPICIOUSLY SMOOTH -- Senior executives at Fannie Mae, the nation's largest buyer of mortgages, ''deliberately and systematically'' manipulated the company's financial results for years as part of an $11 billion accounting scandal, federal regulators concluded. The Office of Federal Housing Enterprise Oversight, or Ofheo, said the manipulation was intended to smooth fluctuations in the company's earnings, letting Fannie Mae regularly meet or exceed earnings targets set by Wall Street and thus set in motion large bonuses for its executives. Ofheo said Franklin D. Raines, the former chairman and chief executive of Fannie Mae, was paid $90 million from 1998 to 2003. At least $52 million was tied to his meeting earnings targets that regulators say were reached by manipulating accounting.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/26/business/26bank.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Alabama-Based Banks in $9.8 Billion Merger<date>Published: May 26, 2006</date><text>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., May 25 (AP)  The Regions Financial Corporation has agreed to acquire the AmSouth Bancorporation for $9.8 billion in stock to create one of the nation's biggest bank holding companies, the banks said Thursday. The combined company would have nearly $140 billion in assets, a market capitalization of about $26 billion and 2,000 branches in the South and the Midwest. The two companies said it would be the nation's 10th-largest bank. Company officials said investors could expect annual savings of $400 million, with much of the money coming from the closing of about 150 branches and the loss of up to 3,600 jobs through layoffs and attrition. The new company will retain the Regions name. Jackson W. Moore, chairman and chief executive of Regions, will be chairman. C. Dowd Ritter, 58, chairman and chief executive of AmSouth, will be chief executive of the new company, which will keep its headquarters in Birmingham, where both companies are based. Benton Gup, a finance professor at the University of Alabama, questioned the logic of the deal since the two companies operate in virtually the same areas. Antitrust approval could be a problem, he said. The merger appeared aimed solely at cutting costs or, perhaps, fending off a hostile takeover of one or both companies, Mr. Gup said. In a conference call, Regions' chief financial officer, D. Bryan Jordan, said Regions and AmSouth have 230 branches within a mile of each other, and about 150 branches could close. Officials said as many as 10 percent of the 36,618 employees of both banks could lose their jobs. Regions will exchange 0.7974 share of its stock for each share of AmSouth common stock. Based on Wednesday's closing price of $35.53 for Regions, it is paying about $28.33 a share for AmSouth. That is about 2 percent less than its closing price of $28.90 on Wednesday. Regions shares lost $1.09 to close at $34.44 AmSouth fell 90 cents to $28. More Articles in Business »BIRMINGHAM, Ala., May 25 (AP)  The Regions Financial Corporation has agreed to acquire the AmSouth Bancorporation for $9.8 billion in stock to create one of the nation's biggest bank holding companies, the banks said Thursday. The combined company would have nearly $140 billion in assets, a market capitalization of about $26 billion and 2,000 branches in the South and the Midwest. The two companies said it would be the nation's 10th-largest bank. Company officials said investors could expect annual savings of $400 million, with much of the money coming from the closing of about 150 branches and the loss of up to 3,600 jobs through layoffs and attrition. The new company will retain the Regions name. Jackson W. Moore, chairman and chief executive of Regions, will be chairman. C. Dowd Ritter, 58, chairman and chief executive of AmSouth, will be chief executive of the new company, which will keep its headquarters in Birmingham, where both companies are based. Benton Gup, a finance professor at the University of Alabama, questioned the logic of the deal since the two companies operate in virtually the same areas. Antitrust approval could be a problem, he said. The merger appeared aimed solely at cutting costs or, perhaps, fending off a hostile takeover of one or both companies, Mr. Gup said. In a conference call, Regions' chief financial officer, D. Bryan Jordan, said Regions and AmSouth have 230 branches within a mile of each other, and about 150 branches could close. Officials said as many as 10 percent of the 36,618 employees of both banks could lose their jobs. Regions will exchange 0.7974 share of its stock for each share of AmSouth common stock. Based on Wednesday's closing price of $35.53 for Regions, it is paying about $28.33 a share for AmSouth. That is about 2 percent less than its closing price of $28.90 on Wednesday. Regions shares lost $1.09 to close at $34.44 AmSouth fell 90 cents to $28.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/24/business/company-news-union-planters-and-regions-financial-to-merge.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; UNION PLANTERS AND REGIONS FINANCIAL TO MERGE<date>Published: January 24, 2004</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, one of the biggest banks in Alabama, agreed to combine with the Union Planters Corporation in a $5.9 billion transaction that would create a bank with 1,400 branches in the South and Midwest. Each share of Union Planters would be exchanged for one share in the new company, and each share of Regions would be converted into 1.2346 shares, the banks said. Shares of both companies rose after the announcement. Profit growth at each of the banks lagged the industry average last year. Regions, based in Birmingham, and Union Planters, based in Memphis, will have an equal number of board seats.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/23/business/company-news-2-midsize-banks-in-talks-on-6-billion-deal.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; 2 MIDSIZE BANKS IN TALKS ON $6 BILLION DEAL<date>Published: January 23, 2004</date><text>In the latest sign of consolidation in the banking industry, the Regions Financial Corporation of Birmingham, Ala., is in talks to buy the Union Planters Corporation of Memphis for about $6 billion in stock, people close to the discussions said last night. The deal, which could be announced as early as today, would create a bank with about $81 billion in assets and branches concentrated mostly in the Southeast and Midwest. While much smaller in scope, it would follow two other recent bank transactions: the combination of J.P. Morgan Chase and Bank One for $58 billion and the merger of Bank of America and FleetBoston Financial for about $48 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/19/business/company-news-regions-financial-agrees-to-buy-morgan-keegan.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL AGREES TO BUY MORGAN KEEGAN<date>Published: December 19, 2000</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, a bank holding company based in Birmingham, Ala., agreed to buy Morgan Keegan, a securities brokerage firmbased in Memphis, for $789 million, or $27 a share, in cash or stock at the shareholder's option. At Friday's closing prices, the offer represented a premium of 39 percent. To retain key Morgan Keegan employees, Regions will establish a bonus pool of 5.55 million stock options. Many of Morgan Keegan's 600 retail brokers are in Southeastern states where Regions already has offices. After the merger, which is expected to close in the first three months of 2001, Regions will have 961 brokers in 14 states.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/17/business/company-news-regions-financial-agrees-to-buy-minden-bancshares.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL AGREES TO BUY MINDEN BANCSHARES<date>Published: July 17, 1999</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to buy the privately held Minden Bancshares Inc. for about $86.5 million in stock. Minden Bancshares is the holding company for the Minden Bank and Trust Company, which operates seven offices in northwestern Louisiana. It has $332 million in assets. Regions Financial, based in Birmingham, Ala., is a bank holding company with 731 offices in Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, South Carolina, Tennessee and Texas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/07/business/company-news-regions-buys-another-banking-company-in-arkansas.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS BUYS ANOTHER BANKING COMPANY IN ARKANSAS<date>Published: August 07, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Arkansas Banking Company for about $64 million in stock, continuing its expansion in Arkansas. Regions, based in Birmingham, Ala., became the largest bank in Arkansas last week, when it completed a $2.7 billion purchase of the First Commercial Corporation of Little Rock. Arkansas Banking, based in Jonesboro, Ark., owns banks in northeastern Arkansas. It has assets of $343 million. Shares of Regions rose 56.25 cents, to $38.4375.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/18/business/company-news-regions-financial-buying-bullsboro-for-35.6-million.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL BUYING BULLSBORO FOR $35.6 MILLION<date>Published: July 18, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to buy Bullsboro Bancshares for $35.6 million in stock, expanding its businesses in Georgia. Regions, based in Birmingham, Ala., said it would exchange 3.65 shares of common stock for each share of Bullsboro common stock. Bullsboro Bancshares is the parent company of the Bank of Newnan, which has assets of $108 million and offices in Newnan and Sharpsburg, Ga. Regions is a bank holding company operating in six Southeastern states. Bullsboro's shares rose $3 each, to $68, while Regions rose 6.25 cents, to $42.0625.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/25/business/company-news-regions-financial-plans-to-acquire-village-bankshares.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL PLANS TO ACQUIRE VILLAGE BANKSHARES<date>Published: March 25, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation signed a definitive agreement yesterday to acquire Village Bankshares Inc. of Tampa, Fla., for $55 million in stock. Regions said it would issue 1.34 common shares for each share of Village Bankshares. Village Bankshares holds Village Bank of Florida, which operates nine offices and had total assets of $199 million at Dec. 31. Regions Financial said it had also signed a definitive agreement to acquire Etowah Bank of Canton, Ga. In January, Regions, based in Birmingham, Ala., agreed to exchange 3.3127 common shares for each Etowah Bank common share in a transaction valued at $117 million. Under the definitive agreement, Regions said it would issue 3.20 shares for each Etowah share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/10/business/company-news-2.7-billion-purchase-for-regions-financial.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; $2.7 BILLION PURCHASE FOR REGIONS FINANCIAL<date>Published: February 10, 1998</date><text>Extending its reach outside Alabama, the fast-growing Regions Financial Corporation is buying the First Commercial Corporation of Little Rock, Ark., for $2.7 billion in stock. Under the deal announced yesterday, Regions will exchange 1.7 shares of its common stock for each share of First Commercial common stock; based on Friday's closing stock price, the deal gives First Commercial shareholders $68.85 a share. First Commercial's stock fell $2.0625 a share yesterday, to $64.8125, and Regions was down $1.375, to $39.125. The deal, which was expected, will create the nation's 26th-largest banking company, with 667 banking offices in nine Southern states.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/09/business/2.6-billion-bank-deal-reported-in-the-works.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">$2.6 Billion Bank Deal Reported in the Works<date>Published: February 09, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, an Alabama bank, could announce as early as today that it has agreed to acquire the First Commercial Corporation of Little Rock, Ark.Bank advisers said the two companies were negotiating last night and that the price could rise above $70 a share. That would give the transaction, which would be in the form of an exchange of stock, a value of more than $2.6 billion.Regions appeared as the favorite last week after several other bidders for First Commercial were told by investment bankers that they were no longer being considered, in part because their bids were too low. First Commercial put itself up for auction in mid-January, when it hired the investment bank Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods to solicit bids from interested companies. Among the companies reported to be interested in bidding were Amsouth Bancorp, the Banc One Corporation, the Union Planters Corporation and the Hibernia Corporation.First Commercial's stock rose $2.1875 on Friday, to $66.875, on speculation that an acquisition was close at hand. Regions closed at $40.50, down 68.75 cents for the day.First Commercial is the largest Arkansas bank and would give Regions a strong foothold in the state. First Commercial has $4.6 billion in deposits and about 125 branches, and is primarily a commercial lender to small and medium-sized businesses. The company is also active in Tennessee and Louisiana. It also owns half interests in two banks in Oklahoma.First Commercial has also been acquiring small banks in recent years. However, one of the reasons it is on the block is because it was expected to have trouble expanding into new markets.Regions, for its part, has actively pursued competitors in the hope of becoming a presence throughout the Southeast. Late last summer, for instance, Regions moved into South Carolina with the purchases of the First United Bancorporation and the Greenville Financial Corporation.Neither Regions nor First Commercial executives returned calls seeking comment yesterday.The First Commercial sale would be the latest in a series of high-priced deals for medium-sized bank in what some analysts describe as a frothy market. Analysts say consolidation in the banking sector is likely to continue this year and more mergers of this size are expected.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/06/business/front-runner-emerges-in-bidding-for-little-rock-bank.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Front-Runner Emerges in Bidding for Little Rock Bank<date>Published: February 06, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, an Alabama-based bank, emerged yesterday as the front-runner in the bidding for the First Commercial Corporation of Little Rock, Ark., which has put itself on the block.Regions Financial has offered $70 a share in a stock swap valued at $2.6 billion for First Commercial, according to bank advisers.But Compass Bancshares, also based in Alabama, could be a candidate if it can top the bid by Regions, the bank advisers said yesterday. And a number of other companies have been reported to be interested in First Commercial, including Amsouth Bancorp, the Banc One Corporation, the Norwest Corporation, the Union Planters Corporation and the Hibernia Corporation.Bids, which First Commercial solicited in an auction, were due on Monday, and the interested companies were told on Wednesday whether their bids had been accepted. It is expected, a person close to the talks said, that the winner will be announced on Monday.First Commercial's stock closed at $64.6875 yesterday, up 18.75 cents. Regions stock traded at $41.1875, up 6.25 cents. Compass traded at $43.25, down $1.375.First Commercial, the biggest Arkansas bank, is on the block because it was expected to have difficulty expanding beyond its relatively narrow market. First Commercial has $4.6 billion in deposits and is best known for lending to small and medium-sized companies. It does business in several states, including Arkansas, Tennessee, Louisiana, and has a 50 percent ownership of two banks in Oklahoma. In recent years it has sought to buy smaller banks.Regions, primarily an Alabama banking company, had not been previously named as a potential bidder, but has been actively buying competitors with the hopes of extending its presence in the Southeast. Late last summer, for instance, Regions entered South Carolina when it said it would buy the First United Bancorporation and the Greenville Financial Corporation. It was a natural extension, management then said, to provide the company with greater growth opportunities. Compass has also been expanding, with offices in Alabama, Florida and Texas.Executives at both Regions and First Commercial did not return repeated phone calls. A representative of Compass would not comment.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/14/business/company-news-regions-financial-will-buy-etowah-bank.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL WILL BUY ETOWAH BANK<date>Published: January 14, 1998</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to buy Etowah Bank of Canton, Ga., for $117.4 million. Regions will exchange 3.3127 of its common shares for each Etowah Bank common share. Regions' shares fell $1 each, to $38.125, in Nasdaq trading. Etowah Bank operates 18 full-service offices in Georgia. Regions will have 139 offices and $5.5 billion in assets in Georgia when the sale is completed. Based in Birmingham, Ala., Regions Financial is a regional multibank holding company providing banking services from more than 430 offices in five Southeastern states.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/13/business/company-news-regions-financial-to-acquire-first-state.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL TO ACQUIRE FIRST STATE<date>Published: December 13, 1997</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire the First State Corporation for $161 million in stock, extending its business into southern Georgia. Regions, Alabama's largest bank, will pay 0.56 share for each share of First State, or $23.38 based on Thursday's close. The purchase, a tax-free exchange, will give Regions another 14 branches and $540 million in assets. Regions, based in Birmingham, has more than 430 branches in Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana and Tennessee. It will have more than $24 billion in assets when it completes these purchases. The stock of First State, based in Albany, Ga., rose $2.75, or 14 percent, to $22, in Nasdaq trading, while Regions rose 25 cents, to $42.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/08/business/company-news-regions-financial-is-set-to-acquire-key-florida-bancorp.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL IS SET TO ACQUIRE KEY FLORIDA BANCORP<date>Published: November 08, 1997</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire Key Florida Bancorp Inc. for about $38.5 million in stock. Key Florida, based in Bradenton, Fla., has seven branches on the west coast of Florida and assets of $212 million. Regions, based in Mongomery, Ala., has 430 offices in five Southeastern states and assets of $22.2 billion. Under terms of the deal, Regions said it would issue 0.3666 of a Regions share for each Key Florida share. The deal is expected to close in the first half of 1998. Regions' stock slipped $1.125, to $37, in Nasdaq trading, while Key Florida rose 25 cents, to $12.75.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/09/24/business/company-news-regions-financial-to-buy-2-south-carolina-banks.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL TO BUY 2 SOUTH CAROLINA BANKS<date>Published: September 24, 1997</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation agreed yesterday to pay $223.5 million in stock to buy two South Carolina banks: Palfed Inc. and First United Bancorp. Regions, Alabama's second-largest bank in terms of assets, said it would acquire Palfed, based in Aiken, S.C., for $27.375 a share, or a total of $144.5 million, based on Monday's close. It also announced a separate agreement to buy First United Bancorp of Anderson, S.C., for $20.24 a share, or a total of $79 million. The purchases would give Regions Financial about $1.09 billion in assets and $913.2 million in deposits in South Carolina. Shares of Regions fell $2.4375 each, to $36.6875; First United Bancorp rose $1.25, to $18, and Palfed rose $2.8125, to $24.3125, all in Nasdaq trading.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/15/business/company-news-regions-financial-to-acquire-allied-bankshares.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS;REGIONS FINANCIAL TO ACQUIRE ALLIED BANKSHARES<date>Published: June 15, 1996</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, a banking company based in Birmingham, Ala., said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire Allied Bankshares Inc. in a $136.3 million stock swap. Regions will offer 0.226 share of its common stock for each Allied share, or a total of about 2.9 million shares, in a tax-free pooling of interests. The acquisition, including four others that are pending, would raise Regions' total assets to about $18.8 billion, with $4.6 billion in Georgia. Regions operates 355 banking offices and has assets of $562 million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/10/24/business/joining-trend-regions-bank-plans-acquisition.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">Joining Trend, Regions Bank Plans Acquisition<date>Published: October 24, 1995</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation, an Alabama-based banking company, will acquire First National Bancorp, the second-largest bank in Georgia, in a stock deal valued at nearly $650 million, the two companies said today.The merger is part of a trend toward regional consolidation in the nation's banking industry.First National, with assets of $3.1 billion, is based in Gainesville and has 63 offices in north Georgia and central Florida. Regions, based in Birmingham, operates 286 offices in Alabama, Florida, Louisiana and Tennessee.Under the agreement, Regions will offer 0.76 shares of its common stock for each of First National's 20.53 million common shares outstanding, in a tax-free exchange, the companies said.Based on Regions' closing stock price of $41.50 on Friday, the deal was worth $31.54 for each First National share, or 2.13 times the company's book value as of Sept. 30.Shares of Regions fell $1.125 today, closing at $40.375. That reduced the value of the deal to about $30.68 a share for First National shareholders. First National's stock gained 25 cents, closing at $29.Bank mergers have taken off at a rapid pace this year, with many banking companies facing slow growth in their home markets and looking to buy rivals to expand.The Chemical Banking Corporation and the Chase Manhattan Corporation, both based in New York, announced a $10 billion merger in late August that would create the nation's largest bank. In California, Wells Fargo &amp; Company last week made a hostile bid worth nearly $11 billion for First Interstate Bancorp of Los Angeles.The Regions-First National deal would increase increase Regions' assets to $17.4 billion and would heighten its presence in Georgia and Florida. The company said the deal was expected to hurt earnings slightly next year but increase them after that.The companies have also agreed on a plan to cut First National's expenses during 1996 but did not provide details. The merger is expected to close during the first half of 1996, subject to approval by both companies' shareholders and by regulators.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/06/03/business/company-news-regions-financial-makes-a-61-million-acquisition.html?ref=regionsfinancialcorporation">COMPANY NEWS; REGIONS FINANCIAL MAKES A $61 MILLION ACQUISITION<date>Published: June 03, 1994</date><text>The Regions Financial Corporation said yesterday that it would buy American Bancshares Inc. of Monroe, La., for stock valued at $61 million. Regions Financial said it had agreed to exchange 2.4445 shares of its stock for each share outstanding of American Bancshares. Regions Financial, of Birmingham, Ala., is a holding company for First Alabama Bank. Shares of Regions Financial slipped 18.75 cents yesterday, to $34.25, in Nasdaq trading.</text></article></page><page index="4" /><page index="5" /><page index="6" /><page index="7" /><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
