<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Sara Lee Corporation"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/04/business/kelloggs-profit-falls-sara-lee-cuts-sales-forecast.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Kellogg’s Profit Falls; Sara Lee Cuts Sales Forecast<date>Published: November 3, 2011</date><text>Kellogg said on Thursday that it was spending an additional $70 million in the second half of 2011 to improve its manufacturing, a move that led to a weaker-than-expected third-quarter profit.Separately, Sara Lee cut its full-year sales forecast when it reported its third-quarter earnings results. Kellogg, the cereal maker, whose brands include Corn Flakes and Rice Krispies, also said its 2012 earnings would be below its long-term forecasts. John A. Bryant, who has been Kellogg’s chief executive for less than a year, said the company “cut deeper than it should have” and was now reversing course to add people back into factories. He said the company was also improving employee training and interaction with suppliers. “We’re making the investments we need to make to ensure that our supply chain is performing at the level we need it to perform at in the future,” said Mr. Bryant, who was chief operating officer when many of the cuts were made. “We’d all rather do that without having to spend $70 million,” he said, adding, “but I think it was absolutely the right thing to do.” In June, regulators found listeria at a Kellogg plant in Georgia that produced Keebler and Famous Amos cookies, and warned the company about “significant violations” of good manufacturing practice regulations. That followed a recall of millions of boxes of cereal in 2010 because of an unusual smell, and a recall of some Keebler cookies and Special K protein bars in 2009. Kellogg’s net income was $290 million, or 80 cents a share, in the third quarter, down from $338 million, or 90 cents a share, a year earlier. The results were also hurt by reinstating a companywide bonus program. Net sales rose 5 percent, to $3.31 billion. Analysts on average had expected earnings of 89 cents a share on sales of $3.41 billion, according to Thomson Reuters. Kellogg expects full-year earnings of $3.27 to $3.33 a share, excluding currency fluctuations, or $3.35 to $3.41, including an estimated 8-cent-a-share benefit from foreign exchange. That is lower than the forecast implied by its previous target and analysts’ estimate of $3.48 a share. The company stood by its net sales growth goal of 4 to 5 percent. For 2012, Kellogg also expects net sales growth of 4 to 5 percent, which is above its long-term annual targets, as it expects benefits from new products and price increases. Kellogg shares fell 7.6 percent, to $49.91, on Thursday. Meanwhile, Sara Lee stood by its full-year earnings forecast, saying it still expected adjusted earnings of 89 to 95 cents a share in fiscal 2012, even though the weakening euro reduced its expected foreign exchange benefit and the company announced a plan to sell its North American food service coffee business. Those issues led the company to cut its full-year sales forecast to $7.9 billion to $8.15 billion, from a previous forecast of $8.5 billion to $8.75 billion. For the first quarter of fiscal 2012, which ended on Oct. 1, Sara Lee reported a net loss of $217 million, or 37 cents a share, compared with a year-earlier profit of $192 million, or 29 cents a share. Excluding one-time items, Sara Lee reported a profit of 18 cents a share, topping analysts’ average expectation by a penny, according to Thomson Reuters. Sales rose to $1.94 billion from $1.73 billion a year earlier. Analysts on average were expecting sales of $1.98 billion. Sara Lee, based in a suburb of Chicago, is planning to split into two companies — one focused on North American meat brands including Jimmy Dean sausages and Ball Park frankfurters, and the other on international coffee and teas, with brands like Douwe Egberts and Pickwick. Sara Lee shares were up $1.09, or 6 percent, at $18.70.Kellogg said on Thursday that it was spending an additional $70 million in the second half of 2011 to improve its manufacturing, a move that led to a weaker-than-expected third-quarter profit.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/09/08/sniffing-sara-lees-coffee/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sniffing Sara Lee's Coffee<date>September 8, 2011, 3:03 pm</date><text>The chief executive of Sara Lee, Marcel Smits, told a conference in Boston that the company had received overtures for its coffee business, which is to be spun off next year, Reuters reports. “We’ve had some incoming calls,” Mr. Smits said. The food-and-beverage business accounts for about $4.6 billion in annual revenue. Read more »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/09/ralcorp-to-buy-a-sara-lee-unit-for-545-million/?ref=saraleecorporation">Ralcorp to Buy a Sara Lee Unit for $545 Million<date>August 9, 2011, 7:57 am</date><text>Sara Lee and Ralcorp are both food companies that have been busy trying to remake themselves this year. On Tuesday, they reached a deal toward that mutual end. Sara Lee has agreed to sell its North American private-brand refrigerated dough business to Ralcorp for $545 million. The sale comes as Sara Lee is preparing to split into two separate food and beverage companies. The sale, said Marcel Smits, the company’s chief executive, “will better enable our North American business to focus on its branded meats and frozen desserts products and establish a platform for a strong and independent future.” Ralcorp, meanwhile, is spinning off its Post Foods cereal business. The refrigerated dough acquisition will bolster its private brand business, while the proceeds from the Post Foods split will help pay back the short-term debt being used to finance the acquisition. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Sara Lee's press release Ralcorp's press release The company has also been trying to fend off an unsolicited $4.9 billion takeover offer from ConAgra Foods. Ralcorp said it expected the acquisition would add to earnings by more 30 cents a share in the first year. “Given its higher margins and free cash flow, we expect this acquisition to result in the creation of significant value for Ralcorp shareholders,” Kevin J. Hunt, co-chief executive of Ralcorp, said. The Sara Lee refrigerated dough business had more than $300 million in revenue last year. It employs about 700 and has manufacturing plants in Forest Park, Ga., and Carrollton, Tex.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/06/business/06sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Posts $153 Million Profit<date>Published: May 5, 2011</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation posted a quarterly profit on Thursday, reversing a loss a year ago, but cut its full-year outlook because of rising commodity costs and said it might sell two units.The company, which has sold several business lines and is splitting in two, says it is considering selling its international bakery and North American refrigerated dough businesses. Sara Lee reported net income of $153 million, or 25 cents a share, for the quarter ended April 2, the third quarter of its fiscal year. That compared with a loss of $336 million, or 49 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding one-time items, the company earned 24 cents a share, up from 22 cents a share a year ago but short of the 25 cents expected by analysts surveyed by FactSet. Revenue in the period rose 7 percent, to $2.22 billion from $2.07 billion, helped by higher prices among other factors. But investors were receptive to Sara Lee’s commitment to narrowing its business and shedding lower-performing operations, and its stock rose 14 cents to close at $19.28 a share on Thursday. Sara Lee, which is based in Downers Grove, Ill., has raised prices and cut costs to offset higher costs for meat, coffee and other commodities. But Sara Lee leaders said prices might now be high enough to make less expensive store brands more attractive to consumers, further hurting profits. The company now expects to earn 79 to 83 cents a share on an adjusted basis, down from its previous forecast of 85 to 89 cents a share and below the 86 cents analysts expected.The Sara Lee Corporation posted a quarterly profit on Thursday, reversing a loss a year ago, but cut its full-year outlook because of rising commodity costs and said it might sell two units.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/28/sara-lee-confirms-plan-to-split/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Confirms Plan to Split<date>January 28, 2011, 8:29 am</date><text>Seth Perlman/Associated Pres Sara Lee‘s board announced Friday the company will split its food and beverage businesses into two separate companies, a deal they expect to close by 2012. The announcement comes after the company rejected at least two preliminary takeover approaches. The food business, which includes meat products like Jimmy Dean and Ball Park, will be spun off into a new public company that will keep the Sara Lee brand name. It had revenue of $4.1 billion last year Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The press release DealBook: Sara Lee Weighs Breakup The as yet unnamed beverage company will carry a number of coffee brands, like Douwe Egberts, Senseo and Pickwick. Beverages generated revenue $4.6 billion last year. Sara Lee also announced that Marcel Smits, 49, who has been serving as interim chief executive since Brenda C. Barnes resigned, will get the job on a permanent basis. Ms. Barnes resigned as chief executive and chairman in August, three months after suffering a stroke. Jan Bennink, 54, will become chairman, replacing Jim Crown, who will continue to serve on the board. The board also said that C.J. Fraleigh, 47, who serves as Sara Lee’s chief executive for North America, will be named chief executive of the food spinoff. The board also announced plans to pay a $3 dollar per share special dividend to common stock shareholders following the sale of its North American Bakery unit, which the company announced in November. The dividend is to be paid in 2012, before the expected spinoff of the company’s food division. “We have carefully considered various strategic alternatives, including unsolicited indications of interest in the company. We believe that the spinoff, plus the one-time special dividend, offers the greatest potential for delivering long-term shareholder value,” James Crown, Sara Lee’s chairman, said in a statement. “These two pure-play companies will have their own distinct growth strategies within their respective core markets that will attract a more focused shareholder base.” Both a private equity consortium led by Apollo Global Management and JBS, a large Brazilian meat producer, have made separate, preliminary takeover approaches for Sara Lee. But on Thursday, Sara Lee directors determined that the prices being mentioned were not high enough, said people briefed on the matter who spoke only on condition of anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly. The split is the latest realignment by an American corporate giant. Both ITT and Fortune Brands plan to break up into three companies, while the Marathon Oil Corporation wants to spin off its refining and marketing business. Sara Lee, based in Illiinois, has been shrinking over the last decade, selling off a wide range of businesses like Coach handbags and and underwear business that included Hanes. More recently the company sold its North American bakery business to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $959 million and its global body care and European detergents business in 2009 to Unilever for 1.3 billion euros, or $1.8 billion. But it began considering a sale or breakup after Ms. Barnes resigned. While Sara Lee had appointed an interim chief executive, the company had slowed its search for a permanent replacement for Ms. Barnes while weighing options for its future.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D91431F93BA15752C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Said Weighing a Breakup, Not a Takeover<date>Published: January 28, 2011</date><text>7:13 p.m. | Updated The board of Sara Lee has rejected takeover overtures from two potential buyers and is likely to pursue a breakup of the company into separate meat and coffee businesses, people briefed on the matter said Thursday. Such a split would be the latest realignment by an American corporate giant. Both ITT and Fortune Brands plan to break up into three companies, while the Marathon Oil Corporationwants to spin off its refining and marketing business. But the move would frustrate those hoping for a bidding war for Sara Lee, which has a market value of $11.3 billion. Both a private equity consortium led by Apollo Global Management and JBS, a large Brazilian meat producer, have made separate, preliminary takeover approaches for Sara Lee. But on Thursday, Sara Lee directors determined that the prices being mentioned were not high enough, the people briefed on the matter, who spoke only on condition of anonymity, said. These people, however, cautioned that the situation remained fluid, adding that Sara Lee might still entertain takeover offers even after it began the process of splitting itself up. A formal announcement may come in the next few days, one of these people said. A Sara Lee spokesman declined to comment. Shares of Sara Lee fell 4.75 percent on Thursday, to $17.64, after TheDeal.com reported on the board's decision. Sara Lee has previously rejected takeover approaches. The company rebuffed several informal merger proposals last fall, including those by Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and JBS, arguing that they were not high enough, people briefed on the matter have previously said. JBS, which already owns beef and pork producers in the United States, has been pursuing Sara Lee to cap a big expansion in North America. JBS has indicated to Sara Lee that if it acquired the American company, it would sell its coffee business to the Blackstone Group, these people said. But JBS has had trouble coming up with the financing to push its bid past $20 a share, these people said, and, by Thursday, had stopped trying to line up the necessary loans. The Apollo-led group, which also includes TPG Capital and Bain Capital, has not submitted a new bid after making a preliminary offer last week that came in under $20, these people said. Sara Lee had suggested to the private equity consortium that it would need to raise its offer to be taken seriously. Sara Lee had told both bidders that it would be willing to pursue a breakup if it received no satisfactory bids by the time its board met on Wednesday and Thursday. That move could prove more attractive than a sale because it could spare shareholders from a big tax bill, though it remains a complicated transaction. Sara Lee has already shed several units in recent years. It sold its North American bakery business last year to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $959 million and its global body care and European detergents business in 2009 to Unilever for 1.3 billion euros, or $1.8 billion. But it began considering a sale or breakup after Brenda C. Barnes resigned as chairwoman and chief executive last August, three months after suffering a stroke. While Sara Lee had appointed an interim chief executive, the company had slowed its search for a permanent replacement for Ms. Barnes while weighing options for its future. This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/27/sara-lee-to-pursue-a-split-up-instead-of-a-sale/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Said to Weigh a Breakup, Not a Sale<date>January 27, 2011, 11:40 am</date><text>Stephen Yang/Bloomberg News 7:13 p.m. | Updated The board of Sara Lee has rejected takeover overtures from two potential buyers and is likely to pursue a breakup of the company into separate meat and coffee businesses, people briefed on the matter said Thursday. Such a split would be the latest realignment by an American corporate giant. Both ITT and Fortune Brands plan to break up into three companies, while the Marathon Oil Corporation wants to spin off its refining and marketing business. But the move would frustrate those hoping for a bidding war for Sara Lee, which has a market value of $11.3 billion. Both a private equity consortium led by Apollo Global Management and JBS, a large Brazilian meat producer, have made separate, preliminary takeover approaches for Sara Lee. But on Thursday, Sara Lee directors determined that the prices being mentioned were not high enough, the people briefed on the matter, who spoke only on condition of anonymity, said. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink These people, however, cautioned that the situation remained fluid, adding that Sara Lee might still entertain takeover offers even after it began the process of splitting itself up. A formal announcement may come in the next few days, one of these people said. A Sara Lee spokesman declined to comment. Shares of Sara Lee fell 4.75 percent on Thursday, to $17.64, after TheDeal.com reported on the board’s decision. Sara Lee has previously rejected takeover approaches. The company rebuffed several informal merger proposals last fall, including those by Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and JBS, arguing that they were not high enough, people briefed on the matter have previously said. JBS, which already owns beef and pork producers in the United States, has been pursuing Sara Lee to cap a big expansion in North America. JBS has indicated to Sara Lee that if it acquired the American company, it would sell its coffee business to the Blackstone Group, these people said. But JBS has had trouble coming up with the financing to push its bid past $20 a share, these people said, and, by Thursday, had stopped trying to line up the necessary loans. The Apollo-led group, which also includes TPG Capital and Bain Capital, has not submitted a new bid after making a preliminary offer last week that came in under $20, these people said. Sara Lee had suggested to the private equity consortium that it would need to raise its offer to be taken seriously. Sara Lee had told both bidders that it would be willing to pursue a breakup if it received no satisfactory bids by the time its board met on Wednesday and Thursday. That move could prove more attractive than a sale because it could spare shareholders from a big tax bill, though it remains a complicated transaction. Sara Lee has already shed several units in recent years. It sold its North American bakery business last year to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $959 million and its global body care and European detergents business in 2009 to Unilever for 1.3 billion euros, or $1.8 billion. But it began considering a sale or breakup after Brenda C. Barnes resigned as chairwoman and chief executive last August, three months after suffering a stroke. While Sara Lee had appointed an interim chief executive, the company had slowed its search for a permanent replacement for Ms. Barnes while weighing options for its future.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/26/bidders-for-sara-lee-face-challenges/?ref=saraleecorporation">Bidders for Sara Lee Face Challenges<date>January 26, 2011, 12:24 pm</date><text>At least one of the potential bidders for Sara Lee, JBS of Brazil, is having difficulty raising the financing necessary for its offer, making a bid increasingly less likely, people briefed on the matter told DealBook on Tuesday. The other potential suitor, a consortium led by Apollo Global Management, is also weighing whether to raise its preliminary bid for Sara Lee after it submitted an offer late last week. Sara Lee has told both bidders that it would be willing to pursue a breakup of itself if it receives no satisfactory bids by the time its board meets on Wednesday and Thursday, said these people, who spoke on condition of anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly on the matter. But a final decision from the company could still be days away, and either bidder could still come back with a higher offer. JBS has indicated to Sara Lee that if it acquired the American company, it would sell its coffee business to the Blackstone Group, these people said. But JBS has had trouble coming up with the financing to push its bid past $20 a share, these people said. JBS had been seeking to buy Sara Lee to cap off a series of acquisitions to expand internationally, a string of deals that included buying a majority stake in Pilgrim’s Pride, the big American poultry producer, in 2009. But Sara Lee had rejected a previous JBS approach last fall, concerned that the combined companies would bear too much debt. Selling off the coffee business to Blackstone was meant in part to alleviate those worries. The Apollo-led group’s offer valued Sara Lee at a range of less than $20 a share, these people said. It is unclear whether the consortium, which also includes TPG Capital and Bain Capital, would also seek to break up the company. A Sara Lee spokesman declined to comment. One concern for the Sara Lee board is how to grapple with tax issues surrounding a potential sale of the company’s coffee business. Before receiving the preliminary offers from JBS and the Apollo group, Sara Lee’s directors had been leaning toward spinning off the beverage unit in a tax-free transaction, hoping to spare shareholders from being stuck with a big bill, these people said. But the company’s board may favor a takeover if the price is high enough to compensate for the tax issues, these people said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDF133EF937A15752C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">Private Equity Firms Are Said to Set Sights on Buying Sara Lee<date>Published: January 24, 2011</date><text>10:56 p.m. | Updated Two potential buyers have expressed interest in buying Sara Lee, people briefed on the matter said on Sunday. The board of Sara Lee, the maker of Jimmy Dean sausages and other products, received a preliminary bid late last week from a group of buyout firms led by Apollo Global Management and includes Bain Capital and TPG Capital, these people said. It is likely to receive one from JBS of Brazil and the Blackstone Group soon. The company's board is expected to meet later this week to compare the offers to a broad plan to split the company into its coffee and meats businesses, these people said. The food conglomerate is weighing options for its future after previously rejecting takeover bids from JBS and buyout firms like Kohlberg Kravis Roberts in the fall. Sara Lee has been leaning toward a break-up, unless a takeover offer proves high enough to compensate for the tax-free advantages of a split into two separate companies, these people said. The company may try to make a decision before its second-quarter earnings announcement on Feb. 8 or a consumer products analyst conference later that month, one of these people said. These people spoke on the condition of anonymity because the discussions were private. A spokesman for Sara Lee, Mike Cummins, declined to comment. News of the Apollo bid was first reported by Reuters on Saturday; news of Blackstone's involvement was first reported by Bloomberg News on Sunday. Shares in Sara Lee closed on Friday at $18.70, up nearly 2.4 percent for the day. That gives the company a market value of approximately $12 billion. Private equity firms have been seeking ever-bigger takeover targets as many have bulging war chests bulging with billions of dollars in investors' capital, as well as access to cheap financing. A leveraged buyout of Sara Lee would be the largest acquisition by private equity in years, and would test the industry's ability to close on such a large transaction. Meanwhile, JBS is one of several Brazilian companies seeking to expand their global presence. The meat processor has been working to secure financing for a Sara Lee bid, though some of the people briefed on the matter said that merging JBS and Sara Lee would leave the combined company with a high amount of debt - a concern to Sara Lee's board. One of the drivers for Sara Lee's efforts to sell or split itself is the absence of a permanent chief executive since Brenda C. Barnes departed last August after suffering a stroke. Marcel Smits, the company's chief financial officer, has been filling in as interim chief executive, but Sara Lee has slowed its search for a permanent leader until it decides on its future plans. This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DC143AF934A35752C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">DealBook Online<date>Published: January 7, 2011</date><text>NEW HIRE Elizabeth Warren, who is setting up the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, announced her latest significant hire: Holly Petraeus, left, the wife of Gen. David H. Petraeus, the top American commander in Afghanistan. Mrs. Petraeus will direct the Office of Servicemember Affairs, a division in the bureau that will be responsible for protecting military families from financial swindles. BEN PROTESS POSSIBLE BREAKUP Sara Lee is leaning toward splitting itself into its meats and coffee businesses after rejecting a takeover bid by JBS of Brazil, people briefed on the matter said. Sara Lee was not convinced that JBS, a meat processor, could secure adequate financing for a takeover, these people said. Because the two are of similar size, any merger would most likely saddle the combined company with significant debt. With no other bidders expected, Sara Lee is looking to split its businesses. MICHAEL J. de la MERCED and EVELYN M. RUSLI EXEMPTION Hermès International's family shareholders won an important victory on Thursday in their battle against Bernard Arnault, left, the acquisitive head of LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton, when the French market regulator said they could group the family's shares without having to offer to buy out minority shareholders. The regulator, Autorité des Marchés Financiers, had been asked to rule on the legality of a plan by the family to park more than 50 percent of the shares in a new holding company. DAVID JOLLY POSITIVE OUTLOOK The fortunes of private equity firms took a big hit during the financial crisis, but Henry R. Kravis, speaking to reporters in Mumbai on Thursday, said business was on the upswing again after two ''terrible'' years during which it was hard to raise money. But the global economy and financial markets started improving last year and should gain speed in 2011, he said. VIKAS BAJAJ nytimes.com/dealbook PHOTOS</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/01/06/sara-lee-leans-toward-split-after-rebuffing-jbs/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Favors Split After Rebuffing JBS<date>January 6, 2011, 4:51 pm</date><text>Stephen Yang/Bloomberg News Sara Lee is leaning toward splitting itself into its meats and coffee businesses after rejecting a takeover bid by JBS of Brazil, people briefed on the matter told DealBook on Thursday. During months of on-again and off-again deal discussions, Sara Lee was not convinced that JBS, a major meat processor, could secure adequate financing for a takeover, these people said. Because the two are of similar size, any merger would likely saddle the combined company with significant debt. With no other bidders on the horizon — preliminary offers by leveraged buyout firms including Kohlberg Kravis Roberts were rejected this fall — Sara Lee is instead looking to split its main businesses. A decision could be made by the end of this month, said one of these people, who requested anonymity because they were not authorized to talk publicly about the split. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink The exact structure has not yet been decided, given the complexity of such a breakup. A split could leave the meats business — which owns brands like Jimmy Dean and Hillshire Farms — financially weakened, since much of Sara Lee’s free cash flow arises from the beverage unit, according to Eric Serotta, an analyst for Wells Fargo Securities. Still, splitting Sara Lee into its meat and coffee units could make the sale of each easier for a suitor like JBS, these people said. Other potential buyers could include Smithfield, Tyson and Hormel, Mr. Serotta said. Trading in Sara Lee shares ended flat on Thursday at $17.46, giving the company a market value of about $11.2 billion. News of Sara Lee’s plans were first reported by The Wall Street Journal online. Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill., has been shedding assets in recent years to focus on faster-growing meat and beverage businesses. In late December, Sara Lee announced the sale of its White King and Janola cleaning brands to Symex Holdings for $50 million. Unilever closed on its purchase of Sara Lee’s body care business this month for $2.5 billion. And in November, Sara Lee sold its North American bakery operations to Mexico’s Grupo Bimbo for $959 million. One of the drivers for Sara Lee’s efforts to sell or split itself is the absence of a permanent chief executive since Brenda C. Barnes departed last August after suffering a stroke. Marcel Smits, who had been chief financial officer at the time of Ms. Barnes’s stroke, is filling in as interim chief executive. But that search has been slowed as the company decides whether to sell itself or more of its units, people briefed on the matter said.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D91F30F933A15751C1A9669D8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee and Brazilian Suitor Are Said to Be at Impasse on Price<date>Published: December 20, 2010</date><text>Sara Lee's discussions about a potential sale to JBS of Brazil have been delayed so far because of a disagreement over the price of a potential deal, a person briefed on the matter told DealBook on Sunday. While the talks have been on and off for several months -- having begun shortly after Sara Lee's chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, resigned in August for health reasons -- the two may still reach a deal at some point in the coming months, this person said. Still, no transaction is imminent. Shares in Sara Lee closed up 5.3 percent on Friday at $17.26, after The Wall Street Journal reported that the two companies had held deal talks. Sara Lee's stock has risen 41.7 percent over the year, and as of Friday had a market value of about $11 billion. One of Sara Lee's concerns is JBS's financing of a potential transaction, this person said. While JBS is believed to have the ability to raise enough money to strike a deal, its being roughly the same size as Sara Lee -- about $10.7 billion in market value as of Friday -- would leave the combined company with significant debt. Sara Lee carried about $2.4 billion in long-term debt as of Oct. 2. Still, while Sara Lee is also considering a further break-up, a sale to JBS would be most likely to yield the highest price. It rebuffed other, less-developed approaches from private equity firms like Kohlberg Kravis Roberts this fall, according to additional people briefed on the matter. No other potential suitor has had an offer as fully developed as JBS, the person briefed on the matter said. Representatives for Sara Lee and JBS were not immediately available for comment. Sara Lee has already shed several units in recent years: It sold its North American bakery business last month to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $959 million and its global body care and European detergents business last year to Unilever for E1.3 billion. It now focuses on faster-growing divisions like coffee and meats. The latter division includes brands like Ballpark, Hillshire Farm and Jimmy Dean. The fate of Sara Lee has been the subject of intense speculation since Ms. Barnes formally stepped down as chairman and chief executive in August, three months after suffering a stroke. The company had been looking for a permanent replacement, looking at both internal and external candidates. Marcel Smits, who had been chief financial officer at the time of Ms. Barnes's stroke, is currently filling in as interim chief executive. But that search has been slowed as the company decides whether to sell itself or more of its units, this person said. Big Brazilian companies have broadened their global ambitions as their home country's economy has grown dramatically, including looking for acquisitions abroad. Last year, JBS agreed to buy a majority stake in Pilgrim's Pride, helping the then-bankrupt chicken producer exit bankruptcy. And earlier this year, the Brazilian investment firm 3G Capital struck a deal to buy Burger King for about $4 billion. This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/12/19/sara-lee-talks-with-jbs-hit-bump-over-price/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Talks Hit a Bump on Price<date>December 19, 2010, 8:22 pm</date><text>M. Spencer Green/Associated Press 6:15 a.m. | Updated Sara Lee’s discussions about a potential sale to JBS of Brazil have been delayed because of a disagreement over the price, a person briefed on the matter said Sunday. While the talks have been on and off for several months — having begun shortly after Sara Lee’s chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, resigned in August for health reasons — the two may still reach a deal at some point in the coming months, this person said. Still, no transaction is imminent. Shares in Sara Lee closed up 5.3 percent on Friday at $17.26, after The Wall Street Journal reported that the two companies had held deal talks. Sara Lee’s stock has risen 41.7 percent over the year, and as of Friday had a market value of about $11 billion. One of Sara Lee’s concerns is JBS’s financing of a potential transaction, this person said. While JBS is believed to have the ability to raise enough money to strike a deal, the combined company would be left with significant debt. JBS is roughly the same size as Sara Lee, with about $10.7 billion in market value as of Friday. Sara Lee carried about $2.4 billion in long-term debt as of Oct. 2. Still, while Sara Lee is also considering a further breakup, a sale to JBS would be most likely to yield the highest price. Sara Lee has rebuffed other, less-developed approaches from private equity firms like Kohlberg Kravis Roberts this fall, according to additional people briefed on the matter. No other potential suitor has had an offer as fully developed as JBS, the person briefed on the matter said. Representatives for Sara Lee and JBS were not immediately available for comment. Sara Lee has already shed several units in recent years: It sold its North American bakery business last month to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $959 million and its global body care and European detergents business last year to Unilever for 1.3 billion euros. It now focuses on faster-growing divisions like coffee and meats through brands like Ballpark, Hillshire Farm and Jimmy Dean. The fate of Sara Lee has been the subject of intense speculation since Ms. Barnes formally stepped down as chairwoman and chief executive in August, three months after suffering a stroke. The company had been looking for a permanent replacement, considering both internal and external candidates. Marcel Smits, who had been chief financial officer at the time of Ms. Barnes’s stroke, is currently filling in as interim chief executive. But that search has been slowed as the company decides whether to sell itself or more of its units, this person said. Big Brazilian companies have broadened their global ambitions as their home country’s economy has grown dramatically, and many have been looking for acquisitions abroad. Last year, JBS agreed to buy a majority stake in Pilgrim’s Pride, helping the then-bankrupt chicken producer exit bankruptcy. And earlier this year, the Brazilian investment firm 3G Capital struck a deal to buy Burger King for about $4 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/10/business/10sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee to Sell Bakery Unit to Grupo Bimbo<date>Published: November 9, 2010</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said on Tuesday that it would sell its North American bakery business to Grupo Bimbo of Mexico for $925 million, the latest move to shrink what was once a sprawling company with a product lineup including hot dogs and underwear.After the sale, in which Bimbo will also assume $34 million in debt, Sara Lee will focus on meats and coffee, with brands like Hillshire Farm lunch meat and Senseo coffee pods. The North American bakery unit generated $2.13 billion in sales in the fiscal year that ended Oct. 2, out of $10.79 billion for the entire company. “It was not a make-it-or-break-it piece for Sara Lee,” said Timothy Ramey, an analyst at D. A. Davidson. He said that the company might look more attractive without that low-margin business, which has been pressured by higher wheat costs and discounts on supermarket store shelves. Because of the sale of the bakery business, Sara Lee said it planned to accelerate its share buyback plans. It expects to complete the repurchase of $2.5 billion to $3 billion in stock by July 2012. For Bimbo, the acquisition is part of its push to become one of the largest players in North American bakeries. The company bought the United States bread-making unit of George Weston Ltd. of Canada for $2.38 billion in December 2008. The companies expect the deal to close in the first half of 2011. Sara Lee also reported first-quarter results and said its income fell to $194 million, or 29 cents a share, from $287 million, or 41 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Sales in the period, which ended Oct. 2 and was the first quarter of its fiscal year, fell 0.5 percent, to $2.58 billion. Shares of Sara Lee, which is based in Downers Grove, Ill., rose 41 cents, to $15.21.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/21/business/global/21coffee.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Nespresso and Rivals Vie for Dominance in Coffee War<date>Published: August 20, 2010</date><text>PARIS — George Clooney and John Malkovich aren’t the only coffee lovers fighting over a Nespresso these days.A coffee war has broken out in Europe pitting the Swiss food giant Nestlé against the struggling American food group Sara Lee as well as a former Nestlé executive. They are at odds over the worldwide monopoly Nespresso has long held on the lucrative espresso pods that fit its coffee-making machines. Helping propel its popularity in Europe is a sleekly wry English-language ad campaign featuring Mr. Clooney and Mr. Malkovich. With billions at stake, Nespresso has sued its rivals, accusing them of making cheaper copycat pods that violate the intellectual property it created in developing a system to make a convenient homemade cup of espresso that it claims can best a barista. The first court test could begin next month here, where Nespresso’s competitors recently put their pods on grocery store shelves in hopes of establishing a beachhead to make inroads throughout Europe and into the United States. “Nestlé has spent millions of dollars on innovation and research in Nespresso over many years,” said Richard Girardot, chief executive of Nestlé Nespresso. “So when someone comes along with a pure copy of the product, we have to protect ourselves.” But Nespresso’s rivals say that Nestlé is trying to lock them out of one of the fastest-growing segments of the coffee market: pods now account for 20 to 40 percent of the value of ground coffee sales in the $17 billion European coffee market, according to Euromonitor International. “What they’re doing is similar to Hewlett-Packard or Epson trying to forbid generic cartridges,” said Jean-Paul Gaillard, who ran Nespresso for a decade but who now is being sued by Nestlé for devising a biodegradable version of its capsule. “They are trying to stop copies — but our product is not a copy,” he said. Competitors have emerged to other single-serve coffee products, but Nestlé is the first to take legal action to try to ward generics away from the gold mine of coffee by the pod. “The real margins now are in capsulized coffee,” Mr. Gaillard said, “where you basically sell five grams of coffee for five times the price of what you’d get from regular roasted ground.” Sales have leapt 30 percent a year, on average, over the last decade, ever since Nespresso underwent an aggressive makeover that transformed it from a humdrum office coffee product to a must-have item among chic urbanites. Through star-studded advertising in Europe and Asia and a growing network of clubby boutiques now numbering 200, it lures upscale customers, whether in New York, Paris or Shanghai. Since 2000, when Nespresso started to break even, the company has sold more than 20 billion capsules through its boutiques and Web site at about 43 to 62 cents apiece. The price of its machines start around $190 and soar beyond $2,500. Given similar projections for future growth, others started trying to angle in. Nestlé has not made that easy: it owns the patents — 1,700 of them — on its personal espresso system, which Mr. Malkovich, playing God in Nespresso’s most recent European ads, trades for Mr. Clooney’s soul. Many of the patents are set to expire in 2012, and Nestlé has been working on other ways to prevent competitors from hacking a system that uses unique water dynamics to pump an espresso kissed with foam out of a hermetically sealed aluminum capsule. Sara Lee, which has been trying since 2005 to engineer a recovery, recently broke through. In mid-July, it put its own plastic perforated version of the capsule, the L’Or, in French supermarkets, at a price of 37 cents. So far, it has sold 30 million capsules, a spokesman said. “Coffee is Sara Lee’s No. 1 business; it accounts for well over 50 percent of their earnings,” said Tim Ramey, an analyst at D. A. Davidson &amp; Company in Portland, Ore. “The single-serve coffee business is the piece that’s growing fast, so it’s important for them.” Sara Lee has its own low-cost version of a personal espresso machine, the Senseo, whose pods alone had sales of $555 million in the fiscal year that ended June 30. Senseo is a top seller in the American market and a rival to other single-serve coffees in the United States, like Green Mountain. About 27 million Senseo machines were sold in the last decade, compared to about eight million Nespresso machines. But the real gold mine is in pods. Sara Lee insists that its capsules do not violate Nestlé’s patents. “In terms of shape, size, color, material — the whole product is different,” said Ernesto Duran, a spokesman for Sara Lee. If Sara Lee is confident, so is Mr. Gaillard, who started the Ethical Coffee Company three years ago to grab a piece of a market he knows inside out. He takes credit for dreaming up the way to make Nespresso a breakthrough product when he was the top executive there from 1988 to 1997, a claim that elicits long moments of silence from current executives. “I wanted to create the Chanel of coffee, and decided to make Nespresso chic and bobo,” he said. “The idea was to keep it to the level of people who have a doorman.”</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/13/business/13sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Swings to a Profit<date>Published: August 12, 2010</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation returned to profitability in its fourth quarter, but investors were wary of the company’s future in the face of rising commodity prices. Sara Lee also said it expected its fiscal 2011 profit to be at the low end of analysts’ expectations.Sara Lee leaders remained confident, saying the company was on the trajectory put in place by its former chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, who stepped down this week to focus on her health after a stroke. Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill., has been trimming costs and product lines for several years to focus on its core food and beverage businesses. The moves appeared to pay off as the company reported net income above Wall Street expectations. It earned $187 million, or 28 cents a share, for the quarter that ended July 3. That compares with a loss of $14 million, or 2 cents a share, a year earlier, when a large tax charge cut its profit. Excluding one-time items, Sara Lee earned 19 cents a share, while analysts surveyed by Thomson Reuters on average forecast 16 cents a share. Revenue rose 4.2 percent to $2.8 billion, helped by an extra week in the quarter. Analysts anticipated revenue of $2.86 billion. Sara Lee said lower prices on some items and higher marketing costs dragged on its results, but it made important gains like increasing market share for certain units and selling off noncore lines like body care. Revenue rose in North American retail and international beverages, Sara Lee’s biggest units. The increase was less pronounced in sales to businesses like hotels because of weak demand. And Sara Lee’s international bakery business also struggled from competition by store brands and weak sales in Spain. Sara Lee said it was focused on three core businesses: coffee, frozen bakery and branded meats like Hillshire Farms products and Jimmy Dean sausage. “We showed substantial progress in developing our capabilities and laying the groundwork for future growth,” said Marcel Smits, the company’s chief financial officer and acting chief executive. “Our ongoing commitment to investing in our best brands and best ideas is paying off.” For the full year, the company earned $506 million or 73 cents a share. That was up from $364 million, or 52 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding one-time items, it earned $1.08 a share for the year. Revenue fell less than 1 percent to $10.79 billion. Sara Lee said it faced rising prices for meat, coffee and wheat and pricing pressure from grocery stores, which want to offer discounts to appeal to budget-minded shoppers. For fiscal 2011, Sara Lee expects to earn 93 cents to $1.02 on revenue of $11.2 billion to $11.5 billion. Analysts expect the company to earn 94 cents on revenue of $10.97 billion. The company also said the search for a new chief executive would occur in a timely manner but did not disclose details.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/10/business/10saralee.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Chief Is Leaving After a Stroke<date>Published: August 9, 2010</date><text>Sara Lee, the food maker, said Monday that its chairwoman and chief executive, Brenda Barnes, would step down permanently to focus on improving her health after a stroke.Ms. Barnes, 56, had been on temporary medical leave since May 14. She will also leave her position on Sara Lee’s board. Marcel Smits, the chief financial officer, who has been handling the chief executive duties in her place, will continue to do so until a new chief is named. Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill., said its board had started a process to select a new chief and was looking inside and outside the company. Possible successors could be Mr. Smits, who joined the company last October from the Dutch telecom company Koninklijke KPN, where he was chief financial officer. Another candidate could be the chief executive of North American Retail and Foodservice, Christopher John Fraleigh. He, Mr. Smits and a board member, James Crown, have been working together to oversee the business in Ms. Barnes’s absence. Mr. Crown took over as chairman and will remain in that position. Ms. Barnes joined Sara Lee as president and chief operating officer in 2004. She became chief executive in 2005. She led the company, known for its namesake breads and brands including Jimmy Dean and Hillshire Farm, through a restructuring, which shed unprofitable plants, jobs and units to focus on its core food business. Shortly after she took over, the company spun off its underwear and clothing unit Hanesbrands in 2006. Last month, Sara Lee completed the sale of its Ambi Pur air freshener business to Procter &amp; Gamble for $470 million. Sara Lee has also sold off interests of an insecticide business in India and sold its personal care business to Unilever. Slimming down the company took it to about $13 billion in revenue in 2009 from nearly $16 billion in 2006. Shares have lost more than 21 percent of their value since early 2006, when they opened trading at $18.95. They closed Monday at $14.82. Ms. Barnes spent the bulk of her career, from 1976 to 1996, with PepsiCo, and served as president and chief executive of PepsiCola North America from 1996 to 1998. She also served as interim president and chief executive of Starwood Hotels and Resorts from late 1999 to early 2000. Sara Lee is set to report its fourth-quarter results Thursday.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/07/21/sara-lee-said-to-ponder-auction-of-bread-unit/?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Said to Ponder Auction of Bread Unit<date>July 21, 2010, 7:41 am</date><text>Is Sara Lee cooking up an auction of its bread and bakery division? According to news reports, the food giant is mulling a sale of the unit, which includes the largest fresh-bread brand in the United States. The Chicago Tribune, citing sources familiar with the matter, said that Sara Lee has been discreetly wooing potential buyers for the division. However, the newspaper cautioned that a sale was unlikely to happen any time soon. One person familiar with the discussions told The Tribune that Sara Lee may wait until the market improves. Bloomberg News, also citing people familiar with the matter, reported that the bread unit, which has seen its sales dwindle amid competition from cheaper store brands, could fetch about $1.5 billion. Sara Lee has chosen Bank of America to advise it on options for the division, according to Bloomberg News. Go to Article from The Chicago Tribune » Go to Article from Bloomberg News »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0D81E3AF935A1575AC0A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">Unilever to Buy Businesses From Sara Lee<date>Published: September 26, 2009</date><text>The consumer products giant Unilever said on Friday that it had agreed to buy soaps and personal care businesses from the Sara Lee Corporation for 1.28 billion euros ($1.88 billion). The businesses to be acquired, subject to regulatory approval, include Sara Lee's worldwide body care products business and its European detergents arm. The products include the Sanex brand of soap; Duschdas, a German shower gel maker; and several strong regional brands like Radox bubble bath and Switzal, a maker of baby shampoo. Unilever said the businesses it would acquire had sales of 750 million euros and operating earnings of 128 million euros in the 12 months that ended in June. Unilever, the world's third-largest consumer products company after the Procter &amp; Gamble Company and Nestlé, says its Dove, Axe and Rexona lines will complement the Sara Lee brands. Sara Lee's chief executive, Brenda Barnes, said her company would use the proceeds to ''invest for growth in our core businesses'' and to buy back $1 billion of stock. For Sara Lee, the sale is part of a strategy to concentrate on food and beverages and follows its 2006 spinoff of the clothing unit Hanesbrands. Sara Lee said potential buyers had shown ''significant interest'' in the rest of its household-products businesses, which are also for sale. The deal would be the largest purchase for Unilever since its $2.6 billion acquisition of Ben &amp; Jerry's in 2000, and the first initiated under the new chief executive, Paul Polman. Unilever has corporate headquarters in London and in the Netherlands.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/08/business/08sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Reports 22% Decline in Profit<date>Published: May 7, 2009</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said on Thursday that its quarterly profit fell 22 percent as softness in its North American food service division and the stronger dollar pushed sales lower. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company, which makes Jimmy Dean sausages, Hillshire Farm deli meats and Ball Park franks, earned $165 million, or 24 cents a share, down from $211 million, or 30 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a tax adjustment, profit was 25 cents a share, better than the 18 cents a share expected by analysts. Sales in the period, which ended March 28 and was the third quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, slipped nearly 7 percent, to $3.03 billion, from $3.24 billion. At its North American food service unit, which sells supplies to commercial customers like restaurants, sales fell 6.7 percent, partly because consumers have cut back on eating out to save money. Sales by its North American retail business, which sells products to grocery stores, rose 3.1 percent, while volume at its fresh bakery business in North America, which includes its namesake breads, rose 2.5 percent. International businesses were hurt primarily by the stronger dollar. Shares in Sara Lee, which is based in Downers Grove, Ill., rose 39 cents, to $9.35. More Articles in Business »The Sara Lee Corporation said on Thursday that its quarterly profit fell 22 percent as softness in its North American food service division and the stronger dollar pushed sales lower. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company, which makes Jimmy Dean sausages, Hillshire Farm deli meats and Ball Park franks, earned $165 million, or 24 cents a share, down from $211 million, or 30 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a tax adjustment, profit was 25 cents a share, better than the 18 cents a share expected by analysts. Sales in the period, which ended March 28 and was the third quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, slipped nearly 7 percent, to $3.03 billion, from $3.24 billion. At its North American food service unit, which sells supplies to commercial customers like restaurants, sales fell 6.7 percent, partly because consumers have cut back on eating out to save money. Sales by its North American retail business, which sells products to grocery stores, rose 3.1 percent, while volume at its fresh bakery business in North America, which includes its namesake breads, rose 2.5 percent. International businesses were hurt primarily by the stronger dollar. Shares in Sara Lee, which is based in Downers Grove, Ill., rose 39 cents, to $9.35.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/10/business/media/10adco.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Down Economic Times Elicit Upbeat Campaigns<date>Published: March 9, 2009</date><text>SAY goodbye to the dutiful Quaker Man who declared of his namesake oatmeal, “Nothing is better for thee than me.” He and the Quaker Oats division of PepsiCo are clambering aboard a fast-moving marketing bandwagon by offering upbeat exhortations during these tough economic times. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image One ad shows a man flying to work with jets on his back powered by two packages of Old Fashioned Quaker Oats. Add to Portfolio PepsiCo Inc Sara Lee Corp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » “Go humans go” is the theme of a major campaign getting under way for Quaker Oats. The theme acts as an umbrella under which all the division’s oat-based products are being peddled; as an announcer in a commercial declares, “The power of Quaker is in everything we make.” Television, print, online (quakeroats.com/gohumansgo) and outdoor ads  along with promotions and events around the country  proclaim that the Quaker oat is a “super grain” that “gives you a little lift, physically and emotionally” and “makes you feel good knowing you’re doing something good for yourself.” It seems counterintuitive to accentuate the positive amid all the downbeat financial news. But Madison Avenue is typically a place called Hope. Besides, gloom-mongering could convince consumers to put off what little spending they still intend. “You could always look at the glass as half-full or half-empty,” Annie Young-Scrivner, chief marketing officer and vice president for sales at the Quaker foods and snacks division, said on Monday at an event in Times Square to introduce the campaign. “We look at it half-full,” she added, which suits “a very iconic brand” like Quaker.  As Quaker Oats cheers on the human race, Visa has a campaign that also plays up the word go, which carries the theme “More people go with Visa.” And the Hillshire Farm unit of Sara Lee is running a humorous campaign under the banner “Go meat!” Those go-go ads join a lengthening list of cockeyed marketers sponsoring campaigns carrying optimistic themes. They include Bank of America, with “Bank of opportunity”; Coca-Cola, with “Open happiness”; the Pepsi-Cola soft drink sold by PepsiCo, with ads in which the o’s in words like “hope” are replaced by a logo resembling a smiling face; and Western Union, with a one-word burst of positivity: “Yes!” “We did a great deal of research around the globe,” said Gail Galuppo, executive vice president and chief marketing officer at Western Union in Englewood, Colo., and determined that customers were still “working hard in pursuit of their dreams.” “In a world today where they hear a lot of ‘no’ and ‘maybe,’ ” she added, “we wanted to say ‘yes’ to them.” The Western Union campaign is by the Hong Kong office of Publicis Worldwide, part of the Publicis Groupe. The Quaker campaign, with a budget estimated at more than $100 million, is being created by Goodby, Silverstein &amp; Partners in San Francisco, part of the Omnicom Group. Another Omnicom agency, OMD, is handling the media part of the campaign. Edelman, part of Daniel J. Edelman Inc., is publicizing elements of the campaign like the Go Project, through which Quaker Oats will donate food to Share Our Strength, and Go Grants, $500 stipends from Quaker to consumers to start efforts to fight hunger in local communities. Many campaigns that are trying to put on a happy face during hard times are including charitable or philanthropic aspects to increase their feel-good appeal to feel-bad consumers.  The Quaker campaign is about “leveraging human energy to fuel your day,” Ms. Young-Scrivner said, “and also leveraging human energy to do more for others.” The development of the campaign began last summer. “Obviously, economic conditions are definitely a factor” in marketing decisions, Ms. Young-Scrivner said, but the premise of the campaign to “fuel yourself to be your very best” ought to resonate in a recession. A TV commercial and an accompanying print ad reflect that attitude, minus any presidents, by showing a man flying to work with a jetpack on his back powered by two packages of Old Fashioned Quaker Oats. A second ad compares Quaker Instant Oatmeal to a ramp that can send a child’s bicycle soaring into the air. A third ad, likening Quaker Chewy Granola Bars to a spring, urges shoppers to “put a little spring in your step.” The fourth ad depicts a section of the oatmeal package in the shape of a heart. “Take good care of your heart, and your heart will take good care of you,” the text reads. “Quaker Oatmeal has been helping lower cholesterol for 20 years.” The campaign represents the first work for Quaker Oats from Goodby, Silverstein since being selected last fall as the company’s lead creative agency. Goodby, Silverstein won the assignment from another Omnicom agency, Element 79 Partners. “Every once in a while as an advertising agency, you are presented with a brand that has great familiarity, great perceptions attached to it, but it’s out there in a latent phase,” said Jamie Barrett, partner and creative director at Goodby, Silverstein. The campaign offers “a focus and a mission for the products as a brand,” he added, which ought to increase product sales as it burnishes the image of the brand. The ads have a contemporary attitude, Mr. Barrett said, while at the same time acknowledging the heritage of Quaker Oats. “The Quaker Man has been an icon for more than a century,” he added, “so we wanted to make sure what we did was true to the brand, served up in a way that rang true and doesn’t take it to a place that’s not genuine.” The campaign began last week with so-called teaser ads, billboards and signs in a dozen large markets that showed only parts of the Quaker Man. The “reveal” came on Monday at the event in Times Square, along with material on the Quaker Oats Web site explaining the campaign. The jetpack TV commercial is scheduled to start next Monday, along with newspaper ads; outdoor ads bearing the “Go humans go” theme, appearing in 20 large markets; and ads on Web sites like health.com and instyle.com. Magazine ads are planned for later this month, as are activities involving bloggers. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on March 10, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.SAY goodbye to the dutiful Quaker Man who declared of his namesake oatmeal, “Nothing is better for thee than me.” He and the Quaker Oats division of PepsiCo are clambering aboard a fast-moving marketing bandwagon by offering upbeat exhortations during these tough economic times. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image One ad shows a man flying to work with jets on his back powered by two packages of Old Fashioned Quaker Oats. Add to Portfolio PepsiCo Inc Sara Lee Corp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » “Go humans go” is the theme of a major campaign getting under way for Quaker Oats. The theme acts as an umbrella under which all the division’s oat-based products are being peddled; as an announcer in a commercial declares, “The power of Quaker is in everything we make.” Television, print, online (quakeroats.com/gohumansgo) and outdoor ads  along with promotions and events around the country  proclaim that the Quaker oat is a “super grain” that “gives you a little lift, physically and emotionally” and “makes you feel good knowing you’re doing something good for yourself.” It seems counterintuitive to accentuate the positive amid all the downbeat financial news. But Madison Avenue is typically a place called Hope. Besides, gloom-mongering could convince consumers to put off what little spending they still intend. “You could always look at the glass as half-full or half-empty,” Annie Young-Scrivner, chief marketing officer and vice president for sales at the Quaker foods and snacks division, said on Monday at an event in Times Square to introduce the campaign. “We look at it half-full,” she added, which suits “a very iconic brand” like Quaker.  As Quaker Oats cheers on the human race, Visa has a campaign that also plays up the word go, which carries the theme “More people go with Visa.” And the Hillshire Farm unit of Sara Lee is running a humorous campaign under the banner “Go meat!” Those go-go ads join a lengthening list of cockeyed marketers sponsoring campaigns carrying optimistic themes. They include Bank of America, with “Bank of opportunity”; Coca-Cola, with “Open happiness”; the Pepsi-Cola soft drink sold by PepsiCo, with ads in which the o’s in words like “hope” are replaced by a logo resembling a smiling face; and Western Union, with a one-word burst of positivity: “Yes!” “We did a great deal of research around the globe,” said Gail Galuppo, executive vice president and chief marketing officer at Western Union in Englewood, Colo., and determined that customers were still “working hard in pursuit of their dreams.” “In a world today where they hear a lot of ‘no’ and ‘maybe,’ ” she added, “we wanted to say ‘yes’ to them.” The Western Union campaign is by the Hong Kong office of Publicis Worldwide, part of the Publicis Groupe. The Quaker campaign, with a budget estimated at more than $100 million, is being created by Goodby, Silverstein &amp; Partners in San Francisco, part of the Omnicom Group. Another Omnicom agency, OMD, is handling the media part of the campaign. Edelman, part of Daniel J. Edelman Inc., is publicizing elements of the campaign like the Go Project, through which Quaker Oats will donate food to Share Our Strength, and Go Grants, $500 stipends from Quaker to consumers to start efforts to fight hunger in local communities. Many campaigns that are trying to put on a happy face during hard times are including charitable or philanthropic aspects to increase their feel-good appeal to feel-bad consumers.  The Quaker campaign is about “leveraging human energy to fuel your day,” Ms. Young-Scrivner said, “and also leveraging human energy to do more for others.” The development of the campaign began last summer. “Obviously, economic conditions are definitely a factor” in marketing decisions, Ms. Young-Scrivner said, but the premise of the campaign to “fuel yourself to be your very best” ought to resonate in a recession. A TV commercial and an accompanying print ad reflect that attitude, minus any presidents, by showing a man flying to work with a jetpack on his back powered by two packages of Old Fashioned Quaker Oats. A second ad compares Quaker Instant Oatmeal to a ramp that can send a child’s bicycle soaring into the air. A third ad, likening Quaker Chewy Granola Bars to a spring, urges shoppers to “put a little spring in your step.” The fourth ad depicts a section of the oatmeal package in the shape of a heart. “Take good care of your heart, and your heart will take good care of you,” the text reads. “Quaker Oatmeal has been helping lower cholesterol for 20 years.” The campaign represents the first work for Quaker Oats from Goodby, Silverstein since being selected last fall as the company’s lead creative agency. Goodby, Silverstein won the assignment from another Omnicom agency, Element 79 Partners. “Every once in a while as an advertising agency, you are presented with a brand that has great familiarity, great perceptions attached to it, but it’s out there in a latent phase,” said Jamie Barrett, partner and creative director at Goodby, Silverstein. The campaign offers “a focus and a mission for the products as a brand,” he added, which ought to increase product sales as it burnishes the image of the brand. The ads have a contemporary attitude, Mr. Barrett said, while at the same time acknowledging the heritage of Quaker Oats. “The Quaker Man has been an icon for more than a century,” he added, “so we wanted to make sure what we did was true to the brand, served up in a way that rang true and doesn’t take it to a place that’s not genuine.” The campaign began last week with so-called teaser ads, billboards and signs in a dozen large markets that showed only parts of the Quaker Man. The “reveal” came on Monday at the event in Times Square, along with material on the Quaker Oats Web site explaining the campaign. The jetpack TV commercial is scheduled to start next Monday, along with newspaper ads; outdoor ads bearing the “Go humans go” theme, appearing in 20 large markets; and ads on Web sites like health.com and instyle.com. Magazine ads are planned for later this month, as are activities involving bloggers.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/05/business/05sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Posts a Loss<date>Published: February 4, 2009</date><text>MILWAUKEE (AP) -- The food maker Sara Lee Corporation said Wednesday that it lost $17 million in its most recent quarter. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company also cut its 2009 earnings forecast for a second time on a write-down and softer results from its international household and body care and international bakery business divisions. The company, based in Downers Grove, Ill., lost 2 cents a share in the period. A year earlier, it earned $182 million, or 25 cents a share. Sales in the period, which ended Dec. 27 and was the second quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, fell to $3.34 billion from $3.41 billion. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 5, 2009, on page B6 of the New York edition.MILWAUKEE (AP) -- The food maker Sara Lee Corporation said Wednesday that it lost $17 million in its most recent quarter. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company also cut its 2009 earnings forecast for a second time on a write-down and softer results from its international household and body care and international bakery business divisions. The company, based in Downers Grove, Ill., lost 2 cents a share in the period. A year earlier, it earned $182 million, or 25 cents a share. Sales in the period, which ended Dec. 27 and was the second quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, fell to $3.34 billion from $3.41 billion.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/08/business/08sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Reports a Loss Despite a Growth in Sales<date>Published: August 7, 2008</date><text>Sara Lee posted a loss in its fiscal fourth quarter Thursday as it reduced the value of its bakery business, but analysts said that sales increases showed the food company was passing on price increases to consumers to offset rising commodity costs. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company, which makes breads and Hillshire Farm deli meat, said revenue rose 12 percent, to $3.51 billion, from $3.13 billion a year earlier. The performance was helped by a weak dollar, price increases and higher sales in all segments. Food makers, struggling with soaring costs for commodities like fuel, corn and wheat, are raising prices and hoping consumers will keep buying their products. Sara Lee said its prices rose a total $350 million in the year, $120 million of that in the fourth quarter, to help offset an equal rise in commodity prices. That represents an across-the-board price increase of about 4 percent for consumers, analysts say. The chairwoman and chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, said the company expected even more pressure on commodity costs in its next fiscal year, roughly about $500 million worth. In the three-month period that ended June 28, Sara Lee said it lost $695 million, or 98 cents a share, compared with a profit of $117 million, or 16 cents a share, a year ago. The results included an impairment charge of $1.20 a share for its Spanish bakery and North American food service bakery operations and write-downs of other assets in North America. Analysts expected earnings of 26 cents and sales of $3.48 billion, according to Thomson Financial. Analysts usually exclude one-time items from their estimates. Shares fell 54 cents, to $13.98. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on August 8, 2008, on page C2 of the New York edition.Sara Lee posted a loss in its fiscal fourth quarter Thursday as it reduced the value of its bakery business, but analysts said that sales increases showed the food company was passing on price increases to consumers to offset rising commodity costs. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Sara Lee Corp Go to your Portfolio » The company, which makes breads and Hillshire Farm deli meat, said revenue rose 12 percent, to $3.51 billion, from $3.13 billion a year earlier. The performance was helped by a weak dollar, price increases and higher sales in all segments. Food makers, struggling with soaring costs for commodities like fuel, corn and wheat, are raising prices and hoping consumers will keep buying their products. Sara Lee said its prices rose a total $350 million in the year, $120 million of that in the fourth quarter, to help offset an equal rise in commodity prices. That represents an across-the-board price increase of about 4 percent for consumers, analysts say. The chairwoman and chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, said the company expected even more pressure on commodity costs in its next fiscal year, roughly about $500 million worth. In the three-month period that ended June 28, Sara Lee said it lost $695 million, or 98 cents a share, compared with a profit of $117 million, or 16 cents a share, a year ago. The results included an impairment charge of $1.20 a share for its Spanish bakery and North American food service bakery operations and write-downs of other assets in North America. Analysts expected earnings of 26 cents and sales of $3.48 billion, according to Thomson Financial. Analysts usually exclude one-time items from their estimates. Shares fell 54 cents, to $13.98.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/07/business/07sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Swings to a Profit<date>Published: February 7, 2008</date><text>CHICAGO (Reuters)  The Sara Lee Corporation posted a quarterly profit on Wednesday, in contrast to a loss a year earlier, as the weaker dollar, new products and increased spending on marketing helped sales. Sara Lee, which makes Sara Lee baked goods, Jimmy Dean sausage and Hillshire Farm deli meats, said profit was $182 million, or 25 cents a share, in contrast to a loss of $62 million, or 8 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding one-time items, the company earned 22 cents a share, missing the 24 cents expected by analysts. Sales in the period, which ended Dec. 29 and was the second quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, rose 9.7 percent, to $3.5 billion from $3.2 billion. Excluding the benefit of the weak dollar, sales were up 4.2 percent. Sara Lee, like most food companies, has been coping with soaring costs for commodities like wheat. The company has raised prices and altered its operations in response to the higher costs. Sara Lee said advertising and promotion spending for continuing operations rose 14 percent. The company also stood by its full-year profit forecast instead of raising it, despite saying that it now expects the dollar to be even weaker against the euro than it had previously thought. A weaker dollar causes sales outside the United States to be worth more in dollars. The company is not reflecting the weak dollar outlook in its forecast because of concerns about volatile commodities costs and economic weakness, Brenda C. Barnes, the chief executive, said in a conference call with analysts. Sara Lee shares closed down 1.7 percent, to $13.74 a share. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO (Reuters)  The Sara Lee Corporation posted a quarterly profit on Wednesday, in contrast to a loss a year earlier, as the weaker dollar, new products and increased spending on marketing helped sales. Sara Lee, which makes Sara Lee baked goods, Jimmy Dean sausage and Hillshire Farm deli meats, said profit was $182 million, or 25 cents a share, in contrast to a loss of $62 million, or 8 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding one-time items, the company earned 22 cents a share, missing the 24 cents expected by analysts. Sales in the period, which ended Dec. 29 and was the second quarter of Sara Lee’s fiscal year, rose 9.7 percent, to $3.5 billion from $3.2 billion. Excluding the benefit of the weak dollar, sales were up 4.2 percent. Sara Lee, like most food companies, has been coping with soaring costs for commodities like wheat. The company has raised prices and altered its operations in response to the higher costs. Sara Lee said advertising and promotion spending for continuing operations rose 14 percent. The company also stood by its full-year profit forecast instead of raising it, despite saying that it now expects the dollar to be even weaker against the euro than it had previously thought. A weaker dollar causes sales outside the United States to be worth more in dollars. The company is not reflecting the weak dollar outlook in its forecast because of concerns about volatile commodities costs and economic weakness, Brenda C. Barnes, the chief executive, said in a conference call with analysts. Sara Lee shares closed down 1.7 percent, to $13.74 a share.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/08/business/08sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Earnings Fall 40% at Sara Lee<date>Published: November 8, 2007</date><text>CHICAGO, Nov. 7 (AP)  A 21 percent increase in marketing expenses weighed down earnings at the food maker Sara Lee, which posted a 40 percent decrease in its fiscal first-quarter profit on Wednesday. Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill., said its operating profit was also hurt by rising prices for commodities like wheat, poultry, pork and green coffee. But executives said the company was able to offset most of those increases by raising its prices. In the quarter ended Sept. 29, Sara Lees net income fell to $200 million, or 28 cents a share. Revenue rose 8 percent, to $3.13 billion, up from $2.89 billion in the first quarter of 2007. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had expected earnings of 27 cents a share and revenue of $3.12 billion. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO, Nov. 7 (AP)  A 21 percent increase in marketing expenses weighed down earnings at the food maker Sara Lee, which posted a 40 percent decrease in its fiscal first-quarter profit on Wednesday. Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill., said its operating profit was also hurt by rising prices for commodities like wheat, poultry, pork and green coffee. But executives said the company was able to offset most of those increases by raising its prices. In the quarter ended Sept. 29, Sara Lees net income fell to $200 million, or 28 cents a share. Revenue rose 8 percent, to $3.13 billion, up from $2.89 billion in the first quarter of 2007. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had expected earnings of 27 cents a share and revenue of $3.12 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/18/washington/18contract.html?ref=saraleecorporation">U.S. Widens Net on Pricing of Food Supplies for G.I.’s<date>Published: October 18, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, Oct. 17  Federal agents are investigating whether several large food companies charged the government excessively high prices for supplies to American troops in Iraq and Kuwait, administration officials said Wednesday. Widening their previously disclosed inquiries into contract fraud and corruption in Kuwait and Iraq, investigators from the Justice and Defense Departments are examining deals that the Sara Lee Corporation, ConAgra Foods Inc. and other American companies made to supply the military, officials said. The inquiry centers on whether the companies overcharged the Army’s principal food supplier for the war zones, a Kuwait-based company called the Public Warehousing Company. Investigators are also looking into whether Public Warehousing improperly took payments from the food companies. Public Warehousing, which supplies enormous amounts of fruits, vegetables and meats for more than 160,000 troops in combat zones, said in a statement that it had done nothing wrong and was fully cooperating. But a Justice Department lawyer, Brian A. Mizoguchi, told a Federal Claims Court judge in Washington on June 12 that Public Warehousing’s business arrangements were the target of “a very large and active investigation into criminal fraud involving amounts in the hundreds of millions of dollars.” “It relates directly to the contracts,” Mr. Mizoguchi said, “because it relates to the pricing and costs under those contracts.” Public Warehousing, which is now called Agility Logistics, receives more than $1 billion a year to feed troops in Iraq and Kuwait. The investigation, which was reported Wednesday in The Wall Street Journal, is also focusing on Army officials who picked the food companies that are Public Warehousing’s suppliers. Procurement specialists said that once vendors like Public Warehousing received guidance from the Army Center of Excellence, Subsistence, at Fort Lee, Va., on what should be on the menu in chow halls, the vendors sought suppliers for that food. In some cases, the Army had designated specific companies to provide certain foods, like beef or chicken, which has drawn protests from rival companies. For example, Tyson Foods, the nation’s largest meat company, has complained to the Pentagon that some food companies have hired former military procurement officials to use their contacts to help win lucrative government contracts. Timothy L. Hale, a spokesman at Fort Lee, said the Army agency had not been notified that it was under investigation. He referred questions to the Justice Department. In a statement, Public Warehousing said its service had been “timely, reliable and cost-effective.” The company’s position is that what investigators are looking at as improper payments were actually discounts received for paying its suppliers ahead of schedule, a widely accepted practice in the food industry. In court papers, Public Warehousing cited an e-mail message in October 2006 from a military contracting officer telling the company that the practice of discounts was appropriate. Public Warehousing attributed its high prices partly to the costs associated with storing, handling and transporting supplies to multiple locations in a war zone. The company said more than 30 of its employees had been killed and 200 wounded in the war zones. Several food companies said they were cooperating with investigators. ConAgra Foods said it first received a request for information from the Pentagon in January. “ConAgra Foods has been assured by the Department of Defense, which is leading the investigation of Public Warehousing Company, that its role in this investigation is limited to that of a witness,” the company said. ConAgra has provided “relevant records and testimony to the government investigators.” ConAgra officials denied that they had overcharged. Officials for Sara Lee said they too had received a subpoena in January and had been assured that the company was not a target of the inquiry but a witness. Kenneth G. Trantowski, a spokesman for Quantum Foods, said the company had received a subpoena during the summer from the federal prosecutors related to an investigation of “food industry practices as it relates to the military,” but said the company was not a target of the investigation. Quantum Foods, based in the Chicago suburbs, has supplied meat, chicken and meals to the military since 2000, and has been shipping to Iraq since 2002. Tyson and some other major companies say they are being excluded from the lucrative war-zone market. Tyson sent a letter to the Defense Logistics Agency on April 3 outlining the company’s concerns about the way some food purchases by the military “appear to favor certain companies employing former military food service personnel,” Gary Mickelson, a company spokesman, said in an e-mail message. In the letter, Jenna R. Johnston, Tyson’s senior counsel and assistant secretary, requested a meeting to discuss what the company believed were unfair procurement practices. Specifically, she complained that some elements of the military were negotiating single-source, multiyear agreements with Tyson’s competitors worth hundreds of millions of dollars. She argued that it was inappropriate for the military to specify brand name merchandise for “commodity raw chicken pieces, French fries, ground beef, liquid eggs,” since they are typically served with no brand visible. Margot Williams contributed reporting from New York. More Articles in Washington »WASHINGTON, Oct. 17  Federal agents are investigating whether several large food companies charged the government excessively high prices for supplies to American troops in Iraq and Kuwait, administration officials said Wednesday. Widening their previously disclosed inquiries into contract fraud and corruption in Kuwait and Iraq, investigators from the Justice and Defense Departments are examining deals that the Sara Lee Corporation, ConAgra Foods Inc. and other American companies made to supply the military, officials said. The inquiry centers on whether the companies overcharged the Army’s principal food supplier for the war zones, a Kuwait-based company called the Public Warehousing Company. Investigators are also looking into whether Public Warehousing improperly took payments from the food companies. Public Warehousing, which supplies enormous amounts of fruits, vegetables and meats for more than 160,000 troops in combat zones, said in a statement that it had done nothing wrong and was fully cooperating. But a Justice Department lawyer, Brian A. Mizoguchi, told a Federal Claims Court judge in Washington on June 12 that Public Warehousing’s business arrangements were the target of “a very large and active investigation into criminal fraud involving amounts in the hundreds of millions of dollars.” “It relates directly to the contracts,” Mr. Mizoguchi said, “because it relates to the pricing and costs under those contracts.” Public Warehousing, which is now called Agility Logistics, receives more than $1 billion a year to feed troops in Iraq and Kuwait. The investigation, which was reported Wednesday in The Wall Street Journal, is also focusing on Army officials who picked the food companies that are Public Warehousing’s suppliers. Procurement specialists said that once vendors like Public Warehousing received guidance from the Army Center of Excellence, Subsistence, at Fort Lee, Va., on what should be on the menu in chow halls, the vendors sought suppliers for that food. In some cases, the Army had designated specific companies to provide certain foods, like beef or chicken, which has drawn protests from rival companies. For example, Tyson Foods, the nation’s largest meat company, has complained to the Pentagon that some food companies have hired former military procurement officials to use their contacts to help win lucrative government contracts. Timothy L. Hale, a spokesman at Fort Lee, said the Army agency had not been notified that it was under investigation. He referred questions to the Justice Department. In a statement, Public Warehousing said its service had been “timely, reliable and cost-effective.” The company’s position is that what investigators are looking at as improper payments were actually discounts received for paying its suppliers ahead of schedule, a widely accepted practice in the food industry. In court papers, Public Warehousing cited an e-mail message in October 2006 from a military contracting officer telling the company that the practice of discounts was appropriate. Public Warehousing attributed its high prices partly to the costs associated with storing, handling and transporting supplies to multiple locations in a war zone. The company said more than 30 of its employees had been killed and 200 wounded in the war zones. Several food companies said they were cooperating with investigators. ConAgra Foods said it first received a request for information from the Pentagon in January. “ConAgra Foods has been assured by the Department of Defense, which is leading the investigation of Public Warehousing Company, that its role in this investigation is limited to that of a witness,” the company said. ConAgra has provided “relevant records and testimony to the government investigators.” ConAgra officials denied that they had overcharged. Officials for Sara Lee said they too had received a subpoena in January and had been assured that the company was not a target of the inquiry but a witness. Kenneth G. Trantowski, a spokesman for Quantum Foods, said the company had received a subpoena during the summer from the federal prosecutors related to an investigation of “food industry practices as it relates to the military,” but said the company was not a target of the investigation. Quantum Foods, based in the Chicago suburbs, has supplied meat, chicken and meals to the military since 2000, and has been shipping to Iraq since 2002. Tyson and some other major companies say they are being excluded from the lucrative war-zone market. Tyson sent a letter to the Defense Logistics Agency on April 3 outlining the company’s concerns about the way some food purchases by the military “appear to favor certain companies employing former military food service personnel,” Gary Mickelson, a company spokesman, said in an e-mail message. In the letter, Jenna R. Johnston, Tyson’s senior counsel and assistant secretary, requested a meeting to discuss what the company believed were unfair procurement practices. Specifically, she complained that some elements of the military were negotiating single-source, multiyear agreements with Tyson’s competitors worth hundreds of millions of dollars. She argued that it was inappropriate for the military to specify brand name merchandise for “commodity raw chicken pieces, French fries, ground beef, liquid eggs,” since they are typically served with no brand visible. Margot Williams contributed reporting from New York.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/09/jobs/09boss.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Arriving, Goal by Goal<date>Published: September 9, 2007</date><text>I GREW up in upstate New York with three siblings. When I was born, my two sisters were 7 and 9 years older; my brother was 12 years older. The three of them were fairly competitive growing up. Skip to next paragraph *JAMES NOLAN* Chief executive, Sara Lee Foodservice BIRTH DATE Nov. 6, 1955 BIRTHPLACE Troy, N.Y. FAVORITE PHRASE If you are going to lead, lead. If you are going to follow, follow. If you are not going to do either, get out of the way. When I was 5 years old, my brother took me to see a regatta on Onondaga Lake. There were a couple of thousand people lining the shore. He was very insistent that I see the end of the race. There were fewer than 50 people at the end. The participants were exhausted. The losers were exasperated. Instead of just seeing the race as an event, my brother also showed me what the outcome meant for the participants. My father died when I was 14  Jan. 13, 1970. His passing was unexpected and marked my entire childhood. I felt compelled to take care of my mother, and within a year and a half I had a job at Aunt Cookies Sub Shop in Geneseo, N.Y., after school and on weekends. I made the sandwiches and learned a lot about interacting with customers. The lessons still apply today. The shop is still there. I order the turkey on Italian bread with extra peppers when I visit. I left home to attend Ithaca College, intending to major in education and become a coach. I decided to go out for the basketball team. By the time I was a senior, I was co-captain. At that years banquet, the basketball coach highlighted my work ethic and leadership. The next day the provost who had been at the dinner called me into his office. I was nervous; I had never met him. He told me that he had been impressed and had a friend who was a recruiter for Procter &amp; Gamble and who could set up an interview for me. It was 1977. I was married and had a baby and I was sending out résumés to be a teacher. I decided to take the interview. I met two recruiters in Ithaca at 6 a.m. They were two Cornell graduates who had been out to some fraternity the night before and stayed out a little too late. I got passed along to the next level. About one month later, I received a job offer for the food service division in Boston. I went door to door selling industrial shortening and oil. There was a clam shack that served fried food in Worcester, Mass., that was a heavy user of oil. If I got the account, it would open the door to other customers. Knowing the place was open only seasonally, I visited the owner twice a week at 6 a.m. the entire summer and landed the account. When he became a client, we went to a celebratory Yankees-Red Sox game in New York. He was a big Red Sox fan. He taught me an important lesson: Let the client know who you are and what you stand for. I went from there to become a national account manager at Pepsi-Cola. Over the years, Ive discussed business with my four kids. Three have business careers now. The youngest is a college senior, majoring in sales management. I used the same sense of structure and incentives with them that I did in managing a work force. I bought my oldest daughter her first car, an old Saab. It was totaled within a few months. I told her I would match whatever she saved to buy a replacement. As a separate incentive, I said that if she received a B or better average I would double the amount that we would pay. It was really no different than structuring an incentive program at work and setting consistent goals. She rode a bicycle, got rides from her mom and dad and her friends. It took her about a year to save for the car. She ended up buying a Jeep and was never in an accident with that car. She also had a few more years of driving experience, which helped us sleep at night. By December 2001 I had moved to the Pepsi bottler, Pepsi Americas. I received a call about an opening in the food service division of Sara Lee. It felt like coming back home. As told to Amy Zipkin. More Articles in Job Market »I GREW up in upstate New York with three siblings. When I was born, my two sisters were 7 and 9 years older; my brother was 12 years older. The three of them were fairly competitive growing up. Skip to next paragraph *JAMES NOLAN* Chief executive, Sara Lee Foodservice BIRTH DATE Nov. 6, 1955 BIRTHPLACE Troy, N.Y. FAVORITE PHRASE If you are going to lead, lead. If you are going to follow, follow. If you are not going to do either, get out of the way. When I was 5 years old, my brother took me to see a regatta on Onondaga Lake. There were a couple of thousand people lining the shore. He was very insistent that I see the end of the race. There were fewer than 50 people at the end. The participants were exhausted. The losers were exasperated. Instead of just seeing the race as an event, my brother also showed me what the outcome meant for the participants. My father died when I was 14  Jan. 13, 1970. His passing was unexpected and marked my entire childhood. I felt compelled to take care of my mother, and within a year and a half I had a job at Aunt Cookies Sub Shop in Geneseo, N.Y., after school and on weekends. I made the sandwiches and learned a lot about interacting with customers. The lessons still apply today. The shop is still there. I order the turkey on Italian bread with extra peppers when I visit. I left home to attend Ithaca College, intending to major in education and become a coach. I decided to go out for the basketball team. By the time I was a senior, I was co-captain. At that years banquet, the basketball coach highlighted my work ethic and leadership. The next day the provost who had been at the dinner called me into his office. I was nervous; I had never met him. He told me that he had been impressed and had a friend who was a recruiter for Procter &amp; Gamble and who could set up an interview for me. It was 1977. I was married and had a baby and I was sending out résumés to be a teacher. I decided to take the interview. I met two recruiters in Ithaca at 6 a.m. They were two Cornell graduates who had been out to some fraternity the night before and stayed out a little too late. I got passed along to the next level. About one month later, I received a job offer for the food service division in Boston. I went door to door selling industrial shortening and oil. There was a clam shack that served fried food in Worcester, Mass., that was a heavy user of oil. If I got the account, it would open the door to other customers. Knowing the place was open only seasonally, I visited the owner twice a week at 6 a.m. the entire summer and landed the account. When he became a client, we went to a celebratory Yankees-Red Sox game in New York. He was a big Red Sox fan. He taught me an important lesson: Let the client know who you are and what you stand for. I went from there to become a national account manager at Pepsi-Cola. Over the years, Ive discussed business with my four kids. Three have business careers now. The youngest is a college senior, majoring in sales management. I used the same sense of structure and incentives with them that I did in managing a work force. I bought my oldest daughter her first car, an old Saab. It was totaled within a few months. I told her I would match whatever she saved to buy a replacement. As a separate incentive, I said that if she received a B or better average I would double the amount that we would pay. It was really no different than structuring an incentive program at work and setting consistent goals. She rode a bicycle, got rides from her mom and dad and her friends. It took her about a year to save for the car. She ended up buying a Jeep and was never in an accident with that car. She also had a few more years of driving experience, which helped us sleep at night. By December 2001 I had moved to the Pepsi bottler, Pepsi Americas. I received a call about an opening in the food service division of Sara Lee. It felt like coming back home. As told to Amy Zipkin.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/16/business/16sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Citing Turnaround, Sara Lee Reports Profit<date>Published: August 16, 2007</date><text>CHICAGO, Aug. 15 (AP)  The Sara Lee Corporation said Wednesday that its quarterly profit soared, and executives pointed to the success of a turnaround plan that has helped sales rise in nearly every division. The better-than-expected results were helped by increased revenue in the bakery, household products and body care businesses. I really can say confidently that we are in a very different place than we were a year ago, the chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, said. We are well positioned for growth and are ready to build on the progress achieved last year. Ms. Barnes said the strong results capped a turnaround year for the company, which is now entering a growth phase. Sara Lee, which makes frozen cheesecakes, Ball Park hot dogs and Hillshire Farm deli meats, said its profit grew to $117 million, or 16 cents a share, from $8 million, or 1 cent a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended June 30 and was the fourth quarter of Sara Lees fiscal year, rose 8 percent, to $3.20 billion, from $2.97 billion in the fourth quarter of 2006. Excluding one-time items, the company earned 15 cents a share, topping the 13 cents expected by Wall Street analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sara Lees stock fell 7 cents, to $15.93 a share. Sara Lee is based in Chicago. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO, Aug. 15 (AP)  The Sara Lee Corporation said Wednesday that its quarterly profit soared, and executives pointed to the success of a turnaround plan that has helped sales rise in nearly every division. The better-than-expected results were helped by increased revenue in the bakery, household products and body care businesses. I really can say confidently that we are in a very different place than we were a year ago, the chief executive, Brenda C. Barnes, said. We are well positioned for growth and are ready to build on the progress achieved last year. Ms. Barnes said the strong results capped a turnaround year for the company, which is now entering a growth phase. Sara Lee, which makes frozen cheesecakes, Ball Park hot dogs and Hillshire Farm deli meats, said its profit grew to $117 million, or 16 cents a share, from $8 million, or 1 cent a share, a year earlier. Revenue in the period, which ended June 30 and was the fourth quarter of Sara Lees fiscal year, rose 8 percent, to $3.20 billion, from $2.97 billion in the fourth quarter of 2006. Excluding one-time items, the company earned 15 cents a share, topping the 13 cents expected by Wall Street analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sara Lees stock fell 7 cents, to $15.93 a share. Sara Lee is based in Chicago.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D7173EF93BA15754C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">National Briefing | Recall | Bread May Contain Metal Pieces<date>Published: July 28, 2007</date><text>Sara Lee Corporation is recalling 27 brands of whole-wheat bread products because they could contain small metal pieces, the company said. A recent routine inspection of a bakery in Meridian, Miss., uncovered problems with a flour-sifting screen, said a company spokesman, Mark Goldman. The problem was isolated to the Meridian bakery, which continued production using bagged flour that did not require the sifting system, Mr. Goldman said. The recall involves EarthGrains, Publix, Sara Lee Delightful, Sara Lee Hearty &amp; Delicious and several other brands that were stamped ''best if purchased by'' July 25, 2007, to Aug. 7, 2007, and included the code ''222.'' The products were sold in Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, Missouri and Tennessee. Consumers can return the bread to the store where it was purchased for a refund, said Sara Lee, based in Downers Grove, Ill.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/business/worldbusiness/16food.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Globalization in Every Loaf<date>Published: June 16, 2007</date><text>DOWNERS GROVE, Ill.  In a glassed-off area in the headquarters of Sara Lee, a handful of specialists study computer screens and flat-screen televisions beaming the latest weather reports and commodity prices. They are sourcing ingredients from all over the world to make Sara Lee’s assortment of breads, deli meats and microwaveable desserts. Skip to next paragraph Illustration by The New York Times Multimedia Graphic A Multinational Loaf Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York Times It is our responsibility to make sure what we are feeding people is safe, said David L. Brown, Sara Lees vice president for procurement. The lowering of trade barriers more than a decade ago has pushed food companies to scour the globe for more exotic  or the cheapest  ingredients to compete in a more global marketplace, not unlike automakers shipping in parts from all over. But with America’s relatively permissible food-import rules and weak inspection regime, is the trend to assemble food from so many far-flung locations heightening the risks of contamination? “Once ingredients are incorporated into processed foods, it is hard to check whether they come from overseas or to verify if there are any unsafe contaminants in the products,” said Michael F. Jacobson, executive director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest, a Washington lobby group. “This is increasing the chances that people will get unsafe food.” The concerns of Mr. Jacobson and some in Congress are being stoked by the recent scandal involving pet food contaminated with an industrial chemical called melamine and imported from China, which has resulted in thousands of pets being sickened or killed. Food industry executives say they understand the risks of foreign sourcing and are taking pains to mitigate them. “Ingredients from overseas are not the issue,” said Robert Earl, senior director of nutrition policy at the Grocery Manufacturers of America, a trade group that represents many of the largest food processors. “The problem comes from incorrect practices from manufacturers that happen to be in another country.” David L. Brown, Sara Lee’s vice president for procurement, said consumers should not be concerned. “We are going to do our homework,” he said, including vetting foreign factories and in some cases investing money to improve food-safety standards. “It is our responsibility to make sure what we are feeding people is safe. But the more variables you enter into, the more risk you have naturally. It is all about how you address those unknowns.” The controls in place to ensure that foreign-sourced ingredients are safe “are evolving as the world changes,” Mr. Brown said. Some people say they still have a long way to go. In the weeks since the pet food controversy broke, federal investigators have also discovered toxic toothpaste exported from China and melamine-laced ingredients for fish feed manufactured in Toledo, Ohio. The discoveries have prompted new calls by Congress to overhaul responsibility for America’s food-safety system, which is currently shared by the Food and Drug Administration, the Department of Agriculture and a grab bag of other agencies. Critics say the F.D.A., which bears the bulk of the food-safety load, is woefully underfinanced and understaffed, and they note that fewer than 1 percent of imported food shipments undergo laboratory analysis. The number of food inspectors has decreased in the last five years. The F.D.A. is exploring ways to use risk analysis to try to pinpoint food shipments that might pose hazards, The Wall Street Journal reported this week. Under the approach, countries and private companies might be required to provide the F.D.A. with more information about imported food. The rise in imported ingredients has been accompanied by an explosion in imported food generally: food imports more than doubled in the last decade, to $79.9 billion, according to the United States International Trade Commission. Consumers can only guess from reading most labels that individual food products today contain ingredients from a handful of continents. Despite having the world’s most expansive and efficient agricultural sector, America is hardly the only place where large food processors like Sara Lee, Kraft and General Mills have looked to acquire the dozens of ingredients that make up their microwaveable meals, processed cheeses, baked snack foods and breakfast cereals. What trade commission figures show is that ingredients are streaming in from more than 100 countries, including China, India, the Philippines and countries in sub-Saharan Africa. In some cases, consumer demand for more ethnic foods in the United States is pushing companies to import harder-to-find foods from exotic locales, but in other cases the phenomenon is simply a function of the way modern processed foods are assembled. The imported ingredients include caseins and caseinates (enzymes found in milk that are used as milk protein substitutes for pizza cheeses) and gums and resins that are used as binders to, for example, give chicken nuggets a certain consistency. The scope of the global food marketplace is evident on the Web site of the Institute of Food Technologists. There, for the last six years, the Food Technology Buyer’s Guide has offered places to buy ingredients from around the world. 1 2 Next Page » Andrew Martin contributed reporting. More Articles in Business »DOWNERS GROVE, Ill.  In a glassed-off area in the headquarters of Sara Lee, a handful of specialists study computer screens and flat-screen televisions beaming the latest weather reports and commodity prices. They are sourcing ingredients from all over the world to make Sara Lee’s assortment of breads, deli meats and microwaveable desserts. Skip to next paragraph Illustration by The New York Times Multimedia Graphic A Multinational Loaf Peter Wynn Thompson for The New York Times It is our responsibility to make sure what we are feeding people is safe, said David L. Brown, Sara Lees vice president for procurement. The lowering of trade barriers more than a decade ago has pushed food companies to scour the globe for more exotic  or the cheapest  ingredients to compete in a more global marketplace, not unlike automakers shipping in parts from all over. But with America’s relatively permissible food-import rules and weak inspection regime, is the trend to assemble food from so many far-flung locations heightening the risks of contamination? “Once ingredients are incorporated into processed foods, it is hard to check whether they come from overseas or to verify if there are any unsafe contaminants in the products,” said Michael F. Jacobson, executive director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest, a Washington lobby group. “This is increasing the chances that people will get unsafe food.” The concerns of Mr. Jacobson and some in Congress are being stoked by the recent scandal involving pet food contaminated with an industrial chemical called melamine and imported from China, which has resulted in thousands of pets being sickened or killed. Food industry executives say they understand the risks of foreign sourcing and are taking pains to mitigate them. “Ingredients from overseas are not the issue,” said Robert Earl, senior director of nutrition policy at the Grocery Manufacturers of America, a trade group that represents many of the largest food processors. “The problem comes from incorrect practices from manufacturers that happen to be in another country.” David L. Brown, Sara Lee’s vice president for procurement, said consumers should not be concerned. “We are going to do our homework,” he said, including vetting foreign factories and in some cases investing money to improve food-safety standards. “It is our responsibility to make sure what we are feeding people is safe. But the more variables you enter into, the more risk you have naturally. It is all about how you address those unknowns.” The controls in place to ensure that foreign-sourced ingredients are safe “are evolving as the world changes,” Mr. Brown said. Some people say they still have a long way to go. In the weeks since the pet food controversy broke, federal investigators have also discovered toxic toothpaste exported from China and melamine-laced ingredients for fish feed manufactured in Toledo, Ohio. The discoveries have prompted new calls by Congress to overhaul responsibility for America’s food-safety system, which is currently shared by the Food and Drug Administration, the Department of Agriculture and a grab bag of other agencies. Critics say the F.D.A., which bears the bulk of the food-safety load, is woefully underfinanced and understaffed, and they note that fewer than 1 percent of imported food shipments undergo laboratory analysis. The number of food inspectors has decreased in the last five years. The F.D.A. is exploring ways to use risk analysis to try to pinpoint food shipments that might pose hazards, The Wall Street Journal reported this week. Under the approach, countries and private companies might be required to provide the F.D.A. with more information about imported food. The rise in imported ingredients has been accompanied by an explosion in imported food generally: food imports more than doubled in the last decade, to $79.9 billion, according to the United States International Trade Commission. Consumers can only guess from reading most labels that individual food products today contain ingredients from a handful of continents. Despite having the world’s most expansive and efficient agricultural sector, America is hardly the only place where large food processors like Sara Lee, Kraft and General Mills have looked to acquire the dozens of ingredients that make up their microwaveable meals, processed cheeses, baked snack foods and breakfast cereals. What trade commission figures show is that ingredients are streaming in from more than 100 countries, including China, India, the Philippines and countries in sub-Saharan Africa. In some cases, consumer demand for more ethnic foods in the United States is pushing companies to import harder-to-find foods from exotic locales, but in other cases the phenomenon is simply a function of the way modern processed foods are assembled. The imported ingredients include caseins and caseinates (enzymes found in milk that are used as milk protein substitutes for pizza cheeses) and gums and resins that are used as binders to, for example, give chicken nuggets a certain consistency. The scope of the global food marketplace is evident on the Web site of the Institute of Food Technologists. There, for the last six years, the Food Technology Buyer’s Guide has offered places to buy ingredients from around the world. 1 2 Next Page » Andrew Martin contributed reporting.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/30/business/30sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Plans to Cut Work Force by 3%<date>Published: January 30, 2007</date><text>CHICAGO, Jan. 29 (Reuters)  The Sara Lee Corporation said on Monday that it planned to cut nearly 1,700 jobs, or about 3 percent of its work force, in its latest effort to reduce costs. It said it would close a pork plant and spice plant in Mississippi, eliminating 1,200 jobs as it moves those product lines to outside suppliers. Sara Lee separately announced 489 job cuts companywide after the latest review of its business. The cuts are part of a revamping to focus on coffee, tea, baked goods and deli meats in the United States and household products in Europe. In filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission, the company said it would record a pretax charge of $40 million related to the 489 layoffs and a $34 million charge for impairment of good will in the North American retail meats business. More Articles in Business »CHICAGO, Jan. 29 (Reuters)  The Sara Lee Corporation said on Monday that it planned to cut nearly 1,700 jobs, or about 3 percent of its work force, in its latest effort to reduce costs. It said it would close a pork plant and spice plant in Mississippi, eliminating 1,200 jobs as it moves those product lines to outside suppliers. Sara Lee separately announced 489 job cuts companywide after the latest review of its business. The cuts are part of a revamping to focus on coffee, tea, baked goods and deli meats in the United States and household products in Europe. In filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission, the company said it would record a pretax charge of $40 million related to the 489 layoffs and a $34 million charge for impairment of good will in the North American retail meats business.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/15/business/15underwear.html?ref=saraleecorporation">No Sex and No Models (What Kind of Bra Ad Is This?)<date>Published: July 15, 2006</date><text>Will bras sell without sexy ads? Victorias Secret and its lineup of curvaceous models with names like Gisele and Heidi may not think so. But Sara Lee Branded Apparel, the maker of Playtex, Bali and Hanes, is testing a new strategy: leave the supermodels out of the advertisements. Starting this month, the company will promote its Barely There brand with a national campaign that shows no slinky body parts and no stiletto heels. Instead, the campaign is part sales pitch, part public service announcement. It tries to illustrate the practical problems women encounter with their underwear, like bumps, ripples and the unintended transparency that the wrong bra can produce under clothing. The ads are meant to take the place of a gimlet-eyed girlfriend  someone who will matter-of-factly tell you that your strap is showing, or that a lacy bra has no place under a shirt made of thin fabric. It is a departure for Barely There, which in the past has subscribed to the standard formula of womens underwear advertising. It was pretty consistent with the market, with high-end fashion models, said Tolli Love, vice president for marketing at Barely There. But the new campaign, she said, is definitely from the female perspective. Men are attracted to that type of advertising, Ms. Love said of the previous campaign. I think theres a perception that with intimate apparel, sex sells, and then women, too, are unfairly grouped into that category. The Barely There print ads look like a before-and-after picture, with two bras side by side that illustrate a result of an ill-chosen bra. On the left is a bra that is bumpy or misshapen (labeled There). On the right, a bra with a monochromatic background (Barely There.) The There bras are adorned with objects that signify bumps, ridges and other bra-related problems. (The objects the Martin Agency of Richmond, Va., dreamed up include headlights, Jiffy Pop, pine cones and pointy pink drink umbrellas.) The ads will appear in the August issues of fashion and consumer magazines like Allure, Cosmopolitan, Essence, InStyle and Real Simple, and on billboards in Times Square and in Los Angeles. Barely There is hoping to occupy a vacant corner of underwear advertising: practicality, which is usually left out of both the ads and the product. After all, this is an industry that created the corset, a garment that could cinch a narrow waist, as Scarlett OHara famously demanded, down to 18 and a half inches. More recently, the industry invented the once-ubiquitous thong, a piece of underwear that many wearers say is every bit as uncomfortable as its appearance suggests. But lately, attention has been lavished on the fact that millions of hapless American women are wearing ill-fitting bras. (By some estimates, as many as 85 percent of the female population.) So more marketers are shying away from ads with over-the-top sexiness in favor of a more educational approach. There are indications that the industry is looking beyond sexy ads. Even Victorias Secret created an ad in 2004 that starred Bob Dylan (though he was in the company of several supermodels). And brands that are famous for their flesh quotient have experimented with more creative alternatives. Wonderbra, mostly known for in-your-face ads showing smiling models from the chest up and not much else, is one: the brand introduced a crop of ads in Britain last year that took an understated, sly approach, depicting a restaurant full of men staring straight ahead, at a woman who is not in the picture. Another Wonderbra ad that ran in France showed only a line of text reading ABRACADAbra atop nothing but white space. But for decades, selling lingerie without buxom models has been practically unthinkable. Maidenform first shocked consumers at the end of World War II with a scandalously revealing ad campaign, depicting women cavorting in a state of toplessness except for their Maidenform bras. Getting maximum publicity from underwear ads is best achieved with nearly naked models. In the early 90s, the unknown-at-the-time rapper Mark Wahlberg dropped his pants for a Calvin Klein ad in Times Square, turning himself into an international celebrity. The original Victorias Secret TV fashion show in 2001 garnered enormous ratings on ABC, followed by more than 900 complaints to the Federal Communications Commission from groups like the Concerned Women for America. Even the planners of the Barely There campaign defend that other, more aspirational type of ad, even if it is primarily done by men, said Rob Schapiro, the creative director and senior vice president of the Martin Agency. (Mr. Schapiro was the only male member of the creative team.) Victorias Secret has had success owning sexy, and I think theres a certain segment of the population that wants a sexier bra, Mr. Schapiro said. But, he added, we realized that a large segment of the population is concerned about how she looks in her bra while actually wearing clothing. More Articles in Business »Will bras sell without sexy ads? Victorias Secret and its lineup of curvaceous models with names like Gisele and Heidi may not think so. But Sara Lee Branded Apparel, the maker of Playtex, Bali and Hanes, is testing a new strategy: leave the supermodels out of the advertisements. Starting this month, the company will promote its Barely There brand with a national campaign that shows no slinky body parts and no stiletto heels. Instead, the campaign is part sales pitch, part public service announcement. It tries to illustrate the practical problems women encounter with their underwear, like bumps, ripples and the unintended transparency that the wrong bra can produce under clothing. The ads are meant to take the place of a gimlet-eyed girlfriend  someone who will matter-of-factly tell you that your strap is showing, or that a lacy bra has no place under a shirt made of thin fabric. It is a departure for Barely There, which in the past has subscribed to the standard formula of womens underwear advertising. It was pretty consistent with the market, with high-end fashion models, said Tolli Love, vice president for marketing at Barely There. But the new campaign, she said, is definitely from the female perspective. Men are attracted to that type of advertising, Ms. Love said of the previous campaign. I think theres a perception that with intimate apparel, sex sells, and then women, too, are unfairly grouped into that category. The Barely There print ads look like a before-and-after picture, with two bras side by side that illustrate a result of an ill-chosen bra. On the left is a bra that is bumpy or misshapen (labeled There). On the right, a bra with a monochromatic background (Barely There.) The There bras are adorned with objects that signify bumps, ridges and other bra-related problems. (The objects the Martin Agency of Richmond, Va., dreamed up include headlights, Jiffy Pop, pine cones and pointy pink drink umbrellas.) The ads will appear in the August issues of fashion and consumer magazines like Allure, Cosmopolitan, Essence, InStyle and Real Simple, and on billboards in Times Square and in Los Angeles. Barely There is hoping to occupy a vacant corner of underwear advertising: practicality, which is usually left out of both the ads and the product. After all, this is an industry that created the corset, a garment that could cinch a narrow waist, as Scarlett OHara famously demanded, down to 18 and a half inches. More recently, the industry invented the once-ubiquitous thong, a piece of underwear that many wearers say is every bit as uncomfortable as its appearance suggests. But lately, attention has been lavished on the fact that millions of hapless American women are wearing ill-fitting bras. (By some estimates, as many as 85 percent of the female population.) So more marketers are shying away from ads with over-the-top sexiness in favor of a more educational approach. There are indications that the industry is looking beyond sexy ads. Even Victorias Secret created an ad in 2004 that starred Bob Dylan (though he was in the company of several supermodels). And brands that are famous for their flesh quotient have experimented with more creative alternatives. Wonderbra, mostly known for in-your-face ads showing smiling models from the chest up and not much else, is one: the brand introduced a crop of ads in Britain last year that took an understated, sly approach, depicting a restaurant full of men staring straight ahead, at a woman who is not in the picture. Another Wonderbra ad that ran in France showed only a line of text reading ABRACADAbra atop nothing but white space. But for decades, selling lingerie without buxom models has been practically unthinkable. Maidenform first shocked consumers at the end of World War II with a scandalously revealing ad campaign, depicting women cavorting in a state of toplessness except for their Maidenform bras. Getting maximum publicity from underwear ads is best achieved with nearly naked models. In the early 90s, the unknown-at-the-time rapper Mark Wahlberg dropped his pants for a Calvin Klein ad in Times Square, turning himself into an international celebrity. The original Victorias Secret TV fashion show in 2001 garnered enormous ratings on ABC, followed by more than 900 complaints to the Federal Communications Commission from groups like the Concerned Women for America. Even the planners of the Barely There campaign defend that other, more aspirational type of ad, even if it is primarily done by men, said Rob Schapiro, the creative director and senior vice president of the Martin Agency. (Mr. Schapiro was the only male member of the creative team.) Victorias Secret has had success owning sexy, and I think theres a certain segment of the population that wants a sexier bra, Mr. Schapiro said. But, he added, we realized that a large segment of the population is concerned about how she looks in her bra while actually wearing clothing.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/25/business/25sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Reports on Spinoff Plan<date>Published: May 25, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News The Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that it expected to complete the spinoff of its Hanes, Playtex and Wonderbra apparel unit by September as it shed assets to focus on faster-growing businesses. The unit, Hanesbrands, had $4.7 billion in sales in fiscal 2005. The distribution ratio for the shares will be determined shortly before the transaction takes place, Sara Lee said. The company, which is based in Chicago, said it would not own any Hanesbrands shares after the spinoff. Sara Lee is disposing of businesses to focus on improving food, beverage and household products units, which sell products that include Kiwi shoe polish and Hillshire Farm deli meats. The company agreed this month to sell its British clothing division and has sold its European apparel units. More Articles in Business »By Bloomberg News The Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that it expected to complete the spinoff of its Hanes, Playtex and Wonderbra apparel unit by September as it shed assets to focus on faster-growing businesses. The unit, Hanesbrands, had $4.7 billion in sales in fiscal 2005. The distribution ratio for the shares will be determined shortly before the transaction takes place, Sara Lee said. The company, which is based in Chicago, said it would not own any Hanesbrands shares after the spinoff. Sara Lee is disposing of businesses to focus on improving food, beverage and household products units, which sell products that include Kiwi shoe polish and Hillshire Farm deli meats. The company agreed this month to sell its British clothing division and has sold its European apparel units.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/15/business/worldbusiness/15sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Selling Its European Apparel Unit<date>Published: November 15, 2005</date><text>CHICAGO, Nov. 14 (AP) - The Sara Lee Corporation said on Monday that it was selling its European clothing unit to an affiliate of the Sun Capital Partners investment firm for more than $117 million as part of a corporate overhaul. Sara Lee said it would be paid 100 million euros ($117.2 million) cash plus potential contingency payments based on future performance. The clothing unit consists of marketing rights for such Sara Lee-owned brands as Dim, Playtex, Wonderbra, Abanderado, Nur Die and Unno in France, Germany, Italy, Spain and Britain and throughout Eastern Europe. The brands generated almost $1.2 billion in sales in fiscal 2005. Sara Lee signaled its intent to get out of the apparel business when it began the overhaul early this year to focus on its food, beverage and household and body-care operations. It retains Playtex and Wonderbra as part of its United States apparel business. A spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, said the company still intended to spin off the United States unit some time from June to September 2006. Sara Lee is based in Chicago, and Sun Capital Partners is based in Boca Raton, Fla. More Articles in Business &gt;CHICAGO, Nov. 14 (AP) - The Sara Lee Corporation said on Monday that it was selling its European clothing unit to an affiliate of the Sun Capital Partners investment firm for more than $117 million as part of a corporate overhaul. Sara Lee said it would be paid 100 million euros ($117.2 million) cash plus potential contingency payments based on future performance. The clothing unit consists of marketing rights for such Sara Lee-owned brands as Dim, Playtex, Wonderbra, Abanderado, Nur Die and Unno in France, Germany, Italy, Spain and Britain and throughout Eastern Europe. The brands generated almost $1.2 billion in sales in fiscal 2005. Sara Lee signaled its intent to get out of the apparel business when it began the overhaul early this year to focus on its food, beverage and household and body-care operations. It retains Playtex and Wonderbra as part of its United States apparel business. A spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, said the company still intended to spin off the United States unit some time from June to September 2006. Sara Lee is based in Chicago, and Sun Capital Partners is based in Boca Raton, Fla.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2D71630F937A35756C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE APPAREL UNIT WILL CUT 350 JOBS<date>Published: May 4, 2005</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation's apparel division said yesterday that it would offer incentives to cut about 350 positions as it prepares to be spun off as an independent company. All 2,300 managerial, professional and support workers in the division, based in Winston-Salem, N.C., will be eligible for the packages, which include health care, salary and continuing education, a spokeswoman, Peggy Carter, said. Employees in the division's manufacturing, distribution and retail stores will not be affected. Sara Lee, which is based in Chicago, plans to spin off the division, which includes Champion sportswear and the Bali, Playtex and L'eggs brands, between March and July of 2006.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/27/business/businessspecial3/27sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee's Earnings Fall<date>Published: April 27, 2005</date><text>HICAGO, April 26 (Reuters) - The Sara Lee Corporation reported sharply lower quarterly earnings on Tuesday, weighed down by sluggish sales in Europe and higher prices for meat, coffee and cotton. Net income for the fiscal third quarter, which ended April 2, fell to $189 million, or 24 cents a share, from $376 million, or 47 cents per share, a year earlier. Sales rose 1 percent to $4.8 billion, helped by price increases and a weak dollar. Advertisement</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/06/business/yourmoney/06refresh.html?ref=saraleecorporation">From Sara Lee to Charities<date>Published: March 6, 2005</date><text>uring John H. Bryan's quarter-century as chairman and chief executive of the Sara Lee Corporation, he was eager to reach everyone through the company's slogan, "Nobody doesn't like Sara Lee." While he ran the company, its annual revenue rose to about $20 billion, from $2.5 billion. He retired in 2000. But now, as a volunteer fund-raiser in Chicago, he is much more selective in making sales pitches. Recently, Mr. Bryan solicited private donations totaling $225 million toward building Millennium Park, a 24½-acre arts showplace developed on a former rail yard and parking lot at the edge of Lake Michigan. It opened in July. The park, which also took about $250 million in public funds to complete, includes a 1,500-seat theater, an ice-skating rink and sculptures, one weighing 110 tons. Operating from an office on the 14th floor of the NBC Tower on the Chicago River, Mr. Bryan, who is 68, says 103 Chicagoans gave at least $1 million, the minimum to have their names etched in stone on the base of the park's Millennium Monument. He convinced a handful of benefactors to give much more. "We chose nine people to donate gifts between $5 million and $15 million," he said. Those nine donors "got things named for them," he said. "The Pritzker Pavilion, Wrigley Square and the like." He added that his long tenure at Sara Lee had helped him develop contacts among Chicago's elite. They are "all contemporaries of mine," he said. As chairman of the Art Institute of Chicago, he has moved on to a new project. He is helping to raising $300 million for a new wing of the museum. "We're about halfway there," he said. And he is still active in the corporate world, serving as a director of BP, General Motors and Goldman Sachs. He says he typically rises at 5:30 a.m. and commutes to his office by chauffeur-driven car from his 150-acre farm in Lake Bluff, Ill. - a distance of about 30 miles. He occasionally is host for arts and crafts festivals at the farm. "It's a different kind of work," he said of fund-raising. "We're building forums that will define Chicago to the world. With government money alone, you could never justify it." Robert Johnson</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/24/business/media/24adco.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Hanes Revives a Successful Campaign From the 90's<date>Published: February 24, 2005</date><text>OR those who have been waiting for Hanes to revive "Just wait'll we get our Hanes on you," the wait is over - kinda sorta. In a campaign scheduled to begin on Monday, which is being billed as the largest in years for the Hanes apparel brand, the "Just wait'll" theme, so successful in the 1990's, returns with a bit of tailoring as "Look who we've got our Hanes on now." Also being revived is the idea of using a roster of celebrities to sell Hanes underwear, sleepwear, socks and other clothing, rather than the single-star approach the brand has recently taken in featuring Michael Jordan. Mr. Jordan remains, joined initially by Damon Wayans, Matthew Perry and Marisa Tomei, making the campaign perhaps the first to present a winner of an Academy Award for best supporting actress cavorting in her scanties. The yearlong television, print and online campaign, which has a budget estimated at more than $50 million, is being created by the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va., owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies. The campaign is an example of efforts by major marketers to capitalize on nostalgia for vintage slogans, themes, characters, commercials and the like. While such mining of the past is popular, the efforts for those brands - including Budweiser, Chicken of the Sea, Mr. Clean and Rheingold, as well as Hanes - also reflect a need to address today's consumers in a more contemporary fashion. In other words, even a campaign like "Just wait'll," which ran from 1992-99, could do with some updating. Brands "have to keep themselves fresh with consumers to be relevant," said Sidney Falken, who has the title of Hanes brand champion at Sara Lee Branded Apparel in Winston-Salem, N.C., a division of the Sara Lee Corporation. Because "consumers know this brand really well," Ms. Falken said, the idea of using celebrities they may not expect to see endorsing Hanes is meant to convey that the Hanes name can be found on apparel that is more stylish, colorful and comfortable than they may expect. In addition to the four stars who will appear in the TV commercials that will start on Monday, Hanes and Martin are considering additional celebrities to join them in print advertisements that are to begin in July. Selecting the stars has been "an exhaustive process," said Rob Schapiro, senior vice president and creative director at Martin, because of the need to find "people we liked, who have their own sense of style, who worked with the brand and who worked with our consumers." Mr. Wayans, in his commercials, is shown shaving his head, "which is something he does every day," Mr. Schapiro said, and kidding around in front of a bathroom mirror. Ms. Tomei is at home alone, dancing and trying on clothes. Mr. Jordan and Mr. Perry play pool together, trading shots and quips as if in scenes from a Hollywood buddy comedy. David Robertson, brand communications director for Hanes at the apparel division, said that because the target market is broad, primarily men and women ages 18 to 49, the commercials will run in a variety of programs, including "Dateline NBC," "E.R.," "Good Morning America," "Law &amp; Order," "Saturday Night Live" and "Without a Trace." In the "Just wait'll" campaign, Hanes was one of the first major marketers to present several stars, rather than one person. The lineup in the 90's included, in addition to Mr. Jordan, then-familiar faces like Carol Alt, Boomer Esiason, Steve Largent, Joe Montana and Phylicia Rashad. Using an array of celebrities can help protect a company if one of its endorsers gets into trouble. For instance, while T-Mobile, part of Deutsche Telekom, may be embarrassed because personal information from the Sidekick hand-held communicator belonging to one of its stars, Paris Hilton, turned up on the Internet, she is only one of more than a dozen celebrities featured in Sidekick commercials, created by Publicis in the West in Seattle, part of the Publicis Worldwide division of the Publicis Groupe. (A spokesman for T-Mobile in Bellevue, Wash., Peter Dobrow, said yesterday that the Sidekick campaign "will run its course as is.") The campaign for Hanes, the largest Sara Lee brand, is scheduled to start two weeks after Sara Lee announced that it would spin off its branded-apparel division and other units in 12 to 18 months, to concentrate on operations like food, beverages and household products. The Sara Lee plans call for the spinoff, which will sell brands including Bali, Champion, Hanes, Just My Size, L'Eggs, Playtex and Wonderbra, to form a stand-alone, publicly traded company, said Peggy Carter, a spokeswoman at the apparel division, which would rank around 380th on the Fortune 500, based on 2003 revenue. The timing of the spinoff and the campaign are coincidental, she said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/11/business/11sara.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Reorganizing at Sara Lee Includes a New Chief<date>Published: February 11, 2005</date><text>fter decades of being a diversified conglomerate, the Sara Lee Corporation has concluded that hot dogs and underwear do not belong under the same roof. In a broad reorganization, Sara Lee named a new chief executive and announced plans to divest four businesses that together account for 40 percent of the company's revenue. C. Steven McMillan, who also announced that he was stepping down as chief executive, said Sara Lee would spin off its $4.5 billion apparel business, its $1.1 billion European packaged meat division, American coffee brands like Hills Bros. and Chock full o' Nuts, and a direct-sales unit for cosmetics and household products. The apparel unit, consisting of well-known brands like Hanes, Champion and Playtex, is Sara Lee's largest business and big enough to be a Fortune 500 company on its own. The division is also responsible for making leg wear under a license with the Donna Karan Company. Mr. McMillan, who will step down as chief executive, said a public offering for the apparel business is the most likely outcome, but he left open the possibility of a sale to another company. "It's highly possible that someone will come in and say we want to buy it," Mr. McMillan said. "But they would have to pay a premium to cover the taxes that shareholders wouldn't incur from a public offering." Brenda C. Barnes, a former PepsiCo executive, will succeed Mr. McMillan, who will remain as chairman through October. Hired by Sara Lee last May to be the company's president and chief operating officer, Ms. Barnes becomes one of eight women to head a Fortune 500 company. She is on the board of The New York Times Company. The extensive divestments are part of Sara Lee's gradual evolution from a company with a diverse array of products to a streamlined food operation. Sara Lee, which was known as Consolidated Foods until 1985, has owned brands as diverse as Piggly Wiggly supermarkets, Electrolux vacuum cleaners and Drum tobacco. The company sold the Coach brand of leather goods four years ago and phased out dozens of its bakery brands over the last two years to better concentrate on its three strongest brands. Mr. McMillan said the company derived little benefit from having both a food business and an apparel unit. "When you're dealing with retailers like Wal-Mart, the people who deal with the food side and the apparel side are totally different," he said. "For a while this was a company that bought anything they thought they could make money in," said Eric J. Larson, an analyst at Piper Jaffray, who has been following Sara Lee since the mid-1980's. "This is the final step to get this company truly focused." After the planned sales and spinoffs, Sara Lee will be left with dozens of bakery, packaged meat and coffee brands that are sold in American supermarkets, as well as a food service division that supplies restaurants and institutions. All of these businesses, now scattered in several cities, will be centralized in Chicago. In Europe, Sara Lee will continue to sell bakery and beverage products, as well as household items like Sanex soaps and Kiwi shoe polish. In a Web conference with financial analysts yesterday, Ms. Barnes said these moves were part of an important effort to make Sara Lee more centralized and cost-efficient. The company's many units have been operating on different technology systems and in different offices. Mr. McMillan said, "In many ways, we were all off in our silos." Later this year, Sara Lee will hire a chief information officer and a chief procurement officer. The company also plans to spend the next two years establishing a companywide supply chain and financial software system from SAP. The chief procurement officer will be responsible for heading a centralized purchasing initiative designed to gain better prices from suppliers. In announcing Ms. Barnes as his successor, Mr. McMillan, 60, portrayed the change as part of a planned transition. But some analysts said his departure after only four years in the job suggested that Sara Lee's board was less than happy with his tenure. While Mr. McMillan consolidated some manufacturing operations and centralized the meat business, he was also responsible for several acquisitions considered failures by analysts. "He wasn't moving fast enough and in a bold enough manner," said Eric Katzman, an analyst at Deutsche Bank. Sara Lee said yesterday's moves would not affect the company's earnings expectations of $1.46 to $1.56 a share for 2005. Theo de Kool, the chief financial officer, said a smaller Sara Lee would be much more profitable. The company hopes that in five years it will have the same level of operating income as today, which translates to an annual 6.5 percent a year growth in profits. Sara Lee's stock was up 4.1 percent, to $23.92, in trading yesterday.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/01/business/media/01adco.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Campaign Offers Alternative to the Low-Carb Craze<date>Published: February 1, 2005</date><text>READ, long under attack, is finally striking back. The goal of a campaign that begins today in two East Coast markets and online (grainpower.org) is to counteract the onslaughts against bread from diet books and regimens that denigrate carbohydrates. The campaign is sponsored by a new organization, the Grain Foods Foundation, with 90 members that include marketers from the baking and milling industries like Cargill, ConAgra, Flowers Industries, General Mills, Interstate Bakeries and Sara Lee, along with trade associations and suppliers. "We'd had enough," said Paul Abenante, president and chief executive of the American Bakers Association in Washington, a foundation member. "We need to stand up for ourselves. Doing nothing is not an option." The campaign - with the theme "Bread. It's essential" - is created by Mullen in Wenham, Mass., part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, which has been developing it for more than a year. The posters and billboards, to appear initially in New York and Washington, are in addition to campaigns from several companies for new bread and cereal products with whole-grain recipes. The campaign is the most recent voice to be raised in the increasingly cacophonous public debate over diet and health, which is intensifying as questions arise over the growing obesity among Americans, especially children. "The noise level is extraordinary," said Marion Nestle, a professor of nutrition at New York University. "I expect health claims from every food in the supermarket." The campaign also comes as the federal government readies a revised version of the "food pyramid" to reflect new dietary guidelines, issued Jan. 12, that call for measures like eating more whole grains. "To the extent that the campaign emphasizes the benefit of eating whole grains in bread, it's a public service," said Dean Ornish, president of the Preventive Medicine Research Institute in Sausalito, Calif., "because whole grains are actually beneficial." But "to the extent the campaign is promoting all breads," said Dr. Ornish, who is also a clinical professor of medicine at the University of California, San Francisco, "it will confuse people" because "eating too many simple carbohydrates, white flour, refined grains, may increase health risks like diabetes and obesity." While doctors and dieticians praise carbohydrates as energy sources, refined carbohydrates like white bread can lead to weight gain because they are not filling. Some ads promote whole grains, like one that declares, "Whole-grain foods help control hunger." Others promote high-fiber diets and the folic acid found in enriched grain foods. But other ads are more general, centered on grains or carbohydrates. One, for instance, says, "A balanced diet that includes grains helps to prevent cataracts." Another declares, "Your brain needs carbohydrates to function properly." And all the ads end the same way: "Bread is delicious. Filled with healthy grains. And makes life better. Bread. It's essential." Judi Adams, president of the foundation, based in Ridgeway, Colo., agreed that "it is very, very important we get people to eat more whole grains, no question." She also said that there were "a lot of whole-grain products out there now that didn't used to be out there" because "we know people are not eating enough whole grains." But "everyone has their own taste preference," Ms. Adams said, "and it's important to get enriched grain, too," like breads fortified with folic acid to reduce birth defects. Mr. Abenante said: "There's no magic bullet. The issue is eating sensibly, eating in a balanced way, exercising." The campaign is not intended to promote refined grains at the expense of whole grains, he added, because it showcases products like "variety breads, whole grains, whole wheat" as well as conventional breads. Michael Jacobson, executive director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest in Washington, a longtime critic of marketing by the processed-food industry, said the ads for whole grains were excellent because "those are the kinds of foods people should be eating more of." "But a general pitch for carbohydrates is painting with too broad a brush because it's trying to bring white bread under the good news umbrella," he said. "I fear the advertising will not be encouraging people to eat the best kind of grains." Mr. Jacobson also offered a wry assessment of the campaign's theme: "I didn't know bread was 'essential.' A billion people in China must be horribly deprived." Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DB163BF935A15752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE LOWERS EARNINGS OUTLOOK FOR 2005<date>Published: January 26, 2005</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation, the food and apparel maker, lowered its 2005 earnings forecast yesterday and announced plans to sell its European clothing business and make other changes in slow-growing units to cut costs. Sluggish sales in Europe and higher expenses for materials such as pork and cotton led Sara Lee to trim 15 cents a share from its fiscal 2005 profit forecast. The company, based in Chicago, also reported second-quarter results and said its net income rose 4.5 percent, to $326 million, led by gains in its apparel and bread businesses. Sales rose 3.6 percent, to $5.2 billion. Sara Lee's stock fell $2.05, to $22.90 a share.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/14/business/media/14adco.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Kiwi Shoe Polish Aims to Escape Invisibility<date>Published: December 14, 2004</date><text>AN an irreverent campaign help a venerable product named after a flightless bird fly off the shelves? That is the ambitious goal of the campaign now under way for Kiwi, the line of shoe care products that dates to 1906. Kiwi is sold in almost 180 countries by the Sara Lee Corporation, the packaged-goods giant that also markets brands like Ball Park, Champion, Jimmy Dean and Hanes. After several years of little or no marketing support for Kiwi, Sara Lee is running print advertisements in a variety of national magazines. The ads, created by the Richards Group in Dallas, use sassy humor to try to stimulate demand for the brand. With the Kiwi campaign, which carries the theme "Look Sharp," Sara Lee joins a growing list of companies - among them Brown-Forman, Coca-Cola, Colgate-Palmolive, PepsiCo and Unilever - that are increasing marketing budgets for aging or neglected brands. The Kiwi ads are printed in bright red, matching the color in the background of the brand's logo, and show a can of Kiwi black shoe paste under snappy headlines. The sardonic tone is reminiscent of campaigns for Cheez-It crackers ("Get your own box") and Dodge ("Grab life by the horns"). The ads intend to persuade consumers, mostly male, to use the Kiwi shoe polish they already have in their homes. That, of course, would lead to more purchases of Kiwi shoe polish, shoe paste and shoe sponges. The strategy is a familiar one for brands that, like Kiwi, dominate their product categories. Remember the longtime theme for Campbell's soup, "Reach for the Campbell's, it's right on your shelf"? Kiwi is the best-selling shoe care brand in the world and has about 65 percent of that market in the United States, Bob Clark, marketing director for shoe care at the Sara Lee household and body care division in Exton, Pa., estimated. But such familiarity breeds, if not contempt, then perhaps indifference, particularly in prosaic product categories like shoe care. That is especially true when it costs so much to buy commercial time and advertising space. Decades ago, there were campaigns galore for ordinary products like hair tonic, gravy, watch bands and - yes - shoe polish, like the jingle for Esquire Boot Polish that promised it "gives your shoes that looking-glass shine." (Esquire, by the way, was acquired by Sara Lee years ago and discontinued.) "Some people say it's a bygone product for a bygone era," said Rob VanGorden, a principal at Richards, citing the trend toward dressing more casually. But "Kiwi dominates the category, has positive associations and a rich heritage," he said. "Although you can find Kiwi in just about every pantry, people only buy Kiwi when they run out," he added. "The real issue is, how do we get them to run out of polish more often?" Mr. Clark said: "When we spoke to consumers, they said they knew all about taking care of their shoes but were not doing it as much as they used to, even though they're taking care of all other kinds of grooming like their hair. It was not that they don't want to do it, it's just not top of mind." The result was the print campaign, with a budget estimated at more than $2 million, which is appearing in 18 magazines with a predominantly or primarily male readership. The jocular approach is meant to slyly nudge men to consider what shape their shoes are in, through irreverent headlines like these: "The difference between 'Here's my number' and 'Here's my real number.' " "The distressed look only works for jeans." "Dull shoes counteract polished résumés." "Hey. A topical cream that really does make you more attractive." "Men, your shoes should be polished regularly. Also, your sleeve is not a napkin." "Raise your chance of dating a supermodel from 0 to 0.001!" "Unpolished shoes are the open fly of footwear." Richards undertook what Mr. VanGorden called a "state of the shoes" exploration, going to bookstores, coffee shops and workplaces, talking to people about their shoes. The research showed that "most men are embarrassed," he said, making remarks like "I was going to polish them tonight" and "Don't take my picture." "The benefits of polishing your shoes are well known," Mr. VanGorden said, noting that even light users of polish say that having shined shoes is good. "The objective is increasing usage frequency that drives purchase, which is pretty simple, but sometimes simple ideas are what are needed." Richards is creating the campaign for Sara Lee on a project basis. The Kiwi agency of record remains Grey Worldwide in New York, part of the Grey Global Group. The Kiwi brand executives called Richards, Mr. VanGorden recalled, after reading an article in the trade publication Brandweek about Chick-fil-A, a Richards client along with brands like Corona, Home Depot and Motel 6. Chick-fil-A, the fast-food chain, is "an under-$10 million client," Mr. VanGorden said, but the Kiwi executives said they thought the media spending was $50 million to $100 million, based on the ubiquity and popularity of the campaign, which presents cows asking consumers to "Save a cow, eat more chicken." The Kiwi campaign is running in magazines like Black Enterprise, Car and Driver, Cargo, Ebony, Esquire, Men's Fitness, National Geographic, Newsweek and Popular Science. There are also plans to create versions of the campaign for ad space in trains and on elevators as well as to put it up on a Web site. Kiwi and Richards would like "to reach men when they're in places they can notice the poor state of their shoes," Mr. VanGorden said, like bars, gyms, health clubs, restrooms and taxicabs.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/11/business/company-news-sara-lee-apparel-to-close-5-plants-and-cut-3825-jobs.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE APPAREL TO CLOSE 5 PLANTS AND CUT 3,825 JOBS<date>Published: June 11, 2004</date><text>Sara Lee Branded Apparel, the makers of Wonderbra, Hanes and Playtex products, will shut five plants and lay off 3,825 workers worldwide by year's end, the company announced yesterday. The job cuts and closings come as the company consolidates its production of intimates, sportswear and underwear, Sara Lee said. Sara Lee will close plants in Puerto Rico and Honduras and three others in Mexico. The company will also shut down part of a plant in Asheboro, N.C., that produces underwear and eliminate 150 jobs at its headquarters in Winston-Salem, where the company has about 5,650 employees. The Asheboro plant will lose 200 jobs. Sara Lee Branded Apparel is one of three business units of the Sara Lee Corporation. The company employs more than 55,000 people worldwide.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/09/business/openers-suits-nobody-doesn-t-like-corporate-suites.html?ref=saraleecorporation">OPENERS: SUITS; NOBODY DOESN'T LIKE CORPORATE SUITES<date>Published: May 09, 2004</date><text>Anyone who's spent time around teenagers can figure why Brenda C. Barnes is ending her six-year stint as a stay-at-home mom to become the president of the Sara Lee Corporation: she probably needs a rest.Ms. Barnes set business tongues achatter in 1997, when she quit as chief executive of Pepsi-Cola North America to spend more time with her three children. Her move rekindled debate about whether motherhood and a career are mutually exclusive. Ms. Barnes, who spent 22 years at PepsiCo, did not retire completely. She serves on several boards, including that of The New York Times Company, and was interim president of Starwood Hotels and Resorts.All of her children will be in high school this fall, and thus no longer likely to consider it a boon to have Mom underfoot all the time.Ms. Barnes, who will start at Sara Lee in July, was not reachable last week. But Julie Ketay, a Sara Lee spokeswoman, says the company is trying to ease her transition.''We've already sent her home with some Champion backpacks for her kids,'' she said. ''Bribery will get you nowhere in business, but it can get you everywhere at home.'' Claudia H. Deutsch</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/03/business/media-business-advertising-designer-coffee-cup-time-while-keeping-your-taste.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING; Designer coffee, a cup at a time, while keeping your taste buds at home.<date>Published: March 03, 2004</date><text>COFFEE drinkers, get ready for $150 million or more worth of java jive, courtesy of the world's best-known sellers of coffee and coffee makers. The ambitious goals of their advertising and marketing campaigns: persuade millions of consumers who increasingly prefer to leave home for their coffee fixes to stay home -- and add another appliance to crowded kitchens.The appliance in question is a new kind of coffee maker, priced at $60 to $120, which is intended to brew a cup at a time in about a minute, using coffee in prepackaged packets called pods. The machines, with names like Home CafÃ©, Senseo and Tassimo, will compete against lower-priced automatic-drip devices as well as more expensive machines, typically imported, that specialize in espresso.The goal of the kaffeeklatsch, Madison Avenue style, is to persuade the fans of coffeehouses like Starbucks that they can brew high-quality beverages at home. That ''Wizard of Oz''-like loyalty to home should not be surprising: the coffee makers and pods are the brainchildren of the companies that are the largest sellers of coffees consumed at home -- the Procter &amp; Gamble Company, Kraft Foods and the Sara Lee Corporation -- along with appliance makers like Applica, which licenses the Black &amp; Decker brand; the Braun division of Gillette; the Krups division of Groupe SEB; Hamilton Beach/Proctor-Silex; Royal Philips Electronics; the Saeco International Group; and the Mr. Coffee division of Sunbeam Products.The Starbucks Coffee Company reported $4.1 billion in consolidated net revenue for fiscal 2003, which ended Sept. 28. That is money not spent on Procter brands like Folgers and Millstone; Kraft brands like Maxwell House, Carte Noire and Gevalia; or Sara Lee brands like Chase &amp; Sanborn, Chock full o'Nuts, Hills Brothers and Douwe Egberts. By joining with the appliance sellers, the coffee sellers hope to reverse the tide of coffee drinkers headed out the door to find their daily doses of joe.The number of consumers who say they drink coffee either regularly or occasionally rose to 166.6 million last year, from 161.2 million in 2002, according to the National Coffee Association. But the NPD Group reports that the average American drank 112.4 cups at home last year compared with 125.4 in 1999.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/23/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-sara-lee-discloses-ad-support-plans.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Sara Lee Discloses Ad Support Plans<date>Published: February 23, 2004</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation in Chicago, seeking to stimulate growth after disappointing results, is categorizing the level of advertising and marketing support that its brands should receive.At a presentation to analysts last week, Lee A. Chaden, executive vice president for global marketing and sales, divided the company's hundreds of brands into four categories. The top category is brands targeted for ''strategic investment,'' Mr. Chaden said, with current or potential sales of at least $500 million that can grow at least 10 percent a year. Those brands include the Ball Park, Hillshire Farm and Jimmy Dean lines of meats; Just My Size apparel; Sara Lee baked goods and cold cuts; and Senseo, a new single-serve in-home coffee system.The second category identified by Mr. Chaden consists of brands to ''support and grow,'' with current or potential sales of at least $100 million that can increase at least 3 percent a year. Those brands include Earth Grains baked goods and Hanes and Playtex apparel.The third category is for brands that Sara Lee will ''sustain,'' Mr. Chaden said, with flat to modest growth rates in regional markets. They include Kiwi shoe polish. The bottom category is for brands that Sara Lee will ''manage for cash,'' Mr. Chaden said. These brands, which will receive little or no marketing spending, include Endust spray polish and L'eggs and Hanes hosiery.Sara Lee spends about $1 billion a year on all marketing communications, Mr. Chaden said, and half that is devoted to traditional advertising like television commercials and print advertisements.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/06/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-accounts-272558.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Accounts<date>Published: February 06, 2004</date><text>Sara Lee Corp., Chicago, to the Los Angeles office of TBWA/Chiat/Day, part of the TBWA Worldwide division of the Omnicom Group, to handle the creative duties for its Jimmy Dean and Ball Park meat brands, which had been handled by Leo Burnett Worldwide, Chicago, part of the Publicis Groupe. Billings were estimated at $25 million to $40 million.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/02/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-sara-lee-consolidates-with-starcom-usa.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Sara Lee Consolidates With Starcom U.S.A.<date>Published: February 02, 2004</date><text>In another consolidation of a large media assignment, the Sara Lee Corporation in Chicago has named Starcom U.S.A. in Chicago, part of the Starcom MediaVest Group unit of the Publicis Groupe, to handle all media strategy, planning and buying duties on its United States accounts. Total annual spending for those assignments, which had been divided among Starcom and six other agencies, was estimated at $200 million.The agencies eliminated from the Sara Lee media roster are two units of the Interpublic Group of Companies, the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va., and the Winston-Salem, N.C., office of Mullen; the Chicago office of MPG, part of Havas; the Chicago office of OMD, part of the Omnicom Group; the Dallas office of Optimedia, part of the ZenithOptimedia division of Publicis; and Shahid &amp; Company in New York. Sara Lee brands include Ball Park Franks, Hanes and Playtex.The decision, made without a review, is part of an effort by Sara Lee to make its ad spending more efficient. Among other large marketers that have recently reassigned or are considering reassigning media accounts are AOL, American Express, Coca-Cola North America, Masterfoods U.S.A. and S.C. Johnson &amp; Son.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/13/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-sara-lee-changes-agency-for-deli-line.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Sara Lee Changes Agency for Deli Line<date>Published: August 13, 2003</date><text>Sara Lee Foods in Cincinnati, part of the Sara Lee Corporation, has named Publicis in Mid America in Dallas to handle the account of its deli products that carry the Sara Lee brand, which had been handled by PGC Advertising in Dallas, part of the Omnicom Group. Billings were estimated at $12 million.The decision, which came without a review, expands the relationship between corporate Sara Lee and Publicis in Mid America, part of the Publicis Worldwide division of the Publicis Groupe. The agency also handles the accounts of the Sara Lee Bakery Group and the Champion and Just My Size clothing lines sold by Sara Lee Branded Apparel.Bill Brunt, 38, was named to the new post of senior vice president and group account director at Publicis in Mid America, overseeing the deli and bakery accounts. He was vice president and group management director at Grey Worldwide in New York, part of the Grey Global Group.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/25/business/sara-lee-shares-tumble-9.8-biggest-drop-in-almost-15-years.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Shares Tumble 9.8%, Biggest Drop in Almost 15 Years<date>Published: April 25, 2003</date><text>Shares of Sara Lee, the maker of baked goods, Jimmy Dean meats and Hanes underwear, posted their biggest decline in 15 years after the company reduced its annual earnings forecast.Sales have been hurt by the turmoil at the U.S. Foodservice unit of Royal Ahold, one of Sara Lee's largest customers, since Ahold disclosed in February that it had inflated revenue. Profit will be less than expected in the fourth quarter, which ends in June, sending the company's shares down almost 10 percent.''We have too large a part of our portfolio in businesses that are in rather significant decline,'' Sara Lee's chief executive, C. Steven McMillan, said on a conference call with investors. ''We have been overly exposed to U.S. Foodservice as they slowed down.''Sara Lee will begin looking more closely at its five main businesses on Monday to weed out products, brands and even units that it sees as not being central, Mr. McMillan said. The company began a similar revamping three years ago that resulted in the closing or selling of 18 divisions and the consolidation of management at its meat operations.Shares of Sara Lee, which is based in Chicago, fell $1.94, to $17.80, in New York Stock Exchange trading. That is the biggest one-day decline since January 1988.Profit will be 36 cents to 38 cents a share in the fourth quarter, compared with 43 cents a year earlier, the company said. Net income rose 4.7 percent in the quarter ended March 29, mostly because of the rise in the euro.''We are the second-largest supplier to Wal-Mart but we're in categories where the discretionary spend is somewhat higher than it is in pure food categories,'' Mr. McMillan said. Beverage, food service and apparel sales will decline this quarter as consumers pare spending, he said.Third-quarter net income increased to $269 million, or 33 cents a share, from $257 million, or 31 cents a year ago. Sales rose 3.6 percent, to $4.35 billion from $4.2 billion.Bakery profit will increase this quarter after being weak the last two periods because of inefficiencies at Earthgrains, which Sara Lee bought in August 2001.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/09/business/company-news-sara-lee-advises-against-mini-tender-offer.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE ADVISES AGAINST 'MINI TENDER' OFFER<date>Published: April 09, 2003</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation advised shareholders yesterday not to support a below-market tender offer from the TRC Capital Corporation to acquire less than 1 percent of the Sara Lee's stock for $19.25 a share. Sara Lee, based in Chicago, said it received the offer to purchase up to five million shares from TRC on March 26, but said it did not ''recommend or endorse'' the proposal. TRC Capital, based in Toronto, routinely makes below-market ''mini tender'' offers, which are defined as bids to acquire less than 5 percent of a company's stock.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/08/business/sara-lee-says-3-employees-under-scrutiny-on-rebates.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Says 3 Employees Under Scrutiny on Rebates<date>Published: April 08, 2003</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that three of its sales representatives had signed off on inaccurate rebate amounts for U.S. Foodservice, whose accounting is under investigation by federal regulators and prosecutors.The sales representatives remain employees at Sara Lee but are not allowed to work on any customer- or sales-related business, the company said.''Their focus is the investigation,'' Julie Ketay, a spokeswoman at Sara Lee, said of the employees. ''Once the investigation is complete, we'll make a further decision.''In examining the promotional and rebate payments, officials at Sara Lee say they discovered a discrepancy between company records and the documents that its sales representatives confirmed last week with Deloitte &amp; Touche, the auditors for U.S. Foodservice. Sara Lee is conducting an internal inquiry and is cooperating with the investigations into U.S. Foodservice and its parent, Royal Ahold of the Netherlands.Royal Ahold said in February that it had overstated earnings by $500 million for the last two years because of accounting problems connected to payments made to U.S. Foodservice. The problems involved the inflation of promotional payments from suppliers, falsely increasing the unit's profit.The three Sara Lee sales representatives, who were not identified, were contacted by senior executives at U.S. Foodservice and asked to verify promotional and rebate amounts and balances due for distributing Sara Lee products, officials at Sara Lee said.The employees independently verified the amounts payable with auditors and confirmed payment amounts that were higher than what Sara Lee owed U.S. Foodservice. Sara Lee said the inaccurate figures that were given to Deloitte &amp; Touche did not match its own accounting of rebate balances that are given to U.S. Foodservice each month.Sara Lee would not disclose the amount by which the payments were inflated but said it realized that the documents could have been used ''improperly by certain U.S. Foodservice personnel to indicate higher than actual earnings.''''While this is a serious matter, we want to emphasize that Sara Lee is not the focus of this internal investigation, and this discovery in no way affects our financial results,'' C. Steven McMillan, Sara Lee's chairman, president and chief executive said. ''Sara Lee's accounting for our business with U.S. Foodservice is both accurate and appropriate.''</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/26/business/company-news-sara-lee-to-cut-1200-jobs-in-puerto-rico.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE TO CUT 1,200 JOBS IN PUERTO RICO<date>Published: February 26, 2003</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation will cut about 1,200 jobs as it scales back operations at three plants in Puerto Rico that make underwear, the company said yesterday. ''The continuing pressures of a weak economy and an intensely competitive atmosphere leave us no other option but to make this difficult decision,'' Rafael Rodriguez, Sara Lee Intimate Apparel's vice president for operations in the Caribbean, said. The job cuts affect plants that produce Playtex products in the towns of Dorado, Humacao and Vega Baja. The company said it would continue operations in other textile divisions in Puerto Rico. In 2001, Sara Lee, based in Chicago, eliminated about 3,900 jobs on the island.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/business/sara-lee-reports-doubling-of-profit.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Reports Doubling of Profit<date>Published: January 24, 2003</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said today that it more than doubled its profit in its fiscal second quarter, helped by cost savings from its restructuring and a favorable comparison with a difficult period a year ago.Net earnings were $348 million, or 42 cents a share, in the three months ended Dec. 28, up from $160 million, or 20 cents a share, a year earlier. The year-earlier total was reduced by $143 million, or 17 cents a share, to reflect costs associated with its restructuring.The latest results matched the estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Revenue climbed 2 percent, to $4.78 billion from $4.69 billion.Sara Lee, whose products range from Hanes underwear to Ball Park hot dogs, said profit gains in its meats and household products divisions offset a down quarter for baked goods. It said the bakery business, which it also expects to show lower profit in the current quarter, is under pressure from weakness in the fresh-bread market, where its sales fell by more than 3 percent despite success with new products.Meat sales declined 2 percent from a year earlier, partly reflecting higher commodity costs, but operating income increased aided by changes in the company's two-year restructuring program.The company said its profits would have been higher if it had not stepped up advertising and promotional spending by 14 percent to back new products.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/28/business/company-news-sara-lee-says-it-plans-to-close-to-two-bakeries.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE SAYS IT PLANS TO CLOSE TO TWO BAKERIES<date>Published: December 28, 2002</date><text>Sara Lee, the food and consumer products company, said yesterday that it would close two bakeries as it continued to cut excess production to reduce costs. Production will end within 90 days at the company's Eau Claire, Wis., bakery and within 60 days at the Huntsville, Ala., bakery, eliminating a total of 127 jobs, Sara Lee said. The plants were among those acquired when Sara Lee bought a breadmaker, the Earthgrains Company, in August 2001. Since then, the company has closed eight bakeries.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/01/business/responsible-party-terri-thompson-your-tag-isnt-showing.html?ref=saraleecorporation">RESPONSIBLE PARTY: TERRI THOMPSON; Your Tag Isnt Showing<date>Published: December 01, 2002</date><text>THE T-shirt tag, that often irritating and scratchy ribbon that sometimes peeks out of shirts and flips up onto the wearers neck, is becoming oh so pass at Hanes.The company, which makes more than 35 million T-shirts a year, eliminated the tags in mens T-shirts in October. On its new, tagless version, the size designation and care instructions are part of the shirt itself, in the same spot where the tags once appeared.Executives at Sara Lee Underwear, the division of the Sara Lee Corporation that makes the Hanes brand, had been toying for a few years with how to make the tags less of a nuisance. But the spark behind the elimination of the tag was an agitated 2-year-old boy whose mother, Terri Thompson, is the director of merchandising at Sara Lee Underwear. Late in the summer of 2001 the boy, Allan, complained of itching because of the tag in his T-shirt. When Mom refused to remove the tag, he found a pair of scissors and cut it out himself.''I missed the whole tagless story and was annoyed with him,'' Ms. Thompson said. ''Then it hit me, Oh my God, this is something I really need to do.''Hanes had been making its T-shirts with tags since 1920; seamstresses affixed the tags while sewing on the neckbands.Information that was previously on the tags is now printed in Haness red and black colors directly on the shirts after they are sewn.The elimination of the tags gave Haness workers less to sew, but the company declined to say if the new system had shortened the overall manufacturing time or lowered production costs. Company officials said that no workers had been laid off and that the price of a three-pack of Hanes T-shirts, generally less than $10, would not change.Sales growth in the underwear category has been relatively flat. In 2001, sales of mens underwear decreased by 4.2 percent, to $2.8 billion from $2.9 billion in 2000, according to NPD Fashionworld. Since Hanes introduced the tagless T-shirts for men, the companys sales of those shirts have increased 30 percent to 70 percent at stores around the country, the company said.Ms. Thompson plans to expand the idea to girls' camisoles, girls' and women's panties, boys' and men's boxer shorts and boys T-shirts. The new boys' shirts are likely to be in stores in early 2003, largely because of the success of the mens line and in no small measure because of Ms. Thompsons son.''We havent made one his size yet,'' Ms. Thompson said. ''He's almost 4, and hes got a lot to say about that.'' SHERRI DAY</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/25/business/sara-lee-says-earnings-jumped-28.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Says Earnings Jumped 28%<date>Published: October 25, 2002</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation reported a 28 percent jump in quarterly earnings today, citing reduced operating costs and other dividends of its two-year company overhaul.Sara Lee, whose products range from Hanes underwear to Ball Park hot dogs to Endust furniture cleaner, posted net income of $308 million, or 38 cents a share, in its first quarter. That compared with $242 million, or 30 cents a share, for the period a year earlier.Excluding certain items, Sara Lee earned 37 cents a share and that was 3 cents higher than the consensus estimate from Thomson First Call.Sales climbed 7 percent, to $4.53 billion from $4.24 billion, reflecting the August 2001 acquisition of the Earthgrains Company, which tripled Sara Lee's bakery operations.Sara Lee shares fell 25 cents, to close at $22.70.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/09/business/company-news-sara-lee-says-quarterly-profits-beat-expectations.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE SAYS QUARTERLY PROFITS BEAT EXPECTATIONS<date>Published: October 09, 2002</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that profits for the quarter just ended would be higher than anticipated as a result of a two-year corporate overhaul. The company, a maker of packaged foods, said it expected to report about a 35 percent increase in per-share earnings when it released results from its fiscal first quarter on Oct. 24. It cited increased sales of higher-margin products and reduced operating costs. The announcement after the end of regular trading sent Sara Lee shares more than 5 percent higher in after-hours trading. Earlier, its shares closed at $19.90, up 47 cents.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/19/world/low-prices-threaten-coffee-farmers-livelihood-report-says.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Low Prices Threaten Coffee Farmers' Livelihood, Report Says<date>Published: September 19, 2002</date><text>Global economic forces are crushing millions of coffee farmers around the world, the British charity Oxfam said in a report released today.In Latin America, Africa and Asia, farmers are paid roughly 24 cents a pound for their beans, which may be the lowest price in a century, the report said.Four multinational companies -- Kraft, Sara Lee, Procter &amp; Gamble and NestlÃ© -- buy nearly half the world's coffee and sell it for an average of $3.60 a pound, the report said. People in New York, Paris and Tokyo may pay almost that much for a single cup.The value of coffee exports has fallen by $4 billion since 1997 as supplies glut a market that was once regulated and is now free. Farmers in places like Mexico, Nicaragua and Guatemala are penniless and starving while ''the coffee companies are laughing all the way to the bank,'' the report said.''Asking some of the poorest and most powerless people in the world to negotiate in an open market with some of the richest and most powerful results, unsurprisingly, in the rich getting richer and the poor getting poorer,'' the Oxfam report said.Oxfam timed the release of its report to coincide with the opening of a five-day meeting of the International Coffee Organization, in London, on Thursday. The organization has a plan to cut the coffee glut by barring export of the lowest-quality beans.Oxfam will ask members of the group -- 40 major coffee importers and exporters -- to agree to destroy about 660 million pounds of the lowest-quality coffee sitting in the world's warehouses, a move that would cost about $100 million.An economic analysis conducted for the International Coffee Organization said destruction would raise prices paid to coffee-producing nations by roughly $750 million and, Oxfam suggested, perhaps save some lives among the rural growers.The four corporations cited by Oxfam each said, in varying ways, that as buyers they were well aware of the crisis among coffee growers. But Kraft says it is ''fundamentally opposed to any scheme that intervenes on price.'' Sara Lee says it is ''uneasy about price support.'' Procter &amp; Gamble says it wants ''to help address the underlaying social and economic issues'' -- but not through the International Coffee Organization.NestlÃ©, alone among the four, says it supports a price-control scheme led by the coffee organization. ''NestlÃ© is against low prices as they are not only bad for farmers, but also bad for NestlÃ©'s business,'' the corporation said.Fair Trade coffee, the response of an international movement that helps businesses buy directly from rural coffee cooperatives, eliminating the corporate middleman and paying farmers double or more the market price, is a growing alternative. Fair Trade coffee now represents about 2 percent of the world market. In the United States, such coffee is sold at about 10,000 retail outlets; sales grew 36 percent last year.But without a worldwide plan to raise prices paid to farmers and give them new alternatives to old ways, Oxfam said, the livelihoods of millions are at risk.''The coffee market is failing,'' the report said. ''It is failing producers on small family farms for whom coffee used to make money. It is failing local exporters and entrepreneurs who are going to the wall in the face of fierce international competition. And it is failing governments that had encouraged coffee production to increase export earnings.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/11/business/many-chiefs-are-retaining-extra-benefits-in-retirement.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Many Chiefs Are Retaining Extra Benefits In Retirement<date>Published: September 11, 2002</date><text>Often described as a model for chief executives, John F. Welch Jr. appears to have also created the model employment contract.The contract that Mr. Welch signed in 1996 as chief executive of General Electric was full of benefits that continue to flow to him in retirement. It quickly became a template for other executives to use to negotiate their own contracts, people in the field of executive pay say.So, like Mr. Welch, many retired chief executives of large companies now enjoy retirement benefits like free lifetime use of a company office and secretary and frequent access to a company plane. The executives typically receive the benefits in exchange for serving as consultants to their companies, the companies say.For John H. Bryan, Sara Lee's former chief executive, the company has agreed to pay for a car and driver through 2008, office space through 2009 and two administrative assistants through 2011. Mr. Bryan, who retired as chief executive in 2000, has a consulting agreement with Sara Lee that runs through 2009.AOL Time Warner is paying Gerald M. Levin, its former chief, who is now an adviser to the company, $1 million a year and providing him with office space in or near AOL's Rockefeller Center corporate offices, according to a report by the Corporate Library, a corporate-governance watchdog group.And Hugh L. McColl Jr., who retired from Bank of America in April 2001, has the use of an office, administrative support and, for up to 150 hours a year, a company plane, according to Executive Compensation Advisory Services, a research company in Alexandria, Va.Some details of Mr. Welch's benefits became public last week in a divorce court filing by his wife, Jane, who is seeking additional money to maintain her standard of living. They include courtside seats at the United States Open, satellite TV at his four homes and the use of a G.E.-owned apartment on Central Park West, in addition to paying for laundry, wine, newspapers and other items associated with the apartment.Some investors and corporate-governance experts have criticized the benefits, calling them another sign that company boards too often choose the welfare of executives over that of shareholders. Once executives retire, they should pay for their expenses with the millions of dollars they received in salary, bonus and stock, rather than using company money, the critics say.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/02/business/sara-lee-earnings-fell-in-4th-quarter.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Earnings Fell in 4th Quarter<date>Published: August 02, 2002</date><text>The consumer goods maker Sara Lee said today that its quarterly net earnings fell from a year ago, when it posted an $862 million gain from the spinoff of its Coach leatherware business.Sara Lee, which makes Ball Park hot dogs, Playtex bras and Kiwi shoe polish, said it earned $351 million, or 43 cents a share, compared with $973 million, or $1.19 a share, a year earlier.Before one-time items, the company earned 42 cents a share, compared with 37 cents a year ago, matching the estimate from Thomson First Call.Revenue in the period ended June 29, the fourth quarter of Sara Lee's fiscal year, rose to $4.5 billion from $3.9 billion.Sara Lee, based in Chicago, has spent the last two years revamping. In addition to the Coach spinoff, it cut slow-growing lines at its PYA Monarch Food service unit and pieces of its Champion apparel line.It added to its bakery business with its August 2001 acquisition of the bread company Earthgrains. It has spent more on marketing and advertising.Bakery sales rose to $803 million from $181 million a year earlier.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/16/business/responsible-party-miguel-llado-bread-without-borders.html?ref=saraleecorporation">RESPONSIBLE PARTY: MIGUEL LLADÓ; Bread Without Borders<date>Published: June 16, 2002</date><text>FOR children who balk at the sight of the bread crust on their peanut butter and jelly sandwiches, the Sara Lee Bakery Group has come up with a crustless alternative.The bread was introduced in the United States just last month as IronKids Crustless, though it is already commonplace in Spain, where Sara Lee began producing it in 1999.''The idea came from a very deep understanding of consumer behavior, and seeing that the parents were trimming the crust off the bread more times than not,'' said Miguel LladÃ³, president for European bakery products at Sara Lee in Madrid. ''We decided to go for that market.''More than 60,000 loaves of the bread are now baked daily in Madrid and the Canary Islands and more than 20,000 in Paris, Tex.The process isn't as easy as it sounds. First, the bread is baked in oversize pans and allowed to cool for two hours, double the usual time, to ensure that its texture is ''more consistent,'' or dense. Then, the bread is whisked into a sterile ''decrusting room,'' where it is sliced and immediately double-wrapped. The discarded bread is used for bread crumbs and croutons or sold for animal feed.''Industrially speaking, it is very difficult to make the bread,'' Mr. LladÃ³ said. ''Peel off the crust and the bread becomes very sensitive to anything in the air.''The bread sells for $2.59 to $3.19 a loaf, depending on the market; regular IronKids Bread, is $1.79 to $2.29. Although the loaves' dimensions are the same, the crustless variety weighs only 16 ounces, compared with 20 for the regular version. Both have the same shelf life, about eight days.''Here in the United States, the crustless bread tested for staying softer longer than regular bread,'' said Matt Hall, a spokesman for Sara Lee in St. Louis. Bread crust, he said, seems to absorb moisture from the white part of the bread. In Spain, the bread is promoted as ''100 percent tender.''All that may explain why Mr. LladÃ³'s children recently changed their dining behavior. ''Now they eat more sandwiches, and they love to produce them themselves because they look nicer,'' he said. ''They were eating the crust before. But now they don't.'' KATHRYN SHATTUCK</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/31/business/sara-lee-settles-race-harassment-case.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Settles Race-Harassment Case<date>Published: May 31, 2002</date><text>The Sara Lee Foods Corporation has agreed to pay $3.5 million to 139 black employees who complained of racial harassment and retaliation at a hot dog plant that closed last year.The former employees worked at the Ball Park Franks plant. They charged that they had been subjected to racial slurs and racist cartoons and graffiti, denied promotions, given extra work and forced to undergo frequent drug testing. They said white employees who wore hoods and pretended to be Ku Klux Klansmen or used slurs were inadequately disciplined, if at all.The employees also complained of retaliation when the company closed the 34-year-old plant and moved production elsewhere. About 230 union workers lost their jobs.The settlement, announced Tuesday, averages about $25,000 a person before lawyers' fees are subtracted.''We are pleased that we have reached a fair and amicable settlement,'' said Robert T. Vance Jr., one of the plaintiffs' lawyers. ''The plaintiffs are now able to move forward with their lives and focus on their futures.''Sara Lee said the closing of the plant was purely a business decision.''Sara Lee Foods is committed to a workplace free from any form of harassment or discrimination,'' William A. Geoppinger, the chief executive, said in a statement.The employees said discrimination increased at the plant after Chicago-based Sara Lee bought it from Hygrade Food Products in the 1990's.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/16/business/longtime-clients-abandon-auditor.html?ref=saraleecorporation">LONGTIME CLIENTS ABANDON AUDITOR<date>Published: March 16, 2002</date><text>Longtime clients, the federal government and even some of its own foreign affiliates abandoned Arthur Andersen yesterday, a day after the accounting firm was indicted for destroying Enron documents.Several of the firm's most loyal clients, including the Sara Lee Corporation and Abbott Laboratories from around its hometown, Chicago, said the time had come to switch auditors. Northeast Utilities and the Brunswick Corporation also said that they planned to replace Andersen, which faces a single count of obstruction of justice.Foreign affiliates of Andersen in Spain and Chile announced that they would sever ties with the firm, and several other operations, in Italy, Poland, Portugal and Switzerland, were considering similar steps.The federal government also announced that it would give no more work to Andersen or to Enron, the bankrupt company whose books Andersen had audited.With the defections at home and abroad mounting, lawyers and Andersen partners met in Chicago yesterday afternoon to try to work out a plan for survival.The indictment describes a concerted effort by Andersen to shred records related to Enron in the firm's offices in four cities: Houston, Chicago, London and Portland, Ore.Although the firm has conceded that documents were destroyed, it has indicated it intends to fight the Justice Department over what it considers a baseless criminal charge and has resisted filing for bankruptcy protection, which might scare off even more clients.In a statement issued last night, Andersen said the government's central allegation was ''false and wholly unsupported by the facts.'' It also said the indictment was ''riddled with factual and legal errors.''Andersen also contended in its statement that there was no evidence that the firm's management in Chicago directed the destruction of documents in Houston.So far, the firm has not managed to find an acquirer, in large part because any potential acquirer fears inheriting Andersen's liabilities from its role in Enron's collapse. An acquirer might be willing to buy Andersen's assets out of bankruptcy court, however, because such a sale could limit transfer of liability.With its options dwindling, Andersen is under increasing pressure to reassure its clients and employees.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/12/business/kmart-s-debt-to-sara-lee.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Kmart's Debt to Sara Lee<date>Published: February 12, 2002</date><text>The Kmart Corporation owed the Sara Lee Corporation $40 million at the time the discount retailer filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection last month, Sara Lee said in a regulatory filing.Sara Lee, which is based in Chicago, has entered into agreements allowing it to shift its receivables to a third party, the company said in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission.The third party would then buy the products, a spokeswoman, Hillary Sterling, said. She declined to identify the potential buyer.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/11/business/company-news-playtex-to-move-most-operations-from-connecticut.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; PLAYTEX TO MOVE MOST OPERATIONS FROM CONNECTICUT<date>Published: January 11, 2002</date><text>Playtex Apparel, maker of the Wonderbra, has announced plans to move most of its operations from Stamford, Conn., to Winston-Salem, N.C. The company, a unit of Sara Lee Intimate Apparel, said yesterday that it would consolidate with Sara Lee's other underwear operations in May to cut expenses. About 50 jobs will be eliminated in marketing, finance, forecasting and human resources. About 20 jobs will remain in Stamford. A design shop will remain in New York City. After consolidating jobs among divisions, the company expects Playtex Apparel to create about 40 new jobs in North Carolina.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/16/business/sara-lee-sells-part-of-unit.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Sells Part of Unit<date>Published: October 16, 2001</date><text>Correction Appended CHICAGO, Oct. 15— The Sara Lee Corporation, a maker of food and consumer goods, said today that it would restructure its Liberty Fabrics textile unit as the company moves to concentrate on its core lines of food, intimates and household goods. Liberty Fabrics makes fabric and lace and had sales of $130 million in 2000, Sara Lee said. It was part of Sara Lee's acquisition of Courtaulds Textiles in June 2000. Sara Lee, based in Seattle, said it had signed a letter of intent to sell the unit's wide-elastic manufacturing plant in Jamesville, N.C., to McMurray Fabrics, based in Aberdeen, N.C. Terms were not disclosed. In addition, Sara Lee said it would leave Liberty's lace business and transfer some assets related to non-Sara Lee business to Metritek, based in Boca Raton, Fla. About 350 jobs will be cut, Sara Lee said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/31/business/allegations-made-about-tainted-meat.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Allegations Made About Tainted Meat<date>Published: August 31, 2001</date><text>Managers at a Sara Lee Corporation plant in western Michigan knew they were shipping tainted meat, which was later linked to a nationwide outbreak of listeriosis that killed at least 15 people, according to statements given to federal investigators.The bacteria, which also caused 6 miscarriages and made 80 people seriously ill, was found in hot dogs and deli meat produced in 1998 at the Bil Mar Foods plant of Sara Lee in Borculo, Mich.In one statement, obtained by The Detroit Free Press, an employee told investigators from the Department of Agriculture that he or she knew with ''virtual certainty'' that meats produced and sold by the Bil Mar plant were contaminated with listeria monocytogenes, the bacteria that causes the disease listeriosis.A federal meat inspector told the investigators that Bil Mar managers knew that the plant had increased levels of listeria about eight months before the nationwide listeriosis outbreak, which began in the fall of 1998.The outbreak led Sara Lee to announce the recall of 15 million pounds of meat in December 1998. The Agriculture Department said the recall eventually grew to 35 million pounds.Federal prosecutors, however, found that the government had ''uncovered no evidence that Sara Lee intentionally distributed'' tainted meat. That was one reason given by Phillip Green, a United States attorney, when he agreed to let Bil Mar plead guilty in June to one charge of preparing and selling ''adulterated poultry and meat products.''As part of that plea, Sara Lee agreed to pay a fine of $200,000 and spend $3 million on food safety research at Michigan State University.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/17/business/media-business-advertising-addenda-sara-lee-apparel-unit-selects-new-agency.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Sara Lee Apparel Unit Selects a New Agency<date>Published: July 17, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Branded Apparel division of the Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that it had named the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va., to handle United States advertising for its Hanes and Hanes Her Way lines. Billings were estimated at $10 million to $15 million.Peggy Carter, a spokeswoman for the Sara Lee division in Winston-Salem, N.C., said the decision came after a nearly three-month review that had been narrowed to Martin and three other finalists: the Chicago offices of Foote, Cone &amp; Belding, part of the FCB Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies; Leo Burnett USA, part of the Leo Burnett Worldwide unit of the Bcom3 Group; and Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide, part of the WPP Group.For almost 20 years, Long Haymes Carr in Winston-Salem and a successor shop, Mullen/LHC, had handled the account.Mullen/LHC was invited to take part in the review when it began, but decided against it about a month later. Both Martin and Mullen/LHC are now part of another Interpublic unit, the Partnership.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/15/business/private-sector-fast-cars-harleys-and-cheesecake.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Private Sector; Fast Cars, Harleys and Cheesecake<date>Published: July 15, 2001</date><text>THE muscular and dapper chief executive of the Sara Lee Corporation, C. Steven McMillan, used to drive Formula 2000 race cars as a hobby. He also took to riding Harley-Davidson motorcycles to relax. And legend has it that he once stuck his head in a tiger's mouth on a dare.These days, his most daring feat is trying to elevate the stock of Sara Lee, the $20 billion food and consumer goods conglomerate. Since taking the helm last July, Mr. McMillan has moved aggressively to remake a company best known for its Sara Lee frozen cheesecake, Hanes underwear and Ball Park franks. He has slashed jobs (8,500, or about 5 percent of the work force), sold or spun off businesses (15 including Coach leather goods and the PYA/Monarch food service) and ordered an extensive restructuring of the company's decentralized food empire.Two weeks ago, Mr. McMillan engineered Sara Lee's biggest acquisition, agreeing to buy the Earthgrains Company of St. Louis, the nation's second-largest bread maker behind Interstate Bakeries, for $1.87 billion in cash.Mr. McMillan, 55, makes no apologies for shaking up Sara Lee. Consumers want more convenient and fresher food, and Earthgrains would instantly make Sara Lee a force in the packaged-bread business.''I've had the question, 'Are you doing too much too fast?,' '' Mr. McMillan said in an interview on Wednesday in his 47th-floor office in downtown Chicago, overlooking Lake Michigan. ''I'd rather relate this to what the market's dictating. We don't have the luxury of taking a leisurely pace.''If Mr. McMillan sounds a little impatient, it may have something to do with the company's shares, which have lost nearly one-third of their value since 1999 on investor perceptions that the company's growth prospects are weak. The shares closed on Friday at $19.09.Mr. McMillan is said to be sharply focused. Friends describe him as a straightforward and disciplined executive who wears custom-made suits and is not one for simple pleasantries.He spent his youth in Troy, Ala., the only child of an insurance salesman and a high-school English teacher. His father later built a hotel in the center of town.''I grew up in the hotel,'' Mr. McMillan said. ''I was the bellhop.''He was also a star athlete at the local public high school, excelling in basketball, football and track. Mr. McMillan said he still held the school's basketball record for scoring the most points in a single game (42), even though he was a relatively short 5-foot-8.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/23/us/sara-lee-corp-pleads-guilty-in-meat-case.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Corp. Pleads Guilty In Meat Case<date>Published: June 23, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation, one of the nation's largest makers of hot dogs and supermarket deli meats, pleaded guilty today to a misdemeanor charge that it had produced and distributed tainted meat that sickened scores of consumers and was linked to about 15 deaths.The company agreed to pay $4.4 million to settle civil and criminal charges brought by the United States attorney for Western Michigan after a 1998 nationwide recall of deli meats and hot dogs that were produced at the company's Bill Mar Foods plant in Zeeland, Mich.Sara Lee, which makes Ball Park and Hygrade hot dogs and Sara Lee Deli Meat, recalled about 15 million pounds of meat in December 1998 after the federal government determined that a rare strain of listeria bacteria in the company's hot dogs and cold cuts had probably sickened people in several states. It was one of the largest meat recalls in United States history.A year ago, Sara Lee settled a class-action lawsuit brought by consumers who said they had been harmed by tainted meat produced at the Bill Mar plant. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention had identified the plant as the source in a nationwide outbreak of listeriosis, which is most harmful to pregnant women, children, the elderly and people with weak immune systems. In healthy people, the bacterium generally causes flulike symptoms.Sara Lee, which is based in Chicago, closed some lines at the plant in December 1998 and has since spent about $25 million on renovations to a site that government inspectors said in the time leading up to the outbreak was infested with roaches and contained old meat and debris.Still, Phillip J. Green, the United States attorney in Grand Rapids, Mich., said today that the company was only charged with a misdemeanor and not a felony because investigators found no evidence that Sara Lee intentionally produced or distributed adulterated meats. The company had cooperated with the investigation, Mr. Green said.''It is tragic that people died,'' he said, ''but the law does not provide for a felony charge unless we can show that the company knew and intended to ship adulterated foods.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/31/business/company-news-sara-lee-forecasts-reduced-profits-next-year.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE FORECASTS REDUCED PROFITS NEXT YEAR<date>Published: May 31, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation, maker of Jimmy Dean sausages and Hanes underwear, said yesterday that profit might fall in the next fiscal year and that it would reorganize its domestic meat and hosiery businesses and European intimate apparel units in an attempt to cut costs and increase sales. Sara Lee, based in Chicago, will earn $1.25 to $1.35 a share in the fiscal year ending June 30, 2002, because it will spend more on marketing and technology, its chief financial officer, Cary D. McMillan, said during a conference with analysts and investors. In April, Sara Lee said it would earn $1.34 to $1.37 a share in fiscal 2001.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/01/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-hanes-advertising-undergoes-review.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Hanes Advertising Undergoes Review<date>Published: May 01, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Branded Apparel division of the Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that it had placed in review the account of its Hanes and Hanes Her Way lines of apparel. The account has been handled for almost 20 years by Mullen/LHC in Winston-Salem, N.C., formerly Long Haymes Carr.Billings were estimated at $10 million to $15 million.Peggy Carter, a spokeswoman for Sara Lee Branded Apparel, confirmed a report of the review in Adweek. It will be confined to Mullen/LHC and other agencies that work for Sara Lee, Ms. Carter said.Other Sara Lee agencies include Leo Burnett USA in Chicago, part of the Leo Burnett Worldwide unit of the Bcom3 Group; and Temerlin McClain in Irving, Tex., part of True North Communications.The review comes three months after the Lowe Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies merged Long Haymes with Mullen Advertising in Wenham, Mass.Ms. Carter said the review was unrelated to the merger, attributing it to a desire ''to assure ourselves we have the best creative possible.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/28/business/company-news-dogi-a-spanish-fabrics-maker-adding-sara-lee-assets.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; DOGI, A SPANISH FABRICS MAKER, ADDING SARA LEE ASSETS<date>Published: April 28, 2001</date><text>Dogi, a Spanish company that makes stretch fabrics, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy four companies and other assets from the Sara Lee International Corporation for Â£30 million ($43 million). The companies being purchased -- four fabric divisions of Sara Lee's Courtaulds International Fabrics in Germany, China, Thailand and the Philippines -- will make Dogi a world leader in the stretch fabric industry. Dogi, which is based in Catalonia, has 18 percent of the European high- quality underwear and swimwear fabric market. It said in November that it was looking at a possible acquisition to strengthen its presence in Asia. Sara Lee is based in Chicago.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/27/business/company-news-sara-lee-plans-to-lay-off-up-to-1400-more-employees.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE PLANS TO LAY OFF UP TO 1,400 MORE EMPLOYEES<date>Published: April 27, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation is laying off an additional 1,300 to 1,400 workers at its underwear manufacturing plants in Central America and South America amid the continuing economic and retail slowdown. Sara Lee makes Hanes underwear and Playtex bras in addition to sausages, baked goods and household products. The job cuts are less than 1 percent of the company's work force and are in addition to the 7,000 announced in January as part of its continuing restructuring, a spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, said yesterday. Sara Lee employs about 150,000 people in 40 countries.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/23/business/company-news-sara-lee-is-selling-its-champion-europe-business.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE IS SELLING ITS CHAMPION EUROPE BUSINESS<date>Published: March 23, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation agreed to sell its Champion Europe business, which markets athletic apparel and footwear, to a group of the unit's managers to focus on more profitable sales of food, underwear and household products. Terms were not disclosed. The transaction is expected to be completed by the end of June, a Sara Lee spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, said. Sara Lee said in January that it would sell seven units, including Champion Europe, and its majority stake in the leather-goods maker Coach Inc. Sara Lee, based in Chicago, is trying to bolster its profit and revenue by focusing on top-selling brands like Jimmy Dean meats and Kiwi shoe polish. Champion Europe is based in Campogalliano, Italy.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/17/business/company-news-sara-lee-to-keep-and-overhaul-champion-products.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE TO KEEP AND OVERHAUL CHAMPION PRODUCTS<date>Published: February 17, 2001</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation has decided to retain and restructure its Champion Products business in the United States after earlier putting the unit, a maker of athletic apparel, up for sale. ''As we talked with potential buyers, it became clear that the Champion property was a more valuable asset within our organization -- especially the core branded business where we hold a competitive advantage,'' Gerald Evans, the chief executive of Sara Lee Activewear, said on Thursday. Sara Lee had put its worldwide Champion operations up for sale last May and announced in January that it expected to sell its Champion Europe operations in the third quarter. Sara Lee plans to revamp its United States business and focus on basic, branded apparel lines and selected exclusive licenses.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/26/business/company-news-sara-lee-says-it-plans-to-eliminate-7000-jobs-this-year.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE SAYS IT PLANS TO ELIMINATE 7,000 JOBS THIS YEAR<date>Published: January 26, 2001</date><text>Sara Lee, the consumer products company, confirmed yesterday that it would cut 7,000 jobs over the next year, primarily in its underwear and food operations, which are under increasing pressure from competition and the retail slowdown. The jobs being eliminated amount to about 4.5 percent of Sara Lee's work force of 154,000 in 40 countries. The company is based in Chicago. A spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, confirmed that the layoffs would come mainly from the company's two biggest operations, intimate apparel and underwear, and food. The job cuts are not directly related to the company's announcement Wednesday that it intends to sell eight more of its 100-plus businesses, she added. The company has sold or closed more than 100 plants since 1997. Sara Lee shares, which fell 5 percent Wednesday, gained 6 cents yesterday, to $21.81.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/26/business/company-news-sara-lee-matches-consensus-estimates-for-the-quarter.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE MATCHES CONSENSUS ESTIMATES FOR THE QUARTER<date>Published: October 26, 2000</date><text>Sara Lee said yesterday that its fiscal first-quarter net income fell 2 percent but matched analysts' consensus estimate as the company continued to reshape business lines. Sara Lee, whose products range from baked goods and Ball Park hot dogs to Hanes underwear and L'eggs hosiery, reported net income of $254 million, or 29 cents a share, in the quarter ended Sept. 30, compared with $258 million, or 28 cents, in the same period a year earlier. The figures include income from the PYA/Monarch food service unit that Sara Lee sold in August for $1.57 billion. Analysts on average had expected earnings of 29 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial. (Reuters)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/business/the-media-business-advertising-addenda-ball-park-brands-selects-two-agencies.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Ball Park Brands Selects Two Agencies<date>Published: October 06, 2000</date><text>Ball Park Brands in Southfield, Mich., a division of Sara Lee that sells the Ball Park line of meat products, has awarded its advertising and media planning accounts to two units of the B Com3 Group in Chicago. Billings were estimated at $20 million.Leo Burnett USA, part of Leo Burnett Worldwide, will handle advertising, and Starcom USA, part of the Starcom MediaVest Group, will handle media planning. Starcom has handled media buying for Ball Park and many other Sara Lee brands since November 1998. Advertising and media planning for Ball Park had been handled by Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners Worldwide in New York, part of the Lowe Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies, which resigned in June.The decision came after a review that involved Burnett, Starcom and other agencies that Ball Park declined to identify. This is the first creative general market assignment from Sara Lee for Burnett; a Burnett division, Lapiz, creates campaigns for Ball Park aimed at Spanish-speaking consumers.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/business/company-news-sara-lee-says-it-is-considering-sale-of-some-businesses.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE SAYS IT IS CONSIDERING SALE OF SOME BUSINESSES<date>Published: October 06, 2000</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation's chief executive, C. Steven McMillan, said yesterday that the company might sell some of its global food and European apparel businesses to winnow the collection of products amassed over the last 25 years. Mr. McMillan said that Sara Lee had received bids for food companies with about $300 million in annual sales. The company is also considering the sale of clothing units in Europe with as much as $150 million in sales. He did not name the units. Sara Lee said in May that the company would sell shares in its Coach leather goods unit and its food-service business, PYA/Monarch, to the public, and find a buyer for its Champion sportswear unit.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/29/business/coach-sets-terms-for-its-public-offering.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Coach Sets Terms for Its Public Offering<date>Published: August 29, 2000</date><text>The leather-goods maker Coach Inc. announced the terms today for its pending initial public offering, which could give it a total market value of as much as $679 million.The company said it planned to sell 7.38 million shares at $14 to $16 a share, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission.On June 16, the company had filed for an offering of up to $140 million in stock but had not detailed the terms.The offering will constitute 17.4 percent of the 42.4 million shares outstanding.Total proceeds from the offering are expected to reach up to $118.1 million, not counting additional shares that might be sold.The company plans to use the proceeds to repay a portion of a note payable to a unit of Sara Lee that it will assume in separating from Sara Lee.Sara Lee will own roughly 80 percent of Coach after the offering, and plans to sell the rest of its interest in the company over the next 18 months.Coach intends to list its common stock on the New York Stock Exchange under the symbol COH.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/20/business/investing-the-pocketbook-issues-in-the-future-of-coach.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Investing; The Pocketbook Issues In the Future of Coach<date>Published: August 20, 2000</date><text>INVESTORS who are awaiting the initial public offering of Coach Inc., the luxury leather goods maker, are likely to be disappointed, analysts warn, because Coach's parent, the Sara Lee Corporation, might well do better if it sells the unit than if it takes it public.Sara Lee reached a similar conclusion last week when it agreed to sell its PYA/Monarch food service unit to Koninklijke Ahold N.V., the Dutch supermarket giant, for $1.57 billion. In June, PYA/Monarch filed with the Securities and Exchange Corporation to raise $160 million in an initial offering to be managed by Goldman Sachs, Bear Stearns and Salomon Smith Barney.In each case, Sara Lee intended initially to keep 80 percent of the company and offer 20 percent to the public.''With the direct sale of PYA/Monarch to Ahold, Sara Lee obtains cash now, eliminates market uncertainty and secures a multiyear supply contract, creating significant value for Sara Lee shareholders,'' said C. Steven McMillan, chief executive of Sara Lee.Mr. McMillan was the architect of the company's plan to sell some assets and focus on its core businesses. Though it is best known for its baked goods, Sara Lee also owns brands including Ball Park franks, L'eggs hosiery, Hanes underwear, Wonderbra, Endust furniture cleaner and Kiwi shoe polish.A Sara Lee spokeswoman, Julie Ketay, said after the PYA/Monarch deal that the $140 million Coach offering, to be managed by Goldman Sachs, was still on track to be completed by the end of the year, but some fund managers and analysts are not convinced.LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton, the French luxury goods group, is among the many names being tossed up as potential buyers of Coach. Last year LVMH teamed up with its archrival Prada S.p.A. to win a bidding war with the Gucci Group for another high-class brand, Fendi, the Italian apparel and accessories group. They paid one trillion lire, or $483.6 million, for a 51 percent stake in Fendi.''For some reason, the market will put a higher multiple on the same business with the same earnings if Bernard Arnault owned this company,'' said Greg Fontana, vice president and co-manager for the John Hancock funds in Boston, referring to the LVMH chairman.PEDRO BERNAL, an analyst at Wachovia Securities in Charlotte, N.C., said: ''The most likely choice is for it to be sold than to do an I.P.O. Just about everybody has been mentioned, so it's not a question of who, but what price.''</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/17/business/company-news-sara-lee-in-1.57-billion-food-service-deal.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE IN $1.57 BILLION FOOD SERVICE DEAL<date>Published: August 17, 2000</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation signed an agreement yesterday to sell its PYA/Monarch food service operation to the Dutch supermarket giant, Royal Ahold, for $1.57 billion. The sale also includes a supply agreement between the Royal Ahold and Sara Lee's United States food and beverage manufacturing operations. The sale of PYA/Monarch is part of a plan to narrow Sara Lee's focus to three product areas in which the company holds strong positions: household products, food and beverage, and intimates and underwear. The reorganization plan, which Sara Lee announced in May, also includes plans to split off Coach leather goods and divest itself of Champion athletic wear and the International Fabrics division of Courtaulds.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/20/business/sara-lee-plans-coach-spinoff.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Plans Coach Spinoff<date>Published: June 20, 2000</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation, the largest United States maker of frozen baked goods, filed to spin off the leather manufacturer Coach Inc. in a stock sale worth $140 million.Coach, which makes handbags, gloves, outerwear and scarves, will trade on the New York Stock Exchange, according to Sara Lee's filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission.The spinoff is part of Chicago-based Sara Lee's plan to whittle down businesses obtained in the last quarter-century. The company said earlier this year that it planned to sell its athletic clothing line, Champion, and its food-service operation, PYA/Monarch.Sara Lee's president, Steve McMillan, who will take over as chief executive in July, said last month that he wanted to focus on brands that are market leaders and can be sold globally. Those include foods like Sara Lee baked goods and Ball Park franks, undergarments including Hanes T-shirts and L'eggs hosiery, and household products like Kiwi shoe polish.Coach will be headed by Lew Frankfort, 54, its chief executive and chairman, who has been with the company since November 1995.After the offerings, Sara Lee will own at least 80.1 percent of each business.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/31/business/markets-market-place-sara-lee-plans-reorganize-some-apparel-food-units.html?ref=saraleecorporation">THE MARKETS: Market Place; Sara Lee Plans To Reorganize Some Apparel And Food Units<date>Published: May 31, 2000</date><text>Sara Lee, the giant consumer goods company that sells everything from Ball Park hot dogs to Playtex bras and Hanes underwear, said today that it would reorganize its operations and divest itself of four divisions.The company, which has annual revenue of about $20 billion, said that later this year it expected to take two of those divisions public: Coach, its leather goods business, and PYA/Monarch, one of the nation's largest food service distributors.Sara Lee executives say the company also intends to sell Champion, the athletic apparel maker, as well as the international fabrics unit of Courtaulds Textiles, the British retailer that Sara Lee acquired in March. Together, the four units generate about $4 billion in revenue.The moves, which executives say will narrow and sharpen the focus of the conglomerate, which is based in Chicago, are also expected to raise about $2.5 billion for Sara Lee, which could use the money to make acquisitions that better complement its core brands.Troubled by lackluster earnings growth and a belief that the stock price was undervalued, top executives moved today to re-energize Sara Lee with promises of a more centralized and efficient management structure, a more focused portfolio and a more aggressive investment strategy, particularly in emerging markets.For more than two decades, the company has been acquiring dozens of major brands. And now, with its longtime chief executive, John H. Bryan, set to step down this summer, the company says it would like to create a more streamlined global enterprise. ''We have a new vision for Sara Lee, a vision that will focus our business portfolio and resources,'' said C. Steven McMillan, the president and chief operating officer of Sara Lee, who will take over as chief executive on July 1.Shares of Sara Lee rose slightly today, up 31.25 cents, to $18.875, on the New York Stock Exchange. The gains may have been tempered because Sara Lee executives also warned today that earnings in the coming year could come in about 5 percent below expectations because of currency weakness in Europe, which accounts for about 40 percent of the company's earnings.Wall Street analysts, however, largely praised the move by Sara Lee. ''It was a good news, bad news day,'' said John McMillin, an analyst at Prudential Securities. ''But now that Sara Lee got a haircut, they should be a better-looking company. Sara Lee had clearly gotten into too many businesses.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/21/arts/inside-art-expanding-its-art-too.html?ref=saraleecorporation">INSIDE ART; Expanding Its Art, Too<date>Published: April 21, 2000</date><text>As the Museum of Modern Art gears up for its $650 million expansion, it is concerning itself with more than bricks and mortar. Making sure its collections continue to grow is more important than ever, since the museum will be twice its present size in 2004.Late last week, the Modern's board approved a number of major acquisitions. Some are gifts from trustees, others purchases from its annual acquisitions' budgets. The list includes seven works spanning different generations, and, as is typical of the Modern, they represent blue-chip artists, from a seminal work from the early 1960's by Joseph Beuys to well-known works by fashionable younger artists like Matthew Barney and Pipilotti Rist.Two sculptures help build the institution's holdings in Arte Povera, works made by a group of Italian artists in the late 1960's who used everyday materials as a way of blurring the lines between art and life. It is an area of European art that has not been one of the museum's strengths. The works include ''Torsione,'' a 1968 construction in cement, wood and leather by Giovanni Anselmo, and ''Mitragliatrice,'' (''Machine Gun'') from 1966, made from reworked automobile parts by Pino Pascali.''The Anselmo is a particularly iconic work,'' said Glenn D. Lowry, director of the Modern. ''It is also the first major Anselmo to enter our collection.''The museum has received its first richly chromatic self-portrait by Chuck Close. ''This is the fourth painting by the artist to enter the collection,'' Mr. Lowry said. ''This is really a defining work by Close.'' It was bought from the artist with the help of Arne Glimcher, the artist's dealer and the chairman of PaceWildenstein, the Manhattan gallery.Another acquisition Mr. Lowry described as a defining example of an artist's work is Beuys's ''Eurasia Siberian Symphony 1963,'' from a private collection in Munich. A panel that resembles a blackboard, it has the word ''Eurasia'' written in the center in white chalk. Along the left of the canvas, also in chalk, is the phrase ''Division the Cross.'' There is also a partial cross along the top. The work is considered a metaphor for the division between Europe and Asia in the 1960's.A more recent work, Chris Burden's ''Medusa's Head'' (1989-92), is made of plywood, steel, cement rock, railroad track and seven model train cars. It is a huge globelike construction with train tracks running through it, a comment on the way human activity is eroding the planet.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/02/business/report-on-executive-pay-jc-penney-bosses-in-stock-bind.html?ref=saraleecorporation">REPORT ON EXECUTIVE PAY; J.C. Penney Bosses in Stock Bind<date>Published: April 02, 2000</date><text>MANAGEMENT experts and institutional investors constantly lobby American executives to own more stock in the companies they run. Unlike options -- which, at worst, are worth nothing -- ownership of actual shares brings a downside. When investors lose money, so do the people running the company.In a year when many old-economy stocks declined, that danger became real for top executives. Few lost as much as the bosses at J.C. Penney, the giant retailer, whose stock lost more than half its value during 1999.Most companies require chief executive to own stock worth three to five times their annual salary, said James A. Hatch, an executive vice president at the Compensation Resource Group, a pay consulting firm in New York. Penney is more aggressive. Its chief executive, James E. Oesterreicher, must own seven times his annual salary, according to the company's most recent proxy. The ratio declines for lower-level executives, down to one and a half times salary for store managers.In 1998, the most recent year's proxy available for Penney, Mr. Oesterreicher made $612,000. He did not own quite seven times that in early 1999, but he did hold about 80,000 shares, worth about $3 million at the time. (The shares had been worth about $4 million only a few months before.)Today, however, with J.C. Penney's stock trading at $14.875, 80,000 shares would be worth just $1.19 million. If Mr. Oesterreicher received no raise last year and still holds 80,000 shares today, he would have to buy an additional 200,000 to comply with the company's policy. Through a spokeswoman, he declined to comment.Many other chief executives find themselves in similar predicaments. Coca-Cola, Eastman Kodak, Sara Lee and Sears, Roebuck all have stock ownership policies, and all saw their price drop in 1999. To follow their own rules, executives there would have to do some serious value investing -- or persuade their boards to hand over thousands of free shares. DAVID LEONHARDT</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/26/us/listeria-fear-forces-recall-of-hot-dogs.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Listeria Fear Forces Recall of Hot Dogs<date>Published: March 26, 2000</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation has recalled 34,500 pounds of Ball Park hot dogs after samples tested positive for the listeria bacterium, the United States Agriculture Department said.Sara Lee, based in Chicago, recalled one-pound packages of its Ball Park Beef Franks and one-pound packages of Ball Park Franks made with beef, pork and turkey. Packages bear the code APR03 EST 12PAB, the department said.Listeria can cause fever, headaches, nausea and neck stiffness. It is most dangerous to children, the elderly, pregnant women and people with weakened immune systems.No illnesses have been connected with the recalled hot dogs, said Carol Blake, a spokeswoman for the agency.The hot dogs were packaged in Philadelphia and distributed in New York, New Jersey, Connecticut, Delaware, Florida, Kansas, Missouri, Maryland, Massachusetts, Nebraska, Virginia, Ohio, Oklahoma, Texas and Pennsylvania.The move comes as the company tries to polish a wholesome image tarnished by the nationwide recall in December 1998 of about 15 million pounds of hot dogs and luncheon meat after listeria was spotted. The meat was linked 21 deaths and more than 100 illnesses in 22 states.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/25/business/world-business-briefing-europe-courtaulds-accepts-bid.html?ref=saraleecorporation">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; COURTAULDS ACCEPTS BID<date>Published: March 25, 2000</date><text>A British clothing supplier, Courtaulds Textiles P.L.C., agreed to a sweetened offer from the Sara Lee Corporation of Chicago that values the company, which makes Gossard lingerie, at $238 million, or 145 pence ($2.31) a share. Courtaulds, the top global supplier of clothes for private labels, had dismissed an earlier offer of 100 pence a share. Alan Cowell</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/14/arts/footlights.html?ref=saraleecorporation">FOOTLIGHTS<date>Published: March 14, 2000</date><text>NEWSSplendor of RomeFrom France came Jean-Honore Fragonard and Jacques-Louis David. From Germany came Anton Raphael Mengs. From Switzerland came Angelika Kauffman. Their destination was Rome, the Rome of the 18th century, the artistic capital of Europe, where civic and religious leaders were constructing and embellishing churches, palaces, fountains, public plazas, gardens and galleries. To this Rome of the Trevi Fountain, the Spanish Steps, carnivals and papal ceremonies flocked amateur, student and professional artists from throughout the Western world. Beginning on Thursday, the Philadelphia Museum of Art will attempt to recapture the vitality and diversity of this time in ''The Splendor of 18th-Century Rome.'' Scheduled to run through May 28, the exhibition consists of some 440 paintings, sculptures, works on paper, decorative objects and architectural renderings.Time MachineFor those who missed the World's Fair of 1939-40, who never saw the Trylon and Perisphere in their heyday or applauded Billy Rose's Aquacade, or visited the General Motors Futurama or laid eyes on Elsie the Cow or gawked at the parachute jump, a door to the past opens at 8 p.m. on Saturday. In the newly restored theater of the landmark Town Hall at 137-35 Northern Boulevard, near Main Street in Flushing, Queens, Pierre Montiel will serve as guide to a glory of another era. Mr. Montiel, a photo-archivist and New York historian who researches world's fairs and collects their pictures, souvenirs and data, will show some 200 of his color slides of the Fair while telling anecdotes about it. To set the mood, the 1999 MAC Award-winning cabaret performer Sammy Goldstein will sings songs of the 1930's.Last ChanceA final opportunity to see 52 works by great artists from Claude Monet to Henry Moore who span the years from 1870 to 1960 is at hand at the Art Institute of Chicago. The museum is the last stop for ''Monet to Moore: The Millennium Gift of Sara Lee Corporation'' before this donation is dispersed to 25 museums in the United States and 15 abroad. The Art Institute is the greatest beneficiary of the donation, receiving 12 masterworks, including works by Degas, Gauguin, Leger, Matisse, Gauguin and Pissarro. The exhibition will continue through May 29. LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/02/business/world-business-briefing-europe-defensive-measures.html?ref=saraleecorporation">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; DEFENSIVE MEASURES<date>Published: March 02, 2000</date><text>Fighting a hostile $165 million bid from the Sara Lee Corporation, Courtaulds Textiles P.L.C. of Britain said it would return more than $79 million to shareholders. The move pushed its stock up by as much as 9 percent, or 11.5 pence, to 137 pence. Courtaulds, the manufacturer of products including Gossard and Berlei lingerie, said it would sell a residual furniture business, its Lyle &amp; Scott sportswear brand and George Rech clothing brand. It would then buy back an unspecified number of shares for up to 175 pence each.Alan Cowell</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/15/business/world-business-briefing-europe-bid-for-courtalds.html?ref=saraleecorporation">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; BID FOR COURTALDS<date>Published: February 15, 2000</date><text>Courtaulds Textiles P.L.C., a clothing maker whoseshares have declined 73 percent in five years, rejected a $165 million takeover bid from the Sara Lee Corporation, saying that the company's worth is ''very significantly in excess'' of the offer. The cash offer of 100 pence a share was 60 percent more than the 62.5 pence closing price of Courtaulds on Friday. Shares of Courtaulds rose 84 percent, to 115 pence, suggesting that investors are expecting a higher bid. Sara Lee said that it was eager to expand in Europe.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/01/business/company-news-sara-lee-completes-3-billion-stock-buyback.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE COMPLETES $3 BILLION STOCK BUYBACK<date>Published: February 01, 2000</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said yesterday that it had completed a $3 billion repurchase of about 114 million shares five months ahead of the company's target of June 30. Sara Lee also said its board had approved the repurchase of an additional 73 million shares, up from 23 million previously authorized. The Chicago-based food and consumer products giant currently has about 883 million shares outstanding valued at approximately $16.2 billion. The commitment to repurchase $3 billion worth of common stock by the end of the 2000 fiscal year in July was part of a revamping announced in 1997.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/01/nyregion/c-corrections-618454.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Corrections<date>Published: February 01, 2000</date><text>An article in Business Day on Friday about John H. Bryan, who is stepping down as chief executive of the Sara Lee Corporation, misstated the location of Rhodes College, from which he graduated. It is in Memphis, not Mississippi.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/28/business/sara-lee-sets-timetable-for-shift-in-power.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Sets Timetable for Shift in Power<date>Published: January 28, 2000</date><text>Correction AppendedJohn H. Bryan, the longtime top executive at Sara Lee who helped transform the company into one of the world's largest consumer packaged goods concerns, said today that he would step down as chief executive in July.Shares of Sara Lee have been suffering for more than a year, partly because of weakness in a mature food and consumer products industry. But Mr. Bryan, whose tenure of 25 years as chief executive is one of the longest at a major American corporation, said today that the recent performance of the Sara Lee Corporation was solid and that his departure was part of a succession plan put in place three years ago.''I've always said I would retire at 65, and it seems to me this is a fairly orderly way to do it,'' said Mr. Bryan, who is 63. ''I've never felt better. The management is in good shape, and the company is performing at a very high level.''Mr. Bryan will remain chairman until he retires in October 2001. The chief executive duties will be assumed by C. Steven McMillan, Sara Lee's 54-year-old president and chief operating officer, who has worked under Mr. Bryan for 24 years.Analysts praised the decision, saying it was indicative of a company that charted a cautious and predictable course of solid earnings growth throughout Mr. Bryan's tenure.''There's no such thing as a revolution at this company; things evolve,'' said William Maguire, an analyst at Wassterstein Perella Securities. ''McMillan is a fine operator, adroit politically.'' Mr. Maguire added, though, that the new chief executive would probably look at whether Sara Lee had the right structure for the next decade.Shares of Sara Lee, based in Chicago, fell 37.5 cents today, to $18.4375.Mr. McMillan will take over a $20 billion conglomerate that owns brands like Hanes underwear, Playtex bras, Coach leather goods, Ball Park hot dogs and Sara Lee baked goods.When Mr. Bryan became chief executive in 1975, the company was called Consolidated Foods and had revenue of about $2.4 billion. Now, after a series of big acquisitions, Sara Lee has leading brands in everything from coffee and tea to cosmetics and pantyhose.Though the company has had a string of quarters with double-digit percentile earnings growth, it stumbled badly last year after a huge recall of bacteria-tainted hot dogs resulted in millions of dollars of write-offs and a battery of lawsuits. Shares of Sara Lee are down more than 35 percent the last year.Correction: February 1, 2000, Tuesday An article in Business Day on Friday about John H. Bryan, who is stepping down as chief executive of the Sara Lee Corporation, misstated the location of Rhodes College, from which he graduated. It is in Memphis, not Mississippi.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/18/sports/tennis-sanex-sponsor-for-wta-tour.html?ref=saraleecorporation">TENNIS; Sanex Sponsor For WTA Tour<date>Published: November 18, 1999</date><text>Bart McGuire, C.E.O. of the WTA Tour, confirmed yesterday that the tour, which lacked a title sponsor for the 1999 season, has completed a five-year deal with Sanex, a subsidiary of the $20 billion Sara Lee Corporation. As of Jan. 1, 2000, the professional women's tennis tour will be known as the Sanex WTA Tour. Though neither party would confirm the amount of the contract, it is believed to be worth $35 million over the next five years.Sanex is a European-based firm that distributes hair and skin-care products in 20 nations but does not have a presence in North America, a situation that is expected to change during the course of the partnership. In exchange for financial support, the women's tour, which has events in 29 countries and has its corporate base in Stamford, Conn., will presumably provide the brand with worldwide exposure.''We believe that we can bring to Sanex, as well as Sanex brings to us, and that is the essence of a good partnership. Sanex brings to us a sponsorship and a sponsorship fee that is substantially greater than the tour has ever had in the history of its existence,'' McGuire said.Sanex, which launched itself in Spain 15 years ago with a shower gel, is marketed throughout Europe and expanding into Asia.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/31/business/acquisition-by-sara-lee.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Acquisition by Sara Lee<date>Published: August 31, 1999</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said today that it had acquired the closely held D. Canale Food Services Inc. for an undisclosed price. Sara Lee said Canale, which is based in Memphis, had annual sales of more than $55 million. The company distributes groceries, frozen foods, meat and poultry, seafood and dairy products. Sara Lee said the purchase would expand its PYA/Monarch food-service business, which is based in Greenvile, S.C.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/04/business/company-news-sara-lee-to-acquire-2-brands-from-dawson.html?ref=saraleecorporation">COMPANY NEWS; SARA LEE TO ACQUIRE 2 BRANDS FROM DAWSON<date>Published: August 04, 1999</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation, maker of clothing brands that include Hanes and Playtex, will pay $95.7 million in cash to buy two businesses from Dawson International P.L.C. to increase its European sales. The companies signed a letter of intent last month and have received American regulatory approval. Dawson, based Scotland, said it was selling its Duofold and J E Morgan brands to focus on making cashmere products. With the purchase, Sara Lee, based in Chicago, expands its business in brand-name clothing, which generates more than a third of its annual revenue, and extends its foothold in Europe. The company, which also makes Sara Lee baked goods and Jimmy Dean meats, had revenue of $20 billion in fiscal 1998.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/23/business/sara-lee-buys-wechsler.html?ref=saraleecorporation">Sara Lee Buys Wechsler<date>Published: June 23, 1999</date><text>The Sara Lee Corporation said today that it had acquired the Wechsler Coffee Corporation, a privately held coffee and beverage marketer, for an undisclosed price. Wechsler Coffee, based in Moonachie, N.J., has annual revenue of more than $110 million. Sara Lee, the Chicago-based consumer packaged-goods giant, produces brands including Hanes, Sara Lee, Playtex and Hillshire Farms.</text></article></page></root>
