<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Schlumberger"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/schlumberger-in-russian-joint-venture-deal/?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger in Russian Joint Venture Deal<date>November 9, 2011, 7:53 am</date><text>Mike Fuentes/Bloomberg NewsA Choice Exploration roughneck works on a Schlumberger oil and natural gas well in Liberty County, Texas in 2007. LONDON — Integra, a Russian oil services group, announced plans on Wednesday to spin off a joint venture with the American energy giant Schlumberger and list the company on the London Stock Exchange. Under the terms of the deal, Integra said it would combine its seismic services, which are used to pinpoint oil reserves and which it runs as a joint venture with Schlumberger, with those of the privately owned Geotech Oil Services of Russia. The new company, to be called IG Seismic Services, would focus on the Russian and Central Asian markets, and would apply for a London listing by the end of the third quarter next year, Integra said. Article Tools E-mail Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink The spinoff does not plan to use the listing to raise funds, the company added. “The creation of IGSS brought together Integra Group’s vast experience in Russia and the C.I.S. with the unique seismic technology and expertise of Schlumberger,” Integra’s chief executive, Antonio Campo, said in a statement. “The combination of IGSS with Geotech Holding will create one of the largest land and transition zone seismic companies in the world.” Integra said the new venture would lead to about $15 million in one-time savings. The listing also could provide an exit for some of Geotech’s shareholders, which include the private equity firms Farallon Capital Management and PineBridge Investments. Morgan Stanley and the law firm Dewey &amp; LeBoeuf advised Integra, and JPMorgan Chase and the law firm Latham &amp; Watkins advised Geotech.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/17/business/energy-environment/17oil.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">As Iraq Oil Industry Rebuilds, American Subcontractors Dominate the Work<date>Published: June 16, 2011</date><text>MOSCOW — When Iraq auctioned rights to rebuild and expand its oil industry two years ago, the Russian company Lukoil won a hefty portion — a field holding about 10 percent of Iraq’s known oil reserves.It seemed a geopolitical victory for Lukoil. And because only one of the 11 fields that the Iraqis auctioned off  went to an American oil company — Exxon Mobil — it also seemed as if few petroleum benefits would flow to the country that took the lead role in the war, the United States. The auction’s outcome helped defuse criticism in the Arab world that the United States had invaded Iraq for its oil. “No one, even the United States, can steal the oil,” the Iraqi government spokesman, Ali al-Dabbagh, said at the time. But American companies can, apparently, drill for the oil. In fact, American drilling companies stand to make tens of billions of dollars from the new petroleum activity in Iraq long before any of the oil producers start seeing any returns on their investments. Lukoil and many of the other international oil companies that won fields in the auction are now subcontracting mostly with the four largely American oil services companies that are global leaders in their field: Halliburton, Baker Hughes, Weatherford International and Schlumberger. Those four have won the largest portion of the subcontracts to drill for oil, build wells and refurbish old equipment. “Iraq is a huge opportunity for contractors,” Alex Munton, a Middle East analyst for Wood Mackenzie, a research and consulting firm based in Edinburgh, said by telephone. Mr. Munton estimated that about half of the $150 billion the international majors are expected to invest at Iraqi oil fields over the next decade would go to drilling subcontractors — most of it to the big four operators, which all have ties to the Texas oil industry. Halliburton and Baker Hughes are based in Houston, as is the drilling unit of Schlumberger, which is based in Paris. Weatherford, though now incorporated in Switzerland, was founded in Texas and still has big operations there. Michael Klare, professor of peace and world security studies at Hampshire College and an authority on oil and conflict, said that American oil services companies were generally dominant both in the Middle East and globally because of their advanced drilling technology. So it is no surprise, he said, they came out on top in Iraq, too — whatever the initial diplomatic appearances. United States officials have said that American experts who advised the Iraqi oil ministry about ways to restore and increase petroleum production did so without seeking any preferences for American companies. And immediately after the 2009 auction round won by Lukoil, the United States Embassy spokesman in Baghdad, Philip Frayne, told Reuters that “the results of the bid round should lay to rest the old canard that the U.S. intervened in Iraq to secure Iraqi oil for American companies.” But Professor Klare said that the American officials who had advised the Iraqi government on its contracting decisions almost certainly expected American oil services companies to win a good portion of the business there, regardless who won the primary contracts. “There’s no question that they would assume as much,” he said. The American oil services companies, which have been in Iraq for years on contract with the United States occupation authorities and military, are expanding their presence even as the American military prepares to pull out. For example, Halliburton, once led by former Vice President Dick Cheney, has 600 employees in Iraq today and said in a statement that it intended to hire several hundred more before the end of the year. “We continue to win significant contracts in Iraq, and are investing heavily in our infrastructure,” Halliburton said. The 11 contracts Iraq signed with oil majors, including the six for the largest fields, are intended to raise Iraqi output from about 2.5 million barrels of oil a day now to 12 million barrels daily in 2017. Some of the oil services contracts are for repairing currently productive fields, others to tap mostly unused sites. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/03/05/energy-geeks-converge-at-m-i-t/?ref=schlumbergerltd">Energy Geeks Converge on M.I.T.<date>March 5, 2011, 2:30 pm</date><text>Tom Zeller Jr./The New York Times A view through the doughnut-shaped, blimp-inspired, high-altitude wind turbine from the upstart company Altaeros. It made a big impression Friday night at the M.I.T. Energy Conference. Put on a blindfold, throw a dart at a calendar, and you’ll probably pierce a date on which an energy conference is being held somewhere around the world. But while many are more lavishly underwritten, few can match the unbridled enthusiasm of the annual energy fête — entirely organized by students — at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Now in its sixth year, the M.I.T. Energy Conference has established itself as a popular destination for industry wonks, venture capitalists and freelance energy geeks looking for a glimpse into how techno-visionaries hope to solve a daunting problem: providing energy for the planet’s six billion people reliably, affordably and, ideally, without making a mess. Little pessimism was on display at Friday night’s “Energy Showcase.” Tom Zeller Jr. The company StranWind was showing off vertical-axis wind turbines aimed at small wind markets. Against an ambient backdrop of bubbly live jazz and $9 beers, StranWind’s vertical axis turbine, designed for residential or commercial customers, turned a lot of heads — even if Clark Gellings, a vice president for technology at the Electric Power Research Institute, dismissed small-scale wind as uneconomical during a Grid 101 session earlier in the day. Across the room, Altaeros Energies, a start-up headed by M.I.T. and Harvard graduates, set its sights on the other end of the wind power spectrum: the tiny but emerging high-altitude wind market. Inside the ballroom of the Westin Hotel in the Back Bay neighborhood of Boston, the inflatable contraption towered somewhat cartoonishly above the cheerful conference-goers. In practice, though, Altaeros’s device — a giant helium-filled shroud in the shape of a jet engine with a conventional wind turbine inside — would be tethered like a kite up to 2,000 feet in the air, accessing stronger and more sustained winds while overcoming some of the challenges of land and sea-based wind power. Nearby, Tyler Bronder, a senior software engineer for OPower, used an iPad to explain the Virginia-based company’s suite of consumer-facing smart-grid applications to a wine-sipping patron. “I’m not lazy,” his bright blue T-shirt explained. “I’m energy efficient.” Looking a bit lonely against the back wall of the ballroom, the oil and gas services company Schlumberger highlighted the technologies behind shale gas exploration and extraction. Chunks of shale rock and other geologic specimens were on display, while Abigail Matteson, an oilfield services manager, fielded the occasional question about hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, and the natural gas industry in general — which has earned a reputation for water pollution. Tom Zeller Jr./The New York Times Tyler Bronder of OPower explains how his company’s software empowers consumers to save energy. The fracking, Ms. Matteson explained to a small group, happens well below the water table, so the hazards there are minimal — a position long held by the industry. Potential problems do exist with fluid and wastewater handling at the surface, Ms. Matteson conceded, adding that the industry is working to address those. Meanwhile, just outside the main ballroom, XL Hybrids, another start-up with M.I.T. roots, slipped lights and mirrors under the jacked-up backside of a black sedan, so visitors could admire its work. The company converts fleet vehicles — chiefly late-model Lincoln Town Cars, Ford Crown Victorias, and Mercury Grand Marquis — into hybrid electrics by adding regenerative braking technology. Improvements in solar cells, a hydrokinetic turbine for small streams and canals, and a variety of innovative energy storage ideas were among the dozens of other displays — including a proposal for giant concrete spherical containers that could act as batteries for excess power. Gokhan Dundar, a first-year masters student at M.I.T., explained that the 30-meter spheres would be relatively cheap to make and could take advantage of pressure differentials at certain ocean depths. Excess power from, say, an offshore wind facility — or even a land-based power plant — could be used to pump water out of the spheres, which sit on the ocean floor. When that power is needed later, a valve would allow high-pressure ocean water to flow back in, spin a turbine inside and send the juice to shore. “I don’t have a business card,” Mr. Dundar, who is from Turkey, said apologetically. “But if you e-mail me I can send you all the details.” Angel investors, meet Mr. Dundar.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/15/science/earth/15rig.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Documents Detail Risky Decisions Before BP Well Blowout<date>Published: June 14, 2010</date><text>Internal BP documents, including an e-mail message calling the well drilled by the Deepwater Horizon a “nightmare,” show a pattern of risky choices made to save time and money in the weeks before the disastrous April 20 blowout, according to a letter sent to the oil company by the leaders of a House committee on Monday.The leaders of the House Committee on Energy and Commerce cited five areas in which the company had made decisions that “increased the danger of a catastrophic well,” including the choice for the design of the well, preparations for and tests of the cement job and assurances that the well was properly sealed on the top. Taken together, the documents offer the strongest case yet that BP bears much of the responsibility for the catastrophic explosion that killed 11 workers and the still-unchecked leaking of millions of gallons of oil into the Gulf of Mexico. Some of the decisions appeared to violate industry guidelines and were made despite warnings from BP’s own employees and outside contractors, said the committee chairman, Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, and Representative Bart Stupak, Democrat of Michigan. They sent their letter to BP’s chief executive, Tony Hayward, in advance of his testimony this week before the committee. An investigation suggested that delays in completing the well “created pressure to take shortcuts,” the letter said, and found that corners were cut in designing the well, in preparing for and testing the cementing job, and in assuring that the well was properly sealed at the top. A BP spokeswoman, Anne Kolton, said that Mr. Hayward would testify before the committee on Thursday. According to the committee schedule, the hearing will be before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, headed by Mr. Stupak. “I’m sure these issues will be covered at the hearing,” she said. The committee leaders said that shortly before the blowout, BP engineers chose a faster, less expensive design for the final string of casing, the steel pipe that lines the well. The design chosen, which used a so-called tapered string, cost about $7 million to $10 million less than another method. But the tapered string afforded less protection if the cementing job were poor and gas were to rise up the well, the congressmen wrote. The choice of the casing design was previously disclosed in The New York Times. In an exchange of e-mail messages in the week before the blowout, BP drilling engineers discussed the casing plans, with one, Brian P. Morel, asking another for a quick review of one schematic diagram. “Sorry for the late notice,” Mr. Morel wrote, “this has been nightmare well which has everyone all over the place.” Time and money were both concerns, the two representatives wrote, because the well was behind schedule. A problem in March had forced the company to apply for a “bypass,” in which a well is drilled around a problem area. By the day of the blowout, the Deepwater Horizon, leased by BP from Transocean for about half a million dollars a day plus contractors’ fees, was 43 days late for its next drilling location, the committee leaders wrote. The choice of a tapered string meant that the well had only two barriers to upward gas flow that could cause a blowout: cement near the bottom of the well and a seal assembly near the top. The congressmen described three flawed decisions relating to the cement, and said the company also decided not to use a device called a “lockdown sleeve” to ensure that the top seal would hold. Among the decisions relating to the cement, the congressmen said, BP opted to use far fewer “centralizers,” devices to keep the final string of casing centered in the well hole and help assure that cement flows evenly around the outside of the casing. BP used six instead of the 21 recommended by the cement contractor, Halliburton, which warned of a potential for a “severe gas flow problem.” A BP official complained in an April 16 e-mail message that it would take 10 hours to install the recommended number. “I do not like this,” he wrote. In addition, the congressmen wrote, BP did not fully circulate heavy drilling mud through the well — which would have taken about 12 hours — before proceeding with the cement job. The congressmen noted that the American Petroleum Institute, a trade group, recommends full circulation before cement work to reduce the possibility that the mud will contaminate the cement, which could contribute to its failure. BP also did not order a cement bond log, a testing procedure that would have more fully evaluated the quality of the cement barrier. BP’s own engineers had run computer models suggesting that a good cement job was unlikely, and the company had a crew from Schlumberger on hand to conduct the test, which would have taken up to 12 hours. But BP officials decided not to proceed with the test and the Schlumberger workers left the Deepwater Horizon the morning of the disaster.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/24/business/24bizbriefs-PROFITISDOWN_BRF.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Profit Is Down, but the Outlook Is Up at Schlumberger<date>Published: April 24, 2010</date><text>Schlumberger, a provider of oil field services, posted a 28 percent decline in first-quarter income but said it saw signs of improving demand. The company said it earned $672 million, or 56 cents a share, compared with $938 million, or 78 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell 6.7 percent, to $5.6 billion from $6 billion. But the company said evidence was mounting that higher oil prices would lead to increased drilling activity by its international customers. Shares of Schlumberger, which is based in Houston, rose $4.50, or 6.6 percent, to $72.68.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/03/25/schlumberger-taps-1-billion-deal-for-geoservices/?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Taps $1 Billion Deal for Geoservices<date>March 25, 2010, 5:58 am</date><text>Schlumberger said Wednesday that it bought a French oil services company for $1.07 billion, The Associated Press reported. Houston-based Schlumberger said it bought the Geoservices Group, a specialized company with 5,000 employees and operations in 52 companies, from French private equity firm Astorg Partners and an unspecified number of minority shareholders. Geoservices has several technologies that will combine with Schlumberger’s to help customers identify and react to drilling hazards, and bring a more complete understanding of the geology of an area, Schlumberger’s chairman and chief executive, Andrew Gould, said in a statement. In 2009, Schlumberger had revenue of $22.7 billion. Geoservices had about $491 million revenue. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Article from The Houston Chronicle » Go to Press Release from Schlumberger »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/23/business/23views.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Excess Skepticism on Schlumberger?<date>Published: February 22, 2010</date><text>Schlumberger’s shareholders have been in a state since news leaked last week of the company’s bid for Smith International, its rival in the oilfield services sector. Skeptical investors have since stripped more than $5 billion from the value of Schlumberger, the industry leader, a powerful slap in the face of its chief, Andrew F. Gould. Such punishment appears excessive. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Pat Sullivan/Associated Press Investors rebuked Andrew F. Gould, of Schlumberger, over his bid for Smith. Add to Portfolio Schlumberger Ltd Smith International Inc Go to your Portfolio » True, Mr. Gould has not negotiated a bargain for Smith. By Schlumberger’s own account, cost savings will be just $320 million a year by 2012. Taxed and capitalized, these would be worth about $2 billion to shareholders. So, by offering a $3 billion premium, at $45.84 a share, Schlumberger looks to be destroying around $1 billion of value. But Schlumberger’s big tumble suggests that investors fear Smith may prove an even bigger liability. The deal may indeed tie up precious management time as the antitrust process grinds forward. Baker Hughes is still in a holding pattern while regulators vet the purchase of BJ Services, which it announced in August. Apart from these anxieties, however, the deal has some powerful strategic logic on its side. It is hard to see a financial exploding gun in Smith’s balance sheet. The company’s $1.2 billion of debt is small potatoes for Schlumberger, which has cash and short-term investments of $4.6 billion. Moreover, the absence of a significant drill-maker, Smith’s forte, in Schlumberger’s product line is becoming an embarrassing omission. Recent oil finds are forcing companies to drill deeper for oil  more than six miles down in the case of BP’s giant find in the Gulf of Mexico. Complex shale gas operations are demanding ever more sophisticated drilling technology. As extracting oil and gas becomes tougher, making sure that tools work perfectly together is becoming crucial. Mr. Gould has his sights set on a new generation of drilling technology. Meanwhile, giant state-run oil companies are increasingly demanding a full-service option. Even if the deal fails to deliver a boost to revenue once the companies combine, it is hard to see how it can hurt them. Shareholders’ lack of faith in Schlumberger’s management is unfair. Mr. Gould has his work cut out proving investors wrong. Merrill’s Fickle Fancy At least one legacy of the old Merrill Lynch is thriving at Bank of America: the kiss-off then embrace-back. The bank just rehired two former Merrill rainmakers who left in the dislocation after the broker’s sale to Bank of America in the financial panic of late 2008. While not an uncommon practice on Wall Street, few firms have made welcoming back bankers as much of a habit as Merrill Lynch has. In the latest instance, it lured Sam Chapin and Todd Kaplan to return as executive vice chairmen of global banking, reporting to Tom Montag, who runs investment banking and trading. Mr. Chapin and Mr. Kaplan, who will focus on clients, have a combined 48 years of Merrill tenure. With the integration of Bank of America and Merrill more settled, it is a good sign the combined institution can win back relatively experienced hands who also know how to win business. Rivals have tried similar back-to-the-future maneuvers. Lazard just welcomed back Felix Rohatyn, its octogenarian former senior partner and Wall Street elder statesman. Morgan Stanley begged John J. Mack to return to run the firm in 2005, four years after he had been ousted. But Merrill seems especially fond of its exiles. E. Stanley O’Neal cut too deeply in the bond market rout of the early part of the century while he was chief executive. To catch up quickly, Merrill rehired some traders, many of whom wound up taking big risks in subprime and structured finance. That led to billions of losses and Mr. O’Neal’s ouster. To help clean up the mess, his successor, John A. Thain, rehired a former fixed-income executive, Jeffrey Kronthal, who departed a year earlier because he thought Merrill was taking too many risks. Flexibility in hiring the best people for the job isn’t necessarily a bad thing, if it shows pragmatism. On the other hand, Merrill’s repetitive practice of having to win back executives it once kicked to the curb suggests a troubling management style. That could be expensive for shareholders, particularly if Merrill has to pay to let people go and then do the same to win them back. CHRISTOPHER SWANN and ROB COX More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 23, 2010, on page B2 of the National edition.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/22/business/energy-environment/22deal.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Oil Servicer to Buy Rival in $11 Billion Agreement<date>Published: February 21, 2010</date><text>Schlumberger, the giant oilfield-services company, announced on Sunday that it would acquire Smith International in an all-stock transaction valued at $45.84 a share. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Schlumberger Ltd Smith International Inc Go to your Portfolio » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » The purchase price works out to more than $11 billion, based on the 247.4 million Smith shares outstanding in November. It would be the biggest acquisition in the United States so far this year. The deal, if completed, would position Schlumberger well ahead of its next-largest rival, Halliburton. And it would keep Schlumberger growing apace with the oil sector itself, where producers have also been looking for acquisitions. The giants of the oil industry want to combine with smaller companies that already own or control oil and gas fields to increase their reserves without finding new places to drill. Oilfield-services companies like Schlumberger are seeking to expand as well, so that they can offer bigger clients more products and services. Schlumberger reported revenue of $22.7 billion in 2009, while Smith had $8.2 billion in revenue last year. Smith is the industry’s biggest provider of drilling fluids, and the second-biggest provider of drill bits, according to a report issued last week by RBC Capital Markets. The report said that by acquiring Smith’s drill-bit business, Schlumberger would secure a “critical link” in the chain of products and services that it sells to oil and gas producers. A statement posted on Schlumberger’s Web site said the offer was a 37.5 percent premium over Smith’s closing stock price on Thursday. Smith’s stock rose about 13 percent on Friday, after The Wall Street Journal reported, citing unnamed sources, that a merger was close. Schlumberger’s stock price fell about 3 percent on Friday. Smith shareholders would receive 0.6966 of a Schlumberger share for each share they owned. The terms, which the statement said had been approved by both companies’ boards, would leave Smith’s current shareholders with 12.8 percent of Schlumberger’s outstanding common stock. The transaction must be approved by Smith’s shareholders and by antitrust regulators. The companies’ statement said that they expected the deal to close in the second half of this year. Schlumberger said it would realize a pretax savings of about $160 million in 2011 and $320 million in 2012, after subtracting the costs of absorbing Smith’s operations. The company is expected to shed some operations to satisfy antitrust regulators. The two companies already had extensive industry ties. They own a 60-40 joint venture called M-I Swaco, which supplies drilling fluids to the oil and gas sector. Smith’s chief executive, John Yearwood, is a former Schlumberger executive. Schlumberger operates corporate headquarters in Paris, the Hague and Houston. Smith is based in Houston. Schlumberger’s chief executive, Andrew F. Gould, said in the statement that the company believed that more drilling, in increasingly difficult environments, was necessary to meet world energy demand. The statement also said that adding Smith’s drilling fluids and other products to Schlumberger’s lines would help clients drill more economically under increasingly challenging conditions. The company did not respond to a call requesting further information. In the statement, Mr. Yearwood said, “Our customers will see accelerated technology development” through the acquisition. Schlumberger had a weak performance last year as the global recession cut demand for energy, which affected drilling. As the economy has shown signs of recovery, oil prices have risen. Schlumberger’s latest earnings report, in January, predicted that its businesses would improve as energy demand grew. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 22, 2010, on page B3 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/02/19/schlumberger-in-talks-to-buy-smith-report-says/?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger in Talks to Buy Smith, Report Says<date>February 19, 2010, 5:46 am</date><text>Schlumberger, the oil services company, is in advanced talks to acquire another major industry player, Smith International, The Wall Street Journal reported. The newspaper, citing people familiar with the negotiations, said the deal could be announced in the coming days. While it said it was unable to determine the price of the potential deal, The Journal said that with Smith’s market value coming in at around $7.5 billion, and the addition of a 20 percent deal premium, the price tag may be in the neighborhood of $9 billion. In response to the article, Shawn Housley, director of investor relations at Smith International, told The Associated Press that the company ”does not respond to rumors of this variety.” A spokesman for Schlumberger did not immediately respond to DealBook’s request for comment. Schlumberger struggled last year as the global recession weakened energy demand and discouraged drilling operations around the world. But prices have since rebounded, and the company said in its most recent earnings report in January that its business will benefit as countries burn more fuel, the news service noted. Go to Article from The Wall Street Journal » Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DD1731F930A15752C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=schlumbergerltd">BUSINESS BRIEFING | COMPANIES; Schlumberger Posts a Decline In Fourth-Quarter Profit<date>Published: January 23, 2010</date><text>Schlumberger said Friday that oil drilling has started to recover after a sharp decline in crude prices last year reduced the company's fourth-quarter profit by 31 percent. The company, one of the nation's leading oil services providers, struggled last year as the global recession sapped energy demand and discouraged drilling operations around the world. Schlumberger said it earned $795 million, or 65 cents a share, in the quarter, down from $1.15 billion, or 95 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell 16.4 percent, to $5.74 billion from $6.87 billion.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/14/realestate/commercial/14Real.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Houston, the Oil Town, Is Sharing in a Boom<date>Published: March 14, 2007</date><text>HOUSTON  The good times are back. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic Transactions Michael Stravato for the New York Times Chevron has leased the 1.2-million-square-foot tower that used to be Enrons headquarters and plans to move in this year. Galvanized by the record profits at energy companies, this city, the center of the countrys energy industry, has shaken off the effects of the Enron implosion six years ago and is enjoying its strongest resurgence in more than 20 years, business officials and real estate developers say. Some energy companies are expanding and putting up new buildings. Others, like Citgo, Schlumberger and Halliburton, have moved their headquarters to Houston. Oil and natural gas companies have helped reduce office vacancy rates to 15 percent, a five-year low, according to Grubb &amp; Ellis, a real estate company. Job growth is double the national average  97,400 jobs were created in 2006. The National Association of Realtors says the housing market in Houston is one of the strongest in the country. The increase in the oil business has made Houston, said Randall Davis, a Houston condominium developer. It feels a touch like the 1980s  everyone is out, the restaurants are full, the bars are full. Its like New York. The good news extends across the city. The port recently opened a $1.4 billion container terminal to tackle soaring traffic. In 2006, it handled 1.6 million 20-foot containers, up 29 percent from 2003. At the Texas Medical Center, hospitals and universities are investing billions in new facilities. Residential and mixed-use developments are going up downtown. The Houston economy has been growing since 2004, when energy companies started investing more in big-ticket projects and hiring thousands of employees to run them. Before that, oil companies had been hesitant to pour more into exploration and production, because they had lost millions in the past when oil and natural gas prices collapsed. There was always a real reluctance to buy into the commodity cycle, said Robert W. Gilmer, vice president and senior economist at the Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas. Those fears are long gone. Real estate investors, enticed by rising rents and occupancy rates, are returning. Over the last five years, sale prices for office buildings in Houston have climbed by 34 percent, to an average of $129 a square foot in 2006, according to Real Capital Analytics, a national research and consulting firm. Compared with other large cities nationwide, like Chicago and San Francisco, where prices average $191 and $338 a square foot, respectively, Houston is still a relative bargain. The office investment market has taken off, said Ariel Guerrero, Texas research and client services manager at Grubb &amp; Ellis in Houston. If you look at the price per pound, theres still value. Brookfield Properties, a New York-based real estate investment trust, seems to think so. Last October, Brookfield became the biggest landowner in downtown Houston when it joined with the Blackstone Group to buy Trizec Properties for $8.9 billion in cash and debt. The deal gave Brookfield eight buildings in Houston, for a total of 7.4 million square feet. Although the merger included properties nationwide, Richard B. Clark, the chief executive of Brookfield, said Houston was one of the deals attractions. (Almost a quarter of Brookfields portfolio is energy-related.) Chevron signed a lease shortly afterward for one of the buildings  the 1.2-million-square-foot tower that used to be Enrons headquarters  and plans to move in this year. The lease, Brookfield says, was the biggest in the country since 2000 and lowered the availability rate for Class A space downtown. In the fourth quarter, the rate dropped six percentage points, to 12 percent, according to Grubb &amp; Ellis. This confirms our belief its a strong market, Mr. Clark said. I think our timing is good, fundamentals are improving and tenants have confirmed that theyre growing. Brookfield is banking that Houston will grow even more. It is considering putting up a new office tower downtown, Mr. Clark said, but is holding off until the availability rate for Class A office space drops below 10 percent. He said he expected it to reach that point within a year. Encouraged, developers have started building again. In the fourth quarter, 2.4 million square feet of office space was under construction, more than double the amount in the third quarter. For the first time in years, developers are building without a signed tenant, though most projects are typically smaller than 500,000 square feet. Nowhere is the growth more apparent than in the citys Energy Corridor. Straddling Interstate 10 west of downtown, the area  home to companies like BP, Royal Dutch Shell, ConocoPhillips, Exxon Mobil and Citgo  has become one of the strongest real estate markets in the city. Occupancy rates are at 92 percent, the highest in the city, and rents average $19.26 a square foot, according to Grubb &amp; Ellis. When occupancy rates reached the mid-90-percent range and there were no blocks of space, we said, Hey, maybe its time to build,  said Aaron Thielhorn, a principal at Trammell Crow in Houston. 1 2 Next Page » More Articles in Real Estate »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E5DC123FF937A35751C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=schlumbergerltd">OPENERS: SUITS; ACTIVE RETIREMENT<date>Published: February 4, 2007</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oil services company, announced this month that its chief financial officer, Jean-Marc Perraud, would retire after 33 years with the company. But that did not mean that Mr. Perraud, 59, would leave the payroll or stop accruing retirement pay right away -- just some time before the end of the decade. For nearly four years after he steps down on March 1, he will advise Schlumberger's C.E.O., Andrew Gould, on financial issues, the company said. Mr. Perraud will collect his current $600,000 salary as a full-time adviser for the first nine months, then take a 25 percent pay cut when he scales back to half-time for three years. All the while, his retirement payout will continue to grow as though he were still earning his full salary. PATRICK McGEEHAN</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6D71E30F933A15752C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=schlumbergerltd">Today In Business | Schlumberger Profit Up<date>Published: January 20, 2007</date><text>Schlumberger, the oil field services provider, said its fourth-quarter profit soared because of price increases, heavy exploration activity worldwide and better-than-expected results at its seismic operation. The company predicted continued growth in 2007 and beyond. Its share price rose sharply, increasing $3.10 to close at $61 in trading. The company said net income rose 71 percent to $1.13 billion, or 92 cents per share, from $660.6 million, or 54 cents a share, a year ago. Excluding charges and credits, earnings per share in the year-ago quarter were 52 cents. Revenue climbed 33 percent to $5.35 billion from $4.02 billion. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had forecast, on average, a quarterly profit of 85 cents a share on revenue of $5.14 billion.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D8163FF932A15753C1A9609C8B63&amp;ref=schlumbergerltd">Today In Business | Oil Field Earnings Grow<date>Published: October 21, 2006</date><text>Schlumberger, the oilfield services provider, reported its fifth consecutive quarter of record profit yesterday as exploration accelerated from North America to Siberia. Net income soared 85 percent to $1 billion, or 81 cents a share, in the third quarter from $540.8 million, or 44 cents, a year earlier. The results exceeded the 77 cents expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue climbed 34 percent, to $4.95 billion. Andrew Gould, Shlumberger's chief executive, said the recent plunge in gas prices had begun to slow gas production in Canada and Shlumberger shares fell as traders speculated that lower energy prices would cut demand for the company's services. Graph shows Schlumberger shares for the week.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6D81331F934A15757C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; EARNINGS MORE THAN DOUBLE AT SCHLUMBERGER<date>Published: April 27, 2005</date><text>The oil-field services company Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that its first-quarter earnings more than doubled on improved revenue and strong activity and pricing in North America. The company's quarterly income jumped to $523.4 million, or 86 cents a share, in the January-March period from $220.3 million, or 37 cents a share, last year. Excluding special items, earnings from continuing operations before items were $390.1 million, or 65 cents a share in the latest quarter, up from $259.6 million, or 44 cents a share a year ago. Revenue rose to $3.16 billion from $2.67 billion in the year-ago quarter.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/23/business/23oilfield.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Profit at Schlumberger Misses Estimate<date>Published: October 23, 2004</date><text>y Bloomberg News Schlumberger Ltd., the oil field services company, said yesterday that it earned $318.2 million in the third quarter as oil topped $50 and producers increased spending. Profit was 53 cents a share in contrast to a loss of 9 cents, or $55.3 million, in the period a year ago. Sales rose 15 percent, to $2.93 billion. Advertisement Profit was less than analysts had expected because of losses on two drilling projects, hurricanes in the Gulf of Mexico and less activity in Venezuela. Profit excluding one-time items was 52 cents a share. On that basis, the average estimate from 25 analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call was 53 cents. Shares of Schlumberger fell $1.90, or 2.8 percent, to $65.79. Storms in the Gulf of Mexico cut Schlumberger's pretax profit by 2 cents a share, the chief executive, Andrew Gould, said on a conference call with analysts and investors. Storms cut daily oil and gas production in the region. Shares of Schlumberger have risen almost 80 percent since Mr. Gould, 57, took over as chief executive in February 2003. He has cut costs and has focused on oil fields. Schlumberger has reduced debt to $1.66 billion at the end of September from $4.18 billion at the start of the year. The company repurchased 3.8 million shares of stock in the quarter for $237 million, or an average of $61.96 a share.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/24/business/schlumberger-s-profit-triples-as-halliburton-reports-a-loss.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger's Profit Triples As Halliburton Reports a Loss<date>Published: July 24, 2004</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the oil field services company, said yesterday that its second-quarter profit tripled as it benefited from a rise in drilling activity in North America and overseas. Its rival, the Halliburton Company, posted a net loss as one-time charges outweighed the benefits of government contract work in Iraq and robust drilling activity.Schlumberger, based in New York, had net income of $356 million, or 59 cents a share, compared with $112.1 million, or 19 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.Earnings from continuing operations before one-time costs were 48 cents a share. Revenue rose 12 percent, to $2.88 billion.Oil companies around the world have increased their drilling efforts as crude oil and natural gas prices have soared and industrial demand has remained healthy.Schlumberger has sold most of its businesses not involving oil field services, strengthening its balance sheet so much in the process that its board has approved a program to buy back up to 15 million shares by December 2006.Growth in drilling operations in Russia and the Caspian Sea and across Asia and the Middle East were especially encouraging signs for Schlumberger, with North America also performing well.Still, shares of Schlumberger fell $1.25, to $63.01.Halliburton, based in Houston, reported a second-quarter net loss of $663 million, or $1.51 a share, in contrast to net income of $26 million, or 6 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier. Revenue rose 38 percent, to $5 billion. Iraq-related work contributed $1.7 billion in revenue, but added just $23 million to operating income.The loss included a charge of $609 million, or $1.39 a share, related to lower-than-expected insurance recoveries to help finance a proposed settlement of asbestos and silica class-action litigation.Excluding discontinued operations, the company lost $54 million, or 12 cents a share, in the quarter, including a charge of $200 million, or 46 cents a share, for problems related to the troubled Barracuda-Caratinga deepwater oil project in Brazil.Excluding the asbestos-related and Brazil charges, the company posted a profit of 34 cents a share, a penny better than analysts' forecasts.Shares of Halliburton fell 49 cents, to $30.55.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/05/business/world-business-briefing-europe-schlumberger-selling-shares-in-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">World Business Briefing | Europe: Schlumberger Selling Shares In Unit<date>Published: May 05, 2004</date><text>Schlumberger, the oil field services company, plans to raise as much as 689 million euros ($833 million) by selling its smart-card unit, Axalto Holding, in a share offering that began yesterday. The company offered 27.86 million Axalto shares, or 70 percent of the company, at 14.8 euros and 17.2 euros each. The number of shares may be increased to 100 percent of the stock, depending on investor demand, Axalto's chief executive, Olivier Piou, said at a presentation in Paris.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/14/business/technology-briefing-deals-ibm-buys-schlumberger-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Technology Briefing | Deals: I.B.M. Buys Schlumberger Unit<date>Published: April 14, 2004</date><text>I.B.M. said yesterday that it had acquired the disaster recovery subsidiary of Schlumberger for an undisclosed sum. The deal will add 40 business backup centers in Europe and North America to the 120 I.B.M. Global Services already operates. The deal rids Schlumberger, which is the world's largest oil services company, of one of the remnants of its expansion into business information services with the 2001 acquisition of Sema. Most of Sema was sold to Atos Origin in January in a cash-and-stock deal valued at $1.45 billion. Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/23/business/world-business-briefing-europe-france-technology-acquisition.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">World Business Briefing | Europe: France: Technology Acquisition<date>Published: September 23, 2003</date><text>The French comput-er services company Atos Origin agreed to purchase the information technology unit of Schlumberger for about 1.3 billion euros ($1.5 billion) in cash and stock. Atos will pay 400 million euros in cash and 19.3 million shares of Atos. Atos said the purchase of the unit, Schlumberger Sema, will create one of the leading information technology companies, with an annual revenue of more than 5 billion euros. Schlumberger acquired Sema in 2001 for 5.2 billion euros. Ariane Bernard (NYT)</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/25/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-sell-semiconductor-testing-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO SELL SEMICONDUCTOR-TESTING UNIT<date>Published: June 25, 2003</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., an oil field services company that is shedding assets to cut debt, agreed to sell its NPTest semiconductor-testing unit to a group led by Francisco Partners and Shah Management for $220 million in cash. Schlumberger said the sale would reduce its second-quarter profit by $12 million. The buyers may pay an additional, undisclosed sum if they sell the unit or raise money through an initial public offering of NPTest shares. Schlumberger, based in New York and Paris, withdrew an initial public offering for NPTest. That offering, which was delayed for more than a year, was expected to raise as much as $575 million, according to a regulatory filing.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/20/opinion/ready-for-the-peace.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Ready for the Peace?<date>Published: March 20, 2003</date><text>Now that U.S. strikes against Iraq have begun, we should get rid of one canard immediately, and that's the notion that criticism of the Bush administration and opposition to this invasion imply in some sense a lack of support or concern for the men and women who are under arms.The names of too many of my friends are recorded on the wall of the Vietnam Memorial for me to tolerate that kind of nonsense. I hope that the war goes well, that our troops prevail quickly and that casualties everywhere are kept to a minimum.But the fact that a war may be quick does not mean that it is wise. Against the wishes of most of the world, we have plunged not just into war, but toward a peace that is potentially more problematic than the war itself.Are Americans ready to pay the cost in lives and dollars of a long-term military occupation of Iraq? To what end?Will an occupation of Iraq increase or decrease our security here at home?Do most Americans understand that even as we are launching one of the most devastating air assaults in the history of warfare, private companies are lining up to reap the riches of rebuilding the very structures we're in the process of destroying?Companies like Halliburton, Schlumberger and the Bechtel Group understand this conflict a heck of a lot better than most of the men and women who will fight and die in it, or the armchair patriots who'll be watching on CNN and cheering them on.It's not unpatriotic to say that there are billions of dollars to be made in Iraq and that the gold rush is already under way. It's simply a matter of fact.Back in January, an article in The Wall Street Journal noted: ''With oil reserves second only to Saudi Arabia's, Iraq would offer the oil industry enormous opportunity should a war topple Saddam Hussein. But the early spoils would probably go to companies needed to keep Iraq's already rundown oil operations running, especially if facilities were further damaged in a war. Oil-services firms such as Halliburton Co., where Vice President Dick Cheney formerly served as chief executive, and Schlumberger Ltd. are seen as favorites for what could be as much as $1.5 billion in contracts.''</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/11/business/schlumberger-is-taking-a-charge-of-3.17-billion.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Is Taking A Charge of $3.17 Billion<date>Published: December 11, 2002</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., one of the world's largest oil field service companies, said yesterday that it would take $3.17 billion in charges to its fourth-quarter income, largely because of a write-down related to its purchase of an information technology company in 2001.The write-downs are part of a sizable revamping the company detailed yesterday that includes trimming 3,300 jobs from its work force of 81,000.Schlumberger warned shareholders on Monday that it would announce a comprehensive list of charges after the stock market closed yesterday. But James H. Stone, an analyst with UBS, noted that the market, when it opens today, might be somewhat surprised by the size of the write-down, in part because it includes charges for the company's seismic operations business, WesternGeco, part of its core oil field services expertise.''The size of the charge is a little bit bigger than we thought it was going to be,'' Mr. Stone said, ''but not disturbingly so.''Thomson First Call, which tracks analysts' estimates of companies' results, predicted that Schlumberger would have earnings in the quarter ending Dec. 31 of 34 cents a share, excluding one-time items.Much of the changes appear to involve a scaling back of the business unit created by the $5.2 billion purchase of the information technology company Sema, which Schlumberger shareholders criticized from the outset. The unit will focus more on regional markets where it is doing well and has the best potential rather than casting a wider net, the company said in a statement.When Schlumberger acquired Sema, Mr. Stone said, ''it thought it could marry Sema's I.T. expertise and its own oil field services strength and offer that to major oil companies around the world.''''They thought they would go in to an oil company and say, 'We should manage your I.T. service infrastructure because we know it better than a generic knowledge-management company like I.B.M. or Accenture because of being in the oil industry,' '' he continued. ''It doesn't appear to us as if they converted a lot of oil customers.''Mr. Stone noted that Sema might have been hurt by the number of clients it had in the telecommunications and energy sectors, industries that have shrunk sharply the last year.The Sema charges, which will reduce good will, will total $2.89 billion, or $4.96 a share.Despite the write-down, ''the jury is still out as to whether Sema will work efficiently with Schlumberger,'' said James K. Wicklund, managing director of energy research at Banc of America Securities. Mr. Wicklund pointed out that Schlumberger's strategy of joining oil field services with an information technology arm could still work and that the retrenching might have as much to do with the overall sluggishness in global information technology markets.The weak economy and limited oil exploration by oil companies also contributed to the cutbacks at WesternGeco, analysts said.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/21/us/exxon-led-group-is-giving-a-climate-grant-to-stanford.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Exxon-Led Group Is Giving A Climate Grant to Stanford<date>Published: November 21, 2002</date><text>Four big international companies, including the oil giant Exxon Mobil, said yesterday that they would give Stanford University $225 million over 10 years for research on ways to meet growing energy needs without worsening global warming.Exxon Mobil, whose pledge of $100 million makes it the biggest of the four contributors, issued a statement saying new techniques for producing energy while reducing emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases were ''vital to meeting energy needs in the industrialized and developing world.''Many scientists and environment experts said the Stanford project was likely to be a valuable new assault on a serious environmental problem. But some environmental campaigners said Exxon, which has long expressed skepticism about risks posed by climate change, was mainly trying to improve its image.In 2000, Ford and Exxon Mobil's global rival, BP, gave $20 million to Princeton to start a similar climate and energy research program.With the new corporate money, Stanford will create the Global Climate and Energy Project, an independent research group controlled by the university. Any resulting technologies or patents will belong to the university, Stanford officials said.Dr. Franklin M. Orr Jr., a chemical engineer, will step down as dean of the university's School of Earth Sciences to run the project.Dr. Orr said the group would focus on technologies that could provide energy without adding to a buildup of greenhouse gases linked by scientists to a warming trend that has lasted decades.Those technologies will include not only hydrogen fuel cells and solar panels but also nuclear power and methods for harnessing coal and other fossil fuels while capturing carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas released by human activities.The initiative is a small step toward what a diverse group of scientists, writing recently in the journal Science, said must be an enormous effort to find clean energy sources for an expected tripling of global demands by midcentury.In addition to Exxon Mobil, the contributors are General Electric, which said it would give $50 million; E.ON, a large German energy company with nuclear and conventional power plants, giving $50 million; and Schlumberger, the oil-field technology company, giving $25 million.Environmental campaigners noted that Exxon Mobil told investors last month that it was plowing $100 billion over the next decade into a search for new oil and gas reserves.The money for climate research is ''only one-tenth of 1 percent of what Exxon Mobil will spend over the same time exploring and developing new sources of oil and gas,'' said Pete Altman, the coordinator of a shareholder group pressing to change the company's environmental practices. That development, Mr. Altman said, ''is what is causing global warming in the first place.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/29/business/company-news-oil-field-tool-company-to-buy-drill-bit-division.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; OIL FIELD TOOL COMPANY TO BUY DRILL-BIT DIVISION<date>Published: October 29, 2002</date><text>Grant Prideco said yesterday that it had agreed to buy a drill-bit maker, Reed-Hycalog, from Schlumberger for about $345 million in cash and stock to add to its line of oil field tools. Grant Prideco will pay $255 million in cash and about 10 million of its own shares, the chief financial officer, Louis A. Raspino, said. The company will also assume about $5 million in debt from Schlumberger, an oil-services company.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/27/business/technology-briefing-hardware-applied-materials-buys-chip-inspector.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Applied Materials Buys Chip Inspector<date>Published: November 27, 2001</date><text>The world's largest manufacturer of chip-making equipment, Applied Materials, said yesterday that it had purchased a defect-detection business from Schlumberger Semiconductor Solutions. Financial terms were not disclosed. Applied Materials, based in Santa Clara, Calif., said Schlumberger's technology would complement its existing defect-detection techniques. Applied Materials, which supplies leading chip makers like Intel, uses light to find defects quickly on the surface of silicon wafers, while Schlumberger's Odyssey 300 technology uses electron beams to scan chips for flaws below the surface. As part of the deal, Applied Materials will receive patents, equipment and about 100 employees from Schlumberger Semiconductor Solutions, a division of Schlumberger Ltd. Shares of Applied Materials rose $1.30, to $40.06, while shares of Schlumberger fell $1.18, to $46.30. Chris Gaither (NYT)</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/30/world/the-hostage-business-a-special-report-kidnapping-with-money-as-the-only-object.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">THE HOSTAGE BUSINESS: A Special Report; Kidnapping With Money as the Only Object<date>Published: June 30, 2001</date><text>The first message crackled over the radio 18 days after kidnappers had taken 10 men from a remote oil-drilling site in the Amazon basin of Ecuador in October. A man with a Colombian accent who called himself Pedro demanded $80 million.In a control center in a rented house in Quito, the Ecuadorean capital, a team of specialists, some drawn from special military units and law enforcement and representing major American oil-field corporations and insurance companies, plunged into another kidnapping negotiation.Both sides knew the stakes in this deadly industry. Eight oil workers had been ransomed for $3.5 million just a year earlier. But after about two weeks of debate, the corporate side gambled with a low bid of $500,000.They lost the bet. The kidnappers killed a hostage and dumped the body on a jungle road. Then the negotiators frantically bid up the ransom offer until the surviving hostages were freed in exchange for $13 million -- 141 days after they were seized on Oct. 12 in northeast Ecuador.A week ago, the Colombian government announced that it had arrested 52 suspects who they said had played a role in this kidnapping as well as others reaching back several years. And yesterday, officials at the State Department said the United States would seek to extradite from Ecuador five of the kidnappers for taking Americans hostage.This is the face of corporate kidnapping in the 21st century. Neither politics nor ideology is at issue. It is just money -- large sums demanded by kidnappers who know what international corporations have been willing to pay to save their workers. The employers, in turn, take out large insurance policies to defray this cost of doing business in the developing world. Specialists estimate that more than $500 million a year goes to pay off professional bands of kidnappers, mostly in South America.''Kidnapping has become probably the biggest overseas worry for American corporations,'' said Brian M. Jenkins, a former United States Special Forces officer and a consultant in Santa Monica, Calif., on international crime and terrorism.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/29/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-sell-natural-gas-unit-to-hanover.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO SELL NATURAL GAS UNIT TO HANOVER<date>Published: June 29, 2001</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the provider of oil field services, agreed yesterday to sell the part of its business that compresses natural gas for shipping and storage to the Hanover Compressor Company for as much as $761 million so it can focus on helping energy explorers extract oil and gas. Hanover, based in Houston, will pay $270 million in cash and $283 million in stock, as well as give Schlumberger a $150 million note. Schlumberger will also get as much as $58 million for a joint venture Hanover will acquire, the companies said. As part of the agreement, Schlumberger will own 10 percent of Hanover.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/15/business/company-news-schlumberger-acquisition-earning-less-than-expected.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER ACQUISITION EARNING LESS THAN EXPECTED<date>Published: June 15, 2001</date><text>Schlumberger, which acquired the British computer services company Sema in April, said yesterday that revenue from the new business had been lower than expected because of a slowdown in the telecommunications industry. The Sema businesses are expected to break even in the first six months under Schlumberger, the company said. Schlumberger, a large provider of oil field services, acquired Sema, which helps businesses set up computer systems, on April 6 for about $5 billion. Analysts have been skeptical about Schlumberger's push into areas unrelated to oil field technology. Schlumberger has headquarters in New York and Paris.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/13/business/world-business-briefing-europe-schlumberger-to-acquire-sema.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; SCHLUMBERGER TO ACQUIRE SEMA<date>Published: February 13, 2001</date><text>Schlumberger, the American energy services company that has begun branching into technology services, confirmed that it had reached an agreement to acquire Sema, the British-French information technology company, for Â£3.6 billion ($5.3 billion), or 560 pence a share. With the acquisition, Schlumberger makes perhaps its largest expansion into technology services, which include smart-card operations in Europe. Schlumberger said it expected to increase revenue by selling some of its products to Sema's customers. It also said the value of the deal represented a 42 percent premium to the closing price of Sema shares on Feb. 2, the last day of trading before Sema said it had been approached by bidders. Shares of Sema surged 13 percent. Suzanne Kapner</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/12/business/schlumberger-is-reported-in-negotiations-to-buy-sema.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Is Reported in Negotiations to Buy Sema<date>Published: February 12, 2001</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the American energy services company that has begun branching out into technology, is negotiating to buy Sema, a European information technology company, in a deal valued around Â£3.5 billion, or a little more than $5 billion, people involved in the talks said today.Last month, Sema hired Rothschild and Credit Suisse First Boston to explore its options after a profit warning related to its $4.7 billion acquisition of LHS, a United States telecommunications software company. In addition to an outright sale, another possibility is dividing the business into two units, one focusing on telecommunications and the other on network services.But Schlumberger is interested in buying Sema outright, people involved in the talks said today. Sema's board met on Friday to consider a Schlumberger offer, these people said, adding that a decision could be reached in the next few weeks.Schlumberger and Sema executives both declined to comment today.For Schlumberger, of New York, the purchase would give it a beachhead in Britain, where the information technology business has been dominated by Electronic Data Systems, the Texas computer services giant founded by Ross Perot and now run by Richard H. Brown, former chief executive of Cable and Wireless.Schlumberger, which has been building its technology interests, said on Friday that it had agreed to buy a smart-card unit, called CP8, from Bull of France for 350 million euros, or $324 million.Nevertheless, technology-related activities are still a small part of Schlumberger's revenue and profit. In 1999, the most recent full year for which there are figures, technology and services contributed just 6 percent of pretax profit that totaled $470 million, and 14 percent of the company's $8.7 billion in revenue.Sema has been under pressure since November, when its shares dropped 44 percent in one day, after it warned that its earnings would not meet analysts' estimates. In January, it reiterated that income for all of 2000 and forecasts for 2001 would fall below expectations when it reports its financial results on Feb. 20.Sema also said that it would search for a successor to its chief executive, Pierre Bonelli, who has come under fire, in part because of the LHS acquisition. Also needling shareholders were the actions of Hartmut Lademacher, the former chairman of LHS, who sold shares in Sema soon after the acquisition deal was completed.Sema shares have risen 37 percent since Nov. 24, the day of the profit warning, on speculation that the company would be taken over or split up to increase the stock price. As of Friday, Sema's market value was Â£2.9 billion, or nearly $4.2 billion.The list of potential bidders has read like a who's who of technology and services, including Logica of Britain, Siemens of Germany, and Cap Gemini of France (which is merging with the computer consulting operation of Ernst &amp; Young) as well as E.D.S. and Computer Sciences of the United States.France TÃ©lÃ©com, Sema's largest shareholder, said last week that it was prepared to sell its 17 percent stake if a fair offer was made.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/04/business/world-business-briefing-europe-bull-to-sell-card-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; BULL TO SELL CARD UNIT<date>Published: January 04, 2001</date><text>The French computer maker Bull S.A., which lost money in 8 of the last 12 years, said it was in talks to sell its CP8 smart-card unit to Schlumberger Ltd. for 300 million to 400 million euros ($286 million to $381 million). Bull is trying to transform itself into a software and services company by selling hardware-making businesses. Schlumberger, best known for oil field services, will add CP8 to its test and transaction unit, whose businesses include security card systems.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/business/company-news-schlumberger-agrees-to-buy-convergent.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER AGREES TO BUY CONVERGENT<date>Published: October 17, 2000</date><text>The oil services company Schlumberger said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Convergent Group for $276 million to expand its presence in the utilities business. The $8-a-share offer for Convergent, which provides consulting and other services to utilities and local government clients, represents a 69 percent premium to its closing price on Friday of $4.72. Schlumberger, based in New York, provides technical services to the oil and gas, utility, semiconductor testing and network software industries. Convergent, based in Englewood, Colo., had 1999 revenue of $66.61 million. Under the deal, Schlumberger will acquire a 72 percent interest in Convergent Group, and Convergent's current management and an affiliate of Convergent's largest client, the Cinergy Corporation, will own the remaining 28 percent of the new entity.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/09/business/company-news-schlumberger-agrees-to-buy-data-marine-of-scotland.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER AGREES TO BUY DATA MARINE OF SCOTLAND<date>Published: August 09, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., an oil field service company that is expanding into meter-reading and electronic-commerce technologies, agreed yesterday to buy the closely held Data Marine Systems Ltd for an undisclosed price. Data Marine, based in Aberdeen, Scotland, owns and runs a satellite network that transmits seismic and other data from oil fields. The Wall Street Journal reported yesterday that Schlumberger, the world's No. 2 oil field services company, would pay almost $100 million for Data Marine. Schlumberger would not confirm that figure. Shares of Schlumberger rose $1.30 each, to $79.4375, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/01/business/company-news-schlumberger-and-baker-hughes-form-seismic-venture.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER AND BAKER HUGHES FORM SEISMIC VENTURE<date>Published: June 01, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's No. 2 oil field services company, agreed yesterday to pay $500 million to a rival, Baker Hughes Inc., for a 70 percent stake in a new joint venture to provide seismic services used to locate oil and gas. Seismic technology is used to study the physical properties of land or water in an effort to save on the expense of drilling into dry areas. Schlumberger and Baker Hughes will combine their seismic divisions to form a venture called Western GECO. The shares of Schlumberger rose $2.3125 each, to $73.3125. Baker Hughes rose $2.125, at $36.25.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/17/business/company-news-schlumberger-buys-the-assets-of-cellnet-data-systems.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER BUYS THE ASSETS OF CELLNET DATA SYSTEMS<date>Published: May 17, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., an oil-service company that is expanding into meter-reading and electronic-commerce technologies, said yesterday that it had bought the assets of the wireless-network provider CellNet Data Systems Inc. for about $117 million in cash. The company will also assume $118 million in debt. Schlumberger, whose meters measure heat, water and electricity use, will use CellNet's network to read information from those meters. It already uses CellNet, which filed for federal bankruptcy protection in February, as a contractor for that purpose. Schlumberger, which is based in New York, also makes ''smart'' cards that improve the security of banking and e-commerce transactions.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/02/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-buy-maker-of-energy-data-networks.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO BUY MAKER OF ENERGY DATA NETWORKS<date>Published: February 02, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. agreed yesterday to buy the money-losing CellNet Data Systems Inc., whose wireless networks gather information about energy use, for $55 million in cash. Schlumberger will also assume about $120 million in debt. CellNet, based in San Carlos, Calif., said it planned to file for Chapter 11 protection in Delaware on Friday. It expects the bankruptcy court to approve its sale to Schlumberger by April 30. Schlumberger, the world's second-largest oil field service company, has headquarters in Paris and New York. Its shares rose $2.875, to $63.9375, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/11/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-take-113-million-charge.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO TAKE $113 MILLION CHARGE<date>Published: January 11, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the second-biggest oil-service company, said yesterday that it would take fourth-quarter charges totaling $113 million, including $50 million for costs of the spinoff and merger of its Sedco Forex unit. Another $37 million will cover costs of revamping its land-drilling operation, and $26 million will pay for reducing its seismic fleet. Schlumberger needs to cut costs after merging Sedco Forex, its offshore drilling business, with Transocean Offshore Inc. on Dec. 31, analysts said. Schlumberger, which has headquarters in New York and Paris, is expected to earn 23 cents a share in the quarter, according to analysts polled by First Call/Thomson Financial. It earned 50 cents a year earlier.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/01/business/company-news-schlumberger-completes-spinoff-of-offshore-oil-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER COMPLETES SPINOFF OF OFFSHORE OIL UNIT<date>Published: January 01, 2000</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., a leading oil services company, said yesterday that the spinoff of its Sedco Forex Offshore unit and its merger with Transocean Offshore Inc. had been completed in a $3.61 billion transaction that creates the world's largest offshore drilling company. Schlumberger investors received one share in Sedco Forex for each share held. The shares were exchanged for 0.1936 share in the new company, Transocean Sedco Forex Inc. Schlumberger shareholders retained a 52 percent stake in the new company. Schlumberger is getting out of offshore rig rentals to concentrate on developing technology that gets more oil out of wells. The merger lets Transocean, the third-largest offshore driller, add to its fleet of deep-water rigs.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/17/business/company-news-dow-exercises-warrant-to-buy-schlumberger-shares.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; DOW EXERCISES WARRANT TO BUY SCHLUMBERGER SHARES<date>Published: December 17, 1999</date><text>The Dow Chemical Company has exercised a warrant to buy $450 million of stock in Schlumberger Ltd., the world's second-biggest oil field services company. Schlumberger gave Dow the warrant in 1993 as partial payment for a 50 percent interest in an oil field joint venture. Schlumberger also paid Dow $675 million. Shares of Schlumberger, which has its main offices in New York and Paris, fell 62.5 cents, to $57.1875. Shares of Dow, which is based in Midland, Mich., fell $6.0625 each, to $121.875.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/28/business/us-seeks-fines-in-antitrust-case.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">U.S. Seeks Fines In Antitrust Case<date>Published: July 28, 1999</date><text>The Justice Department said today that it had asked a Federal judge to find Smith International Inc. and Schlumberger Ltd. in criminal and civil contempt for violating a court order.In the first criminal antitrust contempt case involving a merger decree in more than 15 years, the department said the two companies had formed a joint venture that was prohibited by the 1994 order. It asked the judge to impose unspecified criminal fines and to order payment of a daily fee to compel compliance with the order.''The companies' flagrant and contemptuous disregard of a binding consent decree is wholly unacceptable,'' said Joel I. Klein, the Assistant Attorney General in charge of the antitrust division. ''The department will not hesitate to enforce its decrees to the full extent of the law.''After Dresser Industries sold its interest in M-1 Drilling Fluids to Smith, the 1994 order barred Smith from selling the business or combining it with the drilling fluid operations of certain companies, including Schlumberger, the department said. The department says Smith sold Schlumberger a 40 percent interest in the joint venture and combined M-1 with Schlumberger's drilling fluid operations. It said Schlumberger had acted in concert with Smith.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/13/business/merger-is-planned-to-create-the-biggest-offshore-driller.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Merger Is Planned to Create The Biggest Offshore Driller<date>Published: July 13, 1999</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that it had agreed to spin off its offshore drilling unit, Sedco Forex Offshore, and merge it with Trans-ocean Offshore Inc. to create the world's largest offshore oil-drilling company.Both companies said that the spinoff was a response to the high cost and greater technological demands of offshore oil exploration, where drilling is taking place in ever-deeper waters.The merged company, to be called Transocean Sedco Forex, will employ 7,500 people and have 75 offshore rigs, the most in the world. The new company, which is to be based in Houston, where Transocean Offshore has its headquarters, would have a market capitalization of $6.1 billion.Most major new finds have been in deep water, most recently off the coast of West Africa and in the Gulf of Mexico. ''Deep water is one of the last frontiers of the oil business,'' said Dan Pickering, an analyst for Simmons &amp; Company International.Mr. Pickering said that drilling in deep water continued at high levels last year despite low crude oil prices. To cut their costs, oil companies, and the firms that supply them with exploration and production equipment, underwent major consolidation.Thus, demand for deep-water rigs is expected to increase quickly if crude oil prices continue to move up beyond levels hoped for by most major oil companies. The recent recovery has been a result of strong world demand and cutbacks by major oil-producing countries.Mr. Pickering said the spinoff by Schlumberger, which is based in Paris, ''was not driven by any type of financial distress.'' Instead, he noted, basic expenses are formidable: Rigs that can drill in water 5,000 to 8,000 feet deep can cost from $250 million to $450 million each.Transocean Offshore's merger with the Schlumberger unit ''is advantageous due to the rising capital costs for new rig construction, the increasing size and needs of our customers, the expanding geographic diversity of offshore drilling and the technical challenges posed by the new deepwater drilling activities,'' according to J. Michael Talbert, Transocean's chairman and chief executive.D. Euan Baird, the chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger, said the company would concentrate on technology and methods of getting more oil out of the ground and bringing down the cost.Under the agreement, Schlumberger stockholders would receive roughly one newly issued Transocean Sedco Forex share for every five Schlumberger shares they hold.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/23/business/company-news-profits-down-schlumberger-will-cut-2500-more-jobs.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; PROFITS DOWN, SCHLUMBERGER WILL CUT 2,500 MORE JOBS<date>Published: April 23, 1999</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's second-largest oilfield services company, said yesterday that it would cut 2,500 more jobs by the end of June as first-quarter profit fell 53 percent. The company said it had already cut 7,500 jobs, or 11 percent of its work force, since July, as slumping oil prices reduced demand for its services. It expects the latest cuts to help it save $300 million a year, on top of $300 million in annual savings achieved by last year's cuts. Although first-quarter crude oil prices rallied from December's 12-year low, they still averaged 17 percent less than a year earlier and oil-company spending remained depressed. Schlumberger's shares rose $3.25, to $63.625.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/20/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-buy-camco-a-smaller-rival.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO BUY CAMCO, A SMALLER RIVAL<date>Published: June 20, 1998</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., a leading oilfield services company, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy one of its smaller rivals, Camco International Inc., in a stock swap worth about $3.1 billion. The combined market capitalization of the two companies totals $37 billion. Camco, based in Houston, will be operated as a division of Schlumberger's oilfield services group. Camco's shareholders will receive 1.18 Schlumberger shares for each Camco share. Camco's stock jumped $12.6875 a share, to $74.9375, on the New York Stock Exchange, where Schlumberger's stock fell $3.6875, to $66.25.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/21/business/international-business-schlumberger-sets-big-russian-oil-alliance.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Schlumberger Sets Big Russian Oil Alliance<date>Published: March 21, 1998</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. plans to announce next Tuesday that it will form a five-year strategic alliance with the AO Yuksi Oil Company, Russia's largest oil producer, Yuksi said yesterday. Schlumberger would take over and manage some of the Russian oilfields to make them more productive.The agreement could signal a major change in the way Russian oil companies operate. In the past they have rarely allowed outside companies to take over the management of oilfields although they have contracted for services and equipment with outsiders.Arvind S. Sanger, an analyst for Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, said the agreement could become a model for other Russian companies.Yuksi is the new company being formed with the merger of the AO Yukos Oil Company, Russia's second-largest producer, with the AO Siberian Oil Company, the seventh-largest producer in Russia.The new company, which is close to completing the merger, will produce 1.3 million barrels a day, making it the world's third-largest private company in terms of production, behind the Royal Dutch/Shell Group and the Exxon Corporation.Yuksi spends about $2 billion a year on servicing its fields.The agreement is expected to be announced on Tuesday at a news conference in Manhattan with Mikhail Khodorkovsky, the president of Yuksi, and D. Euan Baird, the chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger, which is based in Manhattan. Schlumberger is the world's largest oilfield service company.Schlumberger stock closed at $73.5625, up $1.9375, in trading on the New York Stock Exchange, sharing in a general rally of oil service stocks.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/07/business/acquisition-set-by-schlumberger.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Acquisition Set By Schlumberger<date>Published: November 07, 1996</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that it would buy Solaic S.A., a maker of magnetic and smart cards, from Sligos S.A. Terms were not disclosed.Smart cards use chips to store personal data, security codes and digitized currency. Though now mainly used in Europe, the cards are expected to become more commonplace in the United States, particularly for private transactions from public kiosks.Solaic, with 1995 revenues of 416 million French francs ($81 million), has plants in France and Spain and marketing operations in Germany, Spain, France and Britain. Schlumberger, based in New York, provides oilfield services, measurement devices and electronic transaction systems. Sligos provides card-processing services and software for the banking industry.Schlumberger said the agreement also provided for a partnership with Sligos for systems based on smart cards.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/26/business/schlumberger-reducing-jobs-and-closing-plants.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">SCHLUMBERGER REDUCING JOBS AND CLOSING PLANTS<date>Published: September 26, 1996</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., which is combining two related energy businesses, said yesterday that it would reduce jobs, manufacturing operations and products and post a credit and charges in the third quarter. Schlumberger planned to take a credit of $360 million as it recognizes a portion of an income tax benefit, and it would take an after-tax charge of $300 million related primarily to its electricity and gas management and Geco-Prakla divisions. Schlumberger expects also to record an after-tax charge of $58 million, including a loss on the divestiture of its remaining military-related activity. Schlumberger's stock was up 37.5 cents, at $83.625, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/12/08/business/company-news-schlumberger-to-acquire-rest-of-venture-with-dow.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; SCHLUMBERGER TO ACQUIRE REST OF VENTURE WITH DOW<date>Published: December 08, 1992</date><text>The oil-services giant Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that it planned to acquire the remaining 50 percent of its Dowell Schlumberger, which provides cementing, coiled tubing and services to oilfield companies, in a deal worth more than $675 million. Schlumberger, based in New York, will pay $675 million in cash to its joint venture partner, the Dow Chemical Company, which will also get warrants entitling it to purchase 7.5 million shares of Schlumberger stock for $59.95.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/10/30/business/business-technology-american-express-to-buy-2-top-supercomputers.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY; American Express to Buy 2 Top Supercomputers<date>Published: October 30, 1991</date><text>Executives of the American Express Company said today that they planned to purchase new massively parallel supercomputers from the Thinking Machines Corporation.American Express's order for two of the machines was among nine sales commitments that Thinking Machines announced at a news conference in Cambridge, Mass., today as the company introduced the new computers.Purchase plans were also announced by officials of Sandia National Laboratories, the Los Alamos National Laboratory and the National Center for Supercomputer Applications, as well as the Army High Performance Computing Research Center at the University of Minnesota; Schlumberger Ltd.; the University of California at Berkeley; the University of Wisconsin at Madison, and Syracuse University."We've crossed over an important line in terms of general acceptance of this technology," said Gary Smaby, an analyst at the Smaby Group in Minneapolis. Massively parallel computers harness thousands or even tens of thousands of off-the-shelf chips, breaking problems up into small parts that can be solved simultaneously. Beyond Previous SupercomputersThey offer the best way to solve a series of scientific problems that are beyond the scope of previous supercomputers.The new machine, known as the CM-5, is the first of a new generation of supercomputers that many industry executives expect will soon start to replace conventional systems based on a single processor or a small number of processors.The CM-5's prices start at $1.4 million for a system that contains 32 processors and can be increased to a maximum of 16,000 processors. Each processor is a chip based on a design created by Sun Microsystems Inc., which supports up to four special math chips for scientific calculations.An American Express official said the company saw massively parallel supercomputing as an important part of its information-processing strategy but was unwilling to say how the machines would be used.A number of large corporations have begun experimenting with massively parallel supercomputers for a variety of applications from technical design to data analysis. Industry analysts said they thought American Express would use the machines to refine its analysis of cardholders' purchasing habits.Mr. Cone said the company planned to install one machine at an American Express processing center in Phoenix and the other in Boston.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/10/19/business/schlumberger-profits-up-33.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Profits Up 33%<date>Published: October 19, 1991</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. yesterday reported a 33 percent rise in earnings for the third quarter, when the oilfield services company increased drilling outside North America and reduced operations in the United States, where oil exploration is in decline.For the July-September quarter, Schlumberger earned $196.3 million, or 82 cents a share, on revenues of $1.47 billion. That compared with earnings of $147.4 million, or 62 cents a share, on revenues of $1.32 billion for the corresponding period in 1990.Oilfield revenue increased by 17 percent, Schlumberger said, even though drilling was off 9 percent, mostly because of a decline in operating rigs in the United States. Schlumberger responded by laying off workers and closing some operations.The company's chairman, Euan Baird, predicted strong business in the future.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/07/19/business/oil-service-s-profit-rises.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Oil Service's Profit Rises<date>Published: July 19, 1991</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the oilfield services company, said yesterday that its profits were up 25 percent in the second quarter on the strength of new products and services. The company said its business recovered from a first-quarter slump that resulted partly from the gulf war.Schlumberger, based in New York, said it earned $180.8 million in the quarter, or 76 cents a share, up from $144.8 million, or 61 cents a share, in the comparable period a year ago. Revenues rose 20 percent, to $1.55 billion from $1.29 billion.Euan Baird, Schlumberger's chairman, said new products and services raised the company's performance despite a 7 percent decline in the number of oil rigs.Schlumberger said its earnings were 36 percent higher than in the first quarter, as oilfields recovered from seasonal dips and the war.On the Big Board yesterday, Schlumberger's share price gained $2.75, to $67.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/02/06/business/company-news-schlumberger-s-profits-are-off.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Schlumberger's Profits Are Off<date>Published: February 06, 1990</date><text>Fourth-quarter net income of Schlumberger Ltd. slipped to $118.1 million, from $118.9 million in the period a year earlier, the company said yesterday.Earnings per share edged ahead to 50 cents a share, from 49 cents a share in the corresponding quarter a year earlier.Revenue in the three-month period totaled $1.2 billion, down about 3 percent from $1.24 billion in the comparable 1988 period.For the year, the New York-based oil-drilling and oilfield services company had net income of $441.5 million, or $1.86 a share, down from $476.2 million, or $1.80 a share, in 1988.Revenue totaled $4.7 billion, down about 5 percent from $4.9 billion in the previous year.Schlumberger said the previous year's stock buyback reduced the company's interest income in 1989. ''Decreased interest income of $63 million primarily resulted from spending $1.2 billion in 1988 to repurchase 34.5 million shares,'' the company's chairman, Euan Baird, said.Higher oil prices in late 1989 helped the company's oilfield businesses recover from a slump in 1988, he said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/08/30/business/company-news-schlumberger-in-joint-venture.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Schlumberger In Joint Venture<date>Published: August 30, 1989</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., a large industrial concern, and the Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corporation of Japan announced they were forming a company to develop advanced testing for integrated circuits. Schlumberger said that under the terms of the agreement, the concern, called Verisys, would develop, manufacture and market the testing systems worldwide.Schlumberger said the company would be based in Japan and would enable N.T.T. to use its technology in the world electronics industry.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/05/16/business/company-news-loral-to-buy-military-systems-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Loral to Buy Military Systems Unit<date>Published: May 16, 1989</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the New York-based oil services company, said yesterday that it had reached an agreement to sell its military systems unit, Fairchild Weston Systems, to the Loral Corporation, a military electronics contractor in New York.Schlumberger said the sale price was about $190 million in cash, and Loral put the price at about $185 million after closing adjustments.Even at $190 million, analysts said, the sale price was slightly below their expectations and reflects a continuing softening of the military electronics industry.Fairchild Weston, with 3,500 employees and revenues of $270 million and an operating income of $22 million in 1988, has operations in Syosset, L.I.; Sarasota, Fla.; Archbald and Horsham, Pa., Milpitas, Calif., and in Britain and France.Its principal activities include advanced technology in electro-optical sensors, communication and control systems for aerospace and ground armament weapons systems. It is also one of the leading manufacturers of flight and cockpit data recorders.Byron K. Callan, a military electronics analyst with Prudential-Bache Securities, said that the sale, which would not include Fairchild Weston's French operations, did not come as a surprise and made sense for each company. ''This is the type of company Loral can buy and squeeze more operating profits out of,'' he said. ''And it was a peripheral business at best for Schlumberger.''Schlumberger first announced its intentions to sell the Fairchild Weston division in late January. The company said then that the sale ''is in line with its strategy to refocus on its principal product lines.''Loral has been in the market for military electronics companies since late March, when it sold its aircraft braking and engineered fabrics divisions. Loral's chairman, Bernard L. Schwartz, said then that the cash from the sale would be used to reduce debt and to make further acquisitions.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/01/24/business/company-news-schlumberger-plans-to-sell-unit.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Schlumberger Plans to Sell Unit<date>Published: January 24, 1989</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the New York-based oil services company, said it was planning to sell its defense systems unit, Fairchild Weston Systems. Schlumberger did not say when the sale would occur or if the unit had a buyer. It said the sale ''is in line with its strategy to refocus on its principal product lines.''Fairchild Weston, with 3,500 employees and 1988 revenues of $320 million, has operations in Syosset, L.I.; Sarasota, Fla., and Archbald, Pa., and in Britain and France. Its principal activities include advanced technology in electro-optical sensors, communication and control systems for aerospace and ground armament weapons systems.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/07/02/business/company-news-semiconductor-in-stock-buyback.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Company News; Semiconductor In Stock Buyback<date>Published: July 02, 1988</date><text>The National Semiconductor Corporation said it would buy back the National common stock and warrants it gave Schlumberger Ltd. for the purchase of Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation last fall. The buyback, in effect, is a decision by National to pay Schlumberger in cash instead of in stock for the acquisition.National had guaranteed a purchase price of $122 million and had given Schlumberger 4.1 million common shares and 4.1 million warrants deemed to be worth that much in October. Because National's stock has dropped since then, the company would have had to give more shares to Schlumberger to achieve the $122 million price. Instead, National said Thursday that it would take back the stock and warrants from Schlumberger and pay the $122 million in cash.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/04/22/business/schlumberger-net-up.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Net Up<date>Published: April 22, 1988</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that its first-quarter earnings rose sharply from the period last year as its revenue from oil exploration services surged. The world's largest oilfield services company reported a profit of $101 million, or 37 cents a share, up from $4.99 million, or 2 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue came to $1.3 billion in the latest quarter, up from $1.1 billion, the company said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/03/05/business/insider-charges-settled-by-2.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Insider Charges Settled by 2<date>Published: March 05, 1988</date><text>Two employees of a unit of Schlumberger Ltd., the oil services company, this week settled civil charges that they illegally purchased stock in the Texas International Company in 1985 while possessing inside information about the discovery of a major oilfield in Egypt by Texas International.Joseph Keherve, a French citizen, and Adel Adib Riffat, an Egyptian citizen, settled the Securities and Exchange Commission charges without admitting or denying guilt. They agreed to pay $25,306 of illegal profits to the Federal District Court in Manhattan and to pay an identical sum as a penalty. The S.E.C. had charged thatMr. Keherve and Mr. Riffat bought 20,000 shares of Texas International one hour before the company announced its oil discovery on Feb. 4, 1985.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/09/18/business/company-news-intergraph-to-buy-rights-to-clipper.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Intergraph to Buy Rights to Clipper<date>Published: September 18, 1987</date><text>The National Semiconductor Corporation has agreed to sell the rights to the Clipper microprocessor product line to the Intergraph Corporation. The sale, for what industry officials said was about $10 million, indicates that National is quickly moving to sell parts of the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation, which it agreed to acquire from Schlumberger Ltd. last month for $122 million in stock.National was expected to divest itself of Fairchild's microprocessor business because it already had its own. Intergraph, a Huntsville, Ala., company that makes systems for computer-aided design, uses the high-speed Clipper chip in a work station. The company is so dependent on the chip that it had considered buying a stake in Fairchild as part of a management buyout effort. Intergraph is expected to offer jobs to about 100 Fairchild employees.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/08/20/business/company-news-citicorp-unit-said-to-seek-fairchild.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Citicorp Unit Said To Seek Fairchild<date>Published: August 20, 1987</date><text>Citicorp Venture Capital has reportedly joined in the bidding for the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation, which is being sold by its parent, Schlumberger Ltd. The San Jose Mercury News said today that Citicorp had been working with Fairchild's president, Donald Brooks, to finance a leveraged buyout. Schlumberger has been considering several buyout offers for Fairchild since March, when it bowed to Government pressure and withdrew a proposal to sell 80 percent of Fairchild to Fujitsu Ltd. of Japan.The Mercury News, quoting unidentified sources, said that under the offer most of the money would come from Citicorp and the current management team and most of the company would remain intact. A Fairchild spokeswoman would not comment.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/07/21/business/schlumberger-net-off-45.5.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Net Off 45.5%<date>Published: July 21, 1987</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's largest oilfield services company, said yesterday that its second-quarter profits fell 45.5 percent, to $30.1 million, or 11 cents a share, from $55.2 million, or 19 cents a share, a year ago.Revenues declined about 15 percent, to $1.1 billion, from $1.3 billion a year earlier. The company attributed the decline primarily to reduced oil drilling resulting from the steep decline in oil prices.The 1986 figures do not include Schlumberger's $23 million second-quarter loss from its Fairchild Semiconductor operation, which the company has been trying to sell.Schlumberger's chairman, Euan Baird, said all the company's operating groups had better results compared with the first quarter. In particular, he said, the results from oilfield services continue to improve, because of significant cost reductions undertaken last year and improved price levels.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/04/21/business/schlumberger-profit-plunges.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Profit Plunges<date>Published: April 21, 1987</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the oilfield service and electronics company, said today that its first-quarter earnings plunged 96 percent, reaching $5 million, or 2 cents a share, from $148.2 million, or 51 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenues fell 24.8 percent, to $1.1 billion, from $1.46 billion. The company blamed the oil industry's slump.The 1986 results included a one-time charge of $44.68 million, stemming from discontinued operations of the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation subsidiary.Schlumberger said that, although North American revenues from its wireline, seismic and testing service division fell 58 percent from last year's first quarter, they increased 6 percent from its fourth quarter.Last month, under pressure from Washington, Schlumberger canceled a plan to sell 80 percent of Fairchild to Fujitsu Ltd. The Government said that such a merger would be a step toward Japanese control of the American semiconductor industry and thus would endanger national security.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/03/17/business/japanese-purchase-of-chip-maker-canceled-after-objections-in-us.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">JAPANESE PURCHASE OF CHIP MAKER CANCELED AFTER OBJECTIONS IN U.S.<date>Published: March 17, 1987</date><text>Bowing to intense pressure from Reagan Administration officials, an American company said yesterday that it had called off the sale of a technology subsidiary to one of Japan's giant electronics companies.The action came days after Defense Secretary Caspar W. Weinberger, Commerce Secretary Malcolm Baldrige and the Central Intelligence Agency, in a rare intervention concerning a private sale, asked the White House to try to block Fujitsu Ltd. from buying the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation, a maker of computer chips and a subsidiary of Schlumberger Ltd.The primary objection to the sale centered on national security. But beyond the spoken objections, some Federal officials concede, was the mounting trade friction with Japan.The deal was viewed by many Government and industry officials as a test case in Japanese efforts to invest in the United States, particularly in strategically important high technology. The Administration's success in scuttling the deal appeared likely to discourage similar purchases by Japanese companies in search of American chip-design technology.''The rising political controversy in the United States concerning the venture made it unlikely that the sale of Fairchild could be completed within a reasonable time,'' Schlumberger said in a three-paragraph statement. Possibility of Pentagon ActionWhile the Government had no means of preventing the acquisition, the Pentagon could have denied military contracts to the combined Fairchild-Fujitsu concern.Schlumberger said the termination of the deal had ''opened other avenues,'' including a buyout by Fairchild's management, for selling the money-losing chip maker. Fairchild, once a pioneer of the American electronics industry, has declined precipitously in recent years as part of an industrywide slump.As a military contractor, Fairchild is an important supplier of some advanced components used in military equipment and computer systems, including the communications systems used to control nuclear missiles and supercomputers. Defense Department and C.I.A. officials said they did not want to see the American computer industry become dependent on semiconductors produced by Japanese-owned manufacturers.''It's really bad policy,'' Mr. Baldrige said at a meeting with reporters last week.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/02/13/business/company-news-schlumberger-loses-2-billion.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; Schlumberger Loses $2 Billion<date>Published: February 13, 1987</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oilfield services company, announced yesterday that it lost $2.18 billion in the fourth quarter.The quarterly loss, largely attributed to one-time charges of $2.1 billion, is one of the largest ever for an American company. In the 1985 fourth quarter, Schlumberger lost $372.7 million, following a charge of $543.1 million.Schlumberger's quarterly revenue dropped about 30 percent, to $1.09 billion, from $1.55 billion in the period a year earlier.Euan Baird, Schlumberger's chairman, said the company's 1986 performance was strongly affected by the absence of oilfield activity, a result of the collapse in oil prices.''The steep decline in the number of drilling rigs, the disappearance of most oilfield exploration - a primary market for Schlumberger - and the sharp drop of oilfield service prices due to the excess capacity prevailing in this market, took their toll,'' a statement quoted Mr. Baird as saying.Schlumberger said that the one-time charges of $2.1 billion in fourth-quarter 1986 included a previously announced $1.74 billion relating to its oilfield services segment, its measurement, control and components segment, and for potential interest relating to pending litigation with the Internal Revenue Service.In addition, the company took a largely expected $464 million charge in the quarter for its Fairchild Semiconductor segment. Most of the charge related to the pending sale of 80 percent of the unit to Fujitsu Ltd. The discontinued operations of the the Fairchild unit lost $312 million in the fourth quarter and $363 million for the year, the company said.For all of 1986, Schlumberger said it lost $2.02 billion, compared with a profit of $351 million in 1985. Revenues declined 17.9 percent, to $4.94 billion, from $6.02 billion in 1985. ----Earnings tables, D18.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/11/03/business/market-place-stock-picking-in-oil-services.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Market Place; Stock Picking In Oil Services<date>November 3, 1986</date><text>SCHLUMBERGER LTD. is the troubled giant of an oilfield service and equipment industry that is going through a period of intense cost-cutting, restructuring and consolidation. Moreover, when it comes to investment suggestions by security analysts, Schlumberger often takes a back seat to smaller companies in its field. ''My two current buys are special situations -McDermott International and Dresser Industries,'' said Suzanne L. Cook of the First Boston Corporation. She favors McDermott for its high cash position, a yield of slightly above 8 percent and for the asset play potential in its Babcock &amp; Wilcox unit, a power plant construction company.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] SCHLUMBERGER LTD. is the troubled giant of an oilfield service and equipment industry that is going through a period of intense cost-cutting, restructuring and consolidation. Moreover, when it comes to investment suggestions by security analysts, Schlumberger often takes a back seat to smaller companies in its field. ''My two current buys are special situations -McDermott International and Dresser Industries,'' said Suzanne L. Cook of the First Boston Corporation. She favors McDermott for its high cash position, a yield of slightly above 8 percent and for the asset play potential in its Babcock &amp; Wilcox unit, a power plant construction company.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/24/business/fujitsu-in-deal-on-chip-maker.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">FUJITSU IN DEAL ON CHIP MAKER<date>October 24, 1986</date><text>Fujitsu Ltd., the giant Japanese electronics company, will buy a majority interest in the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation, a pioneering Silicon Valley computer chip manufacturer now owned by Schlumberger Ltd. Under an agreement in principle announced today by Fujitsu and Schlumberger, Fujitsu will own 80 percent of Fairchild and will make a ''substantial equity investment'' in the company. Fujitsu will combine Fairchild with its own American chip divisions and parts of its European operations. Schlumberger, an oilfield services company with offices in New York and Paris, will retain a 20 percent stake, and Donald W. Brooks, president and chief executive of Fairchild, will become president and chief executive of the new, expanded company.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Fujitsu Ltd., the giant Japanese electronics company, will buy a majority interest in the Fairchild Semiconductor Corporation, a pioneering Silicon Valley computer chip manufacturer now owned by Schlumberger Ltd. Under an agreement in principle announced today by Fujitsu and Schlumberger, Fujitsu will own 80 percent of Fairchild and will make a ''substantial equity investment'' in the company. Fujitsu will combine Fairchild with its own American chip divisions and parts of its European operations. Schlumberger, an oilfield services company with offices in New York and Paris, will retain a 20 percent stake, and Donald W. Brooks, president and chief executive of Fairchild, will become president and chief executive of the new, expanded company.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/03/business/company-news-oil-concern-replaces-chairman.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">COMPANY NEWS; OIL CONCERN REPLACES CHAIRMAN<date>October 3, 1986</date><text>Michel Vaillaud was ousted as chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger Ltd. because some members of the Schlumberger family were anxious to wield greater power over the huge oilfield services concern, sources close to the company said yesterday. The family, which controls about 30 percent of Schlumberger, used the impact of the collapse in oil prices on Schlumberger's earnings as an opportunity to seek Mr. Vaillaud's dismissal, the sources said. Schlumberger's 15-member board voted unanimously on Wednesday to replace Mr. Vaillaud with D. Euan Baird, an executive vice president. Too Close to Predecessor Mr. Vaillaud, 54 years old, had been the hand-picked successor of Jean Riboud, the legendary chief executive who led Schlumberger for 20 years, until last year. Ultimately, it was that close association that may have sealed Mr. Vaillaud's fate.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Michel Vaillaud was ousted as chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger Ltd. because some members of the Schlumberger family were anxious to wield greater power over the huge oilfield services concern, sources close to the company said yesterday. The family, which controls about 30 percent of Schlumberger, used the impact of the collapse in oil prices on Schlumberger's earnings as an opportunity to seek Mr. Vaillaud's dismissal, the sources said. Schlumberger's 15-member board voted unanimously on Wednesday to replace Mr. Vaillaud with D. Euan Baird, an executive vice president. Too Close to Predecessor Mr. Vaillaud, 54 years old, had been the hand-picked successor of Jean Riboud, the legendary chief executive who led Schlumberger for 20 years, until last year. Ultimately, it was that close association that may have sealed Mr. Vaillaud's fate.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/10/02/business/schlumberger-chairman-replaced.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Chairman Replaced<date>October 2, 1986</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., in a surprise move, announced last night the election of Euan Baird to the posts of chairman, president and chief executive officer. Mr. Baird, who is 49 years old, will replace Michel Vaillaud in those posts. Mr. Vaillaud, 54, apparently was ousted by the board after only one year at the helm.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Schlumberger Ltd., in a surprise move, announced last night the election of Euan Baird to the posts of chairman, president and chief executive officer. Mr. Baird, who is 49 years old, will replace Michel Vaillaud in those posts. Mr. Vaillaud, 54, apparently was ousted by the board after only one year at the helm.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/09/30/business/inquiry-urged-on-schlumberger-s-contract-bids.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">INQUIRY URGED ON SCHLUMBERGER'S CONTRACT BIDS<date>September 30, 1986</date><text>Two Democratic Congressmen today called for the Reagan Administration to investigate whether Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oilfield services company, has tried to win contracts from Arab or Moslem countries by agreeing not to do business with Israel. The Congressmen, John Bryant of Texas and Howard Berman of California, also charged that Schlumberger's continued operation of oil well logging services in Libya violated the ''spirit and perhaps the letter'' of President Reagan's sanctions that forced American companies to end their activities in Libya on June 30. A Schlumberger spokesman, Seth T. McCormick, said a Treasury Department inquiry last month had determined the company was not subject to the Libyan sanctions because it is incorporated outside the United States, off the coast of Venezuela in Curacao, the Netherland Antilles.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Two Democratic Congressmen today called for the Reagan Administration to investigate whether Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oilfield services company, has tried to win contracts from Arab or Moslem countries by agreeing not to do business with Israel. The Congressmen, John Bryant of Texas and Howard Berman of California, also charged that Schlumberger's continued operation of oil well logging services in Libya violated the ''spirit and perhaps the letter'' of President Reagan's sanctions that forced American companies to end their activities in Libya on June 30. A Schlumberger spokesman, Seth T. McCormick, said a Treasury Department inquiry last month had determined the company was not subject to the Libyan sanctions because it is incorporated outside the United States, off the coast of Venezuela in Curacao, the Netherland Antilles.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/25/business/market-place-schlumberger-payout-outlook.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Market Place; Schlumberger Payout Outlook<date>July 25, 1986</date><text>DIVIDEND cuts in one of the nation's most troubled industries - oilfield service and equipment - have become common. The Halliburton Company reduced its cash payments by 44 percent in May. Two days ago, Baker International halved its quarterly dividend - to 11.5 cents a share - while Hughes Tool, citing a ''collapse'' in drilling activity, slashed its quarterly payment to 2 cents from 12 cents. Does this portend a possible dividend reduction, too, for Schlumberger Ltd., the industry's acknowledged leader? A Wall Street favorite in its heyday, the company remains a major holding of institutional investors, who own an estimated 43 percent of its stock. Schlumberger, which has raised its cash dividend for at least nine years, now pays 30 cents quarterly, or $1.20 a year.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] DIVIDEND cuts in one of the nation's most troubled industries - oilfield service and equipment - have become common. The Halliburton Company reduced its cash payments by 44 percent in May. Two days ago, Baker International halved its quarterly dividend - to 11.5 cents a share - while Hughes Tool, citing a ''collapse'' in drilling activity, slashed its quarterly payment to 2 cents from 12 cents. Does this portend a possible dividend reduction, too, for Schlumberger Ltd., the industry's acknowledged leader? A Wall Street favorite in its heyday, the company remains a major holding of institutional investors, who own an estimated 43 percent of its stock. Schlumberger, which has raised its cash dividend for at least nine years, now pays 30 cents quarterly, or $1.20 a year.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/19/business/schlumberger-s-net-falls-74.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger's Net Falls 74%<date>Published: July 19, 1986</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., hurt by the continuing steep decline in domestic oil field exploration and development, reported yesterday that its earnings in the second quarter had plunged 74 percent on a 14 percent decline in revenues. Schlumberger said that net income in the three-month period ended June 30 had dropped to $55.2 million, or 19 cents a share, from $212.1 million, or 71 cents a share. Revenues declined to $1.41 billion from $1.64 billion. Michel Vaillaud, the chairman of Schlumberger, attributed the decline specifically to lower exploration activity in Africa and the North Sea. He said that the company's consolidated United States operations remained unprofitable, resulting in an increased tax-loss carry-forward. The sharp decline in oil prices since late last year has put severe pressure on Schlumberger and other oil-service concerns. Schlumberger said that oilfield services revenue declined 30 percent in the latest three months. Wireline and testing revenue in North America plunged 57 percent as the average number of rigs declined 57 percent, to 842, the steepest drop ever recorded.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1986/04/22/business/schlumberger-hughes-drop.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger, Hughes Drop<date>April 22, 1986</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oilfield services company, said yesterday that first-quarter earnings plunged 51.3 percent on a 5.9 percent drop in revenues. Michel Vaillaud, chairman, said the drop in net income was mainly the result of the general decline in the oilfield services business and continuing losses at the company's Fairchild Semiconductor subsidiary.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Schlumberger Ltd., the giant oilfield services company, said yesterday that first-quarter earnings plunged 51.3 percent on a 5.9 percent drop in revenues. Michel Vaillaud, chairman, said the drop in net income was mainly the result of the general decline in the oilfield services business and continuing losses at the company's Fairchild Semiconductor subsidiary.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/13/business/schlumberger-plans-485-million-charge.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">SCHLUMBERGER PLANS $485 MILLION CHARGE<date>December 13, 1985</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., in a major break with the way it has done things in the past, yesterday announced a $485 million charge against earnings and a stock repurchase program. The moves were the first major steps taken by the big oilfield services and electronics company since the death in October of Jean Riboud, whose 20-year leadership of Schlumberger ended in September. Mr. Riboud was noted for his patience in sticking to a course of action he believed in, even if it proposed temporary business setbacks. Michel Vaillaud, the new chairman and chief executive, won approval for the moves yesterday in the company's first board meeting since Mr. Riboud's death. Schlumberger has been facing challenges in its oilfield services business and in its Fairchild Semiconductor subsidiary. The oil business is in a slump and semiconductors are threatened by imports from Japan. Earnings have been dropping. Schlumberger said it would take the $485 million charge against earnings in the current quarter in connection with its troubled Fairchild division. It also approved a stock repurchase program to allow it to buy as many as 25 million shares, or 8 percent of the stock outstanding, depending on market conditions.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Schlumberger Ltd., in a major break with the way it has done things in the past, yesterday announced a $485 million charge against earnings and a stock repurchase program. The moves were the first major steps taken by the big oilfield services and electronics company since the death in October of Jean Riboud, whose 20-year leadership of Schlumberger ended in September. Mr. Riboud was noted for his patience in sticking to a course of action he believed in, even if it proposed temporary business setbacks. Michel Vaillaud, the new chairman and chief executive, won approval for the moves yesterday in the company's first board meeting since Mr. Riboud's death. Schlumberger has been facing challenges in its oilfield services business and in its Fairchild Semiconductor subsidiary. The oil business is in a slump and semiconductors are threatened by imports from Japan. Earnings have been dropping. Schlumberger said it would take the $485 million charge against earnings in the current quarter in connection with its troubled Fairchild division. It also approved a stock repurchase program to allow it to buy as many as 25 million shares, or 8 percent of the stock outstanding, depending on market conditions.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/10/27/business/no-headline-109403.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">No Headline<date>Published: October 27, 1985</date><text>Schlumberger's operations were spread out around the world when Jean Riboud joined the oil services company in 1951. By the time he became president in 1965, he had consolidated the operations and expanded into the then-new field of electronics. And when Mr. Riboud, 65 years old and ill with cancer, stepped down as chairman in September, Schlumberger was acknowledged as one of the world's best-managed companies. Mr. Riboud's style was autocratic, but he brought with him to Schlumberger much of the passion that made him a member of the French Resistance. His philosophy of life, he once told an interviewer, was based on a saying of Naploeon's: ''War is a simple art, but it is all in the execution.'' Photo of Jean Riboud</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/12/business/an-era-ends-at-schlumberger.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">AN ERA ENDS AT SCHLUMBERGER<date>September 12, 1985</date><text>Jean Riboud, the dynamic chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger Ltd., who once told an interviewer that leaving the giant oilfield services company ''would be like trying to shake an oyster off a rock,'' stepped down yesterday, ending a 20-year era of leadership. At a special meeting in Paris called by Mr. Riboud, the company's board elected Michel Vaillaud, who has been president and chief operating officer since 1982, to succeed him. According to sources close to the company, Mr. Riboud has been ill with cancer for about a year. Mr. Vaillaud, a 53-year-old former French Government official, had been his handpicked successor. Mr. Riboud, who turned 65 last November, has already served nearly 10 months beyond the company's normal mandatory retirement age, and a company spokesman, Seth McCormick, took pains yesterday to say that Mr. Riboud was not resigning or retiring. He will remain a director and a member of the executive committee, and will become chairman of the finance committee.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Jean Riboud, the dynamic chairman and chief executive of Schlumberger Ltd., who once told an interviewer that leaving the giant oilfield services company ''would be like trying to shake an oyster off a rock,'' stepped down yesterday, ending a 20-year era of leadership. At a special meeting in Paris called by Mr. Riboud, the company's board elected Michel Vaillaud, who has been president and chief operating officer since 1982, to succeed him. According to sources close to the company, Mr. Riboud has been ill with cancer for about a year. Mr. Vaillaud, a 53-year-old former French Government official, had been his handpicked successor. Mr. Riboud, who turned 65 last November, has already served nearly 10 months beyond the company's normal mandatory retirement age, and a company spokesman, Seth McCormick, took pains yesterday to say that Mr. Riboud was not resigning or retiring. He will remain a director and a member of the executive committee, and will become chairman of the finance committee.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/07/17/business/schlumberger-s-net-off-27.3.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger's Net Off 27.3%<date>Published: July 17, 1985</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's largest oilfield services company, said yesterday that its profit fell 27.3 percent in the second quarter, to $212.1 million, or 71 cents a share, from $291.7 million, or $1.01 a share, a year ago. Revenue rose 4.3 percent, to $1.64 billion, from $1.57 billion. The company attributed the decline to the slump in oil exploration, a major acquisition and depressed conditions in the semiconductor industry. Jean Riboud, the chairman of Schlumberger, said after-tax earnings were reduced by $17 million because of expenses associated with the December 1984 acquisition of Sedco Inc., an offshore oil exploration company. A reduction in oil exploration, related to falling oil prices, reduced overall profits from oilfield services.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/04/19/business/schlumberger-s-net-up-10.8.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger's Net Up 10.8%<date>Published: April 19, 1985</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd., the world's largest oilfield services company, said yesterday that its earnings rose 10.8 percent in the first quarter, to $303.5 million, or $1.01 a share, from $273.9 million, or 95 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue climbed 14.2 percent, to $1.69 billion, from $1.48 billion. Schlumberger said that the costs associated with its acquisition last year of Sedco Inc., an offshore oil exploration company, reduced net income by about $2 million, while an issue of an additional 13 million shares of stock as part of the purchase diluted per-share esrnings by 6 cents. Jean Riboud, the company's chairman, said oilfield activity in North America was only slightly above last year's levels as increased offshore drilling was offset by a slackening of onshore activity.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/04/18/nyregion/c-correction-176423.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">CORRECTION<date>Published: April 18, 1985</date><text>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Tuesday about testing problems at companies selling semiconductors to the military misidentified one such company. It was the Fairchild division of Schlumberger Ltd.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1985/01/03/business/business-people-transition-announced-at-fairchild-camera.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">BUSINESS PEOPLE; Transition Announced At Fairchild Camera<date>January 3, 1985</date><text>Donald W. Brooks has been named president and chief executive officer of the Fairchild Camera and Instrument Corporation, the semiconductor manufacturer said yesterday. Mr. Brooks, 45, succeeds Thomas C. Roberts, 42. Mr. Roberts has held the posts at Fairchild since the company was purchased by Schlumberger Ltd., the oil-service company headed by Jean Riboud, in 1979 for $425 million in cash.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Donald W. Brooks has been named president and chief executive officer of the Fairchild Camera and Instrument Corporation, the semiconductor manufacturer said yesterday. Mr. Brooks, 45, succeeds Thomas C. Roberts, 42. Mr. Roberts has held the posts at Fairchild since the company was purchased by Schlumberger Ltd., the oil-service company headed by Jean Riboud, in 1979 for $425 million in cash.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/12/27/business/schlumberger-ltd.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Ltd.<date>Published: December 27, 1984</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd.'s acquisition of Sedco Inc. has been completed, the companies said. Under the purchase accord, Schlumberger, which is involved in oilfield services and electronics, will issue about 13 million shares of its common stock and pay approximately $482 million in cash. On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, Schlumberger fell 62.5 cents, to $37. Sedco, based in Dallas, is an offshore drilling contractor.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/09/15/business/oil-service-concern-to-buy-sedco.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">OIL SERVICE CONCERN TO BUY SEDCO<date>September 15, 1984</date><text>Sedco Inc. and Schlumberger Ltd. reported yesterday that they had agreed to a merger of Sedco into a subsidiary of Schlumberger in a transaction valued at more than $1 billion. The merger of the Dallas-based Sedco, an offshore drilling company,, into the Schlumberger subsidiary is subject to approval of Sedco's shareholders. Trading in Sedco's stock was halted for much of the day yesterday; it had soared $3.375 in abbreviated activity Thursday, to $37.125, with the volume heavy. After trading was resumed yesterday, the stock rose $8.875, to $46, on the New York Stock Exchange. Schlumberger fell $1.125 a share, to $46.625.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] Sedco Inc. and Schlumberger Ltd. reported yesterday that they had agreed to a merger of Sedco into a subsidiary of Schlumberger in a transaction valued at more than $1 billion. The merger of the Dallas-based Sedco, an offshore drilling company,, into the Schlumberger subsidiary is subject to approval of Sedco's shareholders. Trading in Sedco's stock was halted for much of the day yesterday; it had soared $3.375 in abbreviated activity Thursday, to $37.125, with the volume heavy. After trading was resumed yesterday, the stock rose $8.875, to $46, on the New York Stock Exchange. Schlumberger fell $1.125 a share, to $46.625.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/08/01/business/market-place-the-weakness-in-oil-services.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Market Place; The Weakness In Oil Services<date>August 1, 1984</date><text>ONE of the recurring truths in the energy business is that prices of oil service issues are dependent on the direction - or the perceived direction - of crude oil prices. As a result, current weakness in spot prices for crude and the suspicion, too, that official prices soon might ease have depressed shares of companies that provide an array of services to the petroleum exploration and drilling industry. Schlumberger Ltd., generally regarded as the jewel of its group, traded yesterday at its lowest price in more than a year. The same was true of the Halliburton Company. Shares of the Hughes Tool Company, which recently reported a second-quarter loss of $135.1 million and later cut its common stock dividend, sold Monday at a six-year low.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] ONE of the recurring truths in the energy business is that prices of oil service issues are dependent on the direction - or the perceived direction - of crude oil prices. As a result, current weakness in spot prices for crude and the suspicion, too, that official prices soon might ease have depressed shares of companies that provide an array of services to the petroleum exploration and drilling industry. Schlumberger Ltd., generally regarded as the jewel of its group, traded yesterday at its lowest price in more than a year. The same was true of the Halliburton Company. Shares of the Hughes Tool Company, which recently reported a second-quarter loss of $135.1 million and later cut its common stock dividend, sold Monday at a six-year low.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/04/20/business/schlumberger-net-up.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Net Up<date>Published: April 20, 1984</date><text>Schlumberger Ltd. said yesterday that gains from its semiconductor operations helped offset falling revenues in its oilfield services division and raise its first-quarter profit by 5.8 percent. The company reported profits of $273.9 million, or 95 cents a share, up from $259 million, or 89 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenues were $1.48 billion, up from $1.46 billion. Jean Riboud, chairman, said revenues in the company's measurement, control and components division rose 10 percent.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/02/17/business/dow-chemical-sale-combines-oil-units.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Dow Chemical Sale Combines Oil Units<date>February 17, 1984</date><text>The Dow Chemical Company said yesterday that it had agreed to sell 50 percent of its Dowell subsidiary to a company it jointly owns with Schlumberger Ltd. for $440 million. Dow said this would add the subsidiary's business in the United States and Canada to the Dowell Schlumberger Oil Field Services Company, the jointly owned company.[ DISPLAYING ABSTRACT ] The Dow Chemical Company said yesterday that it had agreed to sell 50 percent of its Dowell subsidiary to a company it jointly owns with Schlumberger Ltd. for $440 million. Dow said this would add the subsidiary's business in the United States and Canada to the Dowell Schlumberger Oil Field Services Company, the jointly owned company.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1983/10/19/business/schlumberger-ltd.html?ref=schlumbergerltd">Schlumberger Ltd.<date>Published: October 19, 1983</date><text>PARIS, Oct. 18— State- owned Compagnie de Saint Gobain said it had sold a 10 percent stake in Compagnie Generale des Eaux to Schlumberger Ltd., of New York. The transaction, valued at the equivalent of about $36 million, ends a move seen at the outset by Generale des Eaux as an attempted backdoor nationalization, industry sources said. It reduces Saint Gobain's holding in Generale des Eaux, a utility involved in water distribution and engineering, to 20.7 percent. That is in line with a ruling by the stock exchange on July 29 after transactions in June and July, partly with other state-owned companies, gave Saint Gobain a 33 percent holding in Generale des Eaux.</text></article></page><page index="10" /></root>
