<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Southern Company"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/08/10/westinghouse-reactor-takes-a-step-forward/?ref=southerncompany">Westinghouse Reactor Takes a Step Forward<date>August 10, 2011, 6:00 am</date><text>Southern CompanyA rendering of Plant Vogtle with the addition of AP-!000 reactors. The reactor at the leading edge of what has been cast as a “nuclear renaissance” has taken a step forward. The staff of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said on Tuesday that it had finished its evaluation of the safety of the proposed Vogtle 3 and 4 reactors, a Southern Company project near Augusta, Ga. The staff has also completed work on Southern’s application for a license to build and run the reactors. Final approval is still months away; the five commissioners will have to hold a hearing and then vote to confirm both approvals. At the moment, that is expected by year’s end. Scott Burnell, a commission spokesman, said that the basic question facing the commission is whether it is satisfied with its staff’s work on safety and environmental evaluations related to the reactor, the new Westinghouse AP-1000. If the commission votes yes, “then things are good,’’ he said. The regulatory advance is especially good news for Westinghouse because it is generic, meant to cover all copies of the AP-1000 design. And while Plant Vogtle is the leading edge, with some structures without the routine safety issues already constructed, only one project is following in its footsteps at the moment: the Virgil C. Summer 2 and 3 reactors in South Carolina. Those, too, are AP-1000’s. For anybody keeping score, final approval of the AP-1000 would make it the fourth design approved under a reformed licensing procedure in which the commission gives a blanket go-ahead for the design so that subsequent builders need only provide an approved site and go through a brief process to assure that the reactor is compatible with it. By contrast, almost all the 104 reactors now running in the United States were approved individually or in pairs. The AP-1000 (the letters stand for “advanced passive” technology and the number is the reactor’s approximate capacity in megawatts) has a complicated history. It was approved once before but after the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, and other considerations, it needed more work. There are still opponents, and they may still seek to delay approval. While the AP-1000 could become the fourth approved model, only two are current designs. General Electric’s Advanced Boiling Water Reactor, or A.B.W.R., approved in May 1997, is available to the industry. The two others that have been approved are no longer considered current: the AP-600, a Westinghouse offering in the 1990’s that no one built but received regulatory approval in December 1999, and the System 80+, based on a design by Combustion Engineering, a company later absorbed by competitors that was approved in May 1997. The boiling water reactor is the one that NRG Energy, a power generation company based in Princeton, wanted to build in a twin-reactor expansion of the South Texas Project. But one of the partners in that venture was the Tokyo Electric Power Company, which was sidelined from participation by the Fukushima Daiichi accident in Japan. NRG itself cited the accident when it said it would not put more money into the project. Fukushima aside, the economics of the expensive nuclear project are far from clear because low natural gas prices have depressed electricity prices in Texas’s competitive market. But the application is still considered active, said Mr. Burnell, the commission spokesman.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/14/scattered-attempts-at-carbon-capture/?ref=southerncompany">Scattered Attempts at Carbon Capture<date>July 14, 2011, 3:54 pm</date><text>Department of EnergyThe Energy Department is aiding eight such projects. (A.E.P.’s was canceled.) As my colleague John Broder and I reported in Thursday’s paper, American Electric Power is dropping its plan to build a commercial-scale version of a carbon dioxide scrubber at Mountaineer, its coal-fired power plant in New Haven, W.Va. The company decided that since public service commissions in West Virginia and Virginia had refused to give it full reimbursement for a pilot version that it ran for two years, it could not expect to recover its investment for the full-scale version — even if the Energy Department was going to pony up $334 million, or half the cost. Senator Jay Rockefeller, the West Virginia Democrat who had helped secure the $334 million as part of the fiscal stimulus act, was quick to praise the pilot project and to say that the money would be available for other carbon-capture projects. In fact, eight other such projects are in the pipeline, although none quite like Mountaineer, a middle-aged coal-fired electric plant that had planned to bury the carbon dioxide. Plants like that will probably continue to pump carbon dioxide into the atmosphere for decades. It is possible that not all of the eight will come to fruition, but they offer interesting possibilities the Southern Company, for example, has already broken ground on a $2.67 billion power plant in Kemper County, Miss., to which the Energy Department will contribute $270 million. The plant will cook coal into a gas, separate out some of the carbon dioxide and burn the gas. The plant will emit very low levels of other pollutants and can use local coals that have low heating value per ton. Some other projects aided by the Energy Department yield carbon dioxide but are not power plants. An Archer Daniels Midland ethanol plant in Decatur, Ill., will sequester its carbon dioxide in an underground sandstone layer. Ethanol production gives off a stream of nearly pure carbon dioxide, so capture is easy. In Meredosia, Ill., the Energy Department is helping pay for the conversion of a plant that was originally built to use oil. In its new configuration, an air separation unit will pull oxygen out of the air and use it to burn coal. At a conventional power plant, the exhaust is mostly nitrogen. But if the coal is burned in oxygen, the exhaust is mostly carbon dioxide. It is by far the Energy Department’s biggest investment, $1.08 billion out of a total cost of about $1.3 billion. The W.A. Parish generating station, a coal-fired power station in Thompsons, Tex., southwest of Houston, and owned by NRG, will be equipped with a carbon scrubber. It sits in the midst of oil fields and could sell its carbon dioxide to drillers, who would pump the material underground to force oil to the surface. Depending on the oil field, a ton of carbon dioxide can produce two to four barrels. At $100 a barrel, that would be a high market value for the carbon dioxide. The Parish project is supposed to cost $339 million, with the Energy Department contributing $167 million. It is about one-quarter the size of the canceled A.E.P. project. Near Odessa, Tex., another plant will also cook coal into a gas and sequester the carbon. But that plant, Summit TX Clean Energy, is a “poly-gen” plant, making both fertilizer and electric power. It is supposed to cost $1.7 billion, with a $450 million taxpayer contribution. In Lake Charles, La., Leucadia Energy will turn petroleum coke into methanol and capture the carbon dioxide. That project is supposed to cost $436 million, with $261 million coming from the Energy Department. And in Port Arthur, Tex., Air Products will expose natural gas to steam to create methanol; the carbon dioxide will be captured and used in the oil fields. That is a $426 million project, of which $261 comes from the Energy Department. In Kern County, Calif., the Energy Department will put $408 million toward a $2.8 billion plant that will take petroleum coke, a leftover from oil refining, and cook it into hydrogen gas for use in power generation, with sequestration of the carbon dioxide. These projects use a variety of capture technologies. A crucial part of A.E.P.’s now-abandoned attempt was the use of ammonia, which is well suited to existing plants, to bind with the carbon dioxide. A.E.P.’s partner in the Mountaineer pilot, Alstom, which built the ammonia system, said it understood the decision to shelve the capture project but cautioned that commercialization of the technology was needed to reduce climate change. “If we deviate from the critical path for commercializing C.C.S. technology and do not build large-scale demonstration plants, it will take longer to drive down the technology cost curve, and significantly increase delivered electricity costs,’’ Alstom said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/16/the-tricky-u-s-reactor-tally/?ref=southerncompany">The Tricky U.S. Reactor Tally<date>June 16, 2011, 12:14 pm</date><text>Associated PressReporters viewed two containment pools for spent fuel this month at the half-built Bellefonte plant in Hollywood, Ala. The T.V.A. will decide this summer whether to finish construction. At the entrance to the unfinished Bellefonte nuclear plant in Hollywood, Ala., are morale-building posters for Tennessee Valley Authority employees. In bold type, they proclaim “106.” The number refers to how many nuclear reactors the United States would have if the Bellefonte 1 reactor were finished, but such prognostications are dicey. As I note in Thursday’s paper, the Bellefonte project was announced in 1970. Ground was broken in 1974, but the plant was ultimately abandoned in 1988 because of weak demand for its electricity. The board of directors of the Tennessee Valley Authority plans to vote in August on whether to finish Unit 1. At present there are 104 operable power reactors in the United States. (On any given day, several are shut down for one reason or another.) The T.V.A. is already working to finish another long-suspended nuclear project, Watts Bar 2 in Tennessee, a two-hour drive from Bellefonte. That plant is supposed to be completed in 2012, and Bellefonte 1 could be finished by 2020, becoming No. 106. Except that two or three of the existing 104 may be shut by then. New Jersey had pressed Exelon to build a cooling tower for its Oyster Creek reactor, in Toms River, N.J. Oyster Creek won a 20-year license extension, but then reached an agreement with the state to skip the cooling tower but retire the plant in 10 years. Vermont Yankee, in Vernon, Vt., on the Connecticut River near the Massachusetts border, has won a 20-year license extension but needs a permit from the state if it is to run beyond next spring. Vermont officials are refusing, and the case is in court . Some other plants around the country may also retire, especially in view of the very low price of natural gas, which makes nuclear power less competitive. Speculation is growing that Progress Energy might decide to shut down its Crystal River reactor near Tampa, Fla., where operators have been trying for nearly two years to fix a problem with the containment building. The Tampa Tribune reported recently that a decision is imminent. Further complicating the reactor numbers game, the Southern Company plans to finish two additional units at Plant Vogtle near Augusta, Ga., by 2020, and two more reactors are planned in South Carolina at the site of the existing V.C. Summer reactor.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/21/business/energy-environment/21nuke.html?ref=southerncompany">Westinghouse Nuclear Reactor Design Flaw Is Found<date>Published: May 20, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — In a setback for the only model of nuclear reactor for which ground has been broken in the United States, government regulators have found additional problems with the design of its shield building, a crucial component, the chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said on Friday.The chairman, Gregory B. Jaczko, said that computations submitted by Westinghouse, the manufacturer of the new AP1000 reactor, about the building’s design appeared to be wrong and “had led to more questions.” He said the company had not used a range of possible temperatures for calculating potential seismic stresses on the shield building in the event of an earthquake, for example. Mr. Jaczko said the commission was asking Westinghouse not only to fix its calculations but also to explain why it submitted flawed information in the first place. Earlier this year the commission staff said it needed additional calculations from Westinghouse to confirm the strength of the AP1000’s shield building. The building has not been built; the analysis of its strength and safety is all computer based. The announcement comes as the commission and the American nuclear industry are facing increased scrutiny as a result of the calamity that began after an earthquake and tsunami damaged the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear plant in Japan in March, leading to releases of radioactive material. Various critics have asked the commission to suspend licensing of new plants, the relicensing of old ones and various other activities until the implications of the Fukushima accident are clearer. While the commission has said it will evaluate the Japanese accident methodically, it had previously said it did not anticipate that this would cause a delay in approving the AP1000. Now, however, it appears far warier that it will finish this summer. Westinghouse countered in a statement that the “confirmatory items” that the commission was asking for were not “safety significant.” It noted, and the commission agreed, that the company had been the first to identify some of the problems itself. Still, the commission seems to have taken a slightly darker view. The Southern Company has already dug the foundations and done other preliminary work for two of the AP1000 reactors adjacent to its existing reactors at Plant Vogtle near Augusta, Ga. The Energy Department has promised loan guarantees for that project provided that the Nuclear Regulatory Commission approves the design. South Carolina Electric and Gas has broken ground for another two, 20 miles northwest of Columbia. The commission had previously said it expected to approve the AP1000 design this summer. But on Friday a spokesman for the commission, Scott Burnell, said the decision would be delayed for a period of time that he could not specify until Westinghouse submitted a third round of revised calculations. “They need to be doing the work correctly and completely, and we need to have confidence that that’s what they’re doing,” said one commission official, who said he was not authorized to be quoted by name. “They have additional work they need to do, and a short time to complete it if it’s not going to have a significant impact on their schedule.” Southern had been expecting to receive a license to construct and operate the new plant by the end of this year and to have the first reactor on line by mid-2016. On Friday, the company said it still planned to proceed. “We have confidence the AP1000 technology,” a company spokesman, Todd Terrell, said. In addition to the plants in Georgia and South Carolina, ground has also been broken on four AP1000 reactors in China, two at Sanmen and two at Haiyang. Westinghouse, which is owned by Toshiba, is making parts for the Chinese units in factories in the Pittsburgh area. The AP1000 was in principle designed so it would be faster to build and safer to run than previous models. The letters stand for “advanced passive,” with many of its safety features depending on natural forces like gravity and convective cooling rather than pumps and valves, which could be knocked out by electrical failures or floods as they were at Fukushima. 1 2 Next Page »WASHINGTON — In a setback for the only model of nuclear reactor for which ground has been broken in the United States, government regulators have found additional problems with the design of its shield building, a crucial component, the chairman of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission said on Friday.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/19/business/energy-environment/19bizbriefs-34BILLIONGUA_BRF.html?ref=southerncompany">$3.4. Billion Guarantee for New Nuclear Plant<date>Published: June 18, 2010</date><text>The Southern Company, the giant utility owner, agreed to a $3.4 billion federal loan guarantee to build the country’s first nuclear power plant in three decades. The guarantee covers up to 70 percent of Southern’s eligible projected costs, the company said Friday. “This is another step forward on the road to nuclear power playing a prominent role in America’s energy future,” David Ratcliffe, the chief executive, said in a statement. Southern would be the first to receive federal aid under a five-year-old law aimed in part at helping add nuclear stations, which usually cost more and take longer to build than coal or natural-gas-fired generators. Southern plans to add two reactors to its Vogtle station near Waynesboro, Ga., in 2016 and 2017.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/17/business/energy-environment/17nukes.html?ref=southerncompany">U.S. Supports New Nuclear Reactors in Georgia<date>Published: February 16, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTON  President Obama, speaking to an enthusiastic audience of union officials in Lanham, Md., on Tuesday, underscored his embrace of nuclear power as a clean energy source, announcing that the Energy Department had approved financial help for the construction of two nuclear reactors in Georgia. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Video Obama on Energy Jobs (CNBC) A Comeback for Nuclear Power? Does the need for new sources of energy outweigh the risks associated with nuclear power? Post a Comment » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » If the project goes forward, the reactors would be the first begun in the United States since the 1970s. The announcement of the loan guarantee  $8.3 billion to help the Southern Company and two partners build twin reactors in Burke County  comes as the administration is courting Republican support for its climate and energy policies. With climate legislation stalled in the Senate and its prospects for success dim, Democrats are seeking new incentives to spur clean energy development and create jobs. At the same time, the president’s embrace of nuclear energy has drawn the ire of environmental groups that have long opposed any return to a reliance on nuclear power. In his speech, Mr. Obama portrayed the decision as part of a broad strategy to increase employment and the generation of clean power. But he also made clear that the move was a bid to gain Republican support for a broader energy bill. “Those who have long advocated for nuclear power  including many Republicans  have to recognize that we will not achieve a big boost in nuclear capacity unless we also create a system of incentives to make clean energy profitable,” Mr. Obama said. Some Republicans, however, said that the announcement would have little effect on their votes. Don Stewart, a spokesman for the Republican Senate leader, Mitch McConnell, said that Mr. McConnell had repeatedly praised Mr. Obama for favoring additional loan guarantees for nuclear power plants. But, he said, this would not translate into support for a cap on carbon dioxide emissions. “It won’t cause Republicans to support the national energy tax,” Mr. Stewart said. He added that Republican and Democratic ideas on energy policy overlapped in some areas, but that much of Mr. Obama’s energy program did not fall into those areas. Robert Dillon, a spokesman for Senator Lisa Murkowski, Republican of Alaska, said that she thought nuclear power was “a core component of a comprehensive energy plan,” but that she would vote on an energy bill as a whole. “One or two provisions aren’t going to offset bad provisions,” he said. The announcement of the loan guarantees, which had been signaled in advance, drew immediate praise from the nuclear industry and criticism from some environmental groups. David M. Ratcliffe, the chairman and chief executive of the Southern Company, said that a nuclear renaissance was in the wings and that “we will get on with that at a more rapid pace now that we’ve made this first step.” Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club, however, said that nuclear power was not the fastest or cheapest way to reduce the greenhouse gases linked to global warming. “The loan guarantees announced today may ease the politics around comprehensive clean energy and climate legislation, but we do not believe that they are the best policy,” he said. Despite the financing, the reactors are far from a done deal: their design has not yet been fully approved by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, whose staff has raised questions about whether changes made to harden the plant against aircraft attack had made it more vulnerable to earthquakes. The builders hope to have a license to build and run the plant by the end of next year, under a revised process that is supposed to eliminate problems that caused huge cost overruns in the 1970s and 1980s, when regulatory changes during construction added billions to costs. About 100 reactors were abandoned during construction in that era. The Southern Company applied two years ago to the commission for permission to build and operate the reactors, adjacent to its Vogtle 1 and 2 reactors. The loan guarantees were authorized by the Energy Policy Act of 2005. If the reactors are built and operate profitably, the borrowers will repay the banks and pay a fee to the federal government in exchange for the guarantee; if the borrowers default, the federal government will repay the banks. Critics have argued that the chance of default is high, and the loans have been delayed by protracted negotiations over what the fee should be. The money for the reactors is the first award from $18.5 billion in loan guarantees provided for under the 2005 act. But Mr. Obama proposed this month to triple that amount. The guarantees can cover up to 80 percent of the estimated project cost, although some builders may ask for less. Southern asked for 70 percent, but the project may also be eligible for loan guarantees from the Japanese government; the reactors were designed by Westinghouse, a unit of Toshiba. The Energy Department is negotiating with potential borrowers for three other projects, two of which could win guarantees soon. The Scana Corporation and Santee Cooper want to build a nuclear plant near Jenkinsville, S.C., and UniStar is planning a reactor in southern Maryland, adjacent to the Calvert Cliffs reactors. A third project, in Texas, is in some doubt because of rising cost estimates and a lawsuit filed by the municipal utility serving San Antonio against its partner in the project, NRG of Princeton, N.J. The United States has 104 operating power reactors, but all the reactors ordered after 1973 were canceled. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 17, 2010, on page B1 of the New York edition.WASHINGTON  President Obama, speaking to an enthusiastic audience of union officials in Lanham, Md., on Tuesday, underscored his embrace of nuclear power as a clean energy source, announcing that the Energy Department had approved financial help for the construction of two nuclear reactors in Georgia. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Video Obama on Energy Jobs (CNBC) A Comeback for Nuclear Power? Does the need for new sources of energy outweigh the risks associated with nuclear power? Post a Comment » A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » If the project goes forward, the reactors would be the first begun in the United States since the 1970s. The announcement of the loan guarantee  $8.3 billion to help the Southern Company and two partners build twin reactors in Burke County  comes as the administration is courting Republican support for its climate and energy policies. With climate legislation stalled in the Senate and its prospects for success dim, Democrats are seeking new incentives to spur clean energy development and create jobs. At the same time, the president’s embrace of nuclear energy has drawn the ire of environmental groups that have long opposed any return to a reliance on nuclear power. In his speech, Mr. Obama portrayed the decision as part of a broad strategy to increase employment and the generation of clean power. But he also made clear that the move was a bid to gain Republican support for a broader energy bill. “Those who have long advocated for nuclear power  including many Republicans  have to recognize that we will not achieve a big boost in nuclear capacity unless we also create a system of incentives to make clean energy profitable,” Mr. Obama said. Some Republicans, however, said that the announcement would have little effect on their votes. Don Stewart, a spokesman for the Republican Senate leader, Mitch McConnell, said that Mr. McConnell had repeatedly praised Mr. Obama for favoring additional loan guarantees for nuclear power plants. But, he said, this would not translate into support for a cap on carbon dioxide emissions. “It won’t cause Republicans to support the national energy tax,” Mr. Stewart said. He added that Republican and Democratic ideas on energy policy overlapped in some areas, but that much of Mr. Obama’s energy program did not fall into those areas. Robert Dillon, a spokesman for Senator Lisa Murkowski, Republican of Alaska, said that she thought nuclear power was “a core component of a comprehensive energy plan,” but that she would vote on an energy bill as a whole. “One or two provisions aren’t going to offset bad provisions,” he said. The announcement of the loan guarantees, which had been signaled in advance, drew immediate praise from the nuclear industry and criticism from some environmental groups. David M. Ratcliffe, the chairman and chief executive of the Southern Company, said that a nuclear renaissance was in the wings and that “we will get on with that at a more rapid pace now that we’ve made this first step.” Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club, however, said that nuclear power was not the fastest or cheapest way to reduce the greenhouse gases linked to global warming. “The loan guarantees announced today may ease the politics around comprehensive clean energy and climate legislation, but we do not believe that they are the best policy,” he said. Despite the financing, the reactors are far from a done deal: their design has not yet been fully approved by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, whose staff has raised questions about whether changes made to harden the plant against aircraft attack had made it more vulnerable to earthquakes. The builders hope to have a license to build and run the plant by the end of next year, under a revised process that is supposed to eliminate problems that caused huge cost overruns in the 1970s and 1980s, when regulatory changes during construction added billions to costs. About 100 reactors were abandoned during construction in that era. The Southern Company applied two years ago to the commission for permission to build and operate the reactors, adjacent to its Vogtle 1 and 2 reactors. The loan guarantees were authorized by the Energy Policy Act of 2005. If the reactors are built and operate profitably, the borrowers will repay the banks and pay a fee to the federal government in exchange for the guarantee; if the borrowers default, the federal government will repay the banks. Critics have argued that the chance of default is high, and the loans have been delayed by protracted negotiations over what the fee should be. The money for the reactors is the first award from $18.5 billion in loan guarantees provided for under the 2005 act. But Mr. Obama proposed this month to triple that amount. The guarantees can cover up to 80 percent of the estimated project cost, although some builders may ask for less. Southern asked for 70 percent, but the project may also be eligible for loan guarantees from the Japanese government; the reactors were designed by Westinghouse, a unit of Toshiba. The Energy Department is negotiating with potential borrowers for three other projects, two of which could win guarantees soon. The Scana Corporation and Santee Cooper want to build a nuclear plant near Jenkinsville, S.C., and UniStar is planning a reactor in southern Maryland, adjacent to the Calvert Cliffs reactors. A third project, in Texas, is in some doubt because of rising cost estimates and a lawsuit filed by the municipal utility serving San Antonio against its partner in the project, NRG of Princeton, N.J. The United States has 104 operating power reactors, but all the reactors ordered after 1973 were canceled.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/13/business/energy-environment/13nuke.html?ref=southerncompany">U.S. to Back Loans for Reactors<date>Published: February 12, 2010</date><text>WASHINGTON  President Obama is to announce on Tuesday a loan guarantee to allow construction of two nuclear reactors in Georgia, according to administration officials. Skip to next paragraph A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » If the project happens, it is likely to be the first nuclear reactor construction in the United States since the 1970s. The Southern Company applied two years ago to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for permission to build and operate two reactors in Burke County, near Augusta, adjacent to its Vogtle 1 and 2 reactors. The company hopes to win a license late next year. The loan guarantee was authorized by the 2005 Energy Policy Act. If the reactors are built and operate profitably, the borrowers will repay the banks and pay a fee to the federal government in exchange for the guarantee; if the borrowers default, the federal government will repay the banks. Critics have argued that the chance of default is high, and the loans have been delayed by protracted negotiations over what the fee should be. The 2005 act provided $18.5 billion in guarantees, but Mr. Obama proposed earlier this month to triple that amount. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on February 13, 2010, on page B6 of the New York edition.WASHINGTON  President Obama is to announce on Tuesday a loan guarantee to allow construction of two nuclear reactors in Georgia, according to administration officials. Skip to next paragraph A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » If the project happens, it is likely to be the first nuclear reactor construction in the United States since the 1970s. The Southern Company applied two years ago to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for permission to build and operate two reactors in Burke County, near Augusta, adjacent to its Vogtle 1 and 2 reactors. The company hopes to win a license late next year. The loan guarantee was authorized by the 2005 Energy Policy Act. If the reactors are built and operate profitably, the borrowers will repay the banks and pay a fee to the federal government in exchange for the guarantee; if the borrowers default, the federal government will repay the banks. Critics have argued that the chance of default is high, and the loans have been delayed by protracted negotiations over what the fee should be. The 2005 act provided $18.5 billion in guarantees, but Mr. Obama proposed earlier this month to triple that amount.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/24/business/energy-environment/24nuke.html?ref=southerncompany">Loan Program May Stir Nuclear Industry<date>Published: December 23, 2009</date><text>WASHINGTON  When experts on power grid reliability asked themselves recently how a cleaner energy future would look, seven of eight regional councils imagined how their systems would work with 10 percent wind power. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Babcock &amp; Wilcox Company Some environmentalists now see nuclear power as part of an effort to combat climate change. Multimedia Graphic Growth and Skepticism in Nuclear Power A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Only one, representing the southeastern United States, chose a radically different option: doubling nuclear power capacity. Thirty years after the American nuclear industry abandoned scores of half-built plants because of soaring costs and operating problems like the Three Mile Island accident, skepticism persists over whether the technology is worth investing in. Yet the pendulum may be swinging back. The 104 plants now running have sharply raised their output, emboldening utilities across the country to make a case for building new ones. And the industry is about to get a big boost. In the next few days, the Energy Department plans to announce the first of $18.5 billion in loan guarantees for building new reactors. The guarantees were authorized in a bill passed by Congress in 2005. It has taken four years for the department to set up a system to evaluate applications and determine how much the borrowers will be charged for the guarantees to compensate the government for taking the risk. Industry experts think the first guarantee will go to the Southern Company to build two units at its Vogtle nuclear plant near Augusta, Ga. The money will flow amid a national credit squeeze and intense jockeying among the nation’s wind, solar, geothermal and nuclear sectors. Each is trying to cast itself as an ideal “clean” energy option as the nation moves toward reining in the carbon dioxide emissions linked to global warming. All of these sources could potentially benefit under a cap-and-trade system that is being considered in Congress as part of climate change legislation. Such a system would set a ceiling on carbon dioxide emissions and allow trading of pollution permits, handicapping the carbon-intensive coal and natural gas sectors. Historically Republicans have been more enthusiastic than Democrats about nuclear power. So as the climate bill winds its way through the Senate, some Democratic members are seeking to add to the $18.5 billion in loan guarantees for the nuclear industry to attract Republicans and some industrial-state Democrats. (The House version passed in June, 219 to 212.) Some of the foremost Congressional climate change campaigners are unenthusiastic. Representative Edward Markey, a Massachusetts Democrat who has hounded the nuclear industry for decades over safety questions and who is a sponsor of the House bill, does not favor direct aid to the nuclear industry. He argues that a cap-and-trade system would give the nuclear sector the only boost it deserves. If that system goes into effect, he said, nuclear power “will be able to compete more effectively in a new marketplace. How effectively they can compete is going to be the question.” Others see combining a cap-and-trade system with a nuclear aid package as a sensible tactic to get Congress to address environmental problems. “One can argue it certainly is bringing about an unusual marriage of interests here,” said Philip R. Sharp, an Indiana Democrat who served in the House of Representatives from 1975 to 1995 and led a House committee with jurisdiction over the electric system. “It is one of the potential paths for actually getting real action and real legislation,” said Mr. Sharp, who now heads the nonpartisan group Resources for the Future. Economic issues have helped scramble alliances on the state and local level, too. Because new reactors create so many jobs and big tax revenue, the Democratic governors of Maryland and Ohio are working hard to get them built in their states. State legislatures from Louisiana to South Dakota and local governments from Port Gibson, Miss., to Oswego, N.Y., are also on record favoring new reactors. Peter A. Bradford, a former member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission who is now vice chairman of the Union of Concerned Scientists, questions the wisdom of direct aid to the industry. Unlike cap and trade, in which industries buy and sell the right to release carbon dioxide in a market-oriented system, he said, the loan guarantees finance projects that the private sector deems too risky. The government would be “picking some winners and bestowing a lot of taxpayer support on them,” he said. By Mr. Bradford’s count, of 28 reactors that the Nuclear Regulatory Commission now lists as planned, half have had major delays, large increases in estimated cost or have been canceled. If new plants built with government guarantees prove to be a commercial success, the program costs taxpayers nothing; if they prove too expensive to finish or are completed but cannot earn enough to repay the loans, the taxpayer is on the hook. Complicating the challenge, the forthcoming loan guarantees amount to only $18.5 billion, and the nuclear industry says it needs tens of billions more. President Obama’s energy secretary, Steven Chu, acknowledged that the sum was small. He said it could finance at most perhaps one plant for each new reactor design, making it hard to determine which design was most practical. “If I were a power company, maybe one of each would not be helpful,” he said. He suggested that the nuclear industry would need to build two or three of each. But Dr. Chu insists that nuclear power will be an important piece of any climate solution. “We have a dormant nuclear industry,” he said. “We have to start it up in a way that gives the people who are going to make investments the confidence that this is economically viable.” Mindful of the challenges posed by global warming, some environmentalists are cautiously evaluating their positions on nuclear power. “There is an increasing number of people who have spent their lives as environmental advocates who believe that carbon is such an urgent problem that they have to rethink their skepticism about nuclear power,” said Jonathan Lash, the president of the World Resources Institute, who puts himself in that category. “But there are many people who are passionate environmentalists who are also passionate opponents of nuclear power, and remain so,” he said. Among the foes is Karen Hadden, executive director of the Sustainable Energy and Economic Development Coalition in Austin, Tex., which is fighting a nuclear project there that is in line for a loan guarantee. While she strongly favors carbon limits, she said, she opposes construction of reactors. She warned that money for solar, wind and geothermal projects could get siphoned off “in these multibillion-dollar projects that may or may not ever get built.” Daniel L. Roderick, senior vice president for nuclear plant projects at GE-Hitachi Nuclear Energy, a partnership between General Electric and Hitachi of Japan, said that a year and a half ago, there were expectations that more than 20 units would be under construction by now in the United States. “That number is currently zero,” he said. Nonetheless, G.E. and other companies have invested tens of millions of dollars in plans for reactors they hope to build around the world, including dozens in the United States. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on December 24, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.WASHINGTON  When experts on power grid reliability asked themselves recently how a cleaner energy future would look, seven of eight regional councils imagined how their systems would work with 10 percent wind power. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Babcock &amp; Wilcox Company Some environmentalists now see nuclear power as part of an effort to combat climate change. Multimedia Graphic Growth and Skepticism in Nuclear Power A blog about energy, the environment and the bottom line. Go to Blog » Only one, representing the southeastern United States, chose a radically different option: doubling nuclear power capacity. Thirty years after the American nuclear industry abandoned scores of half-built plants because of soaring costs and operating problems like the Three Mile Island accident, skepticism persists over whether the technology is worth investing in. Yet the pendulum may be swinging back. The 104 plants now running have sharply raised their output, emboldening utilities across the country to make a case for building new ones. And the industry is about to get a big boost. In the next few days, the Energy Department plans to announce the first of $18.5 billion in loan guarantees for building new reactors. The guarantees were authorized in a bill passed by Congress in 2005. It has taken four years for the department to set up a system to evaluate applications and determine how much the borrowers will be charged for the guarantees to compensate the government for taking the risk. Industry experts think the first guarantee will go to the Southern Company to build two units at its Vogtle nuclear plant near Augusta, Ga. The money will flow amid a national credit squeeze and intense jockeying among the nation’s wind, solar, geothermal and nuclear sectors. Each is trying to cast itself as an ideal “clean” energy option as the nation moves toward reining in the carbon dioxide emissions linked to global warming. All of these sources could potentially benefit under a cap-and-trade system that is being considered in Congress as part of climate change legislation. Such a system would set a ceiling on carbon dioxide emissions and allow trading of pollution permits, handicapping the carbon-intensive coal and natural gas sectors. Historically Republicans have been more enthusiastic than Democrats about nuclear power. So as the climate bill winds its way through the Senate, some Democratic members are seeking to add to the $18.5 billion in loan guarantees for the nuclear industry to attract Republicans and some industrial-state Democrats. (The House version passed in June, 219 to 212.) Some of the foremost Congressional climate change campaigners are unenthusiastic. Representative Edward Markey, a Massachusetts Democrat who has hounded the nuclear industry for decades over safety questions and who is a sponsor of the House bill, does not favor direct aid to the nuclear industry. He argues that a cap-and-trade system would give the nuclear sector the only boost it deserves. If that system goes into effect, he said, nuclear power “will be able to compete more effectively in a new marketplace. How effectively they can compete is going to be the question.” Others see combining a cap-and-trade system with a nuclear aid package as a sensible tactic to get Congress to address environmental problems. “One can argue it certainly is bringing about an unusual marriage of interests here,” said Philip R. Sharp, an Indiana Democrat who served in the House of Representatives from 1975 to 1995 and led a House committee with jurisdiction over the electric system. “It is one of the potential paths for actually getting real action and real legislation,” said Mr. Sharp, who now heads the nonpartisan group Resources for the Future. Economic issues have helped scramble alliances on the state and local level, too. Because new reactors create so many jobs and big tax revenue, the Democratic governors of Maryland and Ohio are working hard to get them built in their states. State legislatures from Louisiana to South Dakota and local governments from Port Gibson, Miss., to Oswego, N.Y., are also on record favoring new reactors. Peter A. Bradford, a former member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission who is now vice chairman of the Union of Concerned Scientists, questions the wisdom of direct aid to the industry. Unlike cap and trade, in which industries buy and sell the right to release carbon dioxide in a market-oriented system, he said, the loan guarantees finance projects that the private sector deems too risky. The government would be “picking some winners and bestowing a lot of taxpayer support on them,” he said. By Mr. Bradford’s count, of 28 reactors that the Nuclear Regulatory Commission now lists as planned, half have had major delays, large increases in estimated cost or have been canceled. If new plants built with government guarantees prove to be a commercial success, the program costs taxpayers nothing; if they prove too expensive to finish or are completed but cannot earn enough to repay the loans, the taxpayer is on the hook. Complicating the challenge, the forthcoming loan guarantees amount to only $18.5 billion, and the nuclear industry says it needs tens of billions more. President Obama’s energy secretary, Steven Chu, acknowledged that the sum was small. He said it could finance at most perhaps one plant for each new reactor design, making it hard to determine which design was most practical. “If I were a power company, maybe one of each would not be helpful,” he said. He suggested that the nuclear industry would need to build two or three of each. But Dr. Chu insists that nuclear power will be an important piece of any climate solution. “We have a dormant nuclear industry,” he said. “We have to start it up in a way that gives the people who are going to make investments the confidence that this is economically viable.” Mindful of the challenges posed by global warming, some environmentalists are cautiously evaluating their positions on nuclear power. “There is an increasing number of people who have spent their lives as environmental advocates who believe that carbon is such an urgent problem that they have to rethink their skepticism about nuclear power,” said Jonathan Lash, the president of the World Resources Institute, who puts himself in that category. “But there are many people who are passionate environmentalists who are also passionate opponents of nuclear power, and remain so,” he said. Among the foes is Karen Hadden, executive director of the Sustainable Energy and Economic Development Coalition in Austin, Tex., which is fighting a nuclear project there that is in line for a loan guarantee. While she strongly favors carbon limits, she said, she opposes construction of reactors. She warned that money for solar, wind and geothermal projects could get siphoned off “in these multibillion-dollar projects that may or may not ever get built.” Daniel L. Roderick, senior vice president for nuclear plant projects at GE-Hitachi Nuclear Energy, a partnership between General Electric and Hitachi of Japan, said that a year and a half ago, there were expectations that more than 20 units would be under construction by now in the United States. “That number is currently zero,” he said. Nonetheless, G.E. and other companies have invested tens of millions of dollars in plans for reactors they hope to build around the world, including dozens in the United States.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/22/science/earth/22carbon.html?ref=southerncompany">States Can Sue Utilities Over Emissions<date>Published: September 21, 2009</date><text>A two-judge panel of a federal appeals court has ruled that big power companies can be sued by states and land trusts for emitting carbon dioxide. The decision, issued Monday, overturns a 2005 District Court decision that the question was political, not judicial. Skip to next paragraph Related Refitted to Bury Emissions, Plant Draws Attention (September 22, 2009) A panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in New York, ruled that eight states  California, Connecticut, Iowa, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Wisconsin  as well as New York City and three land trusts could proceed with a suit against American Electric Power, Southern Corporation, the Tennessee Valley Authority, Xcel Energy and Cinergy Corporation, all large coal-burning utilities. The case, brought in 2004, said the defendants were creating a “public nuisance” and sought reductions in emissions that scientists say are changing the climate. The states cited studies from the United Nations and the National Academy of Sciences that predicted damage and said in fact that their environments had already been damaged. The land trusts said that an increase in sea level would inundate their properties, among other problems. The power companies said that the federal courts had never recognized an argument in common law that greenhouse gas emissions contribute to global warming, and that if action were to be taken, Congress would have to do it. The lower court agreed that the issues demonstrated the “transcendently legislative nature of this litigation,” and that if they found in favor of the states and the land trusts, the courts would have to figure out how to cap emissions, set reduction goals and a schedule for achieving them, and take other steps that would seem to require legislation. The appeal was heard by a three-judge panel, but one of the judges, Sonia Sotomayor, was elevated to the Supreme Court in August. The case was decided by Joseph M. McLaughlin, who was appointed to the court in 1990 by the first President George Bush, and Peter W. Hall, nominated in 2003 by the second President Bush. Matt Pawa, the lead lawyer for the Open Space Institute and the Audubon Society of New Hampshire, both plaintiffs, said in a statement that “for hundreds of years, courts have been there to protect citizens from harm,” and could do so again now. At the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group that was not a plaintiff, David Doniger, a senior lawyer, said the best way to fight global warming was to have Congress act. But he added, “The court’s decision guarantees that if the Congress fails to do its job, or blocks the E.P.A. from doing its job, the biggest power companies will still be held accountable in the federal courts.” At American Electric Power, Pat D. Hemlepp, a spokesman, said the company’s lawyers had not decided whether to appeal. But he added: “We don’t feel that litigation is a proper avenue to address climate concerns. In our view, it’s a policy issue.” “Legislation would be the best approach, and that’s happening now,” Mr. Hemlepp said, referring to a bill that has passed the House and that the Senate may take up this year. Many participants in the global warming debate appear to prefer a decision by the Congress, because it could balance competing interests, between and among regions and industries, to cut emissions of global warming gases. But Monday’s decision means that all three branches of the federal government could have a role. In addition to the possibility that Congress will act, the Supreme Court held in April 2007, that global warming gases were a pollutant under the Clean Air Act, and thus could be regulated by the Environmental Protection Agency. More Articles in Science » A version of this article appeared in print on September 22, 2009, on page A18 of the New York edition.A two-judge panel of a federal appeals court has ruled that big power companies can be sued by states and land trusts for emitting carbon dioxide. The decision, issued Monday, overturns a 2005 District Court decision that the question was political, not judicial. Skip to next paragraph Related Refitted to Bury Emissions, Plant Draws Attention (September 22, 2009) A panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, in New York, ruled that eight states  California, Connecticut, Iowa, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Vermont and Wisconsin  as well as New York City and three land trusts could proceed with a suit against American Electric Power, Southern Corporation, the Tennessee Valley Authority, Xcel Energy and Cinergy Corporation, all large coal-burning utilities. The case, brought in 2004, said the defendants were creating a “public nuisance” and sought reductions in emissions that scientists say are changing the climate. The states cited studies from the United Nations and the National Academy of Sciences that predicted damage and said in fact that their environments had already been damaged. The land trusts said that an increase in sea level would inundate their properties, among other problems. The power companies said that the federal courts had never recognized an argument in common law that greenhouse gas emissions contribute to global warming, and that if action were to be taken, Congress would have to do it. The lower court agreed that the issues demonstrated the “transcendently legislative nature of this litigation,” and that if they found in favor of the states and the land trusts, the courts would have to figure out how to cap emissions, set reduction goals and a schedule for achieving them, and take other steps that would seem to require legislation. The appeal was heard by a three-judge panel, but one of the judges, Sonia Sotomayor, was elevated to the Supreme Court in August. The case was decided by Joseph M. McLaughlin, who was appointed to the court in 1990 by the first President George Bush, and Peter W. Hall, nominated in 2003 by the second President Bush. Matt Pawa, the lead lawyer for the Open Space Institute and the Audubon Society of New Hampshire, both plaintiffs, said in a statement that “for hundreds of years, courts have been there to protect citizens from harm,” and could do so again now. At the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group that was not a plaintiff, David Doniger, a senior lawyer, said the best way to fight global warming was to have Congress act. But he added, “The court’s decision guarantees that if the Congress fails to do its job, or blocks the E.P.A. from doing its job, the biggest power companies will still be held accountable in the federal courts.” At American Electric Power, Pat D. Hemlepp, a spokesman, said the company’s lawyers had not decided whether to appeal. But he added: “We don’t feel that litigation is a proper avenue to address climate concerns. In our view, it’s a policy issue.” “Legislation would be the best approach, and that’s happening now,” Mr. Hemlepp said, referring to a bill that has passed the House and that the Senate may take up this year. Many participants in the global warming debate appear to prefer a decision by the Congress, because it could balance competing interests, between and among regions and industries, to cut emissions of global warming gases. But Monday’s decision means that all three branches of the federal government could have a role. In addition to the possibility that Congress will act, the Supreme Court held in April 2007, that global warming gases were a pollutant under the Clean Air Act, and thus could be regulated by the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/27/us/27alaska.html?ref=southerncompany">Flooded Village Files Suit, Citing Corporate Link to Climate Change<date>Correction: February 28, 2008Published: February 27, 2008</date><text>Correction Appended SAN FRANCISCO  Lawyers for the Alaska Native coastal village of Kivalina, which is being forced to relocate because of flooding caused by the changing Arctic climate, filed suit in federal court here Tuesday arguing that 5 oil companies, 14 electric utilities and the country’s largest coal company were responsible for the village’s woes. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Global Warming The New York Times Flooding is forcing Kivalina, Alaska, to relocate. The suit is the latest effort to hold companies like BP America, Chevron, Peabody Energy, Duke Energy and the Southern Company responsible for the impact of global warming because they emit millions of tons of greenhouse gases, or, in the case of Peabody, mine and market carbon-laden coal that is burned by others. It accused the companies of creating a public nuisance. In an unusual move, those five companies and three other defendants  the Exxon Mobil Corporation, American Electric Power and the Conoco Phillips Company  are also accused of conspiracy. “There has been a long campaign by power, coal and oil companies to mislead the public about the science of global warming,” the suit says. The campaign, it says, contributed “to the public nuisance of global warming by convincing the public at large and the victims of global warming that the process is not man-made when in fact it is.” Kivalina, an Inupiat village of 400 people on a barrier reef between the Chukchi Sea and two rivers, is being buffeted by waves that, in colder times, were blocked by sea ice, the suit says. “The result of the increased storm damage is a massive erosion problem,” it says. “Houses and buildings are in imminent danger of falling into the sea.” The estimated cost of relocating the village is up to $400 million, the suit says. Some lawyers in the case participated in the long-running litigation against American tobacco companies in the 1990s, and some of the same legal theories echo through the complaint. But the hurdles may be greater than those in the tobacco wars. Global warming is a diffuse worldwide phenomenon; a successful public nuisance case requires that defendants’ behavior be directly linked to the harm. “Public nuisance law has been used from time immemorial to address issues that have not been addressed by the political branches,” said Kirsten H. Engel, a law professor at the University of Arizona. But Professor Engel added, “It’s very difficult to get a court to jump in here and say that what these companies are doing, and have been doing for years, is unreasonable and creating a public nuisance.” Two similar lawsuits, one brought by California against six automakers and another by a coalition of Eastern states against utility companies, have been dismissed by federal judges. Both judges said the issues involved were political and did not belong in the courts. Those decisions have been appealed. Matt Pawa, a lawyer for Kivalina, said this case was different because it sought monetary damages for an injured party. “The kind of harms to property and public welfare caused by global warming are classic public nuisance injuries,” Mr. Pawa said. He added that the other cases had no conspiracy claims, which he said courts routinely addressed. Reached late Tuesday, spokesmen for three defendants  Jason Cuevas of Southern, Vic Svec of Peabody and Gantt Walton of Exxon Mobil  said they would not comment on the substance of the lawsuit. But Mr. Svec said, “Rather than unreasonably suing companies for the weather, we would encourage everyone to join Peabody in supporting aggressive development of carbon capture and storage projects and other technologies that help us provide both energy security and carbon solutions.” Of the accusation that Exxon Mobil participated in a disinformation campaign, Mr. Walton said, “The recycling of this type of discredited conspiracy theory only diverts attention from the real challenge at hand  how to provide the energy to improve living standards while also reducing greenhouse gas emissions.” This article has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: February 28, 2008 Because of an editing error, an article on Wednesday about a lawsuit filed against energy companies by an Alaska Native coastal village that is being forced to relocate because of flooding caused by the changing Arctic climate misstated the estimated cost of moving the village. It could cost up to $400 million, not up to $400,000. More Articles in US »Correction Appended SAN FRANCISCO  Lawyers for the Alaska Native coastal village of Kivalina, which is being forced to relocate because of flooding caused by the changing Arctic climate, filed suit in federal court here Tuesday arguing that 5 oil companies, 14 electric utilities and the country’s largest coal company were responsible for the village’s woes. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Global Warming The New York Times Flooding is forcing Kivalina, Alaska, to relocate. The suit is the latest effort to hold companies like BP America, Chevron, Peabody Energy, Duke Energy and the Southern Company responsible for the impact of global warming because they emit millions of tons of greenhouse gases, or, in the case of Peabody, mine and market carbon-laden coal that is burned by others. It accused the companies of creating a public nuisance. In an unusual move, those five companies and three other defendants  the Exxon Mobil Corporation, American Electric Power and the Conoco Phillips Company  are also accused of conspiracy. “There has been a long campaign by power, coal and oil companies to mislead the public about the science of global warming,” the suit says. The campaign, it says, contributed “to the public nuisance of global warming by convincing the public at large and the victims of global warming that the process is not man-made when in fact it is.” Kivalina, an Inupiat village of 400 people on a barrier reef between the Chukchi Sea and two rivers, is being buffeted by waves that, in colder times, were blocked by sea ice, the suit says. “The result of the increased storm damage is a massive erosion problem,” it says. “Houses and buildings are in imminent danger of falling into the sea.” The estimated cost of relocating the village is up to $400 million, the suit says. Some lawyers in the case participated in the long-running litigation against American tobacco companies in the 1990s, and some of the same legal theories echo through the complaint. But the hurdles may be greater than those in the tobacco wars. Global warming is a diffuse worldwide phenomenon; a successful public nuisance case requires that defendants’ behavior be directly linked to the harm. “Public nuisance law has been used from time immemorial to address issues that have not been addressed by the political branches,” said Kirsten H. Engel, a law professor at the University of Arizona. But Professor Engel added, “It’s very difficult to get a court to jump in here and say that what these companies are doing, and have been doing for years, is unreasonable and creating a public nuisance.” Two similar lawsuits, one brought by California against six automakers and another by a coalition of Eastern states against utility companies, have been dismissed by federal judges. Both judges said the issues involved were political and did not belong in the courts. Those decisions have been appealed. Matt Pawa, a lawyer for Kivalina, said this case was different because it sought monetary damages for an injured party. “The kind of harms to property and public welfare caused by global warming are classic public nuisance injuries,” Mr. Pawa said. He added that the other cases had no conspiracy claims, which he said courts routinely addressed. Reached late Tuesday, spokesmen for three defendants  Jason Cuevas of Southern, Vic Svec of Peabody and Gantt Walton of Exxon Mobil  said they would not comment on the substance of the lawsuit. But Mr. Svec said, “Rather than unreasonably suing companies for the weather, we would encourage everyone to join Peabody in supporting aggressive development of carbon capture and storage projects and other technologies that help us provide both energy security and carbon solutions.” Of the accusation that Exxon Mobil participated in a disinformation campaign, Mr. Walton said, “The recycling of this type of discredited conspiracy theory only diverts attention from the real challenge at hand  how to provide the energy to improve living standards while also reducing greenhouse gas emissions.” This article has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: February 28, 2008 Because of an editing error, an article on Wednesday about a lawsuit filed against energy companies by an Alaska Native coastal village that is being forced to relocate because of flooding caused by the changing Arctic climate misstated the estimated cost of moving the village. It could cost up to $400 million, not up to $400,000.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/04/us/04nuke.html?ref=southerncompany">Nuclear Drill Performance Raises Issues on Safety<date>Published: April 4, 2007</date><text>WASHINGTON, April 3  As a simulated nuclear accident unfolded at a Georgia power plant, the drill called for a pump shaft to break and to dump metal parts into the reactor coolant system. Radiation in the containment building levels was to rise and the water level was to start dropping so fast that the regular pumps could not keep up. The emergency director concluded that there might have been a pipe break, and declared a site-area emergency, the second-highest classification of accident. But the script for the drill, held March 22, 2006, at the Vogtle Nuclear Plant near Augusta, did not include a pipe break, and the staff of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission graded the performance of the plant’s owner, the Southern Company, poor. It said afterward that the emergency director had overdiagnosed the problem. Further, the commission said, the company had failed to spot the mistake and had therefore failed to identify its own weakness. Now, the company has made an unusual appeal to top commission officials to revise its grade on the drill. Southern argued that it was not reasonable for the commission staff, which had read the script in advance, to second-guess the emergency director, for whom the script was a secret and whose job was to develop an accurate picture of an unfolding “accident” based on fragmentary bits of information. The company contends that penalizing it for making a tough call within the short time allotted will have a chilling effect on the rest of the industry and lead to reactor operators’ being too slow in giving public safety officials their assessments of what is happening. “In accordance with our plans and our procedures,” the emergency director “had no choice but to declare a site-area emergency,” said Jeffrey T. Gasser, the executive vice president and chief nuclear officer of the Southern Nuclear Operating Company, which operates the Vogtle plant. The commission’s finding, Mr. Gasser said, would make the emergency manager in a real accident “take longer to evaluate conditions, before making a classification.” And that, he said, could delay putting an emergency plan into effect. But the commission said the emergency director and the control room crew should have responded to the indications in their simulator control room “in a methodical manner, assessing the event and utilizing the diagnostics in such a manner to ensure that ‘undue haste’ did not result in misdiagnosis, misoperation, or undesired plant conditions.” The indications that the emergency director used to diagnose a possible water leak were ambiguous. The water level in a reactor can fall for a variety of reasons; one is that when a reactor shuts down, its water cools and, like a piece of metal, shrinks. The radiation level in the containment building was up, according to the simulation, but that did not prove there was a leak, Mr. Gasser said, because the elevated readings came from water that was still inside the reactor. The water had higher readings because the fuel had been damaged by the loose metal parts, in the simulation. The reactor has a water sensor, but it is nine inches off the floor. David Lochbaum, a nuclear engineer at the Union of Concerned Scientists, a group that is often critical of nuclear safety regulation, said that a leak of 150 gallons per minute would take 90 minutes for the sensor to detect. But the emergency director is supposed to categorize the event in the first 15 minutes. Mr. Lochbaum said this raised the question of whether the sensor was in the right place, or should be nearer the floor. Mr. Gasser said that if the sensor was too near the floor, debris that might be present during an accident could affect its operation. The commission pays close attention to how the industry and the public react to nuclear events. Last November, a Tennessee school district sent children home after an instrument at the Watts Bar Nuclear Plant indicated (falsely, as it turned out) there might be a leak. Commission officials said the reaction was unwarranted. For Southern, the impact of the poor rating could be enhanced scrutiny by regulators, which could in turn make Southern’s stock price fall or make it harder for the company to raise money. More Articles in National »WASHINGTON, April 3  As a simulated nuclear accident unfolded at a Georgia power plant, the drill called for a pump shaft to break and to dump metal parts into the reactor coolant system. Radiation in the containment building levels was to rise and the water level was to start dropping so fast that the regular pumps could not keep up. The emergency director concluded that there might have been a pipe break, and declared a site-area emergency, the second-highest classification of accident. But the script for the drill, held March 22, 2006, at the Vogtle Nuclear Plant near Augusta, did not include a pipe break, and the staff of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission graded the performance of the plant’s owner, the Southern Company, poor. It said afterward that the emergency director had overdiagnosed the problem. Further, the commission said, the company had failed to spot the mistake and had therefore failed to identify its own weakness. Now, the company has made an unusual appeal to top commission officials to revise its grade on the drill. Southern argued that it was not reasonable for the commission staff, which had read the script in advance, to second-guess the emergency director, for whom the script was a secret and whose job was to develop an accurate picture of an unfolding “accident” based on fragmentary bits of information. The company contends that penalizing it for making a tough call within the short time allotted will have a chilling effect on the rest of the industry and lead to reactor operators’ being too slow in giving public safety officials their assessments of what is happening. “In accordance with our plans and our procedures,” the emergency director “had no choice but to declare a site-area emergency,” said Jeffrey T. Gasser, the executive vice president and chief nuclear officer of the Southern Nuclear Operating Company, which operates the Vogtle plant. The commission’s finding, Mr. Gasser said, would make the emergency manager in a real accident “take longer to evaluate conditions, before making a classification.” And that, he said, could delay putting an emergency plan into effect. But the commission said the emergency director and the control room crew should have responded to the indications in their simulator control room “in a methodical manner, assessing the event and utilizing the diagnostics in such a manner to ensure that ‘undue haste’ did not result in misdiagnosis, misoperation, or undesired plant conditions.” The indications that the emergency director used to diagnose a possible water leak were ambiguous. The water level in a reactor can fall for a variety of reasons; one is that when a reactor shuts down, its water cools and, like a piece of metal, shrinks. The radiation level in the containment building was up, according to the simulation, but that did not prove there was a leak, Mr. Gasser said, because the elevated readings came from water that was still inside the reactor. The water had higher readings because the fuel had been damaged by the loose metal parts, in the simulation. The reactor has a water sensor, but it is nine inches off the floor. David Lochbaum, a nuclear engineer at the Union of Concerned Scientists, a group that is often critical of nuclear safety regulation, said that a leak of 150 gallons per minute would take 90 minutes for the sensor to detect. But the emergency director is supposed to categorize the event in the first 15 minutes. Mr. Lochbaum said this raised the question of whether the sensor was in the right place, or should be nearer the floor. Mr. Gasser said that if the sensor was too near the floor, debris that might be present during an accident could affect its operation. The commission pays close attention to how the industry and the public react to nuclear events. Last November, a Tennessee school district sent children home after an instrument at the Watts Bar Nuclear Plant indicated (falsely, as it turned out) there might be a leak. Commission officials said the reaction was unwarranted. For Southern, the impact of the poor rating could be enhanced scrutiny by regulators, which could in turn make Southern’s stock price fall or make it harder for the company to raise money.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/16/magazine/16nuclear.html?ref=southerncompany">Atomic Balm?<date>Published: July 16, 2006</date><text>A Nuclear Renaissance? Skip to next paragraph Mitch Epstein for The New York Times The cooling towers at the Vogtle nuclear power plant, near Waynesboro, Ga. More Photos » Times Topics Atomic Energy » Multimedia Slide Show: Atomic Balm orkers at the Alvin W. Vogtle nuclear-power generating station sometimes describe it as being in the middle of nowhere, and in many respects theyre right: situated on a bend in the Savannah River, in the thick pine forests of central Georgia, the plant is an hour south of Augusta and a two-hour drive, if you disobey the speed limit, from the outskirts of Atlanta. On the final approach to Vogtle, a narrow country road cuts through vast stretches of undeveloped land punctuated with small ranch-style homes; in some places, you can still discern remnants of convenience stores and cheap motels set back from the pavement, all now shuttered, some barely standing. When Vogtle (pronounced VOH-gull) was being built in the 1970s and 80s, it was more aptly described as the middle of everything, a bustling, improvised city of engineers and tradesmen, some 14,000 workers in all, many of whom lived nearby in tents and trailers. It was one of the largest construction projects in the history of Georgia. An entire concrete factory, now defunct, was built here during that time; so was a factory to manufacture ice, a necessary ingredient in making the superdense nuclear-grade concrete required for the reactor-containment buildings. To Ellie Daniel, a local man who has worked as an administrator at Vogtle for more than two decades, only two significant things have happened in the history of Georgias Burke County. One is the Civil War, he told me. The other is Plant Vogtle. The boom that swept through the region as Vogtle rose from the forest floor  its immense cooling towers are each 548 feet tall  ended somewhat badly, however, at least in a financial sense. The plant took almost 15 years to move from blueprints to being operational. And by the time it began producing electricity in the late 1980s, its total cost, $8.87 billion, was so far overbudget that Vogtle became yet another notorious example of the evils of nuclear energy. In the public mind, the issue was safety. For the industry, the larger concern was economics. Indeed, as originally designed in the early 1970s, Vogtle was intended to generate a total of around 4,500 megawatts of electricity, enough power to serve the needs of several million homes. The grand plan was to have four reactors. Instead, it was scaled back to two, Vogtle Unit 1 (finished in 1987) and Vogtle Unit 2 (1989). Today these reactors together produce about 2,400 megawatts, satisfying about 15 percent of the states power needs. One day this May, on a brisk morning so clear that I could see its cooling towers from 20 miles away, I visited Vogtle on one leg of a tour to assess what many in the energy industry are calling a nuclear renaissance. Thanks partly to large government incentives and to market forces that have pushed the price of other electric plant fuels (especially natural gas) to historic heights, the prospect of starting a new nuclear reactor in this country for the first time in 30 years has become increasingly likely. By early summer a dozen utilities around the country had informed the U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission, which oversees all civilian nuclear activity in this country, that they were interested in building 18 new facilities, nearly all of which would be sited next to existing nuclear reactors. Vogtle was in this group of 18. In fact, the Southern Company, the large utility that runs Vogtle, also announced that it would formally apply to the N.R.C. next month for an early site permit, the first step in readying the community for a nuclear project that would complement the existing reactors. Whether Vogtle will turn out to be the 1st, 5th or 10th next-generation plant to break new ground is difficult to say; trying to predict which utility will be able to overcome formidable obstacles  public approval, regulatory scrutiny, billions in financing and complex engineering challenges  is akin to predicting the winner of a presidential election years in advance. Still, if things move smoothly (a rarity when it comes to nuclear power in this country), the Southern Company will receive a license to build and operate a new plant in 2010. Construction will take five years. Electricity will begin to flow to the residents of Georgia in 2015. Over the past year, the debate over nuclear power has increasingly been framed as an environmental one, as several commentators  most notably Patrick Moore, a founder of Greenpeace (and now estranged from the organization); the British conservationist James Lovelock; and the Whole Earth Catalog founder Stewart Brand  have stepped forward to assert that global warming requires an embrace of new nuclear plants, because unlike gas- or coal-powered plants, nuclear reactors produce electricity without emitting greenhouse gasses. The nuclear industry, in turn, has capitalized on the chance to adopt a green tinge, or at least greenish one; among its recent slogans is the exhortation to Go nuclear: because you care about the air. Most environmental groups have not softened their opposition, however. This is more a propaganda exercise than a serious discussion of the viability of the industry, Jim Riccio, the nuclear policy analyst at Greenpeace, told me. By using global warming, he added, the nuclear industry is trying to find some fear greater than the nuclear fear to be their selling point. Nonetheless, whether any new nuclear plants are built in the United States depends less on the sentiments of the American public than on the countrys individual utilities. And for conglomerates like the Southern Company, which runs Vogtle as well as two other nuclear plants in Georgia and Alabama, the determining factor is not air quality. Its money. Over the next 12 to 24 months, as utilities like Southern determine what to do, their fundamental concern is the bottom-line cost. And the feeling among many in the industry is that the financial prospects are almost certainly looking up. One afternoon at Vogtle, Ellie Daniel took me just west of the plant. The reactors here sit amid 3,150 acres of wilderness; the snap of pine in the air and the low hills that roll toward the riverbank lend it the serenity of a fine vacation spot. We drove past the old concrete factory, past the crumbling foundation of the ice works and halted by a clearing at the side of the road. At the edge of the clearing, small pine trees had been planted in neat lines, stretching like vineyard rows up the hill to Vogtle Units 1 and 2. The ground beneath our feet was covered in a carpet of fallen needles. Its all part of the effort to preserve the area as a pristine environment, Daniel explained to me: Were trying to return the area to how it looked before we built here. Much of this will be swept away, though, if plans progress the way the Southern Company hopes. In the clearing, some engineers at Vogtle had painted a green circle, about 60 feet in diameter, to mark the location and size of the planned reactor building. And in the center of the circle was a pole, also painted green, to mark the hot reactor core. This would be Vogtle Unit 3, Daniel said. Not far off, perhaps a few hundred yards, was another pole and another green circle. If you can imagine it, he added, this would be Vogtle Unit 4. Hard Times After T.M.I. On the evening before my visit to Vogtle, the prospect of new reactors at the site was the subject of a public meeting, convened by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, at a technical college in Waynesboro, Ga., a small town about 30 minutes from the plant. Anyone intrigued or appalled by the idea of new construction could come to ask questions. These kinds of community gatherings have become a frequent occurrence around the country over the past year as utilities have shown a renewed interest in building reactors. Were in whats called the preapplication space for Plant Vogtle, David Matthews, the head of new-reactor licensing at the N.R.C., told me as people milled about before the evening meeting. Matthews brought a dozen colleagues with him  engineers and science advisers, mainly  to address any technical points that might arise after he made a few brief remarks explaining the N.R.C. licensing process. But some attendees had come not so much to ask questions as to encourage the Southern Company to build Units 3 and 4. Can you do it any quicker? asked one representative from the local chamber of commerce. Meanwhile, a number of antinuclear advocates wanted to quiz the commission officials about the possible hazards of a new plant design and the plants radioactive (and highly toxic) spent fuel; some had even set up tables to distribute brochures alongside the agencys own informational pamphlets. The rancorous debates that defined these sorts of public meetings two decades ago were largely absent: the exchanges followed a protocol that kept tempers in check while lending the meeting a formality that N.R.C. representatives, all dressed in formal business attire, tried to promote. Vogtle Units 3 and 4 were serious business. The received wisdom about the United States nuclear industry is that it began a long and inexorable decline immediately after the near meltdown, in 1979, at Three Mile Island in central Pennsylvania, an accident that  in one of those rare alignments of Hollywood fantasy and real-world events  was preceded by the release of the film The China Syndrome two weeks earlier. To be sure, the events at T.M.I., as those in the industry invariably refer to it, as well as the radioactive steam explosion at Chernobyl seven years later, galvanized public opinion against nuclear power as never before. In the case of Long Islands Shoreham plant, steadfast community opposition eventually stopped a newly finished plant from ever operating. But the fortunes of the nuclear business have been defined by many factors that arent so conspicuous. Several years before T.M.I., the growing expense of new nuclear projects, coupled with the realization that many predictions for future electricity demand were overblown, had already hobbled the business. New orders for plants had fallen off drastically by 1978. The industry was in a depressed state, says J. Samuel Walker, the historian at the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. And what T.M.I. did was finish things off. In fact, T.M.I. didnt kill the industry. It killed the growth of the industry  ensuring, in a way, that nuclear power would not assume more than a fraction of the U.S. electric business. The last year a plant was approved for construction by the N.R.C. was 1978. But interminable construction schedules meant that many facilities approved before T.M.I., like Plant Vogtle in Georgia, were finished long after the accident. Some didnt even start generating power until a few years ago; the last was the Watts Bar plant in eastern Tennessee, which began operations in 1996. Since then the contribution of nuclear energy to our electrical grid has remained fairly steady. All told, the 103 active nuclear reactors in the United States supply about 20 percent of our electricity. And in some places the contribution is much larger. New York gets 29 percent of its power from nuclear energy, New Jersey 52 percent. Abroad, nuclear energy has its hot spots too  in France, for instance, 78 percent of the electricity comes from nuclear energy. There are currently 337 working reactors in 30 countries outside the United States, and there may soon be many more, as India and China embark upon ambitious plans to build dozens over the next decade to satisfy their thirst for electricity. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8Next Page » Jon Gertner, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about student-loan forgiveness. More Articles in Magazine »A Nuclear Renaissance? Skip to next paragraph Mitch Epstein for The New York Times The cooling towers at the Vogtle nuclear power plant, near Waynesboro, Ga. More Photos » Times Topics Atomic Energy » Multimedia Slide Show: Atomic Balm orkers at the Alvin W. Vogtle nuclear-power generating station sometimes describe it as being in the middle of nowhere, and in many respects theyre right: situated on a bend in the Savannah River, in the thick pine forests of central Georgia, the plant is an hour south of Augusta and a two-hour drive, if you disobey the speed limit, from the outskirts of Atlanta. On the final approach to Vogtle, a narrow country road cuts through vast stretches of undeveloped land punctuated with small ranch-style homes; in some places, you can still discern remnants of convenience stores and cheap motels set back from the pavement, all now shuttered, some barely standing. When Vogtle (pronounced VOH-gull) was being built in the 1970s and 80s, it was more aptly described as the middle of everything, a bustling, improvised city of engineers and tradesmen, some 14,000 workers in all, many of whom lived nearby in tents and trailers. It was one of the largest construction projects in the history of Georgia. An entire concrete factory, now defunct, was built here during that time; so was a factory to manufacture ice, a necessary ingredient in making the superdense nuclear-grade concrete required for the reactor-containment buildings. To Ellie Daniel, a local man who has worked as an administrator at Vogtle for more than two decades, only two significant things have happened in the history of Georgias Burke County. One is the Civil War, he told me. The other is Plant Vogtle. The boom that swept through the region as Vogtle rose from the forest floor  its immense cooling towers are each 548 feet tall  ended somewhat badly, however, at least in a financial sense. The plant took almost 15 years to move from blueprints to being operational. And by the time it began producing electricity in the late 1980s, its total cost, $8.87 billion, was so far overbudget that Vogtle became yet another notorious example of the evils of nuclear energy. In the public mind, the issue was safety. For the industry, the larger concern was economics. Indeed, as originally designed in the early 1970s, Vogtle was intended to generate a total of around 4,500 megawatts of electricity, enough power to serve the needs of several million homes. The grand plan was to have four reactors. Instead, it was scaled back to two, Vogtle Unit 1 (finished in 1987) and Vogtle Unit 2 (1989). Today these reactors together produce about 2,400 megawatts, satisfying about 15 percent of the states power needs. One day this May, on a brisk morning so clear that I could see its cooling towers from 20 miles away, I visited Vogtle on one leg of a tour to assess what many in the energy industry are calling a nuclear renaissance. Thanks partly to large government incentives and to market forces that have pushed the price of other electric plant fuels (especially natural gas) to historic heights, the prospect of starting a new nuclear reactor in this country for the first time in 30 years has become increasingly likely. By early summer a dozen utilities around the country had informed the U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission, which oversees all civilian nuclear activity in this country, that they were interested in building 18 new facilities, nearly all of which would be sited next to existing nuclear reactors. Vogtle was in this group of 18. In fact, the Southern Company, the large utility that runs Vogtle, also announced that it would formally apply to the N.R.C. next month for an early site permit, the first step in readying the community for a nuclear project that would complement the existing reactors. Whether Vogtle will turn out to be the 1st, 5th or 10th next-generation plant to break new ground is difficult to say; trying to predict which utility will be able to overcome formidable obstacles  public approval, regulatory scrutiny, billions in financing and complex engineering challenges  is akin to predicting the winner of a presidential election years in advance. Still, if things move smoothly (a rarity when it comes to nuclear power in this country), the Southern Company will receive a license to build and operate a new plant in 2010. Construction will take five years. Electricity will begin to flow to the residents of Georgia in 2015. Over the past year, the debate over nuclear power has increasingly been framed as an environmental one, as several commentators  most notably Patrick Moore, a founder of Greenpeace (and now estranged from the organization); the British conservationist James Lovelock; and the Whole Earth Catalog founder Stewart Brand  have stepped forward to assert that global warming requires an embrace of new nuclear plants, because unlike gas- or coal-powered plants, nuclear reactors produce electricity without emitting greenhouse gasses. The nuclear industry, in turn, has capitalized on the chance to adopt a green tinge, or at least greenish one; among its recent slogans is the exhortation to Go nuclear: because you care about the air. Most environmental groups have not softened their opposition, however. This is more a propaganda exercise than a serious discussion of the viability of the industry, Jim Riccio, the nuclear policy analyst at Greenpeace, told me. By using global warming, he added, the nuclear industry is trying to find some fear greater than the nuclear fear to be their selling point. Nonetheless, whether any new nuclear plants are built in the United States depends less on the sentiments of the American public than on the countrys individual utilities. And for conglomerates like the Southern Company, which runs Vogtle as well as two other nuclear plants in Georgia and Alabama, the determining factor is not air quality. Its money. Over the next 12 to 24 months, as utilities like Southern determine what to do, their fundamental concern is the bottom-line cost. And the feeling among many in the industry is that the financial prospects are almost certainly looking up. One afternoon at Vogtle, Ellie Daniel took me just west of the plant. The reactors here sit amid 3,150 acres of wilderness; the snap of pine in the air and the low hills that roll toward the riverbank lend it the serenity of a fine vacation spot. We drove past the old concrete factory, past the crumbling foundation of the ice works and halted by a clearing at the side of the road. At the edge of the clearing, small pine trees had been planted in neat lines, stretching like vineyard rows up the hill to Vogtle Units 1 and 2. The ground beneath our feet was covered in a carpet of fallen needles. Its all part of the effort to preserve the area as a pristine environment, Daniel explained to me: Were trying to return the area to how it looked before we built here. Much of this will be swept away, though, if plans progress the way the Southern Company hopes. In the clearing, some engineers at Vogtle had painted a green circle, about 60 feet in diameter, to mark the location and size of the planned reactor building. And in the center of the circle was a pole, also painted green, to mark the hot reactor core. This would be Vogtle Unit 3, Daniel said. Not far off, perhaps a few hundred yards, was another pole and another green circle. If you can imagine it, he added, this would be Vogtle Unit 4. Hard Times After T.M.I. On the evening before my visit to Vogtle, the prospect of new reactors at the site was the subject of a public meeting, convened by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, at a technical college in Waynesboro, Ga., a small town about 30 minutes from the plant. Anyone intrigued or appalled by the idea of new construction could come to ask questions. These kinds of community gatherings have become a frequent occurrence around the country over the past year as utilities have shown a renewed interest in building reactors. Were in whats called the preapplication space for Plant Vogtle, David Matthews, the head of new-reactor licensing at the N.R.C., told me as people milled about before the evening meeting. Matthews brought a dozen colleagues with him  engineers and science advisers, mainly  to address any technical points that might arise after he made a few brief remarks explaining the N.R.C. licensing process. But some attendees had come not so much to ask questions as to encourage the Southern Company to build Units 3 and 4. Can you do it any quicker? asked one representative from the local chamber of commerce. Meanwhile, a number of antinuclear advocates wanted to quiz the commission officials about the possible hazards of a new plant design and the plants radioactive (and highly toxic) spent fuel; some had even set up tables to distribute brochures alongside the agencys own informational pamphlets. The rancorous debates that defined these sorts of public meetings two decades ago were largely absent: the exchanges followed a protocol that kept tempers in check while lending the meeting a formality that N.R.C. representatives, all dressed in formal business attire, tried to promote. Vogtle Units 3 and 4 were serious business. The received wisdom about the United States nuclear industry is that it began a long and inexorable decline immediately after the near meltdown, in 1979, at Three Mile Island in central Pennsylvania, an accident that  in one of those rare alignments of Hollywood fantasy and real-world events  was preceded by the release of the film The China Syndrome two weeks earlier. To be sure, the events at T.M.I., as those in the industry invariably refer to it, as well as the radioactive steam explosion at Chernobyl seven years later, galvanized public opinion against nuclear power as never before. In the case of Long Islands Shoreham plant, steadfast community opposition eventually stopped a newly finished plant from ever operating. But the fortunes of the nuclear business have been defined by many factors that arent so conspicuous. Several years before T.M.I., the growing expense of new nuclear projects, coupled with the realization that many predictions for future electricity demand were overblown, had already hobbled the business. New orders for plants had fallen off drastically by 1978. The industry was in a depressed state, says J. Samuel Walker, the historian at the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. And what T.M.I. did was finish things off. In fact, T.M.I. didnt kill the industry. It killed the growth of the industry  ensuring, in a way, that nuclear power would not assume more than a fraction of the U.S. electric business. The last year a plant was approved for construction by the N.R.C. was 1978. But interminable construction schedules meant that many facilities approved before T.M.I., like Plant Vogtle in Georgia, were finished long after the accident. Some didnt even start generating power until a few years ago; the last was the Watts Bar plant in eastern Tennessee, which began operations in 1996. Since then the contribution of nuclear energy to our electrical grid has remained fairly steady. All told, the 103 active nuclear reactors in the United States supply about 20 percent of our electricity. And in some places the contribution is much larger. New York gets 29 percent of its power from nuclear energy, New Jersey 52 percent. Abroad, nuclear energy has its hot spots too  in France, for instance, 78 percent of the electricity comes from nuclear energy. There are currently 337 working reactors in 30 countries outside the United States, and there may soon be many more, as India and China embark upon ambitious plans to build dozens over the next decade to satisfy their thirst for electricity. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8Next Page » Jon Gertner, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about student-loan forgiveness.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DB1731F932A3575AC0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=southerncompany">HURRICANE KATRINA: THE POWER GRID; Utility Workers Come From Afar to Help Their Brethren Start Restoring Service<date>Published: September 1, 2005</date><text>Convoys of utility trucks and reinforcement workers from as far away as Massachusetts and Ohio are arriving in the gulf states to help restore electricity to the estimated 1.6 million household and business customers still without power in the wake of Hurricane Katrina. Some, like the thousands transferred by the Southern Company, are on loan from other branches of big utility conglomerates with a presence in the storm-damaged region. Others, like the 10 two-man truck units dispatched from New York City by Consolidated Edison have been sent with the industry's tacit understanding that no company is an island on the weather-vulnerable power grid. ''You volunteer to go with the understanding that it's at least two weeks,'' Steve Daquila, the leader of the ConEd unit, said by cellphone yesterday on the way to Birmingham, Ala. The trip is Mr. Daquila's first on-the-job plunge into hurricane country -- his past repair sorties have been to clean up winter storm damage in upstate New York and New England -- but he expects most of the challenges to be familiar. The power industry has master plans honed by decades of experience with natural disasters. ''You go because you want to help other people out,'' Mr. Daquila said. The priorities, as always, are restoring service to hospitals and other vital service providers like water treatment plants. In the gulf region, attention is also focused on oil refineries and natural gas pipelines that play crucial roles in supplying energy to the rest of the nation. Telephone companies are a priority as well, because a lack of communication has been hampering rescue and repair operations of all sorts. [Page C7.] But even as the crews cleared trees from downed power lines, rebuilt transmission towers and carefully re-energized short-circuited lines, the utility companies warned that it might be weeks before the full extent of the rebuilding challenge would be known. Entergy, the region's biggest provider of electricity, said portions of New Orleans might be without power for at least two months. Some smaller nearby utilities in flooded areas were also pessimistic. ''We can't even estimate when restoration of power will begin in St. Tammany Parish,'' said Susan Broussard, a spokeswoman for Cleco, a utility serving 80,000 in St. Tammany, a southeastern Louisiana county just across Lake Pontchartrain from New Orleans. The temporary migration of technical help has become a standard feature of the utility industry's response to earthquakes and violent weather. Regional utility organizations, in this case the Southern Electric Exchange in Atlanta, serve as clearinghouses linking those willing to send help with utilities that need it. In the gulf states, thousands of linemen and other technical workers from out of state are expected to join local workers before the repairs are completed. Mississippi Power expects 2,500 workers from New York, Maryland, Kentucky and Texas. Alabama Power and Light, which like Mississippi Power, is a subsidiary of the Southern Company, has received help from Massachusetts, New York, New Jersey, Ohio and Oklahoma. Entergy, of New Orleans, has temporarily abandoned its headquarters and is managing its restoration efforts from a backup command center in Jackson, Miss., a city that has also suffered extensive damage. The command center operated on backup power until electrical service was restored early yesterday, a spokeswoman, Yolanda Pollard, said. Entergy said that 1.1 million of its 2.7 million residential and business customers were without power as of 5 a.m. yesterday. By yesterday afternoon, roughly 200,000 customers had power again. Many of Entergy's biggest industrial customers take power directly from the large transmission lines that run from Baton Rouge, La., to New Orleans. Those lines had been built to withstand 150 m.p.h. winds and were among the first restored to full service on Tuesday, according to George Bartlett, Entergy's director of transmission operations. He said that he expected most refiners and manufacturers in the corridor to be able to resume business and that some had already done so. Mr. Bartlett said that refineries owned by Exxon Mobil and Murphy Oil were the only major ones situated south of New Orleans, an area where marshy conditions had forced the company to build less storm-resistant transmission lines. Entergy has made helicopter surveys of those lines and hopes soon to complete projections about when they can be restored. The Mississippi Power unit of the Southern Company appears to have been the hardest-hit utility. Katrina damaged 70 percent of its 8,000 miles of transmission and distribution lines and blacked out all 195,000 of its customers in southeastern Mississippi, the company said. A generating station just east of Gulfport, Miss., was knocked out by flooding. ''It may take as long as four weeks to restore service in the worst-hit areas,'' said Michael L. Tyndall, a Southern Company spokesman. As of yesterday, only about 5,000 Mississippi Power customers in Meridian, an inland city, were back online. Technology for managing the power grid helped some utilities limit the damage and could speed repairs. Alabama Power, for instance, has new control systems that recognize when transmission and distribution lines have been disrupted by weather-related damage. The controls stop the system from trying to restore power automatically before the hurricane has passed. The grid in years past would repeatedly start up and shut down during storms, which sometimes damaged equipment and delayed the restoration of service. Generally, beyond the priority services and industries, repair work for other customers proceeds from the least damaged areas toward the hardest-hit regions. ''There's a massive logistical challenge involved,'' said Jim Owen, a spokesman for the Edison Electrical Institute, an industry trade group. For the workers from other states, who are generally housed in schools and armories, even details as mundane as laundry are a factor. ''You pack for a week,'' Mr. Daquila of ConEd said, and hope for the best. Photos: Gasoline prices at grim new heights in Chicago. (Photo by Charles Rex Arbogast/Associated Press); A tugboat pushing barges into place at St. Paul, Minn. (Photo by Jim Mone/Associated Press); A phone worker tying warning ribbons in Louisiana. (Photo by Matt Stamey/The Courier)(pg. C1) Chart: ''Still Without Power'' At least 1.6 million customers remain without power in the wake of Monday's hurricane. Map shows the number of customers without power as of 5 p.m. wednesday: MISS.: 506,376 TENN.: 27,000 LA.: 773,956 FLA.: 6,000* ALA.: 322,701 (Sources or Electricity providers surveyed: Entergy, Southern Co., Cleco, T.V.A., GEMC. *Panhandle region only.)(pg. C7)</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/21/politics/21delay.html?ref=southerncompany">DeLay Charity for Children Financed by Corporations<date>Published: April 21, 2005</date><text>ASHINGTON, April 20 - A children's charity established by Tom DeLay, the House majority leader, has been underwritten by several of the nation's largest companies and their executives, including companies that routinely lobby lawmakers on issues before Congress, according to a review of charity records released by the companies and other documents. Advertisement The 19-year-old charity, the DeLay Foundation for Kids, has consistently declined to identify its donors, citing their desire for privacy. But a review of corporate and charitable records shows that recent donors have included AT&amp;T, the Corrections Corporation of America, Exxon Mobil, Limited Brands and the Southern Company, as well as Bill and Melinda Gates, the Microsoft founder and his wife, and Michael Dell of Dell computers. The Gates and Dell family foundations have donated at least $350,000 to Mr. DeLay's charity since 2001. Among the largest corporate gifts was a $100,000 check given to Mr. DeLay last year by the Corrections Corporation of Nashville, which manages federal prisons. AT&amp;T and Exxon Mobil say they have each donated $50,000. Like other charities, the DeLay Foundation, which operates from a post office box near Mr. DeLay's house in Sugar Land, Tex., is not required under federal laws to release a donors' list. Nor does it have to account in detail for how it spends millions of dollars in donations on behalf of abused and neglected children. Building permits in Texas show that the charity's largest project, a $7 million 50-acre housing complex near Houston for foster children, is being built by Bob Perry, a Texas contractor and a top Republican Party donor. Mr. Perry drew attention last year after providing the seed money for Swift Boat Veterans for Truth, the conservative group that sought to undermine Senator John Kerry's Vietnam War record during his campaign for the presidency. Mr. Perry said through a spokesman that he was building the children's homes at cost. His company's involvement in the project has been reported by other news organizations, although not in detail. There is no accusation of illegality in the corporate donations to the DeLay Foundation, one of several charities that members of Congress have established in recent years for worthy causes. Mr. DeLay and his wife, Christine, have been praised for their commitment to abused children; the couple have helped raise three foster children. Spokesmen for some of the corporate donors said they were motivated to help the charity because of the housing near Houston, the Oaks at Rio Bend. Some people describe it as a possible role model for the care of foster children. "The majority leader has a long commitment to helping children," his spokesman, Dan Allen, said. "He has a strong record that proves that." Mr. Allen referred detailed questions about the charity to its director, Dana Benoit, a former campaign worker for Mr. DeLay who has not responded to repeated telephone calls in recent weeks. In a brief interview last month, Ms. Benoit said the Oaks at Rio Bend would open this year. The foundation and other charities linked to members of Congress have faced criticism from advocacy groups that seek to tighten Congressional ethics rules and charity regulations. They say that whatever its charitable purpose, the DeLay Foundation is also an important fund-raising operation for Mr. DeLay and allows corporate lobbyists and executives to curry favor with him in a way that skirts campaign finance laws. Mr. DeLay is facing scrutiny in Washington for possible ethics lapses involving overseas travel and ties to lobbyists. His activities are also being examined by a state grand jury in Texas that has indicted two of his closest political operatives on charges of illegal fund-raising. In a letter to constituents this week, Mr. DeLay said he was under attack by Democrats and a "legion of Democrat-friendly press." Watchdog groups say that with the disclosure of new names on the donors' list and details of Mr. Perry's involvement at Rio Bend, the ethics committee should review Mr. DeLay's involvement with the charity and how he has used it to organize golf tournaments and other events where he meets lobbyists and executives under the auspices of charity. Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/24/politics/24donate.html?ref=southerncompany">Energy Companies Help Lift Inaugural Fund to $8 Million<date>Published: December 24, 2004</date><text>ASHINGTON, Dec. 23 - Drawing support from the energy industry and other longtime backers of President Bush, the Presidential Inaugural Committee has raised almost $8 million since it began gathering money this month, according to a list it released Thursday. ExxonMobil, the Occidental Petroleum Corporation, ChevronTexaco and the Southern Company were among more than 20 donors to give the maximum $250,000, which entitles executives to attend the ceremonies, black-tie balls and events with the president. Many others gave smaller amounts in return for fewer perks, like the $100,000 contributed by the military contractors Boeing and Northrop Grumman. Advertisement The Presidential Inaugural Committee is seeking to raise as much as $40 million to kick off Mr. Bush's second term, with multiple events leading up to the Jan. 20 swearing-in, and has spent much of December soliciting donors across the country, despite the holidays and the exhaustion brought by an election that raised record amounts. "There is some donor fatigue," said Brad Freeman, a longtime Bush supporter and fund-raiser who is a co-chairman of the committee. "But they have had a nice rest." So far, the roster of donors is thick with people and companies loyal to Mr. Bush and the Republican Party, and fund-raisers expect it to grow substantially. For corporations, the inauguration represents a rare opportunity to write large checks. Though companies are forbidden to contribute directly to candidates or political parties during an election, campaign finance laws do not restrict them from donating to events like political conventions or inaugurations. Roughly half the 52 contributors identified so far are companies, including well-known names like International Paper, Union Pacific and Qualcomm. Several donors are individuals who also played a major role in this year's election. For example, T. Boone Pickens, a Texas oilman who contributed $250,000 for the inauguration, had given a total of about $5.5 million to the Progress for America Voter Fund and Swift Vets and P.O.W.'s for Truth, two groups that supported Mr. Bush. Ameriquest Capital Corporation also gave $250,000 to the inauguration. Dawn Arnall, who is co-chairwoman of the company along with her husband, Roland Arnall, gave $5 million to the Progress for America Voter Fund this year. The two were also $200,000 "ranger" fund-raisers for Mr. Bush's campaign. Another $250,000 donor for the inauguration is Richard Kinder, a former president of the Enron Corporation, who is now chief executive of the Kinder Morgan energy transportation companies. His wife, Nancy Kinder, was a ranger fund-raiser for Mr. Bush and both are members of the inauguration's finance committee. Though there is no legal limit to the amount donors can give to an inauguration, the committee has voluntarily capped donations at $250,000 per contributor. That apparently does not stop related organizations from each giving the maximum. For example, Ameriquest, which is a holding company for several financial services firms, gave $250,000, as did Argent Mortgage Company, Long Beach Acceptance Corporation and Town and County Credit, which are each part of Ameriquest. Collectively, the affiliated companies gave $1 million. Some advocates of tighter campaign finance restrictions say the lack of limits on inaugural fund-raising is a shortcoming in the McCain-Feingold campaign finance law, which was passed in 2002 to ban unlimited soft-money contributions to candidates and political parties. "It's a problem because the opportunity for wealthy donors to funnel huge sums of money to the president and receive recognition from the president could translate into access and influence," said Donald J. Simon, a lawyer who has worked to tighten campaign finance laws.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/31/us/7-companies-band-together-hopes-building-nation-s-first-new-nuclear-plant.html?ref=southerncompany">7 Companies Band Together in Hopes of Building Nation's First New Nuclear Plant in Decades<date>Published: March 31, 2004</date><text>In an effort to revive the nuclear reactor construction industry, seven major companies plan to announce on Wednesday that they will apply for a license to build a new commercial power plant. The last time a plant was ordered but not later canceled was 1973.The companies, including the two largest nuclear plant owners in the United States and two reactor manufacturers, have not specified what they would build or where. In fact, they have not made a committment to build at all. But they have agreed to spend tens of millions of dollars to get permission to build, and they anticipate tens of millions from the federal government, which requested such proposals in November. The money would go to finish design work useful for a new generation of reactors and to develop a firm estimate of what such plants would cost.''In order to keep the nuclear option open for the future, we've got to take this next step,'' said Gary J. Taylor, president and chief executive of Entergy Nuclear, a participant.The industry successfully operates existing plants, Mr. Taylor said, but it must build more to sustain itself. ''Without a future, there's an inability to attract new talent,'' he said.''It can't be just any one company,'' Mr. Taylor added. ''Entergy believes it's going to have to be some sort of consortium.''Other executives said the consortium would help the industry. ''Somebody needs to take the responsibility to advance the momentum, or there won't be an option,'' said an executive at another company who asked not to be more closely identified before the announcement. ''There haven't been any orders since Three Mile Island, we've got an aging fleet, and at some point they won't be there any more.''The Three Mile Island accident occurred 25 years ago this month. The last orders were placed nine months later, in December 1979, but every one after 1973 was canceled, mostly because of soaring costs. There are 103 commercial reactors now operating; those in service the longest began operation in 1969.The consortium's other goal is to test a simplified licensing system created by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission 12 years ago to help the industry go from reactor order to electricity production in 5 years, as opposed to the 10 or 12 years it took under the previous system.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/29/business/environmental-groups-gain-as-companies-vote-on-issues.html?ref=southerncompany">Environmental Groups Gain As Companies Vote on Issues<date>Published: May 29, 2003</date><text>Almost a quarter of the shareholders of the Southern Company, one of the nation's largest utilities, voted at the annual meeting today to require the company to analyze and report on the potential financial risks associated with its emissions of the pollutants that cause global warming.At the same time, shareholders of Exxon Mobil, the world's biggest oil company, meeting in Dallas, gave a similar level of support to several resolutions on environmental issues. One, which would require the company to report on how it would increase its investments in renewable energy, was backed by 21 percent of the shareholders, and another, on how it would respond to the risks of global warming, was supported by 22 percent.No one expected any of these resolutions to win majority support. But they are a measure of the increasing intensity of shareholders' challenges to corporations to respond to environmental concerns.Spurred on by a coalition of environmental and religious groups, shareholders have filed 31 global warming resolutions with 23 companies in the United States this year and 5 in Canada. The companies include auto manufacturers, electric power companies and oil companies.''It is a trend that I don't think is going to disappear,'' said Sister Barbara Aires, coordinator of corporate responsibility for the Sisters of Charity of St. Elizabeth in New Jersey, who introduced the resolution today at Southern's meeting in Georgia. ''I think more institutional investors are looking for assessments of the triple bottom line -- social, environmental and financial -- not simply financial.''Last year, resolutions concerning global warming won about 18 percent of shareholders' support at a dozen or so companies, according to the United States Public Interest Research Group, which has helped organize efforts for the resolutions. This year, they have averaged more than 25 percent at more than twice the number of companies, the group said.The Investor Responsibility Research Center, a nonprofit group in Washington that advises institutions on proxy issues, was more cautious in interpreting the numbers. Its overall figures were lower because they included a low of 5.2 percent for a resolution at Citigroup, which finances energy ventures. That resolution called for Citigroup to review the effect of these financial ventures on climate.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/24/business/company-news-dynegy-and-southern-agree-to-nullify-three-contracts.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; DYNEGY AND SOUTHERN AGREE TO NULLIFY THREE CONTRACTS<date>Published: April 24, 2003</date><text>Dynegy Inc., a power producer that is quitting energy trading after losses brought the company close to filing for bankruptcy court protection, agreed to pay $155 million to the Southern Company to nullify three wholesale electricity contracts. The agreement will cancel $1.7 billion in payments Dynegy would have had to make to Southern over the next 30 years, Dynegy said. Dynegy will get back $96 million in collateral. The contracts were for a combined 1,100 megawatts of power, or enough for about 880,000 homes. Dynegy, which is based in Houston, has sought to end ''tolling contracts'' like those with Southern, under which Dynegy pays power plant owners a fee for the right to sell their electricity. For Southern, an Atlanta-based utility owner with four million customers and about 37,000 megawatts of generating capacity, the agreement will result in a one-time gain of $88 million after taxes, the company said in a filing today with the S.E.C.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/17/business/utility-shareholders-demand-liability-disclosure.html?ref=southerncompany">Utility Shareholders Demand Liability Disclosure<date>Published: January 17, 2003</date><text>A group of shareholders that includes the Connecticut treasurer's office and several religious organizations have begun a campaign to compel the largest electric utilities in the nation to publish information about liabilities they might face because of their emission of gases that contribute to global warming.Led by the State of Connecticut Plans and Trust Fund and members of the New York-based Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, the shareholder coalition has filed resolutions to be voted upon at the annual meetings later this year of American Electric Power, the Southern Company, Xcel Energy Inc., the TXU Corporation and the Cinergy Corporation.The shareholders contend that there are hidden risks at the large power companies because of their release of carbon dioxide, which is widely thought to be linked to global warming, and the pollutants sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and mercury. They contend that companies could face risks if emissions of carbon dioxide were regulated and limited, which many environmentalists and some power companies think is inevitable. They also assert that the electric utilities may have to grapple with litigation linked to the emissions.''In American Electric Power's own disclosure to the S.E.C., they acknowledge climate change as a risk factor,'' said Denise L. Nappier, the Connecticut treasurer. ''What they haven't done, and what most utility companies haven't done, so far, is present to their shareholders a comprehensive assessment of these risks and how they plan to address them.''American Electric Power, the nation's largest utility, has filed a letter seeking no action against it from the Securities and Exchange Commission if it chooses not to include the shareholder resolution in the proxy statement for its annual meeting. A company spokeswoman said that American Electric Power already provided the kind of information the shareholders seek, and accused them of seeking to stop the burning of fossil fuels for electricity generation.But the investors contend that they seek disclosure of information rather than a radical change in business practices.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/23/business/alabama-s-power-struggle.html?ref=southerncompany">Alabama's Power Struggle<date>Published: June 23, 2002</date><text>THE really sultry weather will probably drift into this city around the Fourth of July, Dr. Jack Hasson figures, and then his asthma patients will become sicker.The humidity and air pollution will make drawing a breath bruising. On some days, after a morning run, Dr. Hasson can tell that he will be busy at work just by the way his own lungs feel. Asthma patients will stream into his pulmonology clinic, complaining that they cannot catch their breath. He will give stronger medication to most and hospitalize the frailest.''It's frustrating that their condition is well controlled and they do fine and then their attacks are triggered by pollution,'' he said. ''It just sabotages our work.''The steel mills that once fired Birmingham's economy and filled it with blue smoke are mostly gone. The pollution that worries Dr. Hasson now is barely visible: a tremulous summer haze that washes in from three large coal-burning power plants that surround Birmingham and are owned by the Southern Company, one of the country's largest utility holding corporations.The pollution over Birmingham seems the inevitable side effect of being neighbors with such a big power company. Southern, which has headquarters in Atlanta, contends that anti-pollution improvements it is installing at its plants take time, because it has to make sure that the environmental science is sound and that the regulatory requirements are fair before investing billions of dollars.But critics like Dr. Hasson and a range of environmentalists and regulators contend that Southern has always marshaled its considerable political and economic might to resist changes, particularly stricter environmental requirements, that threaten a comfortable status quo and healthy profits. Southern, for example, fought doggedly for years against the same federal regulations that have now compelled it to install new anti-pollution equipment at its power plants through the Southeast.But after the arrival in Washington of an administration sympathetic to the energy industry, Southern has had greater success in challenging environmental initiatives.Ten days ago, the Bush administration handed energy companies a crucial victory, proposing to relax an important enforcement statute of the Clean Air Act. The statute, known as the new source review, requires them to install anti-pollution equipment on old upgraded coal-fired plants.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/13/business/energy-giants-push-to-weaken-a-pollution-rule.html?ref=southerncompany">Energy Giants Push to Weaken a Pollution Rule<date>Published: April 13, 2002</date><text>Two years ago, at the height of the presidential campaign, some of the country's biggest energy companies came up with a wish list of top priorities should a friendly Republican administration come to office. Far ahead of issues like drilling for oil in Alaska or electricity deregulation, their top goal was to weaken an arcane air pollution rule that has cost corporations billions of dollars and embroiled the industry in litigation.With President Bush's election, the lobbying against the rule -- called new source review -- has been relentless. The effort is led by the Southern Company, the nation's second-biggest utility operator, and backed by energy companies that, like Southern, are being sued by the government to clean up power plants and refineries.The latest evidence of the industry's push to overhaul the rule is an e-mail message released two weeks ago by the Energy Department, part of 11,000 pages of documents mapping the formulation of the Bush administration's energy policy.In it, a lobbyist for Southern, while making plans for lunch with a top Energy Department official, recommended the relaxation of new source review. Eight days later, Vice President Dick Cheney's energy task force put the possible revision of the rule on its agenda, according to a participant in the formulation of the energy policy who insisted on remaining anonymous for fear of alienating the White House.The Energy Department said that the timing was a coincidence. ''We didn't need anyone from the outside telling us that new source review needed to be studied,'' said Jill Schroeder, a spokeswoman for the department. Ultimately, though, the task force's report said that the rule should be reconsidered, and President Bush agreed.Though the re-examination has been slowed by battles between the Energy Department and the Environmental Protection Agency, and within the E.P.A., a decision is expected in a few months. If the rule is weakened, as many expect, the lawsuits built on it could crumble -- which may be the ultimate goal, industry experts said.''The thinking was: How can you do things that will influence the N.S.R. issue and the pending litigation?'' said one Washington lawyer for the energy industry who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''The two are tied together. If you affect the program, you can affect the progress of lawsuits. If the administration recants N.S.R. provisions, the lawsuits fall apart.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/20/business/major-utility-chief-set-to-resign-post.html?ref=southerncompany">Major Utility Chief Set to Resign Post<date>Published: February 20, 2001</date><text>After nearly six years as chief executive of the Southern Company, the largest power generator in the United States, A. W. Dahlberg, 60, said yesterday that he will retire on April 2, the scheduled day of completion for his signature project, the spinoff of the company's competitive energy businesses.H. Allen Franklin, 56, who has retraced much of Mr. Dahlberg's career path through the utility holding company's upper echelons, will replace him, the company said.Mr. Dahlberg's retirement is effective with the spinoff of the Mirant Corporation, formerly called Southern Energy, which is the primary growth engine for the 56-year-old company.''As we thought over the last year about the spinoff of Mirant, we did something that made Allen and me a duplication,'' Mr. Dahlberg said in a telephone interview. ''One person can probably do this job.''The unit encapsulates Mr. Dahlberg's accomplishments, wrapping together the company's international and competitive retail businesses.Shortly after taking the chief executive's job in 1995, Mr. Dahlberg had promised those businesses would generate 30 percent of income by 2003; they nearly did so last year.Fearing shareholders had missed the rewards, the company completed a $1.8 billion initial public offering of stock in the unit last year.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/05/business/world-business-briefing-europe-talks-to-resume-in-berlin-utility-fight.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; TALKS TO RESUME IN BERLIN UTILITY FIGHT<date>Published: December 05, 2000</date><text>The Southern Company, the largest power producer in the United States, said it would resume negotiations over control of Bewag, a Berlin electric utility, after a court upheld an injunction blocking E.ON A.G., a major German utility group, from selling its stake in Bewag to a rival, HEW A.G. Southern acquired 26 percent of Bewag in 1997 and wants to buy the rest. E.ON is obliged to sell its stake because of antitrust concerns about the merger that created E.ON.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/business/in-utility-power-play-east-meets-west-buyers-circle-debt-ridden-german-pawn.html?ref=southerncompany">In Utility Power Play, East Meets West; Buyers Circle Debt-Ridden German Pawn<date>Published: October 13, 2000</date><text>Until recently, the sparkling new power plant in eastern Germany looked like a Taj Mahal of good intentions gone wrong.Built by VEAG, an eastern German power company owned by western German utilities, the coal-fired generators in Lippendorf hum almost silently inside spotless white buildings. Gone is the sulfurous black soot that the old Communist-era power plant here once rained down on the countryside. Today, the two giant white cooling towers emit little more than white clouds of water vapor.But for all its virtues, VEAG is reeling. Steered by both the hubris of its western German owners as well as political correctness, the company has spent nearly $8 billion rebuilding the dilapidated power system in the east.Now, thanks to abrupt deregulation of the electricity market here, it has been forced to reduce its prices by nearly half in the last year. With debt of more than $2 billion, VEAG lost nearly $800 million in 1999.Would anybody want to buy a company like this? Surprisingly, yes.In a battle that reflects the tumultuous change in Europe's power industry, at least a dozen potential bidders have emerged from Europe and the United States. One of the most determined suitors is the Southern Company, the Atlanta-based electricity conglomerate, which is already locked in a bitter legal battle for control of Berlin's electric utility.Southern's biggest rival is Hamburg's electric utility, whose biggest shareholder is the Swedish power conglomerate Vattenfall. Others circling the prey include NRG Energy, a Minneapolis power company; Enel, the Italian power company; Endesa, the Spanish electric utility; and a German utility backed by Electricite de France.The battle shows how little control easterners have over their economy. Until now, VEAG's fate has been dictated by the western German power companies that often had their own agendas. In the future, it may well be determined by companies in Atlanta, Stockholm, Paris or even Milan.''It will not be VEAG tomorrow,'' said Jurgen Stotz, VEAG's chief executive, in a recent interview at the company's headquarters in Berlin. ''It is clear we cannot do it alone. We are only one piece of the puzzle.''The pursuers of VEAG have been motivated by the rapid expansion of cross-border competition in Europe. As former national electric monopolies increasingly attack one another's territories, VEAG represents a rare opportunity for foreigners to enter Europe's biggest market.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/business/world-business-briefing-europe-court-blocks-eon-purchase.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; COURT BLOCKS E.ON PURCHASE<date>Published: August 25, 2000</date><text>An Atlanta-based power company, the Southern Company, won at least a temporary victory in its battle to keep a grip on the Berlin electric utility Bewag A.G. A German court blocked E.ON A.G, Germany's second-biggest utility company, from selling its 49 percent stake in Bewag to Hamburgische Electricitats-Werke. Southern, which owns 26 percent of Bewag, wants to acquire full control as part of an effort to bid on the big eastern German power company, VEAG A.G. A court upheld an injunction against E.ON's deal. Edmund L. Andrews(NYT)</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/17/business/world-business-briefing-europe-us-bid-for-hyder-gains.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; U.S. BID FOR HYDER GAINS<date>Published: August 17, 2000</date><text>Western Power Distribution looked set to win a marathon battle for the Welsh utility Hyder P.L.C. after Britain's Takeover Panel dismissed an appeal by the rival bidder, Nomura International. The appeal came after Western Power -- owned by the PPL Corporation and the Southern Company of the United States -- won a sealed bid conducted by the panel. Nomura, a Japanese investment bank, may now appeal the ruling of the regulatory body, but it is not expected to respond until the panel publishes its full report on Friday.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/27/business/utilities-take-stake-in-power-trade-site.html?ref=southerncompany">Utilities Take Stake In Power-Trade Site<date>Published: July 27, 2000</date><text>Abandoning plans to create their own Internet energy-trading exchange, the Duke Energy Corporation, the El Paso Energy Corporation, the Southern Company and three other power-trading companies acquired a stake in IntercontinentalExchange, an online power and metals trading site.The six companies, which did not disclose the financial terms of the transaction, handle about 37 percent of the electricity and 27 percent of the gas traded in the United States. Partners' stakes in the exchange are based on the size of their trading business.The Atlanta-based exchange was founded in March by seven energy and investment companies.In addition to Duke, El Paso Energy and Southern, the other three utilities joining in the exchange are American Electric Power, Reliant Energy and UtiliCorp United.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/30/business/world-business-briefing-europe-bidding-for-welsh-utility.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; BIDDING FOR WELSH UTILITY<date>Published: June 30, 2000</date><text>The Welsh utility Hyder P.L.C. said it had withdrawn its backing of the Nomura Securities Company's $3.5 billion offer for it as it waited to see if either Nomura or a second suitor, a venture owned by the utilities Southern Company and the PPL Corporation, would increase their bid, which analysts expect will happen. Andrew Ross Sorkin (NYT)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/09/business/company-news-southern-is-buying-four-plants-from-potomac.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN IS BUYING FOUR PLANTS FROM POTOMAC<date>Published: June 09, 2000</date><text>The Southern Company, the largest electricity producer in the United States, agreed yesterday to buy four power plants from the Potomac Electric Power Company, for $2.65 billion in cash. The plants, three in Maryland and one in Virginia, can produce 5,154 megawatts of electricity, enough to light more than five million homes. They will join a network stretching from California to Massachusetts. Southern, based in Atlanta, is buying and building plants across the United States to support its energy-trading business. Potomac Electric, based in Washington, is one of several utilities to abandon power production.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/24/business/management-the-boss-flamingo-fundamentals.html?ref=southerncompany">MANAGEMENT: THE BOSS; Flamingo Fundamentals<date>Published: May 24, 2000</date><text>My family moved to the country outside Atlanta when I was around 5. I used to tell people I helped my dad build the old family place. We had a mule, Kate, and a sled, and we'd pick up fieldstones, load the sled and haul it to the house. My mom still lives there.I went to work for Georgia Power, a Southern Company affiliate, when I was 19. For the first month or so, I washed meter covers. After eight years and several promotions in the meter department, I got a job repossessing appliances. We were pretty generous; we never repossessed unless the situation was entirely hopeless. The man I worked for, Walter Bartley, was a great role model.I had been going to college at night. One day, Walter called me into his office and said, ''You dropped out.'' I said, ''Yessir.'' He said he was going to school, too, in Athens, driving 60 miles each way twice a week. He said, ''You go about six miles to school, right?'' I said ''Yessir.'' He said, ''Well if you don't go back, I'm gonna fire you.'' I graduated when I was 30. He didn't graduate till he was almost 40.I've been with the Southern Company, through one affiliate or another, for 40 years, working my way up in operations, finance and marketing. I understand the fundamentals of electricity. I always tell people I signed up to take the correspondence course and never got beyond batteries. Actually, I flunked batteries.As chief executive, I've been known to dress in funny outfits. I created a George Patton uniform. I've worn a gorilla suit. Was a bhagwan. A ninja. A coach. Most of the time it's been internal at the company. If it inspires someone, that's great. If it makes it fun to work at the company, that's great. I don't mind one bit if people laugh at me.My office is filled with things people send me. If people come by, they like to see that what they sent is there. Our 1999 annual report had a ''This is not Joe'' theme; I just got a hat with ''I'm not Joe'' on it, and I'm expecting more Joe things. When we did the gorilla, I got gorillas -- 12 of them. I have a hockey stick from the new Atlanta team. A baseball that Hank Aaron sent. A hat that Michael Jordan sent.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/02/business/world-business-briefing-europe-more-interest-in-hyder.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: EUROPE; MORE INTEREST IN HYDER<date>Published: May 02, 2000</date><text>A bidding war for the Welsh utility company Hyder P.L.C. loomed after a another suitor emerged for the company. Western Power Distribution, a joint venture of the PPL Corporation of Allentown, Pa., and the Southern Company of Atlanta, acknowledged it was considering a bid for Hyder. Last month, Hyder agreed to be bought by the Nomura Securities Company for $:2.3 billion ($3.6 billion), but if Western Power decides to make a bid, it could derail that deal. Andrew Ross Sorkin</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/23/business/world-business-briefing-americas-aes-expands-in-argentina.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; AES EXPANDS IN ARGENTINA<date>Published: February 23, 2000</date><text>Extending its reach in Latin America, the AES Corporation will acquire a controlling stake in an Argentine hydroelectric power plant for $205 million from the Southern Company. AES, which will use the plant in the province of Neuquen to supply electricity to as many as one million homes, expects half of its earnings to come from South America within five years. AES is based in Arlington, Va., and operates in 18 countries. Southern, based in Atlanta, is one of the biggest American power utilities. Simon Romero (NYT)</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/02/business/company-news-southern-co-in-talks-with-utility-in-virgin-islands.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN CO. IN TALKS WITH UTILITY IN VIRGIN ISLANDS<date>Published: February 02, 2000</date><text>The Southern Company said yesterday that it was in talks to buy 80 percent of the Virgin Islands Water and Power Authority for about $100 million. The Virgin Islands' government will retain the other 20 percent of the utility, said Marce Fuller, chief executive of the company's Southern Energy unit. Southern expects to reach a purchase agreement this quarter. The Atlanta-based company owns electric utilities in Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi and Florida.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/04/us/7-utilities-sued-by-us-on-charges-of-polluting-air.html?ref=southerncompany">7 UTILITIES SUED BY U.S. ON CHARGES OF POLLUTING AIR<date>Published: November 04, 1999</date><text>In what federal officials called one of the biggest enforcement actions in the nation's history, the government sued seven giant electric companies in the Midwest and the South today, accusing the utilities of defying anti-pollution regulations and illegally contaminating the air breathed by millions of Americans.The government took legal or administrative action against 32 coal-fired plants in 10 states, saying that if the plants reduced pollution as required it would have the same effect as taking 26 million cars off the road.In the suits, filed by the Justice Department on behalf of the Environmental Protection Agency, the government accused the companies of modernizing their generating plants without modernizing their pollution controls as required by the Clean Air Act. The government contends that 17 of the companies' plants have fouled the air for years and contributed ''to some of the most severe environmental problems facing the United States today.''''When children have trouble breathing because of pollution from a utility plant hundreds of miles away, something must be done,'' Attorney General Janet Reno said.The civil suits, which seek to fine the companies and force them to install modern anti-pollution equipment, were filed in Federal District Court in five Midwestern and Southern cities.The E.P.A. administrator, Carol Browner, said the seven defendants had committed ''very, very significant violations of the Clean Air Act,'' an accusation that the utilities immediately denounced.Ms. Browner said the companies had illegally retooled old, pollution-spewing coal plants without notifying regulators, getting the necessary permits and installing expensive new equipment to reduce emissions and meet pollution standards that apply to new plants.''They chose not to,'' Ms. Browner said, ''because they knew that if they did they'd have to reduce their pollution, and they didn't want to do it.''The utilities' motive, she added, was to prolong the lives of the old plants and to avoid the cost of building new plants with tough, modern standards.The defendants denounced the government's action. ''We regret that the agency has again demonstrated that it prefers headlines and confrontation over consensus-building,'' said Dale Heydlauff, a vice president of American Electric Power of Columbus, Ohio. ''We are fully prepared to vigorously defend against these allegations, and we believe we will prevail.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/20/business/company-news-southern-tells-of-efforts-to-buy-gas-pipeline-company.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN TELLS OF EFFORTS TO BUY GAS PIPELINE COMPANY<date>Published: October 20, 1999</date><text>The Southern Company, the largest United States power generator and owner of Atlanta's electric utility, has tried unsuccessfully for a year to negotiate a buyout of a natural-gas pipeline company, including the El Paso Energy Corporation or the Coastal Corporation, Southern's chief financial officer said yesterday. The executive, William Westbrook, said that Southern had had talks with El Paso, Coastal and other gas companies but that no agreement could be reached on price. Both El Paso and Coastal declined to comment. El Paso has a stock market value of about $4.8 billion, and Coastal, $8.5 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/19/business/world-business-briefing-americas-meeting-boycotted-by-americans.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; MEETING BOYCOTTED BY AMERICANS<date>Published: October 19, 1999</date><text>A shareholders meeting of Companhia Energetica de Minas Gerais was postponed for one week after two of the Brazilian power company's shareholders, the Southern Company and the AES Corporation, boycotted the event. The American companies, which are minority partners in the state-controlled utility known as Cemig, were hoping to prevent a vote confirming an earlier decision curtailing their management capacities. A legal battle is under way between the companies and Itamar Franco, the Governor of Minas Gerais state, because Mr. Franco moved to annul the effects of a 1997 transaction allowing them to manage Cemig.Simon Romero (NYT)</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/09/business/international-business-politics-threatens-brazilian-utility-sales.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Politics Threatens Brazilian Utility Sales<date>Published: October 09, 1999</date><text>He's up to his old tricks again. With an eye to his political fortunes, the same maverick Governor and former President who provoked Brazil's currency crisis in January by defaulting on his state's foreign debt is now seeking to sabotage a crucial federal government program to privatize state-owned companies.Heeding a call by Itamar Franco, the Governor of Minas Gerais state, the board of its electric utility agreed on Thursday to expel directors representing minority shareholders including two American companies, the AES Corporation and the Southern Company. In 1997, the companies acquired a one-third interest in the utility, known as Cemig, and have since invested nearly $1 billion under a contract that Mr. Franco, backed by a sympathetic state court, now refuses to recognize.''We are completely shocked by the action taken by Minas Gerais,'' said Richard Owen, vice president for Latin America and the Caribbean for Southern, one of the biggest utilities in the United States. ''This could reflect on the appetite foreign companies have in future privatizations.''Mr. Franco has also campaigned to block the privatization of Furnas Electrical, a utility that supplies power to nearly half of Brazil's 165 million people. Recently he went so far as to threaten to divert the course of the rivers that feed the giant Furnas dam, situated in his state, if the utility is sold.In addition, Mr. Franco has dispatched state military police to conduct maneuvers in the area around the dam and has established a command base there. Though he has not explicitly threatened to use those forces to block private investors from taking control of Furnas, he has cited the crucial role of the military police in coups in 1932 and 1964.To what extent the actions of Mr. Franco, who was elected Governor of Brazil's third-most populous state last year, are motivated by ideology, as opposed to personal grievances, is hard to determine. As President from 1992 through 1994, he ushered in a period of economic stability, but most of the credit went to Fernando Henrique Cardoso, who was his Finance Minister and is now serving a second term as President.One of Mr. Franco's first acts after taking office in January was to decree a moratorium on payment of his state's debts both to the central government and to foreign creditors, which set off a crisis that resulted in a 40 percent devaluation of the Brazilian currency.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/08/business/world-business-briefing-americas-brazil-utility-shake-up.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; BRAZIL UTILITY SHAKE-UP<date>Published: October 08, 1999</date><text>Representatives of minority shareholders in Cemig, a Brazilian electric utility controlled by Minas Gerais state, were ousted in a display of anti-privatization ire by Gov. Itamar Franco, the former President whose refusal to pay debts helped provoke Brazil's currency crisis last January. The Cemic executives -- from the AES Corporation, the Southern Company and Grupo Opportunity -- were dismissed after a state court ruled their 1997 purchase of a voting-rights stake in Cemig for about $1 billion did not give them veto power over investment decisions. The investors plan to appeal the decision in federal courts.Simon Romero (NYT)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/09/29/business/world-business-briefing-americas-brazil-utility-fight.html?ref=southerncompany">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; BRAZIL UTILITY FIGHT<date>Published: September 29, 1999</date><text>A court in Minas Gerais, the Brazilian state governed by a former President, Itamar Franco, curtailed the management powers of the AES Corporation, the Southern Company and Grupo Opportunity over Companhia Energetica de Minas Gerais, a state electric utility. The ruling nullifies a shareholders' agreement that had given the American and Brazilian companies management control of the utility after they paid $1 billion for one-third of its voting shares in 1997. Simon Romero</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/12/business/international-business-two-us-utilities-to-sell-british-unit.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Two U.S. Utilities to Sell British Unit<date>Published: June 12, 1999</date><text>PP&amp;L Resources Inc., owner of Pennsylvania's second-largest electric utility, and the Southern Company said today that they had agreed to sell their British power-supply business to London Electricity for about $256 million.London Electricity, the supply arm of South Western Electricity P.L.C., buys power from Britain's grid and sells it to 1.3 million customers in southwestern England. PP&amp;L owns 51 percent of South Western and Southern operates South Western and owns 49 percent.PP&amp;L and Southern said that their focus in Britain would be on delivering power over their wires.Other United States utilities have retreated from Britain because of disappointing profits. The Entergy Corporation in New Orleans sold London Electricity to Electricite de France, France's state-owned electric utility, for $3.2 billion last year.Southern, which is based in Atlanta, acquired South Western in 1995 for $1.8 billion. It sold a 25 percent stake to PP&amp;L, which is based in Allentown, the following year for $181 million and another 26 percent last year for $170 million.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/16/business/el-paso-energy-to-buy-sonat-creating-gas-pipeline-giant.html?ref=southerncompany">El Paso Energy to Buy Sonat, Creating Gas Pipeline Giant<date>Published: March 16, 1999</date><text>The El Paso Energy Corporation agreed today to buy a rival, Sonat Inc., for $3.9 billion in stock and $1.9 billion in assumed debt, creating the largest interstate natural gas pipeline company in the United States.El Paso will exchange one of its shares for each share of Sonat. The transaction values Sonat at $35.75 a share, a 32 percent premium to its closing price of $27.125 on Thursday, the day before the company's stock started to rise on speculation about the purchase.The deal will let El Paso expand in the electricity business without merging with a utility, as other gas companies have done, analysts said. Sonat's pipelines provide gas to fast-growing markets in the Southeast, including Florida. El Paso, based in Houston, can build gas-fired power plants along those lines. Sonat is based in Birmingham, Ala.''El Paso is getting pipelines in an area it doesn't have them now, which should provide a good platform to continue their power plant projects,'' said Mark Easterbrook, an analyst at Dain Rauscher Wessels.The bid comes a month after the Southern Company in Atlanta, the largest publicly traded United States power company, ended talks to buy El Paso. Those talks fell apart after the chairman of El Paso, William Wise, demanded to be chief executive of the new company when Southern's chief executive leaves, people close to the negotiations said.In an interview, Mr. Wise said the purchase would save $60 million a year beginning in 2000. Some jobs will be cut after the acquisition, though Mr. Wise did not give specific figures. El Paso will take a charge of $200 million to $300 million before taxes to account for some of the costs of the deal.The companies said the acquisition would raise earnings and cash flow of the combined entity in 2000, the first full year of the merger.The high premium that El Paso is paying is an indicator of how strongly El Paso wants to stay independent, analysts said. Buying Sonat makes El Paso big enough to fend off hostile bids, said Michael Barbis, an analyst with Warburg Dillon Read.Shares of El Paso fell $3.6875, or 10.3 percent, to $32.0625, as investors reacted to the size of the bid. Sonat fell 43.75 cents, to $29.625.Mr. Easterbrook suggested that one reason shares were falling was that investors were worried about the financial prospects of Sonat's oil and gas exploration business.Earlier this month, Sonat said it would take a first-quarter charge of about $200 million, or $1.81 a share, to write down the value of reserves because of low oil and gas prices. Inflation-adjusted oil prices have been at their lowest levels since the Great Depression most of this year.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/05/business/international-business-chinese-company-delays-offering-s-pricing.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Chinese Company Delays Offering's Pricing<date>Published: February 05, 1999</date><text>Shandong International Power Development Ltd., a Chinese state-run power generator, delayed the pricing of its initial public offering by one business day, the company's underwriter said today.''The company asked for and received a one-business-day extension until Monday the 8th,'' Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, which is arranging Shandong International's first-time sale of shares to the public, said in a statement.Shandong is still in pricing discussions with institutional investors around the world, said a spokesman for Goldman Sachs Asia, Peter Rose. The offering seeks to raise up to $282 million for Shandong.The company's shares were to begin trading on Tuesday after being priced Friday.Analysts have said that Goldman may be forced to lower Shandong's initial stock price, or shelve the initial offering entirely, because investors are growing reluctant to put money in China.The Southern Company in Atlanta, the largest publicly traded United States power producer, has agreed to buy about 40 percent of Shandong's offering. Goldman plans to sell about 90 percent of the remaining stake to international investors.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/11/25/business/company-news-southern-to-buy-orange-and-rockland-plants.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN TO BUY ORANGE AND ROCKLAND PLANTS<date>Published: November 25, 1998</date><text>The Southern Energy Inc. unit of the Southern Company, agreed yesterday to acquire all the electric power plants of Orange and Rockland Utilities Inc. in a deal valued at $480 million. The sale includes the Bowline Point Generating Plant in West Haverstraw, N.Y., which is one-third owned by Orange and Rockland and two-thirds owned by the Consolidated Edison Company of New York. Orange and Rockland will receive $345 million in the transaction and Con Ed $135 million. The Southern Company, based in Atlanta, is the parent company of five electric utilities. The divestiture is part of a New York State-mandated program to introduce competition to the retail power market.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/25/nyregion/metro-business-electricity-marketer-in-bankruptcy-court.html?ref=southerncompany">Metro Business; Electricity Marketer In Bankruptcy Court<date>Published: August 25, 1998</date><text>Power Company of America, an electricity marketer in Greenwich, Conn., has been forced into bankruptcy proceedings by two utilities and an electricity trader that say the company failed to deliver on contracts.Southern Company, Entergy Corporation and American Energy Solutions jointly filed a Chapter 11 reorganization petition yesterday in Federal Bankruptcy Court in Bridgeport against the company, which is the 13th largest electricity marketer in the country. Cinergy Corporation also has filed a claim against Power in the court.Power failed to deliver electricity to some customers or pay some suppliers as promised during a heat wave in June, according to the filing, setting up a chain reaction of defaults that sent power prices soaring to more than 125 times last year's average and created utility losses totaling more than $300 million.In the filing, Southern is seeking $51.8 million, Entergy $43.4 million, American Energy $24.3 million and Cinergy $6.6 million from Power.Power officials said the company had planned to file for bankruptcy protection anyway. The company has been working with creditors, and will stop trading electricity.Electricity trading among power companies emerged from a 1992 Federal law that deregulated wholesale electricity trading by requiring utilities to open their wires to other suppliers.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/28/business/company-news-southern-to-buy-9-power-plants-in-massachusetts.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN TO BUY 9 POWER PLANTS IN MASSACHUSETTS<date>Published: May 28, 1998</date><text>The Southern Company, an electric utility holding company, agreed yesterday to buy nine power plants from Commonwealth Energy System and Eastern Utilities Associates for $537 million to bolster its electricity-trading operations in the Northeast. The gas- and oil-fired power plants are in Massachusetts. The purchase also includes a 1.4 percent interest in a Maine power plant. Combined, the plants will give Southern about 1,260 megawatts of generating capacity. Southern, based in Atlanta, is buying the plants to have a secure supply of electricity in New England as that market opens to competition.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/01/02/business/southern-to-buy-generator.html?ref=southerncompany">Southern to Buy Generator<date>Published: January 02, 1998</date><text>The Southern Company has agreed to acquire the coal-fired State Line Generating Station in Hammond, Ind., from Commonwealth Edison for $68 million. Commonwealth Edison is a unit of the Chicago-based Unicom Corporation. Southern, based in Atlanta, is an electric utility holding company with 1996 revenue of $10.32 billion. Under a 15-year power purchase agreement, Southern will supply power to Commonwealth Edison. Southern will spend $65 million to help the 490-megawatt plant maintain safety.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/17/business/news-of-cepa-sale-causes-hopewell-to-slip.html?ref=southerncompany">News of C.E.P.A. Sale Causes Hopewell to Slip<date>Published: July 17, 1997</date><text>Shares of Hopewell Holdings Ltd. fell yesterday after the company, an infrastructure developer based in Hong Kong, said that it would sell its remaining 20 percent stake in Consolidated Electric Power Asia Ltd. Hopewell's stock closed at $4.90 (Hong Kong), down 20 cents.Hopewell announced late on Tuesday that it had agreed to sell its remaining interest in C.E.P.A to the Southern Company of Atlanta in exchange for an 80 percent stake in the Tanjung Jati B power project in Indonesia plus $150 million in cash. Hopewell sold an 80 percent interest in C.E.P.A. to Southern late last year in a deal valued at $2.7 billion.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/29/business/aes-and-southern-acquire-brazil-utility-stake.html?ref=southerncompany">AES AND SOUTHERN ACQUIRE BRAZIL UTILITY STAKE<date>Published: May 29, 1997</date><text>The Southern Company and the AES Corporation joined yesterday with a Brazilian partner to buy a $1 billion stake in the Brazilian utility Cia. Energetica de Minas Gerais as part of a plan to expand into the Latin American electricity market. Southern, based in Atlanta, and AES, based in Arlington, Va., bought the 33 percent stake in the regional utility, which is known as Cemig, for 1.13 billion reals ($1.05 billion). Their Brazilian partner is Opportunity Capital Partners Ltda., a Rio de Janeiro fund manager. Cemig serves 4.3 million customers and accounts for 13 percent of Brazil's total electricity sales.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/14/business/big-us-utility-spreads-its-reach-to-berlin.html?ref=southerncompany">Big U.S. Utility Spreads Its Reach to Berlin<date>Published: May 14, 1997</date><text>The Southern Company, a huge utility based in Atlanta, said yesterday that it and two German utilities had formed a consortium that would seek to buy a controlling interest in the utility that serves the city of Berlin for $1.7 billion.Southern, which has already made major acquisitions in Britain, Asia and Latin America, said it would pay $830 million for a 25 percent stake in the utility, Berliner Kraft und Licht A.G., known informally as Bewag.The two other members of the consortium are Preussen Elektra, which is owned by Veba A.G., a huge German conglomerate, and Bayernwerk, owned by another big, diversified German company, Viag A.G..While the three partners are buying a 50.8 percent stake from the City of Berlin, each will have 25 percent when the transaction is completed because the two German partners already own shares in Bewag.Ulrich Hartmann, chairman and chief executive of Veba, said in an interview that the bid was expected to run into tough antitrust review and political problems in Germany because Veba already owned two other utilities in the region surrounding Berlin.''It is major problem,'' he said. The German Federal Cartel Office said earlier this week that it wanted to review the bid, saying it would give Veba a near-monopoly in the Berlin area.Mr. Hartmann said that the chances of approval by the European Union were better. The Berlin Senate approved the deal yesterday.In an issue that could complicate matters, the consortium is expected to ask for cost reductions and layoffs -- something that has already raised the concern of German unions.In addition, Berlin's finance chief, who negotiated the deal, has been criticized in the Senate for not getting a high enough price.Mr. Hartmann conceded that politics would play a role. He added, however, that political leaders in Berlin liked the idea of an American company buying a major stake.And he said that Veba -- based in Dusseldorf with holdings in electricity, chemicals, real estate and, soon, telecommunications -- might want to cooperate in other ventures with Southern.Veba already has holdings in the United States and plans to make major investments in its American chemical and silicon-wafer businesses.Bewag has about two million customers and access to the power lines of Europe, where the deregulation of utilities is proceeding rapidly.''It offers us an opportunity to capture growth in the world's second-largest integrated utility market,'' said A. W. Dahlberg, chairman of the Southern Company.Southern is the parent of five utilities in the South and one of the nation's largest producers of low-cost power.It has been aggressive in buying overseas, acquiring Consolidated Electric Power Asia for $2.7 billion last October. In 1995, Southern acquired South Western Electricity P.L.C., a British power-distribution company.Its strategy has been different from many other American utilities facing deregulation. Many have merged with nearby utilities to cut costs and get more control over a larger customer base.Since Southern already has a huge customer base and low-cost power, it is in a good position to sell its power in other areas as utility monopolies are stripped away.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/08/business/utilities-index-shifts-lineup.html?ref=southerncompany">Utilities Index Shifts Lineup<date>Published: May 08, 1997</date><text>The Southern Company, the Duke Power Company and four other utilities will be added to the Dow Jones utilities average, replacing six existing members.Editors of The Wall Street Journal said yesterday that they had overhauled the 15-member average, which dates to 1929, to better reflect the growing population of the South and to invigorate the average's weak performance.The Texas Utilities Company, the Enron Corporation, the Williams Companies and Columbia Gas Systems will also be added to the average.To make room for the new additions, the Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation, Centerior Energy, Panenergy, the People's Energy Corporation, Houston Industries and the DTE Energy Company will be removed. The changes take effect on Monday.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/25/business/asian-utility-sees-rival-to-southern-s-bid.html?ref=southerncompany">Asian Utility Sees Rival to Southern's Bid<date>Published: October 25, 1996</date><text>Consolidated Electric Power Asia Ltd. said yesterday that another party might challenge the Southern Company's $2.7 billion bid. A bidding war may help shareholders of the power company -- including the biggest, Hopewell Holdings Ltd. of Hong Kong -- land a higher price. Two weeks ago, Hopewell agreed to sell control of the power company to Southern, based in Atlanta.Hopewell may be the only shareholder to profit if a new bidder buys less than 35 percent of the power company. In that case, the buyer would not have to extend the offer to minority shareholders, as Southern agreed to do. In a statement issued through the Stock Exchange of Hong Kong, the power company said it had yet to receive a formal offer from the potential buyer, which it did not name. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/12/business/a-deal-that-brings-together-2-players-in-electric-power.html?ref=southerncompany">A Deal That Brings Together 2 Players in Electric Power<date>Published: October 12, 1996</date><text>It is surprising how far an aggressive electric power company must go these days to find a growing market. For the management of the Southern Company of Atlanta, places like Keti Bandar, Pakistan, and Sual, in the Philippines, are no longer just answers on a geography quiz.After acquiring 80 percent of Consolidated Electric Power Asia Ltd. for $2.1 billion this week, Southern's chairman, A. W. Dahlberg, hopes those cities will become some of the company's most profitable operations.The takeover was Mr. Dahlberg's largest and most daring move so far, and it has linked his fortunes with one of the boldest entrepreneurs in Asia, Gordon Wu, and his company, Hopewell Holdings Ltd., which controlled Consolidated Electric.The acquisition enables Southern to tap into one of the world's fastest-growing markets, a place where demand for electricity exceeds supply and where profits for power generators have been substantial, but Southern is also opening itself up to substantial risk.The risk was apparent from the terms of the agreement. For Hopewell to get the total purchase price from Southern, Consolidated Electric must be able to complete a $1.8 billion construction project for two plants in Indonesia. So far, it has been delayed by difficulty acquiring the land.In addition, Consolidated has run into delays in getting a major power project going in Keti Bandar.Nevertheless, Mr. Dahlberg said in an interview, he is comfortable with the trade-off. Consolidated Electric is the fifth-largest independent power producer in the world, and Mr. Wu will remain as its chairman.Mr. Wu and his managers have already done much of the work in putting together the complex financing and preparing the political ground needed to build the power plants. And one analyst, who did not want to have his name used, said that Southern had had difficulty putting together deals overseas. He said Southern was eager to get control of the Consolidated team to lead its efforts in Asia.In fact, Southern and Consolidated also tangled over a project in the Philippines last year, and Consolidated won. Mr. Dahlberg acknowledged that his staff had proved to be no match for Consolidated there.The sale enables Consolidated to combine its expertise at building plants in Asia with Southern's financial muscle, making it a formidable competitor. For Hopewell, the sale of its 60.4 percent stake in Consolidated Electric eased its heavy debt burden.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/10/business/southern-co-unit-getting-role-in-asia.html?ref=southerncompany">Southern Co. Unit Getting Role in Asia<date>Published: October 10, 1996</date><text>The Southern Company said today that its Southern Electric International unit had agreed to buy a majority interest in Consolidated Electric Power Asia Ltd. in a deal worth $2.7 billion.Consolidated Electric, one of Asia's largest independent power producers, is now 60.4 percent owned by Hopewell Holdings Ltd. in Hong Kong, whose managing director is Gordon Wu, the Hong Kong entrepreneur.Southern's announcement said Consolidated Electric shareholders ''will receive $2.1 billion from Southern and $600 million in dividends for 80 percent of the company. Hopewell will become the largest minority shareholder of C.E.P.A.''Company executives were not immediately available to explain how the transaction would be carried out.''Combining the assets of Southern Electric International and C.E.P.A. will create one of the world's largest independent power producers, supplying electricity to the heart of Asia -- including three of the world's most populated countries -- as well as Europe, North America and South America,'' A. W. Dahlberg, Southern's chief executive, said.The company is betting that Asia's strong economic growth will continue to increase demand for electricity, analysts said.Consolidated Electric owns and operates generating plants in China and the Philippines and has projects under development in Pakistan and Indonesia.The company was established in 1993 as a holding company for Hopewell's electricity projects.Southern, based in Atlanta, said the transaction was subject to approval by the Hong Kong Stock Exchange and by shareholders of Consolidated Electric.Southern, the largest producer of electricity in the United States, is the parent of five Southeastern utilities: Alabama Power, Georgia Power, Gulf Power, Mississippi Power and Savannah Electric. It also owns power plants and transmission systems in Britain, Argentina, Chile, Trinidad and Tobago and the Bahamas. Southern's stock lost 62.5 cents to close at $21.875 on the New York Stock Exchange.Hopewell is a major developer in Asia with projects as diverse as highways, bridges, mass transit projects, hotels and retail, residential and commercial properties. The sale would provide much needed funds for the cash-strapped company.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/03/business/amended-bid-filed-for-cajun-electric.html?ref=southerncompany">AMENDED BID FILED FOR CAJUN ELECTRIC<date>Published: October 03, 1996</date><text>The Central and South West Corporation and Entergy Inc. said yesterday that they had filed an amended $780 million offer for Cajun Electric Power Cooperative Inc. that has the support of Cajun's primary customers. The cash offer filed with the United States Bankruptcy Court in Baton Rouge, La., replaces an earlier bid of $405 million in cash and an estimated $500 million in future payments. The companies would pay as much as $20 million more to cover other bankruptcy claims and expenses. Central and South West and Entergy are trying to defeat a higher bid by a partnership of the Northern States Power Company, the Zeigler Coal Holding Company and the Southern Company, which has offered $1.09 billion for Cajun.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/02/business/southern-switches-to-joint-bid-for-cajun-electric.html?ref=southerncompany">SOUTHERN SWITCHES TO JOINT BID FOR CAJUN ELECTRIC<date>Published: October 02, 1996</date><text>The Southern Company has dropped its $1.04 billion bid for the bankrupt Cajun Electric Power Cooperative Inc. and joined a rival offer by the Northern States Power Company and the Zeigler Coal Holding Company. Together, the three companies offered $1.09 billion in an amended bid filed on Monday in United States Bankruptcy Court in Baton Rouge, La., where Cajun is operating under Chapter 11 protection. In June, Southern became the fourth energy company to submit a reorganization plan for Cajun. The field also includes the Enron Corporation, the Entergy Corporation and the Central and South West Corporation. The Zeigler-Northern States bid had already won the approval of the trustee overseeing Cajun's sale.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/02/business/pp-l-unit-acquires-stake-in-british-utility.html?ref=southerncompany">PP&amp;L Unit Acquires Stake in British Utility<date>Published: July 02, 1996</date><text>The Southern Company's international arm said today that it had sold a 25 percent stake in South Western Electricity P.L.C. of Britain for $189 million to the Power Market Development Company, a subsidiary of PP&amp;L Resources Inc. PP&amp;L, whose Pennsylvania Power and Light Company supplies power to residents in eastern Pennsylvania, said in May that it was in talks to acquire a stake in South Western, the British regional electricity company that the Southern Company bought in October for $1.8 billion.Southern noted that several South Western assets had previously had been sold and were not included in this transaction.Based in Bristol, England, South Western Electricity serves about 1.3 million customers in Bristol and in Cornwall, Devon and Somerset counties. The Southern Company supplies power in Georgia, Alabama, Florida and Mississippi. PP&amp;L said the venture would help it learn more about operating in a deregulated business environment since Britain's electricity market was already open to competition. Under the agreement, South Western Electricity will remain in control of day-to-day operations. Power Market Development will have two seats on the nine-member Southern Investments British board and one seat on the five-member South Western board.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/27/business/latest-offer-for-utility-is-1-billion.html?ref=southerncompany">Latest Offer For Utility Is $1 Billion<date>Published: June 27, 1996</date><text>A subsidiary of the Southern Company said yesterday that it would offer $1.04 billion in cash for the nonnuclear power plants of the Cajun Electric Power Cooperative, a Louisiana electric utility.The bid by the Atlanta-based Southern, which is the parent of five electric utilities and also one of the nation's most profitable utilities, is lower than some made this year.Cajun, which serves about one million customers in Louisiana, is being reorganized under Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection, but outsiders are attracted to the company, which has 1,700 megawatts of mostly coal-generating capacity and sells power to 12 rural electric cooperatives.William Tilles, the utility analyst for Smith Barney, said that Cajun's bankruptcy status provided a rare opportunity for other utilities and companies to buy regulated assets without having to deal with management, which currently has little say.Cajun Electric has accumulated debt of $4 billion partly because of its investment in the River Bend nuclear power plant. A Federal agency, the Rural Utilities Service, urged the cooperative to invest in the River Bend plant in the 1980's as an economical way to increase capacity -- and offered Federal financing.After Cajun bought a 30 percent stake in River Bend, the demand for electricity began to stagnate and construction delays and cost overruns made the plant more expensive.The cooperative began to increase its rates to cover the servicing of its debt, but the Louisiana Public Service Commission ordered Cajun to lower rates, which put the cooperative in default on its debt to the Rural Utilities Service. Cajun filed for bankruptcy on Dec. 21, 1994.The Rural Utilities Service and the Louisiana Public Service Commission are still battling in bankruptcy court over who has the right to set rates for Cajun Electric.Mr. Tilles said a final decision on a reorganization plan would be made by Ralph R. Mabey, the court-appointed trustee, Frank J. Polozola, the bankruptcy judge, and Cajun's creditors. Cajun has until Aug. 24 to present its plan.Bidders believe that they can get the assets at a good price and then run them better, Mr. Tilles said. "It extends your reach and your ability to move bulk power," he said.Under Southern's plan, its subsidiary, Southern Electric International, would agree to 25-year contracts to provide all the electricity to the Louisiana cooperatives. Rates would be about one-fifth less than the current wholesale rate of 4.88 cents a kilowatt-hour, the company said.Mr. Mabey has backed a $1.11 billion bid by the Ziegler Coal Holding Company and the Northern States Power Company. A $1.2 billion bid has been filed by Entergy Inc. and the Central and South West Corporation. There is also a $1 billion offer from the Enron Corporation, a natural gas company based in Houston.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/05/03/business/international-business-britain-says-it-will-not-allow-takeovers-2-big-electric.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Britain Says It Will Not Allow Takeovers of 2 Big Electric Utilities<date>Published: May 03, 1996</date><text>The British Government said today that it would not permit takeovers of the nation's two biggest utilities, National Power P.L.C. and Powergen P.L.C., after the Southern Company of Atlanta said it was considering a bid for National Power.The Department of Trade and Industry, one of Prime Minister John Major's Cabinet departments, said in a statement that National Power and Powergen were too important to be allowed to be taken over, at least until the electricity market in England and Wales became more competitive.Its move came a week after the department halted a series of utility takeovers by barring National Power and Powergen, which are power-generating companies, from selling electricity to homes for the first time by acquiring regional suppliers.Today's action presumably ended the chances of Southern to expand its British distribution business with one big acquisition. A bid for National Power could have cost as much as L8 billion -- about $12 billion.David Campbell, a utilities-industry analyst with Greig, Middleton &amp; Company, said: "It means for the two companies that they're bid-proof in the short term. It's difficult to see how the Government can justify this."And Daniele M. Seitz of UBS Securities in New York said the Government's move was a blow to Southern to the extent that "these kind of buying opportunities do not come along every day."Officials at Southern declined to comment. Its shares, selling ex-dividend, fell 12.5 cents today, to close at $21.75 on the New York Stock Exchange.In London, National Power shares fell 34 pence, or 6.1 percent, to L5.25. Powergen shares fell 18 pence, or 3.3 percent, to L5.30.In a statement, National Power said that with the announcement, it expected that Southern would quickly clarify its position. Officials of Powergen declined to comment.The Trade and Industry Department will prevent acquisitions by retaining its "golden shares" in each company, which give it the right to veto any takeover and restrict any shareholder from acquiring more than 15 percent of either company.Without mentioning the Southern Company by name, it said it felt the need to act because of previous mergers in the electricity industry and "the possibility of bids being made for the generators." It said it would consider redeeming the special shares when it decided that there was "adequate competition in the market."</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/27/business/cheap-gas-vs-stiff-upper-lips-so-far-deregulation-is-leaving-most-britons-cold.html?ref=southerncompany">Cheap Gas vs. Stiff Upper Lips;So Far, Deregulation Is Leaving Most Britons Cold<date>Published: April 27, 1996</date><text>You might think that American and other foreign energy companies would have an easy time stealing British Gas's residential customers, now that the Government is ending the giant utility's monopoly on home deliveries of natural gas.After all, British Gas charges more for the fuel than just about any other supplier, and it is widely reviled for its shoddy service and, recently, for the huge compensation package it paid its chief executive.But if that's what you think, you probably haven't met the likes of Mark King, the director of a community center in this southwestern coastal town. "The way I understand it, it's the same pipeline, and gas is gas," said Mr. King, expressing the same kind of consumer befuddlement that greeted competition in the long-distance telephone business in the United States a decade ago. "So how is it I get a bill from any one of 9 or 10 different companies?"Partly because of the confusion, the Government is proceeding cautiously with its free-market experiment, which officially begins April 29 in just three southwestern counties -- Devon, Cornwall and Somerset -- with 500,000 consumers. Deregulation will be expanded to the densely populated southeast in 1997 and to all of Britain in 1998.But the American companies -- Amerada Hess, Texaco and the Southern Company -- are moving aggressively, hoping to glean experience they can apply back home when competition sweeps the utility business there.Already, the barriers to competition for industrial and some commercial customers have come down in the United States, but homeowners are still locked into buying their gas from local utilities, with the price set by state regulators.Scattered experiments are beginning, however, that allow residential customers a choice. Soon, residential customers in Wyoming will be asked to choose a gas company, for example, and last month, the public utility that delivers electricity to portions of Orange and Rockland Counties in New York and Passaic and Bergen Counties in New Jersey proposed a plan to allow 1,500 residents to choose their electricity supplier.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/23/business/international-business-british-utility-parrying-a-bid-by-southern.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS;British Utility Parrying a Bid by Southern<date>Published: April 23, 1996</date><text>National Power P.L.C. sought today to fend off a hostile takeover bid from the Southern Company of Atlanta by agreeing to buy a British utility for L2.5 billion, or $3.78 billion.The acquisition of the utility, Southern Electric, could make National Power too big to swallow. Southern already owns a British utility, South Western Electricity, and Government regulators might balk at the American company's proposed merger with National Power.Southern Company is unlikely to get over the obstacles, not least of which is political," said Nigel Hawkins, utilities analyst at the brokers Yamaichi International.But other analysts noted that Southern's pockets might be deep enough to buy both National and Southern Electric. Southern is the second-largest power generator in the United States.Southern proposed the merger with National last week, contingent on approval of further vertical integration of Britain's electric industry by the Monopolies and Mergers Commission.Southern has not yet suggested financial arrangements for its proposed merger, but it would create one of the world's largest electricity groups.In response to National's bid for Southern Electric, a spokesman for Southern said today that it was still considering such a merger. "I think the original statement still stands," the spokesman said, declining to comment further.The chairman of National Power, John Baker, said last week that his company would be prepared to consider meeting with Southern if it presented a bid with a price, financing and plans.In a statement today, Mr. Baker said the acquisition of Southern Electric would significantly enhance earnings, helping to create scope for a "revised dividend policy involving increased distributions."National Power supplies up to a quarter of Britain's electricity needs and is keen to forge a deal that would give it access to secure demand for its electricity ahead of the liberalization of the supply market in 1998.National Power offered L2.8 billion for Southern Electric last year, but the offer lapsed after the Government said it would review bids by power generators for regional electric companies. Last year's offer, however, included Southern Electric's stake in the National Grid, a distribution network that was jointly owned by all 12 regional utilities before being sold off last year.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/19/business/international-briefs-national-power-rejects-talks-with-southern.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BRIEFS;National Power Rejects Talks With Southern<date>Published: April 19, 1996</date><text>National Power P.L.C., Britain's largest utility, has rejected meeting with the Southern Company to discuss a merger, saying National Power was not for sale and questioning whether the United States company could offer a fair price. The rebuff came in a letter from John Baker, the British company's chairman, to the head of Southern's international unit, Tom Boren. Southern announced on Wednesday that it might bid for National Power.While National Power would consider an offer, Mr. Baker said in his letter that "there is no point" in meeting unless Southern made a compelling offer "in a credible way." Southern, based in Atlanta, had requested a meeting in advance of a formal bid. Bloomberg Business News</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/18/business/international-briefs-southern-seeking-british-power-concern.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BRIEFS;Southern Seeking British Power Concern<date>Published: April 18, 1996</date><text>The Southern Company, the Atlanta-based utility holding company that entered the British electricity market last year by taking over a regional utility, said yesterday it hoped to combine that business with National Power P.L.C., one of Britain's two electricity generators. Southern said it would wait to see whether the British Government would allow combinations of power-generating companies and regional utilities that distribute power.National Power's stock has soared 80 pence in the last two days on the London Stock Exchange, closing at 570 pence yesterday, after rising more than 8 percent Tuesday. But National Power advised shareholders not to sell if they got a bid from Southern. (AP)</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/26/business/international-business-british-utility-to-be-acquired-by-southern-co.html?ref=southerncompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; British Utility To Be Acquired By Southern Co.<date>Published: August 26, 1995</date><text>South Western Electricity P.L.C. today accepted a sweetened $1.7 billion takeover bid from the Southern Company of Atlanta in what would be the first American acquisition of a British electric utility.The accord is part of a wave of merger agreements and takeover offers that is reshaping Britain's power industry. The nation's power distribution and generating business has changed sharply in recent years as a state-owned monopoly was broken up and privatized and the industry was partly deregulated.There are 12 regional power distribution companies, including South Western, and 3 power generation companies.South Western agreed to the deal after Southern raised its offer to $:9.65 ($14.95) a share, from the $:9 a share it offered initially. The terms value South Western at a total of $:1.1 billion, or $1.7 billion. Southern already owns 14.4 percent of South Western.South Western had rejected Southern's initial offer as too low and had been trying to find another bidder. Two weeks ago, South Western said it was in negotiations with another British utility, Southern Electric P.L.C., for a deal of more than $:10 a share. But the talks broke up on the same day they were announced because the companies feared a merger agreement would be blocked by British antitrust regulators.Under the accord announced today, the American company's Southern Electric International subsidiary is to pay $:9 a share in cash plus a net dividend of 65 pence for each South Western share.The dividend, which would be paid to South Western shareholders from that company's cash reserves, is structured to allow some big institutional shareholders, including British pension funds, to claim an additional tax credit of 16 pence a share, bringing the effective price for them to $:9.81 a share.On the London Stock Exchange today, South Western shares rose 38 pence, or 4.2 percent, to $:9.50.Southern, like many other American utilities, has been seeking to diversify internationally. Britain was a logical place for it to look because of the sweeping changes in the domestic power industry.Southern Electric International's chief executive, Thomas G. Boren, said at a news conference today that the American company was interested in further acquisitions in Britain. In particular, he said he was interested in parts of the two biggest power-generating companies, National Power and Power Gen, both of which have been ordered by antitrust regulators to sell some generating capacity.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/23/business/international-briefs-takeover-bid-extended.html?ref=southerncompany">International Briefs; Takeover Bid Extended<date>Published: August 23, 1995</date><text>The Southern Company, the big utility based in Atlanta, said yesterday that it was extending its $1.5 billion takeover bid for South Western Electricity P.L.C. of Britain until Sept. 4. Southern also said it already held about 14.4 percent of the British utility's shares. Southern is offering $:9 (about $13.79) a share for South Western, valuing the regional electricity company at about $:1 billion ($1.53 billion). (Reuters)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/12/business/international-briefs-2-british-utilities-end-takeover-talks.html?ref=southerncompany">International Briefs; 2 British Utilities End Takeover Talks<date>Published: August 12, 1995</date><text>South Western Electricity P.L.C. of Britain said yesterday that it had ended talks to acquire Southern Electric P.L.C., which is the target of a hostile takeover bid by the Southern Company of the United States. South Western Electricity, which like Southern Electric is a regional utility, said regulatory officials had expressed concern about a merger's impact on competition. The negotiations were announced earlier in the day.The Southern Company, a utility company based in Atlanta, has offered $:9, or $14.20, a share for Southern Electric, valuing the entire company at $:1 billion, or $1.6 billion. Before the collapse of yesterday's talks, South Western Electricity had said that its discussions could lead to an offer for Southern Electric of more than $:10 a share. At that price, the company would be valued at $:1.1 billion.Yesterday's developments were the latest in a wave of merger and takeover activity in the British electricity distribution industry.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/29/business/company-news-british-utility-fights-bid-by-southern-company.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; BRITISH UTILITY FIGHTS BID BY SOUTHERN COMPANY<date>Published: July 29, 1995</date><text>South Western Electricity P.L.C., a utility based in Bristol, England, urged its shareholders yesterday to reject an unsolicited takeover bid of $:1 billion, or $1.6 billion, from the Southern Company. In its filing mailed to shareholders, South Western repeated its position that Southern's $:9-a-share offer undervalued the utility. In its message to shareholders, South Western stated that it would soon provide details of its own plans to "enhance shareholder value." While Southern, an Atlanta-based utility, did not rule out a higher bid, a spokesman said that Southern had no plan to raise its bid and was waiting to get shareholder reaction to its offer.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/12/business/company-news-british-utility-rejects-offer-by-southern.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; BRITISH UTILITY REJECTS OFFER BY SOUTHERN<date>Published: July 12, 1995</date><text>The Southern Company of Atlanta held takeover talks with South Western Electricity P.L.C. of Britain and mentioned a price of $:785 million, or about $1.25 billion, but the overture was rejected. Southern disclosed on Monday that it had bought an 11.2 percent stake in South Western Electricity for $170 million. The offer by Southern was the first by an American company for a British utility. South Western said the offer would "significantly undervalue the company." The announcement that talks had broken down was made after the close of trading in London. Earlier, shares of South Western closed at a record of 939 pence, up 29 pence. At that price, acquiring all of South Western's stock would have cost $1.66 billion. On the New York Stock Exchange, shares of Southern were unchanged at $22.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/11/business/company-news-southern-electric-buys-stake-in-a-british-utility.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN ELECTRIC BUYS STAKE IN A BRITISH UTILITY<date>Published: July 11, 1995</date><text>The Southern Company said yesterday that its Southern Electric International unit bought an 11.2 percent stake in South Western Electricity P.L.C., a British utility, for about $170 million. Analysts said Southern, which is based in Atlanta, may be considering a takeover of South Western, which distributes electricity to 2.7 million homes and businesses. The Southern unit bought 12.5 million shares of South Western. A spokesman for Southern would only say that officials from Southern and South Western would meet today in London. Officials at South Western could not be reached for comment. A spokesman for the Pacific Gas and Electric Company in San Francisco, said the utility would consider acquiring South Western if the company put itself up for sale but would probably not make a hostile bid.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/10/25/business/company-news-scott-paper-is-selling-power-plant-in-alabama.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Scott Paper Is Selling Power Plant in Alabama<date>Published: October 25, 1994</date><text>Accelerating a drive to pare down operations outside its consumer-products business, the Scott Paper Company announced plans yesterday to sell a power plant in Mobile, Ala., to a unit of the Southern Company for $350 million.Albert J. Dunlap, Scott's chairman and chief executive, also said he hoped to sell other assets soon, including another power plant, as well as timber and food businesses and real estate. And he announced the possibility of stock buybacks within the next quarter."Six months ago we vowed to put in a new management team, to complete our restructuring and to put on sale all assets that do not fit our core business, and that's what we've done," Mr. Dunlap said yesterday in an interview. "With this money coming in, we will have an enormously strong balance sheet and can begin a stock repurchase plan."He added that Scott would "look very favorably at a stock buyback in the next three months."Investors seemed to endorse the sale announcement; Scott stock rose 12.5 cents, to $62.125, on the New York Stock Exchange."This is another very logical move that will increase shareholder value," said Kathryn McAuley, a stock analyst with Brown Brothers Harriman &amp; Company. She said she thought that $350 million was "a good price" for such a power plant.The sale of the 105-megawatt power plant in Mobile follows Scott's recent sale of S. D. Warren, its coated printing-papers subsidiary, for $1.6 billion to a group headed by Sappi Ltd. of Johannesburg.For Mr. Dunlap, the turnaround specialist who came out of retirement last April to run Scott, the proposed sale was another opportunity to reduce the size of the company, its debt and the diversity of its interests. Scott hopes to realize about $3 billion on the assets to be sold, Mr. Dunlap estimated.Mr. Dunlap said that he had also put up for sale a 45-megawatt steam and electricity plant in Chester, Pa., and Scott's food-service business in the United States and Britain, as well as some of the company's worldwide pulp and paper operation, including 1.5 million acres of forest in the United States and Canada.Pending regulatory approval, the sale of the Mobile plant is expected to close by December. Mr. Dunlap sold the power plant, he said, because "we are not a utility company."He added that he had come to an arrangement with the Southern Company to buy back about 25 percent of the plant's power at market rates to continue its pulp operations in Alabama.The Southern Company is the holding company for regulated utilities in Alabama, Georgia, Mississippi and Florida. A wholly owned subsidiary, Southern Electric International, will operate the Mobile plant and assume employment of 120 Scott employees currently working there.Mr. Dunlap also announced that Scott's corporate headquarters in Philadelphia had been put on the market. Mr. Dunlap has reduced the headquarters staff by 71 percent; remaining employees have moved into three floors in one of the three former headquarters buildings.The chief executive has not decided whether the company will remain in Philadelphia. "We can lease the space we're in, move elsewhere in the area, or go somewhere else," Mr. Dunlap said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/08/business/company-news-utilities-settle-contract-fight.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Utilities Settle Contract Fight<date>Published: November 08, 1991</date><text>The Southern Company and the Gulf States Utilities Company ended a five-year-old contract dispute today that gives Southern cash and stock worth up to $300 million.The utility companies were fighting over Gulf States' halting of payments to Southern in 1986 on an energy sales agreement signed four years earlier.Gulf States, based in Beaumont, Tex., had been buying energy from Southern but said in 1985 that demand had dropped and the electricity was not needed.Southern, the Atlanta-based parent company of five Southeastern utilities, argued that Gulf States was obligated to keep buying the electricity. But Gulf States said the contract required good-faith negotiations whenever changes in purchases were requested.The dispute went to Federal courts and regulatory agencies before the settlement was reached out of court. Gulf States took a $135 million write- off last year to cover its costs in the dispute.Southern is to receive $79 million in cash, 6 million new shares of Gulf States common stock and promissory notes for $160 million in the settlement. The payments to Southern will be made through 1999. Gulf States' Lewis Creek Generating Plant near Willis, Tex., has been pledged as collateral.In trading on the New York Stock Exchange today, Gulf States' stock lost 12.5 cents a share, closing at $9.50. Southern rose $1, to $30.50.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/05/23/business/southern-co-inquiry-ends.html?ref=southerncompany">Southern Co. Inquiry Ends<date>Published: May 23, 1991</date><text>The Southern Company said Tuesday that the Securities and Exchange Commission had closed its investigation of the utility holding company without pressing charges.The agency has been investigating the Atlanta-based company's financial disclosure practices since 1989.Southern's president, Edward L. Addison, announced the end of the investigation at the company's annual meeting. It marked the second time in a year that a long Federal investigation of the company had ended without charges being filed.Last May, the United States Attorney's office in Atlanta said it was closing a 21-month-old tax fraud investigation without filing criminal charges. The office is still investigating other matters, including political contributions and pension fund transactions, according to the Southern Company's annual report. And the Internal Revenue Service is reviewing the company's tax returns from 1983 through 1987.In 1989, Southern's Florida subsidiary, the Gulf Power Company, was fined $500,000 after pleading guilty to conspiracy to make illegal political contributions.Federal officials have refused to comment on the Southern Company investigations. A spokesman for the S.E.C. office in Atlanta, Bill Woodward, said he could not even confirm the existence of an investigation.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1991/01/31/business/company-news-southern-co-unit.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Southern Co. Unit<date>Published: January 31, 1991</date><text>The Swiss-based engineering company, ABB Asea Brown Boveri Ltd., signed a contract for 16 gas turbine generators worth about $300 million with the Southern Company Services Inc. in Birmingham, Ala. The generators will be delivered by ABB Energy Services Inc. in 1993, with service to start the next year at Southern, a unit of the Southern Company in Atlanta. ABB will build the rotating turbine parts in Switzerland and will assemble them at its plant in Virginia.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/12/28/business/company-news-southern-settles-with-gulf-states.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Southern Settles With Gulf States<date>Published: December 28, 1990</date><text>The Southern Company said today that it would receive cash and securities worth $300 million before taxes under a settlement with the Gulf States Utilities Company over power sales contracts.Southern, which serves the Southeast, and Gulf States, serving Texas and Louisiana, said the settlement would end their four-year dispute and that the terms were similar to those of a tentative agreement announced in June.Under the agreement, Southern will receive $75 million in cash, including $68 million that Gulf States accrued in escrow in lieu of payment for energy from Southern, and a promissory note for $160 million that must be paid by Jan. 1, 1999.Southern also said it would get six million shares of Gulf States common stock, to be issued, and that it had agreed to remain a passive holder for the entire period it holds the stock.Southern also said that if the price of the Gulf States stock does not average $18.25 a share in any five consecutive days between the settlement date and Jan. 1, 1993, Gulf States will pay Southern the difference.Gulf States has pledged its Lewis Creek generating plant in eastern Texas as collateral for the settlement.The settlement, which is subject to several contingencies, including approval of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and the Securities and Exchange Commission, will end the contracts and most litigation between the two companies.On the New York Stock Exchange, shares of the Southern Company fell by 25 cents each, to $27.25, while shares of Gulf States slipped 12.5 cents, to $10.125.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/26/business/company-news-southern-settles-contract-dispute.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Southern Settles Contract Dispute<date>Published: June 26, 1990</date><text>The Southern Company said today it had reached a tentative agreement worth $300 million to settle a dispute over an energy sales contract with the Gulf States Utilities Company. The agreement, which is subject to Federal regulatory approval, would end all litigation between Atlanta-based Southern and Gulf States, which is based in Beaumont, Tex.Under the proposed settlement, Southern will receive $75 million in cash, 6 million new shares of Gulf States common stock and a $160 million promissory.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/04/21/business/southern-notes-sec-inquiry.html?ref=southerncompany">Southern Notes S.E.C. Inquiry<date>Published: April 21, 1989</date><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission has begun a formal investigation to determine if the Southern Company filed false and misleading financial reports with the agency, the company says in its annual report. Southern says it believes theS.E.C. investigation is related to the continuing investigation by the Internal Revenue Service and a Federal grand jury into Southern's Federal tax payments.That inquiry involves whether Southern's Georgia Power unit improperly accounted for certain spare parts for its nuclear power plants in a way that gave the company significant tax savings in 1985 and 1986. Southern said that the investigation had expanded to include political contributions and that ''the full scope of the investigation is not currently known.''Georgia Power has denied any wrongdoing.A spokesman for the S.E.C. would neither confirm nor deny the investigation.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/12/08/business/texas-utility-faces-claim.html?ref=southerncompany">Texas Utility Faces Claim<date>Published: December 08, 1988</date><text>The Gulf States Utilities Company disclosed today that the Southern Company had asked a Federal court in Texas to force Gulf States to pay it an estimated $1.1 billion to settle a contract dispute between the two utility holding companies.Gulf States, based in Beaumont, Tex., said that if it lost the litigation, it might be forced to seek protection from its creditors under Federal bankruptcy proceedings. Gulf States made the disclosures in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission.At issue is a contract, signed in 1982, giving Gulf States access to capacity and energy from Southern's coal-fired generating units for 10 years.Gulf States sued Southern in 1986, saying Southern had breached the contract by refusing to bargain to alter its terms. The case went to the Federal Regulatory Commission, which said it found no basis to relieve Gulf States of its contract obligations and said the breach-of-contract issue was up to the courts.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/08/31/business/georgia-power-faces-tax-inquiry.html?ref=southerncompany">Georgia Power Faces Tax Inquiry<date>Published: August 31, 1988</date><text>In an affidavit unsealed today in Federal District Court here, a special agent of the Internal Revenue Service maintained that high-ranking executives of the Georgia Power Company and its parent, the Southern Company, had engaged in a complex six-year plan to evade millions of dollars in corporate taxes.No party has been charged with wrongdoing. At a news conference, Robert L. Barr Jr., the United States Attorney for the Northern District of Georgia, said the affidavit was filed to help obtain warrants to search Georgia Power headquarters and the home of Timothy L. Fallaw, Southern's director of taxes and a former I.R.S. agent.Mr. Barr also said the investigation was but one part of a ''complex and very lengthy investigation'' involving several electric utilities and Arthur Andersen &amp; Company, the accounting firm. $61 Million in Spare Parts In the 33-page affidavit, the I.R.S. special agent, Arthur D. McGovern Jr., contends that the tax evasion occurred from 1982 through 1987. He said Georgia Power improperly accounted for $61 million in spare parts held in inventory.Mr. McGovern said the investigation involved a confidential informant highly placed in Georgia Power's executive hierarchy and secret tape recordings of company meetings.Reacting to the report, Robert W. Scherer, Georgia Power's chairman and chief executive, said at a news conference: ''The information contained in this document, if true, is shocking to me personally and I'm sure very disturbing to all of our employees. Deliberate wrongdoing will not be tolerated at Georgia Power, and I personally will get to the bottom of this matter.''Gale Klappa, a spokesman for Southern, said an internal investigation would extend to employees of the parent company who were involved in tax accounting. 'It Seems Real Sneaky'According to the affidavit, executives of Arthur Andersen, Southern's auditors, participated in meetings at which the tax matters were discussed.The affidavit quotes one Arthur Andersen employee as having told Georgia Power executives: ''This seems awfully sneaky at best - I mean, at worst it seems real sneaky.''</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/08/29/business/inquiry-seen-for-southern.html?ref=southerncompany">Inquiry Seen For Southern<date>Published: August 29, 1988</date><text>The United States Attorney in Atlanta is expected to confirm that the Justice Department is investigating the Southern Company for possible tax fraud. Robert L. Barr Jr., the United States Attorney, said he would comment Monday on reports of the investigation.Late Friday, Robert W. Scherer, the chairman and chief executive of the Georgia Power Company, a division of Southern, acknowledged that Georgia Power's tax accounting practices were being investigated.''There is an implication that some of Georgia Power Company's tax accounting practices are fraudulent,'' Mr. Scherer said. ''Never in my 42 years with this company have I known Georgia Power to do business in such a way. Not knowing what the Justice Department believes it knows, I am not going to stand here and dismiss out of hand the allegations that have been reported.''On Saturday, The Atlanta Journal-Constitution reported that the Oglethorpe Power Corporation, Georgia's second-largest utility company, and the accounting firm of Arthur Andersen &amp; Company were also under investigation.The newspaper quoted unidentified law enforcement sources as saying that the Internal Revenue Service was involved in the investigation.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/11/03/business/company-news-savannah-electric.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Savannah Electric<date>Published: November 03, 1987</date><text>The Southern Company said that its board had agreed to buy the Savannah Electric and Power Company for stock in a deal valued at more than $230 million. Southern said that 1.05 shares of Southern common would be exchanged for each of Savannah Electric's 10.6 million shares. The deal must be approved by the Securities and Exchange Commission and the shareholders of Savannah Electric.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/02/business/company-news-texas-utility-contract-fight.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; Texas Utility Contract Fight<date>Published: May 02, 1987</date><text>A Federal regulatory agency is backing the Southern Company in its fight to force a Texas utility to honor a contract worth $900 million.The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission filed briefs last month with an administrative law judge who is reviewing the Gulf States Utilities Company's attempt to void the contract, which calls for it to buy more than $100 million worth of electricity annually through 1992 from the Atlanta-based utility holding company. Financially pressed GulfStates says it no longer needs the electricity and cannot afford it. Utility commissions in Texas and Louisiana have refused to allow Gulf States to collect money from its rate payers to pay for the River Bend nuclear plant in Louisiana. The Southern Company is trying to recover $100 million for power already supplied.In a 100-page brief filed April 15, the commission's staff said Gulf State's reasons for voiding or modifying the power agreement ''are not supported by the record'' and the contract itself is ''not unjust, unreasonable or unduly discriminatory under prevailing legal standards.''A Southern Company spokesman, Bob Dawson in Birmingham, Ala., said an administrative law judge, Michel Levant, was expected to issue his ruling on the dispute May 17.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/03/10/business/company-news-southern-co.html?ref=southerncompany">COMPANY NEWS; SOUTHERN CO.<date>Published: March 10, 1987</date><text>The Southern Company said it would take an after-tax charge of $226 million against earnings no later than January 1988 because the projected cost of the Vogtle nuclear power plant had risen above the amount that retail customers in Georgia would be asked to pay. The company's largest subsidiary, the Georgia Power Company, said the budget for the plant had increased by 6.3 percent, or $522 million, to $8.87 billion. However, because of a pledge the company made to state regulators last year, the increased cost will not be included in the utility's retail electric rates.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1984/08/16/business/georgia-power-raises-plant-cost.html?ref=southerncompany">Georgia Power Raises Plant Cost<date>Published: August 16, 1984</date><text>ATLANTA, Aug. 15— The Southern Company's Georgia Power Company subsidiary said it was raising the projected construction cost of the Vogtle nuclear power plant about 9 percent, to $7.2 billion, from $6.6 billion. Georgia Power, which has a 45.7 percent interest in the plant, said its share of the increase came to about $240 million. The rise was attributed to higher engineering costs and below-target productivity. Georgia Power also said it had decided to cut or defer $640 million of construction projects and to establish a $250 million construction reserve to cover interest, inflation and other possible cost increases. It said the net effect of the actions would be a cut in its construction spending of about $150 million during the balance of the Vogtle project. Georgia Power said the plant, near Waynesboro, was 61 percent completed.</text></article></page><page index="10" /></root>
