<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Texas Instruments"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/25/technology/Texas-Instruments-Expects-Lower-Sales-in-Fourth-Quarter.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Expects Lower Sales in Fourth Quarter<date>Published: October 24, 2011</date><text>Texas Instruments, the maker of analog semiconductors, forecast lower fourth-quarter sales than some analysts had estimated, indicating that demand for electronic components remained sluggish. Revenue will be $3.26 billion to $3.54 billion in the period, the company said in a statement on Monday. Doug Freedman, an analyst at RBC Capital Markets, had estimated $3.57 billion for the period. This is the first quarter that Texas Instruments is including its acquisition of National Semiconductor acquisition in the forecasts. Texas Instruments’ stock declined 30 cents, to $31.39 in after-hours trading. Profit in the fourth quarter, including costs related to the acquisition of National Semiconductor, will be 28 cents to 36 cents a share, the company said. “Economic uncertainty continues to weigh on demand in almost every major market segment in which we operate,” Richard K. Templeton, the company’s chief executive, said in the statement. Third-quarter profit fell to $601 million, or 51 cents a share, from $859 million, or 71 cents, a year earlier. Revenue declined 7.3 percent to $3.47 billion. On Sept. 8, Texas Instruments said profit in the third quarter would be 56 to 60 cents a share on sales of $3.23 billion to $3.37 billion, citing a slump across its product lines.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/09/12/finding-the-next-netlogic/?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Finding the Next NetLogic<date>September 12, 2011, 1:07 pm</date><text>Broadcom is opening its wallet wide — to the tune of $3.7 billion — to acquire NetLogic, a maker of advanced chips for routers. The transaction, Broadcom’s biggest to date, will give NetLogic’s shareholders a 57 percent premium to the company’s closing price on Friday. Now, analysts are wondering, who’s next? On Monday, several chip makers rose following news of the deal. Shares of Cavium, one of NetLogic’s closest rivals, rose about 5 percent in afternoon trading. Meanwhile, EZchip Semiconductor jumped about 9 percent. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Broadcom to Buy NetLogic for $3.7 Billion Momentum for the market has been building, as the world’s data needs surge. As more consumers buy smart phones and spend more hours scanning the Web, the companies that help build the pipelines of the communications industry are becoming increasingly important. NetLogic, for instance, designs the processors that are built into the routers, created by companies like Cisco and Shenzhen, China-based Huawei. NetLogic, analysts say, was able to command a high premium because of its patent portfolio and the technological complexity of its products. If Broadcom tried to build a similar suite from scratch, its team would need five, potentially more, years according to Cody Acree, a Williams Financial analyst. “All of these companies, whether NetLogic, or Cavium or EZchip have been primary candidates for acquisitions,” said Mr. Acree. “Its such a fast growing, technically challenging space, and its very difficult to get in on your own.” According to analysts, Broadcom was likely interested in both NetLogic and Cavium, which also makes semiconductor processors for routers. Earlier this year, Cavium recorded sales of $71.6 million for the second quarter, a 12.7 percent increase from the year ago period. It also reported profit of $1.9 million. For comparison, NetLogic posted revenue of $103.7 million and a loss of $35.2 million for the period. EZchip, an Israeli-chip maker operates in the same space as NetLogic, but its high-speed processors serve different functions on the router. It does, however, serve many of the same customers, including Chinese chip makers Huawei and ZTE. According to analysts, large chip-makers like Marvell Technology, which has a considerable presence in the communications infrastructure market, Altera, and Texas Instruments, could be among the suitors. However, Dan Berenbaum, a MKM Partners analyst, says Texas Instruments may have a muted appetite in the near term, since it is still digesting its acquisition of National Semiconductor and has been very focused on its analog portfolio.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/26/business/texas-instruments-misses-forecasts.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Misses Forecasts<date>Published: July 25, 2011</date><text>Texas Instruments, the chip maker, reported a decline in second-quarter income and forecast a third-quarter profit that fell short of analysts’ estimates. The company cited sluggish demand for consumer devices. Second-quarter net income declined to $672 million, or 56 cents a share, compared with $769 million, or 62 cents, in the same period a year earlier, the company said in the statement. Sales fell 1 percent to $3.46 billion. Profit in the next quarter will be 55 to 65 cents a share, the company said. The midpoint of that range missed the 64 cents predicted on average by analysts, according to data compiled by Bloomberg. Texas Instruments gets most of its revenue from analog chips, semiconductors that are important components in a wide variety of products, including military hardware and digital picture frames. Slow consumer spending has hurt the industry, said Tore Svanberg, an analyst at Stifel Nicolaus &amp; Company. And now businesses are threatening to cut expenditures as well, he said. “Consumer is not where it should be, and enterprise spending is starting to fade a bit,” said Mr. Svanberg, who recommends buying Texas Instruments shares on its long-term growth prospects. “C.E.O.’s of chip companies think this is a one-quarter correction. We’re taking a more conservative view.” Texas Instruments fell 31 cents, to $31.47, on Monday in regular trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Third-quarter sales will be $3.4 billion to $3.7 billion, the company said. Analysts had projected $3.61 billion. “Production at some computing and consumer manufacturers appears lukewarm even though we’re heading into the back-to-school and holiday seasons,” said Richard K. Templeton, the company’s chief executive.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/09/technology/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Lowers Quarterly Profit Estimate<date>Published: June 8, 2011</date><text>Texas Instruments cut its earnings and revenue forecasts on Wednesday and blamed the shortfall on loss of business at a major wireless customer. The company warned in April that revenue from wireless baseband chips, the main chip in cellphones, had been hurt by weak sales at one customer, which it did not name. T.I.’s biggest baseband client is Nokia, which has had a tough time competing in advanced phones. Last week, Nokia, which once dominated the global market but has since been eclipsed by the likes of Apple, warned that phone sales in the second quarter would come in sharply below forecast. “The reductions are due to lower demand from a single wireless customer where most of our sales are baseband products,” said Ron Slaymaker, head of investor relations. The lowered quarterly results outlook comes as the chip maker continues to recover from earthquake-related production disruptions in Japan. Texas Instruments forecast second-quarter revenue of $3.36 billion to $3.50 billion, well below Wall Street expectations for $3.55 billion, according to Thomson Reuters. Analyst estimates were at the mid-point of T.I.’s previous target range for the quarter. The company also cut its earnings forecast to 51 cents to 55 cents a share, compared with its previous target of 52 cents to 60 cents a share. Analysts had expected earnings of 57 cents a share — a penny above the midpoint of the previous target announced in April. In April, Texas Instruments warned of slower-than-normal sales growth as Japan’s earthquake damage continued to disrupt supply and production, adding that it could not say when supplies would recover fully. The company, which plans to buy National Semiconductor to shore up its position in analog chips, also took a hit to its bottom-line from expenses related to recovering from the aftermath of the quake in Japan.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/12/technology/personaltech/12smart.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">New and Better Apps Help Students Study for SAT<date>Published: May 11, 2011</date><text>Teenagers have a hard time paying attention to anything that’s not flashed across a smartphone screen. Yet somehow, parents still expect results when they plop an SAT study book in front of their children.Note to parents: Meet your children halfway. Apps that help teenagers study for the SAT (or, for those not living on either coast, the ACT) are improving, as traditional test-prep businesses like Princeton Review and Kaplan refine their mobile software to compete with start-ups. Several to consider on this front include Princeton Review’s SAT Score Quest for iPad (free) and SAT Vocab Challenge for iPhone ($5), Kaplan SAT Flashcubes (free) and SAT Connect ($10 for Apple). For math, Adapster ($10 on Apple) is designed nicely. Android users, as usual, have fewer choices, since the best-known test-prep companies haven’t yet built apps for these devices. But Flash of Genius: SAT Vocab ($1 Android, free on Apple) has earned good marks from users, as has ACT/SAT Math Booster (Free, Android). For those looking to sample the wares, the category’s best entry point is Kaplan’s SAT Flashcubes, which are tailored to the verbal part of the SAT. Presumably, this could also help ACT students. It’s easy to use, and the app’s interactive features make it a lot more fun to study than a static book. Flashcubes will quiz users on hundreds of vocabulary words, using interactive 3-D cubes. The front presents the word, and if you flip the cube, it shows the definition. Other sides of the cube show synonyms, or a sentence that uses the word. The app tracks the student’s performance, so users can watch their progress over time, and it stores a list of incorrect responses so users can test themselves on those words only if they wish. SAT Vocab Challenge offers a gamelike format, with four games in each round — covering antonyms, synonyms, connotation and definitions — and 20 words per game. The fastest answers gain and lose the most points. Some of the app’s most puzzling moments do not come from the tests. I tried one round of all four categories (thankfully, I aced them). When I clicked to the game stats page, to view my average response time, the page had no data to offer about the quizzes. When I returned to the main page, it told me I hadn’t yet mastered a single word. Vocab Challenge comes in two volumes, with each covering 250 words. Princeton Review’s SAT Score Quest for iPad is much less fun, but more helpful. It offers abbreviated practice tests for each of the SAT’s three elements — math, writing and critical reading. The tests help users diagnose possible areas of weakness, but they also offer instruction. Each question includes a tutorial on the logic behind the correct answer, and a strategy for eliminating incorrect responses. SAT Connect also includes review materials as well as quizzes and diagnostic tests, and offers explanations of more than 800 questions. But SAT Connect boasts some elements that other apps lack, like a much longer list of vocabulary words (4,000), and the ability to compare a user’s test scores against those of others who use the app. Users who complete the five sample tests in the app can buy two additional tests for $2 each. SAT Connect has earned good reviews from users even at its initial price of $25. According to a company spokesman, Andrew Fisher, the current $10 price will remain in place at least until the end of the month. Adapster, which is exclusively for math, is among the few highly rated apps in this category for both Apple and Android. As the name implies, the software adapts to the user’s needs over time. Users can take a diagnostic test to help Adapster tailor future tests to the user’s needs, or skip that step and the app will change every new test to account for the student’s performance on the previous one. ACT/SAT Math Booster is another interesting one for Android users who bring a Texas Instruments TI-83 or TI-84 calculator into the test. The calculators can be programmed to include shortcuts for complex equations like the quadratic formula, and Math Booster offers step-by-step instructions for doing so. The app is from the Advantage Point Test Group, an SAT prep company. A company spokeswoman, Devorah Goldblatt, said the programs are “completely within the boundaries of both ACT and SAT” guidelines, and a section on the Web site of the College Board, which administers the tests, supports her assertion. For Android users who are looking for vocabulary help, Flash of Genius is probably their best bet. It’s not as good as the other vocabulary apps on Apple, because it relies on you to tell the software that you know a word’s definition. Users who overestimate their mastery of a particular word will suffer later as a result. As a free app on iTunes, in other words, it’s not worth your time to download. But for $1 on Android, it may be as good as you can get, until the industry leaders work their way over to the other side of the street. Quick Calls Jazz fans will appreciate An Evening With Dave Grusin ($10 on iPad), which includes hours of video and more than 300 pages of content about the landmark 2009 performance of the jazz artist Dave Grusin with the Henry Mancini Institute Orchestra in Miami. ... The Apple version of Kayak (free), for travelers, recently had a big upgrade. It now allows users to book hotels from within the app, rather than being shuttled off to a hotelier’s mobile Web site. ... Google Docs has a new, dedicated Android app. Users can view, create, edit and upload files.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/19/technology/19chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Quake Damage at Texas Instruments Plant Affects Income<date>Published: April 18, 2011</date><text>DALLAS (AP) — The chip maker Texas Instruments said Monday that production setbacks linked to the March 11 earthquake and tsunami in Japan curbed its first-quarter net income and would cut into second-quarter growth. Richard K. Templeton, the Texas Instruments chief executive, said that the quarter started strong, but the Japan earthquake damaged two of its factories in the country and disrupted local demand. He said that one of the company’s Japanese factories would soon be back in full production and that he expected the second factory damaged by the quake to be running at full speed in July, as predicted. But many of the company’s Japanese customers are still working on reopening their factories, which could result in supply chain issues. “We expect growth in the second quarter, though it will be pressured by the situation in Japan. Provided consumer and enterprise demand remain strong, we expect a good second half of the year,” Mr. Templeton said. For the quarter, Texas Instruments earned $666 million, or 55 cents a share, compared with $658 million, or 52 cents a share, in the first quarter of 2010. The company said repercussions from the quake trimmed $30 million, or 2 cents a share, from results. Revenue rose 6 percent, to $3.39 billion. On average, analysts had expected earnings of 58 cents a share on nearly $3.40 billion in revenue, according to FactSet. Revenue from T.I.’s analog chip unit rose 12 percent, to $1.54 billion. Revenue from its wireless chip unit fell 8 percent, to $658 million, partly because of “substantially weaker demand” for wireless baseband chips. Shares of Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas, fell 54 cents, to $34.25, in after-hours trading. They fell 20 cents in regular trading, to $34.79.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/04/07/deals-creep-back-though-not-yet-to-the-mega-level/?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Deals Creep Back, Though Not Yet to the Mega Level<date>April 7, 2011, 12:01 am</date><text>Bigger deals are back. Despite a series of potential shocks to the global economy, deal makers just completed their strongest quarter since before the financial crisis. And with that robust start, capped by AT&amp;T’s $39 billion bid for T-Mobile USA, many bankers are hopeful that the revival will pick up speed. As if to confirm that, another batch of deals was announced just after the quarter ended on March 31, including Vivendi’s $11.3 billion buyout of Vodafone’s stake in SFR of France, an $11.3 billion rival bid for NYSE Euronext by the Nasdaq OMX Group and IntercontinentalExchange, and Texas Instruments’ $6.5 billion takeover of National Semiconductor. The dollar volume of mergers struck in the first quarter jumped 54.7 percent from the comparable period a year eariler, to $799.8 billion, according to data from Thomson Reuters. The overall number of deals fell about 5 percent, to 9,600, Thomson Reuters said. But the real story lay in the number of deals over $5 billion, which made up a little more than 41 percent of all mergers in the quarter. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links  Video: The Dot-com Boom, Then and Now  Graphic: The Silicon Valley Money Network  Graphic: Deal Mashup Word Cloud Special Section: Wall Street and the New Web Boom “With regards to the size and types of transactions, more is being permitted now by shareholders than we’ve seen in a while,” said Paul Parker, Barclays Capital’s head of global mergers and acquisitions. North America still has the largest slice of the deal-making pie for the quarter, accounting for $408.3 billion worth of mergers, or about 51 percent. But deals in emerging markets grew to about a quarter of the total, at $196.3 billion. Buyers from rising industrial powers, including China, India and Brazil, are likely to continue looking beyond their borders for natural resources. This week, Minmetals Resources, a publicly traded unit of a Chinese state-owned mining company, offered $6.5 billion for Equinox Minerals of Canada in an effort to buy a major producer of copper. By many measures, the ingredients for deal-making remain in place. The stock markets have largely shrugged off unforeseen events like the market flash crash of last May and the Japanese earthquake and tsunami of last month, helping to establish a steady line for stock prices. Companies remain flush with cash that they began stockpiling in late 2008; some $1.9 trillion is in American corporate coffers, according to the Federal Reserve. (Most of that cash is being held abroad, however, and for tax reasons companies may choose not to spend it on deals in the United States.) The New York Times Management teams have shown more confidence in pursuing new avenues of growth that complement their existing businesses, although several conglomerates — among them Sara Lee, ITT and Fortune Brands — have chosen to break themselves into parts to focus on a few operations. “Strategic acquirers are reinforcing their core business,” Antonio Weiss, the global head of investment banking at Lazard, said at the Tulane Corporate Law Institute last week. “You don’t see a lot of diversifying transactions.” Another measure of growing corporate confidence is the unsolicited or hostile deal. Like Nasdaq and ICE in their bid for NYSE, or Valeant Pharmaceuticals International in its $5.7 billion hostile bid for Cephalon, rebuffed suitors have shown a willingness to mount a fight and press forward, hoping to find shareholders willing to sell. Cheap financing remains widely available as interest rates stay near record lows, and debt investors continue to buy up riskier loans and bonds in pursuit of better yields. Nowhere was this clearer than in JPMorgan Chase’s $20 billion loan to AT&amp;T to help it finance its T-Mobile deal. It was the largest loan ever by a single originating bank. But JPMorgan was also confident that it could quickly sell off pieces to other banks to help lower the risk on its own books, and it syndicated the loan in a matter of days. The New York Times The preponderance of cheap debt has also supported buyout firms, which struck $51.4 billion worth of deals during the first quarter. Deal makers are still breathlessly awaiting the return of megabuyouts over $10 billion — a level not attained since the Blackstone Group’s $25 billion takeover of Hilton Hotels nearly four years ago. Buyout firms have been getting closer: Blackstone spent $9.4 billion to acquire the American assets of Centro Properties in February. This week, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts agreed to buy Pfizer’s capsule-making business for $2.4 billion, while Apax Partners agreed to buy two software companies for about $2 billion. More private equity deals are likely to be in the offing. K.K.R. executives told public investors last month that the firm had more than $11 billion in untapped capital to spend on buyouts. “That is incredible capital to take advantage of the opportunities we see in private equity around the globe,” Alexander Navab, the firm’s co-head of North American private equity, said at a meeting with investors last month. But the pace of their deals may be slowed if strategic buyers fully re-emerge as competitors. During the buyout boom, private equity firms were often the only bidders in big auctions. The uptick in announced deals has also benefited the bankers who put them together. Fees from mergers and acquisitions grew 3.3 percent in the first quarter from the same time last year, to $7.1 billion. That accounted for about a third of all investment banking fees for the quarter, according to Thomson Reuters. But the sunny outlook is not without some clouds. While continued unrest in the Middle East has not yet dented the pace of deal-making, advisers caution that the uprisings may spread. Rising prices of commodities like oil and cotton could also weigh on corporate profits, making companies more hesitant to spend. And the European sovereign debt crisis, which has hung over the Continent for more than a year, may again resurface as a serious threat to corporate confidence. Deal makers almost universally profess to seeing a continued increase in deal-making, but a gradual one, with no sharp jumps in volume and numbers. So far, they say, their backlogs of pending transactions appear to bear that out. “People are upbeat, and while it gets sometimes overused, ‘cautiously optimistic’ is a great description,” said Robert E. Spatt, a partner at the law firm Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett. The New York TimesSource: Thomson Reuters The New York TimesSource: Thomson Reuters</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/04/07/the-valleys-banker-returns-to-the-top/?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">The Valley's Banker Returns to the Top<date>April 7, 2011, 12:38 am</date><text>Illustration by Quickhoney Frank Quattrone never shied away from the spotlight a decade ago. Now, Silicon Valley’s star banker tries to stay behind the deal-making scenes. “I’d really prefer you didn’t write about me,” Mr. Quattrone said recently, trying to dissuade me from this column. But it is hard to ignore Mr. Quattrone. In the last year, his boutique advisory firm, Qatalyst Partners, has been involved in nearly every major technology merger. As Hewlett-Packard and Dell battled over 3Par last summer, Mr. Quattrone was calling the shots. He orchestrated the sale of Palm to H.P. for $1.2 billion in April 2010. And Texas Instruments’ $6.5 billion deal to buy National Semiconductor this week? Yes, that was his deal, too. His three-year-old firm — which has just 30 employees, including the administrative staff — is challenging Goldman Sachs, Morgan Stanley and other top investment banks for the industry’s most lucrative deals. Qatalyst ranks No. 3, behind Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, on technology deals worth more than $1 billion so far this year, according to Thomson Reuters, besting the likes of JPMorgan Chase and Citigroup. “What Steve Jobs is to technology products, Frank Quattrone is to tech banking. The best there ever was — period,” Roger McNamee, the veteran venture capitalist who is an investor in Facebook, said without betraying any sense of hyperbole. Mr. Quattrone’s is a story of redemption. His career was sidelined for four years as he fought obstruction of justice charges. After an appeals court overturned his conviction, the government dropped the case. In Silicon Valley, the period is often described as Mr. Quattrone’s “intermission.” Video: The Dot-com Boom, Then and Now. The experience humbled Mr. Quattrone — or at least toned down his showmanship. Back in the dot-com boom, when he worked at Credit Suisse First Boston, Mr. Quattrone sent a live mule to the office of a prospective client who had complained about being “dragged around to meetings” like a pack animal. The note attached read: “Stop feeling like a mule and pick CSFB.” Mr. Quattrone landed the business. Graphic: Click for a fuller picture of the Silicon Valley money network Today, he has traded his over-the-top gestures for a kind of quiet resolve, rarely conducting interviews or trying to bring attention to himself. “The story isn’t about Qatalyst,” he said. “This story is about the great technology companies we are privileged to advise.” DealBook Column View all posts Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links  Graphic: Deal Mashup Word Cloud Special Section: Wall Street and the New Web Boom That is the kind of self-serving remark I would normally discount. But Mr. Quattrone believes it. He longs for the day when profiles of him will focus on his current successes without dredging up his past legal challenges. Before Mr. Quattrone started Qatalyst, there were questions about whether he would be able to resurrect his career. East Coast bankers and executives thought corporate boards would snub his services out of fear of risking their reputations. But Silicon Valley stalwarts have stood by him. Dave Roux, the co-founder of Silver Lake Partners and the former executive vice president of Oracle, portrays Mr. Quattrone as a man who was “persecuted by the government and temporarily dethroned” and who is “now more popular than ever.” It’s rare to hear clients talk about their banker so effusively, but Mr. Quattrone is one of the bankers who helped build the modern-day Silicon Valley, taking companies like Cisco and Amazon.com public in the 1990s. He can talk about semiconductors with the same fluency as deal premiums. “Most people in Silicon Valley did not see the justice in the way he was treated by the government,” said Eric E. Schmidt, Google’s chairman. “When he became available again, it was easy for his deep relationships to kick back in.” Google was one of Qatalyst’s first clients. In 2008, Mr. Quattrone helped the search engine giant sort out its stance on Microsoft’s bid for Yahoo, a deal that never came to fruition. “His recent successes are a repudiation of his critics who saw him as over and finished,” Mr. Schmidt said. “He must be smiling every day.” That is not to say that Mr. Quattrone does not have detractors. The catty world of Wall Street has a lot to say about him, albeit rarely on the record. While rival bankers have a grudging respect for Mr. Quattrone, some question whether a number of his recent successful deals have had to do more with luck than talent. Mr. Quattrone negotiated the sale of 3Par to Dell for $18 a share, an 86.5 percent premium. But after the deal was announced, Hewlett-Packard re-emerged as a potential suitor, pushing the price even higher. Eventually, H.P. bought the storage maker for $33 a share. Since then, Mr. Quattrone has become known as the go-to guy for sellers looking to command sky-high prices. Texas Instruments paid a 78 percent premium for National Semiconductor, which was advised by Qatalyst. Unlike other boutique banks with ambitions to one day go public, Mr. Quattrone seems content with a small, old-school partnership. Last year, he hired his former partner and close friend George Boutros from Credit Suisse, and he has populated his firm with many of his closest colleagues from his days in the 1990s when he ran a sprawling technology banking empire. Mr. Roux said the mystique around Mr. Quattrone had been overblown. It’s simple, he said: “Frank’s a very likable guy who knows what he’s talking about.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/05/technology/texas-instruments-to-buy-national-semiconductor.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments to Buy National Semiconductor<date>Published: April 4, 2011</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO — Texas Instruments said Monday that it planned to acquire National Semiconductor for $6.5 billion in a deal that places a big bet on the increasing need to translate the physical world of humans into the digital form of computers and then back again.Both companies specialize in making “analog” processors, a particular kind of computer chip that converts data from the real world — temperature, light intensity, dust concentrations, shifting magnetic fields — into digital data that a computer can interpret and then back again, if need be, into visual or aural information that a human can understand. Such chips are critical components in devices like cameras and phones, but they are crucial in a host of other electronic devices and sensors used in industry and medicine. They are frequently custom designed and carry high profit margins compared with commodity computer chips. Demand for the chips has grown as the number of devices needing sensors has grown. Under terms of the deal, Texas Instruments has agreed to pay $25 a share for National Semiconductor. That is more than a 77 percent premium for National, whose share price closed at $14.07 just before the announcement. In after-hours trading, National’s shares rose almost 73 percent, to $24.30. Texas Instruments shares lost 1.55 percent after hours, to $33.58. Texas Instruments said it expected to finance the deal by borrowing $3 billion to $4 billion and paying the rest in cash. The deal would make Texas Instruments the world’s third-largest semiconductor maker, after Intel and Samsung Electronics. Richard K. Templeton, the chief executive of Texas Instruments, said he believed that the deal would repay shareholders in three to four years by creating accelerated sales growth. And while such multibillion-dollar mergers are often justified on the grounds of cost savings that may come through layoffs or other consolidation, Mr. Templeton said the bigger emphasis in this case was to use a combined sales force to push the product portfolios of both companies. “This acquisition is about strength and growth,” Mr. Templeton said in a press release announcing the deal. He also said the companies could save around $100 million a year in administrative costs. In a conference call with investors, executives from the two companies faced immediate questions on two fronts: whether the companies have too much overlap in their product lines and whether the deal might face antitrust issues. Texas Instruments now sells about 14 percent of the chip industry’s analog chips, while National sells about 3 percent of that market. Texas Instruments has around 30,000 analog products, while National has around 12,000. “There is a certain amount of, how do I say this gently, duplication of products,” said Will Strauss, a chip industry analyst with the Forward Concepts Company, which follows the analog chip market. He said that, in light of such redundancies, he and other analysts he talked to were shocked by the deal. Mr. Templeton deflected such concerns by telling analysts that the product lines differ more than it may appear at first glance. For instance, he said that both companies have strength in analog communications chips but that National’s focus is on making such chips for industrial applications, while Texas Instruments has focused on the consumer market. In the conference call with investors, Mr. Templeton was asked how many of the product lines were redundant and he answered: “The intent is none.” He argued that National Semiconductor’s engineers would continue to be able to work independently in coming up with new product lines but would enjoy the benefits of having them sold by the much-larger combined sales force. “The combined sales team will be 10 times larger than National’s is today,” he said in a statement. Steve Ohr, a chip industry analyst with Gartner, said he did not accept that the two companies had no or few redundant product lines. “I don’t buy it. I simply don’t,” he said. But he said he did not doubt that the combination of the companies would lead to increased sales. “If you take T.I.’s sales staff and give them more products to sell, obviously you’re going to see more revenue.” Mr. Templeton also said that the companies were not likely to face antitrust problems in part because of what he said were the differences in their product lines. Still, the companies said they expected it could take six to nine months for the deal to close because they must obtain regulatory approval not just in the United States but in several overseas markets.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/25/business/25chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Narrowly Beats Forecasts<date>Published: January 24, 2011</date><text>Texas Instruments, the chip maker, posted fourth-quarter results on Monday that narrowly surpassed forecasts, and the company said it was past a “short and shallow downturn” that hit in the second half of 2010.The company said it earned $942 million, or 78 cents a share, in the quarter, up from $655 million, or 52 cents a share, a year earlier. The most recent period included 14 cents a share in one-time gains from the sale of a product line and a tax benefit. Excluding those, earnings beat the average estimate of analysts polled by FactSet by 1 cent a share. Revenue rose 17 percent to $3.53 billion, up from $3.0 billion last year and beating the analysts’ forecast of $3.51 billion. For much of last year, the company’s results reflected a rebound from the recession. Then, in October, the company warned that the market was weakening, and that its outlook for 2011 was cautious. Demand for chips for laptop computers, hard disk drives and televisions started to look poor, while chips for video games and smartphones stayed in strong demand. But on Monday, the chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, said the fall’s downturn looked “mostly complete.” The company used it to replenish its inventories and return product lead-times to normal, he said. For the first quarter, Texas Instruments projected a revenue range of $3.27 billion to $3.55 billion and net income of 54 cents to 62 cents a share. Analysts had forecast revenue of $3.34 billion and net income of 58 cents. The company, based in Dallas, reported its results after the close of market trading. Its stock rose 74 cents, to $34.65 a share, during the trading session but fell by about 2 percent in after-hours trading.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/26/technology/26chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit and Revenue Rise at Texas Instruments<date>Published: October 25, 2010</date><text>Texas Instruments said its fourth-quarter revenue would be hurt by slowing demand for chips for computers and televisions, even as its third-quarter revenue beat Wall Street forecasts. The company, which makes chips used in products like cars and cellphones, said strong demand from industrial customers was offset by weak chip sales for consumer products. Its chief financial officer, Kevin March, said consumer chip weakness would persist this quarter. “I wouldn’t be surprised if we’re looking at a couple of quarters of correction,” Mr. March said, referring to the second half of the year. Texas Instruments posted a third-quarter profit of $859 million, or 71 cents a share, up from $538 million, or 42 cents a share, in the year-ago quarter. Revenue rose to $3.74 billion from $2.88 billion, compared with analysts’ expectations for $3.69 billion according to Thomson Reuters.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/20/technology/20chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit Almost Triples for Texas Instruments<date>Published: July 19, 2010</date><text>Texas Instruments said Tuesday that its second-quarter profit nearly tripled from the year-earlier period, but its revenue fell short of Wall Street forecasts. The company said results in the current quarter could be better than Wall Street expectations, but the chief financial officer, Kevin March, said revenue in the second quarter was hurt because one customer ordered fewer chips than expected. “They did not pull the inventory we’d expected in the quarter,” Mr. March said, without identifying the customer. Stock in Texas Instruments, which makes chips for a broad range of consumer and commercial products, rose 78 cents, or 3.15 percent, to close at $25.55 on Monday, but fell nearly 5 percent, to $24.30, in after-hours trading. The company said profit rose to $769 million, or 62 cents a share, from $260 million, or 20 cents a share a year earlier. Revenue rose to $3.50 billion from $2.46 billion, but fell short of the $3.52 billion analysts forecast. The company forecast third-quarter earnings of 64 cents to 74 cents a share on revenue of $3.55 billion to $3.85 billion. Analysts, on average, were expecting earnings of 64 cents a share on revenue of $3.6 billion. Mr. March said the company expected broad-based strength in demand to push up revenue and earnings in the third quarter.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/09/technology/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Bolsters Forecast<date>Published: June 8, 2010</date><text>Texas Instruments said on Tuesday that its sales and profit would be at the upper end of earlier forecasts, buoyed by demand for industrial machinery. Second-quarter profit will be 60 to 64 cents a share on sales of at least $3.45 billion, the company said in a statement. That compares with April predictions of 56 to 64 cents a share on revenue of at least $3.31 billion. Texas Instruments, based in Dallas, is the biggest producer of analog chips, which go in things as varied as automobiles and digital cameras, making its earnings an indicator of demand for electronics. The company has struggled to keep up with orders, limiting its ability to increase earnings. It is now better able to increase output, said Tristan Gerra, an analyst for Robert W. Baird &amp; Company. “For the first time in several quarters, they’ve been able to address their supply issues,” said Mr. Gerra, who is based in Milwaukee, and has an outperform rating on the stock and does not own it. “There is a catch-up effect from the first quarter.” Analysts estimated second-quarter profit of 61 cents a share and revenue of $3.47 billion on average. Shares of Texas Instruments rose slightly in after-hours trading after the report. The shares closed at $23.88, up 21 cents. “We are seeing some pretty broad-based strength,” a company vice president, Ron Slaymaker, said on a conference call. He played down concerns that European demand was slowing.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/04/business/04shares.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Some C.E.O.’s Strike Gold in Stock Options<date>Published: April 3, 2010</date><text>WERE they smart, or just lucky?As the stock market dived in late 2008 and early 2009, chief executives of the biggest American companies received their annual grants of stock and options, and the timing couldn’t have been better. The subsequent rally has benefited nearly all investors, but for a select group of C.E.O.’s who were fortunate enough to get options, it has created a windfall. And while much of the attention has focused on the pay for executives at banks, a sector that enjoyed a back-from-the-dead performance last year, many of the biggest winners from options were C.E.O.’s at nonfinancial companies. Some executives on the top rungs of corporate America, including Alan Mulally of Ford Motor, Howard Schultz of Starbucks and Andrew Liveris of Dow Chemical, have seen the value of their 2009 options packages double, triple and quadruple — and, in Mr. Mulally’s case, jump nearly 10 times in value, to more than $50 million. In most cases, they can’t cash in now: options typically take three to four years to fully vest. But the gains have set off renewed criticism that C.E.O. compensation is out of control, especially in a year plagued by the recession and high unemployment. “You’re going to see big numbers and people are going to squawk about it, as they should,” said Charles M. Elson, director of the John L. Weinberg Center for Corporate Governance at the University of Delaware. “There was concern at the time about unjustified returns, and that’s what happened. They clearly took advantage of the timing.” Not so fast, say other pay experts, who argue that the first quarter, and occasionally the fourth quarter, are typically the time when stock and option grants are made, regardless of how the stock market is performing. “They had no way to know the market would begin to recover in March,” said Carol Bowie, head of the governance institute at the RiskMetrics Group, a financial analytics company. “The fact of the matter is that many, many companies grant awards at the beginning of the year. It turned out to be an opportune time, but it’s not necessarily untoward.” Nevertheless, the outsize gains from stock and options last year are likely to fuel what’s already a fierce debate about executive pay levels. What’s more, companies like Ford, Starbucks, Dow, Whirlpool and American Express were making deep job cuts even as they showered options on their chief executives. “It reinforces the view that the rules of the game are rigged and that no matter what these guys do, they always come out ahead,” said Sarah Anderson, who tracks executive pay at the Institute for Policy Studies, a liberal research group in Washington. “In a time of national crisis, it wasn’t appropriate to be giving out boatloads of new stock options.” For all the criticism of the options windfall, it’s worth noting that some pay experts have argued for years that chief executives should receive more options and stock, rather than cash, in order to link their pay to long-term corporate performance. But in a twist, the options packages have proved incredibly lucrative in the short term. The gains, Mr. Elson said, weren’t based on corporate performance but simply reflect the broad market rebound. AMONG 200 C.E.O.’s of companies tracked by Equilar, an executive compensation research firm that analyzed data for The New York Times, the biggest beneficiary of an options grant and subsequent stock market rally was Mr. Mulally at Ford. On March 11, 2009, two days after the Dow Jones industrial average hit a 12-year low of 6,547, Mr. Mulally received options to buy five million shares of Ford at $1.96, which the company estimated would be worth just over $5 million, using a complicated formula to predict their eventual value. The company usually grants options in March. A year later, the market is up more than 60 percent, but Ford shares are worth nearly 10 times what they were then, making Mr. Mulally’s options worth an estimated $53.3 million, according to Equilar. Mr. Mulally was eligible to receive the first batch on March 27 — worth more than $17 million — and is set to receive the rest within two years. Defenders of Mr. Mulally argue that Ford was the only one of the Big Three automakers not to file for bankruptcy last year; it actually earned a profit for the full year. But critics say an award of that size is still inappropriate, especially given the huge job cuts at Ford over the last few years. “The sector is going through hard times,” Ms. Anderson said. “For workers, it’s demoralizing to see that kind of money going into executives’ pockets when jobs are being cut.” A spokesman for Ford, Mark Truby, said Mr. Mulally’s options award was based on Ford’s long-term performance. “The ultimate value of these options will depend on how Ford’s stock performs over the next two years,” he said. Mr. Mulally, he added, took a 30 percent cut in salary in 2009 and 2010, and did not receive a cash bonus for 2008 and 2009. “The vast majority of his compensation is at risk and tied directly to the performance of the company and the stock,” Mr. Truby said. A corporate comeback and great timing also drove gains of the second-biggest options winner among the executives in the survey: Mr. Schultz of Starbucks.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/03/12/sensata-closes-higher-after-years-biggest-i-p-o/?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Sensata Closes Higher After Year's Biggest I.P.O.<date>March 12, 2010, 5:54 am</date><text>Shares in Sensata Technologies Holding closed up slightly Thursday after raising $568.8 million in the biggest initial public offering so far this year, The Associated Press reported. Sensata closed up about 3 percent at $18.50 after pricing its shares at the bottom of its expected range in its I.P.O. Sensata priced 31.6 million shares for $18 apiece. It had hoped to fetch up to $20. The Netherlands company makes sensors and controls, with more than half of its revenue coming from the auto industry. It is a former subsidiary of chip maker Texas Instruments and is now backed by private equity firm Bain Capital. Despite pricing at the low end of its range, it is the second company this week to sell shares to initial investors within its hoped-for range. That’s happened in only about 38 percent of this year’s I.P.O.’s as a volatile stock market and fears of a slowing recovery curbed investors’ taste for risky bets. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/09/business/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Raises View on Profit<date>Published: March 8, 2010</date><text>Texas Instruments, the chip maker, said on Monday that profit and sales in its current quarter would be at the high end of its forecasts, helped by increasing demand for phone systems and industrial machinery.First-quarter profit will be 48 to 52 cents a share on sales of $3.07 billion to $3.19 billion, the company said. In January, Texas Instruments predicted sales of as little as $2.95 billion and profit as low as 44 cents a share. Texas Instruments said it expected all of its businesses to grow this quarter from the previous three months, a vice president, Ron Slaymaker, said in a conference call. The improvements in Texas Instruments’ business reflected increasing demand, Mr. Slaymaker said, after trading closed. The company is the biggest producer of analog chips, which go ito products as diverse as washing machines and supercomputers. Its earnings are a broad indicator of demand for electronics.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/26/technology/26chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Rising Demand for Chips Lifts Profit at Texas Instruments<date>Published: January 25, 2010</date><text>Texas Instruments on Monday posted a quarterly profit at the top end of its target range and the chip maker said there was strong demand in all its product areas and markets, including Europe and the Americas. The company’s shares rose 2.51 percent, or 58 cents, to $23.69. The company also reported better demand in the current quarter than in a typical first quarter. The company forecast revenue of $2.95 billion to $3.19 billion for the first quarter, higher than Wall Street’s expectation of $2.94 billion. The chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said the first-quarter outlook was much better than usual because manufacturers were struggling to keep up with growing demand as the world’s economies improved. “We believe we’re shipping into our customers’ production, that they’re not actually building inventory,” Mr. March said. Texas Instruments, whose chips go in a broad array of products including consumer electronics and industrial gear, said its fourth-quarter profit was $655 million, or 52 cents a share, compared with $107 million, or 8 cents a share, in the fourth quarter of 2008. Before a penny tax-related benefit the profit was 51 cents a share  in line with the high end of a December forecast, the company’s chief financial officer said. “In the fourth quarter, demand was strong across end markets without the usual holiday slowdown,” the chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, said in a statement. Revenue rose 21 percent, to $3 billion from $2.49 billion in the year-ago quarter, when the entire industry was suffering from a sharp decline in demand amid global economic weakness. This was slightly ahead of average analyst expectations for revenue of $2.97 billion. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on January 26, 2010, on page B7 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/20/technology/companies/20chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Tops Forecast but Profit Falls<date>Published: October 19, 2009</date><text>The chip maker Texas Instruments posted better-than-expected third quarter results on Monday, citing strong demand across all business segments including computers, phones and cars. Skip to next paragraph Related Times Topics: Texas Instruments Inc. Texas Instruments also said results in the fourth quarter should also beat current forecasts, adding that its customers have stopped the inventory corrections that depressed demand earlier in the year. The company announced its results and its forecast after the close of market trading, and in the after-hours session its shares rose 2 percent. The chief financial officer, Kevin March, noted that it was not unusual to see production levels increase in the third quarter in anticipation of the holiday shopping season. Still, he warned that he expected demand to be softer than normal for the season. But at least one analyst said the results and forecast, which followed a better-than-expected report from the Intel Corporation, suggested demand was strengthening for Texas Instruments’ customers. “It’s clear that the recovery for the semiconductor guys is both real and not inventory-driven. That gives a lot of people hope that we’re not seeing a false start. This is actually real demand,” Ed Snyder, an analyst at Charter Equity Research, said. The company said third-quarter profit fell to $538 million, or 42 cents a share, from $563 million, or 43 cents a share, a year earlier. That beat Wall Street analysts’ average forecast for profit of 40 cents a share. The company, which is recovering from an industry-wide decline in chip demand because of the global recession, said revenue fell to $2.88 billion from $3.39 billion, but that figure was also better than Wall Street had forecast. Texas Instruments forecast fourth quarter revenue of $2.78 billion to $3.02 billion, while Wall Street analysts had forecast revenue of $2.788 billion for the period. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on October 20, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/21/technology/companies/21chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Profit Falls, but Worst May Be Past<date>Published: July 20, 2009</date><text>DALLAS (AP)  Texas Instruments, the computer chip maker, said Monday its second-quarter profit fell 56 percent on a 27 percent decline in sales. The company said sales were up from the first quarter as customers started building their inventories to more closely reflect demand. “For us, it’s encouraging to see that revenue appears to have bottomed,” Ron Slaymaker, vice president for investor relations, said. However, “we don’t necessarily see a significant strengthening in the broader economy,” he said. Texas Instruments said it earned $260 million, or 20 cents a share, in the period, down from $588 million, or 44 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell to $2.46 billion from $3.35 billion. The results were better than what analysts had been expecting. In a survey by Thomson Reuters, analysts on average had forecast a profit of 18 cents a share on sales of $2.41 billion. The company’s third-quarter forecast for a profit of 29 to 39 cents a share, and revenue of $2.5 billion to $2.8 billion, was also better than most forecasts, which averaged 27 cents a share on sales of $2.52 billion. Sales in its three main divisions all fell compared with the year-earlier quarter but rose compared with the first quarter. Sales of analog chips used in music players and other personal devices fell 24 percent, to $983 million, from a year ago, but were up 21 percent from the first quarter. Sales of chips used in machinery and cars were down 20 percent, to $350 million, from last year but up 11 percent from the first quarter. And chips used in wireless devices like mobile phones were down 33 percent, to $601 million, from last year but up 9 percent from the first quarter. Orders in the second quarter were down 19 percent from last year but improved by 27 percent from the prior quarter. Mr. Slaymaker said he did not expect the company to cut any more jobs beyond those announced in January. The company has said it plans to cut 3,400 jobs, or 12 percent of its work force, through layoffs or attrition. Texas Instruments released the results after the close of trading Monday. Shares in the company, which is based in Dallas, fell 31 cents, or 1.3 percent, to $23.30 in after-hours trading. The stock rose 60 cents, or 2.6 percent, to $23.61 during the regular session. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on July 21, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/09/technology/companies/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Forecasts a Boost in Earnings<date>Published: June 8, 2009</date><text>Texas Instruments said on Monday that its second-quarter earnings and revenue could come in above its previously announced target range, showing signs of improving demand in the chip market. T.I., which makes chips for items as varied as cellphones and industrial equipment, said it expected second-quarter earnings a share of 14 to 22 cents, much higher than its previously announced goal of 1 to 15 cents. It estimated that its revenue in the current quarter would be $2.3 billion to $2.5 billion, compared with its previous expectation of $1.95 billion to $2.4 billion. On average, analysts had expected revenue of $2.21 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on June 9, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/21/technology/companies/21chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Posts a Small Profit<date>Published: April 20, 2009</date><text>Texas Instruments posted a small quarterly profit and better-than-expected revenue on Monday as demand for its chips appeared to stabilize even though it emphasized “caution about the business climate.” The company also said that it expected to moderately increase production levels in its factories in the current quarter. Texas Instruments posted a profit of $17 million, or 1 cent a share, compared with a profit of $662 million, or 49 cents a share, in the first quarter of 2008. Revenue fell 36 percent, to $2.09 billion, from $3.27 billion. The company, a maker of computer chips for cellphones, industrial equipment and other products, had forecast first-quarter results ranging from a loss of 8 cents a share to break-even on revenue of $1.79 billion to $2.05 billion. Analysts on average had expected a net loss of 4 cents a share on revenue of $1.9 billion. Texas Instruments said its forecast for the current quarter is for earnings of 1 cent to 15 cents a share on revenue of $1.95 billion to $2.40 billion. Shares rose more than 2 percent in after-market trading, having ended the regular session of the New York Stock Exchange at $17.32. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on April 21, 2009, on page B8 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/10/technology/companies/10chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">New Forecast at Chip Maker<date>Published: March 9, 2009</date><text>Texas Instruments narrowed the range of its first-quarter forecast for earnings and revenue Monday after it said it was idling factories and reducing inventory after a sharp fall-off in demand. T.I., a maker of chips for everything from cellphones to industrial equipment, now expects to post first-quarter results ranging from a loss of 8 cents a share to breaking even. On Jan. 26, it forecast a range from a loss of 11 cents to a profit of 3 cents a share, including a revamping charge of 3 cents a share. Revenue will be in the range of $1.79 billion to $2.05 billion, compared with its previous forecast ranging from $1.62 billion to $2.12 billion, the company said. Analysts, on average, expected revenue of $1.868 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. The company has said it would cut its work force by about 12 percent to reduce expenses. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on March 10, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/11/technology/11shepherd.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Mark Shepherd Jr., a Force in Electronics, Dies at 86<date>Published: February 10, 2009</date><text>Mark Shepherd Jr., who as an engineer, manager and chief executive of Texas Instruments headed its rise to power as a maker of semiconductors and consumer electronics, died last Wednesday at his ranch in Quitman, Tex. He was 86. The cause was complications of pulmonary fibrosis, his son Marc Shepherd said. During his 40 years at Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd helped turn the company from a niche outfit catering to the needs of oil and gas companies into an electronics pioneer, producing goods for both businesses and consumers. As a hard-charging engineer, Mr. Shepherd was given the task of building Texas Instruments’ first transistors and semiconductor products, which soon found their way into calculators, computers and toys. Later, as chief executive and chairman of the company, Mr. Shepherd fought to expand the semiconductor business overseas, while also fending off budding electronics giants in Asia. Mr. Shepherd’s rise through Texas Instruments paralleled the rise of the transistor and semiconductor technology in which he specialized. In 1952, he and three other Texas Instruments engineers were sent to Bell Laboratories to learn about the company’s transistor, which had been invented in 1947. Texas Instruments bought a license for the technology and began to explore broad applications for the transistor. Former employees at Texas Instruments credited Mr. Shepherd with understanding the significant role transistors and semiconductors would play in reshaping electronics. As a replacement for clunky, unreliable vacuum tubes, the transistors led to cheaper, smaller and more stable devices like portable radios and pocket calculators. Having just learned about the transistor technology, Mr. Shepherd managed to assemble and lead a team that produced a working product in short order. Mr. Shepherd was also the head of the semiconductor team in 1958, when Jack S. Kilby invented the integrated circuit, the precursor to modern computer chips. Texas Instruments created ground-breaking products, perhaps most notably a portable calculator, based on its semiconductor technology. In addition, the company built devices like printers and PCs with the technology. Like many of the prominent engineers of his day, Mr. Shepherd demonstrated a precocious gift for electronics. He is said to have built a vacuum tube at the age of 6 and a radio shortly thereafter. He graduated from high school at 14. “I heard him say that after those early experiences he never thought of doing anything else but going into electronics,” said Max Post, a former Texas Instruments engineer who had worked with Mr. Shepherd. Mr. Shepherd went on to receive a degree in electrical engineering with honors from Southern Methodist University and a master’s degree in the same field from the University of Illinois. Mr. Shepherd applied his engineering expertise during a stint in the Navy where he served as a lieutenant for three years, working on radar and electronics systems on the U.S.S. Tucson. After jobs at General Electric and the Farnsworth Television and Radio Corporation, in 1948 Mr. Shepherd joined Geophysical Service, which would become Texas Instruments. During his four decades at Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd spent time either overseeing crucial semiconductor projects directly or serving on the leadership groups approving them. He had roles as chief engineer and chief operating officer at the company before becoming its chief executive in 1969. In 1976, Mr. Shepherd was named chairman of Texas Instruments and held that position until 1988. As a manager, Mr. Shepherd was credited with driving Texas Instruments’ overseas expansion, turning the company into one of the first to open semiconductor manufacturing facilities abroad, including a factory in Japan. Through an intense focus on cost controls and computer-aided mechanisms for semiconductor manufacturing, Mr. Shepherd worked to lower the prices of Texas Instruments’ technology. “Driving the cost down was an obsession for him,” Mr. Post said. “He just kept telling everyone that the semiconductor market will only grow if we can get the cost down for consumer products.” The breadth of products introduced during Mr. Shepherd’s tenure as a prominent manager established Texas Instruments as a force in the electronics industry. “He drove T.I. into world leadership not only in semiconductors, but took the chip industry into consumer electronics with calculators, digital watches and toys where Texas Instruments dominated even companies like Hewlett-Packard and Intel,” said Michael Malone, an author who has covered the technology industry and Silicon Valley. “That was T.I.’s golden age.” Later in his career, Mr. Shepherd and Texas Instruments were forced to confront a powerful set of suppliers in Asia and falling profits on the consumer electronics products. As a result, Texas Instruments refocused its efforts on advancing semiconductor technology. After his retirement from Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd and his wife, Mary Alice, raised longhorn cattle at their ranch in Quitman. Marykay Shepherd, his daughter, now handles affairs on the ranch. Debra Shepherd Robinson, his other daughter, lives in Dallas. He is also survived by three granddaughters. Still an engineer to the core, Mr. Shepherd oversaw the construction of dams, fire protection systems and buildings on the ranch. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on February 11, 2009, on page B19 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/10/technology/companies/10shepherd.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Mark Shepherd, a Force in Electronics, Dies at 86<date>Published: February 9, 2009</date><text>Mark Shepherd Jr., who as an engineer, manager and chief executive of Texas Instruments, headed its rise to power as a maker of semiconductors and consumer electronics, died Wednesday at his ranch in Quitman, Tex. He was 86. Skip to next paragraph Texas Instruments Mark Shepherd Jr. The cause was complications of pulmonary fibrosis, his son Marc Shepherd said. During his 40 years at Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd helped turn the company from a niche outfit catering to the needs of oil and gas companies into an electronics pioneer, producing goods for both businesses and consumers. As a hard-charging engineer, Mr. Shepherd was given the task of building Texas Instruments’ first transistors and semiconductor products, which soon found their way into calculators, computers and toys. Later, as chief executive and chairman of the company, Mr. Shepherd fought to expand the semiconductor business overseas, while also fending off budding electronics giants in Asia. Mr. Shepherd’s rise through Texas Instruments paralleled the rise of the transistor and semiconductor technology in which he specialized. In 1952, he and three other Texas Instruments engineers were sent to Bell Laboratories to learn about the company’s transistor, which had been invented in 1947. Texas Instruments bought a license for the technology and began to explore broad applications for the transistor. Former employees at Texas Instruments credited Mr. Shepherd with understanding the significant role transistors and semiconductors would play in reshaping electronics products. As a replacement for clunky, unreliable vacuum tubes, the transistors led to cheaper, smaller and more stable devices like portable radios and pocket calculators. Having just learned about the transistor technology, Mr. Shepherd managed to assemble and lead a team that produced a working product in short order. Mr. Shepherd was also the head of the semiconductor team in 1958, when Jack S. Kilby invented the integrated circuit, the precursor to modern computer chips. Texas Instruments created ground-breaking products, perhaps most notably a portable calculator, based on its semiconductor technology. In addition, the company built devices like printers and PCs with the technology. Like many of the prominent engineers of his day, Mr. Shepherd demonstrated a precocious gift for electronics. He is said to have built a vacuum tube at the age of 6 and a radio shortly thereafter. He graduated from high school at 14. “I heard him say that after those early experiences he never thought of doing anything else but going into electronics,” said Max Post, a former Texas Instruments engineer who had worked with Mr. Shepherd. Mr. Shepherd went on to receive a degree in electrical engineering with honors from Southern Methodist University and a master’s degree in the same field from the University of Illinois. Mr. Shepherd applied his engineering expertise during a stint in the Navy where he served as a lieutenant for three years, working on radar and electronics systems on the U.S.S. Tucson. After jobs at General Electric and the Farnsworth Television and Radio Corporation, in 1948 Mr. Shepherd joined Geophysical Services, which would become Texas Instruments. During his four decades at Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd spent time either overseeing crucial semiconductor projects directly or serving on the leadership groups approving them. He had roles as chief engineer and chief operating officer at the company before becoming its chief executive in 1969. In 1976, Mr. Shepherd was named chairman of Texas Instruments and held that position until 1988. As a manager, Mr. Shepherd was credited with driving Texas Instruments’ overseas expansion, turning the company into one of the first to open semiconductor manufacturing facilities abroad, including a factory in Japan. Through an intense focus on cost controls and computer-aided mechanisms for semiconductor manufacturing, Mr. Shepherd worked to lower the prices of Texas Instruments’ technology. “Driving the cost down was an obsession for him,” Mr. Post said. “He just kept telling everyone that the semiconductor market will only grow if we can get the cost down for consumer products.” The breadth of products introduced during Mr. Shepherd’s tenure as a prominent manager established Texas Instruments as a force in the electronics industry. “He drove T.I. into world leadership not only in semiconductors, but took the chip industry into consumer electronics with calculators, digital watches and toys where Texas Instruments dominated even companies like Hewlett-Packard and Intel,” said Michael Malone, an author who has covered the technology industry and Silicon Valley. “That was T.I.’s golden age.” Later in his career, Mr. Shepherd and Texas Instruments were forced to confront a powerful set of suppliers in Asia and falling profits on the consumer electronics products. As a result, Texas Instruments refocused its efforts on advancing semiconductor technology. After his retirement from Texas Instruments, Mr. Shepherd and his wife, Mary Alice, raised longhorn cattle at their ranch in Quitman. Marykay Shepherd, his daughter, now handles affairs on the ranch. Debra Shepherd Robinson, his other daughter, lives in Dallas. He is also survived by three granddaughters. Still an engineer to the core, Mr. Shepherd oversaw the construction of dams, fire protection systems and buildings on the ranch. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/27/technology/companies/27chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Tech Company to Cut Workers<date>Published: January 26, 2009</date><text>Texas Instruments posted a smaller-than-expected decline in fourth-quarter profit Monday, but said it might post a loss in the current quarter and announced a 12 percent cut in jobs as demand for cellphone chips fell. But the company’s shares rose 5 percent in after-hours trading as analysts said the better-than-expected fourth quarter and the cost-cutting measures meant Texas Instruments could be positioned for growth when demand recovers. The company said it was cutting its work force by 3,400 to reduce costs. Profit in its most recent quarter was $107 million, or 8 cents a share, compared with $753 million, or 54 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell to $2.49 billion from $3.56 billion. The company warned that it still had tough times ahead, forecasting a possible loss for the first quarter, when utilization of its factories was expected to fall below 35 percent, from 48 percent in the fourth quarter. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/03/technology/03chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">November Chip Sales Slipped 10%<date>Published: January 2, 2009</date><text>Global semiconductor sales fell almost 10 percent in November, as the economic slowdown shook the chip sector, an industry trade group said Friday. Semiconductor sales dropped to $20.8 billion in November, from $23.1 billion a year earlier, the Semiconductor Industry Association reported. Sales through the first 11 months of the year rose 0.2 percent to $232.7 billion. November sales were 7.2 percent lower than the $22.4 billion in October 2008. Excluding memory products, chip sales declined 4.8 percent to $17.3 billion. “The worldwide economic crisis is having an impact on demand for semiconductors, but to a lesser degree than some other major industry sectors,” the group’s president, George Scalise, said in a statement. “We expect the industry will remain the second largest exporter in the U.S. for 2008.” Mr. Scalise said that in the memory market, which has been under severe price pressure throughout the year, sales have declined significantly while many other product sectors have year-to-date sales above 2007 levels. Sales in the Americas fell 19.5 percent while in Europe sales fell 13.9 percent. However, the Asia Pacific region had the smallest decline, 6.2 percent in sales. The trade group represents makers of silicon chips that run computers, mobile phones and other electronics devices. Its members include Intel, Texas Instruments and Advanced Micro Devices. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on January 3, 2009, on page B3 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/09/technology/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Lowers Earnings Forecast<date>Published: December 8, 2008</date><text>DALLAS (AP)  Texas Instruments said Monday that its fourth-quarter earnings and revenue would fall significantly below earlier forecasts, as the global market for semiconductors continued to weaken. The company, which is based in Dallas, said it now expected to earn 10 to 16 cents a share, down from the prior forecast of 30 to 36 cents a share. Analysts polled by Thomson Reuters were expecting a profit of 31 cents a share, on average. The company expects revenue to be $2.3 billion to $2.5 billion, down from its prior expectation of $2.83 billion to $3.07 billion. Analysts were forecasting $2.91 billion. Analysts were expecting Texas Instruments to report a bleak outlook in the fourth quarter, as the chip market has gotten weaker since the company’s last guidance. Notably, Nokia, the world’s largest maker of cellphones and a large customer of Texas Instruments, has cut its estimate for next year’s handset industry production twice since then. In October, the Texas Instruments chief executive, Rich Templeton, warned that order trends had been weak in the last few months. The company also said in October it would cut 650 people from its unit that made chips for cellphones to more than $200 million a year. Texas Instruments was in talks to sell part of that unit, which has suffered because of a sales drop at Motorola, one of its main clients. Shares of Texas Instruments rose 26 cents to $14.82 on Monday. The company disclosed its forecast after the market’s close. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/21/technology/companies/21chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Plans to Cut 650 Jobs<date>Published: October 20, 2008</date><text>Texas Instruments, which makes chips for cellphones and other devices, warned on Monday that orders were slowing rapidly and said it would cut jobs to save money. The company said it would reduce its work force by 650 in six countries from a unit that makes chips for cellphones. And it is in talks to sell part of the unit, which has struggled because of a drop in sales at a big client, Motorola. The company essentially met analyst expectations for third-quarter earnings on Monday, but the chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, said order trends have been weak in the last few months. Texas Instruments said it expected sales of $2.83 billion to $3.07 billion in the fourth quarter, well below the $3.3 billion that analysts polled by Thomson Reuters were expecting. In the fourth quarter last year, sales were $3.56 billion. The company expects 30 cents to 36 cents a share in fourth-quarter earnings, while analysts were expecting 44 cents. There have been other indications that the fourth quarter would be a bad one for semiconductor companies; last week, a rival, Linear Technology, warned of a sales drop. Investors, however, seemed taken aback by Texas Instruments’ warning. Its shares were down 93 cents, or 5 percent, at $17.05 in extended trading Monday, after the release of the results. For the third quarter, the company earned $563 million, or 43 cents a share, down 27 percent, from $776 million, or 54 cents a share, in the same quarter last year. Excluding earnings from discontinued operations in the year-ago period of $18 million, income from continuing operations a year ago were $758 million, or 52 cents a share. Revenue declined 8 percent to $3.39 billion. Analysts were expecting earnings of 44 cents a share on sales of $3.4 billion. However, their estimates generally exclude one-time charges and benefits. Such items reduced earnings in the quarter by $10 million, or nearly a penny a share. The job cuts will come from the division that makes so-called baseband chips, which beam a phone call to a cell tower. The cuts will save $200 million a year, the company said. The unit to be sold is the one that supplies off-the-shelf baseband processors to smaller manufacturers. Of the 650 layoffs, 350 will be in this unit, said Ron Slaymaker, the vice president for investor relations. The company has about 30,000 employees. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on October 21, 2008, on page B12 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/10/technology/10chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Affirms Forecasts<date>Published: September 9, 2008</date><text>Texas Instruments said Tuesday that earnings and revenue for the current quarter were on track, sending shares up 6 percent on shareholder relief that it did not cut its outlook after profit warnings were issued by mobile phone providers. The company, which makes analog and wireless chips, barely changed its targets, reassuring Wall Street after its biggest client, Nokia, had warned last week of aggressive pricing in the handset market and a weakened consumer market. Texas Instruments forecast third-quarter earnings of 42 cents to 46 cents a share, compared with its July forecast of 41 cents to 47 cents, which was below Wall Street estimates. It forecast revenue of $3.33 billion to $3.47 billion for the quarter, compared with its previous estimate of $3.26 billion to $3.54 billion. The midpoints of the forecasts were unchanged and matched average Wall Street expectations. Stock in Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas, rose to $23.01 in extended trading, after closing at $21.71 on the New York Stock Exchange. More Articles in Technology » A version of this article appeared in print on September 10, 2008, on page C7 of the New York edition.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/22/technology/22chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Disappoints and Predicts Weak 3rd Quarter<date>Published: July 22, 2008</date><text>Texas Instruments posted disappointing second-quarter results and gave a weak third-quarter outlook on Monday, blaming a broad-based slowdown in customer orders. Skip to next paragraph Texas Instruments Earnings Release The results, released after the close of market trading, fell short of Wall Street forecasts and set off a decline of more than 10 percent in the company’s share price in the after-hours session. While Texas Instrument’s wireless chip business has been weakening for some time, the company is showing signs that the downturn was spreading to analog chips, which are used in products ranging from consumer electronics to industrial equipment. The company said profit was $588 million, or 44 cents a share, compared with $614 million, or 42 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue dropped 2 percent, to $3.35 billion from $3.42 billion. The results were worse than the average analyst target for earnings of 46 cents on revenue of $3.39 billion. Texas Instruments said demand slowed unexpectedly in June as distributors reduced inventory levels and did not replenish supplies. It said revenue from wireless products also continued to decline. The company, which is based in Dallas, forecast third-quarter earnings of 41 to 47 cents a share on revenue of $3.26 billion to $3.54 billion. Wall Street on average expected earnings of 51 cents a share on revenue of $3.57 billion. The chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, blamed the weaker economic environment for the slower demand. “Our orders were up in the quarter and backlog grew, but we are cautious given the demand environment we just experienced,” Mr. Templeton said. The chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said that demand increased for chips used in phones with third generation high-speed Web access, but demand fell for lower-end phones. More Articles in Technology »</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4DD103AF934A25755C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">$14 Billion In Deals Precede Trade Talks<date>Published: June 17, 2008</date><text>CORRECTION APPENDED Leading businesses in China and the United States, seeking to overcome mutual suspicion of foreign investment, announced $14 billion in new business deals on Monday, on the eve of high-level economic talks to ease tensions between the two countries. The deals involve $8 billion in Chinese investments and purchases of aircraft engines, telecommunications equipment, semiconductors and electronic components, said Chen Deming, minister of commerce in China. He added that $6 billion in other deals involved American purchases and investments in China. Among the American companies signing deals at the United States Chamber of Commerce were Chrysler, Cisco Systems, Ford Motor, General Motors, I.B.M., Motorola, Sun Microsystems, Qualcomm and Texas Instruments. Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr., who will be leading a delegation of Bush administration officials at the talks beginning on Tuesday in Annapolis, Md., said the sessions were not meant to resolve specific disputes but instead to discuss how to overcome economic downturns and deal with impending crises in energy and the environment. ''The tone will be one of constructive engagement,'' Mr. Paulson said in an interview on Monday. ''We're going to be dealing with some of the most fundamental economic issues there are. I know some people would like to see quick fixes. But the most important issues don't avail themselves to quick fixes.'' On Wednesday afternoon, the Chinese delegation is scheduled to meet with President Bush at the White House. The Annapolis talks are the fourth in a twice-a-year series that Mr. Paulson started when he left Goldman Sachs to become Treasury chief in 2006. The biggest issue at the time was American irritation over China's intervention in currency markets to purchase dollars and keep the value of the dollar high in relation to China's currency. Since mid-2005, China has allowed its currency, the yuan, to appreciate nearly 20 percent, easing at least some of the criticism in Congress. The Bush administration continues to accuse China of raising barriers to foreign investment, and China has increasingly complained that its attempts to invest in America often provoke an outcry. Mr. Paulson said that, although China had made only limited reforms in its economy and had taken limited steps to open its market to American goods and investment, the ''strategic economic dialogue,'' known as the S.E.D., produced more progress than otherwise would have been the case. ''I would argue that the reason we've made progress is that the S.E.D. is a mechanism for convincing China that certain things are in their interest,'' he said, citing American efforts to get China to open its economy to foreign investment and to lift government subsidies of export industries. In recent months, the Chinese government has pushed back with tough-talking demands that the United States do more to open its own economy to Chinese investments and to halt the depreciation of the dollar against European and other currencies, a trend many economists say has helped drive up oil and food prices. The Chinese delegation will be led by Wang Qishan, a vice premier and former mayor of Beijing, and also a graduate of Northwestern University, who took office as his country's chief economic negotiator earlier this year. He succeeded Wu Yi, one of the highest-ranking women in China and often described as a tough negotiator. Mr. Paulson said that though China had lately stepped up its criticism of the United States, ''I sure didn't find Wu Yi to be a shrinking violet.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/10/technology/10chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Revises Target<date>Published: June 10, 2008</date><text>SAN FRANCISCO (Reuters)  Texas Instruments narrowed on Monday a quarterly earnings and revenue goal it issued in April because of caution among its chip customers and weak demand for high-end phones. The company, which makes chips, forecast second-quarter earnings of 43 to 47 cents a share on revenue of $3.33 billion to $3.46 billion. Shares of the company fell 18 cents to $31.15 in extended trading. They rose 9 cents, or less than 1 percent, to close at $31.33 in regular trading Monday. On April 21, Texas Instruments disappointed investors with a forecast of 42 to 48 cents a share on revenue of $3.24 billion to $3.5 billion. The company, based in Dallas, said Monday it expected semiconductor revenue in the quarter of $3.17 billion to $3.28 billion, compared with the previously given range of $3.08 billion to $3.32 billion. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DA163EF932A25757C0A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING | EUROPE; SWITZERLAND: A VENTURE IN CHIPS<date>Published: April 11, 2008</date><text>STMicroelectronics and NXP will merge their wireless chip businesses into a $3 billion joint venture controlled by STMicroelectronics to challenge the market leaders, Qualcomm and Texas Instruments. STMicroelectronics said it would pay NXP $1.55 billion from its cash reserves to own 80 percent of the venture in a first sign of consolidation, which had been expected to combat falling prices and share the costs of research and development. STMicroelectronics, of Geneva, and NXP, based in the Netherlands, combined had about 10.5 percent of the global market last year, according to iSuppli, a research firm.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/11/technology/11chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Lowers Profit Forecast<date>Published: March 11, 2008</date><text>DALLAS (AP)  Texas Instruments, which makes chips used in about half the world’s cellphones, has lowered its range of expected profits and sales for the first quarter. The company said on Monday that it expected to earn 41 to 45 cents a share in the quarter that ends March 31, a range with a midpoint 3 cents lower than the midpoint of a January forecast. Analysts expected 46 cents a share, according to a survey by Thomson Financial. Texas Instruments also said sales would total $3.21 billion to $3.35 billion, or about $130 million below the midpoint of the January estimate. Analysts had forecast $3.40 billion. In January, the company said it would earn 43 to 49 cents a share on sales of $3.27 billion to $3.55 billion in the first quarter. Texas Instruments shares had risen 35 cents, or 1.2 percent, to $29.65 before the first-quarter update. In the first few minutes of extended trading, the shares fell $1.40, or 4.7 percent. The company, based in Dallas, suffered setbacks last year when Nokia, its largest customer, and Sony Ericsson decided to seek other suppliers of chips used in their phones. The chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, said on Friday that the company expected to remain the largest supplier to Nokia. Texas Instruments sells chips both for low-end mobile phones used in emerging markets like China and India and for advanced, feature-laden models used in developed countries. The company also said that its educational unit, which makes the calculators for which the company was once known, would generate first-quarter sales of $70 million to $90 million, unchanged from an earlier forecast. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/23/technology/23chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Reports Profit Rose by 13%<date>Published: January 23, 2008</date><text>DALLAS  Texas Instruments, the largest maker of chips for mobile phones, said Tuesday that its fourth-quarter profit rose 13 percent and that sales reversed a yearlong decline. The company posted net income of $756 million, or 54 cents a share, including a penny a share from a tax gain. That compared with $668 million, or 45 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial had expected earnings of 52 cents a share. Revenue was $3.56 billion, down 3 percent from the third quarter and $20 million less than analysts had predicted. But sales grew 3 percent from the same quarter in 2006, which analysts consider a better yardstick. The company said sales growth was strongest in digital signal processors and analog chips used in a variety of electronic gadgets. It forecast first-quarter earnings of 43 to 49 cents a share on revenue of $3.27 billion to $3.55 billion. Analysts were projecting profit of 45 cents a share on sales of $3.41 billion. Ron Slaymaker, the company’s vice president, called the increase in revenue from late 2006, after four quarters of year-over-year sales declines, a turning point. He said the company expected revenue to grow faster this year. The company plans to trim research and development spending by about 7 percent this year, to $2 billion, partly as the result of restructuring. The wireless business is critical to Texas Instruments. A Deutsche Bank analyst, Ross Seymore, said before the company’s report that sales to wireless customers were probably stronger than expected for both ends of the market  low-end phones in emerging markets like China and India, and expensive phones for consumers in developed nations. Shares of Texas Instruments ended regular trading down 48 cents, at $28.98. In extended trading after the earnings report, shares rose as much as 88 cents. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/21/business/21texas1.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Betting on a Bright Future for Rear-Projection TVs<date>Published: January 21, 2008</date><text>PLANO, Tex.  Back in the early years of this decade, when plasma high-definition televisions cost $10,000, consumers found that buying a rear-projection TV was a more affordable way to jump into the digital era. But with prices plummeting for liquid-crystal display and plasma TVs, the rear-projection market is quickly drying up. Sony and Philips got out of that business last month. “The market is moving rapidly to L.C.D.,” said Todd Richardson, vice president for marketing of connected displays for Philips Consumer Lifestyle North America, a division of Royal Philips Electronics. But Texas Instruments, the chip maker that developed the digital light processor most commonly found in most rear-projection TVs, is holding the line. It isn’t going to be easy. Texas Instruments’ third-quarter 2007 revenue from D.L.P. chip sales decreased 21 percent from the same period in 2006, after similar dips in previous quarters. D.L.P. TV sets are still being made by Samsung, Mitsubishi and Toshiba, but according to market researchers at iSupply, sales of such TVs will drop 25 percent over the next two years. DisplaySearch, another market research firm, believes that in 2009, less than 1 percent of the TVs sold will be rear-projection sets using D.L.P. Which begs the question: Can there be a second act for Texas Instruments’ digital light processor technology? The company says there can be with improved technology. T.I. executives reject analysts’ projections, arguing that they fail to take product improvements into account. The next generation of D.L.P. chips, said Doug Darrow, D.L.P. products brand and marketing manager, will stabilize its market share. “Most analysts use a rear view mirror when forecasting results,” Mr. Darrow said. “They do not think of trends in the technology. We serve a different type of customer: the home theater enthusiast.” At the Consumer Electronics Show last week, the company displayed smaller chips that TV makers could use to create slimmer sets with brighter, high-contrast pictures and smoother motion in the images. It also showed  behind closed doors  projectors tiny enough to fit in a cellphone. Digital light processor technology uses up to two million microscopic tilting mirrors, all housed on a single chip, that direct light to the screen. The technology, which was invented in 1987 by Larry Hornbeck, a T.I. engineer, has inherent advantages. Its TV sets weigh less than equivalent-size plasma displays. The sets can be frameless, increasing the size of the display that can fit into a given space. And D.L.P. sets consume less energy than plasma displays, an increasingly important factor as consumers opt for very large sets. But if Texas Instruments wants to reverse or stem the slide in sales, it needs to attract consumers looking at L.C.D. TVs. D.L.P. sets have a price advantage over L.C.D. and even plasma in screens larger than 50 inches. Mitsubishi’s 70-inch model can be commonly found for $2,500 at online retailers. Plasma and L.C.D. TVs with a 65-inch screen, the closest size, typically cost $5,100 to $6,700. “The D.L.P. business for us has never been better,” said Frank DeMartin, a Mitsubishi marketing vice president. He expects industry D.L.P. sales for sets 70 inches and larger to double this year, to 180,000 units. Still, that price advantage gets squeezed as the L.C.D. makers cut the costs of producing larger panels. In July, Sharp announced that it would have a plant capable of economically producing 60-inch L.C.D. panels in 2010. “Then we will have to look at our strategy,” Mr. DeMartin said. So a lot is riding on the latest version of the D.L.P. chip. The new chip delivers a contrast ratio of 500,000-to-1, up from 20,000-to-1 for the current chip, which makes the image sharper. “Contrast ratio is the big knob of picture quality,” Mr. Darrow said. The picture will be further improved by new TV sets that use light-emitting diodes and lasers as light sources, rather than bulbs. Mr. Darrow says this year’s D.L.P. sets could have more than twice the brightness of previous models. Depending on the manufacturer, the increased light from these sources can be used either to improve the image’s brightness or to create a more uniform light level across the screen, eliminating the “hot spot” that forces viewers of rear-projection TVs to sit at a particular height to see the best picture. But the biggest rap against rear-projection TVs is that consumers cannot hang one on the wall as they can with L.C.D. sets. It does not matter that most buyers never mount their TV on a wall. They want to think they can. To mimic the “hang-on-the-wall” concept of flat panel TVs, Texas Instruments has developed a lightweight prototype set that is less than 7 inches deep, not much different from the depth of today’s flat panel TVs. It has also developed several features to attract game enthusiasts and sports fans. Current D.L.P. sets are able to generate a three-dimensional picture if the user is wearing special glasses and a decoder is attached to a video game console or DVD player. The company expects to have installed 500,000 3-D-capable sets by February, but that would still be only half the number needed to encourage the movie studios to create high definition, 3-D DVDs. The same technology offers intriguing possibilities. It can be used to create two different images on a screen simultaneously. When two viewers wear special glasses, each one sees a different scene. In a demonstration at T.I.’s labs here, two video game players raced cars through city streets, each seeing only his own vehicle. While the screen contained two images, each seemed as sharp as would a normal view. By shrinking the chip even more, Texas Instruments has not only lowered its production costs but opened the way to new applications that could save the technology. In one prototype shown at C.E.S., a miniature projector was incorporated into a device no bigger than a book of matches. Build that into a cellphone, and on-the-go business and entertainment presentations become possible. Put it into a music player and users can project videos against a wall for their friends. There are a lot of TVs, but there are even more cellphones, digital cameras and other portable hand-held devices. “All of a sudden,” said Mr. Darrow, “we’re into a market of 100 million game machines, cellphones, iPods, and other portable devices used to consume media.” And no one thinks about mounting those devices on a wall. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/23/technology/23chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Posts Gain, but Lowers Its Forecast<date>Published: October 23, 2007</date><text>Texas Instruments posted a 10 percent increase in quarterly profit yesterday, but gave a disappointing revenue forecast, sending its shares down after hours. The company, which makes products like calculators and chips for cellphones and televisions, said fourth-quarter wireless revenue would remain at third-quarter levels despite growth in other parts of its business, like analog chips. It forecast fourth-quarter revenue of $3.4 billion to $3.68 billion, compared with the average analyst view of $3.7 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. The companys third-quarter profit from continuing operations rose to $758 million, or 52 cents a share, from $686 million, or 45 cents a share. But revenue fell to $3.66 billion, from $3.76 billion in the period a year earlier, when the result was bolstered by excess ordering by customers that overestimated demand. The excess ordering led to an inventory glut that Texas Instruments cleared this year. Analysts were looking for third-quarter earnings of 50 cents a share on revenue of $3.66 billion, according to Reuters Estimates. A Charter Equity Research analyst, John Dryden, said Texas Instruments was probably losing market share to STMicroelectronics, which signed a new contract with Ericsson late last year. Texas Instruments chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said market share losses would put pressure on the company until the second half of next year. He also said wireless revenue would be hurt by customers working to reduce chip inventory in the fourth quarter. The company forecast fourth-quarter earnings of 48 cents to 54 cents a share. Analysts, on average, expect earnings of 50 cents a share, before unusual items. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DA1230F931A35753C1A9619C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Europe Revives Qualcomm Antitrust Inquiry<date>Published: October 2, 2007</date><text>The European Commission elevated its antitrust investigation against the chip maker Qualcomm to priority status Monday, after two years of apparent inactivity on the case. The regulatory agency said an in-depth investigation would be conducted as ''a matter of priority.'' The move does not imply that the commission has conclusive proof of an infringement, it added. In October 2005, six telecommunications companies accused Qualcomm of breaking antitrust laws in its licensing of mobile phone technology. The companies -- Broadcom, Ericsson, NEC, Nokia, Panasonic Mobile Communications and Texas Instruments -- said Qualcomm's royalty fees for next-generation mobile phone chips were excessive, breaking a series of agreements to keep fees at reasonable levels. Qualcomm makes chips for cellphones and charges royalties to handset makers and chip makers that use technology covered by its patents. The investigation focuses on whether the licensing terms and royalties imposed by Qualcomm are ''fair, reasonable and nondiscriminatory,'' the commission said. The inquiry is the first major antitrust investigation the commission is undertaking after its landmark victory against Microsoft in September. If the commission finds against Qualcomm, it could force the company to change its licensing practices and fine it as much as 10 percent of its annual revenue. The six complainants welcomed the development in the investigation, saying that they were concerned that Qualcomm's practices were ''harmful to the mobile telecommunications industry globally,'' resulting in higher prices and less choice for carriers and consumers alike. Qualcomm argues, however, that its licensing practices have not harmed the end customers, as prices have declined over the two-year period of the investigation.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/22/technology/22chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Adds $5 Billion to Buyback<date>Published: September 22, 2007</date><text>The chip maker Texas Instruments said yesterday that it had expanded its share buyback program by $5 billion, or about 10 percent of its market capitalization, sending shares up. The company, which also makes calculators and television chips, also said it would raise its dividend by 25 percent, the second such increase this year. Directors authorized the expansion of the repurchase program to $8.8 billion, or about 17 percent of the market capitalization of about $51 billion. It does indicate they will be more aggressive going forward on buybacks, said a Jefferies analyst, John Lau. He estimated that Texas Instrument buys an average of $1 billion to $2 billion of shares a quarter. This raises the profile of Texas Instruments as a solid growth company with increasing profitability, Mr. Lau said. This is of great interest to the value investor. The companys head of investor relations, Ron Slaymaker, noted that the company had increased its buyback authorization by $5 billion twice last year, in September and earlier in the year. The increases in the buyback program and the dividend come as Texas Instruments resumes growth after being dogged by wireless industry inventory overloads last year and early this year. Shares rose 85 cents, to $36.62. Texas Instruments said the latest move brings its total stock purchase authorization since September 2004 to $20 billion. Under these programs, it had reduced its shares outstanding by 17 percent, with roughly $11.2 billion in buybacks by the end of June, it said. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DD1F30F931A2575AC0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Quarterly Outlook Is Lifted Slightly<date>Published: September 12, 2007</date><text>The chip maker Texas Instruments revised its third-quarter forecast on Tuesday, saying it expected earnings of 49 cents to 53 cents a share on revenue of $3.56 billion to $3.72 billion. In July, the company said it expected fiscal third-quarter earnings of 46 cents to 52 cents a share on revenue of $3.49 billion to $3.79 billion. The July sale of a semiconductor product line associated with D.S.L. equipment bolstered the per-share estimate by 2 cents, the company said. Analysts polled by Thomson Financial predicted earnings of 49 cents a share on revenue of $3.66 billion for the quarter ending Sept. 30. Before the report was released, Texas Instruments shares rose 50 cents, or 1.4 percent, to close at $35.72. The stock fell 40 cents in after-hours trading. On Monday, Texas Instruments detailed plans to lay off 191 workers whose manufacturing jobs here were being eliminated and who could not find other positions at the company. The layoffs will begin in early November and continue until the end of January, the company, which is based here, said. The workers will be put on paid leave for 60 days after their release, the company said.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/24/technology/24chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Supplier’s Profit Fell 75% in 2nd Quarter<date>Published: July 24, 2007</date><text>DALLAS, July 23 (AP)  Texas Instruments, the largest supplier of chips used in mobile phones, said on Monday that its second-quarter profit plunged almost 75 percent from a year ago, when its results in the quarter were bolstered by the $1.65 billion sale of a sensor business. Net income met analysts expectations, however, at $610 million, or 42 cents a share, down from $2.39 billion, or $1.50 a share, in the second quarter of 2006. On an operating basis, the company, based in Dallas, earned $739 million, or 47 cents a share, after excluding parts of the business it sold last year. Revenue for the quarter was $3.42 billion, down from $3.7 billion in the year-ago period, because of weaker demand for a broad range of products. Analysts had expected $3.45 billion in revenue, according to a Thomson Financial survey. Ron Slaymaker, the companys vice president of investor relations, said it had emerged from an inventory glut, and that sales of high-performance analog products were helping to offset declines in other products. The president and chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, repeated his prediction, made in May, that gross profit margins, which were 52.1 percent in the second quarter of 2007, would reach 55 percent in the next few years. Texas Instruments said it expected to earn 46 cents to 52 cents a share in the third quarter  in line with Wall Street forecasts  on revenue of $3.49 billion to $3.79 billion. Analysts were expecting third-quarter sales of $3.7 billion. In May, the company unveiled plans to invest about $1 billion over 10 years in a new test and assembly facility in the Philippines, and also announced the sale of its digital subscriber line, or D.S.L., customer equipment business to the German chip maker Infineon Technologies for an undisclosed amount. That sale is expected to close at the end of this month. In a separate announcement that coincided with Mondays earnings report, Texas Instruments said it was working with Ericsson, the worlds largest maker of wireless networks, to build a cellphone platform that could run on any operating system that manufacturers and carriers choose. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDC1531F932A15754C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Corrections: For the Record<date>Published: July 21, 2007</date><text>An article in Science Times on July 10 about William A. Wulf, an engineer and entrepreneur of computer science, referred imprecisely to the duration of Dr. Wulf's work with Tartan Laboratories. Dr. Wulf left Tartan in 1988, before the company was sold to Texas Instruments, not after. Also, the article misstated the year that Texas Instruments acquired Tartan. It was 1996, not 1995.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/technology/24chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Chip Maker Posts 4% Profit Decline<date>Published: April 24, 2007</date><text>DALLAS, April 23 (AP)  Texas Instruments, the world’s leading maker of chips for cellphones, reported a 4 percent drop in first-quarter earnings Monday as it struggled with a glut of inventory and shifting demand toward lower-end phones with less expensive chips. But its earnings still exceeded Wall Street expectations and the company said that it expected growth to resume in the current quarter. The company said it earned $516 million, or 35 cents a share, in the most recent quarter, compared with $585 million, or 36 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue fell to $3.19 billion, from $3.33 billion a year ago. Analysts were expecting profit of 31 cents a share on sales of $3.15 billion, according to a survey by Thomson Financial. The report was posted after markets closed Monday. The company’s shares closed down 9 cents, at $32.41, on the New York Stock Exchange but gained nearly 10 percent in after-hours electronic trading. Sphere: Related Blogs &amp; Articles More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/23/technology/23chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit Increases at Chip Maker<date>Published: January 23, 2007</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world’s biggest maker of chips for cellphones, said yesterday that its quarterly profit rose from a year ago because of a tax credit. The company, which makes chips for everything from calculators to the latest high-tech televisions, said its fourth-quarter profit was $668 million, or 45 cents a share, compared with $655 million, or 41 cents a share, in the year-ago quarter. Revenue rose to $3.46 billion, from $3.32 billion. In December, Texas Instruments cut its forecast for earnings from continuing operations to a range of 37 cents to 40 cents a share, and cut its revenue target to $3.35 billion to $3.50 billion. Its shares have fallen almost 16 percent in the last four months on investor concern that growth in the wireless industry is increasingly dependent on the sale of cheaper phones in emerging markets. The company said its challenges would continue in the first quarter because customers wanted lower levels of inventory, and growth in the wireless market was skewed to low-priced cellphones instead of higher-priced, full-featured phones. Texas Instruments said it expected first-quarter earnings of 28 cents to 34 cents a share on revenue of $2.95 billion to $3.2 billion. On average, analysts had expected first-quarter earnings of 35 cents a share on revenue of $3.3 billion. The company’s shares closed up 20 cents, to $28.59, yesterday in regular trading. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/24/technology/24chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit Rises 11% at Chip Maker<date>Published: October 24, 2006</date><text>Texas Instruments said yesterday that third-quarter profit rose 11 percent on increased sales of chips for the newest cellphones. It also said sales would miss analysts estimates this quarter. Net income increased to $702 million, or 46 cents a share, from $631 million, or 38 cents, a year earlier. Profit excluding some items was 45 cents, exceeding the average estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Sales rose 13 percent, to $3.76 billion, missing the $3.8 billion average estimate of analysts. The chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, has shed less-profitable units to focus on handsets, which are showing signs of slowing. Last week, the two largest handset makers, Nokia and Motorola, reported results that disappointed investors, partly from sales of cheaper, less-profitable models. Lower-price handsets and excess inventory in Japan are affecting sales, Mr. Templeton said in a statement. The companys shares fell 43 cents, to $31.45, in extended trading after the results came out. They gained 51 cents, to $31.88, in regular trading and are little changed this year. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/12/technology/12chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Narrows Its Forecast for Quarterly Results<date>Published: September 12, 2006</date><text>Texas Instruments, a maker of chips for mobile phones, narrowed its forecasts for third-quarter sales and profit yesterday amid signs of slower growth in handset demand. Sales will be $3.71 billion to $3.87 billion, compared with a July forecast of $3.63 billion to $3.95 billion, the company said. Profit is forecast to be 44 cents to 46 cents a share, compared with the 42 cents to 48 cents predicted earlier. The report may ease investors worries about a possible drop in demand for mobile phones. On Sept. 7, a smaller chip maker, National Semiconductor, reported that sales growth had slowed as cellphone makers cut back orders. Texas Instruments sales of chips for wireless products are running a little bit below seasonal trends, a company vice president, Ron Slaymaker, said on a conference call. Its in line with expectations, said Doug Freedman, an analyst for American Technology Research, who does not own the shares and who had predicted 47 cents a share. The margins are a little lower than I was expecting. Shares of Texas Instruments fell 35 cents, to $31.43, in extended trading yesterday. They rose 78 cents, to $31.78, in regular trading. More Articles in Technology »</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/27/automobiles/27FORD.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Unraveling the Mystery of Ford’s Fire-Prone Switches<date>Published: August 27, 2006</date><text>JUST two inches long, the Texas Instruments Model 9F924 speed control deactivation switch does not look like a menacing device. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic: Recalled Models Related T.S.B. to the Rescue Enlarge this Image Fordfires.com In a suit, Mr. Mohlis charged that a faulty cruise switch caused the fire, which killed his wife. But a sporadic malfunction in the switch that sparked engine fires stumped engineers at the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration for two years. The $20 switch, which shuts off the cruise control when a driver taps the brakes, became the subject of one of the most exhaustive and complex investigations in the agencys history. It created an expensive and embarrassing problem for the Ford Motor Company, which initially disputed suggestions that the switches were starting fires. When the repairs are made to the last of 6.7 million potentially defective switches, the Ford recall may be the second largest in United States history. Ive been through hundreds of investigations, and the complexities here were enormous, said Richard Boyd, chief of the medium- and heavy-duty vehicle division in the safety administrations office of defects investigation. Going in we had no idea. Was the switch causing the problem or was the vehicle? The answer, spelled out in a government report issued this month, turns out to be both. After an investigation that involved collecting damaged cruise control switches from across the country, installing them in Ford vehicles and waiting for them to cause fires, the agency determined that a phenomenon never seen before was to blame. Unbeknown to anybody, Mr. Boyd said, you can actually create a small vacuum when you let off the brakes. The force of that vacuum, investigators determined, was weakening a seal in the switches installed in millions of Ford pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles. With the plastic seal broken down, brake fluid was able to leak onto the electrical side of the switch and cause corrosion. Over time, that corrosion can build up, causing the switch to overheat and ignite an electrical fire. Government investigators began hearing complaints about the switches catching fire in 1999. That year, Ford recalled 279,000 cars from the 1992-93 model years: the Crown Victoria, Lincoln Town Car and Mercury Grand Marquis. Then, the problem was thought to be a manufacturing defect, but the recent investigation suggests that the vacuum-weakened seal was the culprit. The number of complaints declined, and the agency considered the issue resolved. In 2002, there were reports of more Crown Victoria fires. But after monitoring the situation for two years, the agency decided the number was too low to warrant a recall. Around the time the agency decided that a second Crown Victoria recall was not necessary, reports of fires in F-150 pickups began to trickle in. By June 2004, the agency had begun an inquiry into the truck fires. At first, investigators believed the switches were overheating because of a problem that originated in manufacturing the switch. The switch was in 16.5 million vehicles when the investigation began, but it appeared to overheat only in the 12.5 million that were wired so that the switch received power continuously, even when the ignition was off. Perplexing investigators further was the fact that the switch was malfunctioning in some models but not in others. Explorers, for example, had a relatively low fire rate; fires were more common in Expeditions. The simplest solution would have been to tell Ford to recall all 12.5 million vehicles with switches that always had power. But the agency did not yet understand the cause of the problem, and it cannot order a recall without making a solid case. The burden of proof in a defect investigation is on the government, Mr. Boyd said. So at the end of the day, if we went to Ford and said we want you to recall 12 million vehicles, Ford would say, Oh, really?  Fords response to the fires  first refusing to acknowledge that the switches posed a fire hazard, then conducting four recalls over seven years  angered fire victims and consumer advocates. It does not hurt their cases that Ford was accused of dragging its feet in other high-profile recalls. Its a cultural issue within Ford Motor Company, said Rob Ammons, a Houston lawyer who is suing Ford on behalf of an Iowa man, Earl Mohlis, whose wife, Dolly, died after their home caught fire. The lawsuit claims the mans 1996 Ford F-150 pickup caught fire in the garage. The blaze spread to the house, killing Mrs. Mohlis. Its the same exact pattern, Mr. Ammons said. You saw it with the Pinto. You saw it with the ignition fires a decade ago. You saw it with Firestone. And you see it here. In the handful of wrongful-death suits it faces, Ford denies that the switches caused the fires. With all the possible sources of a house fire, it is impossible to say the switch was the sole cause, Ford says. The company stopped using the switch in its vehicles in 2002. Kristen Kinley, a Ford spokeswoman, said there was no proof that the fires started in the vehicles. Based on the evidence that we found, it does not indicate that the fires originated at the truck. Ford did not acknowledge that the switches were causing fires until last September, when it recalled 4.5 million vehicles from the 1994-2002 model years, including Ford Broncos and Expeditions and Lincoln Navigators. But Ford and the government still did not know why the fires were starting, despite exhaustive efforts to find the cause. In a field in suburban Atlanta, with firefighters standing by, the traffic safety agency put faulty switches in four Ford vehicles and waited until they caught fire. Some of the defective switches were obtained by Bruce York, the chief investigator on the case, who went to dealerships and junkyards in the Washington area in search of used switches and samples of brake fluid. Government engineers then studied the burn patterns. The agency eventually sent defective switches to the National Institute of Standards and Technology, a federal agency, which determined that the switches were failing because the seal separating the electric side from the side containing brake fluid was wearing down. Why that was happening was still unclear, however. One possibility was a vacuum effect in the brake line, created when a driver releases the brake, that would cause the seal to invert and wear down over time. Engineers had never seen that happen in cars. This summer, they began to focus their investigation on what role that vacuum might play. So they looked at data on brake-line vacuum that had been collected in an unrelated investigation. They found that with the right amount of vacuum the seal would invert, and they determined that the seal was especially vulnerable in vehicles with more vacuum in their brake lines. That was when we looked at each other and said, I think we got it,  Mr. Boyd said. More Articles in Automobiles »</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/25/business/25chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Posts Strong Quarter<date>Published: July 25, 2006</date><text>DALLAS, July 24 (AP)  The semiconductor maker Texas Instruments said Monday that second-quarter operating profit rose on strong and broad-based sales of components for mobile phones and electronic devices. Including one-time items and proceeds from businesses it has sold, the company had net income of $2.39 billion, or $1.50 a share in the April-June period, up from $628 million, or 38 cents a share a year earlier. About $1.65 billion, however, came from selling a sensors business to private-equity groups. On an operating basis, Texas Instruments  the biggest maker of chips for mobile phones  said it earned $739 million, or 47 cents a share, after excluding parts of the business it has sold. That matched the forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial. Revenue rose 24 percent, to $3.7 billion from $2.97 billion a year ago. Analysts had forecast $3.68 billion in the just-finished quarter. The company, based in Dallas, said it expected to earn 42 to 48 cents a share in the third quarter  in line with Wall Street forecasts  on revenue of $3.63 billion to $3.95 billion. In trading before the income reports release, the companys shares rose 84 cents or 3.1 percent, to $27.84. They gained another $1.02, or 4 percent, in after-hours trading. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/business/yourmoney/09chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Cashing In Its Chips<date>Published: July 9, 2006</date><text>IT is not easy to beat Intel. Skip to next paragraph Multimedia Graphic: A Lone Star in Texas Allison V. Smith for The New York Times Richard K. Templeton, chief of Texas Instruments, says working with many companies gives it a head start as consumers warm up to new technologies. It is not easy to beat Intel if you are running a company that many analysts and investors have written off as moribund and out of touch. It is not easy to beat Intel if you are running a moribund company that loses its chief executive to a heart attack just as he embarks on a risky strategy. But Texas Instruments beat Intel. Twice. And Texas Instruments, an early darling of the technology industry that later lost its way, accomplished this feat in bravura fashion, not by eking out a few extra percentage points of market share from Intel, the legendary silicon-chip giant. Instead, Texas Instruments scored throw-in-the-towel, pack-up-the-lab and sell-the-division kinds of victories. That, in turn, has emboldened it. "Rarely has a leader of a previous era succeeded in the next period," said Richard K. Templeton, a former salesman and engineer who rose through Texas Instruments' ranks to become its chief executive in 2004. "I think there will be a leadership change. If not Texas Instruments, why not?" Why not, indeed. More to the point, how did Texas Instruments, which posted revenue of $13.4 billion last year, arrive at the enviable position of considering itself primed and ready to assume Intel's mantle as standard-bearer for the entire chip industry? In short, it pulled off its own resuscitation  a decade-long effort  by abandoning ill-fitting product lines, focusing more closely on its core integrated circuits business and linking up with large but underestimated companies eager to champion new uses for its chips. It dusted off a chip called a digital signal processor and convinced Nokia, which had yet to become the leader in cellphones, to make it the core of its products. It dusted off a second underutilized chip called a digital light processor and wooed Samsung Electronics, then a scrappy South Korean electronics company trying to conquer the American market, to use it in big-screen, high-definition televisions. "Their efforts to get back to their I.C. roots by shedding so many other business lines could be characterized as 'focused diversity,' " said David Carey, chief executive of Portelligent, a firm in Austin, Tex., that analyzes consumer electronics components. "Pretty much one basket, but a lot of different eggs." FOR his part, Mr. Templeton says he believes that the path Texas Instruments is following is not only logical but also unavoidable. He views the entire technology industry as beholden to 20-year product cycles that introduce seismic changes. The mainframe computer business gave way to the minicomputer and then to the personal computer. Now, he says, the industry has entered the era of the hand-held entertainment and communication device. "It's unforgiving," he advised. "You can argue that the PC era isn't ending, but it is." It has been a long road back for Texas Instruments, a company that at the dawn of the electronics era a half-century ago created the first commercial silicon transistor and invented the integrated circuit. But Intel and other aggressive tech companies began running circles around it by the mid-1980's because Texas Instruments' corporate attic was cluttered with underperforming businesses that had nothing to do with chips, like oil and gas exploration services and radar and missile guidance systems. By the early 1990's, Intel was forcing Texas Instruments out of the PC microprocessor business, and analysts considered the company roadkill in Intel's relentless drive to dominate computer chip manufacturing. That crushing defeat forced Texas Instruments to reorganize and eventually go for what became the next big thing: cellphones. Jerry R. Junkins, Texas Instruments' chief executive at the time, began an effort to slim down the bloated company: he started selling off nearly everything except the chip business. But in 1996, Mr. Junkins died of a heart attack on an overseas business trip. His successor, Thomas J. Engibous, finished the garage sale. Out went radar and missile-guidance systems, mold manufacturing, inspection equipment, software and chemicals. He forced the company to stick to its knitting by nurturing a chip that was the brains in the Speak &amp; Spell educational toy, the one E.T. used to phone home in Steven Spielberg's blockbuster film. It turns out that Mr. Engibous and the movie alien were both on to something. That chip, a digital signal processor, is now the core technology in cellphones. And the Texas Instruments manager who made it a cash cow by forging a tight relationship with Nokia was a tall, square-jawed engineer  Mr. Templeton. His deal with Nokia became a template for the company's future successes. He aligned Nokia's and Texas Instruments' interests by having his engineers customize the D.S.P. chip for Nokia's phone software. It wedded the Finnish company to Texas Instruments and the successful partnership attracted other phone makers to the Dallas chipmaker. Today, Texas Instruments controls 58 percent of the $8 billion market for wireless phone chips, the fastest-growing category in the semiconductor business, according to Forward Concepts, a market research firm. Texas Instruments' chips also allow a new generation of cellphones to display video images and capture network television broadcasts. The success of wireless phone chips secured Mr. Templeton the top job at Texas Instruments in 2004. (Mr. Engibous is now chairman.) 1 2 3Next Page » More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6DA1231F933A25755C0A9609C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">TODAY IN BUSINESS: CHIP MAKER SLIPS ON REPORT<date>Published: June 10, 2006</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's biggest mobile phone chip maker, had its 2007 profit estimate cut by a Citigroup analyst who cited concerns over slowing handset demand. The shares fell the most in three months. The cut, a day after Texas Instruments raised its forecasts for this quarter, reflected the chance that cellphone component sales might begin to drop in the fourth period, said the analyst, Glen Yeung. Shares of the company, based in Dallas, dropped $1.04, or 3.4 percent, to $29.68.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/19/business/19chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Posts 42% Gain in Profit<date>Published: April 19, 2006</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's biggest maker of chips for mobile phones, said yesterday that its first-quarter profit rose 42 percent as sales surged in India and China. Sales of handsets with Texas Instruments chips are soaring in India and China, and the company says worldwide cellphone demand may exceed analysts' estimates over the next five years. Nokia, Texas Instruments' biggest customer, has raised its forecast for growth in industry shipments to 15 percent this year from 10 percent. Texas Instruments said its first-quarter net income rose to $585 million, or 36 cents a share, from $411 million, or 24 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales increased 23 percent, to $3.33 billion, from $2.7 billion. In January, Texas Instruments agreed to sell its sensors and controls division to Bain Capital for $3 billion. The company classified the business as discontinued in yesterday's report. Income from continuing operations rose to $542 million, or 33 cents a share. Results included stock option costs of 4 cents a share. Shares of Texas Instruments gained $1.32, to $34 in regular trading. They rose $1.07, to $35.07, in late trading after the results came out. More Articles in Business »</text></article><article index="2" href="http://select.nytimes.com/2006/03/19/business/yourmoney/19gret.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Old Options Produce New Hangover<date /><text /></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/12/business/yourmoney/12mark.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Previews That Steal the Thunder<date>Published: March 12, 2006</date><text>ON Wall Street, the coming attractions can stir more interest than the features. The first quarter still has a couple of weeks to go, but by the time that companies report their earnings for the period, traders may no longer care. Skip to next paragraph Welcome to the preannouncement season, when the companies update the market with their best guesses of the earnings they will report when all the information and revenues are in. This "guidance," as these preannouncements are called, often moves stocks more than the real thing. When the actual earnings are reported, they tend to be near these predictions. Corporate earnings guidance may take on even more importance as this quarter wanes because analysts and market strategists have been trimming their estimates for many companies and sectors, and for the market as a whole. Operating profits for the companies in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index are expected to grow by 10.6 percent this year, but as recently as the end of last year the consensus forecast was a gain of 12.9 percent, David Rosenberg, an economist at Merrill Lynch, said in a note to investors. Some of the biggest downward revisions have been in the technology sector, he said, and recent guidance lower from such bellwethers as Intel and Texas Instruments has particularly soured investors' mood. Kenneth A. Shea, managing director for global equity research at S.&amp; P., said that these sneak peeks at earnings come from corporate executives' desire to let analysts down, or up, gently. "Companies often solicit analysts' input in terms of expectations on earnings and will guide up or down in the last week or two prior to the close of a quarter to make sure they are realistic in their expectations," he said. "They guide to a tight range, and analysts fall in line with that." Mr. Shea says some retailers are likely to make preannouncements this week, but he questions just how useful this dance of the pennies per share is. "You can argue whether corporate earnings should be such an important signal," he said. "It seems that there is an overemphasis on them." When it comes to the preannouncements, Mr. Shea's advice to buy-and-hold investors is not to get carried away. "If you're a short-term trader, it's very important, but for long-term investors probably not much," he said. Using the example of one very successful investor who tends to hold stocks for years, if not decades, he added, "I don't think Warren Buffett pays much attention to it." DATA WATCH Important economic reports this week will cover consumer prices in February and the current-account balance for the fourth quarter of 2005. A Bloomberg News poll of economists expects the reading on consumer prices, due Thursday, to be tame: a 0.2 percent increase in the core reading, excluding food and energy, and a 0.1 percent increase over all. The current-account deficit, to be announced on Tuesday, is forecast to have been anything but tame, expanding to $218 billion from $195.8 billion in the third quarter. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/08/business/08stox.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Shares Fall on Texas Instruments Forecast<date>Published: March 8, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell for a fourth day yesterday after Texas Instruments said first-quarter sales would fall short of its highest forecast and a government report signaled inflation may accelerate. "Texas Instruments is a bellwether," said John Wilson, co-director of equity strategy at Morgan Keegan &amp; Company. The estimate, he said, "reflects the economic slowdown we expect to see." The Dow Jones industrial average rose amid a pullback of emerging-market stocks and shares of smaller companies. The Dow industrials rose 22.10 points, or 0.2 percent, to 10,980.69. The S.&amp; P. 500 declined 2.38 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,275.88. The Nasdaq composite index, which gets 43 percent of its value from technology shares, slid 17.65 points, or 0.8 percent, to 2,268.38. Texas Instruments slumped $1.07, to $31.26. The company said first-quarter sales would be $3.22 billion to $3.35 billion, compared with an earlier forecast of as much as $3.38 billion. The company's projection comes less than a week after Intel cut its revenue estimate. Shares of Intel declined 24 cents, to $20.06. Nineteen of 20 chip-related stocks in the S.&amp; P. 500 fell. National Semiconductor, a maker of chips used to increase the battery life of cellphones, lost $1.07, to $28. Broadcom, which produces chips for consumer products, slid $2.03, to $45.85. "There's not a broad advance in the business prospects for companies across the technology area," said Jeff Layman, a portfolio manager at BKD Wealth Advisors. "That's been symptomatic of the whole technology area here in the last couple of months." Telecommunications stocks slumped 1.6 percent for the steepest loss among 10 industry groups as investors doubted that more mergers will follow AT&amp;T's bid for BellSouth. Stocks slid after the Labor Department's report showed productivity fell for the first time since 2001 and labor costs rose the most in a year. The figures suggested the Federal Reserve might continue to raise interest rates. "The Fed is still in play," Joseph Besecker, president of Emerald Asset Management in San Francisco, said. "The market is really focusing still on interest rates." General Motors gained on a proposal to reduce pension costs for salaried workers. Shares of G.M. rose 48 cents, to $20.29. The company said it would freeze the defined-benefit pension plans for its 36,000 salaried workers in the United States to save $420 million before taxes next year and reduce its year-end 2006 pension liability by $1.6 billion. Energy shares fell after the April contract for crude oil declined 1.3 percent, to $61.58 a barrel, on speculation that the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries will leave production targets unchanged at a meeting today. A gauge of energy stocks in the S.&amp; P. 500 slumped 1.2 percent. ConocoPhillips declined $1.10, to $59.48. Myogen, which develops drugs for hypertension and other cardiovascular diseases, lost $6.08, to $35.23. The company said it would receive up to $100 million from GlaxoSmithKline as the drug makers work on two medicines that treat a lung condition. Some investors may be disappointed by the terms of the deal, said Louis Lemos, an analyst at Variant Research. In the bond market, the 10-year Treasury note rose 7/32, to a price of 988/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, declined to 4.72 percent from 4.75 percent on Monday. Following are the results of yesterday's auctions of six-day cash management bills and four-week Treasury bills: More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/24/business/24chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit Up 34% at Chip Maker in 4th Quarter<date>Published: January 24, 2006</date><text>By Bloomberg News Texas Instruments, one of the world's largest makers of cellphone chips, said yesterday that fourth-quarter profit rose 34 percent. Net income was $655 million, or 40 cents a share, compared with $490 million, or 28 cents a share, in the year-earlier period, the company said. Sales rose to $3.59 billion, from $3.15 billion. The chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said sales were at the lower end of the company's December forecast, however, because assembly and testing centers could not keep up with demand. Last week, Intel reported revenue that trailed its own forecast. "People were too optimistic," said Alex Vallecillo, who helps manage $18 billion at Allegiant Funds, based in Cleveland, which holds Texas Instrument shares. "This stock will experience some weakness like the others have in recent weeks." Texas Instruments reported its results after the close of regular trading. The company, based in Dallas, fell 63 cents, to $31.07, in late trading after a close of $31.70, up 4 cents. Texas Instruments said last month that profit would be 38 cents to 40 cents a share, at the top end of its previous forecast. The company also predicted sales of $3.56 billion to $3.71 billion. The company forecast first-quarter sales of $3.11 billion to $3.38 billion. The average estimate of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial was $3.46 billion. The company also forecast earnings of 29 cents to 33 cents a share. Mr. March said the discrepancy in revenue may be related to the sale of Texas Instruments' sensors and controls unit. The company's forecast does not include revenue from the sale of that unit, which is to be completed in the first half of this year. Texas Instruments' chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, 47, agreed earlier this month to sell the sensors and controls business, which makes parts for air conditioners and cars, to Bain Capital for $3 billion. Shedding that unit may help Texas Instruments focus on consumer electronics. The company sells digital light-processing chips used in high-definition televisions. A Texas Instruments spokesman, Ron Slaymaker, also said the company was gaining market share in chips for mobile phones with features like music and video players. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/10/business/10chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Is Selling Its Sensors Unit for $3 Billion<date>Published: January 10, 2006</date><text>Texas Instruments said yesterday that it had reached a deal to sell its sensors and controls unit to a private equity firm, Bain Capital, for $3 billion in cash, ending an auction that had attracted several private equity firms as bidders. The division, which has $1 billion in annual revenue and 5,400 employees, is a small part of Texas Instruments and is not closely tied to the company's main business of making semiconductors for cellphones and other electronics. Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas, put the unit up for sale in September. Morgan Stanley ran the auction. Reports that Bain Capital was near a deal for the unit surfaced about two weeks ago. The division, based in Attleboro, Mass., makes temperature and lighting sensors and controls for use in homes, cars, planes and industrial settings. A little more than half its sales come from outside the United States. Texas Instruments has been divesting businesses that are either not directly related to its dominant position in the wireless chip business or not successful enough to help lift the average profit margins of all its businesses. The company has sold divisions that made memory and personal computer chips. The chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said, "The semiconductor business has not only been growing much faster but the profitability in that business has also expanded very strongly, exceeding the profitability of our sensors and controls business." Mr. March said the company had no specific plans for the $3 billion, but he noted that Texas Instruments had used excess cash in recent times to increase its dividend, buy back shares and make acquisitions. He declined to say if the company planned to sell other businesses. Bain Capital, based in Boston, said that it would keep the division's current management after the transaction, which has been approved by the board of Texas Instruments and is expected to be completed before July. A managing director at Bain, Stephen M. Zide, said, "There is a considerable amount of value that can be unlocked by focusing solely on growing sensors and controls' competitive position" in a market that it already leads. The sale does not include the radio frequency identification business, which is part of the sensors division. That fast-growing technology is being used by companies and governments to keep track of products, assets and even people with transmitters that send signals over short distances. Shares of Texas Instruments fell 27 cents yesterday, to $34.18. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/23/business/23deal.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Talks to Buy Sensor Maker<date>Published: December 23, 2005</date><text>Bain Capital, the private equity firm, is near a deal to acquire the sensors and controls unit of Texas Instruments for more than $2.4 billion, executives involved in the deal said last night. Texas Instruments has been locked in exclusive talks with Bain for more than a week, the executives said, and an announcement of a deal is expected within days. Texas Instruments put its sensors and controls business - which makes temperature sensors for automobiles - up for sale in September. Among the unit's customers are automakers, making it susceptible to any downturn in that industry. The company hired Morgan Stanley to run the auction. The sale of the unit comes as Texas Instruments is seeking to shed noncore assets. Still, the business contributed more than $1 billion in revenue last year. The auction attracted several equity firms, including Thomas H. Lee and Texas Pacific. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/08/business/08chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Strong Sales Bolster Profit at Chip Maker<date>Published: December 8, 2005</date><text>Texas Instruments, one of the biggest makers of cellphone chips, said yesterday that profit this quarter would be at the top end of its forecast, partly on increased holiday sales of new handsets. Fourth-quarter profit will rise to 38 to 40 cents a share, compared with the company's October forecast of 36 to 40 cents. The range of its sales forecast was narrowed to $3.56 billion to $3.71 billion, from $3.42 billion to $3.72 billion, the company said. Texas Instruments said demand for chips for wireless devices and for TV's was exceeding its expectations. Holiday shoppers are buying electronics, including new phones that use twice as many chips as earlier models. The company's forecast equates to profit growth of as much as 43 percent from a year earlier. "The electronics market is healthy," said David Wu, an analyst at Global Crown Capital in San Francisco. "Phones are selling well, and PC's are selling well." Ron Slaymaker, vice president for investor relations at Texas Instruments, said yesterday on a conference call with investors, "We're seeing strength in a range of areas." The company also raised the lower end of the forecast for revenue at its semiconductor unit. It now expects sales of $3.2 billion to $3.33 billion, compared with an earlier range of $3.08 billion to $3.33 billion. Shares of Texas Instruments rose 27 cents, to close at $33.56 on the New York Stock Exchange. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/25/technology/25chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Profit Up 12%<date>Published: October 25, 2005</date><text>By Bloomberg News Texas Instruments, which makes chips for cellphones, said yesterday that third-quarter profit rose 12 percent but that sales in its current quarter were lagging Wall Street estimates. Net income rose to $631 million, or 38 cents a share, from $563 million, or 32 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 10 percent, to $3.59 billion, from $3.25 billion, the company said. Inventory slipped lower than the company wanted in the quarter, presenting "challenges if fourth-quarter demand surges," the chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said in an interview. New handsets require at least twice as many chips to play videos and download data. Phone orders also soared in emerging markets like China. Profit this quarter will be 36 cents to 40 cents a share on sales of $3.43 billion to $3.72 billion, Texas Instruments projected. Analysts expected profit of 41 cents and sales of $3.63 billion, according to Thomson First Call. Shares of Texas Instruments fell $1.27, or 4.1 percent, to $29.65 in extended trading after the report, according to ECN. They gained 40 cents, to $30.92 a share, at the close of regular trading on the New York Stock Exchange. The company's chip sales gained 13 percent, to $3.14 billion. The sensors and controls unit added 1.4 percent, to $280 million, and the unit that makes calculators fell 6.8 percent, to $177 million. Profit excluding some items was 41 cents a share in the third quarter, beating the 40-cent average of Wall Street analysts. Demand soared in the wireless business in the quarter, leading Texas Instruments to raise its forecasts in September. The unit, which accounts for about a third of sales, makes chips used in mobile phones from Nokia and Motorola, two of the world's top handset manufacturers. The higher-than-expected sales caught Texas Instruments off guard, and it failed to begin making enough chips to keep inventory at "a desirable level," Mr. March said in the interview. More Articles in Technology &gt;</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/08/technology/08chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Will Offer a Video Technology Platform<date>Published: September 8, 2005</date><text>Texas Instruments succeeded in transforming itself from the best-known maker of calculators to the largest seller of chips for cellphones. Now it wants to repeat that success in the market for video chips. Skip to next paragraph Forum: Technology and the Internet The company plans todayto announce an all-in-one video chip technology that will make it easier for electronics producers to design and manufacture video products including digital cameras, video phones and portable media players. Its chief executive, Richard K. Templeton, said in an interview that digital video products are now limited by short battery life, long development time and high price. Texas Instruments' new video technology, called Da Vinci, aims to solve those problems by providing manufacturers with an integrated set of chips, software and development tools. This approach, it said, could help keep production costs down while ensuring that devices are compatible. Video chips are fast becoming an important market. "The opportunity in the video world looks a lot like what it once did in the wireless world," Mr. Templeton said. As the third-largest semiconductor company, Texas Instruments supplies nearly 60 percent of the chips for cellphones. It expects to have Da Vinci technology, including processors, software and tools, ready to market by the end of the year. In an era when companies are increasingly selling technology "platforms," rather than individual components, Texas Instruments' approach with Da Vinci is no surprise to analysts. Its announcement is coming two weeks after Intel announced its own new platform for digital home electronics, called Viiv. With Viiv, which will be marketed in the first half of 2006, Intel hopes to make it easier for users to share digital content over networks and make their personal computers compatible with other electronic devices. IdaRose Sylvester, senior analyst with IDC in San Mateo, Calif., said: "As semiconductor companies, they are both trying to take the reins of the digital home. Having a brand identity in this market is extremely important." Like Intel's Viiv platform, Da Vinci is a repackaging of existing technology, along with some new components, and requires the cooperation of other component makers. "The launch will be more about platforms and a brand than a revolutionary new product," Ms. Sylvester said. Both companies hope to dominate the chip market for digital home devices but are taking different approaches, with Texas Instruments coming from the wireless hand-held device industry and Intel from the personal computer industry. More Articles in Technology &gt;</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/28/books/review/28THOMPSO.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">'The Man Behind the Microchip': The Next Small Thing<date>Published: August 28, 2005</date><text>''If nearly any invention is examined closely enough, it almost immediately becomes apparent that the innovation was not the product of a single mind, even if it is attributed to one,'' Leslie Berlin writes. ''Invention is best understood as a team effort.'' Skip to next paragraph Grinnell College/From ''The Man Behind the Microchip'' Robert Noyce. THE MAN BEHIND THE MICROCHIP Robert Noyce and the Invention of Silicon Valley. By Leslie Berlin. 402 pp. Oxford University Press. $30. Forum: Book News and Reviews Right. In America, we're conditioned to valorize the individual genius. To some extent we owe this caricature to biographies of famous inventors, because they play to the lone-gunman theory of brilliance. But many increasingly complex pieces of high-tech engineering -- the Apple computer, the mobile phone, the Web browser -- were the collaborative products of large teams, each person doing a small piece of work: less ''eureka'' than barn-raising. This leads Berlin into a conundrum in her first book, ''The Man Behind the Microchip: Robert Noyce and the Invention of Silicon Valley.'' For the last 40 years, Noyce, a founder of Intel, has been famous as ''the inventor of the integrated circuit,'' that infinitesimal sliver of silicon and metal that forms the core of a computer's brain. This achievement was so remarkable that Noyce (1927-90) was hailed in the press for decades, awarded a National Medal of Science by President Carter, and made wealthy. An inspiring tale! Except for one thing: Noyce didn't singlehandedly invent the integrated circuit. Texas Instruments produced a working model years before Intel did; and even when Noyce's company finally released its rather superior chip, it was a team of Noyce's employees who did the hands-on and theoretical work, with Noyce serving mostly as inspiration and administration. ''Noyce had almost nothing to do with building the device,'' Berlin herself concludes. This is not to say that Noyce is an unworthy subject of a book; he's quite intriguing. But trying to write a biography of a guy who didn't do what he's most famous for gently bedevils Berlin, and her book morphs inadvertently into a sort of detective story: precisely what did Robert Noyce actually do? One thing is certain: Noyce was a prodigy in the study of transistors. Transistors, the first step in the modern computer age, were invented in 1947; and William Shockley, John Bardeen and Walter H. Brattain shared the 1956 Nobel Prize in physics for the achievement. Transistors worked like little electronic off-on switches: put voltage in one way, and the transistor would amplify the signal; send it in the other way, and it would shut the flow down entirely. Everyone could see how useful these devices would be, but the physics of how transistors worked were poorly understood. At M.I.T., Noyce in his 20's became a groundbreaking expert. He quickly drew the attention of Shockley, who hired him to help make specialized transistors for military and business-machine companies like I.B.M. This is where Berlin is best: she superbly evokes the hacker inventiveness of Shockley and his gang. Their work was more alchemy than science; they'd shove transistors in furnaces and bombard them with chemical fumes, with few clues as to what would work. (The engineers referred to these processes as ''witches' brew'' and ''black magic.'') Shockley was a character of almost necromantic strangeness: an egomaniac who insulted his staff (''Are you sure that you actually went to school?'' Berlin paraphrases a characteristic assault) and at one point became convinced a competitor had planted a booby trap in his lab. After nearly two years in which Shockley was unable to forge a corporate direction, his brilliant central group left en masse to found Fairchild Semiconductor. They picked Noyce to lead them. He radiated a mix of laid-back calm and confidence rare among engineers, which served him well in the commercial deal-cutting that made them all rich. Noyce hated confrontation: he preferred to give his brainy employees wide latitude to pursue oddball projects, convinced that smart nerds would always wind up doing something interesting and valuable. His distaste for conflict eventually destroyed his marriage; unable to grapple with the unhappiness of his wife, who, university educated and born to a wealthy New England family, was slowly driven mad with ennui by her child-centered suburban life, he retreated into a risky affair, which ended when one of his children actually found his mistress in bed with him. At work, though, Noyce's surfer disposition formed the perfect bridge between his prickly geeks and the bean-counting business world that relied on transistors. ''Your charisma is scary,'' an assistant told him. ''Use it wisely.'' 1 2Next Page &gt; Clive Thompson is a contributing writer for The New York Times Magazine. More Articles in Books &gt;</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/26/business/26chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Profit Rises 42% at Chip Maker<date>Published: July 26, 2005</date><text>DALLAS, July 25 (AP) - Texas Instruments, one of the world's largest semiconductor makers, said Monday that its second-quarter profit climbed 42 percent on stronger sales of core chip products and educational calculators. Quarterly income rose to $628 million, or 38 cents a share, from $441 million, or 25 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a tax benefit, the company said it earned 32 cents a share in the quarter. The results beat the company's forecast made in June of 27 cents to 30 cents a share, and analysts' estimates for profit of 29 cents a share, according to Thomson First Call. The company's stock rose nearly 6 percent in after-hours trading. Revenue was $3.24 billion, relatively unchanged from a year ago but up 9 percent from the first quarter. Texas Instruments said the increase from the first quarter was driven by stronger demand for analog and digital signal processing semiconductor products, as well as seasonal demand for educational calculators. Semiconductor orders rose 15 percent from the first quarter, the company said. Texas Instruments said it expected third-quarter earnings of 31 cents to 35 cents a share, or 34 cents to 38 cents a share excluding the cost of employee stock options. Revenue will range from $3.29 billion to $3.56 billion, the company said. Shares of Texas Instruments rose $1.75, or 5.7 percent, to $32.35 a share, in after-hours trading, after falling 16 cents to $30.60 during the regular trading session. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/22/business/22kilby.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Jack S. Kilby, an Inventor of the Microchip, Is Dead at 81<date>Published: June 22, 2005</date><text>Jack S. Kilby, an electrical engineer whose invention of the integrated circuit gave rise to the information age and heralded an explosion of consumer electronics products in the last 50 years, from personal computers to cellphones, died Monday in Dallas. He was 81. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Henrick Montomery/Pressens Bild Jack Kilby, inventor of the integrated circuit, died on Monday. He was 81. Mark Earthy/Scanpix, via Reuters Jack S. Kilby received the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2000. Mr. Kilby claimed more than 60 patents. Texas Instruments, via Reuters Jack S. Kilby created this, his first integrated circuit, in 1958. His death, after a brief battle with cancer, was announced yesterday by Texas Instruments, the Dallas-based electronics company where he worked for a quarter-century. The integrated circuit that Mr. Kilby designed shortly after arriving at Texas Instruments in 1958 served as the basis for modern microelectronics, transforming a technology that permitted the simultaneous manufacturing of a mere handful of transistors into a chip industry that routinely places billions of Lilliputian switches in the area of a fingernail. His achievement - the integration - yielded a thin chip of crystal connecting previously separate components like transistors, resistors and capacitors within a single device. For that creation, commonly called the microchip, he was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2000. During his career at Texas Instruments he claimed more than 60 patents and was also one of the inventors of the hand-held calculator and the thermal printer. But it was Mr. Kilby's invention of the integrated circuit that most broadly shaped the electronic era. "It's hard to find a place where the integrated circuit doesn't affect your life today," Richard K. Templeton, Texas Instruments' president and chief executive officer, said in an interview yesterday. "That's how broad its impact is." It is an impact, Mr. Kilby said, that was largely unexpected. "We expected to reduce the cost of electronics, but I don't think anybody was thinking in terms of factors of a million," he said in an undated interview cited by Texas Instruments. The remarkable acceleration of the manufacturing process based on the integrated circuit was later described by Gordon E. Moore, co-founder of the Intel Corporation, whose partner, Robert N. Noyce, invented another version of the integrated circuit just months after Mr. Kilby. In 1965, three years after the first commercial integrated circuits came to market, Dr. Moore observed that the number of transistors on a circuit was doubling at regular intervals and would do so far into the future. The observation, which came to be known as Moore's law, became the defining attribute of the chip-making industry, centered in what is now known as Silicon Valley, where Intel was based, rather than in Dallas. That was partly because Dr. Noyce's version of the integrated circuit, using silicon and based on a photolithographic printing technology known as the planar process, was easier to manufacture than Mr. Kilby's original invention, which employed germanium and used individual wires. In 1959 Mr. Kilby and Dr. Noyce, then with Fairchild Semiconductor, were named as inventors in their companies' applications for patents for the integrated circuit. After years of legal battles, Fairchild and Texas Instruments decided to cross-license their technologies, ultimately creating a world information industries market now worth more than $1 trillion annually. Dr. Noyce died in 1990. Dr. Moore remembered Mr. Kilby as a tall - he was 6-foot-6 - and gentle man with whom he would occasionally socialize while attending technical meetings. "He was mild mannered," Dr. Moore recalled in a telephone interview yesterday, "but I would never worry when I was walking down the street with him in New York City." Mr. Kilby's contribution came in an era when manufacturing industries were hunting for new approaches to miniaturization for reasons of both cost and performance. It was a drive that began during World War II and pushed beyond military uses into consumer products in the postwar era. He began his career in 1947 with the Centralab division of Globe Union Inc. in Milwaukee, developing ceramic-based silk-screen circuits for consumer electronic products. Michael Riordan, co-author of "Crystal Fire: The Invention of the Transistor and the Birth of the Information Age" (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1998), noted that Globe Union and Texas Instruments were both pioneers in miniaturization, and that Mr. Kilby "came to T.I. with a drive to make things small." Mr. Kilby had also been sent by Globe Union to attend an early workshop held by the Bell Laboratories of A.T.&amp; T. to familiarize the technical world with the transistor in the early 1950's. It was Mr. Kilby who first pulled the idea of miniaturization together with the transistor. A lifelong optimist who rarely showed signs of anger, according to his daughter, Janet Kilby Cameron, Mr. Kilby took his Nobel Prize in stride. When asked what he did after learning of the award, he said simply, "I made coffee." Jack St. Clair Kilby was born in Jefferson City, Mo., on Nov. 8, 1923, to Hubert and Vina Kilby. He grew up in Great Bend, Kan., and was exposed early on to the world of engineers: his father ran the local electric utility. He decided in high school that he would become an electrical engineer and applied to M.I.T., even then the mecca for aspiring engineers. He took a train to Cambridge, Mass., but fell slightly short in his score on the entrance exam in June 1941 and was unable to enroll. A few months later he joined the Army and was assigned to a radio repair shop at an outpost on a tea plantation in northeast India. After the war he attended college on the G.I. Bill of Rights. After receiving a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering from the University of Illinois and a master's from the University of Wisconsin, he went to work for Globe Union. He arrived at Texas Instruments in 1958 and during his first summer, working with borrowed equipment, improvised a working integrated circuit. A successful laboratory demonstration of the first simple microchip took place on Sept. 12, 1958. He formally retired from the company in 1983 but continued his association as a consultant. His other awards included both the National Medal of Science and the National Medal of Technology, the highest technical awards given by the United States government. His wife, Barbara Annegers Kilby, died in 1982. In addition to Ms. Cameron, of Palisade, Colo., Mr. Kilby is survived by another daughter, Ann Kilby, of Austin, Tex., and five granddaughters. More Articles in Business &gt;</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/08/technology/08chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Raises Forecasts<date>Published: June 8, 2005</date><text>ALLAS, June 7 (AP) - Texas Instruments raised its second-quarter earnings forecast Tuesday and refined its revenue outlook, citing higher demand for semiconductor products and seasonal growth for educational calculators. The company said it expected earnings of 27 cents to 30 cents a share for the quarter, up from a prior forecast of 25 cents to 29 cents. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expect the company to earn 27 cents a share. Texas Instruments also projected second-quarter revenue of $3.12 billion to $3.24 billion, raising the low end of its forecast from $3 billion. The company forecast higher revenue ranges for semiconductors, sensors and controls, and educational and productivity products. Analysts expect the company to post revenue of $3.14 billion for the quarter. Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas, released its forecast after the close of market trading and its shares rose 57 cents, or 2.1 percent, in after-hours trading.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/19/business/businessspecial3/19texas.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Posts Increase of 12% in First-Quarter Income<date>Published: April 19, 2005</date><text>exas Instruments, whose processors run more than half the mobile phones sold last year, said yesterday that first-quarter net income rose 12 percent and profit might exceed analysts' estimates this period. Net income increased to $411 million, or 24 cents a share, from $367 million, or 21 cents, a year earlier. Analysts had expected Texas Instruments to earn 23 cents. Advertisement Sales rose 1.2 percent, to $2.97 billion, from $2.94 billion, the Dallas-based company said. The increased profit forecast by Texas Instruments might help allay some investors' concerns about demand for consumer electronics products, coming after disappointing results from I.B.M. and Samsung Electronics. The chief financial officer, Kevin P. March, said in an interview that chip demand was improving. The company cut costs to help balance any slowing in demand. "We should collectively breathe a sigh of relief when it comes to Texas Instruments," said Alex Vallecillo, who helps manage $7 billion, including shares of Texas Instruments, at the National City Investment Company in Cleveland. "It's good news that the company was able to deliver on expectations. Many companies, including I.B.M. last week, weren't able to do that." Texas Instruments said profit this quarter would be 25 cents to 29 cents a share on sales of $3 billion to $3.24 billion. Analysts expected 26 cents, the average of 33 estimates in a Thomson Financial survey, on sales of $3.17 billion. The company had net income of 25 cents and sales of $3.24 billion in last year's second quarter. Shares of Texas Instruments rose as high as $24.35 in extended trading after the announcement. They gained 16 cents, to $22.92, in regular trading.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/08/technology/08chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Lowers Its Sights on Sales<date>Published: March 8, 2005</date><text>y Bloomberg News Texas Instruments, one of the world's biggest makers of cellphone semiconductors, said yesterday that first-quarter sales and profit would be at the low end of forecasts as demand for chips used in televisions falls and clients deplete inventory. In a scheduled update, the company said yesterday that sales would be $2.91 billion to $3.03 billion, compared with the $2.9 billion to $3.14 billion predicted in January. Net income will be 22 cents to 24 cents a share, after a forecast of 22 cents to 26 cents, the company said. Chip orders for large-screen televisions and projectors are trailing predictions, Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas, said. Big phone makers have also reduced purchases to sell off inventory built last year, analysts said. Texas Instruments has been speeding up production this quarter, anticipating higher growth rates from top clients including Nokia. "It takes a while for inventories to get cleaned out," said Brett Crawford, an analyst in Chicago at Mesirow Financial, which owns the stock and manages $10 billion. "Investors had started to buy back in, possibly a little too early." The digital light processor chips for consumer electronics account for 9 percent of total sales for Texas Instruments, an analyst at Deutsche Bank Securities, Ben Lynch, said in New York. The TV chips are usually more profitable than other semiconductors, a company vice president, Ron Slaymaker, said in a conference call. Analysts expected profit of 24 cents a share on $3.04 billion in sales, the average estimates in a Thomson Financial survey. Texas Instruments faces stiffer competition from Qualcomm, its nearest rival in the mobile-phone chip business, as they pursue sales of processors for higher-speed handsets. Qualcomm's largest client is Samsung Electronics, a leading cellphone maker. Texas Instruments said in February that it had won its first order for an applications processor from Samsung. Qualcomm, based in San Diego, said fiscal second-quarter sales might trail the company's January forecast and profit might be higher than expected. Texas Instruments is reducing its reliance on Nokia, which accounted for less than 10 percent of Texas Instruments' sales in 2004, compared with about 14 percent in 2003.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/17/technology/circuits/17soon.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">With a Palm-Size Projector, Presentations Can Go Places<date>Published: February 17, 2005</date><text>hile portable digital projectors have slimmed down over the last few years, they are still largely a business tool. But now after shrinking a projector to palm size, Mitsubishi is hoping to appeal to consumers who want the ability to present spur-of-the-moment digital slide shows or other displays. The PocketProjector 8482, which will be available in July for $700, uses a new, slightly smaller version of the Texas Instruments Digital Light Processing chip to create its images. The key to its size reduction, however, is that it relies on light-emitting diodes as its light source. They are much smaller than conventional bulbs and allow Mitsubishi to do away with a cooling fan. The projector produces an SVGA (800 by 600 pixels) image, and is designed to be used at short distances. From little more than a foot away, for example, it will project a 20-inch-diagonal image. James Chan, director of projector product marketing for Mitsubishi Digital Electronics America, said the PocketProjector works best when the drapes are drawn and the lights are dimmed. The projector can connect to many digital still and video cameras. For the ultimate in portability, an optional battery pack ($150) will be available. Ian Austen</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/29/national/29key.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Graduate Cryptographers Unlock Code of 'Thiefproof' Car Key<date>Published: January 29, 2005</date><text>ALTIMORE - Matthew Green starts his 2005 Ford Escape with a duplicate key he had made at Lowe's. Nothing unusual about that, except that the automobile industry has spent millions of dollars to keep him from being able to do it. Mr. Green, a graduate student at Johns Hopkins University, is part of a team that plans to announce on Jan. 29 that it has cracked the security behind "immobilizer" systems from Texas Instruments Inc. The systems reduce car theft, because vehicles will not start unless the system recognizes a tiny chip in the authorized key. They are used in millions of Fords, Toyotas and Nissans. All that would be required to steal a car, the researchers said, is a moment next to the car owner to extract data from the key, less than an hour of computing, and a few minutes to break in, feed the key code to the car and hot-wire it. An executive with the Texas Instruments division that makes the systems did not dispute that the Hopkins team had cracked its code, but said there was much more to stealing a car than that. The devices, said the executive, Tony Sabetti, "have been fraud-free and are likely to remain fraud-free." The implications of the Hopkins finding go beyond stealing cars. Variations on the technology used in the chips, known as RFID for radio frequency identification, are widely used. Similar systems deduct highway tolls from drivers' accounts and restrict access to workplaces. Wal-Mart is using the technology to track inventory, the Food and Drug Administration is considering it to foil drug counterfeiting, and the medical school at the University of California, Los Angeles, plans to implant chips in cadavers to curtail unauthorized sale of body parts. The Johns Hopkins researchers say that if other radio frequency ID systems are vulnerable, the new field could offer far less security than its proponents promise. The computer scientists are not doing R.&amp;D. for the Mafia. Aviel D. Rubin, a professor of computer science who led the team, said his three graduate students did what security experts often do: showed the lack of robust security in important devices that people use every day. "What we find time and time again is the security is overlooked and not done right," said Dr. Rubin, who has exposed flaws in electronic voting systems and wireless computer networks. David Wagner, an assistant professor of computer science at the University of California, Berkeley, who reviewed a draft of a paper by the Hopkins team, called it "great research," adding, "I see it as an early warning" for all radio frequency ID systems. The "immobilizer" technology used in the keys has been an enormous success. Texas Instruments alone has its chips in an estimated 150 million keys. Replacing the key on newer cars can cost hundreds of dollars, but the technology is credited with greatly reducing auto theft. - Early versions of in-key chips were relatively easy to clone, but the Texas Instruments chips are considered to be among the best. Still, the amount of computing the chip can do is restricted by the fact that it has no power of its own; it builds a slight charge from an electromagnetic field from the car's transmitter. Cracking the system took the graduate students three months, Dr. Rubin said. "There was a lot of trial and error work with, every once in a while, a little 'Aha!' " The Hopkins researchers got unexpected help from Texas Instruments itself. They were able to buy a tag reader directly from the company, which sells kits for $280 on its Web site. They also found a general diagram on the Internet, from a technical presentation by the company's German division. The researchers wrote in the paper describing their work that the diagram provided "a useful foothold" into the system. (The Hopkins paper, which is online at www.rfidanalysis.org, does not provide information that might allow its work to be duplicated. The researchers discovered a critically important fact: the encryption algorithm used by the chip to scramble the challenge uses a relatively short code, known as a key. The longer the code key, which is measured in bits, the harder it is to crack any encryption system. "If you were to tell a cryptographer that this system uses 40-bit keys, you'd immediately conclude that the system is weak and that you'd be able to break it," said Ari Juels, a scientist with the research arm of RSA Security, which financed the team and collaborated with it. Continued 1 | 2 | Next&gt;&gt;</text></article><article index="9" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DB163BF935A15752C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Earnings: Sales Rise For Chip Maker<date>Published: January 26, 2005</date><text>Texas Instruments Inc., the chip maker, said that fourth-quarter net income declined, but that holiday demand for handsets raised revenue to its highest level in nine years. Net income fell to $490 million, or 28 cents a share, from $512 million, or 29 cents a share, a year earlier. Sales rose 14 percent to $3.15 billion.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/24/technology/24chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Texas Instruments Integrates Cellphone Tasks on One Chip<date>Published: January 24, 2005</date><text>exas Instruments will announce today that it has integrated most of the computing functions of a mobile phone onto a single microchip, an innovation that may lead to lower manufacturing costs and improvements like longer battery life and higher data transfer rates. The company plans to have the more integrated semiconductor widely available by the middle of 2006, making it the first major manufacturer to produce an integrated cellphone chip for the mass market, according to industry analysts. Advertisement At present, the components of a mobile phone include numerous specialized chips that control functions like sending and receiving radio frequencies, managing power and overseeing the phone's basic computing functions. "This isn't an incremental step," said Bill Krenik, manager of wireless advanced architectures for Texas Instruments. "It's a big leap forward." Texas Instruments is not the only company to have integrated much of that technology on a single chip. Last November, Qualcomm said it had developed integrated technology. However, its product may be in the mass market somewhat later than the Texas Instruments technology, said Alex Slawsby, an industry analyst with IDC, a research firm. Qualcomm said its chip would be available in the second half of 2006. Mr. Slawsby said that the advantage of such chips might come initially in the production of inexpensive entry-level phones. The integrated chip, Mr. Slawsby said, would allow phone manufacturers to more quickly and cheaply produce handsets that could be sold to emerging markets. Despite the advances toward integration of functions onto a single chip, some will remain separate. Specifically, the major chipmakers have not yet figured out how to economically integrate the memory, a specialized chip that stores phone numbers and other information. A significant advancement is that the technology integrates two basic chips, Mr. Krenik said, the one that controls sending and receiving radio frequencies and the one that controls basic computing functions.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/23/technology/circuits/23next.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Researchers Seek Truth in the Secret Life of the Battery<date>Published: December 23, 2004</date><text>RIVERS can trust the fuel gauges in their cars to tell them whether the tank is half full or down to its last gallon. But laptop owners don't have the same security when they check the time left in a lithium-ion battery. A click on the battery icon may suggest that 20 minutes are left when, in reality, only a few minutes remain. Advertisement Now Texas Instruments researchers have come up with a monitor they say laptop users can trust to measure remaining battery energy accurately. The new gauges should help people avoid unexpected shutdowns that could result in a loss of data. "Whether the battery is new or old, you will know within 1 percent accuracy what the remaining energy is," said Scott Eisenhart, director of battery management at the company. In the technology, each battery pack contains a two-chip system that can constantly calculate the remaining energy. The chip sets have algorithms that take into account impedance, the opposition to electrical current flow, which changes with conditions like age, temperature and use. Based on mathematical models of lithium-ion chemistry, the chips use these impedance measurements to adjust predictions of the charge remaining in the battery. The new chips have not yet proven themselves in consumer products. They will not be available in laptops, Texas Instruments' first target for the new technology, until the middle of 2005 or later. "We're ready to go," said Dave Heacock, vice president for portable power management, "but our customers need some time to engineer the gauges into their new products." If proven successful, the new gauges could be used in other devices as well. In digital cameras, for example, they could provide an accurate estimate of how many pictures could be taken before the battery was exhausted. In an MP3 player, a screen could indicate how many more songs could be played, Mr. Eisenhart said. The devices currently used to measure remaining run time on laptops are typically known as gas or fuel gauges. "Right now, fuel gauges on computers are basically worthless," said Robert M. Spotnitz, who heads Battery Design in Pleasanton, Calif., a small company that makes software to simulate battery performance. "They will say an hour when you have 10 minutes." But the new devices actually monitor the battery and determine its state throughout its lifetime, he said. "These devices measure continually to see you lost 8 percent or 10 percent, and are therefore more accurate." Newer laptops typically have chip systems within them that include a gauge to monitor charge in and out of the battery, as well as a microprocessor that runs software that estimates remaining battery energy, Mr. Heacock said. But because the programs do not include continuing, real-time monitoring, they can soon produce large errors. The use of lithium-ion batteries is widespread in portable devices, and the batteries must work in a range of environmental conditions. But run time and performance of batteries vary depending on storage conditions and use, as well as how fast the batteries are discharged, how old they are and other factors. "When the car gets hot, a laptop stored on the front seat gives you a completely different usage than one stored at room temperature," Mr. Heacock said. Users will know something is wrong, although they can't measure the degradation of performance accurately. "You start off with four hours' run time on your laptop," Mr. Eisenhart said. "But after a year, it's 1.5 hours, and the system starts shutting down on you." Part of this change in performance has to do with impedance, which builds as the battery ages. "Typically you are looking at 500 to 800 charge cycles as the lifetime of a lithium-ion battery," Mr. Eisenhart said. "But after as few as 70 charge cycles, impedance of the battery can double." The Texas Instruments chip takes into account temperature, current and voltage recovery time of the battery. "It looks at how the computer is pulling energy out of the battery over the 500 to 800 cycles," said Mr. Heacock, who added that it also tracks impedance changes as the battery ages. This constant tracking of a battery's actual state of health is innovative, said Jiang Fan, an engineering manager at Gold Peak Industries North America, a manufacturer and distributor of batteries based in San Diego. "In older systems, all the modeling factors for prediction have been determined, and they can't be changed once the battery is installed," he said. Texas Instruments may have gotten around this problem, he said, by tracking actual impedance changes. "Only battery energy can predict running time accurately," Dr. Fan said, and impedance has a significant effect on this energy. Impedance builds up normally in batteries as electrolytes dry up, he said, inevitably affecting the rate of the chemical reaction inside the battery. "When electrolytes decompose," he said, "there is no carrier for the lithium ions to transfer from negative to positive during discharge." It's like a river with 200 boats to transfer 2,000 people, he said. "When 100 of the boats burn, it takes longer to transfer the 2,000 people." But the new controls will lead to greater efficiency, he said. "Battery control can be set so that the user doesn't have to stop when the gauge says there's still 20 percent energy left." Lance Chandler, a computer scientist and senior manager for design engineering at Intersil in Milpitas, Calif., a competitor of Texas Instruments, said that the new technology merited consideration. "But it is still in its infancy as far as acceptance," he said. "It will take time for the technology to prove itself." E-mail: Eisenberg@nytimes.com</text></article><article index="2" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D81231F93BA35751C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Narrows Forecast<date>Published: December 8, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's largest maker of chips for cellphones, said yesterday that it expected fourth-quarter revenue and earnings per share at the midrange of its previous estimates, as order trends remain soft. Texas Instruments, based in Dallas, said it now expected revenue of $3.02 billion to $3.14 billion, with earnings per share of 25 cents to 27 cents. It forecast revenue for the crucial semiconductor unit of $2.68 billion to $2.78 billion. Ron Slaymaker, vice president and investor relations manager, said internal inventory would be down by the end of the quarter, as the company starts production on fewer wafers for new chips than it ships out during the period. Inventory problems have plagued chip companies this year, both in their own warehouses and in the distribution channel.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DC1E3DF932A35752C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA; Texas Instruments Reviews for Agency<date>Published: November 1, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments in Dallas has begun a review for an agency to handle its worldwide account, which has been handled by TM Advertising in Irving, Tex., part of the Interpublic Group of Companies. Spending has not been determined. David Beals, president and chief executive at Jones Lundin Beals in Chicago, which is managing the review, confirmed reports about it that appeared on AdAge.com and Adweek.com. About 15 agencies have been contacted, including TM, which is expected to participate. A decision is expected in December.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/22/technology/22chip.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Intel Cancels Digital TV Chip<date>Published: October 22, 2004</date><text>y Reuters The Intel Corporation said yesterday that it was scrapping a plan to enter the digital television chip business, in a retreat from its push into consumer electronics. The cancellation, which follows a string of missteps by Intel, could ease competition for Texas Instruments, which has had success with its chips used in rear-projection televisions. "What we've decided is that for the investment that's required and the returns we would get and the timeline to get to those returns, that it doesn't make sense for us to pursue this particular technology," an Intel spokesman, Bill Calder, said. Advertisement Nine months ago, Intel announced plans for an aggressive push beyond the personal computer and into consumer electronics with new chips for big-screen high-definition televisions. The company's president, Paul S. Otellini, said at the time that Intel would take advantage of a novel technology for television displays - combining liquid crystals, a mirror-like surface and a silicon chip - that would appear in $2,000 televisions.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/21/technology/21phone.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Coming Soon: High-Definition TV Phones<date>Published: October 21, 2004</date><text>iniature mobile phones, which already double as cameras, Internet devices and music players, are poised to merge with the largest of home appliances, the television. The cellphone industry is working to build phones able to receive high-definition television signals over the air, even though HDTV has yet to make its way into most American living rooms. Advertisement Texas Instruments, the largest maker of computer chips for mobile phones, plans to announce today that it is developing technology that will allow wireless handsets to receive hundreds of high-definition channels. The phones would not be marketed until 2007. Although Sprint and AT&amp;T Wireless currently offer a service that allows cellphone users to watch live streaming from more than a dozen television channels over the cellular networks, the picture delivery is very slow and not much like a real TV viewing experience. The push into high-definition television reception by Texas Instruments and a handful of other chip makers could change all that. Qualcomm, the world's second largest maker of chips for mobile phones, is also working on a chip to enable phones to receive digital television signals, the company said Tuesday. Both companies said the HDTV phones would be in widespread tests by 2006. Already, a telecommunications company in South Korea is testing a television phone in Seoul. The new chips would receive digital signals that would display uninterrupted images while a user is moving. Texas Instruments and other chip makers envision consumers receiving television signals, not over the existing cellular network, but from a separate network, like a satellite television network. "There's no reason why, in three to four years, you won't have 200 channels on your cellphone," said Marc Cetto, a general manager in the handset division of Texas Instruments. He said he expected that the technology's appeal would be "event-driven," attracting consumers who want to watch programming like sports and news. Analysts and phone company executives said future programming might be similar to existing television content, but might also emphasize shows of shorter length. But before consumers can carry true HDTV sets in their pockets, substantial technological challenges need to be overcome. The companies have to create phones with enough battery life that users will not have to choose between making calls and tuning into shows. On the other hand, mobile phone makers and cellular carriers have successfully added new functions and features like color screens to the ever-smaller gadgets - making the move into television less of a leap. From a business standpoint, finding popular new uses is crucial to the growth of the cellphone business. In the case of television technology, there are a number of unanswered questions, like whether consumers would want to pay for programming as they do now for standard satellite TV or how much they would be asked to pay. Mr. Cetto said he did not expect the actual handsets to cost much more than the current generation of phones. Another question is whether consumers who have become accustomed to watching television on huge sets at home would be interested in watching shows on tiny screens. Allen Leibovitch, a semiconductor analyst with IDC, a market research company, said the technology might actually be a dangerous distraction to people who use their mobile phones while driving. The concept of miniature televisions is not new. Sony, with its Watchman, and other consumer electronics makers have for years sold portable televisions with small screens, but those devices have had very limited markets. Rich Templeton, the chief executive of Texas Instruments, conceded the appeal of the tiny appliances has not been vast. But he said the phone-based television would be more widely used because most users would be carrying them anyway. In Seoul, SK Telecom, a major telecommunications provider, is testing phones that receive a television signal, said James E. Katz, director of mobile computing studies at Rutgers University. Mr. Katz, who saw the tests in Korea this week, said the screens were small, but the picture and sound were quite sharp. "You can sit in a cafe and watch your show by yourself," he said, "or you can gather around it with a couple of small-headed friends." But he added that he was not sure whether American consumers would take to the technology. SK Telecom is delivering TV programming over its existing cellular network, Mr. Katz said. Phone makers have not offered analog TV service, Mr. Cetto said, because analog signals can be easily interrupted. By contrast, he said, the digital signal can be processed in such a way as to compensate for interruptions in the frequency. But while digital technology makes it easier to display a constant stream of images while the phone user is moving, digital programming has been slow to develop. Mr. Cetto said Texas Instruments was already participating in tests in Berlin, Helsinki, Finland and Pittsburgh, that have shown that disruption can be overcome. "A month ago, I was in Europe going 60 miles an hour in a car, watching television on a cellphone," said Mr. Cetto, who added that he was in Berlin and that he was not driving at the time. Sanjay Jha, president of Qualcomm's chip set and system software division, said digital TV technology on phones was the next logical step.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DE133AF93AA25753C1A9629C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Telecommunications: Texas Instruments Says Sales Reached 9-Year High<date>Published: October 19, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's biggest maker of mobile-phone processors, said yesterday that profit rose to $563 million as third-quarter sales reached their highest point for the period in nine years. Net income increased to 32 cents a share for the three months that ended Sept. 30, from $447 million, or 25 cents a share, a year earlier, the company, based in Dallas, said. Sales climbed 28 percent to $3.25 billion. Nokia, the world's biggest handset maker and Texas Instruments' largest client, said global sales of wireless handsets will gain 20 percent this year. Wireless products generated 35 percent of first-half sales in Texas Instruments' semiconductor unit, which also makes chips that control household electronics like televisions. Shares of Texas Instruments rose $1.07, or 5.1 percent, to $22.16 in extended trading after results were released. They had fallen 13 cents, to $21.09, in regular trading. Texas Instruments expects a fourth-quarter profit of 24 cents to 28 cents a share on sales of $2.96 billion to $3.2 billion.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/19/business/yourmoney/19watch.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Step Right Up and Beat the Numbers<date>Published: September 19, 2004</date><text>MAZING, isn't it, how investors still reward companies for pulling out all the stops to meet or exceed the financial results they promised? Witness, for example, how they applauded the midquarter update that Texas Instruments delivered on Sept. 8. In recent weeks, hundreds of technology companies have made grim midquarter revisions to third-quarter forecasts made in happier times. So investors cheered when Texas Instruments actually raised, by the oh-so-predictable penny a share, the lower end of its earnings range for the quarter. Never mind that the company cut its overall revenue forecast by as much as 6 percent and shaved expected sales figures in its biggest business - semiconductors - by anywhere between 4.1 percent and 6.5 percent. Texas Instruments pushed up its per-share earnings range for the quarter, to 27 cents to 29 cents. The previous range was 26 cents to 29 cents. Advertisement Bravo, investors shouted, as they raced to buy Texas Instruments shares. The company's stock rose 10 percent the day after the update, and further in the following days. Such enthusiasm from investors is mystifying, given how Texas Instruments wrung that all-important penny out of its operations. As the company noted in the update, its tax rate plummeted in the quarter - dropping to 21 percent from the 29 percent it estimated in the previous period - and it also said it was setting aside a smaller amount for its employee profit-sharing plan. These two factors accounted for a nickel of the new earnings range that investors chose to celebrate. Since when are smaller tax bills and a shrinking contribution to a profit-sharing plan reasons to snap up shares in a company? Ron Slaymaker, Texas Instruments' vice president for investor relations, agreed that without those factors, the company would have missed its estimates by a wide margin. But he said he thought that investors reacted favorably to the update not because the earnings estimate rose, but because the numbers weren't as bad as they had feared. "It appears to our investors that what we are dealing with is an inventory adjustment and not a big turnaround in demand,'' he said. Still, because Texas Instruments' employee profit-sharing plan is based on exceeding growth targets for profit and revenue over the year, a reduction in contributions means that the results are not coming in as rosily as management had expected. "Estimates are made each quarter based on what they think the forecast is going to be over the year," said Chris Rongone, a Texas Instruments spokeswoman. "As you move through the year and have better visibility to what the year is going to be, it could go up or down." The company had expected to contribute $340 million for 2004, but in the third quarter that figure fell to $260 million, helping earnings. But the big profit propellant in the quarter was the disappearing tax rate. There is nothing wrong, of course, with lower taxes. Companies everywhere are paying far less in taxes nowadays, largely because of international sales. Companies operating in countries where tax rates are below the 35 percent rate in the United States incur lower taxes on earnings generated in those countries. Since 1972, companies have not been forced to pay the difference between the tax rate in the United States and that of a foreign nation on overseas profits as long as those gains are "indefinitely reinvested" in that country. If a company expects to bring any of those profits back home, deferred taxes must be recorded. Jack T. Ciesielski, an accounting expert and editor of The Analyst's Accounting Observer, recently published a report on untaxed foreign earnings at the nation's largest companies. He noted the "tremendous amount of leeway for earnings management" that foreign operations provide for companies. They can move production to a different country to bolster profits, he pointed out, or change the proportion of earnings subject to reinvestment. Investors are in the dark, however, about the moves' contributions to earnings. Companies do not have to disclose the amount of untaxed foreign earnings generated each year. But they do have to disclose how much they have accumulated in untaxed foreign earnings. At the end of 2003, Texas Instruments had $1.6 billion in untaxed foreign earnings, up from $1.3 billion in 2002. Obviously, Texas Instruments does a lot of business in lower-tax countries. But its plummeting tax rate in the third quarter seemed odd, given that its business in Asia - a lower-tax region than the United States - was down considerably. The tax-rate decline added 3 cents a share to the company's projections. Mr. Slaymaker said that the tax rate dropped suddenly because the company had just completed its 2003 tax return and found that its deductions for profits on products that it exported were greater than anticipated. So the company cut its 2004 effective tax rate to reflect the continuation of that trend. Mr. Ciesielski said: "There are levers you can pull in the effective tax rate that will help you. Some are legitimate, others not so legitimate. The bigger question is, what do you want as an investor? If you're looking for someone to meet the numbers and go on with the scripted Wall Street dance, this is what you're going to get." Sure, investors are looking for positive results from their companies. But there is a difference between good news from actual operations and good news from gimmicks. Sooner or later, gimmicks run out.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3D61639F934A2575AC0A9629C8B63&amp;ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Plans Buyback<date>Published: September 17, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, the largest maker of chips for cellphones, said yesterday that it planned to buy back $1 billion in stock and bolster its quarterly dividend by more than 17 percent, becoming the latest technology company to return extra cash to investors. Shares of the company, based in Dallas, rose in after-hours trading after the announcement. The company said the move would increase its annual dividend to 10 cents a share, from the current 8.5 cents. Texas Instruments' repurchase plan, which was authorized by its board, comes in addition to the plan announced in February to repurchase 21 million shares. In July, Microsoft, under pressure from shareholders, announced a three-part plan to return $75 billion in cash to shareholders over the next four years. As technology sales have slowed, Wall Street has become increasingly vocal about the need for new or higher dividends. Texas Instruments shares jumped to $22.25 after the news, from a close of $21.59 in regular trading.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/19/technology/news-watch-calculators-a-cool-looking-math-whiz-sheds-its-drab-school-uniform.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">NEWS WATCH: CALCULATORS; A Cool-Looking Math Whiz Sheds Its Drab School Uniform<date>Published: August 19, 2004</date><text>Graphing calculators have long been considered a must among a segment of the school-bound crowd. But Texas Instruments has added a touch of fashion to function with its latest model for junior high and high school students.The TI-84 Plus Silver Edition calculator, available for around $130, is no slacker on the function side, of course.It builds on the popular TI-83 graphing calculator, with more than double the processing speed and nine times as much memory. It comes with 30 built-in programs, like the periodic table of the elements, algebra, geometry and science guides, a flash-card maker and a contact organizer.The TI-84 is Texas Instruments' first graphing calculator with a U.S.B. port, which can be used to link it to a projector to show off calculations in class and connect it to a computer for software downloads and system upgrades.And calculating no longer has to look drab.In another first for Texas Instruments, students can customize their calculators' welcome screens or add blue, orange or pink faceplates -- lending a little color to typically black-and-white subjects. Tim Gnatek</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/09/business/technology-a-digital-world-with-analog-as-its-workhorse.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">TECHNOLOGY; A Digital World With Analog As Its Workhorse<date>Published: August 09, 2004</date><text>Phonograph records are relics. Traditional cameras sit in closets gathering dust. Clocks with hands? How quaint.Digital technology, as every marketer knows, is synonymous with speed, precision and the future.The challenge, though, for those designing digital products is that no human experiences reality as a pattern of 1's and 0's. The natural world is, in engineering terms, a thoroughly analog realm of endlessly variable waves of sound and light, temperature and pressure fluctuations, and shifting magnetic fields.So it turns out the digital revolution is driving strong demand for advances in analog electronics, an arcane realm in which tens of thousands of products translate reality into 1's and 0's for computers and retranslate digital results into forms humans can perceive.In a digital camera, for example, analog chips translate wavelengths and intensities of light into digital code and, if the photographer wants to check the image, they retranslate the code into a visual display. Analog or mixed analog-digital chips also manage timing functions, signal filtering and amplification and battery performance.Few companies understood the interplay better than Texas Instruments Inc., which in the late 1990's decided to invest heavily in analog devices along with its higher-profile digital products. Last year, it moved past STMicroelectronics of France to become the global leader in the $26.8 billion analog chip market, according to Databeans, a market research firm in Reno, Nev.''Most people think that the world has gone digital and analog is old and not hip,'' said Gregg A. Lowe, the senior vice president who oversees most of Texas Instruments' analog business. ''On average, there's probably 15 analog chips needed for every digital processor you use.''In fact, analog semiconductors have become Texas Instruments' biggest business, generating about 40 percent of its $8.36 billion in semiconductor revenue in 2003.''The only thing exciting about analog electronics is the results,'' said Richard K. Templeton, who has been at the company for 20 years and became its chief executive in May.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/21/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-profit-up-264.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Profit Up 264%<date>Published: July 21, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, whose semiconductors powered more than half the cellphones sold last year, said yesterday that its second-quarter profit almost quadrupled after sales rose at the fastest pace in more than 13 years. Net income increased to $441 million, or 25 cents a share, from $121 million, or 7 cents a share, a year earlier, the company said. Sales rose 39 percent, to $3.24 billion. Texas Instruments' profit has more than tripled for two consecutive quarters as consumers bought cellphones with cameras and other functions.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/19/business/technology-intel-hopes-its-chips-can-become-more-mobile.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">TECHNOLOGY; Intel Hopes Its Chips Can Become More Mobile<date>Published: July 19, 2004</date><text>Correction AppendedWhen Sean Maloney was 12, a teacher admonished him for trouble-making and assigned him to write 1,000 times: ''I will not talk in class.'' The next day, he showed up with a computer program that wrote the sentences automatically.Mr. Maloney, now 48, might hope he can conjure another quick, innovative fix. In January, Mr. Maloney, a self-taught engineer and rising star at the Intel Corporation, was tapped to run the company's struggling communications division, which is responsible for making chips that operate in laptops, hand-held computers and cellphones.For Intel, the wireless business is increasingly important, as it is for other technology leaders, given the boom in mobile communications. Yet the division has been a trouble spot in the company, despite the marketing success of Centrino, its wireless chip for laptop computers. In fact, the communications division has been floundering after a series of poor business and engineering decisions that left it losing around $850 million in 2003.''We plan to become profitable in 2005,'' Mr. Maloney said of the communications division, which did $4 billion in sales last year. But he said that skeptical investors were ''wondering if we can do that.''Intel, with $30 billion in sales last year, had a surge in profits in its recent second quarter, with earnings nearly doubling from the same period a year earlier. But its shares dropped more than 12 percent last week, closing at $22.73 on the Nasdaq on Friday, on news that its inventories are rising, which causes a decline in gross profit margins. At the same time, the market is showing jitters about an overall softening in the technology sector.Investors have expressed concern about Intel's long-term growth, though it still owns some 85 percent of the market for microprocessors that run PC's. But the PC sector has stagnated even as demand for mobile devices has skyrocketed.For some skeptics on Wall Street, Intel's failure to translate its expertise and dominance of the computer microprocessor market into expertise building chips for mobile devices is a serious issue -- particularly because they say dominating the wireless field will be pivotal to Intel's future. Making gains in ''the communications business is just critical in terms of broadening the market and enabling growth for Intel,'' said Tim Luke, an analyst with Lehman Brothers.Correction: July 20, 2004, Tuesday A chart in Business Day yesterday with an article about the Intel Corporation's communications division misstated the 2003 market share of worldwide flash-memory sales for three companies. Samsung Electronics' market share was 21 percent, not 15; Toshiba's was 14 percent, not 21; and Intel's was 15 percent, not 14.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/08/business/technology-chip-maker-narrows-sales-forecast-for-quarter.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">TECHNOLOGY; Chip Maker Narrows Sales Forecast For Quarter<date>Published: June 08, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, whose semiconductors run more than half the cellphones sold last year, narrowed its second-quarter sales forecast yesterday and said demand for its products was ''slightly exceeding'' projections.Sales will rise from $3.17 billion to $3.29 billion, the company said in a statement. Profit will be 24 to 26 cents a share, compared with an April estimate of 23 to 26 cents.Texas Instruments, based in Dallas, raised the midpoint of its sales forecast to $3.23 billion from the $3.21 billion it predicted in April as demand increases for new handsets with color screens and built-in digital cameras. Some investors expected sales of new phones, especially in Asia, would enable Texas Instruments to reach the highest forecast of $3.33 billion made in April.''People were hoping for a little bit more, so it's slightly disappointing,'' said Greg Barlage, who helps manage $7.5 billion, including Texas Instruments shares, for Stein Roe Investment Counsel in San Francisco. ''When you don't think about expectations and look at the numbers, it's still impressive.''The announcement came after the close of regular trading, where shares of Texas Instruments rose $1.02, to $26.23. They fell as low as $25.81 after hours.Business is ''slightly exceeding expectations,'' Ron Slaymaker, Texas Instruments' vice president for investor relations, said in a conference call. Customers are not increasing inventories, making it less likely they will cut orders, he said.Analysts expected profit of 25 cents a share on sales of $3.21 billion, the average estimates in Thomson Financial surveys. Texas Instruments earned $121 million, or 7 cents a share, on sales of $2.34 billion in the period a year earlier.The company's chief executive, Rich Templeton, 45, won his first mobile-phone processor order from Samsung Electronics yesterday as Texas Instruments sought to reduce its dependence on Nokia. In the first quarter, Texas Instruments overcame lower-than-expected Nokia orders and sales grew 34 percent.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/15/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-profit-more-than-triples.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments' Profit More Than Triples<date>Published: April 15, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments said yesterday that first-quarter profits more than tripled, matching Wall Street's expectations, as revenue rose 34 percent because of strong semiconductor sales. The company, which makes chips used in half the world's mobile phones, said it earned $367 million, or 21 cents a share, in the quarter, compared with $117 million, or 7 cents a share, a year earlier. That met the forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call. Revenue was $2.94 billion, compared with $2.19 billion a year earlier. Semiconductors, the bulk of the company's business, bucked the seasonal trend by rising 5 percent from the previous three months -- and 38 percent from a year ago -- because of strong sales for chips used in digital television sets and projectors and analog chips used in a variety of consumer electronics products. In the crucial wireless business, however, revenue fell from the fourth quarter of 2003. The company said that was partly because of a seasonal decline in mobile phone sales and lower demand from Nokia, its largest customer. Wireless revenue was still 35 percent higher than a year ago, said the company, which is based in Dallas. The shares fell 30 cents, to $28.68.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/09/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-revises-sales-forecasts.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Revises Sales Forecasts<date>Published: March 09, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, whose chips powered more than half the mobile phones sold last year, said yesterday that first-quarter sales would reach the high end of its forecasts as demand accelerates for cellphones with advanced features. Revenue for the quarter will rise to $2.84 billion to $2.95 billion, said the company, which is based in Dallas. Earnings will be 19 cents to 22 cents a share. In January, Texas Instruments predicted profit of 16 cents to 22 cents a share on revenue of $2.72 billion to $2.95 billion. Phone makers including Nokia are increasing chip orders as consumers demand new phones that give them access to the Internet or allow them to take and send pictures. This year will be the first that shipments of handsets with color screens will surpass those of phones with monochrome screens, according to the iSuppli Corporation, a market researcher. Revenue from the semiconductor unit will be $2.5 billion to $2.6 billion, Texas Instruments said. Analysts had forecast profit of 19 cents a share on sales of $2.85 billion, the average of 33 estimates in a Thomson Financial survey. The shares rose 9 cents, to $30.69, after adding as much as $1.29 in after-hours trading. In regular trading, shares dropped 87 cents, to $30.60.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/27/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-reports-profit.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Reports Profit<date>Published: January 27, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's top maker of chips for cellphones, reported a fourth-quarter profit yesterday, reversing a loss from a year earlier, on surging demand for wireless chips. Dallas-based Texas Instruments, which raised its forecasts in December, posted a net profit of $512 million, or 29 cents a share. That compares with a loss of $589 million, or 34 cents a share, a year earlier, when it had a large investment write-down. Revenue was $2.77 billion, compared with $2.15 billion a year earlier. Excluding investment gains and the benefit of a tax cut, the company posted a profit of 20 cents a share. On that basis, analysts surveyed by Reuters Research, a unit of Reuters Group, were expecting earnings per share of 19 cents on revenue of $2.72 billion. Shares rose $1.02, or 3.3 percent, to $31.99.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/16/business/technology-briefing-people-texas-instruments-names-new-chief-executive.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | People: Texas Instruments Names New Chief Executive<date>Published: January 16, 2004</date><text>Texas Instruments will promote Richard K. Templeton, left, its chief operating officer, to president and chief executive. He will succeed Thomas J. Engibous. Mr. Templeton, 45, was named to the board in July and has been with Texas Instruments since 1980. Mr. Engibous, 50, will continue as chairman, the company said yesterday. The stock has more than doubled in the last 12 months as consumers bought new cellphones with cameras and MP3 players that use the company's chips. Mr. Engibous and Mr. Templeton both have headed the semiconductor division, which accounted for 84 percent of the company's sales in its most-recent quarter. Shares of Texas Instruments rose $1.17, to $33.65.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/15/business/technology-in-india-a-high-tech-outpost-for-us-patents.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">TECHNOLOGY; In India, a High-Tech Outpost for U.S. Patents<date>Published: December 15, 2003</date><text>In clusters of modern low-and high-rise office buildings set amid acres of lush greenery here, thousands of engineers are hard at work, writing software for the latest telephones, designing next-generation microprocessors and developing wireless broadband technology.The work of these engineers is generating significant amounts of intellectual property for American companies like Cisco Systems, General Electric, I.B.M., Intel, Motorola and Texas Instruments -- whose various Indian units have filed more than 1,000 patent applications with the United States Patent and Trademark Office. Some applications, with patents already granted, date to the early 1990's. But most applications from India have been filed in the last two years and still await decisions by the patent examiners in Washington.For American technology companies, under pressure to generate quick breakthroughs and develop products while curbing costs, India's big draw is its low-cost, deep pool of well-educated technical talent. The Indian research centers of Cisco and Motorola, for example, are now those companies' largest outside the United States.While outsourcing lower-level technical tasks to India has been a practice of American industry for years, the United States technology titans' increasing reliance on Indian research-and-development operations is a relatively new and growing trend.''In the process of getting low-end work done in India, multinationals discovered that there are not too many locations where they can find this abundance of superior talent at these kinds of costs,'' said Chandra Srinivasan, chairman of the Indian unit of the consulting firm A.T. Kearney.Thousands of engineers in disciplines as diverse as textile engineering and aeronautics graduate each year from India's engineering schools. Top-notch graduates can be hired at salaries beginning at $10,000 a year, even as their peers in the United States earn six times that amount or more. In all, personnel experts estimate that in the next 18 months, the Indian centers of multinational technology companies will double their head counts from 40,000 today.Intel plans to move into a $41 million, 42-acre Bangalore campus next year and more than double its number of employees in India to 3,000. ''It would easily cost twice as much to set up a similar operation in the United States,'' Ketan Sampat, the president of Intel Technology India, said.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/09/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-shares-rise-on-sales-forecast.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Shares Rise On Sales Forecast<date>Published: December 09, 2003</date><text>Shares in Texas Instruments, the world's biggest maker of chips used in cellphones, rose in after-hours trading yesterday after the company increased its fourth-quarter earnings and sales forecast. Shares of Texas Instruments added 36 cents, to $28.60, in extended trading. Fourth-quarter income, excluding a gain from the sale of Micron Technology shares, will be 18 cents to 20 cents a share. On that basis, the company had forecast a profit of 14 cents to 19 cents a share. Sales will be from $2.64 billion to $2.77 billion, higher than its earlier forecast of $2.49 billion to $2.7 billion.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/21/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-says-profit-more-than-doubles.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Says Profit More Than Doubles<date>Published: October 21, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments, the leading maker of chips for cellphones, said yesterday that rising sales across its semiconductor markets helped profit to more than double in the third quarter. The company said it had earned $447 million, or 25 cents a share, up from $188 million, or 11 cents, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had expected the company to earn 9 cents a share. Revenue rose to $2.53 billion from $2.25 billion, exceeding analysts' expectation of $2.49 billion. The company also said it expected to earn 14 cents to 19 cents a share in the fourth quarter, compared with the 11 cents a share forecast by analysts. Texas Instruments said fourth-quarter revenue would be $2.49 billion to $2.70 billion; analysts had expected the lower figure. The chief executive, Thomas J. Engibous, said the company grew faster during a period of recovery in the semiconductor industry because of research and development it undertook in slower times. In trading before the release of the report, shares of Texas Instruments rose 71 cents, or 2.8 percent, to $25.67. The shares gained $1.93 in after-hours trading.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/24/business/technology-briefing-telecommunications-texas-instruments-sues-qualcomm.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Telecommunications: Texas Instruments Sues Qualcomm<date>Published: September 24, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments, a leading maker of computer chips, said yesterday that it had sued Qualcomm, the wireless telephone technology company, accusing it of breach of contract in a confidential handset licensing agreement. Texas Instruments brought its action after receiving reports that Qualcomm was offering discounts to handset makers only if they bought code division multiple access, or C.D.M.A., chipsets from Qualcomm, Joseph Hubach, the general counsel for Texas Instruments, said. Texas Instruments, based in Dallas, and Qualcomm, based in San Diego, reached an agreement in December 2000 allowing each company to supply integrated circuits for all wireless standards using the other's technology through 2005. Qualcomm owns most of the patents to the C.D.M.A. wireless transmission standard, the leading wireless technology in the United States and Asia, and faces increasing competition from Texas Instruments. A spokeswoman for Qualcomm said the company had not seen the Texas Instruments complaint.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/11/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-settles-lawsuit.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Settles Lawsuit<date>Published: September 11, 2003</date><text>The Intergraph Corporation, a computer services and software company, said yesterday that Texas Instruments had agreed to pay $18 million to end patent litigation over digital signal processors used in cellphones and electronic organizers. Texas Instruments, a leading maker of chips that run cellphones, will get a license for three Intergraph patents in return for the payment, Intergraph said. Texas Instruments also agreed to end two patent-infringement lawsuits it filed against Intergraph, which is based in Huntsville, Ala. Executives at Texas Instruments, which is based in Dallas and reported $8.38 billion in sales last year, had no immediate comment. Intergraph, which has collected $450 million from Intel in a dispute over the patents, is also suing Hewlett-Packard, Dell and Gateway over the patents. A lawsuit Hewlett-Packard filed against Intergraph was dismissed, Intergraph said.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/10/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-sales-outlook-improves.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Sales Outlook Improves<date>Published: September 10, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments, whose chips were used in half the cellphones sold worldwide last year, said yesterday that third-quarter sales would rise to the high end of its forecast. Net income will be 20 cents to 22 cents a share in the quarter ending this month, with revenue at $2.39 billion to $2.49 billion, the company said. In July, the company forecast net income of 19 cents to 23 cents on sales of $2.29 billion to $2.49 billion. Demand is increasing for semiconductors used in cellphones with new features like cameras and MP3 audio players, Texas Instruments executives have said, echoing comments from competitors including Intel and National Semiconductor. The Dallas-based company had net income of $188 million, or 11 cents a share, on sales of $2.25 billion in last year's third quarter. Shares fell 62 cents to $24.70 in extended trading after the announcement. The stock fell 71 cents in regular trading.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/22/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-posts-rise-in-net-profit.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Posts Rise In Net Profit<date>Published: July 22, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments Inc., one of the world's biggest makers of semiconductors for cellphones, said yesterday that its second-quarter net income and revenue rose as weakness in its wireless business was offset by strength in other markets. The company reported a second-quarter net profit of $121 million, or 7 cents a share, compared with net income of $95 million, or 5 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose to $2.34 billion from $2.16 billion. Texas Instruments said it expected third-quarter revenue to be from $2.29 billion to $2.49 billion. Shares fell 81 cents, or 4.3 percent, to $17.88.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/08/business/world-business-briefing-asia-japan-venture-in-picture-phones.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">World Business Briefing | Asia: Japan: Venture In Picture Phones<date>Published: July 08, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments and the Sharp Company will jointly develop and sell components used in cellphones with cameras to cut down on design and production time. Sharp will contribute its imaging censors, flash memory chips and liquid crystal displays; Texas Instruments will add communication chips and processors that support multimedia functions like video. Sharp produced Japan's first camera phone three years ago, and now 80 percent of all new handsets sold in Japan include a camera. Japanese handset makers, though, have had a harder time breaking into markets overseas. Ken Belson (NYT)</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/11/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-lowers-forecasts.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Lowers Forecasts<date>Published: June 11, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments, the world's largest maker of cellular phone chips, cut second-quarter sales and profit forecasts yesterday as demand in Asia fell short of its expectations. Sales will increase about 5 percent from the first quarter's $2.19 billion and profit will be about 6 cents a share, the company said in a statement. Net income was 5 cents on sales of $2.16 billion a year earlier. Last month the company, which is based in Dallas, reaffirmed profit and sales projections it made in April. Texas Instruments on May 5 predicted profit of about 8 cents a share, and a sales increase of about 7 percent from the first quarter. Texas Instruments will cut 250 jobs in Japan, in addition to the 1,250 workers the company said in April that it would lay off. Shares of Texas Instruments rose 17 cents, to $20.39.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/16/business/technology-briefing-hardware-qualcomm-faces-challenge-on-chips.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Qualcomm Faces Challenge On Chips<date>Published: May 16, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments Inc., STMicroelectronics and Nokia have agreed to design mobile telephone semiconductors that will challenge the dominance of Qualcomm Inc. in sales of the industry-standard chips that it created. The companies are collaborating on chips using code division multiple access technology and will begin sales in the third quarter, they said yesterday. Qualcomm developed the technology and gets a royalty payment on every phone using it. Texas Instruments, the world's biggest maker of chips for mobile phones, has an agreement with Qualcomm to use the technology without paying fees. Qualcomm shares fell 61 cents, or about 2 percent, to $30.23. Shares of Texas Instruments rose 18 cents, to $19.60.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/07/business/technology-briefing-telecommunications-texas-instruments-expects-more-growth.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Telecommunications: Texas Instruments Expects More Growth<date>Published: May 07, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments said yesterday that it expected revenue and profit margins to continue to grow in 2003 and that it planned to expand into the fast-growing market for code division multiple access, or C.D.M.A., mobile Internet phones. In a statement ahead of the company's annual briefing for financial analysts today in Dallas, the company repeated previous guidance for growth in its results. Analysts already project steady quarter-over-quarter revenue growth during 2003, to $2.49 billion in the fourth quarter, up from the $2.19 billion reported in the first quarter of 2003. The company noted that since the market bottomed in the fourth quarter of 2001, revenue has increased 23 percent and operating profit is up 22 percent. It also said it would expand its presence in the market for CDMA2000 mobile-phone chips beginning next quarter. CDMA2000 is the latest generation of technology developed by Qualcomm and licensed to a variety of chip and mobile phone makers. CDMA2000 has been one of the fastest-growing technologies in wireless markets in Asia and the United States in the last two years.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/06/business/technology-briefing-hardware-texas-instruments-increases-chip-speed.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">Technology Briefing | Hardware: Texas Instruments Increases Chip Speed<date>Published: May 06, 2003</date><text>Texas Instruments said yesterday that it had broken the one-gigahertz barrier for digital signal processing chips, increasing the top speed for such chips by nearly 40 percent. The company said that the new chip design would cut costs for communications systems and make new applications possible, such as image processing implants that could allow a blind person to see well enough to distinguish a face. Barnaby J. Feder (NYT)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/16/business/3-chip-makers-post-results-that-meet-expectations.html?ref=texasinstrumentsinc">3 Chip Makers Post Results That Meet Expectations<date>Published: April 16, 2003</date><text>Intel, Motorola and Texas Instruments, three of the world's largest chip makers, all reported earnings yesterday that met or slightly exceeded Wall Street's expectations.The companies, which reported their results after the close of regular stock trading, warned that the outlook remained hard to predict and that the appearance of a new respiratory illness in Asia only added to the difficulties. But none of the companies have detected an effect on sales from the disease so far. Analysts said that, along with I.B.M. earnings reported Monday, the results pointed to a solid start to the year for major technology companies in a challenging environment.Intel, the world's largest chip maker, based in Santa Clara, Calif., said the revenue for the current quarter would be $6.4 billion to $7 billion, the same broad range it presented a year ago for the second quarter.''We are bouncing along a very soft bottom,'' said Ashok Kumar, who follows the chip makers for U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray. ''The environment is no different than a year ago, except that we are one year closer to a recovery.''For the three months ended March 29, Intel said it had net income of $915 million, or 14 cents a share, down from $936 million in the quarter a year earlier. Earnings per share were also 14 cents in the 2002 quarter because more shares were outstanding. Revenue fell slightly, to $6.75 billion from $6.78 billion.Intel had a stronger-than-expected performance from its computer chip businesses but came in below expectations in its sales of flash memories to Nokia and other cellphone companies, which cut back purchases when Intel raised its memory prices.Intel said that the notebook computing segment was its strongest and that it was increasing shipments of Centrino, its new chipset that includes wireless communications capabilities. Paul S. Ottelini, the president and chief operating officer, said Intel would ship more than a million Centrino chips in this quarter.Andrew Bryant, Intel's chief financial officer, said that Intel was ''slightly encouraged'' that demand from businesses had been at the upper end of seasonal patterns for the last two quarters.</text></article></page></root>
