<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="US Bancorp"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/08/25/buffett-adds-another-bank-to-his-investment-portfolio/?ref=usbancorp">Buffett Adds Another Bank to His Portfolio<date>August 25, 2011, 12:15 pm</date><text>Pankaj Nangia/Bloomberg NewsWarren E. Buffett, chairman of Berkshire Hathaway. With his $5 billion investment in Bank of America, Warren E. Buffett is adding yet another American financial giant to his stock portfolio. His investment vehicle, Berkshire Hathaway, has long been an investor in the nation’s banks, and counts five firms in which it has a major stake. Here were Berkshire’s top holdings in financial companies as of June 30, according to a regulatory filing: FIRM MARKET VALUE OF STAKE AMOUNT OF SHARES CHANGE FROM 1ST QUARTER American Express $7.84 billion 151,610,700 No change Wells Fargo $9.89 billion 352,327,608 + 9,703,683 shares US Bancorp $1.76 billion 69,039,426 No change Source: Bloomberg News/S.E.C. filing Berkshire also owns smaller stakes in the Bank of New York Mellon and the M&amp;T Bank Corporation. Of course, Mr. Buffett’s most notable bets on the finance sector of late came from his big capital injections into Goldman Sachs and General Electric during the financial crisis. Those two deals closely resemble his new investment in Bank of America; he bought $5 billion worth of perpetual preferred shares in Goldman and $3 billion in G.E. Those purchases were highly profitable for Mr. Buffett, with the preferred shares carrying a 10 percent annual dividend, as well as requirement that Goldman and G.E. pay a 10 percent premium to buy Berkshire out. Goldman has since bought back Mr. Buffett’s holdings, while G.E. has said that it intends to do so. Still, not all of Mr. Buffett’s Wall Street moves have turned out well. While Berkshire earned a profit from its Goldman and G.E. investments, warrants that it received along with the preferred shares remain underwater. (The 700 million warrants that Berkshire received from Bank of America, on the other hand, are currently in the money: They carry a strike price of $7.142857, while the firm’s stock price is at $7.89 as of late Thursday morning.) Going further back, just before the market crash of 1987, Berkshire bought $700 million of Salomon Brothers preferred shares. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Buffett Invests $5 Billion in Bank of America To protect his holdings, Mr. Buffett undertook a highly unusual move. He stepped in as Salomon’s chairman in 1991 after John Gutfreund was forced to resign following a Treasury securities bidding scandal. Mr. Buffett was widely credited with saving the firm from collapsing by quickly cleaning house and winning over angry clients, politicians and investors. (He famously delivered the following lines in his testimony before Congress on the scandal: “Lose money for the firm, and I will be understanding; lose a shred of reputation for the firm, and I will be ruthless.”) Mr. Buffett stepped down as Salomon’s chairman after roughly 10 months. Berkshire sold its shares in the firm in 1997, after Salomon was sold to what is now Citigroup. Outside of banks, Mr. Buffett declined to invest in the hedge fund Long-Term Capital Management in 1993. After LTCM faced collapse in 1998 amid a global financial crisis, its officials approached Mr. Buffett — and he again passed. This post has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: August 25, 2011 A previous version of this article misstated the size and value of Berkshire Hathaway's holdings in Wells Fargo.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/13/when-its-o-k-to-skip-a-loan-payment/?ref=usbancorp">When It's O.K. to Skip a Loan Payment<date>July 13, 2011, 3:27 pm</date><text>It’s generally a bad idea to skip mortgage and other loan payments. Late payments damage your credit score and add late fees to your monthly total. But U.S. Bank, based in Minneapolis, is allowing borrowers affected by the Minnesota state government shutdown to skip a payment without any adverse effects like late fees, penalties or effect on their credit ratings. (Keep in mind that interest will still accrue, though.) On July 1, the state government shut down most functions after the governor, a Democrat, and the Republican-controlled Legislature, failed to agree on a two-year budget. The governor wants to raise taxes; the Legislature disagrees. Roughly 22,000 state workers were laid off, and many businesses are affected, too. According to the bank, existing customers as of June 30 whose accounts are in good standing can choose what month’s payment they’d like to skip and notify the bank by calling 800-890-2233. Mortgage loans are eligible, as are installment loans like those for cars and boats, as well as small business and consumer lines of credit. Borrowers don’t have to be state employees to qualify, said a bank spokesman, Tom Joyce. Small businesses affected by the shutdown can also qualify. Would you skip a payment if knew it wouldn’t hurt your credit rating?</text></article><article index="3" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/20/u-s-bank-and-chase-add-to-e-m-v-chip-cards-for-travelers/?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bank and Chase Add to E.M.V. Chip Cards for Travelers<date>June 20, 2011, 4:18 pm</date><text>U.S. Bank is joining the small-but-growing ranks of American financial institutions offering credit cards with tiny, secure microprocessing chips that are widely used overseas. But U.S. Bank’s card, aiming for maximum flexibility, uses technology that lets the card work with three different payment systems. The bank, the main banking unit of Minneapolis-based U.S. Bancorp, says its FlexPerks Travel Rewards Visa card offers the embedded E.M.V. (for Europay, Mastercard and Visa) chips, which are becoming prevalent in Europe, as well as the older magnetic stripe technology, which is still dominant in the United States. The U.S. Bank card also can be used in “contactless” payment systems available at some locations in the United States. These systems let the customer wave the card at a payment terminal to make a purchase, rather than sliding it through a reader at checkout. That’s a lot of technology sitting in a little plastic rectangle. The bank says that will allow its customers to have the “best experience possible wherever they go.” “While we believe E.M.V. is important for our international travel cardholders, we are committed to driving contactless mobile payments in the United States,” said Cliff Cook, chief marketing officer for the bank’s retail payments unit, in a press release. Roughly 20,000 FlexPerks Visa cardholders will get the new cards this month. The bank plans to expand the card to other travel reward cardholders in the coming year. E.M.V. technology is considered more secure than magnetic stripes and is widely used in Europe. Some American cardholders have had trouble using their magnetic stripe cards abroad, particularly at unattended kiosks used to sell train tickets and the like, as this Practical Traveler column discussed. The cards have been slow to catch on in the United States, in part because of the expense merchants will incur to install new, compatible card readers at their registers. Recently, some big banks—Wells Fargo and JPMorgan Chase—as well as some smaller credit unions have introduced cards with E.M.V chips for customers who travel internationally. Chase has said it will expand its E.M.V. offerings in the coming months, and on Monday it introduced a second E.M.V. card, JPMorgan Select Visa Signature® card. Unlike some versions of E.M.V. cards, which require a PIN, Chase’s smart-chip cards use a signature, but you don’t have to sign at unmanned kiosks, according to the bank.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/05/11/prepaid-cards-subject-jobless-to-host-of-fees/?ref=usbancorp">Prepaid Cards Subject Jobless to Host of Fees<date>May 11, 2011, 4:35 pm</date><text>When you’re getting unemployment benefits, you by definition don’t have a lot of cash to spare. So it seems especially unfair that people who receive their jobless benefits on prepaid debit cards are subject to a variety of fees they can ill afford to pay. A report out this week from the National Consumer Law Center lays out a host of ways in which banks nibble away at jobless benefits with fees the center called “junk.” The prepaid cards are most often used by jobless recipients who don’t have checking accounts, and so are ineligible for direct deposit. Practices vary from state to state because jobless benefits are distributed at the state level, and state governments negotiate the terms of agreements with card providers. In many states, charges apply for using A.T.M.’s, even if they’re in network; checking balances; and even for not using the card enough (inactivity fees, as high as $3). The report is especially critical of a card issued in five states by U.S. Bank, which charges overdraft fees of $10 to $20 if recipients use more than the amount on their cards. Charging an overdraft fee to someone who doesn’t even have a bank account struck me as particularly ingenious — what are they overdrawing, exactly? U.S. Bank is able to do this, the report explains, because jobless benefits are typically paid into pooled accounts that then have subaccounts designated for individual recipients. In most states, if a recipient uses the card to make a purchase that exceeds his or her benefits, the transaction is simply denied. But in five states — Arkansas, Idaho, Nebraska, Ohio and Oregon — U.S. Bank lets the transaction go through, and then deducts the amount, plus the overdraft fee, from the recipient’s next benefits check. (The bank issues cards without overdraft fees in several other states.) Those fees can make a big dent, considering that the typical weekly unemployment check is just $294. Teri Charest, a spokeswoman for U.S. Bank, said in an e-mail that overdraft protection is an option that states can choose to add to their prepaid card programs. But even when it is offered, cardholders must opt in to overdraft coverage. “The terms are clearly disclosed so cardholders are aware of the fee should they need to use it,” she said. Other banks don’t charge such hefty fees, but some do charge “denial” fees, ranging from 25 cents to $1.50, when an attempted A.T.M. or retail transaction fails for lack of funds. Some even charge for live customer service calls or withdrawing funds using a human teller. The practice occurs despite a directive from the Department of Labor stating that deducting “overdraft, overdraft fee, or denial fee” from future unemployment payments is “inconsistent” with federal law. The “best” cards, offering free in-network A.T.M. withdrawals, at least two free out-of-network withdrawals, no balance inquiry fees and no inactivity fees, are offered in New York and New Jersey by Bank of America, the report found. The worst for junk fees, in addition to the U.S. Bank version with overdraft fees, is the Tennessee card issued by JPMorgan Chase. It is one of only two states that fail to offer any free A.T.M. withdrawals. The report recommends that smaller states band together for more clout when negotiating card terms with banks. And it urges the new Consumer Financial Protection Bureau to take up the cause of excessive fees on prepaid cards when it opens for business this summer. “We hope prepaid cards are high on the agenda,” said Lauren Saunders, managing attorney at the Consumer Law Center in Washington, and the primary author of the report. Have you received jobless benefits on a prepaid card? What has your experience been?</text></article><article index="5" href="http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/04/18/ally-bank-offers-remote-deposit-but-not-from-your-phone/?ref=usbancorp">Ally Bank Offers Remote Deposit, but Not From Your Phone<date>April 18, 2011, 3:19 pm</date><text>Ally Bank 4/19/11 4:55 p.m. | Updated A holy grail of modern consumer banking is the ability to deposit checks electronically without having to schlep to a branch or an A.T.M. Because online-only banks don’t have branches to begin with, you would think they would be leaders in this, but others have beaten them to the punch. Both USAA in San Antonio, a bank with limited walk-in locations that serves military families, and J.P. Morgan Chase, with thousands of brick-and-mortar branches, have been out in front on mobile deposits. Both allow customers to deposit paper checks instantly by snapping photos of them with their smartphones and pressing a button. PNC Bank and U.S. Bank, too, offer deposits via apps for the iPhone. Pretty cool. Now the online Ally Bank said it would start offering remote deposit on Wednesday for its customers. (“Finally!” one commented on the bank’s Facebook page.) Compared with smartphone deposits, Ally’s approach seems almost quaint: Customers use a computer and a scanner. There’s no mobile phone option. “We are currently evaluating mobile deposit capture,” said a bank spokeswoman, Beth Coggins. Still, Ally is ahead of its branchless competitor ING Direct, which will offer remote deposit “in the near future,” a spokesman said. And the move is welcomed by Ally’s customers, who previously had to arrange for direct deposits into their account, transfer funds from another bank or send checks for deposit via snail mail. Customers who already have a computer and a desktop scanner don’t need to buy extra equipment, Ms. Coggins, said. When they log into their bank account, they can access  instructions that walk them through the deposit process, which involves scanning both sides of the check before zapping it to Ally. They’ll get an e-mail confirming the transaction. Ms. Coggins said the bank tested the system over several months with its own employees to work out bugs before offering it to customers. “Safety and security are extremely important for us,” she told me in a phone interview. For example, the system requires checks be endorsed in a specific way, so that they can’t be presented for deposit or cashing elsewhere after they’re scanned, she said. Not everyone will get to use the service right away; the bank is offering it in stages so it can make adjustments as it rolls out. Paper checks are less common than they used to be, but there’s clearly still a demand for ways to convert them electronically into bank funds, Ms. Coggins said. “Our customers have been asking for it, and so we think there’s a need.” Does your bank offer remote deposit? If not, how do you handle check deposits? Or, if you can already deposit checks remotely at your bank, what has been your experience? Updated to add a comment from the bank on status of mobile phone deposit option.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/02/08/when-poverty-tax-breaks-go-to-posh-hotels/?ref=usbancorp">Upscale Projects Tapping Tax Credits Aimed at Fighting Poverty<date>February 8, 2011, 4:08 am</date><text>Douglas C. Pizac/Associated Press Prudential Financial is one of the companies that claimed millions in tax credits aimed at fighting poverty for financing projects like luxury hotels. Banks and insurance companies are taking advantage of a federal aid program aimed at disadvantaged communities, claiming tax credits worth millions of dollars on projects like luxury hotels, Bloomberg Markets magazine reports in its March issue. Take the Blackstone Hotel in Chicago (no relation to the Blackstone Group). Between 2006 and 2008, $116 million was spent to renovate this high-end resort, which charges visitors up to $699 per night. Prudential Financial, one of the largest insurance companies in America, received a $15.6 million tax credit for financing the project. That credit came under the New Markets Tax Credits program, a $10.1 billion program to provide incentives for companies to develop poor neighborhoods and towns. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Bloomberg News » But the criteria for gauging poverty have allowed some backers of upscale developments to avoid taxes by tapping into the program. A Prudential spokesman declined to comment specifically about the Blackstone Hotel to Bloomberg News. “Things like luxury hotels are entirely contrary to what we set out to do,” said Cliff Kellogg, a former senior policy adviser at the Treasury Department. “Some hotels may create jobs and spur other nearby investment, but you have to ask if these projects prevent worthwhile ones from getting done.” The New Markets program has steered $3.9 billion into areas with family poverty rates of more than 30 percent, Treasury data shows. To qualify, an areas must either have a 20 percent rate of poverty or have an average income 20 percent below that of surrounding neighborhoods. But the Treasury Department allows individuals to be counted in its census — a measure that can include many college students — even though tallying the poverty rate of families would be more accurate. Altogether, Prudential Financial (the biggest recipient), U.S. Bancorp and PNC Financial Services received tax credits worth $79 million to build luxury hotels, an automobile museum and a shopping mall, Bloomberg reported.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/08/business/08mortgage.html?ref=usbancorp">Court Voids Foreclosures by U.S. Bancorp and Wells Fargo<date>Published: January 7, 2011</date><text>The highest court in Massachusetts ruled Friday that U.S. Bancorp and Wells Fargo erred when they seized two troubled borrowers’ properties in 2007, putting the nation’s banks on notice that foreclosures cannot be based on improper or incomplete paperwork.Concluding that neither institution had proved it had the right to evict the borrowers, the Supreme Judicial Court voided the foreclosures, returning ownership of the properties to the borrowers and opening the door to other foreclosure do-overs in the state. Legal experts said that while this ruling did not set a precedent for other states, the outcome will be closely watched across the country because it is the first such ruling from a state’s highest court. Investors viewed the ruling as negative for banks; an index of financial company shares fell almost 1 percent on the day. “The broad implication is you’ve got to dot your i’s and cross your t’s,” said Kathleen G. Cully, an expert in bankruptcy and lender regulatory law in New York. “You need a proper chain of title, and in both of these cases there was a gap in the chain.” The case dates to 2007, when Wells Fargo and U.S. Bancorp began foreclosure proceedings against delinquent borrowers on two separate properties. Neither borrower fought the proceedings — the courts in Massachusetts are not obligated to oversee foreclosures — and both banks quickly seized the properties. The banks’ problems began in the fall of 2008, when Wells Fargo and U.S. Bancorp sought judgments from the Massachusetts Land Court that would have given them clear title to the properties. In 2009, the court rejected the banks’ arguments, ruling that the banks had not been assigned the mortgages before they foreclosed, as is required. Instead, the banks had acquired the mortgages after they had begun foreclosure proceedings. The ruling on Friday upheld that decision. Foreclosures are supposed to occur only when lenders can prove they own the note underlying the property. While it is common now for borrowers to question whether banks moving to seize their properties have the right to do so, in 2007, most borrowers assumed that the institutions foreclosing on them were acting properly. Since then, lenders’ foreclosure practices have come under intense scrutiny. Borrowers’ advocates have argued that lenders flouted private property rights in their rush to foreclose on troubled borrowers. As lenders and Wall Street firms bundled thousands of mortgage loans into securities, banks often failed to record each link in the chain of documents demonstrating ownership of a note and a property. Attorneys general in all 50 states are investigating foreclosure improprieties, which include forged signatures on legal documents and other dubious practices meant to patch up holes in loan documentation. Both mortgages in the Massachusetts case had been bundled into securities and sold to investors. The banks that foreclosed on the borrowers were acting as trustees, bringing the actions on behalf of investors in the trusts, which held the properties at the time of the ruling. In a statement, Steve Dale, a U.S. Bancorp spokesman, said: “Our role in this case is solely as trustee concerning a mortgage owned by a securitization trust. This judgment has no financial impact on U.S. Bancorp. The issues addressed by the court revolved around the process of the servicing of the loan on behalf of the securitization trust, which was preformed in this case by the servicer, American Home Mortgage Servicing.” Vickee J. Adams, a Wells Fargo spokeswoman, said: “The loans at issue in the court’s ruling were not originated, owned, serviced or foreclosed upon by Wells Fargo. As trustee of a securitized pool of loans, Wells Fargo expects the entities who service these loans to abide by all applicable state laws, including those laws that govern foreclosure sales.” Paul R. Collier III, a lawyer in Cambridge, Mass., represented Antonio Ibanez, one borrower in the case. “It’s been pretty clear and becoming ever more clear that the securitization industry has behaved as though it were immune from consumer protection laws, state homeowner protection laws and real estate regulations in its underwriting, securitization and foreclosure practices,” Mr. Collier said. “I am quite confident that this is merely the first petal off the rose with regard to predatory foreclosure practices.” A special education teacher in Brookline, Mr. Ibanez and his wife moved out of the house and are now living in a rental condominium, his lawyer said. U.S. Bancorp, as trustee, will either have to pay Mr. Ibanez to buy a deed from him, Mr. Collier said, or walk away from the property, leaving it to Mr. Ibanez. The loss on the property will be taken by investors in the trust that had claimed ownership of the mortgage. The other borrowers whose foreclosure was overturned — Mark and Tammy LaRace — are still living in the home. They could not be reached. The banks involved in the matter had asked the Massachusetts court to make its ruling prospective, meaning that it would affect only new foreclosures. The court declined to do so, allowing foreclosure cases that have been completed to be reopened and brought under scrutiny. Mr. Collier said he had a dozen similar cases. In a legal brief presented to the Massachusetts court, representatives of the real estate industry said there were thousands of foreclosure cases in the state with facts like those in the Ibanez matter.The highest court in Massachusetts ruled Friday that U.S. Bancorp and Wells Fargo erred when they seized two troubled borrowers’ properties in 2007, putting the nation’s banks on notice that foreclosures cannot be based on improper or incomplete paperwork.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/25/business/25labor.html?ref=usbancorp">Unions Make Strides as They Attack Banks<date>Published: March 24, 2010</date><text>When the city of Los Angeles started looking into its complex financial contracts with banks earlier this year, some council members turned to an unusual corner for financial advice: labor unions.Turns out that union leaders had amassed an armory of research on derivatives, mortgage foreclosures and even Wall Street pay as part of their effort to hold bankers accountable for the economic pain they helped cause in Los Angeles and across the country. Unions have criticized Wall Street before. But their attacks have taken on a new shape, both in ferocity and style, over the last 18 months, ever since the federal government doled out billions of dollars in bank bailouts. Why? Labor leaders say the fortunes of banks and unions are linked more than people realize. Wall Street manages union pension portfolios worth hundreds of billions of dollars. Much of that is invested in financial institutions, giving unions a loud voice as shareholders. Then there are all the unionized workers whose fates are indirectly shaped by the world of high finance. The jobs of hundreds of thousands of union members, like police officers and teachers, have been threatened by municipal budget cuts, made worse in some cases by exotic investments gone bad. More abstractly, union leaders are framing their fight against Wall Street as a symbolic one, underscoring America’s large disparities in wealth and wages. “Many unions see that they need to be responsible for not just members’ needs at the bargaining table, but other hardships in their lives, like foreclosures and high mortgage costs,” said Peter Dreier, a political science professor at Occidental College in Los Angeles. Unions are holding up many of their own members as victims of the banks’ bad bets, like subprime mortgages, and are providing a steady stream of research in an effort to demystify the exotic financial products that they say are harming dozens of cities. Unions have also helped underwrite Americans for Financial Reform, a prominent group pushing for further bank regulation. Labor leaders were among the first to call for the resignation of Bank of America’s chief executive, who did retire months later. Unions issued a scathing report on bank bonuses, months before the federal pay czar presented his findings, and they criticized Goldman Sachs’s bonus pool just before the bank said its chief would receive only stock. This month, the A.F.L.-C.I.O., the nation’s main labor federation, has organized 200 protests nationwide to publicly shame bankers, calling for new taxes on bankers’ bonuses and on speculative short-term financial transactions — in the hope of collecting tens of billions of dollars to finance a job creation program. “They played Russian roulette with our economy, and while Wall Street cashed in, they left Main Street holding the bag,” Richard L. Trumka, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.’s president, said last Friday at a rally in Philadelphia. “They gorge themselves in a trough of taxpayers’ dollars, while we struggle to make ends meet.” Labor is directly at odds with Wall Street on unionization drives and many other matters. Banks and private equity firms own stakes in many businesses that unions would like to unionize, like nursing home chains and food service companies. Labor groups like the Service Employees International Union and the A.F.L.-C.I.O. are pressuring financial companies not to oppose union membership drives. It is hard to know for certain whether the unions’ efforts have affected decisions made by Wall Street firms. But for cities like Los Angeles, feeling the squeeze of lower tax receipts, the service employees’ pressure campaign seemed to have had an impact. “They knew more about our own water deal than I knew,” said Richard Alarcón, a Los Angeles councilman, referring to an interest-rate swap between the city’s water system and the Bank of New York Mellon that converted the system’s variable-rate bonds into bonds with a fixed rate. “They also knew the dynamics of swap deals, and they were very helpful.” As the city faces a deficit of nearly $500 million, the council was unhappy that Los Angeles would have to pay Bank of New York millions of dollars a year. “Our members don’t like it any more than other Americans when cities have less firefighters, less teachers or less police officers,” said Andy Stern, president of the service employees’ union. The labor protests against the banks sometimes have murky targets. This month, service employees joined community leaders on the City Hall steps in Oakland, Calif., to denounce Goldman Sachs for arranging interest-rate swaps that have the city paying the bank millions a year. After that rally, union leaders led a march to a local Citigroup branch. Goldman declined to comment, but a Citigroup representative scoffed. “We weren’t even involved in those deals,” said Alex Samuelson, a Citigroup spokesman. “We were just a symbolic place to go and rail against Wall Street. You can’t go to a Goldman Sachs branch.”</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/02/business/02fees.html?ref=usbancorp">Bank Fees Rise as Lenders Try to Offset Losses<date>Published: July 1, 2009</date><text>Bounced check: $32. Stop-payment: $30. A.T.M. charge: as high as $3. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Foley/European Pressphoto Agency Customers using A.T.M.s, like these at a Bank of America branch in New York, are noticing higher fees for transactions. Multimedia Graphic Add to Portfolio Bank of America Corp US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » Even now, after all those bailouts, banks never seem to tire of dipping a little deeper into your wallet. Despite the tough economic times and increased scrutiny from Washington, they are keeping most fees at record highs, and are eking out slight increases on others like overdraft charges  a step they rarely took during past recessions. The result? Americans are paying more to save and spend their money. And while the increases are still relatively small by historical standards, they illustrate how banks are looking for almost any nugget of income to help offset huge loan losses and lower revenue as consumers buckle down on spending. The nation’s biggest banks  those that received the biggest bailouts from taxpayers, and are once again gaining strength  charge fees that are on average at least 20 percent higher than those at smaller lenders, according to Moebs Services, a economic research firm used by banks and federal regulators. Some of the charges are getting more creative. Several big banks  including JPMorgan Chase, US Bancorp and Wells Fargo &amp;  recently began billing some small-business customers for federal deposit insurance increases. Citigroup and PNC Financial assess around a 3 percent international transaction fee when customers swipe their debit cards overseas. Bank of America recently introduced a raft of changes. In June, it raised the fees on its basic monthly checking account to $8.95 from $5.95. In April, the bank considered raising its overdraft charge to $39, nearly double what the typical bank charged a decade ago. It backed down only after an eruption of consumer complaints, tweaking its rules to keep its initial fee at $35. And then there are credit cards: banks are scrambling to raise rates and fees before a credit card reform bill that President Obama signed into law last month takes effect. JPMorgan Chase recently announced it would raise some balance transfer fees to 5 percent, from 3 percent, in August. Citigroup, Bank of America and other lenders have also been raising the interest rates for millions of cardholders. Over all, fees at the biggest banks are running at their highest levels on record. The average A.T.M. charge, which generates billions of dollars for banks annually, rose at the end of 2008 to $1.97, up from $1.78 the year before and nearly double the 89-cent average recorded in 1998, according to Bankrate.com. Other charges are more eye-popping: today’s typical $30 stop-payment fee is about twice as much as a decade ago, according to Moebs. But the most unexpected change has occurred in overdraft fees  the industry’s most lucrative and controversial charge  where the typical fee rose to $26 after five years at $25. That is only a modest 4 percent increase, compared with the double-digit overdraft fee increases a few years ago, when charges rose to $25 from $22. But amid intense scrutiny from regulators and lawmakers, consumer advocates  and even some bankers are surprised. “We’ve never seen a price increase during a recession,” said Michael Moebs, the chief economist and founder of the research firm that analyzed the fee data at more than 2,200 lenders. “What the bankers are saying is that I want to maintain my revenue.” Scott E. Talbott, a lobbyist for the Financial Services Roundtable, said that the banks’ fees reflect the cost of providing those services and the rise in overdraft charges reflects increased risk. “There is an increased riskiness around repayment because of the recession,” he added. Most banks have been reluctant to raise overdraft fees or have made subtle but potentially lucrative changes to how they are assessed. Bankers are worried about criticism from Washington and would rather find ways to bolster profits under the radar. For instance, many banks already generate rich profits by charging consumers high interest rates for loans, while keeping interest rates paid on money market and checking accounts low  a trend that has become more acute as the Federal Reserve keeps rates near zero to help stoke an economic recovery. But that may not be enough. Large banks, which tend to charge the highest fees, incur a range of expenses that smaller banks do not, including high nationwide advertising bills and the costs of operating networks of A.T.M.’s and retail branches. Many smaller banks are also struggling now more than ever to offset losses and dwindling revenue. And as consumers themselves rein in their finances, raising the overdraft fee has become an easy option. With fewer customers overdrawing their accounts, overdraft fees risk shrinking to a smaller income stream from what Moebs estimates is a $38.5 billion business this year. That is, unless banks raise fees on customers who run into trouble. Aaron Fine, a retail banking consultant at Oliver Wyman, said that overdraft fee income could fall 5 to 20 percent for some banks in the second and third quarter. “That is the multibillion-dollar question,” he said. “How do you replace those fees with something else?” Two large regional banks, which have been hit hard by the recession, appear to be struggling to find answers. KeyCorp, a regional lender based in Cleveland, raised its overdraft fee by 50 cents to a dollar for repeat offenders in the last few months, bringing its maximum charge to as much as $39. Comerica, which has big operations in Michigan and California, raised similar fees by approximately $2 to $3 when it introduced a tiered fee structure that charges $25 to $37 as the number of offenses increase. Regulators and lawmakers say they plan to crack down on excessive service fees, just as they did with a new bill barring unfair credit card practices. Federal Reserve officials have proposed new rules that would let debit and A.T.M. customers “opt in” for overdraft protection, or allow existing customers to opt out of the service. Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, Democrat of New York, introduced more stringent legislation this spring requiring banks to notify customers before they overdraw their accounts. Of course, consumers do not have to be taken in. Consumer advocates suggest comparing the fees charged by big banks with those of credit unions and community lenders in a given area. When possible, use an A.T.M. in the bank’s network. And if you do incur fees, ask your bank manager about waiving them. Greg McBride, a senior financial analyst at BankRate.com, said that as banking fees head into overdrive, consumers simply need to be more alert. “We will have to be on our toes to avoid getting tripped up,” he said. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on July 2, 2009, on page B1 of the New York edition.Bounced check: $32. Stop-payment: $30. A.T.M. charge: as high as $3. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Peter Foley/European Pressphoto Agency Customers using A.T.M.s, like these at a Bank of America branch in New York, are noticing higher fees for transactions. Multimedia Graphic Add to Portfolio Bank of America Corp US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » Even now, after all those bailouts, banks never seem to tire of dipping a little deeper into your wallet. Despite the tough economic times and increased scrutiny from Washington, they are keeping most fees at record highs, and are eking out slight increases on others like overdraft charges  a step they rarely took during past recessions. The result? Americans are paying more to save and spend their money. And while the increases are still relatively small by historical standards, they illustrate how banks are looking for almost any nugget of income to help offset huge loan losses and lower revenue as consumers buckle down on spending. The nation’s biggest banks  those that received the biggest bailouts from taxpayers, and are once again gaining strength  charge fees that are on average at least 20 percent higher than those at smaller lenders, according to Moebs Services, a economic research firm used by banks and federal regulators. Some of the charges are getting more creative. Several big banks  including JPMorgan Chase, US Bancorp and Wells Fargo &amp;  recently began billing some small-business customers for federal deposit insurance increases. Citigroup and PNC Financial assess around a 3 percent international transaction fee when customers swipe their debit cards overseas. Bank of America recently introduced a raft of changes. In June, it raised the fees on its basic monthly checking account to $8.95 from $5.95. In April, the bank considered raising its overdraft charge to $39, nearly double what the typical bank charged a decade ago. It backed down only after an eruption of consumer complaints, tweaking its rules to keep its initial fee at $35. And then there are credit cards: banks are scrambling to raise rates and fees before a credit card reform bill that President Obama signed into law last month takes effect. JPMorgan Chase recently announced it would raise some balance transfer fees to 5 percent, from 3 percent, in August. Citigroup, Bank of America and other lenders have also been raising the interest rates for millions of cardholders. Over all, fees at the biggest banks are running at their highest levels on record. The average A.T.M. charge, which generates billions of dollars for banks annually, rose at the end of 2008 to $1.97, up from $1.78 the year before and nearly double the 89-cent average recorded in 1998, according to Bankrate.com. Other charges are more eye-popping: today’s typical $30 stop-payment fee is about twice as much as a decade ago, according to Moebs. But the most unexpected change has occurred in overdraft fees  the industry’s most lucrative and controversial charge  where the typical fee rose to $26 after five years at $25. That is only a modest 4 percent increase, compared with the double-digit overdraft fee increases a few years ago, when charges rose to $25 from $22. But amid intense scrutiny from regulators and lawmakers, consumer advocates  and even some bankers are surprised. “We’ve never seen a price increase during a recession,” said Michael Moebs, the chief economist and founder of the research firm that analyzed the fee data at more than 2,200 lenders. “What the bankers are saying is that I want to maintain my revenue.” Scott E. Talbott, a lobbyist for the Financial Services Roundtable, said that the banks’ fees reflect the cost of providing those services and the rise in overdraft charges reflects increased risk. “There is an increased riskiness around repayment because of the recession,” he added. Most banks have been reluctant to raise overdraft fees or have made subtle but potentially lucrative changes to how they are assessed. Bankers are worried about criticism from Washington and would rather find ways to bolster profits under the radar. For instance, many banks already generate rich profits by charging consumers high interest rates for loans, while keeping interest rates paid on money market and checking accounts low  a trend that has become more acute as the Federal Reserve keeps rates near zero to help stoke an economic recovery. But that may not be enough. Large banks, which tend to charge the highest fees, incur a range of expenses that smaller banks do not, including high nationwide advertising bills and the costs of operating networks of A.T.M.’s and retail branches. Many smaller banks are also struggling now more than ever to offset losses and dwindling revenue. And as consumers themselves rein in their finances, raising the overdraft fee has become an easy option. With fewer customers overdrawing their accounts, overdraft fees risk shrinking to a smaller income stream from what Moebs estimates is a $38.5 billion business this year. That is, unless banks raise fees on customers who run into trouble. Aaron Fine, a retail banking consultant at Oliver Wyman, said that overdraft fee income could fall 5 to 20 percent for some banks in the second and third quarter. “That is the multibillion-dollar question,” he said. “How do you replace those fees with something else?” Two large regional banks, which have been hit hard by the recession, appear to be struggling to find answers. KeyCorp, a regional lender based in Cleveland, raised its overdraft fee by 50 cents to a dollar for repeat offenders in the last few months, bringing its maximum charge to as much as $39. Comerica, which has big operations in Michigan and California, raised similar fees by approximately $2 to $3 when it introduced a tiered fee structure that charges $25 to $37 as the number of offenses increase. Regulators and lawmakers say they plan to crack down on excessive service fees, just as they did with a new bill barring unfair credit card practices. Federal Reserve officials have proposed new rules that would let debit and A.T.M. customers “opt in” for overdraft protection, or allow existing customers to opt out of the service. Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, Democrat of New York, introduced more stringent legislation this spring requiring banks to notify customers before they overdraw their accounts. Of course, consumers do not have to be taken in. Consumer advocates suggest comparing the fees charged by big banks with those of credit unions and community lenders in a given area. When possible, use an A.T.M. in the bank’s network. And if you do incur fees, ask your bank manager about waiving them. Greg McBride, a senior financial analyst at BankRate.com, said that as banking fees head into overdrive, consumers simply need to be more alert. “We will have to be on our toes to avoid getting tripped up,” he said.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/08/business/08views.html?ref=usbancorp">Tests May Spur Bank Mergers<date>Published: May 7, 2009</date><text>For America’s regional banks, it’s merger time. With the results of the stress tests now public, it’s clear that none of the country’s largest financial institutions will fail. Those that need capital will find it, even if it takes de facto nationalization. But that doesn’t mean the banking system is robust. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Regions Financial Corporation US Bancorp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » A handful of regional institutions received the equivalent of barely passing grades  including SunTrust, Regions Financial, KeyCorp and Fifth Third. These banks have more than $500 billion of assets among them. Even if they can raise the extra capital that regulators say they need, they may not be in a position to act as engines of credit creation  a requirement for their local economies to pull out of the recession. Moreover, if they can’t raise private money over the next six months, they may need to have the government take significant, or even majority, stakes in them. One risk is that they will stagger along, zombielike, for years. There’s an alternative: Let the strong eat the weak. A core group of relatively robust regional banks has also emerged from the Treasury’s examinations, including U.S. Bancorp and BB&amp;T, as well as PNC Financial, which has to raise a relatively modest $600 million. An alternative to propping up troubled banks with new capital is to actively encourage a wave of consolidation. This approach would make life simpler for the government should the banks fail to raise private capital. Rather than taking controlling positions in many midsize banks, the government could take smaller stakes (or none at all) in fewer, larger banks that in turn use the capital to buy troubled rivals. By encouraging, for instance, the acquisition of SunTrust by BB&amp;T, the takeover of KeyCorp by U.S. Bancorp and the purchase of Regions by PNC, the government would foster the creation of three new heavyweights better equipped to compete with JPMorgan Chase, Wells Fargo and Bank of America. These three went from big to megabanks by acquiring troubled rivals like Washington Mutual, Wachovia and Countrywide early in the banking crisis, in deals blessed by regulators. In theory, this approach would also streamline and improve regulation. Instead of scattering oversight among six institutions, the government could focus on three. By favoring more of the banks that fared best in the crisis and not just the very biggest, it rewards those executives whose teams proved better at risk management, like Richard Davis, chief of U.S. Bancorp. Finally, the enormous savings that would come from cutting overlapping operations, extra branches and redundant workers would accrue to shareholders and add to the capital cushions. Last year Fifth Third, SunTrust, KeyCorp and Regions had combined noninterest expenses of $18.5 billion. As a general rule of thumb, knowledgeable bank acquirers aim to save about one-third of these costs. Gentlemen, start your M.&amp; A. spreadsheets. Boon for Underwriters Banks must raise $75 billion of equity over the next six months. That sounds bad, but on Wall Street it may be cause for some celebration. That’s because the underwriters who sell all of that stock can charge fees of as much as $3 billion for doing so. In the grand scheme of a $75 billion capital shortfall, it’s a pittance. But on the equity capital markets desks of the big investment banks, it would be a bonanza. Dealogic estimates it could add up to 12 times the amount they’ve earned so far this year. Underemployed bankers at Merrill Lynch may finally have a reason to applaud their new bosses’ missteps. Merrill’s new owner, Bank of America, needs the biggest capital infusion of all  $34 billion. Of course, the lead manager on a bank’s stock offering is often the bank itself, which is motivated not to ratchet up fees. And many of the banks that the government has ordered to raise more capital may do so by swapping existing preferred shares for common stock. But with most bank stocks trading at decent premiums to the prices at which they would have to convert the government’s preferred stock, it’s a fair bet the next six months will be happier for the underwriters of Wall Street. ROB COX and DWIGHT CASS For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on May 8, 2009, on page B2 of the New York edition.For America’s regional banks, it’s merger time. With the results of the stress tests now public, it’s clear that none of the country’s largest financial institutions will fail. Those that need capital will find it, even if it takes de facto nationalization. But that doesn’t mean the banking system is robust. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio Regions Financial Corporation US Bancorp Bank of America Corp Go to your Portfolio » A handful of regional institutions received the equivalent of barely passing grades  including SunTrust, Regions Financial, KeyCorp and Fifth Third. These banks have more than $500 billion of assets among them. Even if they can raise the extra capital that regulators say they need, they may not be in a position to act as engines of credit creation  a requirement for their local economies to pull out of the recession. Moreover, if they can’t raise private money over the next six months, they may need to have the government take significant, or even majority, stakes in them. One risk is that they will stagger along, zombielike, for years. There’s an alternative: Let the strong eat the weak. A core group of relatively robust regional banks has also emerged from the Treasury’s examinations, including U.S. Bancorp and BB&amp;T, as well as PNC Financial, which has to raise a relatively modest $600 million. An alternative to propping up troubled banks with new capital is to actively encourage a wave of consolidation. This approach would make life simpler for the government should the banks fail to raise private capital. Rather than taking controlling positions in many midsize banks, the government could take smaller stakes (or none at all) in fewer, larger banks that in turn use the capital to buy troubled rivals. By encouraging, for instance, the acquisition of SunTrust by BB&amp;T, the takeover of KeyCorp by U.S. Bancorp and the purchase of Regions by PNC, the government would foster the creation of three new heavyweights better equipped to compete with JPMorgan Chase, Wells Fargo and Bank of America. These three went from big to megabanks by acquiring troubled rivals like Washington Mutual, Wachovia and Countrywide early in the banking crisis, in deals blessed by regulators. In theory, this approach would also streamline and improve regulation. Instead of scattering oversight among six institutions, the government could focus on three. By favoring more of the banks that fared best in the crisis and not just the very biggest, it rewards those executives whose teams proved better at risk management, like Richard Davis, chief of U.S. Bancorp. Finally, the enormous savings that would come from cutting overlapping operations, extra branches and redundant workers would accrue to shareholders and add to the capital cushions. Last year Fifth Third, SunTrust, KeyCorp and Regions had combined noninterest expenses of $18.5 billion. As a general rule of thumb, knowledgeable bank acquirers aim to save about one-third of these costs. Gentlemen, start your M.&amp; A. spreadsheets. Boon for Underwriters Banks must raise $75 billion of equity over the next six months. That sounds bad, but on Wall Street it may be cause for some celebration. That’s because the underwriters who sell all of that stock can charge fees of as much as $3 billion for doing so. In the grand scheme of a $75 billion capital shortfall, it’s a pittance. But on the equity capital markets desks of the big investment banks, it would be a bonanza. Dealogic estimates it could add up to 12 times the amount they’ve earned so far this year. Underemployed bankers at Merrill Lynch may finally have a reason to applaud their new bosses’ missteps. Merrill’s new owner, Bank of America, needs the biggest capital infusion of all  $34 billion. Of course, the lead manager on a bank’s stock offering is often the bank itself, which is motivated not to ratchet up fees. And many of the banks that the government has ordered to raise more capital may do so by swapping existing preferred shares for common stock. But with most bank stocks trading at decent premiums to the prices at which they would have to convert the government’s preferred stock, it’s a fair bet the next six months will be happier for the underwriters of Wall Street. ROB COX and DWIGHT CASS For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/05/business/economy/05bancorp.html?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bancorp Cuts Its Dividend by 88%<date>Published: March 4, 2009</date><text>MINNEAPOLIS (AP)  U.S. Bancorp, the large regional bank, said Wednesday that its directors had approved a plan to slash its quarterly dividend on common stock by 88 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » The dividend will be cut to 5 cents a common share, from 42.5 cents per common share. The new dividend will be paid April 15 to shareholders of record as of March 31. U.S. Bancorp cut its dividend because of “uncertainty in the financial markets and a weakening economy,” the president and chief executive, Richard K. Davis, said in a statement. Dozens of banks have been slashing their dividends amid the continuing credit crisis and recession. With banks facing mounting loan losses, dividend cuts have been used to help preserve capital to cover those expected losses. Mr. Davis added the bank would return the dividend to ”a normalized rate as soon as possible,” though no further details were provided. U.S. Bancorp also declared dividends on two classes of preferred stock. Series B noncumulative perpetual preferred stockholders will receive a dividend of $218.75 a share. Series D noncumulative perpetual preferred stockholders will receive a dividend of $492.19 a share. Those dividends will also be paid April 15 to shareholders of record on March 31. More Articles in Business »MINNEAPOLIS (AP)  U.S. Bancorp, the large regional bank, said Wednesday that its directors had approved a plan to slash its quarterly dividend on common stock by 88 percent. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » The dividend will be cut to 5 cents a common share, from 42.5 cents per common share. The new dividend will be paid April 15 to shareholders of record as of March 31. U.S. Bancorp cut its dividend because of “uncertainty in the financial markets and a weakening economy,” the president and chief executive, Richard K. Davis, said in a statement. Dozens of banks have been slashing their dividends amid the continuing credit crisis and recession. With banks facing mounting loan losses, dividend cuts have been used to help preserve capital to cover those expected losses. Mr. Davis added the bank would return the dividend to ”a normalized rate as soon as possible,” though no further details were provided. U.S. Bancorp also declared dividends on two classes of preferred stock. Series B noncumulative perpetual preferred stockholders will receive a dividend of $218.75 a share. Series D noncumulative perpetual preferred stockholders will receive a dividend of $492.19 a share. Those dividends will also be paid April 15 to shareholders of record on March 31.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/22/business/22bancorp.html?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bancorp Posts Loss<date>Published: January 21, 2009</date><text>U.S. Bancorp posted a 72 percent decline in earnings in the final three months of last year, its eighth consecutive quarterly profit decline. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » For the fourth quarter of 2008, the company reported net income applicable to common shareholders of $260 million, or 15 cents a share, down from $927 million, or 53 cents a share, a year earlier. The company set aside $1.27 billion during the quarter to cover bad loans. More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on January 22, 2009, on page B7 of the New York edition.U.S. Bancorp posted a 72 percent decline in earnings in the final three months of last year, its eighth consecutive quarterly profit decline. Skip to next paragraph Add to Portfolio US Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » For the fourth quarter of 2008, the company reported net income applicable to common shareholders of $260 million, or 15 cents a share, down from $927 million, or 53 cents a share, a year earlier. The company set aside $1.27 billion during the quarter to cover bad loans.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/22/business/22bank.html?ref=usbancorp">Regional Banks Struggled Through 3rd Quarter<date>Published: October 21, 2008</date><text>In the Depression year of 1933, Cleveland suffered a citywide run on the banks. When the panic subsided, National City Bank was the first to reopen. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Aaron Josefczyk/Reuters National City, among regional banks feeling the strain of the credit squeeze, will lay off 4,000 employees as its losses surge. Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis  The Essentials Add to Portfolio National City Corporation US Bancorp Keycorp Fifth Third Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » But today that Ohio bank, now known as National City Corporation, has come to symbolize the crisis that is hobbling regional lenders across the nation. Many of these midsize institutions face uncertain futures, despite the government’s bank rescue plan. Five regional banks, National City among them, reported another round of painful results on Tuesday, and analysts say their business will worsen as the economy deteriorates. Several of these banks said they hoped to sell stock to the government to shore up their finances, as nine big national banks have done. But with losses mounting, it is unclear how many small and midsize lenders the government will choose to save. In some cases, analysts said, the Treasury will probably play kingmaker, nudging weak banks into the arms of stronger rivals. In others, banks could drag on, reporting disappointing results for at least the next four quarters. “We began over a year ago to try to configure the company for a difficult period,” Peter Raskind, National City’s chief executive, said in an interview Tuesday. “I don’t think anybody thought it would be this difficult.” For National City and many of the other regional banks, things are quickly moving from bad to worse. Mortgages and home equity losses continue to rise as housing prices have yet to find a bottom. Losses on auto and credit card loans have surged. New problem areas, like loans made to small corporations and commercial real estate developers, are starting to come under pressure. And that is with an unemployment rate that up until now has been unusually resilient. As the economy continues to slow and more jobs are lost, the banking industry’s problems could grow even bleaker. National City said it would cut 4,000 jobs as it reported a surge in losses to $729 million for the period, up from $19 million a year earlier. The bank had to increase the cushion it set aside for loan losses to $1.18 billion. Fifth Third, another Ohio-based bank, lost $56 million. KeyCorp of Cincinnati lost $36 million. Regions Financial of Alabama eked out a $79.5 million profit. Shares in the banks rose because their troubles were not as deep as expected, but other banks fell on concerns about their health. U.S. Bancorp of Minneapolis fell almost 3 percent, to $30.20, after reporting a drop in earnings tied to higher projected losses. Bank stocks generally are down about 42 percent in the last year. Investors are staring through a looking glass of diminished expectations, industry experts say. “You get to a point where it is not about the earnings,” said Brian R. Sterling, the co-head of investment banking at Sandler O’Neill and Partners. “It’s all about the book value” of assets and the strength of its balance sheet. They may also be looking to the future. “Historically, bank stocks have bottomed a full year before losses peaked,” said Jason Goldberg, a banking analyst at Barclays Capital. That, he said, is what happened during the recessions that followed the savings and loan crisis and the bursting of the technology bubble. The prospect of deeper losses at banks is setting the stage for a second round of consolidation in the industry, after the recent wave of blockbuster deals that occurred as the nation’s biggest banks swallowed troubled competitors. One regional bank, Sovereign Bancorp, was bought this month by a big Spanish bank amid signs that its finances were deteriorating. Citigroup is on the prowl for a deal that could bolster its relatively small domestic retail banking operations. While some regional banks had been reluctant to undertake or unable to complete such transactions, several regional lenders said Tuesday they would seek to take advantage of the government’s program of capital infusions to snap up weaker rivals. Regions Financial said it would seek to raise as much as $3.5 billion from the government; KeyCorp said it would seek $1.1 billion to $3.3 billion, and Zions Bancorporation of Utah said it would consider asking the government to take a stake of $500 million to $1.5 billion. Executives at BB&amp;T, PNC Financial and U.S. Bancorp also said in conference calls that they found the government’s offer quite attractive. “I am telegraphing that we’re more active and more interested than we might have been before” to pursue a deal, Richard Davis, U.S. Bancorp’s chief executive, said in a conference call Tuesday. Banks will have until Nov. 14 to apply for the Treasury program. Some are being encouraged by their regulators to apply. But others may be deemed too far gone to receive government funds. Indeed, analysts said they expected the government might use the money as an inducement to spur healthier banks to do a deal, or withhold it to urge weaker institutions to consider selling. Mr. Sterling said he would expect “deal dialogue to pick up” as it becomes clear who is getting financing and who is not. But other lenders may have fewer options. National City said that while it was interested in selling troubled assets into the government’s $700 billion bailout fund, it had not decided whether it would seek government capital. “There are a number of implications of taking advantage of it or not taking advantage of it,” Mr. Raskind said. “That is what we are thinking through right now.” Mr. Raskind said the company was cutting costs and had stockpiled enough funds to weather the worsening economy. “We pretty firmly believe we have more than adequate capital to see us through that,” he added. Still, there are more signs of trouble in other areas. Beyond worsening mortgages and consumer loans, analysts say that there are signs that loans made to small and midsize businesses appear to be souring across the country. This had been the bread-and-butter of regional banks, which took advantage of local ties after being elbowed out of the credit card and mortgage business by national players. First Horizon National of Tennessee, Capitol Bancorp of Michigan and Arizona and Sovereign Bancorp of Philadelphia had sharp increases in the percentage of bad loans in their commercial and industrial portfolio, according to an analysis by Friedman, Billings, Ramsey. “It is definitely a sign the economy is weakening,” said Paul Miller, one of its banking analysts. “You have another loan category coming down the road.” And analysts are beginning to see stress in loans to commercial real estate developers, especially in mall properties that are dependent on the retail sector. “There are lots of bank lines and loans out to developers and that type of commercial real estate,” said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. “We are beginning to see a few cracks in office space as well.” More Articles in Business » A version of this article appeared in print on October 22, 2008, on page B9 of the New York edition.In the Depression year of 1933, Cleveland suffered a citywide run on the banks. When the panic subsided, National City Bank was the first to reopen. Skip to next paragraph Enlarge This Image Aaron Josefczyk/Reuters National City, among regional banks feeling the strain of the credit squeeze, will lay off 4,000 employees as its losses surge. Related Times Topics: Credit Crisis  The Essentials Add to Portfolio National City Corporation US Bancorp Keycorp Fifth Third Bancorp Go to your Portfolio » But today that Ohio bank, now known as National City Corporation, has come to symbolize the crisis that is hobbling regional lenders across the nation. Many of these midsize institutions face uncertain futures, despite the government’s bank rescue plan. Five regional banks, National City among them, reported another round of painful results on Tuesday, and analysts say their business will worsen as the economy deteriorates. Several of these banks said they hoped to sell stock to the government to shore up their finances, as nine big national banks have done. But with losses mounting, it is unclear how many small and midsize lenders the government will choose to save. In some cases, analysts said, the Treasury will probably play kingmaker, nudging weak banks into the arms of stronger rivals. In others, banks could drag on, reporting disappointing results for at least the next four quarters. “We began over a year ago to try to configure the company for a difficult period,” Peter Raskind, National City’s chief executive, said in an interview Tuesday. “I don’t think anybody thought it would be this difficult.” For National City and many of the other regional banks, things are quickly moving from bad to worse. Mortgages and home equity losses continue to rise as housing prices have yet to find a bottom. Losses on auto and credit card loans have surged. New problem areas, like loans made to small corporations and commercial real estate developers, are starting to come under pressure. And that is with an unemployment rate that up until now has been unusually resilient. As the economy continues to slow and more jobs are lost, the banking industry’s problems could grow even bleaker. National City said it would cut 4,000 jobs as it reported a surge in losses to $729 million for the period, up from $19 million a year earlier. The bank had to increase the cushion it set aside for loan losses to $1.18 billion. Fifth Third, another Ohio-based bank, lost $56 million. KeyCorp of Cincinnati lost $36 million. Regions Financial of Alabama eked out a $79.5 million profit. Shares in the banks rose because their troubles were not as deep as expected, but other banks fell on concerns about their health. U.S. Bancorp of Minneapolis fell almost 3 percent, to $30.20, after reporting a drop in earnings tied to higher projected losses. Bank stocks generally are down about 42 percent in the last year. Investors are staring through a looking glass of diminished expectations, industry experts say. “You get to a point where it is not about the earnings,” said Brian R. Sterling, the co-head of investment banking at Sandler O’Neill and Partners. “It’s all about the book value” of assets and the strength of its balance sheet. They may also be looking to the future. “Historically, bank stocks have bottomed a full year before losses peaked,” said Jason Goldberg, a banking analyst at Barclays Capital. That, he said, is what happened during the recessions that followed the savings and loan crisis and the bursting of the technology bubble. The prospect of deeper losses at banks is setting the stage for a second round of consolidation in the industry, after the recent wave of blockbuster deals that occurred as the nation’s biggest banks swallowed troubled competitors. One regional bank, Sovereign Bancorp, was bought this month by a big Spanish bank amid signs that its finances were deteriorating. Citigroup is on the prowl for a deal that could bolster its relatively small domestic retail banking operations. While some regional banks had been reluctant to undertake or unable to complete such transactions, several regional lenders said Tuesday they would seek to take advantage of the government’s program of capital infusions to snap up weaker rivals. Regions Financial said it would seek to raise as much as $3.5 billion from the government; KeyCorp said it would seek $1.1 billion to $3.3 billion, and Zions Bancorporation of Utah said it would consider asking the government to take a stake of $500 million to $1.5 billion. Executives at BB&amp;T, PNC Financial and U.S. Bancorp also said in conference calls that they found the government’s offer quite attractive. “I am telegraphing that we’re more active and more interested than we might have been before” to pursue a deal, Richard Davis, U.S. Bancorp’s chief executive, said in a conference call Tuesday. Banks will have until Nov. 14 to apply for the Treasury program. Some are being encouraged by their regulators to apply. But others may be deemed too far gone to receive government funds. Indeed, analysts said they expected the government might use the money as an inducement to spur healthier banks to do a deal, or withhold it to urge weaker institutions to consider selling. Mr. Sterling said he would expect “deal dialogue to pick up” as it becomes clear who is getting financing and who is not. But other lenders may have fewer options. National City said that while it was interested in selling troubled assets into the government’s $700 billion bailout fund, it had not decided whether it would seek government capital. “There are a number of implications of taking advantage of it or not taking advantage of it,” Mr. Raskind said. “That is what we are thinking through right now.” Mr. Raskind said the company was cutting costs and had stockpiled enough funds to weather the worsening economy. “We pretty firmly believe we have more than adequate capital to see us through that,” he added. Still, there are more signs of trouble in other areas. Beyond worsening mortgages and consumer loans, analysts say that there are signs that loans made to small and midsize businesses appear to be souring across the country. This had been the bread-and-butter of regional banks, which took advantage of local ties after being elbowed out of the credit card and mortgage business by national players. First Horizon National of Tennessee, Capitol Bancorp of Michigan and Arizona and Sovereign Bancorp of Philadelphia had sharp increases in the percentage of bad loans in their commercial and industrial portfolio, according to an analysis by Friedman, Billings, Ramsey. “It is definitely a sign the economy is weakening,” said Paul Miller, one of its banking analysts. “You have another loan category coming down the road.” And analysts are beginning to see stress in loans to commercial real estate developers, especially in mall properties that are dependent on the retail sector. “There are lots of bank lines and loans out to developers and that type of commercial real estate,” said Nancy A. Bush, a longtime banking analyst. “We are beginning to see a few cracks in office space as well.”</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/22/business/22nocera.html?ref=usbancorp">Emerald City of Giving Does Exist<date>Published: December 22, 2007</date><text>Correction Appended My philanthropic tour of Minneapolis began on the banks of the Mississippi River, where the Great Northern Railroad once transported flour from the giant mills of General Mills and Pillsbury. The Great Northern is long gone  merged into the Burlington Northern almost 40 years ago, and though the mills are still standing, they have long since been converted to other uses, as General Mills moved to the suburbs, and, in time, acquired its rival Pillsbury. Bill King, the head of the Minnesota Council on Foundations  and my tour guide  pointed out the mills as we got into our car. As well he should have. One lasting legacy of the Great Northern is the Northwest Area Foundation, which was founded by James J. Hill, the Great Northern’s founder. As of March 2007, it had $500 million in assets and is devoted primarily to antipoverty efforts. Indeed, Minneapolis and St. Paul have an abundance of foundations that were started by the founders or top executives of many of its biggest companies, like 3M and Target. General Mills, meanwhile, was an early member of an organization begun in the mid-1970s called the Five Percent Club  in which Minneapolis-St. Paul corporations agreed to set aside 5 percent of their pretax income for philanthropy. Believe it or not  and it is a little hard to believe, given the modern emphasis on maximizing profits and pleasing Wall Street  the club still exists. Now known as the Keystone Club, it has 214 members, and 134 of them donate at the 5 percent level. (The others give away 2 percent of their profits.) Last year, General Mills donated more than $57 million, second only to Target, which gave away nearly $160 million. “Here’s the new Guthrie,” said Mr. King as we began the tour. The Guthrie Theater, the city’s fine regional theater, recently moved into a sparkling new building by the river  one of five major arts organizations that have recently built new buildings or major additions. All of them were built, in no small part, with corporate contributions. We drove a little farther. “This is where the bridge collapsed,” he said, pointing directly in front of us. He was speaking, of course, of the Interstate 35W bridge, which collapsed in August. “When it fell, there was an immediate response from corporations,” Mr. King continued. “And a fund for victims was set up by the Minneapolis and St. Paul Foundations.” The latter groups solicit donations from local people who want to be involved in philanthropy but lack the means to set up their own foundations. Combined, the two foundations have over $1.5 billion in assets and are major forces in the Twin Cities. We headed north. “North Minneapolis has long been a low-income neighborhood,” Mr. King said. “We have had wonderful success over all as a community, but we still have lots of problems. But we keep working at it.” We drove past a storefront that said, in bright lettering, “The Cookie Cart.” “This is a cookie business that is run by kids in the community,” Mr. King said. “It helps them learn skills that can really be useful. It has been around for 10 or 15 years.” Among the companies backing it are Wells Fargo, U.S. Bancorp and The Star Tribune. As we neared a school, Mr. King told me about a Medtronics-funded program that began years ago as a $75,000 pilot program to help children get interested in science. The company now spends more than a $1 million a year on it. And on, and on. We drove under a walking bridge, the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, built with donations from the Whitney family and others. In a neighborhood called Hawthorne, Mr. King explained that in 1996, after The New York Times noted that some people were calling Minneapolis “Murderapolis,” General Mills began investing in the neighborhood, with redevelopment and other efforts, including something called the Hawthorne Huddle, a monthly meeting that brought together residents and city officials to hash out solutions to problems. Ask anybody in the world of corporate philanthropy and they’ll tell you: Minneapolis-St. Paul is like no place else, a bastion of giving in an age when most companies are cutting back. “It is an unusual city in regards to corporate giving,” said former Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich. In the 1970s, John D. Rockefeller III said in a speech to the Minneapolis Chamber of Commerce that he had heard so much about “the public spirit of its business community, about your remarkable Five Percent Club that I feel a bit like Dorothy in the Land of Oz. I had to come to the Emerald City myself to see if it really exists.” So did I. And sure enough, it does exist. But why here? If you put this question to people in Minneapolis, you hear all kinds of theories. “When you live in such a harsh climate, you understand the need for the common good,” said Emmett D. Carson, the former president of the Minneapolis Foundation. Others suggested that the area’s corporate generosity grew out of the Scandinavian culture that took hold in this region, with its deep Lutheran roots. Christina L. Shea, the senior vice president for external relations at General Mills, thought it had to do with enlightened self-interest. “How do you attract high-powered talent?” she asked. A large part of the answer, she believed, had to do with building communities in which talented people wanted to live. Steve Rothschild, a former General Mills executive who left the company to found an antipoverty group called Twin Cities Rise, said he thought that Minneapolis-St. Paul companies have long viewed their responsibilities broadly. “Most Twin Cities companies have a stakeholder model, not a shareholder model,” he said. There is probably some truth to all of these theories. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: December 28, 2007 The Talking Business column in Business Day on Saturday, about corporate philanthropy in Minneapolis-St. Paul, misstated the names of two organizations involved in charitable work in the area. They are the Minnesota Council on Foundations, not the Minneapolis Council on Foundations, and Twin Cities Rise, not Twin Cities Rising. The column also referred incorrectly to financing of a pedestrian bridge over an interstate highway. The bridge  the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, which crosses I-94 to connect the Walker Art Center to the city’s park system  was built with donations from the Whitney family and others. Dayton-Hudson, a predecessor to the Target Corporation, did not build the bridge. More Articles in Business »Correction Appended My philanthropic tour of Minneapolis began on the banks of the Mississippi River, where the Great Northern Railroad once transported flour from the giant mills of General Mills and Pillsbury. The Great Northern is long gone  merged into the Burlington Northern almost 40 years ago, and though the mills are still standing, they have long since been converted to other uses, as General Mills moved to the suburbs, and, in time, acquired its rival Pillsbury. Bill King, the head of the Minnesota Council on Foundations  and my tour guide  pointed out the mills as we got into our car. As well he should have. One lasting legacy of the Great Northern is the Northwest Area Foundation, which was founded by James J. Hill, the Great Northern’s founder. As of March 2007, it had $500 million in assets and is devoted primarily to antipoverty efforts. Indeed, Minneapolis and St. Paul have an abundance of foundations that were started by the founders or top executives of many of its biggest companies, like 3M and Target. General Mills, meanwhile, was an early member of an organization begun in the mid-1970s called the Five Percent Club  in which Minneapolis-St. Paul corporations agreed to set aside 5 percent of their pretax income for philanthropy. Believe it or not  and it is a little hard to believe, given the modern emphasis on maximizing profits and pleasing Wall Street  the club still exists. Now known as the Keystone Club, it has 214 members, and 134 of them donate at the 5 percent level. (The others give away 2 percent of their profits.) Last year, General Mills donated more than $57 million, second only to Target, which gave away nearly $160 million. “Here’s the new Guthrie,” said Mr. King as we began the tour. The Guthrie Theater, the city’s fine regional theater, recently moved into a sparkling new building by the river  one of five major arts organizations that have recently built new buildings or major additions. All of them were built, in no small part, with corporate contributions. We drove a little farther. “This is where the bridge collapsed,” he said, pointing directly in front of us. He was speaking, of course, of the Interstate 35W bridge, which collapsed in August. “When it fell, there was an immediate response from corporations,” Mr. King continued. “And a fund for victims was set up by the Minneapolis and St. Paul Foundations.” The latter groups solicit donations from local people who want to be involved in philanthropy but lack the means to set up their own foundations. Combined, the two foundations have over $1.5 billion in assets and are major forces in the Twin Cities. We headed north. “North Minneapolis has long been a low-income neighborhood,” Mr. King said. “We have had wonderful success over all as a community, but we still have lots of problems. But we keep working at it.” We drove past a storefront that said, in bright lettering, “The Cookie Cart.” “This is a cookie business that is run by kids in the community,” Mr. King said. “It helps them learn skills that can really be useful. It has been around for 10 or 15 years.” Among the companies backing it are Wells Fargo, U.S. Bancorp and The Star Tribune. As we neared a school, Mr. King told me about a Medtronics-funded program that began years ago as a $75,000 pilot program to help children get interested in science. The company now spends more than a $1 million a year on it. And on, and on. We drove under a walking bridge, the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, built with donations from the Whitney family and others. In a neighborhood called Hawthorne, Mr. King explained that in 1996, after The New York Times noted that some people were calling Minneapolis “Murderapolis,” General Mills began investing in the neighborhood, with redevelopment and other efforts, including something called the Hawthorne Huddle, a monthly meeting that brought together residents and city officials to hash out solutions to problems. Ask anybody in the world of corporate philanthropy and they’ll tell you: Minneapolis-St. Paul is like no place else, a bastion of giving in an age when most companies are cutting back. “It is an unusual city in regards to corporate giving,” said former Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich. In the 1970s, John D. Rockefeller III said in a speech to the Minneapolis Chamber of Commerce that he had heard so much about “the public spirit of its business community, about your remarkable Five Percent Club that I feel a bit like Dorothy in the Land of Oz. I had to come to the Emerald City myself to see if it really exists.” So did I. And sure enough, it does exist. But why here? If you put this question to people in Minneapolis, you hear all kinds of theories. “When you live in such a harsh climate, you understand the need for the common good,” said Emmett D. Carson, the former president of the Minneapolis Foundation. Others suggested that the area’s corporate generosity grew out of the Scandinavian culture that took hold in this region, with its deep Lutheran roots. Christina L. Shea, the senior vice president for external relations at General Mills, thought it had to do with enlightened self-interest. “How do you attract high-powered talent?” she asked. A large part of the answer, she believed, had to do with building communities in which talented people wanted to live. Steve Rothschild, a former General Mills executive who left the company to found an antipoverty group called Twin Cities Rise, said he thought that Minneapolis-St. Paul companies have long viewed their responsibilities broadly. “Most Twin Cities companies have a stakeholder model, not a shareholder model,” he said. There is probably some truth to all of these theories. 1 2 Next Page » Correction: December 28, 2007 The Talking Business column in Business Day on Saturday, about corporate philanthropy in Minneapolis-St. Paul, misstated the names of two organizations involved in charitable work in the area. They are the Minnesota Council on Foundations, not the Minneapolis Council on Foundations, and Twin Cities Rise, not Twin Cities Rising. The column also referred incorrectly to financing of a pedestrian bridge over an interstate highway. The bridge  the Irene Hixon Whitney Bridge, which crosses I-94 to connect the Walker Art Center to the city’s park system  was built with donations from the Whitney family and others. Dayton-Hudson, a predecessor to the Target Corporation, did not build the bridge.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/17/business/17bank.html?ref=usbancorp">Earnings Are Disappointing at 3 Big Banks<date>Published: October 17, 2007</date><text>Three large banking companies  Wells Fargo, Regions Financial and KeyCorp  reported lower-than-estimated third-quarter profits yesterday and said rising loan losses might hurt future earnings. Wells Fargo, based in San Francisco, said an increase in bad home equity and consumer loans held earnings growth to 4 percent. Net income at Regions, of Birmingham, Ala., rose 12 percent, and profit at KeyCorp, in Cleveland, dropped 33 percent. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, beat estimates with a 2.2 percent drop. The worsening housing slump caused borrowers to miss payments, with Wells Fargo and KeyCorp reporting higher loan losses. Regions said it expected charge-offs for bad loans to rise gradually in coming quarters. Wells Fargos chief financial officer, Howard I. Atkins, said weakness linked to housing market problems would continue to affect results this quarter. Mortgage cycles last years, not quarters, said Fred Cannon, an analyst at KBW. The issues in the mortgage markets are going to cause pressure for some time. Fallout from reduced home loan values and tighter lending standards in the quarter just concluded would take 90 days or more to show up in earnings reports, he said. Wells Fargo earned a penny a share less than analyst estimates compiled by Bloomberg. Regions earned 64 cents a share, excluding acquisition-related costs, or 5 cents under estimates. KeyCorps income from continuing operations of 57 cents was well short of a 73 cent average estimate. Profit of 67 cents a share at U.S. Bancorp was a penny better than predicted. Net income advanced at Wells Fargo to $2.28 billion, or 68 cents a share, from $2.19 billion, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Wells Fargo has turned in the best stock performance this year among the nations five biggest banking companies, having succeeded so far in containing losses tied to troubled mortgages. Yesterdays report may signal that the bank cannot meet its target of 10 percent annual earnings growth, Mr. Cannon at KBW said. More Articles in Business »Three large banking companies  Wells Fargo, Regions Financial and KeyCorp  reported lower-than-estimated third-quarter profits yesterday and said rising loan losses might hurt future earnings. Wells Fargo, based in San Francisco, said an increase in bad home equity and consumer loans held earnings growth to 4 percent. Net income at Regions, of Birmingham, Ala., rose 12 percent, and profit at KeyCorp, in Cleveland, dropped 33 percent. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, beat estimates with a 2.2 percent drop. The worsening housing slump caused borrowers to miss payments, with Wells Fargo and KeyCorp reporting higher loan losses. Regions said it expected charge-offs for bad loans to rise gradually in coming quarters. Wells Fargos chief financial officer, Howard I. Atkins, said weakness linked to housing market problems would continue to affect results this quarter. Mortgage cycles last years, not quarters, said Fred Cannon, an analyst at KBW. The issues in the mortgage markets are going to cause pressure for some time. Fallout from reduced home loan values and tighter lending standards in the quarter just concluded would take 90 days or more to show up in earnings reports, he said. Wells Fargo earned a penny a share less than analyst estimates compiled by Bloomberg. Regions earned 64 cents a share, excluding acquisition-related costs, or 5 cents under estimates. KeyCorps income from continuing operations of 57 cents was well short of a 73 cent average estimate. Profit of 67 cents a share at U.S. Bancorp was a penny better than predicted. Net income advanced at Wells Fargo to $2.28 billion, or 68 cents a share, from $2.19 billion, or 64 cents, a year earlier. Wells Fargo has turned in the best stock performance this year among the nations five biggest banking companies, having succeeded so far in containing losses tied to troubled mortgages. Yesterdays report may signal that the bank cannot meet its target of 10 percent annual earnings growth, Mr. Cannon at KBW said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DD1E3FF93BA25757C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=usbancorp">Bad Loans Inhibit Profit at Three Regional Banks<date>Published: April 18, 2007</date><text>Problems with consumer credit, particularly in subprime mortgages, weighed on earnings at regional banks that reported their first-quarter results yesterday. Regional banks including Wells Fargo &amp; Company, U.S. Bancorp and Washington Mutual followed the trend set on Monday by two larger banks, Citigroup and Wachovia, which said they had set aside more reserves to cover losses from bad loans. Wells Fargo said its consumer loan problems were offset by an increase in core deposits and in total loans and reported an 11 percent increase in profit for the period. Washington Mutual and U.S. Bancorp each reported a decline in earnings. Wells Fargo, which is based in San Francisco, said it earned $2.24 billion, or 66 cents a share, up from $2.02 billion, or 60 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue was $9.44 billion, up more than 10 percent from $8.56 billion a year earlier. Wells Fargo said that deterioration in subprime mortgages forced it to cut revenue by $90 million as it wrote down those loans and set aside money for defaults. Wells Fargo's average loans grew 3 percent, to $321.4 billion, and average core deposits increased 13 percent, to $290.6 billion. U.S. Bancorp, which is based in Minneapolis, said its first-quarter profit declined as the spread between what it pays in interest and what it charges for loans narrowed. The company said it earned $1.13 billion, or 63 cents a share, down from $1.15 billion, or 63 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue of $3.36 billion was up from $3.34 billion. U.S. Bancorp said the number of its bad loans declined from the fourth quarter, although net charge-offs increased by $22 million. It increased its provision for credit losses to $177 million, or $62 million higher than during the period last year. Washington Mutual, which is based in Seattle, said income was $784 million, or 86 cents a share, down from $985 million, or 98 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue was $3.62 billion, up from $3.59 billion. Kerry Killinger, Washington Mutual's chief executive, said retail banking, card services and commercial groups fared well, while the home loan market, particularly the subprime segment, remained a serious challenge. ''Over the past 12 months, we have taken a number of prudent actions to reduce our exposure to the subprime mortgage industry,'' Mr. Killinger said in a statement. ''These actions, along with a diversified business mix, limited our exposure to the mortgage market's downturn and position us well to expand and grow as market conditions improve.''</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/17/business/17wells.html?ref=usbancorp">Profits Rise at Wells Fargo and U.S. Bancorp<date>Published: January 17, 2007</date><text>Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp reported higher fourth-quarter profits yesterday, helped by growth in business lending and fee-generating units. Profit rose 13 percent at Wells Fargo to $2.18 billion, or 64 cents a share, from $1.93 billion, or 57 cents a share, a year earlier. U.S. Bancorp said profit rose 4 percent to $1.19 billion, or 66 cents a share, from $1.14 billion, or 62 cents a share. Both banks, which operate mainly in the western two-thirds of the United States, have increased their reliance on lending to small and midsize businesses after slowed growth in consumer borrowing in the wake of 17 Federal Reserve rate increases. “Growth is supported by the western markets they serve, where commercial growth has been strong,” said Gerard Cassidy, an analyst at RBC Capital Markets. “However, there is a clear trend of credit quality deterioration compared with the third quarter.” Wells Fargo, which is based in San Francisco, said revenue rose 11 percent, to $9.41 billion, compared with forecasts for $9 billion. Compared with the third quarter, average loans and core low-cost deposits rose an annualized 11 percent, and net interest margin rose to 4.93 percent, from 4.79 percent. Profit rose 9 percent in retail banking, 14 percent in business banking and 64 percent at Wells Fargo Financial, which lends to less creditworthy customers. The bank set aside $726 million for credit losses, up 9 percent from the third quarter. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, said net revenue rose 3 percent, to $3.42 billion, while expenses rose 10 percent. Acquisitions helped feed a 12 percent increase in fee income, including gains of 26 percent in merchant processing services and 24 percent in trust and investment management. This more than offset a 5 percent drop in lending income and a 77 percent decline in mortgage banking revenue. Credit losses rose 25 percent from the third quarter, to $169 million. New Chief at Fifth Third CINCINNATI, Jan. 16 (AP)  Fifth Third Bancorp said Tuesday that George A. Schaefer Jr. would give up his title as chief executive as the company struggles to increase profit after a series of acquisitions. Mr. Schaefer, 61, will continue as chairman of the board and the board’s executive committee in a nonexecutive capacity, the board said in a statement The president of Fifth Third, Kevin T. Kabat, 49, will become the chief executive at the shareholders meeting on April 17, the statement said. Mr. Schaefer has been chief executive since January 1991. More Articles in Business »Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp reported higher fourth-quarter profits yesterday, helped by growth in business lending and fee-generating units. Profit rose 13 percent at Wells Fargo to $2.18 billion, or 64 cents a share, from $1.93 billion, or 57 cents a share, a year earlier. U.S. Bancorp said profit rose 4 percent to $1.19 billion, or 66 cents a share, from $1.14 billion, or 62 cents a share. Both banks, which operate mainly in the western two-thirds of the United States, have increased their reliance on lending to small and midsize businesses after slowed growth in consumer borrowing in the wake of 17 Federal Reserve rate increases. “Growth is supported by the western markets they serve, where commercial growth has been strong,” said Gerard Cassidy, an analyst at RBC Capital Markets. “However, there is a clear trend of credit quality deterioration compared with the third quarter.” Wells Fargo, which is based in San Francisco, said revenue rose 11 percent, to $9.41 billion, compared with forecasts for $9 billion. Compared with the third quarter, average loans and core low-cost deposits rose an annualized 11 percent, and net interest margin rose to 4.93 percent, from 4.79 percent. Profit rose 9 percent in retail banking, 14 percent in business banking and 64 percent at Wells Fargo Financial, which lends to less creditworthy customers. The bank set aside $726 million for credit losses, up 9 percent from the third quarter. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, said net revenue rose 3 percent, to $3.42 billion, while expenses rose 10 percent. Acquisitions helped feed a 12 percent increase in fee income, including gains of 26 percent in merchant processing services and 24 percent in trust and investment management. This more than offset a 5 percent drop in lending income and a 77 percent decline in mortgage banking revenue. Credit losses rose 25 percent from the third quarter, to $169 million. New Chief at Fifth Third CINCINNATI, Jan. 16 (AP)  Fifth Third Bancorp said Tuesday that George A. Schaefer Jr. would give up his title as chief executive as the company struggles to increase profit after a series of acquisitions. Mr. Schaefer, 61, will continue as chairman of the board and the board’s executive committee in a nonexecutive capacity, the board said in a statement The president of Fifth Third, Kevin T. Kabat, 49, will become the chief executive at the shareholders meeting on April 17, the statement said. Mr. Schaefer has been chief executive since January 1991.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/19/business/19bank.html?ref=usbancorp">2 Banks Post Record First-Quarter Profits<date>Published: April 19, 2006</date><text>Two banks, Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp, posted record first-quarter profits yesterday, shrugging off a recent home mortgage slowdown caused by rising interest rates. Profit at Wells Fargo, which is based in San Francisco, rose 9 percent to $2.02 billion  the first time in the company's 154-year old history it passed the $2 billion mark. U.S. Bancorp posted a 7.7 percent increase in profit to $1.15 billion. For both banks, diversification was crucial to the higher returns. Both leaned on acquisitions and an expansion of their retail branch network to increase lending revenue despite the cooling of the mortgage market. "We had solid, broad-based and, in many businesses, accelerating revenue growth, with revenue in businesses other than home mortgage up a combined 17 percent from a year ago," the chief financial officer of Wells Fargo, Howard Atkins, said in a statement. Wells Fargo reported that earnings rose to $1.19 a share from $1.08 in the year-ago period. Revenue totaled $8.56 billion, a 6 percent increase from $8.09 billion a year ago. The company's home mortgage division posted revenue of $853 million, a 44 percent drop from $1.52 billion last year. Accounting adjustments to Wells Fargo's home mortgage servicing portfolio contributed to the erosion. Profit at U.S. Bancorp climbed to 63 cents a share, from 57 cents, or a total of $1.07 billion, a year earlier. More Articles in Business »Two banks, Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp, posted record first-quarter profits yesterday, shrugging off a recent home mortgage slowdown caused by rising interest rates. Profit at Wells Fargo, which is based in San Francisco, rose 9 percent to $2.02 billion  the first time in the company's 154-year old history it passed the $2 billion mark. U.S. Bancorp posted a 7.7 percent increase in profit to $1.15 billion. For both banks, diversification was crucial to the higher returns. Both leaned on acquisitions and an expansion of their retail branch network to increase lending revenue despite the cooling of the mortgage market. "We had solid, broad-based and, in many businesses, accelerating revenue growth, with revenue in businesses other than home mortgage up a combined 17 percent from a year ago," the chief financial officer of Wells Fargo, Howard Atkins, said in a statement. Wells Fargo reported that earnings rose to $1.19 a share from $1.08 in the year-ago period. Revenue totaled $8.56 billion, a 6 percent increase from $8.09 billion a year ago. The company's home mortgage division posted revenue of $853 million, a 44 percent drop from $1.52 billion last year. Accounting adjustments to Wells Fargo's home mortgage servicing portfolio contributed to the erosion. Profit at U.S. Bancorp climbed to 63 cents a share, from 57 cents, or a total of $1.07 billion, a year earlier.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/10/national/10tower.html?ref=usbancorp">A Distinctive Shape, and an Inviting Target<date>Published: February 10, 2006</date><text>Skip to next paragraph Bush Gives New Details of 2002 Qaeda Plot to Attack Los Angeles Correction Appended LOS ANGELES, Feb. 9  The U.S. Bank Tower here, the city's tallest building, has long been presumed to be an inviting target for terrorists. Rising 1,018 feet from Bunker Hill in downtown Los Angeles, the gleaming I. M. Pei-designed building is the most distinctive shape in the skyline and the tallest office building west of Chicago. President Bush said on Thursday that the 72-story building, known as the Library Tower until U.S. Bancorp acquired naming rights in 2003, was to have been the target of a follow-up attack by Al Qaeda after the terrorist strikes of Sept. 11, 2001. Officials have discussed the alleged plot numerous times in recent years as an example of terrorist actions that might have been foiled by government vigilance, but Mr. Bush offered new details. Mayor Antonio R. Villaraigosa complained at a news conference on Thursday that he had not been called directly by the White House, learning of the new information on the alleged plot only from state officials and staff members. The White House press secretary, Scott McClellan, said federal officials had passed along the new information to the authorities in Los Angeles and Sacramento, telling them that Mr. Bush would discuss it on Thursday. Mayor Villaraigosa, a Democrat, said that he had twice written to the White House to request a meeting with the president to discuss security threats to Los Angeles, but that he had received no response. "I'm mayor of the second largest city in the country," Mr. Villaraigosa said. "I have tried to meet with the president at the White House on a number of occasions every time that I've gone to Washington, D.C., to discuss specifically this issue of homeland security, and to no avail. Let's be clear about that." He also said that the president's antiterrorism budget had shortchanged a number of potential targets, including Los Angeles. "Given the known terrorist plots against our city, I firmly believe that Los Angeles deserves a greater share of that funding," the mayor said. Mr. Bush mistakenly referred to the building in his remarks Thursday as Liberty Tower; the White House later corrected the error. Chief William J. Bratton of the Los Angeles Police Department said in an interview that he had been aware of threats to the skyscraper since he took over as chief in 2002. He said he had devoted significant counterterrorism resources to the building and to Los Angeles International Airport, another potential target, because Al Qaeda is known to carefully research its targets and to try to strike more than once, as it did at the World Trade Center. He said he was working with federal and local law enforcement officials on a program, Operation Archangel, to identify critical sites around the country that might be targets for terrorist attack and to design methods to defend them. Mr. Bratton was in Washington on Thursday with other big-city police chiefs for a brief White House meeting with Mr. Bush that he characterized as "mostly a photo op." The bank tower opened in 1989 and has nearly 1.4 million square feet of rentable space. It was designed to withstand an 8.3 magnitude earthquake, but not an alien invasion. It was the first building destroyed by space invaders in the 1996 film "Independence Day." Correction: Feb. 13, 2006 An article on Friday about the U.S. Bank Tower in Los Angeles, which President Bush described as the target of a thwarted attack by Al Qaeda, misidentified the building's designer. He is Henry N. Cobb, not I. M. Pei. (Both men are partners in Pei Cobb Freed.) More Articles in National &gt;Skip to next paragraph Bush Gives New Details of 2002 Qaeda Plot to Attack Los Angeles Correction Appended LOS ANGELES, Feb. 9  The U.S. Bank Tower here, the city's tallest building, has long been presumed to be an inviting target for terrorists. Rising 1,018 feet from Bunker Hill in downtown Los Angeles, the gleaming I. M. Pei-designed building is the most distinctive shape in the skyline and the tallest office building west of Chicago. President Bush said on Thursday that the 72-story building, known as the Library Tower until U.S. Bancorp acquired naming rights in 2003, was to have been the target of a follow-up attack by Al Qaeda after the terrorist strikes of Sept. 11, 2001. Officials have discussed the alleged plot numerous times in recent years as an example of terrorist actions that might have been foiled by government vigilance, but Mr. Bush offered new details. Mayor Antonio R. Villaraigosa complained at a news conference on Thursday that he had not been called directly by the White House, learning of the new information on the alleged plot only from state officials and staff members. The White House press secretary, Scott McClellan, said federal officials had passed along the new information to the authorities in Los Angeles and Sacramento, telling them that Mr. Bush would discuss it on Thursday. Mayor Villaraigosa, a Democrat, said that he had twice written to the White House to request a meeting with the president to discuss security threats to Los Angeles, but that he had received no response. "I'm mayor of the second largest city in the country," Mr. Villaraigosa said. "I have tried to meet with the president at the White House on a number of occasions every time that I've gone to Washington, D.C., to discuss specifically this issue of homeland security, and to no avail. Let's be clear about that." He also said that the president's antiterrorism budget had shortchanged a number of potential targets, including Los Angeles. "Given the known terrorist plots against our city, I firmly believe that Los Angeles deserves a greater share of that funding," the mayor said. Mr. Bush mistakenly referred to the building in his remarks Thursday as Liberty Tower; the White House later corrected the error. Chief William J. Bratton of the Los Angeles Police Department said in an interview that he had been aware of threats to the skyscraper since he took over as chief in 2002. He said he had devoted significant counterterrorism resources to the building and to Los Angeles International Airport, another potential target, because Al Qaeda is known to carefully research its targets and to try to strike more than once, as it did at the World Trade Center. He said he was working with federal and local law enforcement officials on a program, Operation Archangel, to identify critical sites around the country that might be targets for terrorist attack and to design methods to defend them. Mr. Bratton was in Washington on Thursday with other big-city police chiefs for a brief White House meeting with Mr. Bush that he characterized as "mostly a photo op." The bank tower opened in 1989 and has nearly 1.4 million square feet of rentable space. It was designed to withstand an 8.3 magnitude earthquake, but not an alien invasion. It was the first building destroyed by space invaders in the 1996 film "Independence Day." Correction: Feb. 13, 2006 An article on Friday about the U.S. Bank Tower in Los Angeles, which President Bush described as the target of a thwarted attack by Al Qaeda, misidentified the building's designer. He is Henry N. Cobb, not I. M. Pei. (Both men are partners in Pei Cobb Freed.)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/10/politics/10bush.html?ref=usbancorp">Bush Gives New Details of 2002 Qaeda Plot to Attack Los Angeles<date>Published: February 10, 2006</date><text>WASHINGTON, Feb. 9  President Bush offered new information on Thursday about what he said was a foiled plot by Al Qaeda in 2002 to fly a hijacked airplane into the tallest building west of the Mississippi, the U.S. Bank Tower in Los Angeles, as he sought to make the case for his record on national security. Skip to next paragraph A Distinctive Shape, and an Inviting Target (February 10, 2006) Kim D. Johnson/Associated Press The terrorists' intended target in the 2002 plot was the U.S. Bank Tower in downtown Los Angeles. Although the administration made public the Los Angeles plot in general terms four months ago, Mr. Bush, in a speech to the National Guard Association, disclosed more specific details, including what he said was the planned use of a "shoe bomb" by hijackers to breach the airplane's cockpit door and take over the controls. In addition, Mr. Bush and one of his counterterrorism advisers said that four extremists were recruited from Southeast Asia to carry out the plan, that their leader received training in shoe bombs and that all four had traveled to an undisclosed place after the Sept. 11 attacks to meet with Osama bin Laden and pledge their loyalty to Al Qaeda. Mr. Bush and White House officials gave no reason for releasing details of a plot that they first disclosed last October. But Mr. Bush's speech came at a time when Republicans are intent on establishing their record on national security as the pre-eminent issue in the 2006 midterm elections, and when the president is facing questions from members of both parties about a secret eavesdropping program that he describes as pivotal to the war on terrorism. In his speech, Mr. Bush said the plot had been "derailed in early 2002, when a Southeast Asian nation arrested a key Al Qaeda operative." He added that "subsequent debriefings and other intelligence operations made clear the intended target and how Al Qaeda hoped to execute it." Mr. Bush and his counterterrorism adviser, Frances Fragos Townsend, made no claim on Thursday that the eavesdropping program, conducted by the National Security Agency, had helped to foil the 2002 plot. But in a conference call with reporters, Ms. Townsend did not rule out the program as a factor in discovering the plan. "We use all available sources and methods in the intelligence community, but we have to protect them," Ms. Townsend said. "So I'm not going to talk about what ones we did or didn't use in this particular case." She added that the Los Angeles plot had grown out of the Sept. 11 attacks. As described in the staff report by the independent commission that investigated the Sept. 11 attacks, Khalid Shaikh Mohammed, who is said to be the mastermind behind them, had originally envisioned an elaborate plan with 10 planes that would attack the East and West Coasts simultaneously on Sept. 11, 2001. But Mr. bin Laden rejected the plan, the report said, because of its difficulty. "It was bin Laden who decided that it should just focus on the East Coast, and the West Coast should be held in abeyance until there was a follow-on attack," Ms. Townsend told reporters. "It's our understanding now that it was too difficult to get enough operatives for both the East and West Coast plots at the same time." Weeks after the Sept. 11 attacks, Ms. Townsend said, Mr. Mohammed turned his attention to the West Coast and to recruits from Southeast Asia affiliated with Jemaah Islamiyah, a Qaeda offshoot with roots in Indonesia. Working with another terror figure, Riduan Isamuddin, better known as Hambali, Mr. Mohammed recruited a cell leader and three other men in October 2001, Ms. Townsend said. Mr. Mohammed trained the leader of the group in building a shoe bomb, similar to the device recovered from Richard Reid, who had tried to set off a bomb in his shoe on an American Airlines flight from Paris to Miami in December 2001. Significantly, each of the four men, whom Ms. Townsend would not identify, were found to have traveled to Afghanistan to meet with Mr. bin Laden in the months after the Sept. 11 attacks. Each pledged loyalty to him, she said. Such pledges were a significant gesture in the bin Laden network and usually a prerequisite to carrying out an attack. Ms. Townsend said that American counterterrorism officials, working with four other regional governments, which she would not identify, arrested the cell leader and three others in February 2002. The plot was effectively extinguished. Several American counterterrorism officials said Thursday that, at the time the plot was broken up in early 2002, the authorities believed that they had disrupted an active terrorist planning effort, but that they possessed only fragmentary evidence and were unsure whether the threat was significant. Only later did they conclude that the plot was genuine and potentially serious. The outline of the plot became clear, the officials said, primarily through the interrogations of captured Qaeda figures like Mr. Mohammed, who was apprehended in March 2003, and Hambali, captured in August 2003. In Los Angeles, the office of Mayor Antonio R. Villaraigosa said that the White House on Wednesday had given them a heads up about the president's disclosure but said that the mayor was not personally informed. "I would have expected a direct call from the White House," the mayor said at an afternoon news conference. In his remarks, Mr. Bush referred to the West Coast target as "the Liberty Tower," but White House officials said he had meant to say Library Tower, the name of the U.S. Bank Tower in 2002. The building, completed in 1989, is 1,018 feet tall and was "destroyed" by alien invaders in the 1996 movie "Independence Day." More Articles in Washington &gt;WASHINGTON, Feb. 9  President Bush offered new information on Thursday about what he said was a foiled plot by Al Qaeda in 2002 to fly a hijacked airplane into the tallest building west of the Mississippi, the U.S. Bank Tower in Los Angeles, as he sought to make the case for his record on national security. Skip to next paragraph A Distinctive Shape, and an Inviting Target (February 10, 2006) Kim D. Johnson/Associated Press The terrorists' intended target in the 2002 plot was the U.S. Bank Tower in downtown Los Angeles. Although the administration made public the Los Angeles plot in general terms four months ago, Mr. Bush, in a speech to the National Guard Association, disclosed more specific details, including what he said was the planned use of a "shoe bomb" by hijackers to breach the airplane's cockpit door and take over the controls. In addition, Mr. Bush and one of his counterterrorism advisers said that four extremists were recruited from Southeast Asia to carry out the plan, that their leader received training in shoe bombs and that all four had traveled to an undisclosed place after the Sept. 11 attacks to meet with Osama bin Laden and pledge their loyalty to Al Qaeda. Mr. Bush and White House officials gave no reason for releasing details of a plot that they first disclosed last October. But Mr. Bush's speech came at a time when Republicans are intent on establishing their record on national security as the pre-eminent issue in the 2006 midterm elections, and when the president is facing questions from members of both parties about a secret eavesdropping program that he describes as pivotal to the war on terrorism. In his speech, Mr. Bush said the plot had been "derailed in early 2002, when a Southeast Asian nation arrested a key Al Qaeda operative." He added that "subsequent debriefings and other intelligence operations made clear the intended target and how Al Qaeda hoped to execute it." Mr. Bush and his counterterrorism adviser, Frances Fragos Townsend, made no claim on Thursday that the eavesdropping program, conducted by the National Security Agency, had helped to foil the 2002 plot. But in a conference call with reporters, Ms. Townsend did not rule out the program as a factor in discovering the plan. "We use all available sources and methods in the intelligence community, but we have to protect them," Ms. Townsend said. "So I'm not going to talk about what ones we did or didn't use in this particular case." She added that the Los Angeles plot had grown out of the Sept. 11 attacks. As described in the staff report by the independent commission that investigated the Sept. 11 attacks, Khalid Shaikh Mohammed, who is said to be the mastermind behind them, had originally envisioned an elaborate plan with 10 planes that would attack the East and West Coasts simultaneously on Sept. 11, 2001. But Mr. bin Laden rejected the plan, the report said, because of its difficulty. "It was bin Laden who decided that it should just focus on the East Coast, and the West Coast should be held in abeyance until there was a follow-on attack," Ms. Townsend told reporters. "It's our understanding now that it was too difficult to get enough operatives for both the East and West Coast plots at the same time." Weeks after the Sept. 11 attacks, Ms. Townsend said, Mr. Mohammed turned his attention to the West Coast and to recruits from Southeast Asia affiliated with Jemaah Islamiyah, a Qaeda offshoot with roots in Indonesia. Working with another terror figure, Riduan Isamuddin, better known as Hambali, Mr. Mohammed recruited a cell leader and three other men in October 2001, Ms. Townsend said. Mr. Mohammed trained the leader of the group in building a shoe bomb, similar to the device recovered from Richard Reid, who had tried to set off a bomb in his shoe on an American Airlines flight from Paris to Miami in December 2001. Significantly, each of the four men, whom Ms. Townsend would not identify, were found to have traveled to Afghanistan to meet with Mr. bin Laden in the months after the Sept. 11 attacks. Each pledged loyalty to him, she said. Such pledges were a significant gesture in the bin Laden network and usually a prerequisite to carrying out an attack. Ms. Townsend said that American counterterrorism officials, working with four other regional governments, which she would not identify, arrested the cell leader and three others in February 2002. The plot was effectively extinguished. Several American counterterrorism officials said Thursday that, at the time the plot was broken up in early 2002, the authorities believed that they had disrupted an active terrorist planning effort, but that they possessed only fragmentary evidence and were unsure whether the threat was significant. Only later did they conclude that the plot was genuine and potentially serious. The outline of the plot became clear, the officials said, primarily through the interrogations of captured Qaeda figures like Mr. Mohammed, who was apprehended in March 2003, and Hambali, captured in August 2003. In Los Angeles, the office of Mayor Antonio R. Villaraigosa said that the White House on Wednesday had given them a heads up about the president's disclosure but said that the mayor was not personally informed. "I would have expected a direct call from the White House," the mayor said at an afternoon news conference. In his remarks, Mr. Bush referred to the West Coast target as "the Liberty Tower," but White House officials said he had meant to say Library Tower, the name of the U.S. Bank Tower in 2002. The building, completed in 1989, is 1,018 feet tall and was "destroyed" by alien invaders in the 1996 movie "Independence Day."</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/18/business/18bank.html?ref=usbancorp">Bankruptcies Cut Into Profit at Two Lenders<date>Published: January 18, 2006</date><text>Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp, two of the nation's largest banks, said quarterly earnings rose at the slowest rate in four years as an increase in bankruptcy filings led to higher credit losses. The lenders each reported an 8 percent increase in net income. Almost 487,500 Americans filed for bankruptcy in the week before an Oct. 17 change in United States law made it harder to wipe out personal debts. While the surge in filings swelled bad loans, pushing up costs for banks, some also reported an increase in commercial and consumer borrowing, indicating that profit growth may accelerate in future quarters. "The bankruptcy issue is a one-time situation," said Mark Batty, an analyst at PNC Advisors, which owns shares of Wells Fargo and U.S. Bancorp. "Commercial and industrial loan growth was fairly strong and should be the key driver of earnings growth this year for the regional banks." Wells Fargo's net income rose to $1.93 billion, or $1.14 a share, from $1.79 billion, or $1.04 a share, a year earlier. Earnings fell short of some analysts' estimates. Shares of Wells Fargo fell 65 cents, to $62.60. Wells Fargo is the nation's largest home equity lender. U.S. Bancorp said its net income climbed to $1.14 billion, or 62 cents a share, from $1.06 billion, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. Credit losses related to the bankruptcy statute amounted to about $56 million, the bank said. Shares of U.S. Bancorp fell 56 cents, to $30.03. A narrowing of the gap between short-term and long-term interest rates, a so-called flattening yield curve, also eroded banks' profit growth. Wells Fargo's net interest margin, the difference between the money it earns by lending and its cost of funds, shrank 4 basis points, or 0.04 percentage point, to 4.84 percent. U.S. Bancorp said its net interest margin narrowed to 3.9 percent, from 4.2 percent. More Articles in Business &gt;Wells Fargo &amp; Company and U.S. Bancorp, two of the nation's largest banks, said quarterly earnings rose at the slowest rate in four years as an increase in bankruptcy filings led to higher credit losses. The lenders each reported an 8 percent increase in net income. Almost 487,500 Americans filed for bankruptcy in the week before an Oct. 17 change in United States law made it harder to wipe out personal debts. While the surge in filings swelled bad loans, pushing up costs for banks, some also reported an increase in commercial and consumer borrowing, indicating that profit growth may accelerate in future quarters. "The bankruptcy issue is a one-time situation," said Mark Batty, an analyst at PNC Advisors, which owns shares of Wells Fargo and U.S. Bancorp. "Commercial and industrial loan growth was fairly strong and should be the key driver of earnings growth this year for the regional banks." Wells Fargo's net income rose to $1.93 billion, or $1.14 a share, from $1.79 billion, or $1.04 a share, a year earlier. Earnings fell short of some analysts' estimates. Shares of Wells Fargo fell 65 cents, to $62.60. Wells Fargo is the nation's largest home equity lender. U.S. Bancorp said its net income climbed to $1.14 billion, or 62 cents a share, from $1.06 billion, or 56 cents a share, a year earlier. Credit losses related to the bankruptcy statute amounted to about $56 million, the bank said. Shares of U.S. Bancorp fell 56 cents, to $30.03. A narrowing of the gap between short-term and long-term interest rates, a so-called flattening yield curve, also eroded banks' profit growth. Wells Fargo's net interest margin, the difference between the money it earns by lending and its cost of funds, shrank 4 basis points, or 0.04 percentage point, to 4.84 percent. U.S. Bancorp said its net interest margin narrowed to 3.9 percent, from 4.2 percent.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/21/business/fees-help-lift-banks-profits-in-first-quarter.html?ref=usbancorp">Fees Help Lift Banks' Profits In First Quarter<date>Published: April 21, 2004</date><text>Wells Fargo &amp; Company, the Bank One Corporation and U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that first-quarter profits rose as fees from credit cards, bank accounts and consumer loans bolstered revenue.Wells Fargo, the nation's fifth-biggest bank, based in San Francisco, said net income increased 18 percent to $1.77 billion. Chicago-based Bank One, the sixth-biggest United States bank, recorded a 51 percent increase in net income to $1.2 billion. Seventh-ranked U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, said first-quarter net income rose 14 percent to a record $1 billion.Nine of the nation's 10 largest banking companies -- including Citigroup, the world's biggest financial company by assets, and the Bank of America Corporation, the biggest United States consumer bank -- have reported higher profits in the quarter. Tax cuts and a rising stock market have encouraged consumer spending and borrowing, buoying bank revenue.Fears over interest rates kept the three companies' shares in check yesterday. Wells Fargo shares fell 55 cents, to close at $56.36. Bank One fell $1.27, or 2.5 percent, to $50.29, and U.S. Bancorp fell 16 cents, to $25.83.Wells Fargo's net income increased to a record $1.03 a share, from $1.49 billion, or 88 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial expected it to report earnings per share of 98 cents. Revenue rose 7 percent, to $7.1 billion, from a year earlier.Noninterest income rose 9 percent to $3.1 billion, driven by higher revenue from deposit service charges, investment fees and credit card charges. Net interest income, which the bank makes from lending, increased 5 percent to $4.05 billion.Bank One, which will be bought by J.P. Morgan Chase for $55 billion this summer, said net income rose to $1.09 a share, from $818 million, or 71 cents a share. Card services profit gained 29 percent, to $319 million. Excluding some investment and commercial-banking gains, the company would have had a profit of 87 cents a share. On that basis, Bank One was expected to earn 81 cents, the average estimate of 17 analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial.U.S. Bancorp profit rose to 52 cents a share, from $884.8 million, or 46 cents a share, a year earlier. That was higher than the 51-cent average forecast of analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/22/business/3-large-banks-report-rise-in-3rd-quarter-profits.html?ref=usbancorp">3 Large Banks Report Rise in 3rd-Quarter Profits<date>Published: October 22, 2003</date><text>Wells Fargo, Bank One and U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that third-quarter profit rose as consumer lending increased and bad loans fell.Net income rose 8 percent at Wells Fargo, 7 percent at Bank One and 14 percent at U.S. Bancorp.Wells Fargo shares rose 13 cents, to $55.50; Bank One shares climbed 42 cents, to $42.43; and U.S. Bancorp shares rose 70 cents, to $26.23.Wells Fargo, the No. 4 bank, with $390.8 billion of assets, said its net income rose to a record $1.56 billion, or 92 cents a share, from $1.44 billion, or 84 cents a share, a year earlier. Revenue rose 19 percent, to $7.17 billion. Analysts polled by Reuters Research expected profit of 93 cents.Wells Fargo handled $161 billion of new mortgages in the quarter, up 19 percent from the second quarter. Mortgage banking fees rose 81 percent from a year earlier, to $773 million.Bank One, the No. 6 bank, with $290 billion of assets, said its net income rose to $883 million, or 79 cents a share, from $823 million, or 70 cents a share, a year earlier. Net revenue fell 2 percent, to $4.1 billion. Analysts forecast a profit of 75 cents.The bank said net income from retail banking rose 9 percent, to $392 million, while commercial banking income doubled, to $361 million.U.S. Bancorp, the No. 8 bank, with $188.8 billion of assets, said net income rose to a record $984.9 million, or 51 cents a share, from $860.3 million, or 45 cents a share, a year ago, meeting expectations. Revenue fell 3 percent, to $3.21 billion, largely because of a loss from securities sales.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/03/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-add-to-supermarket-branches.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP TO ADD TO SUPERMARKET BRANCHES<date>Published: September 03, 2003</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it would open 163 branches in Safeway Inc. and Vons stores in the next two years to increase its presence in California and Arizona. The new outlets will increase U.S. Bancorp's in-store branch network by one-third, to 446, the bank said. Most of the branches will be in Sacramento, San Diego, San Francisco and Los Angeles. The remainder will be in Phoenix and Tucson. U.S. Bancorp has been building the its branch network by purchasing offices from competitors. Based in Minneapolis, U.S. Bancorp has branches at 30 retailers including Wal-Mart and Target stores.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/08/business/senators-question-effectiveness-of-1.4-billion-settlement.html?ref=usbancorp">Senators Question Effectiveness of $1.4 Billion Settlement<date>Published: May 08, 2003</date><text>Senior United States senators questioned today whether the $1.4 billion Wall Street settlement would change attitudes at the top of the biggest brokerage firms, while regulators defended the agreement as a historic move toward reform.''Firms are not contrite and simply consider the fines and penalties as a means to make a problem go away,'' said Richard C. Shelby, Republican of Alabama, at a Senate Banking Committee hearing on the settlement that was made final last week with 10 firms.''I am not convinced that the global settlement has done enough to change attitudes at the top of these banks,'' said Mr. Shelby, chairman of the committee.The Securities and Exchange Commission on April 28 released final terms of a settlement resulting from almost two years of investigations into analysts issuing overly positive research, mostly in the 1990's market bubble, to please corporate managers and win investment-banking business.Mr. Shelby compared huge investor losses with the relatively modest payout and asked William H. Donaldson, chairman of the S.E.C., whether the settlement punished Wall Street enough.Mr. Donaldson, a multimillionaire former investment banker and former chairman of the New York Stock Exchange, pledged further inquiries of brokerage executives. He said, ''You cannot dismiss the fact that these are the largest fines that have ever been given.''This is not the end,'' he said. ''This is just the beginning.''The settlement banned two analysts from the securities business for life: Henry Blodget, the former Internet analyst at Merrill Lynch, and Jack B. Grubman, once the top telecommunications analyst at Citigroup's Salomon Smith Barney.But no other individuals have been singled out despite thousands of memos and e-mail messages released by investigators showing managers deeply involved in an intertwining of research and investment banking that compromised analysts' work.Senator Paul S. Sarbanes of Maryland, the top Democrat on the banking panel, said Wall Street must ''get with the program.''Mr. Sarbanes, who helped write the 2002 Sarbanes-Oxley corporate and accounting reforms that came after the collapse of Enron, added, ''If the people on Wall Street can't be sensitized to what's happened, then obviously the regulators are going to have to sensitize them.''The New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, who spearheaded the first inquiries into analyst misconduct, told the committee that his investigation of individuals would intensify. He called brokerage executives ''fair game'' for regulators.Turning the tables on Congress as the hearing moved to the historic causes of the scandal, Mr. Spitzer attacked ''an overarching effort to deregulate the financial services industry over the last 20 years.''He said, ''I think we may now be paying the price for that deregulation,'' which came amid reassurances from investment and commercial banks that they could police themselves.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/04/business/market-watch-shopping-spree-by-the-famous-5.html?ref=usbancorp">MARKET WATCH; Shopping Spree By the Famous 5<date>Published: May 04, 2003</date><text>EVEN folks wise to the ways of Wall Street were stunned by the revelation in last Monday's regulatory action that five brokerage firms had paid others to issue research on stocks of companies the firms had underwritten. The practice, at Morgan Stanley, J. P. Morgan Securities, U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray, UBS Warburg and Bear, Stearns, seemed designed to ensure that the shares of the companies would be bid up by investors as the claque of ''analysts'' delivered the applause for which they had been paid.Keeping prices high on companies that had recently issued shares meant that future securities offerings would be easier to do and that the fees generated by such offerings would keep coming.A perhaps unintended result of the pay-for-research arrangements was that in two cases involving Morgan Stanley, the rosy research reports landed in the months leading up to or simultaneously with sales by Morgan of shares that regulatory filings said it owned in each company.Morgan Stanley said the filings show positions that ''were acquired and hedged by our equity division to facilitate customer transactions.'' But it did not supply documents relating to the trades or say what it made on them.Of the five firms identified as paying for research, Morgan Stanley paid the most. It handed out $2.7 million in so-called research guarantees to about two dozen competing firms. By comparison, J. P. Morgan paid $1.3 million, U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray and UBS each paid about $430,000 and Bear, Stearns paid one firm $103,000.Regulators identified 11 companies, mostly in the technology arena, for which Morgan Stanley paid competitors to issue research. The firm began payments in 1999 and apparently stopped in 2000, when the bull market music died.Consider Nvidia, a maker of graphics processors and software that replaced Enron in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index after it collapsed in late 2001. Morgan Stanley managed the initial public offering of Nvidia in January 1999, when the company raised about $42 million. On Oct. 5, 2000, Nvidia issued more shares, a deal again managed by Morgan Stanley. In that deal, it paid three lesser-known firms about $160,000 for research.Morgan Stanley's own analyst, Mark L. Edelstone, had recommended Nvidia to the firm's clients since February 1999, following its I.P.O. He first gave the shares an outperform rating and then raised it to a strong buy in April 2000. He kept that rating on Nvidia shares until March 2002.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/02/opinion/the-case-against-restitution.html?ref=usbancorp">The Case Against Restitution<date>Published: May 02, 2003</date><text>Of the record $1.4 billion settlement between Wall Street regulators and investment banks, less than a third will be returned to investors as restitution. Criticism of this plan began almost as soon as it was announced; it will be years before investors receive anything, and even then they will get only a fraction of what they lost.These complaints miss the mark. The problem with the restitution fund is not that it is too small ($387.5 million), that it covers only those who invested in certain stocks (about three dozen listed in various documents released by the Securities and Exchange Commission), or that it is ill-defined (it does not even have an administrator yet). The problem is the very idea of the restitution fund itself.As part of the settlement, state and federal regulators released a detailed report accusing 10 Wall Street firms of misleading investors and in some cases issuing fraudulent research. Although these firms neither admitted nor denied these charges, they agreed to change some of their business practices and to pay the historic fine -- the highest ever negotiated. Some of the $1.4 billion will go to the states, some will go to a fund for investor education, some will go to a fund to pay for independent stock research, and some will go to a restitution fund.Prior experience with similar restitution funds, like the one created for investors in the fraudulent limited partnerships that Prudential Securities sold in the 1980's, has shown them to be complex and costly. In the Prudential cases a cumbersome and costly adjudication system had to be created to determine the validity and size of each investor's claim.Those of us who had clients in the Prudential cases found that the process was not necessarily an improvement over the arbitration system then (and currently) in place for resolving investors' claims. Those who filed claims against the restitution fund still needed to pay a lawyer to get through the forms and the hearings, and many were unhappy with the results. Tens of thousands of people thus opted out of the restitution fund, which was created by the S.E.C. -- far more than the number who sought relief through it.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/02/opinion/the-acid-test.html?ref=usbancorp">The Acid Test<date>Published: May 02, 2003</date><text>There is, alas, only one Eliot Spitzer. And while you want to stand up and cheer when Mr. Spitzer, New York's attorney general, wins another round against malefactors of great wealth, his side -- our side, unless you happen to be a corporate insider -- is losing the war.On Monday, thanks mainly to Mr. Spitzer, a group of investment banks paid $1.4 billion to settle charges that their stock analysts had been shilling for corporate clients. This was, however, a mere slap on the wrist. And it's increasingly obvious that neither the investment bankers nor corporate evildoers in general are feeling chastened.Indeed, last week Stanley O'Neal, the chief executive of Merrill Lynch, wrote an op-ed article caricaturing the likes of Mr. Spitzer -- though without naming him -- as enemies of capitalism who teach investors that ''if they lose money in the market they're automatically entitled to be compensated.'' By the way, Henry Blodget -- the analyst whose internal e-mail famously used a scatological term to describe a stock he was publicly touting, and who was permanently banned from the industry under Monday's settlement -- worked for Merrill Lynch.Mr. Spitzer's scathing reply, addressed to ''Mr. C.E.O.,'' is a classic. (''Indeed, you did not want to tolerate risk. Because what you did was shift the risk to unknowing investors while you got the fees up front.'') But it's revealing that Mr. O'Neal felt empowered to write that piece in the first place. Like the New York Stock Exchange, which tried to appoint Citigroup's Sanford Weill to its board -- Mr. Weill is now forbidden to talk to his own company's analysts unless a lawyer is present -- Mr. O'Neal overreached. But he clearly knows which way the wind is blowing.And it's not just investment bankers: corporate insiders across America are feeling their oats. Consider the executives at American Airlines, who paid themselves big bonuses and secretly set up a special trust to secure their own pensions, even while demanding pay cuts from their workers to save the company. Well, why not? Trust funds protecting executive pensions even when ordinary workers' pension plans are underfunded, and hefty ''retention'' bonuses for executives of near-bankrupt companies, are all the rage these days.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/30/business/the-markets-market-place-grabbing-for-a-patch-of-moral-high-ground.html?ref=usbancorp">THE MARKETS: Market Place; Grabbing for a Patch of Moral High Ground<date>Published: April 30, 2003</date><text>Most Wall Street firms and their executives, embarrassed by details in the industrywide settlement on how they duped investors to keep their corporate clients happy, have either kept quiet or issued statements of contrition for the lapses that occurred during the stock boom of the 1990's.Then there is Philip J. Purcell, the chief executive of Morgan Stanley. According to Mr. Purcell, Morgan Stanley and its clients should not be disturbed by the firm's activities during the bubble.Addressing an institutional investor conference in New York yesterday, Mr. Purcell said, ''I don't see anything in the settlement that will concern the retail investor about Morgan Stanley.''His remarks to a packed ballroom at the Pierre Hotel lasted about 15 minutes. Taking questions, Mr. Purcell appeared to contradict directly the regulators' findings that Morgan Stanley had failed to disclose to investors that it had paid $2.7 million to other Wall Street firms to publish research on companies whose shares Morgan Stanley had underwritten.When a reporter asked about the $2.7 million in payments, Mr. Purcell said that everything about them had been disclosed. And he said that the firm was simply doing what its customers had wanted. ''The issuer asked for it so that they could get more coverage,'' he said. ''The $2.7 million went to pay firms for independent research. We didn't make the decision.''Mr. Purcell's comments came as a surprise to Eliot Spitzer, the New York attorney general, whose office investigated Morgan Stanley. ''We believe,'' he said, ''that the allegations set forth in the Morgan Stanley document establish a record that should deeply trouble retail investors because the document reflects that supposedly neutral analytical work was indeed subservient to the investment banking needs of the company. Moreover, the process of making payments to third parties for supposedly neutral research is entirely unacceptable and intolerable.''When asked about the apparent discrepancy in Mr. Purcell's remarks, Ray O'Rourke, a Morgan Stanley spokesman, said: ''Mr. Purcell was clearly and only referring to the fact that as the S.E.C.'s complaint states, the issuers' registration statements and other offering documents disclosed both the other banks as part of the underwriting syndicate and as receiving payments. What the complaint charged was that payment for research was not specifically disclosed.''</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/30/business/wall-st-settlement-plan-may-take-years.html?ref=usbancorp">Wall St. Settlement Plan May Take Years<date>Published: April 30, 2003</date><text>Correction AppendedThe good news for the thousands of people who may want part of the $387.5 million restitution fund created by the Wall Street settlement announced on Monday is that it will not prevent them from also suing their investment firms. The not-so-good news is that it may take years for the money to become available.Officials with the Securities and Exchange Commission said that the first step for the restitution fund was to appoint ''as soon as practicable'' an administrator who would set up a plan to repay investors who bought certain stocks through the 10 firms that reached the settlement and who have filed claims with the government.The administrator will determine whether investors can prove they relied on faulty research for their stock transactions and how much each should receive.The money from several past large settlements has gone to government entities, like the states, so the logistics of dividing nearly $400 million among perhaps thousands of individual investors could be daunting.On Monday, William H. Donaldson, the S.E.C. chairman, acknowledged as much. ''While there are challenges and difficulties in establishing such a fund,'' he said, ''the commission feels strongly that those challenges and difficulties are worth taking on.''Because the claimants will still be able to sue the investment firms, the research conducted by the S.E.C. fund to compensate stockholders will most likely be used as ammunition for the litigation to follow.The $387.5 million comes from the $1.4 billion total settlement, which includes $487.5 million in penalties, $432.5 million to finance independent research and $80 million for investor education.The $80 million education component also remains somewhat unclear. The plan calls for the money to come from Bear, Stearns; Goldman, Sachs; Lehman Brothers; J. P. Morgan; Merrill Lynch; Citigroup; and UBS Warburg. Of that total, $52.5 million will go into a fund created by the S.E.C. A spokesman for the agency said an administrator would be appointed to manage this fund as well. The S.E.C. already operates an investor education office and will likely integrate the new fund into its activities.The rest of the $80 million will be spread among state securities regulators to be used for education.Several regulators said yesterday that while the settlement made headlines and the brokerage houses might be chastened, many of their constituents were buying stocks promoted by Internet schemes.''We always have investor education needs to advise the investing public of potential scams at state or local levels,'' said Richard Djokic, Colorado's deputy securities commissioner. ''With the way that the economy is going on, there's a panic on the part of the investor to refill the cup with regard to their 401(k) or pension plan, and unfortunately these kinds of programs are flourishing.''Chat rooms, bulletin boards, online touts of stocks -- if Christmas were to come early, the investor education piece would look at that particular aspect,'' Mr. Djokic added.Correction: May 2, 2003, Friday An article in Business Day on Wednesday about the settlement between 10 Wall Street firms, on one side, and regulators on the other referred incorrectly to a separate fund to be created for investor education. It will not be integrated into the Securities and Exchange Commission's existing education programs.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/wall-street-settlement-investment-banking-citigroup-s-chairman-barred-direct.html?ref=usbancorp">WALL STREET SETTLEMENT: INVESTMENT BANKING; Citigroup's Chairman Is Barred From Direct Talks With Analysts<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>Moving decisively to prevent bias in future research reports, the regulatory settlement announced yesterday bars Sanford I. Weill, chairman of Citigroup, and other senior officers from talking to Citigroup's research analysts on investment banking matters without a company lawyer present.By highlighting Citigroup executives, regulators and prosecutors demonstrated their determination to stymie conflicts of interest within the investment bank's sprawling operations.The restrictions, which Citigroup officials agreed to, are also the legacy of an unorthodox campaign by Mr. Weill, spelled out in previously undisclosed detail, to persuade Jack B. Grubman, his star telecommunications analyst, to change his rating on AT&amp;T's stock from neutral to positive. Mr. Grubman had a neutral rating -- Wall Street code for negative -- on the stock from 1995 to November 1999, at which time he issued a new report with a positive rating.While Mr. Weill has publicly acknowledged asking Mr. Grubman to take a fresh look at AT&amp;T, documents released yesterday show that their discussions were intricate and numerous and dated as far back as the fall of 1998.Mr. Weill accompanied Mr. Grubman to meetings with C. Michael Armstrong, then the chief executive of AT&amp;T, and asked that Mr. Grubman's AT&amp;T report be sent to him, before its publication, e-mail messages show.Such a close interaction with an analyst is unusual and might open Mr. Weill and other Citigroup executives to future claims by regulators that they failed to supervise Mr. Grubman, legal experts say -- even though Mr. Grubman never reported directly to Mr. Weill.''The AT&amp;T matter could be pertinent in a failure-to-supervise case, given the interaction between Mr. Weill and Mr. Grubman,'' said Robert G. Heim, a former Securities and Exchange Commission lawyer now at Meyers &amp; Heim. ''If Mr. Weill was aware that Mr. Grubman was basing his recommendations on investment banking considerations, that may make Mr. Weill vulnerable.''Regulators say that a failure-to-supervise complaint is unlikely to be brought solely on the AT&amp;T episode. They do say, though, that it could be used as a relevant example in proving a broader case that Mr. Weill and other senior executives failed, individually, to adequately supervise Mr. Grubman.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/opinion/finding-fraud-on-wall-street.html?ref=usbancorp">Finding Fraud on Wall Street<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>After five months of negotiating the fine print, 10 Wall Street firms accused of issuing tainted stock research agreed yesterday to the terms of a landmark $1.4 billion settlement. Three of the firms -- Citigroup's Salomon Smith Barney, Merrill Lynch and Credit Suisse First Boston -- were charged with actually issuing ''fraudulent'' stock recommendations. This unambiguous language, not the fines' dollar amounts, may be the most significant outcome of the inquiry undertaken by the New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, and other regulators.The language sets the record clear: brokerage firms compromised their integrity in an effort to curry favor with their banking clients at the expense of individual investors. Along with a treasure trove of new evidence, this finding should strengthen the legal position of investors seeking restitution through private litigation.Jack Grubman and Henry Blodget, analysts who became celebrities during the market bubble, agreed to a lifetime ban from the securities industry. They will also pay fines totaling $19 million, a modest sum in light of their combined compensation and the nature of their behavior. But as with their former employers -- Citigroup and Merrill Lynch -- these fines may represent only a fraction of their eventual liability.Mr. Spitzer's inquiry became front-page news when he produced e-mail showing how Mr. Blodget, Merrill's Internet analyst, touted stocks he privately called ''junk.'' Mr. Grubman issued similarly inflated valuations to please Citigroup's investment banking clients. Evidence released yesterday also pointed to improper contacts between Mr. Grubman and Sanford Weill, Citigroup's chairman. Citigroup is paying the largest penalty and is being singled out for the most intrusive monitoring of its research operations.The settlement's structural reforms, announced last December, are aimed at insulating research analysts from their investment-banking brethren. Brokerage firms must also provide clients with competing independent research and end the infamous practice, called ''spinning,'' of allotting hot initial public offering shares to favored clients. Firms are already adopting many of these reforms to regain investors' trust. Even experienced investors were shocked to discover how widespread these practices were. The settlement should be closely monitored to prevent their reappearance.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/wall-street-settlement-overview-10-wall-st-firms-reach-settlement-analyst.html?ref=usbancorp">WALL STREET SETTLEMENT: THE OVERVIEW; 10 WALL ST. FIRMS REACH SETTLEMENT IN ANALYST INQUIRY<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>Prosecutors announced a settlement today with the nation's biggest investment firms that bars the head of the largest bank from talking to his analysts, details a far greater range of conflicts of interest than previously disclosed, and leaves the industry exposed both to further regulation and costly litigation.The $1.4 billion settlement by 10 firms and 2 well-known stock analysts reached tentatively last December but completed in the last few days, resolved accusations that the firms lured millions of investors to buy billions of dollars worth of shares in companies they knew were troubled and which ultimately either collapsed or sharply declined.The Securities and Exchange Commission, state prosecutors and market regulators accused three firms in particular -- Citigroup's Salomon Smith Barney, Merrill Lynch, and Credit Suisse First Boston -- of fraud. But the thousands of pages of internal e-mail messages and other evidence that regulators made public today painted a picture up and down Wall Street of an industry rife with conflicts of interest during the height of the Internet and telecommunications bubble that burst three years ago. [Page C1.]At firm after firm, according to prosecutors, analysts wittingly duped investors to curry favor with corporate clients. Investment houses received secret payments from companies they gave strong recommendations to buy. And for top executives whose companies were clients, stock underwriters offered special access to hot initial public offerings.''These cases reflect a sad chapter in the history of American business -- a chapter in which those who reaped enormous benefits based on the trust of investors profoundly betrayed that trust,'' said William H. Donaldson, the new chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission. ''The cases also represent an important new chapter in our ongoing efforts to restore investors' faith and confidence in the fairness and integrity of our markets.''In a reflection of regulators' concerns about the prospect for conflicts of interest at Citigroup, Wall Street's biggest bank, the settlement bars its chairman and chief executive, Sanford I. Weill, from communicating with his firm's stock analysts about the companies they cover, unless a lawyer is present. [Page C1.]But the regulators found fault with every major bank on Wall Street.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/wall-street-settlement-financial-services-subject-barely-mentioned-merrill.html?ref=usbancorp">WALL STREET SETTLEMENT: FINANCIAL SERVICES; A Subject Barely Mentioned at Merrill Meeting<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>Correction AppendedA year after David H. Komansky, the chairman of Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, apologized to shareholders for the firm's tainted investment advice, he barely discussed the topic at the firm's annual meeting here today.As Mr. Komansky led his sixth and final meeting, he spent more time defending the firm's treatment of women in its brokerage business and the pay of its executives than discussing the global settlement that regulators were preparing to announce a few hours later in Washington. State and federal regulators said that Merrill, the first of 12 firms caught up in the scandal, had defrauded buyers of certain Internet stocks. It agreed to pay $200 million of the $1.4 billion settlement.Merrill's punishment was harsher than those of all but two of its competitors. Citigroup agreed to pay $400 million and to issue a statement of contrition from its chairman and chief executive, Sanford I. Weill. Credit Suisse First Boston also agreed to pay $200 million.''This past year was a difficult year to be in business for our clients, our employees and our company,'' Mr. Komansky said. ''There is nothing more important to us than being able to reposition ourselves in the public eye as we think we should be.''Mr. Komansky, 64, did not broach the subject of the settlement, nor did his successor, E. Stanley O'Neal, who has been chief executive since December. But a shareholder did, asking what the firm was doing to restore investor confidence.Mr. O'Neal, 51, said that the firm had already made most of the changes required by regulators to reduce the influence investment bankers have over the analysts who rate companies' stocks for investors. He said the firm was ''redoubling'' efforts to restore its reputation.''Clearly we're not perfect and we have not always lived up to our ideals,'' Mr. O'Neal told a full auditorium at Merrill's training center here.After the meeting, which lasted less than an hour, Mr. O'Neal said there would probably be more lawsuits against Merrill as a result of the announcement of the regulators' findings that some of the firm's research had been fraudulent, coupled with the announcement that Henry M. Blodget, Merrill's former senior Internet analyst, had agreed to pay $4 million to settle with state and federal regulators.Correction: April 30, 2003, Wednesday A picture caption in Business Day yesterday about remarks made on Monday at the annual meeting of Merrill Lynch by David H. Komansky, who is stepping down as chairman, misidentified the scene shown. It was a news conference in May 2002, not the meeting.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/29/business/wall-street-settlement-market-place-wall-street-hierarchy-short-shrift-little.html?ref=usbancorp">WALL STREET SETTLEMENT: MARKET PLACE; In Wall Street Hierarchy, Short Shrift To Little Guy<date>Published: April 29, 2003</date><text>Documents disclosed as part of yesterday's settlement show how Wall Street firms, in pursuit of investment banking fees, put the interests of their individual clients dead last.As an analyst at Lehman Brothers told an institutional investor in an e-mail message, ''well, ratings and price targets are fairly meaningless anyway,'' later adding, ''but, yes, the 'little guy' who isn't smart about the nuances may get misled, such is the nature of my business.''In a newly disclosed tactic, Morgan Stanley and four other brokerage firms paid rivals that agreed to publish positive reports on companies whose shares Morgan and others issued to the public. This practice made it appear that a throng of believers were recommending these companies' shares.From 1999 through 2001, for example, Morgan Stanley paid about $2.7 million to approximately 25 other investment banks for these so-called research guarantees, regulators said. Nevertheless, the firm boasted in its annual report to shareholders that it had come through investigations of analyst conflicts of interest with its ''reputation for integrity'' maintained.Among the firms receiving payments for their bullish research on companies whose offerings they did not manage were UBS Warburg and U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray. UBS received $213,000 and Piper Jaffray, more than $1.8 million.What jumps off the page in these documents is the Wall Street firms' disregard for the individual investor in pursuit of personal benefit.One comment made by a Bear, Stearns analyst is telling. While participating in a conference call by SonicWall, an Internet company whose shares Bear, Stearns had sold to the public, the analyst told a colleague that he was trying to make the company look good with his questions. A few moments later, he said, ''we got paid for this,'' adding, ''and I am going to Cancun tomorrow b/c of them.''But because greed is a part of human nature and human nature seldom seems to change, Alan Bromberg, professor of securities law at Southern Methodist University, remains skeptical that the terms of the settlement will bring substantive change to Wall Street.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/20/business/company-news-us-bancorp-plans-to-spin-off-piper-jaffray.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP PLANS TO SPIN OFF PIPER JAFFRAY<date>Published: February 20, 2003</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it planned to spin off its Piper Jaffray securities unit to shareholders. The bank, based in Minneapolis, said Andrew Duff, currently chief executive of the Piper Jaffray unit, would have the same role at the new independent company. U.S. Bancorp, which acquired Piper Jaffray in 1998, said it expected to hold a subordinated debt interest of about $215 million in the company. U.S. Bancorp shareholders will receive shares of the new company in a tax-free stock dividend distribution, the company said.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/31/business/piper-jaffray-agrees-to-settle-charges-on-ratings-of-stocks.html?ref=usbancorp">Piper Jaffray Agrees to Settle Charges on Ratings of Stocks<date>Published: December 31, 2002</date><text>The investment firm U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray, said today that it had agreed to pay $25 million and to change the way it does business to settle charges that it provided biased stock ratings.Piper Jaffray said it had agreed in principle with federal and state regulators to resolve its part of an industrywide investigation into accusations that 12 firms misled investors by inflating stock ratings to help them investment banking business.The case drew widespread attention when regulators uncovered e-mail messages at some firms in which analysts privately derided stocks they were recommending to the public.Piper Jaffray and another investment banker, Thomas Weisel Partners, had held out while 10 others -- including Citigroup; Goldman, Sachs; and Credit Suisse First Boston -- agreed to pay $1.44 billion in a settlement on Dec. 20 with the New York State attorney general's office, which handled the negotiations. In addition to $900 million in fines, the firms will also pay $450 million over five years for independent research and $85 million for a nationwide investor education program.In agreeing to the fines, the firms neither admitted nor denied that they had misled investors.Piper Jaffray and Thomas Weisel had raised objections to the settlement and continued negotiations.Besides the $25 million in fines, Piper Jaffray, which is based in Minneapolis, agreed to pay $1.5 million annually for five years. The firm said it had also agreed to make ''structural changes'' relating to its research and investment banking program, but it did not detail the changes.Andrew S. Duff, the chief executive of Piper Jaffray, said in a statement: ''Since this process began, our regulators and we have shared the goals of reinforcing equity research independence, bringing about progressive changes to various industry practices and restoring confidence in the capital markets system. We believe this settlement will accomplish these goals.''A Piper Jaffray spokeswoman, Erin Freeman, declined to comment further. The New York attorney general's office also did not immediately comment.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/04/business/the-markets-market-place-five-brokerage-firms-fined-for-not-keeping-messages.html?ref=usbancorp">THE MARKETS: Market Place; Five Brokerage Firms Fined For Not Keeping Messages<date>Published: December 04, 2002</date><text>Regulators fined five of the nation's largest brokerage firms yesterday for failing to preserve internal e-mail communications as required under securities laws.The Securities and Exchange Commission, NASD and the New York Stock Exchange announced joint actions against Deutsche Bank Securities; Goldman Sachs; Morgan Stanley; Salomon Smith Barney; and U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray. Each firm was fined $1.65 million and was told to review procedures to ensure that record-keeping practices comply with regulations in the future. All the firms settled the actions without admitting or denying the accusations.The fines, which total $8.25 million, are the largest ever in a record-keeping case, regulators said.''The message here to our member firms is the form of the communications doesn't matter, it's the substance,'' said Barry Goldsmith, executive vice president for enforcement at NASD, ''and that the rules requiring broker-dealers to keep those records apply to e-mails and will be enforced.''Securities laws require that brokerage firms preserve electronic communications related to the business of the firm for three years. Such messages must be kept in an accessible place for two years.But during the investigations into analyst practices on Wall Street and the firms' allocation of hot new stock offerings to favored clients, securities regulators began to see how haphazard the retention of e-mail messages was at some brokerage firms.For example, regulators found that some firms discarded, recycled, or wrote over the e-mail tapes that should have been kept, sometimes after less than a year. While some firms relied on their employees to preserve copies of their e-mail messages on their computers' hard drives, there were no systems in place to ensure that the e-mail messages were in fact maintained. In some cases, the hard drives of computers used to preserve e-mail messages were erased when an employee left a firm.In recent years, securities firms have argued to regulators that retaining e-mail messages is too onerous and that it is unclear which messages have to be kept. The firms have also been lobbying Congress to exempt e-mail messages from the records that must be maintained under securities laws. But the S.E.C. reaffirmed its position in November 2001 that e-mail messages are among the documents that must be preserved.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/14/business/company-news-us-bancorp-buys-trust-division-from-state-street.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP BUYS TRUST DIVISION FROM STATE STREET<date>Published: August 14, 2002</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the State Street Corporation's corporate trust business for $725 million to expand in New England. The division, which acts as a trustee for corporate and municipal bondholders, will add 20,000 clients and $689 billion in assets under management, a U.S. Bancorp spokesman, Steve Dale, said. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, has made four acquisitions since the Firstar Corporation bought U.S. Bancorp in February 2001 and adopted its name. State Street, which is based in Boston, said the sale would not affect its 2003 results.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/02/business/e-mail-gaps-may-mean-fines-for-big-firms.html?ref=usbancorp">E-Mail Gaps May Mean Fines for Big Firms<date>Published: August 02, 2002</date><text>Securities regulators have told six investment banks, including the biggest firms on Wall Street, that they may have to pay as much as $10 million in penalties for not keeping e-mail messages as required, people close to the matter said yesterday.At a meeting in Washington on Tuesday, officials of the Securities and Exchange Commission, NASD and the New York Stock Exchange proposed the fines as part of a settlement of inquiries into the disposal of e-mail messages, these people said. The regulators discovered that the firms were not complying with the rules during their investigation into possible conflicts of interest among stock analysts.Regulators say the firms are required to preserve all business communications they have sent -- both internally and externally -- for three years. For at least two years, they must be kept in an easily accessible place. But the firms failed to produce all of the e-mail messages the regulators expected under those rules.The firms that the regulators may punish are the Salomon Smith Barney unit of Citigroup, Morgan Stanley, the Goldman Sachs Group, Merrill Lynch, Deutsche Bank and U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray, these people said. Each would pay an equal share of the fine in the proposed settlement, one of these people said.The firms have each come under scrutiny for links between their investment banking business and the investment recommendations of their stock analysts, they said.The commission and the regulatory arm of NASD, which monitors securities firms and their employees, have requested documents related to the firms' procedures for rating companies and evaluating and paying analysts.Those subjects came to the fore after Eliot L. Spitzer, the New York State attorney general, released e-mail messages written by Henry Blodget and other Internet stock analysts at Merrill Lynch. The messages appeared to catch the analysts exchanging negative views about companies whose stocks they were recommending to investors. They described companies in disparaging terms, like a ''piece of junk.''To end the New York investigation, Merrill agreed to pay penalties of $100 million to New York and the other states. Merrill, the nation's biggest brokerage firm, also agreed to make several changes in how it monitors, evaluates and pays its analysts to better insulate them from its investment bankers.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/23/business/company-news-us-bancorp-buys-57-bay-view-branches-in-california.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP BUYS 57 BAY VIEW BRANCHES IN CALIFORNIA<date>Published: July 23, 2002</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it had agreed to buy 57 branches from the Bay View Capital Corporation for $429 million. The purchase includes $3 billion in consumer and small-business deposits and $376 million in loans, a U.S. Bancorp spokesman said. The final price will be based on the value of the consumer deposits when the deal closes by the end of the year. U.S. Bancorp has been making small purchases in California to expand its consumer business on the West Coast. In September, the bank bought 20 branches in Southern California from the Pacific Century Financial Corporation. With the Bay View branches, the company will have 215 offices in the state.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/27/nyregion/c-corrections-742635.html?ref=usbancorp">Corrections<date>Published: June 27, 2002</date><text>A headline with a brief report in the Company News column of Business Day yesterday about fines imposed by regulators on US Bancorp Piper Jaffray and one of its senior investment bankers for threatening to drop a company as a research client unless it hired the firm to arrange a stock sale misstated the entity that imposed the fines. It was the National Association of Securities Dealers, not the Nasdaq stock market, which is no longer owned or operated by the N.A.S.D.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/26/business/company-news-us-bancorp-unit-fined-250000-by-nasdaq-body.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; US BANCORP UNIT FINED $250,000 BY NASDAQ BODY<date>Published: June 26, 2002</date><text>Correction AppendedUS Bancorp Piper Jaffray and one of its senior investment bankers were fined by regulators for threatening to drop Antigenics Inc. as a research client unless the biotechnology company hired the firm to arrange a stock sale. The National Association of Securities Dealers fined the unit of US Bancorp $250,000 and a managing director, Scott Beardsley, $50,000. The case is the first in which the N.A.S.D. punished a company for making a threat linking underwriting and research coverage, said Brian Rubin, a deputy chief counsel with N.A.S.D. regulation. In settling, the firm and Mr. Beardsley neither admitted nor denied wrongdoing.Correction: June 27, 2002, Thursday A headline with a brief report in the Company News column of Business Day yesterday about fines imposed by regulators on US Bancorp Piper Jaffray and one of its senior investment bankers for threatening to drop a company as a research client unless it hired the firm to arrange a stock sale misstated the entity that imposed the fines. It was the National Association of Securities Dealers, not the Nasdaq stock market, which is no longer owned or operated by the N.A.S.D.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/10/business/company-news-analyst-s-report-sends-shares-of-edison-down-40.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; ANALYST'S REPORT SENDS SHARES OF EDISON DOWN 40%<date>Published: May 10, 2002</date><text>Stock in Edison Schools Inc., the operator of public schools, fell 40 percent yesterday after an analyst downgraded the stock. The analyst, Mark Marostica at U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray, said he expected the shares to trade at $3 each. His previous 12-month forecast was $32. Edison's shares fell $1.48, to $2.22. Shares of Edison, based in New York, had fallen 71 percent since the company was selected last month to run 20 of Philadelphia's worst-performing schools, fewer than half the number sought. Officials from Edison could not be reached for comment. The company, which has been losing money, is scheduled to release its earnings next week.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/06/business/company-news-midwest-bank-raises-provision-for-possible-loan-losses.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; MIDWEST BANK RAISES PROVISION FOR POSSIBLE LOAN LOSSES<date>Published: October 6, 2001</date><text>U.S. Bancorp, a regional banking company based in Minneapolis, said yesterday that its third-quarter profit would be cut by $655 million because it increased the amount of money it had set aside to account for possible loan losses after the terrorist attacks last month. The company said it raised its provisions to 2.12 percent of its outstanding loans as of Sunday from 1.45 percent as of June 30. U.S. Bancorp said loans at risk were primarily those made to the transportation industry, particularly aviation, and the manufacturing industry. The report set off a 16 percent decline in U.S. Bancorp's stock price.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/08/business/us-bancorp-buys-processor-of-credit-card-debt.html?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bancorp Buys Processor of Credit Card Debt<date>Published: May 08, 2001</date><text>U.S. Bancorp, the eighth-largest United States bank, agreed to buy the Nova Corporation, a credit card payment-processing company, for $2.1 billion to expand in a business that is growing faster than lending.Shareholders of Nova, which is based in Atlanta, will have the option of receiving either 1.407 shares of U.S. Bancorp stock -- worth $31.91 at U.S. Bancorp's closing price on Friday -- or $31 in cash for each Nova share. The cash portion represents a 32 percent premium over Nova's share price of $23.52 on Friday.Buying Nova would make U.S. Bancorp the No. 3 processor of payments for merchants, handling everything from approving credit card purchases to settling transactions. It will also bolster an operation where revenue grew 14 percent, to $249.7 million in the first quarter, compared with 4.1 percent growth in its lending business.''If you've traditionally been in a business where you're subject to the ups and downs of interest rates, this is a good diversification away from that,'' said Scott Edgar, who helps manage $750 million of assets at Sife Trust Fund, which owns U.S. Bancorp shares.U.S. Bancorp shares fell $1.44, closing at $21.24. Nova jumped $5.53, a 24 percent gain, to $29.05.U.S. Bancorp processes credit card and other electronic payments for 90,000 large merchants, including some airlines. Nova has 560,000 smaller clients. Together, the companies will process more than $100 billion of payments in 2001, U.S. Bancorp said.The purchase adds a business that had $1.58 billion of revenue last year, 8 percent more than the year before. It will increase U.S. Bancorp's cash earnings once it is completed in the third quarter, and cut $27 million out of the companies' costs by 2003. The one-time expense of completing the purchase is expected to total $100 million before taxes.''Payment processing is a higher-growth, higher-return business than traditional banking,'' said Jennifer Thompson, an analyst at Putnam Lovell Securities.''This combination creates the economies of scale that are critical to being a long-term survivor in this desirable segment of the payment services industry,'' Jerry Grundhofer, U.S. Bancorp's chief executive, said in a statement.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/30/business/company-news-us-bancorp-sets-deal-to-renew-indonesian-debt.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP SETS DEAL TO RENEW INDONESIAN DEBT<date>Published: December 30, 2000</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said it had arranged for six institutional bondholders to renew $632 million of secured debt owed by Polysindo Eka Perkasa, a unit of the Texmaco Group, Indonesia's most indebted company. Under the agreement, bonds and bank debt will be converted into a new obligation backed by the assets of Polysindo; the investors will also get an equity stake in Polysindo after it is reorganized. U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, acted as trustee for the debt instruments but does not own any of the Polysindo notes itself, a spokesman said. Texmaco, whose main business is textiles, is struggling to pay off $2.7 billion owed by itself and its affiliates.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/business/us-bancorp-to-be-acquired-by-firstar-for-21-billion.html?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bancorp to Be Acquired By Firstar for $21 Billion<date>Published: October 05, 2000</date><text>The Firstar Corporation agreed yesterday to acquire U.S. Bancorp in a $21 billion stock deal that unites two large regional banks led by brothers.The combination of the Milwaukee-based Firstar, whose chief executive is Jerry A. Grundhofer, and the Minneapolis-based U.S. Bancorp, which is led by his younger brother, John F. Grundhofer, will create the nation's eighth-biggest bank, with more than $160 billion in assets.The negotiations started with a telephone call by John Grundhofer in mid-September. His brother was eager to talk. ''Our board always looks at alternatives'' Jerry Grundhofer said yesterday. ''We had a wish list, and it always seemed to gravitate toward U.S. Bancorp.''The fact that he is buying his brother's company will only help, he said, adding, ''I've always found it easy to talk to Jack.''Firstar is paying 1.265 shares of its stock for each share of U.S. Bancorp, valuing the bank at $28.15 a share, a 21 percent premium to its closing price of $23.19 on Tuesday. Shares of U.S. Bancorp rose $1.81 yesterday, to $25. Firstar fell $2.25, to $20, reducing the value of the deal to $25.30 a share, or $19 billion.The boards of both companies have approved the deal. The surviving company will be known as U.S. Bancorp, but Firstar's management will control 14 of 25 board seats and 50.5 percent of the stock. Jerry Grundhofer will serve as president and chief executive, while John Grundhofer will be chairman until the end of 2002.The deal unites two institutions with complementary strengths and weaknesses. Firstar has a strong retail franchise, which accounted for 50 percent of its earnings in the most recent quarter and has been growing at 21 percent a year. U.S. Bancorp has struggled with its retail business, and an anemic 6 percent growth rate has largely contributed to the company's recent earnings disappointments.''That business has been an albatross around their necks for the last year,'' said Jon Arfstrom, an analyst with Dain Rauscher Wessels in Minneapolis.The U.S. Bancorp acquisition allows Firstar to diversify away from its core lending business. U.S. Bancorp owns the regional brokerage firm Piper Jaffray, which it acquired in 1998, as well as a payment-systems business that includes corporate charge and purchasing cards. Thanks largely to these subsidiaries, fee-based activities will account for 43 percent of the combined company's earnings, compared with 35 percent currently for Firstar.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/05/business/company-news-computer-learning-centers-hires-investment-bank.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; COMPUTER LEARNING CENTERS HIRES INVESTMENT BANK<date>Published: November 05, 1999</date><text>Computer Learning Centers said yesterday that it had hired U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray to help it explore options, including a possible sale. The company, based in Fairfax, Va., provides computer education and training at 28 centers in the United States and Canada. It reported revenue of $68.8 million and a loss of $3 million for the six months ended July 31. Computer Learning rose 43.75 cents, to $3.25, giving the company a market value of about $59 million.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/09/03/business/company-news-us-bancorp-is-acquiring-peninsula-bank-of-san-diego.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP IS ACQUIRING PENINSULA BANK OF SAN DIEGO<date>Published: September 03, 1999</date><text>Peninsula Bank of San Diego agreed yesterday to be acquired by one of its larger competitors, U.S. Bancorp, in a stock transaction valued at about $104 million. Peninsula, which opened in 1975, operates 11 branches in San Diego County and has 240 employees. It has about 30,000 individual and business accounts and recorded assets of $456 million as of June 30. U.S. Bancorp, which is based in Minneapolis, has $77 billion in assets. It is the 13th-largest bank in the country and has been expanding its presence in California.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/10/business/company-news-michael-foods-exploring-strategic-options.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; MICHAEL FOODS EXPLORING STRATEGIC OPTIONS<date>Published: August 10, 1999</date><text>Michael Foods Inc., one of the largest United States egg producers, said yesterday that it had hired the investment bankers United States Bancorp Piper Jaffray and Merrill Lynch &amp; Company to help it explore strategic options, including an outright sale. The food processing and distribution company said other alternatives include strategic alliances, acquisitions and the sale of some of its businesses. Michael Foods said it was trying to raise its share value. Its shares have fallen 21 percent so far this year. Michael Foods' shares rose $1.125 each, to $23.5625. At that price the company's stock market value is $408 million. The Minneapolis-based company had $1.02 billion in revenue in 1998.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/15/nyregion/c-corrections-171328.html?ref=usbancorp">Corrections<date>Published: June 15, 1999</date><text>An article in Business Day on Saturday about concerns over consumers' financial privacy referred incompletely to the involvement of Memberworks, a telemarketing firm based in Stamford, Conn., in a suit filed against U.S. Bancorp by the Minnesota Attorney General's office. Although the suit contends that the bank illegally sold credit histories and other information to Memberworks, the firm is not a defendant in the case.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/11/business/minnesota-sues-us-bank-on-privacy-data.html?ref=usbancorp">Minnesota Sues U.S. Bank on Privacy Data<date>Published: June 11, 1999</date><text>The State of Minnesota has filed a lawsuit against a unit of U.S. Bancorp contending that it violated Federal and state consumer protection laws by providing customers' financial information to a telemarketing company.The suit was filed Wednesday by the state Attorney General, Michael Hatch. Although it does not name the telemarketing company, Memberworks Inc., as a defendant, the suit says Memberworks paid U.S. Bancorp $4 million plus commissions to release financial and personal information on 900,000 customers.The lawsuit against U.S. Bank, a unit of U.S. Bancorp, comes as Congress is trying to add new protections for consumers' financial information in a bank modernization bill.The practices are ''much more widespread than just U.S. Bank,'' said Ed Mierzwinski, consumer program director of Public Interest Research Group, an affiliate of Ralph Nader.Minnesota's suit, which says the bank violated the Federal Fair Credit Reporting Act and consumer fraud and deceptive advertising laws, seeks a jury trial and calls on the bank to pay civil penalties to consumers. Consumer losses were not specified, though the amount could reach into the millions of dollars, Mr. Hatch said. The bank was accused of turning over customers' Social Security numbers, account balances, names, addresses, checking and credit card numbers, average account balances, finance charges and credit limits.U.S. Bancorp denied violating customer privacy rights or Minnesota consumer protection laws.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/20/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-buy-southern-california-banks.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP TO BUY SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA BANKS<date>Published: May 20, 1999</date><text>U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Western Bancorp for $958 million in stock, expanding its operations in the Midwest and West into Southern California. U.S. Bancorp, which is based in Minneapolis and has about 1,000 branches and $76 billion in assets, will add 31 branches with the purchase. Western Bancorp, which is based in Newport Beach, Calif., and is the parent of Santa Monica Bank and Southern California Bank, has $2.5 billion in assets. U.S. Bancorp said that it had agreed to exchange 1.2915 of its shares for each Western share, which valued Western at $44.40 a share, based on Tuesday's closing share prices. Western Bancorp shares rose $1.3125, to $40.3125. U.S. Bancorp shares fell $1.8125, to $32.5625.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/15/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-sell-28-branches-in-two-states.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP TO SELL 28 BRANCHES IN TWO STATES<date>Published: May 15, 1999</date><text>The Minneapolis-based bank holding company U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it planned to sell 20 bank branches in Kansas and 8 bank branches in Iowa. Financial terms of the deals were not disclosed. The Kansas branches will be sold to Intrust Bank N.A., based in Wichita, Kan. The Iowa branches will be sold to seven financial institutions in that state. After the deals close in the third quarter, U.S. Bancorp will have 21 branches in Iowa and none in Kansas.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/20/business/company-news-us-bancorp-adding-bank-of-commerce-in-stock-deal.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP ADDING BANK OF COMMERCE IN STOCK DEAL<date>Published: February 20, 1999</date><text>U.S. Bancorp has agreed to buy the San Diego-based Bank of Commerce in a stock deal valued near $314 million. Under terms of the agreement reached on Thursday, Bank of Commerce shareholders will receive 0.6 share of U.S. Bancorp's common stock for each common share of Bank of Commerce. Bank of Commerce services $742 million worth of government-backed small business loans and originated $242 million last year. It has 10 branches and $638 million in assets. Commerce will be the fifth acquisition for the former First Bank System since it acquired U.S. Bancorp, of Portland, Ore., in August 1997 and took its name.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/09/04/business/company-news-us-bancorp-in-deal-for-high-yield-bond-specialist.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP IN DEAL FOR HIGH-YIELD BOND SPECIALIST<date>Published: September 04, 1998</date><text>U.S. Bancorp, based in Minneapolis, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Libra Investments Inc., a privately held investment bank that specializes in high-yield bonds, for an undisclosed sum. Libra, based in Los Angeles, provides corporate finance and advisory services, securities research, and sales and trading of high-yield securities. It has 65 employees in Los Angeles and New York and plans to open a 30-person office in Minneapolis later this year. U.S. Bancorp, which has been investing in Libra funds for two years, has $74 billion in assets and about 1,000 branches in 17 states. U.S. Bancorp bought the investment bank Piper Jaffray for $730 million earlier this year.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/07/16/business/a-number-of-banks-report-strong-profits-in-2d-quarter.html?ref=usbancorp">A Number of Banks Report Strong Profits in 2d Quarter<date>Published: July 16, 1998</date><text>The BankAmerica Corporation and several other large banks met or beat second-quarter earnings expectations as they generated higher fees from consumers and corporations.Earnings at BankAmerica, the fifth-largest bank, rose 11.4 percent, and Fleet Financial Group Inc., the 10th-largest bank, said its net income increased 13 percent.''They're strong,'' said Anthony Gray, chairman and chief investment officer of STI Capital Management in Orlando, Fla., which oversees $14 billion. ''And they should be for the next couple of quarters'' because of a robust United States economy, he said.Gains from mortgages and credit cards, and profits from investment banking and asset-management units outpaced flat or declining net interest revenue.The San Francisco-based BankAmerica, said profit in the second quarter rose on higher fee income from investment banking and other businesses. BankAmerica, which is being acquired by the Nationsbank Corporation for $65 billion, said net income was $890 million, or $1.24 a share, including several one-time gains and losses.Fleet's second-quarter earnings rose as new brokerage and investment businesses thrived. The Boston-based bank said net income rose to $393 million, or $1.29 a diluted share, from $347 million, or $1.17, a year earlier. The results beat estimates of $1.26 a share.Fleet's purchases of the brokerage firm Quick &amp; Reilly and the Advanta Corporation's credit card unit pushed noninterest income up 35 percent, even as net interest income gained 5 percent.U.S. Bancorp, the country's 17th-largest bank, with assets of $73.8 billion, said second-quarter earnings rose as the bank generated more fees from investment and trust services. The Minneapolis-based bank said net income, including one-time items in both periods, rose 5.5 percent, to $320.6 million, or 43 cents a diluted share.The Wachovia Corporation, which has $63.9 billion in total assets, said its operating earnings rose 17 percent, led by gains in fees from capital markets and mortgage services.The bank, which is based in Winston-Salem, N.C., said net income rose 6.7 percent, to $209.9 million, or $1 a diluted share, from $196.8 million, or 98 cents.Republic, with $56.4 billion in assets, said second-quarter earnings rose 7.5 percent on foreign exchange and equity gains. The New York bank said net income rose to $118.8 million, or $1.05 a diluted share, from $110.5 million, or 98 cents a share.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/10/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-repurchase-up-to-2.5-billion-of-stock.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP TO REPURCHASE UP TO $2.5 BILLION OF STOCK<date>Published: June 10, 1998</date><text>U.S. Bancorp plans to repurchase up to $2.5 billion of its common stock. The buyback amounts to about 62.5 million shares, or 8 percent of the company's shares outstanding as of March 31. U.S. Bancorp said yesterday that it planned to complete the buyout by March 31, 2000. Shares of U.S. Bancorp rose 31.25 cents, to $40.3125. Companies use share buybacks to tighten the supply of their stock and increase earnings per share. U.S. Bancorp was formed by the merger last year of the Minneapolis-based First Bank System Inc. and U.S. Bancorp, based in Portland, Ore. The merged company has more than $70 billion in assets, making it the 15th-largest banking company in the nation. U.S. Bancorp has about 742.5 million shares outstanding.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/16/business/us-bancorp-seeks-piper-jaffray-for-730-million.html?ref=usbancorp">U.S. Bancorp Seeks Piper Jaffray for $730 Million<date>Published: December 16, 1997</date><text>U.S. Bancorp, the nation's 15th-biggest banking company, agreed yesterday to buy the Piper Jaffray Companies, a securities firm, for $730 million in cash to lock in Midwestern customers with a broader array of financial services.The acquisition would add retail and institutional brokerage services, investment banking and merger and acquisition assets to U.S. Bancorp, a leading commercial bank in 17 states stretching from Minnesota to Washington. The deal will also increase its assets under management by about $13 billion. After the purchase, U.S. Bancorp will have about $30 billion of mutual fund assets and about $65 billion of assets. U.S. Bancorp and Piper Jaffray are both based in Minneapolis.''This is a rational, sensible acquisition of an investment banking house,'' said Nancy Bush, a bank analyst at Brown Brothers Harriman &amp; Company. ''This is additive to their core customer base, which includes retail and small- to middle- market businesses.''But the transaction values Piper at $37.25 a share, or about four times book value -- assets minus liabilities -- a bigger premium than the already lofty prices that other banks paid this year to buy securities firms. Piper shares rose $6.625, or 22 percent, to $36.375.The acquisition comes at a time when large commercial banks have been swallowing smaller regional investment banks as the Depression-era walls that banned banks from investment banking and other securities businesses erode. U.S. Bancorp is paying a high price for Piper because the number of available securities firms is dwindling, analysts said.''The price that U.S. Bancorp is paying seems higher than usual,'' said Amy Laguardia, senior vice president at Gray, Seifert &amp; Company, which owned almost 303,000 U.S. Bancorp share as of Sept. 30.This year, BankAmerica bought Robertson, Stephens &amp; Company for 3.7 times book value and First Union bought Wheat First Butcher Singer for about 3.1 times book value.Officials at U.S. Bancorp said the price was consistent with what other banks have paid for brokerage firms. ''If you calculate what funds are going for these days, this is a little different situation than buying a retail brokerage house,'' said Richard Zona, vice chairman at U.S. Bancorp.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/26/business/business-travel-those-headed-for-middle-east-south-asia-are-warned-be-extra.html?ref=usbancorp">Business Travel; Those headed for the Middle East and South Asia are warned to be extra cautious these days.<date>Published: November 26, 1997</date><text>THE Middle East and South Asia are hot spots for business travelers these days because of Muslim terrorist attacks in Egypt and Pakistan, along with the still- simmering confrontations between the United States and Iraq.''It's a time to go into a country, do your business and get out,'' said E. C. Ackerman, managing director of the Ackerman Group, an executive-security firm based in Miami with a large ex-C.I.A. staff and many multinational company clients.The Middle East is an especially proceed-with-caution place, Mr. Ackerman said. ''Anti-American sentiment is currently running high throughout the Muslim world,'' the Ackerman Group wrote in a memo to its clients earlier this month. ''If Mir Aimal Kansi, recently convicted of the 1993 murders of two C.I.A. employees, is sentenced to death, personnel have every reason to remain cautious.'' A Virginia jury recommended the death penalty on Nov. 14; formal sentencing is scheduled for Jan. 23.The most dangerous countries in the Middle East and South Asia, according to the Ackerman Group, are Egypt, Jordan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Pakistan and Saudi Arabia. In the second tier -- with less risk -- are Bahrain, Turkey, the United Arab Emirates and Yemen.Mr. Ackerman's advice: ''Don't go to the first-tier countries if you can avoid it. Stay away from mosques and tourist sites. It's not a time to visit St. Sophia in Istanbul or the pyramids in Egypt. Limit your circulation on Friday during midday prayers. I probably wouldn't go into souks. That's where fundamentalists feel comfortable. I think if I absolutely had to go shopping, I'd stick to hotels or malls associated with hotels.''Mr. Ackerman added: ''Vary your route to work. Keep away from the watering holes of the expatriate community -- they're a potential target. Have meals in your hotel restaurant -- or to be really safe, order from room service.''Scanning the globe, the security company notes that two Muslim countries, Malaysia and Indonesia, are an exception to the threat of violence. ''The problem may be different in Southeast Asia,'' Mr. Ackerman said. ''It's traditionally a fairly safe area for travelers on the beaten track. But with their economies in turmoil, we'll probably see an uptick in street and other types of crime.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/21/business/first-bank-system-to-buy-us-bancorp-of-oregon.html?ref=usbancorp">First Bank System to Buy U.S. Bancorp of Oregon<date>Published: March 21, 1997</date><text>First Bank System appears to have finally reached the Pacific. The acquisitive Minneapolis banking company, which tried unsuccessfully a year ago to buy the First Interstate Bancorporation of Los Angeles, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy U.S. Bancorp of Portland, Ore., for $9 billion in stock.First Bank, which will assume the U.S. Bancorp name though it will keep its Minnesota headquarters, will become the nation's 14th-largest banking company, with $70 billion in assets. It will serve 17 Midwestern and Northwestern states, with the largest share of deposits of any bank in Idaho, North Dakota and Oregon. It will rank second in Colorado, Minnesota and Nebraska.Each U.S. Bancorp share will be exchanged for 0.755 share of First Bank -- valued on Wednesday at $59.08, a 22 percent premium over U.S. Bancorp's closing stock price.As is usual after mergers are announced, the shares of the acquiring company, First Bank, fell yesterday -- by $2.75, to $75.50. The shares of U.S. Bancorp jumped $6.875, to $55.125. The deal was reported yesterday in The Wall Street Journal.First Bank agreed to pay stock worth 3.4 times U.S. Bancorp's book value, a phenomenally high price for a bank. The average price last year was 1.9 times book value. Nonetheless, First Bank said it would increase its earnings per share by the middle of next year.''They paid a full price but got something that was worth a fortune,'' said Thomas Hanley, a bank analyst with UBS Securities. ''God isn't going to make another dominant bank franchise in the Northwest.''The merger will eliminate 4,000 jobs, mostly in Portland, as administrative functions are combined. Although the companies have few overlapping territories, First Bank still plans to close U.S. Bancorp branches to encourage customers to do business by telephone and automated teller machines.As a result, it estimated that it would be able to cut $340 million in annual expenses, about 28 percent of U.S. Bancorp's total, an unusually high level for such a merger.First Bank said it would take a pretax charge to earnings of $625 million in the second quarter to cover severance and other merger costs. Analysts said this was higher than typical because of above average severance payments.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/28/business/u-s-bancorp-to-buy-california-bank-for-35-million.html?ref=usbancorp">U. S. BANCORP TO BUY CALIFORNIA BANK FOR $35 MILLION<date>Published: December 28, 1996</date><text>U. S. Bancorp agreed to buy Business and Professional Bank for $35 million in cash as the bank continued to expand in California. U. S. Bancorp plans to slash costs as it takes over Business and Professional, closing three of the bank's four branches. Customers will be absorbed by U. S. Bancorp's California unit, U. S. Bank of California. U. S. Bancorp would pay $18 a share for Business and Professional stock, roughly 14 percent above trading prices before the purchase was announced. Business and Professional shares rose 62.5 cents, to $15.75. Trading was halted shortly before the announcement. U. S. Bancorp shares rose 25 cents, to $45.875.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/13/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-buy-california-bancshares.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS;U.S. BANCORP TO BUY CALIFORNIA BANCSHARES<date>Published: February 13, 1996</date><text>U.S. Bancorp has signed an agreement to acquire a California Bancshares Inc. of San Ramon, Calif., for $327 million, the companies announced yesterday. Under the acquisition agreement, each share of California Bancshares common stock will be converted into 0.95 share of U.S. Bancorp common stock. U.S. Bancorp, which is based in Portland, Ore., will add the 36 California Bancshares branches to its U.S. Bank of California operations. U.S. Bancorp is one of the 30 largest bank holding companies in the nation, with assets of about $32 billion. In Nasdaq trading yesterday, shares of U.S. Bancorp fell $1.313, to $32.938, while California Bancshares jumped $2.563, to $30.313.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/28/business/company-news-us-bancorp-completes-purchase-of-west-one.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS;U.S. BANCORP COMPLETES PURCHASE OF WEST ONE<date>Published: December 28, 1995</date><text>U.S. Bancorp Inc. said yesterday that it had completed its $1.8 billion purchase of West One Bancorp, creating one of the largest banks in the Northwest. U.S. Bancorp, based in Portland, Ore., paid 1.47 shares of its own stock for each share of West One, based in Boise, Idaho. The acquisition created a bank holding company with nearly 600 branches and $30 billion in assets. The Federal Reserve approved the transaction this month, after U.S. Bancorp agreed to sell 27 bank offices in Washington and Oregon. U.S. Bancorp's shares fell $2.25 yesterday, to $33.75, in heaving Nasdaq trading.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/12/05/business/company-news-first-hawaiian-to-buy-30-banks-in-northwest.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS;FIRST HAWAIIAN TO BUY 30 BANKS IN NORTHWEST<date>Published: December 05, 1995</date><text>First Hawaiian Inc. agreed yesterday to acquire 30 bank branches in the Pacific Northwest that U.S. Bancorp and West One Bancorp are shedding in connection with their proposed merger. First Hawaiian said it would acquire about $720 million in total deposits, for which it would pay a 5.25 percent premium, or about $38 million, and about $457 million in loans, plus other assets, at book value. First Hawaiian, based in Honolulu, said the deal includes 25 bank branches in Oregon, 4 in Washington and 1 in Idaho -- all but 1 of the 31 branches included in the original divestiture package.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/09/business/purchase-by-us-bancorp-to-create-northwest-giant.html?ref=usbancorp">Purchase by U.S. Bancorp To Create Northwest Giant<date>Published: May 09, 1995</date><text>The U.S. Bancorp said today that it would acquire West One Bancorp of Idaho in a $1.6 billion deal that will create a banking powerhouse in the Northwest.The marriage would create a regional bank based in Portland, Ore., with $30 billion in assets, $21 billion in deposits and a market capitalization of more than $4 billion, which would place it among the 30 largest banking organizations in the country."We're interested in growing this company and expanding the network of services we provide," said Gerry Cameron, chairman of U.S. Bancorp, who would remain chairman of the merged company.Mr. Cameron said he expected the deal, which has been approved by the directors of both institutions, to produce at least $84 million in savings, most of it next year.The merger would mean the elimination of 1,100 jobs, or 7.5 percent of the banks' combined work forces, which would mainly come from duplicated branch offices and consolidation of the two head offices, in Portland and in Boise, Idaho.The cuts would occur on top of nearly two years of streamlining at U.S. Bancorp, which has slashed 24 percent of its work force through layoffs and sales of noncore subsidiaries.Under the merger agreement, each share of West One, which is based in Boise, will be exchanged for 1.47 shares of U.S. Bancorp, based in Portland. West One's stock climbed $1.375 today, closing at $33.50 in Nasdaq trading. But shares of U.S. Bancorp fell $2.125, to $24.625, also on Nasdaq."They saw an opportunity to really enhance their franchise down the road, cement their position in Washington and Oregon and get into Idaho, which they've been largely closed out of," Jim Bradshaw, an analyst with Pacific Crest, said. "Obviously the big cherry is Idaho."The merger would make U.S. Bancorp the No. 1 bank in Idaho, where it had only a token presence. "U.S. Bancorp is the logical merger partner for West One," Daniel Nelson, West One chairman, said.Steven Schroll, an analyst at Piper Jaffray, said that U.S. Bancorp was able to offer a relatively high price because the company's stock had risen about 20 percent this year, giving it the "currency" to make the all-stock deal.Mr. Nelson would be president and chief operating officer of the new company. The agreement also provides for him to succeed Mr. Cameron as chief executive in about three years, when Mr. Cameron would retire.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/03/30/business/company-news-mellon-bank-getting-us-bancorp-s-aaa-credit-cards.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; MELLON BANK GETTING U.S. BANCORP'S A.A.A. CREDIT CARDS<date>Published: March 30, 1995</date><text>The Mellon Bank Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire U.S. Bancorp's credit card portfolio, which it offers to American Automobile Association members. Terms were not disclosed. U.S. Bancorp's A.A.A. portfolio includes about 480,000 accounts and about $230 million in money currently owed. U.S. Bancorp, based in Portland, Ore., said it would retain its credit card portfolio of about $500 million that was unrelated to A.A.A. The stock of Mellon, based in Pittsburgh, climbed $1.25, to $41 a share, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/09/business/company-news-accord-is-reached-with-us-bancorp-of-portland.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; ACCORD IS REACHED WITH U.S. BANCORP OF PORTLAND<date>Published: July 09, 1994</date><text>The Mellon Bank Corporation said yesterday that it had agreed to acquire 50 mortgage offices and $3.6 billion in loan servicing from U.S. Bancorp of Portland, Ore., for about $75 million in cash. The purchase will expand Mellon's mortgage loan operations from 27 offices mostly in the Northeast to 77 offices in 21 states in the Northeast, Rockies and Pacific Northwest. It will also expand Mellon's mortgage servicing portfolio to $27.4 million. U.S. Bancorp said it will realize a pretax gain of $50 million in the third quarter from the sale. U.S. Bancorp's shares rose 25 cents, to $26, in Nasdaq trading yesterday, while Mellon's shares were down 75 cents, to $56.375 yesterday, in Big Board trading.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/20/business/company-news-chairman-of-us-bancorp-steps-down.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; CHAIRMAN OF U.S. BANCORP STEPS DOWN<date>Published: April 20, 1994</date><text>The chairman of U.S. Bancorp, Roger L. Breezley, resigned yesterday. He will be succeeded by Gerry B. Cameron, the chief executive. The company, based in Portland, Ore., also said it planned to buy back up to six million shares to finance the company's 1993 stock incentive plan and for other corporate purposes. The company has about 99.7 million shares outstanding. Mr. Breezley, 56, will remain on the board. He relinquished the chief executive's post in January, the company said.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/03/17/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-trim-its-staff-by-10.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. Bancorp to Trim Its Staff by 10%<date>Published: March 17, 1994</date><text>In a move that its chief executive said was being taken in hopes of averting a takeover, U.S. Bancorp, the largest banking company based in the Northwest, said today that it would cut 10 percent of its work force, or 1,400 jobs, in six months, despite record profits.In a news conference at the company's headquarters here, Gerry B. Cameron, the chief executive of the banking company, announced a sweeping plan intended to improve the company's efficiency. He said he hoped the cuts would convince Wall Street to raise the value of the company's stock enough to dissuade any hostile takeover efforts. Mr. Cameron said it was the company's policy not to comment on takeover rumors.Shares of U.S. Bancorp closed unchanged, at $25.75, in Nasdaq trading today."If Wall Street sees the company do something about cost structure, they will respond favorably," Mr. Cameron said. "They are entitled to wait and see, however."Mr. Cameron said the company was spending too much to earn money. He said its expense ratio was 65.7 percent, and he intended to get it below 63 percent this year, and ultimately below 60 percent. Cost-Cutting PressureRegional banking firms have been under pressure to cut costs. The move follows an announcement last week by Fleet Financial Group Inc., the largest banking company in New England, that it would eliminate 5,500 of its 27,500 jobs to produce $350 million in "sustainable profit improvements."U.S. Bancorp is the last independent banking company in the Northwest, with assets of $21.4 billion as of Dec. 31. It is one of the 35 largest bank holding companies in the United States, with 420 branches in Oregon, Washington, California, Nevada, Idaho and Canada.Mr. Cameron said the staff reductions were intended to make the stock "less visible" to any other company that might want to move into the Northwest. He said if the value of the stock were higher, such a company would be "less inclined to pay a premium for it." If U.S. Bancorp were taken over, he said, the acquiring company would make the cuts he is making. A $100 Million ChargeU.S. Bancorp is taking a charge of $100 million against its first-quarter earnings to make the staff reductions. The company began restricting external hirings in February.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/10/27/business/company-news-visa-international-is-set-to-replace-top-officer.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; Visa International Is Set To Replace Top Officer<date>Published: October 27, 1993</date><text>The longtime chief executive of Visa International, Charles Russell, will announce today that he is resigning from the credit card organization. He will be replaced by Edmund P. Jensen, a vice chairman of U.S. Bancorp in Portland, Ore.News of the change, which was not expected, was distributed by Visa by facsimile to its member banks late last night. The board of Visa is meeting in Buhl, Germany.Several executives close to Visa said yesterday that the Visa board had grown increasingly frustrated with Mr. Russell and had pressured him to step aside. A spokesman for Visa, which is based in San Mateo, Calif., declined to comment. But Visa has scheduled a news conference in Frankfurt for this morning.Visa is the leading brand of credit card in the world, but the organization, which is a nonprofit association of banks, has been beset by internal strife, largely as a result of increased competition.In August, Visa abruptly fired H. Robert Heller, the president of its United States region, and replaced him with Carl F. Pascarella, who had run the Asian operation. Hurt by NewcomersLarge Visa card issuers like Citibank and Chase Manhattan, have been hurt by newcomers like A.T.&amp; T., General Motors and the Discover card, which was recently spun off by Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company. In the United States, Visa has lost market share to Mastercard International.The large banks on the Visa board have been frustrated that Mr. Russell and the management of Visa have been more interested in the organization's computer systems than in updating its marketing, credit card executives said.In 1991 the board stripped Mr. Russell of the responsibility for the United States, leaving him only with his position at the parent international organization. Since then, he has fought with Mr. Heller to regain control of the domestic activities, according to people close to Visa. Joined in 1971Mr. Russell joined National Bankamericard, the predecessor of Visa, in 1971, soon after it was founded, in the operations area. He was named chief executive of Visa International and Visa USA in May 1984.Mr. Jensen, 56, is one of two executives who report to the chairman of U.S. Bancorp, Roger L. Breezley, but because Mr. Breezley is only 55, Mr. Jensen's chances of succeeding him were limited.At U.S. Bancorp, Mr. Jensen is responsible for strategic planning, especially the bank's rapid expansion through acquisitions in Washington, California and Nevada, and oversees its securities and credit card units. U.S. Bankcorp has issued credit cards jointly with other organizations, including U S West and the Automobile Association of America.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/04/15/business/company-news-us-bancorp-and-u-s-west-to-offer-visa-card.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. BANCORP AND U S WEST TO OFFER VISA CARD<date>Published: April 15, 1993</date><text>U.S. Bancorp, the largest bank holding company in the Northwest, and U S West, the Denver-based telecommunications provider, said yesterday that they would jointly offer a Visa credit card beginning May 10. The agreement gives U.S. Bancorp access to nearly 10 million households and businesses served by U S West in 14 western states. They estimated the U S West Visa would attract one million new accounts in the next five years.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/02/27/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-buy-branches.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. Bancorp To Buy Branches<date>Published: February 27, 1992</date><text>United States Bancorp, a bank holding company based in Portland, Ore., said it had agreed to acquire the Northern California and Nevada operations that the BankAmerica Corporation and the Security Pacific Corporation were divesting themselves of because of their planned merger. The deal calls for a cash purchase of about $70 million.The California properties include 2 Bank of America branches and 18 Security Pacific offices, with total deposits of about $750 million. The deal also includes Bank of America Nevada, with 21 branches, plus 8 Security Pacific outlets in Nevada, with about $830 million in deposits.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/21/business/business-people-seattle-bank-ending-its-family-ownership.html?ref=usbancorp">BUSINESS PEOPLE; Seattle Bank Ending Its Family Ownership<date>Published: May 21, 1987</date><text>The Peoples Bancorporation of Seattle has been controlled by the Green family for three generations. As other banks in Seattle were being bought by large California banks, Peoples proudly proclaimed its local ownership.But local ownership is now coming to an end. On Tuesday, Peoples announced it had agreed to be acquired by U.S. Bancorp of Oregon in a stock transaction valued at about $275 million.Joshua Green 3d, the chairman and chief executive of Peoples, said the bank was not abandoning its region. Its merger with a conservative Oregon bank, rather than one from Southern California, is ''simply a reinvestment in banking in the Northwest,'' he said.Mr. Green, who has voting rights for the 40 percent of Peoples stock controlled by his family, will emerge from the merger as U.S. Bancorp's largest shareholder, with control of 10 percent of the shares.He will become a vice chairman and a director of U.S. Bancorp. He will also become chairman and chief executive of U.S. Bank of Washington, which will be a combination of Peoples and another bank, Old National Bancorp of Spokane, that was also recently purchased by U.S. Bancorp. The new bank will become the third largest in Washington, with assets of more than $4 billion.Mr. Green, who is 50, said the combination of three banks would provide coverage of the three major regions in the Northwest - Seattle, Spokane and Portland. Indeed, he said, for three generations the Green family has harbored desires to merge with Old National in Spokane, though a deal could never be worked out.The merger would also allow Peoples to compete better with Seafirst, Rainier and First Interstate of Washington, all of which are owned by huge banks elsewhere.Banking is in Mr. Green's family. His great-grandfather owned a bank in Jackson, Miss. Mr. Green's grandfather, Joshua Green, a big shipping executive, bought what became Peoples Bank in 1926, when he was in his 50's, and stayed active in management until he was 102. The person he hired as president of the bank was to become Mr. Green's other grandfather. Mr. Green's father, Joshua Green Jr., ran the bank from the 1940's to the 1970's.The current Mr. Green, who is known as Jay, received a degree in English from Harvard and worked briefly at Citicorp. He began work at Peoples in 1960 in the trust department, rising to become chief executive in 1977.Mr. Green's boss at U.S. Bancorp will probably be Roger L. Breezley, the chief operating officer, who is likely to become chief executive later this year. John A. Elorriaga, the current chairman and chief executive of U.S. Bancorp, is set to retire in October.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/20/business/company-news-us-bancorp-to-buy-peoples.html?ref=usbancorp">COMPANY NEWS; U.S. Bancorp To Buy Peoples<date>Published: May 20, 1987</date><text>The U.S. Bancorp of Portland, Ore., said it had agreed to acquire the Peoples Ban Corp of Seattle in a stock transaction valued at about $275 million. Under the terms of the definitive agreement, U.S. Bancorp will issue 2.6 new shares of its common stock for each of Peoples' 3.8 million shares outstanding.Based on U.S. Bancorp's closing stock price of $27.75 today, the offer is worth $72.15 per Peoples share. Peoples stock rose $4.50 to $63.25 in over-the-counter trading today. The acquisition will raise U.S. Bancorp's assets to well over $12 billion, making it clearly the largest bank in the Northwest, ahead of the Seafirst Corporation and the Rainier Bancorporation.Peoples Bancorp, with $2.3 billion in assets, had prided itself on its local ownership. Forty percent of its stock is controlled by the prominent Green family of Seattle, which said it would vote its shares in favor of the transaction.</text></article></page><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
