<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Wal-Mart">
  <page index="1">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/08/business/wal-mart-benefits-from-anger-over-banking-fees.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Benefits From Anger Over Banking Fees<date>Published: November 7, 2011</date><text>DICKSON CITY, Pa. — Americans say they are fed up with banks. They are protesting on Wall Street and raising a ruckus over outsize fees. Now there is a surprising beneficiary: Wal-Mart.Geoffrey Cardone, a 26-year-old factory worker, said he dumped his bank account because he felt that he was being nickeled and dimed by fees. His new payday ritual includes a trip to the Wal-Mart here in northeastern Pennsylvania. “It’s cheaper,” said Mr. Cardone, who was charged a flat fee of $3 to cash his paycheck. Many check-cashing stores keep a percentage of the check, which tends to be higher. The Wal-Mart here has a clerk in a brightly painted Money Center near the entrance, like more than 1,000 other Wal-Marts across the country. Customers can cash work and government checks, pay bills, wire money overseas or load money on to a prepaid debit card. At most Wal-Marts without dedicated Money Centers, the financial services are available at the customer service desks or kiosks. Four years ago, Wal-Mart abandoned its plans to obtain a long-sought federal bank charter amid opposition from the banking industry and lawmakers, who feared the huge retailer would drive small bankers out of business and potentially conflate its banking and retail operations. Ever since, Wal-Mart has been quietly building up à la carte financial services, becoming a force among the unbanked and “unhappily banked,” as one Wal-Mart executive put it. Even before the recent outcry against banks, the services had become popular with cash-poor customers, many of whom never had a bank account and found the services more affordable than traditional check-cashing operations. Now newcomers to the ranks of the banking disaffected are helping to swell the numbers, Wal-Mart officials said. The run from banks is happening elsewhere, too. In the last four weeks, as anger over debit card fees festered, more than 650,000 customers signed up for credit unions, according to the Credit Union National Association. The association was still tallying how many additional consumers had signed up on Bank Transfer Day, an initiative on Saturday to abandon traditional banks organized by people associated with Occupy Wall Street. “We have a tremendous opportunity ahead of us, and it’s largely due to what you’re seeing around us happen in the industry,” said Daniel Eckert, the head of Wal-Mart Financial Services. “We’re not a bank, but we can serve a lot of types of functions you would see someone go into a bank for.” Wal-Mart says it has no intention of reviving its plans to become a full-blown bank that could make loans and accept federally insured deposits. But the retailer has obtained bank charters in both Mexico and Canada, leading some bankers to suggest the company is laying similar groundwork in this country. ”It’s the proverbial camel’s nose under the tent,” said Terry J. Jorde, senior executive vice president at the Independent Community Bankers Association. “Once they get in and offer some financial services, they will continue to push for other products.” Wal-Mart said it was simply offering financial products for less than its competitors, much the same way it does for underwear, detergent and milk. Wal-Mart does not produce the financial products, but sells them on behalf of financial firms. In doing so, the retailer is able to avoid financial regulations and, because of its size, offer steep discounts. For instance, it offers prepaid debit cards via the Green Dot Corporation. The cards cost up to $4.95 to buy and $5.95 a month to maintain at other retailers, while at Wal-Mart they cost $3 to buy and $3 a month to maintain. Wal-Mart officials declined to provide details on how much money it makes from financial services, or how many customers it serves. However, company officials and outsiders both said Wal-Mart’s financial products are gaining share. “It is a big focus,” said Tien-tsin Huang, an analyst at J.P. Morgan. “They’ve invested in these Money Centers, and they’ve been very, very successful; they’ve all adopted the low-cost, low-prices model, and I think it’s brought in a lot of traffic that they normally wouldn’t see, meaning the lower-end demographics that typically use check-cashing services at rival stores.” He added, “It’s clearly growing a lot faster than what we normally see for check cashers.” 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/28/opinion/moving-beyond-civil-rights.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Moving Beyond Civil Rights<date>Published: October 27, 2011</date><text>Stanford, Calif.CIVIL rights have transformed American society, and made it fairer and less divided, by outlawing overt racial discrimination and making bigotry socially unacceptable. That success has inspired a host of social groups to press for new civil rights. But civil rights have barely made a dent in today’s most severe and persistent social injustices, such as the disproportionate incarceration of African-Americans, the glass ceiling that blocks career advancement for many women and high unemployment among the elderly; in fact, some of these problems have gotten worse despite civil rights laws intended to address them. Today’s most pressing injustices require comprehensive changes in the practices of the police, schools and employers — not simply responses to individual injuries. It’s tempting to insist that we simply need more of what has worked in the past: more civil rights laws and more lawsuits. Today, Americans think of almost every social injustice as a civil rights issue. The result has been an explosion of new claims; for instance, the number of lawsuits alleging employment discrimination almost tripled between 1991 and 2000. As civil rights have been reshaped in the attempt to serve so many diverse ends, they have become almost infinitely plastic. Consequently, today civil rights are as likely to undermine equality as they are to further it. The most striking example of civil rights gone wrong is the repudiation of school integration: in Brown v. Board of Education (1954) the Equal Protection Clause was read to require desegregation, while in Parents Involved in Community Schools v. Seattle School District No. 1 (2007) it was turned around to prohibit efforts to achieve integration. To be sure, part of the problem is a federal bench that has grown increasingly hostile to civil rights over the past three decades, but that’s unlikely to change. The progressive jurisprudence of the 1960s was an aberration; a reactionary judiciary was the historical norm in American history from Reconstruction through the New Deal. The problem is not simply the judiciary. The attempt to achieve collective justice through individual entitlements is inherently conflicted. Litigation driven by individuals often produces perverse effects. For example, because laws prohibiting age discrimination outlaw mandatory retirement, older executives and professionals who suffer little if any discrimination can extract lucrative “golden handshake” retirement incentives from their employers. But because job seekers rarely sue over the job that got away, those laws don’t address a bigger problem: age discrimination in hiring. Similarly, civil rights intended to help profoundly disabled students don’t work well in cases involving mild learning and emotional disabilities that even experts can’t distinguish from garden-variety eccentricity or poor concentration. As a result poor and minority children tend to be tracked into dead-end remedial or special education classes, while children with similar conditions but wealthier and savvier parents receive one-on-one instruction, immunity from discipline and sometimes even private school paid for at public expense. The recent unsuccessful sex discrimination lawsuit against Wal-Mart demonstrates the inadequacy of the civil rights model. The suit accused Wal-Mart of a nationwide pattern of sex discrimination potentially affecting over a million women. Women were 72 percent of the hourly wage employees from whom Wal-Mart typically selected its managers — but were less than 10 percent of store managers and only 4 percent of district managers. Despite this statistical evidence, the Supreme Court rejected the lawsuit in June, saying there was no evidence of a nationwide policy or coordinated practice of discrimination, since most staffing decisions were left to store and district managers. Statistics can show a pattern of discrimination, but they are not enough to prove that any particular woman was discriminated against. Wal-Mart managers typically used vague criteria like “teamwork” and “integrity” to give promotions. It’s easy for bias to hide out in the fog of subjectivity such decisions entail: how can a plaintiff prove that she had more integrity than the man who got the promotion she deserved? 1 2 Next Page » Richard Thompson Ford, a professor of law at Stanford, is the author of âRights Gone Wrong: How Law Corrupts the Struggle for Equality.â</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/28/business/women-file-new-class-action-bias-case-against-wal-mart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Women File New Class-Action Bias Case Against Wal-Mart<date>Published: October 27, 2011</date><text>Four months after the Supreme Court tossed out their national class-action lawsuit, lawyers representing women who claimed that Wal-Mart Stores had discriminated against them filed a new lawsuit on Thursday that narrowed their claims to the California stores of the retail chain.The lawyers promised an “armada” of other lawsuits in the next six months making discrimination claims in other regions of the country, as opposed to nationwide. “The case we are starting today is the first of many,” said Brad Seligman, one of the lead plaintiff lawyers. He added that the new lawsuits are “what we like to call Wal-Mart 2.0.” In rejecting the earlier lawsuit, the Supreme Court found that the plaintiffs, who had sought back pay for as many as 1.5 million women nationwide, had failed to establish that the legal and factual issues involving all those women had enough in common to be examined as a single class. The lawsuit filed Thursday in the United States District Court for the Northern District of California contends that Wal-Mart’s discriminatory practices on pay and job promotion affected more than 90,000 women currently or formerly employed at Wal-Mart and Sam’s Club stores in four regions in California and neighboring states. Wal-Mart dismissed the latest lawsuit as more of the same. “As we have said all along, these claims are unsuitable for class treatment because the situations of each individual are so different, and because the claims of these five plaintiffs are not representative of the thousands of women who work at Wal-Mart,” said Greg Rossiter, a company spokesman, in an e-mail. Theodore J. Boutrous Jr., a lawyer for Wal-Mart, said, “It’s the same theory, in a different wardrobe, and I don’t think it’s going to work.” He added later in a statement, “These lawyers seem more intent on alleging classes for their publicity value than their legal virtue.” In its June ruling in Dukes v. Wal-Mart, the Supreme Court did not determine whether Wal-Mart had discriminated against any women. Rather, in a 5-4 vote, the court concluded that the lawsuit did not satisfy requirements that the group of people in the class had questions of law or fact in common. Writing for the majority, Justice Antonin Scalia said the case involved “literally millions of employment decisions.” The plaintiffs, he added, were required to point to “some glue holding the alleged reasons for all those decisions together.” Joseph M. Sellers, one of the plaintiffs’ lawyers, said the new lawsuit was specifically tailored to address the Supreme Court’s concerns. He said the plaintiffs were subject to the same decision makers and that there was some sort of overall animus directed at the women. The lawsuit describes Wal-Mart’s California region as being governed by a “good old boy philosophy” where job opportunities were not posted, but were passed along word-of-mouth, usually to men. One California regional vice president, for instance, suggested that women did not seek management positions because of their “family commitments,” the lawsuit says. A California district manager for Sam’s Club said he had paid a female employee less than a male counterpart because the male manager “supports his wife and two kids,” the lawsuit says. The lawsuit suggests that such attitudes were pervasive companywide. At a 2004 meeting of district managers, for instance, Thomas Coughlin, then chief executive of Wal-Mart Stores, told the group that the key to their success was “single focus to get the job done.” “Women tend to be better at information processing,” he said, according to the lawsuit. “Men are better at focus single objective.” The origins of the lawsuit date to 1999 when Stephanie Odle was fired after complaining that she was discriminated against because of her sex. She said she had discovered that a male employee with the same job and less experience was making $23,000 a year more than she was. The lead plaintiff in the case decided by the Supreme Court, Betty Dukes, is also the lead plaintiff in the case filed Thursday.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/21/business/wal-mart-cuts-some-health-care-benefits.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Cuts Some Health Care Benefits<date>Published: October 20, 2011</date><text>After trying to mollify its critics in recent years by offering better health care benefits to its employees, Wal-Mart is substantially rolling back coverage for part-time workers and significantly raising premiums for many full-time staff.Citing rising costs, Wal-Mart, the nation’s largest private employer, told its employees this week that all future part-time employees who work less than 24 hours a week on average will no longer qualify for any of the company’s health insurance plans. In addition, any new employees who average 24 hours to 33 hours a week will no longer be able to include a spouse as part of their health care plan, although children can still be covered. This is a big shift from just a few years ago when Wal-Mart expanded coverage for employees and their families after facing criticism because so many of its 1.4 million workers could not afford or did not qualify for coverage — rendering many of them eligible for Medicaid. Under pressure from states saddled with rising Medicaid costs and from labor unions and community groups, Wal-Mart had agreed to offer part-time employees, even those averaging less than 24 hours a week, health care insurance after a year on the job, shaving a year off the eligibility requirement. Wal-Mart also said that it was offering health plans that cost its employees about $250 a year for family coverage. At the time, the moves were considered a departure from some of its major rivals and large employers, more than half of whom offer no company-sponsored health plan for part-time workers. On Thursday, the company would not say what percentage of its work force was part time or worked fewer than 24 hours a week. Greg Rossiter, a Wal-Mart spokesman, said the decision to deny coverage to new part-time employees resulted from the company’s revamping of its health care offerings in light of rising costs. “Over the last few years, we’ve all seen our health care rates increase and it’s probably not a surprise that this year will be no different,” Mr. Rossiter said. “We made the difficult decision to raise rates that will affect our associates’ medical costs. The decisions made were not easy, but they strike a balance between managing costs and providing quality care and coverage.” The company said the changes were not a result of the new federal health care law. But the higher rates along with steep spikes in premiums for other plans this year are likely to stoke the national debate over the year-old legislation that has pitted President Obama and Democrats against Republicans opposed to the changes. Challenges to the law by several states are now before the Supreme Court. These moves are also occurring in a postrecession period when Wal-Mart has been struggling to regain its footing after months of disappointing or flat sales. And with unemployment still hovering around 9 percent, employers may feel less compelled to offer expansive benefits to people desperate for work. Nationwide, employer-sponsored health premiums are up 9 percent, and increases of 5 percent or more are predicted for next year, with workers shouldering higher burdens on premiums and deductibles. In 2009, Wal-Mart said 52 percent of its employees obtained health coverage through it, but on Thursday it declined to give the percentage. Documents on Wal-Mart’s health and other benefit offerings were obtained by The New York Times from the Organization United for Respect at Walmart, a union-backed group of Wal-Mart employees that is seeking to pressure the company to improve wages and benefits. In Wal-Mart’s 2012 health offerings, premiums will increase for some plans by more than 40 percent, although many of their workers pay relatively low premiums in comparison to more generous plans offered by other employers. But many Wal-Mart employees complain that their low premiums are accompanied by high deductibles that sometimes exceed 20 percent of their annual pay. Wal-Mart’s new health offerings will require many employees who smoke to pay a significant penalty. They will be required to pay an extra $10 to $90 each pay period — $260 to $2,340 a year — if they want health coverage. Several other large employers have begun charging higher premiums to employees who smoke, according to Mercer, a benefits consulting firm. Among the largest employers, about 28 percent vary their premiums based on tobacco use. Mr. Rossiter defended the penalty for smokers, saying, “Tobacco users generally consume about 25 percent more health care services than nontobacco users.” In its health care brochures, Wal-Mart told its employees that diseases caused by tobacco result in $96 billion in extra health care costs nationwide. And it noted that some other prominent companies, including Home Depot, Macy’s and PepsiCo, charge smokers more as part of their health plans. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/10/20/wal-mart-face-south-african-deal-appeal/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Faces Appeal of South African Deal<date>October 20, 2011, 12:42 pm</date><text>Lawyers for the South African government are asking a court to force antitrust regulators to review their approval of Wal-Mart Stores’ $2.4 billion bid for a majority stake in Massmart, Bloomberg News reports. Read more »</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="2">
    <article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/09/28/untapped-and-growing-frontier-markets-beckon/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Untapped and Growing, Frontier Markets Beckon<date>September 28, 2011, 6:42 pm</date><text>  Burdened by slowing consumer spending at home, Wal-Mart Stores sought another jolt to its sales. The world’s biggest retailer turned its eyes to a continent where it has little presence: Africa. Wal-Mart announced last fall that it would seek to buy Massmart, its closest counterpart in sub-Saharan Africa, and this year it won approval to buy half of the retailer for $2.4 billion. Special Section Fall 2011 View all posts Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Special Section Fall 2011 It is the latest company from the economically stagnant developed world to seek growth in perhaps the last untapped area of international commerce. Corporations and investors alike are raising their bets on so-called frontier markets by buying mines in Zimbabwe, leasing airport stores in Uruguay and acquiring lenders in Sri Lanka. While mergers and acquisitions in emerging markets over all have slowed this year from a robust 2010 — they are down 9 percent from the same period a year ago, according to Thomson Reuters data — more and more new markets are being sized up for opportunities by deal makers. “You’ve got high growth rates and relatively large populations that are underserviced,” said Colin Coleman, the head of Goldman Sachs’s sub-Saharan Africa team. “That’s what’s driving a lot of institutional and private equity investments.” The traditional risks, like capricious or corrupt local governments and sudden eruptions of violence, are still present in many places. Billions of dollars’ worth of investments in the Middle East suffered this year as the Arab Spring revolutions swept through Libya, Tunisia and Egypt. “The concept of airtight doesn’t exist in these markets,” said Anthony Armstrong, co-head of Americas mergers and acquisitions at Credit Suisse. “You can never control it completely, and you don’t know what you don’t know.” But as many of these countries develop, outside investors are seeking to harness the growth of middle classes. While in developed economies the middle class is well established, populations in these countries are growing wealthier and more sophisticated and are demanding a wider array of luxuries, like cellphones and clothing. That was the thinking of Wal-Mart last year. Having suffered several consecutive quarters of falling same-store sales, the retailer thought again of bolstering its one area of growth, its international operations. Wal-Mart already is in China and South America. To help round out its portfolio, the company looked to Massmart, a retailing giant with stores in 13 sub-Saharan countries. While the bulk of its Marko warehouse stores and Builders Warehouses are in relatively developed South Africa, Massmart also has beachheads in countries like Botswana, Nigeria and Uganda. “South Africa presents a compelling growth opportunity for Wal-Mart and offers a platform for growth and expansion in other African countries,” Andy Bond, Wal-Mart’s top executive for Africa, said at the time of the company’s initial Massmart offer. Bankers, lawyers and consultants that advise companies like Wal-Mart are racing to expand their presence in these regions, with the expectation that they are entering the next Brazil or China. JPMorgan Chase, for instance, opened an affiliate in Dhaka, Bangladesh, last fall. Deal makers say that some countries remain highly risky, including Zimbabwe and Venezuela. But huge pools of resources like oil and minerals are like the sirens’ song to companies and investors. Those types of riches prompted the Essar Group, an Indian conglomerate, to form a natural resources joint venture with the Zimbabwe government. The $750 million deal was meant to revive the ailing Zimbabwe Iron and Steel Company, splitting it into a mining company and a steel maker. Yet it requires working with Robert Mugabe, a leader whose takeover of Zimbabwe’s farms a decade ago decimated the country’s economy and drove out foreign investors. Essar was apparently undaunted. “We view this union as a long-term partnership with Zimbabwe and its people,” Ravi Ruia, Essar’s vice chairman, said in a statement after the deal. The company did not respond to requests for comment. Such forays into precarious political climates don’t always end well. African Barrick Gold learned a tough lesson with a gold mine it bought in Tanzania. Local miners have repeatedly tried to steal scraps of gold, leading to bloody conflicts with the company’s security forces and local police officers. In May, five people were killed by police forces when a gang of several hundred people tried to storm the mine with machetes and stones. Local knowledge, experts say, is irreplaceable. Companies and investors often work with governments or other local business specialists before making an entry. The beverage giant SABMiller is among the most active companies in the world when it comes to tapping frontier markets. Having operated in the tumult of South African apartheid, the company was accustomed to operating in uncertain, atypical conditions, from sub-Saharan Africa to Latin America. That has helped shape its philosophy when approaching new acquisitions or business ventures. In 2009, SABMiller executives flew to southern Sudan, which was still healing from civil war, to negotiate the opening of a new plant. But instead of sitting around a conference table signing deeds, the officials followed local custom. They bought a tractor for the community and promised to pay royalties and provide clean water. They also slaughtered a cow. “One can’t just send in a bunch of guys with briefcases to try and do deals,” said Mark Bowman, managing director of SABMiller’s Africa business. “You can’t just buy your way in from the outside. You have to be an insider or know what’s going on to try to create a transaction.” Deciding which countries are worth the risks can be difficult. Many businesses in Venezuela, mostly oil companies, are profitable, but are often forced to reinvest their earnings in the country. And Angola ranks 10th on Transparency International’s 2010 list of the most corrupt countries in the world. But it possesses a significant portion of the continent’s arable uncultivated land. One thing has changed this calculus. Earlier investors often sought to withdraw their investments at the first sign of trouble, but this latest wave of development appears more durable, deal makers say. “There was often a withdrawal of capital from risky places,” said Tihir Sarkar, a partner at the law firm Cleary Gottlieb Steen &amp; Hamilton. “But the difference now is that investors have become a bit more sophisticated, and they are more willing to keep money in.” The education of investors has followed recognition of a pattern in frontier markets. The first deals struck are those related to commodities like oil or metals. As countries grow more advanced, consumer goods companies and media and telecommunications concerns are the next to be scooped up. In August, the Swiss retailer Dufry acquired airport store space in five emerging markets for about $1 billion. The deal gave it 21 shops in airports in Argentina, Uruguay, Ecuador, Armenia and Martinique. And Bharti Airtel, the Indian telecommunications giant, bought Zain Africa for $9 billion last year, bolstering its presence in 15 African countries like Gabon and Burkina Faso. With landlines rare and prohibitively expensive to build and maintain in most of sub-Saharan Africa, cellphones have long been seen as an industry with potentially explosive growth prospects. The deal also highlighted another phenomenon: the so-called BRIC countries of Brazil, Russia, India and China are also hunting for new areas of growth. One class of investors that is also growing is private equity firms. While heavyweights like the Carlyle Group have recently raised Africa-focused funds, many of the longtime players in frontier markets are smaller firms like Helios Capital and Actis. Increasingly, those leading the efforts at these firms are local. They are part of a generation that left their native countries to pursue Ivy League degrees and careers at top Wall Street firms. Helios, for instance, was co-founded by Tope Lawani, a Harvard-educated investor who spent years working at the buyout shop TPG Capital. Helios said earlier this year that it had raised the largest private equity fund ever dedicated to sub-Saharan Africa, about $1 billion.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/23/now-democrats-want-solyndra-backers-to-testify/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Now, Democrats Want Solyndra Backers to Testify<date>September 23, 2011, 1:46 pm</date><text>ReutersBrian Harrison, left, Solyndra’s chief executive, and Bill Stover, its chief financial officer, at a House hearing on Friday. Both declined to testify under the Fifth Amendment. What’s next in the Solyndra hearings? On Friday, two top executives of the bankrupt solar company appeared before a House Energy and Commerce subcommittee but refused to testify, invoking their fifth amendment rights against self-incrimination. The executives were there at the request of the subcommittee’s Democratic minority. (Only the majority party can call the hearing itself.) Attention on the two may have been intended to deflect blame away from the Obama administration. Now the Democrats are asking for testimony from two private equity firms: Argonaut, which represents the interests of George Kaiser, a billionaire oilman who was a fund-raising “bundler” for the Obama presidential campaign, and Madrone, which invests money for the Walton family, heirs to the Wal-Mart fortune and prominent Republican donors. Those two firms, as investors in Solyndra, stepped forward in February with others to provide additional money to the company after the Energy Department loans. Under that deal, they get priority in repayment in the event that Solyndra is liquidated. The Energy Department acquiesced to that, but even some Democrats have expressed doubts about whether that was a good idea. The Republicans have not said publicly how they would respond to the Democrats’ request for testimony from Argonaut or Madrone, but they have asked for copies of communications between the investment firms and the government. In another challenge for the Department of Energy, private-sector kibitzers are piping up with commentaries that run somewhere between “You should have known better” and “I told you so.” In a blog post published on Friday, for example, an analyst at Lux Research, Matt Feinstein, argued that the drop in silicon prices, cited as a reason that Solyndra become uncompetitive, was easy to see coming. Another shoe that may soon drop concerns companies that got “conditional” loan guarantees from the Energy Department but do not yet have money in hand. Fourteen projects had conditional approval, but under the law, the loans must be wrapped up by the end of the fiscal year, which is Sept. 30. On Thursday, FirstSolar, which makes solar cells and builds solar farms, said it had three projects in the pipeline but that one of them, Topaz in California, could not get all the necessary approvals before the deadline. It was pointedly silent about whether the other two could do so. Other projects may also fall by the wayside, especially since the Energy Department may want to take extra care in documenting its new loan decisions. 2:22 p.m. | Updated On Friday, a company that received a conditional commitment for a $275 million loan sent a pleading letter to Cliff Stearns, the Florida Republican who is chairman of the subcommittee that held the Solyndra hearing, and Fred Upton, the chairman of the full committee. The company, SolarCity of San Mateo, Calif., said it was told by the Energy Department that it would not get the loan guarantee after all. “The reason provided was the increased documentation requirements that are the result of the current Congressional investigation into the Solyndra bankruptcy,’’ the company said in its letter to Mr. Stearns. The project is supposed to put solar arrays on top of residential buildings on military bases and employ relatives of active-duty military personnel to do the work. In the letter, SolarCity said that it was using proven technology and that the project would have “very predictable cash flows based on long-term contracts.” 4:11 p.m. | Updated But as the fiscal year winds down, some loan guarantees are squeaking through: on Friday, the Energy Department announced three loans. One is a partial loan guarantee (meaning it guarantees only a percentage of the loan) for three new geothermal plants in Nevada. The loan amount is $350 million and the plants, to be built by Ormat, will supply 113 megawatts. The department announced a partial guarantee on a $170 million loan for a 99-megawatt wind farm in northern New Hampshire to be built by BAIF Granite Holdings and Freshet Wind Energy. And it finalized a $105 million loan guarantee for an add-on to a conventional ethanol plant in Emmetsburg, Iowa. The addition will make ethanol from corn cobs instead of corn kernels. Since there is no commercial-scale production of ethanol now from crop wastes, successful operation would be a major step forward. The federal fiscal year begins on Oct. 1; given the stakes, look for a grim fiscal New Year’s Eve next Friday.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/14/business/wal-mart-to-announce-women-friendly-plans.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart to Announce Women-Friendly Plans<date>Published: September 14, 2011</date><text>Wal-Mart planned to announce on Wednesday new programs aimed at helping women-owned businesses and women workers, as the company continues to deal with the possibility of individual claims of sex discrimination after the Supreme Court threw out a class-action suit by women workers this summer.In an advance draft of the announcement, Wal-Mart said it planned to source a total of $20 billion in products from women-owned businesses in the United States over the next five years, which works out to an average of $4 billion a year, versus the $2.5 billion a year it currently spends, and to double what it buys from women-owned businesses globally by 2016. The company said it would also support training of women in factories and farms that are Wal-Mart suppliers, donate $100 million to causes supporting women’s economic development, and ask its vendors and services firms like ad agencies or public relations firms to increase gender and minority representation on their Wal-Mart accounts. “If you look at retail, the vast majority of our customers are women, and if you look at Wal-Mart, the majority of our associates are women,” said Leslie A. Dach, executive vice president of corporate affairs for Wal-Mart, in an interview. “It makes complete sense for us to really have a focus on how we have the best associates we can, how we help women suppliers succeed and how we engage our communities.” The $5 billion a year that Wal-Mart plans to spend with women-owned businesses would still be a small percentage of Wal-Mart’s overall budget. The $4 billion a year, on average, that Wal-Mart will spend sourcing from women in the United States works out to about 5 percent of the company’s annual operating expenses. “Over the course of the five years, we are going to both have to seek out the businesses that are there, and open ourselves up to that, and also we’re going to help these businesses grow,” he said. “They’ll range from construction to farming to food, and one of the great things about this is we will also improve the assortment of products we sell to people, and help our products become more relevant.” Mr. Dach said the announcement on Wednesday was not in reaction to the class-action suit against Wal-Mart, which charged unfair treatment of women in the workplace; the Supreme Court recently threw out the case. Some of the plaintiffs have said they will still try to sue the company through individual claims. But some critics were quick to fault Wal-Mart’s plans. Janet Shenk, a former A.F.L.-C.I.O. official, said its move to buy more products from women was a way of not dealing with problems. “Once again, Wal-Mart is avoiding every issue that touches on how its products are produced,” said Ms. Shenk, who oversees some corporate grants at the Panta Rhea Foundation, which works to combat corporate influence. “It’s not about who owns the factory. So far as I know, there’s no evidence that factories and businesses owned by women treat their employees better or have better conditions than factories and businesses owned by men.” Yet CARE, a nonprofit development and relief agency, said Wal-Mart support would help advance its work. “The typical woman we work with is a woman working in an apparel factory in, say, Bangladesh,” said Melanie Minzes, senior director for development at CARE. “She is probably illiterate, probably gets sick pretty easily because she doesn’t have much health education. With Wal-Mart’s commitment, we are going to be able to reach tens of thousands of women like her and improve their lives and economic positions. We will be able to teach them to read, how to address common abuses they face and what proper nutrition is, all things that will make her a better, healthier employee.” Wal-Mart has measured the gender and ethnic diversity at law firms that work for it since 2005. In the draft of Wednesday’s announcement, it did not specify what new standards might be. Asked why there were no specifications, Mr. Dach said that “it’s important for us to be realistic about that as we make change — we’re not asking anyone to turn over their work force, but we’re confident that it will help us get results like it did in the legal field.” According to the draft, Wednesday’s announcement will be similar to ones Wal-Mart has made in the past several years outlining goals on locally sourced agriculture, addressing “food deserts” in urban areas and reducing energy use.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/09/business/wal-mart-to-bring-back-layaway.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart to Bring Back Layaway<date>Published: September 8, 2011</date><text>Wal-Mart said on Thursday that it planned to bring back its layaway payment plan for the holidays, an indication that shoppers at the nation’s largest retailer were feeling more and more strapped.Wal-Mart had discontinued layaway in 2006, saying that so many customers were using credit cards or gift cards that the program was obsolete. Now, though, consumers are demanding it, said Duncan Mac Naughton, chief merchandising officer for Wal-Mart’s United States stores. “It just tells us the customer’s still struggling, as they tell us about their concerns with energy prices, housing prices, the job security, that 9.2 percent unemployment — it tells us that this is a fragile economy and the customer needs our help,” Mr. Mac Naughton said. Layaway means that a store sets aside a product and requires customers to pay for it over time, usually charging a small service fee but no interest. With layaway, someone living paycheck to paycheck could potentially afford a more expensive item than otherwise, given the extra time to pay for it. It was a common way to pay for expensive items through much of the 20th century. But as credit cards became popular, layaway dwindled and was mainly used by lower-income consumers who could not qualify for credit cards. That has been changing in the last couple of years. As the recession hit and the recovery dragged on, some Wal-Mart competitors have offered layaway. Toys “R” Us started offering layaway on expensive items in 2009, while Sears brought back layaway in 2008 after a long hiatus. (Sears Holdings’ Kmart division has offered layaway for decades.) The other retailers’ jump on layaway puts Wal-Mart into the unusual position of being a holiday season follower. Because of its size, it often sets the standards that other stores follow over the holidays, whether that is pricing on toys or its offer last year of free shipping on hundreds of online items. Now, with nine consecutive quarters of declining same-store sales in the United States, and having said that improving those sales is a central focus, Wal-Mart is struggling to figure out how to get its consumers to spend. Executives have said throughout the year that shoppers are increasingly shunning credit and paying with cash, and are running out of money at the end of the month. Wal-Mart’s revival of layaway indicates it does not expect consumers to feel flush anytime soon. The layaway program will “alleviate the pressures they may have in their homes,” Mr. Mac Naughton said. “We think this is an opportunity for a cash-paying customer to create a payment program on their own time.” Wal-Mart is limiting the program’s scope and time frame. Only toys and electronics may be paid for on layaway, starting Oct. 17 and ending Dec. 16. Each item must cost $15 or more, and the total layaway purchase must be $50 or more. There is a $5 service fee, and a 10 percent down payment is required. Other retailers have similar conditions: Sears has a $5 service fee and a 20 percent down payment, while Toys “R” Us has a $10 service fee and 20 percent down payment. On a site where shoppers can offer feedback to Wal-Mart, layaway has been one of the more popular suggestions. A commenter by the name of PamS wrote that even when she set aside money for gifts, “the saved money usually gets used for some other unexpected bill or what not; whereas if I was able to do layaway I feel I could better budget and especially for special holidays.” “I know for some the idea of layaway probably seems silly; but for those of us on very fixed and limited incomes, it does help,” she wrote. Another commenter, SueH, had a similar view. “I can’t get many things now either,” she wrote. “I don’t make enough money to pay all at one time. I can’t do extra for my grandkids. Please bring back layaway.” Other shoppers said they were going to competitors because of their layaway programs. “You would think in this economy every store would have it! During Christmas I have to shop at Kmart cause of the layaway,” wrote a commenter under the name “wishing” on a West Virginia forum. Mr. Mac Naughton also outlined other plans for the holiday season. Holiday merchandise will hit stores in mid-October, about two weeks earlier than usual, he said. And Wal-Mart will put a number of toys on sale for $15 starting Monday, including some Lego play sets and Princess Toddler dolls from Disney.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/18/business/target-and-other-retailers-report-higher-earnings.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Target and Other Retailers Report Higher Earnings<date>Published: August 17, 2011</date><text>The Target Corporation reported a bigger-than-expected increase in quarterly profit on Wednesday and forecast a more profitable year than analysts had been anticipating, as its credit card business continued to grow and sales heated up with the summer weather.Retail results were highlighting a split between middle- and upper-income shoppers, who might be waiting a bit before they buy, versus the unemployed and low-income workers struggling to make ends meet. “While optimism at all income levels has improved since the recession, wealthy households continue to be the most optimistic,” Kathryn Tesija, Target’s executive vice president for merchandising, said during a conference call. “The 20 percent of households with the highest incomes are shopping more often and spending more, while the other 80 percent have been cutting trips and spending less,” Ms. Tesija said about retailers’ experience in general. Target’s shoppers are buying closer to when they need things, so the company said it was a bit too early to fully judge August sales, which include back-to-school purchases. August sales have been within Target’s forecast for an increase of about 5 percent, though slightly below the increases in June and July, the chief financial officer, Douglas Scovanner said. Target’s same-store sales rose 4.5 percent in June, 4.1 percent in July and 3.9 percent in the second quarter. Target was not the only retailer reporting better-than-expected results. Wal-Mart Stores said Tuesday that its profit rose more than expected. On Wednesday, retailers such as BJ’s Wholesale Club and the office-supply store Staples also reported results that surpassed expectations. Staples’ chief executive, Ronald L. Sargent, said he did not see a double-dip recession in the nation’s economy, though the country is “probably more likely to stay in economic purgatory for a while longer.” Stock in Staples, which is based in Framingham, Mass., was flat, as was BJ’s Wholesale, which is based in Westborough, Mass. The Abercrombie &amp; Fitch Company’s quarter was also better than anticipated, but it warned of troubles as it enters “a period of greater uncertainty,” and its shares tumbled. Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, based in New Albany, Ohio, fell $6.15, to $64.87. Target’s move to add groceries to more stores has raised sales but pressured profitability because food carries lower margins than merchandise like apparel. Still, the second-quarter gross margin decline was not too steep. Gross margin dipped to 31.6 percent from 32 percent. Target earned $704 million, or $1.03 a share, up from $679 million, or 92 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts, on average, had expected Target to earn 97 cents a share. Sales in the period, which ended July 30 and was the second quarter of Target’s fiscal year, increased 5.1 percent to $15.9 billion. Stock in Target, which is based in Minneapolis, rose $1.18, to $50.55 a share.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="3">
    <article index="1" href="http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/05/as-it-campaigns-to-build-in-the-city-wal-mart-donates-4-million/?ref=walmartstoresinc">As It Campaigns to Build in the City, Wal-Mart Donates $4 Million<date>July 5, 2011, 4:32 pm</date><text>He called Wal-Mart “one of the great corporate citizens in this country.” He praised its efforts to conduct background checks before selling guns. He flatly rebuffed suggestions that the company was killing jobs. Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg took on the role of ardent defender of big-box America on Tuesday at a news conference announcing a $4 million donation by Wal-Mart to a city program that offers summer jobs to young people. With Wal-Mart in the midst of an aggressive campaign to open its first store in New York City, was the donation simply a coincidence? Michelle Gilliard, a representative for the company’s philanthropic division, said the money was part of an effort to help children across the country. But when reporters pressed further, it was Mr. Bloomberg who took over as spokesman. “You’re telling me that your company’s philanthropy doesn’t look to see what is good for your company?” the mayor shot back at a reporter. When a reporter tried to follow up with Ms. Gilliard, Mr. Bloomberg grew impatient, saying: “She answered it. You’re just not listening.” Mr. Bloomberg, a longtime defender of free-market principles, brushed aside a question about whether it was coincidental that the news conference, held at a recreation center in Brownsville, Brooklyn, was just miles from one of the company’s potential construction sites. “This is city is not in the business of promoting any more than it is in the business of discriminating against stores,” he said. Wal-Mart has encountered opposition from some City Council members and labor advocates, who have criticized its hiring practices and expressed concern that its presence in New York would hurt small businesses. But the company’s donation, which will help finance some 3,400 jobs, seemed to help win over some skeptics. The Brooklyn borough president, Marty Markowitz, who has expressed concern about Wal-Mart’s expansion in the past, praised the company at Tuesday’s announcement. “This is a good, major first step,” he said.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/03/opinion/lweb03walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Giving Credit to Wal-Mart<date>Published: July 1, 2011</date><text>To the Editor: Re “Wal-Mart’s Authoritarian Culture,” by Nelson Lichtenstein (Op-Ed, June 22): Wal-Mart has the right to follow whatever corporate policies it deems appropriate to fit its extraordinarily successful business model. The company is tough on suppliers and has a very successful distribution system, and from the efficiencies of both it passes along substantial savings to its customer base. And it provides some 1.4 million jobs for both men and women throughout the United States. Wal-Mart didn’t get to be the world’s No. 1 corporation by standing still! You have a choice of where to work, and if you don’t want to work at Wal-Mart, you don’t have to. As a professor of business and marketing, I beg to differ with Mr. Lichtenstein on his assumptions and conclusions. Sure, employees at some point have to make tough choices during their working lifetime — and some may well involve balancing the demands of work and family, especially during this current economic downturn. A corporation cannot run its business model strictly around the family. Certainly Wal-Mart is not the only company with aspiring lower-level managers who eventually get promoted and have to relocate. How about we give Wal-Mart some credit once in a while rather than always trying to put a “Target” on its back. GEORGE R. COOK Rochester, June 23, 2011</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/28/opinion/l28walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">‘The Wal-Mart I Know’: An Executive’s Story<date>Published: June 27, 2011</date><text>To the Editor: Re “Wal-Mart Wins. Workers Lose” (editorial, June 21): I’m amazed by the negative and false assumptions I’ve seen about Wal-Mart since the Supreme Court’s decision in the class action lawsuit on June 20. The Wal-Mart I know has offered a world of opportunity to me and countless other women. When I started at Wal-Mart in 1992 in California, I rose from an hourly trainee to salaried store manager in less than four years. Soon I was asked to manage a larger store, where at one time four of my six assistant managers were women. All of this happened at the same time as the accusations in the lawsuit. Anyone who believes she has a claim deserves her day in court, and the three plaintiffs can now have their individual cases heard on their merits. But as the court ruled, the class should never have been certified because the experiences that individual women had working at Wal-Mart were too different. The way the case was filed, I would technically have been a plaintiff in the case. My experience has been profoundly different from those of the plaintiffs, which is exactly why the court rejected their attempt to sue Wal-Mart on my behalf. The Supreme Court made the right decision. GISEL RUIZ Bentonville, Ark., June 24, 2011 The writer is executive vice president, People Division, at Walmart U.S.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/23/opinion/l23walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Fallout From the Wal-Mart Ruling<date>Published: June 22, 2011</date><text>To the Editor:Your June 21 editorial “Wal-Mart Wins. Workers Lose” should have been titled “Lawyers Lose. America Wins.” The travesty that has allowed class action law firms to form a class effortlessly and commence a lawsuit has placed all of us at the mercy of large judgments, the primary beneficiary of which is often the law firm. The Supreme Court’s decision in the Wal-Mart case levels the playing field and requires law firms to invest meaningful capital to create an acceptable class and bring suit. I hope that it will discourage the often baseless legal claims and allow courts and lawyers to focus on bona fide issues. Now if only we could get Congress to address the malpractice and other misused tort proceedings that are inflating our medical costs. That would be a great class action suit — all of us against the trial lawyers. ALAN H. SCHECHTER Fresh Meadows, Queens, June 21, 2011 To the Editor: The Supreme Court’s conservative majority has once again chipped away at longstanding legal precedent to ensure an individual’s right to seek redress against large organizations with vastly more resources, financial and otherwise. This court’s shortsighted reasoning takes away yet one more stone from David in his battle against the corporate Goliaths that the court seems so intent on protecting the rights of, at the expense of the individual. It is time for Congress to step into this fray and enact laws to counterbalance the skewed view that this current court holds with respect to the legal rights of the people. LAWRENCE A. ABEL San Diego, June 21, 2011 The writer is a lawyer. To the Editor: Wal-Mart has strict policies against sexual discrimination and disciplinary procedures for legitimate cases of discrimination. Promotion decisions are left to store managers’ discretion, and the assertion that all managers nationwide simultaneously violated corporate policy is absurd. Of 1.5 million women whom Wal-Mart has employed since 1998, 120 sexual discrimination affidavits were filed as part of the lawsuit. That’s roughly 1 discrimination case for every 12,500 female employees, as Justice Antonin Scalia noted. That sample hardly represents a “class” of Wal-Mart’s women employees. The facts speak for themselves. The Supreme Court made the right call. MEGAN ROBERTS Arlington, Va., June 22, 2011 To the Editor: When much of the general culture sees women as less competent and committed workers, employers must assume that some supervisors likely share this view and take proactive steps to correct it. That’s the “common direction,” to use Justice Antonin Scalia’s term, that was needed and sorely lacking at Wal-Mart (and many other corporations). Such direction includes giving guidance on personnel decisions and monitoring supervisory performance. If the percentage of women promoted, for example, falls far below the percentage employed, top managers should be asking why, analyzing how promotion and pay decisions were made, and rooting out whatever bias they uncover. Few employers today are foolish enough to mandate discrimination. The problem is their failure to recognize and end it. ELLEN BRAVO Milwaukee, June 22, 2011 The writer is director of Family Values @ Work and former director of 9to5.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/22/opinion/22Lichtenstein.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart’s Authoritarian Culture<date>Published: June 21, 2011</date><text>Santa Barbara, Calif.MONDAY’S Supreme Court decision to block a class-action sex-discrimination lawsuit against Wal-Mart was a huge setback for as many as 1.6 million current and former female employees of the world’s largest retailer. But the decision has consequences that range far beyond sex discrimination or the viability of class-action suits. The underlying issue, which the Supreme Court has now ratified, is Wal-Mart’s authoritarian style, by which executives pressure store-level management to squeeze more and more from millions of clerks, stockers and lower-tier managers. Indeed, the sex discrimination at Wal-Mart that drove the recent suit is the product not merely of managerial bias and prejudice, but also of a corporate culture and business model that sustains it, rooted in the company’s very beginnings. In the 1950s and ’60s, northwest Arkansas, where Wal-Mart got its start, was poor, white and rural, in the midst of a wave of agricultural mechanization that generated a huge surplus of unskilled workers. To these men and women, the burgeoning chain of discount stores founded by Sam Walton was a godsend. The men might find dignity managing a store instead of a hardscrabble farm, while their wives and daughters could earn pin money clerking for Mr. Sam, as he was known. “The enthusiasm of Wal-Mart associates toward their jobs is one of the company’s greatest assets,” declared the firm’s 1973 annual report. A patriarchal ethos was written into the Wal-Mart DNA. “Welcome Assistant Managers and Wives” read a banner at a 1975 meeting for executive trainees. And that corporate culture — “the single most important element in the continued, remarkable success of Wal-Mart,” asserted Don Soderquist, the company’s chief operating officer in the 1990s — was sustained not only by the hypercentralized managerial control that flowed from the Bentonville, Ark., home office but by the evangelical Protestantism that Mr. Soderquist and other executives encouraged. Wal-Mart attorneys have argued, and the Supreme Court agreed this week, that even if sex discrimination was once part of the company’s culture, it is now ancient history: if any store managers are guilty of bias when it comes to promoting women, they are at odds with corporate policy. Wal-Mart is no longer an Ozark company; it is a cosmopolitan, multinational operation. But that avoids the more essential point, namely that Wal-Mart views low labor costs and a high degree of workplace flexibility as a signal competitive advantage. It is a militantly anti-union company that has been forced to pay hundreds of millions of dollars to current and former employees for violations of state wage and hour laws. In other words, the patriarchy of old has been reconfigured into a more systematically authoritarian structure, one that deploys a communitarian ethos to sustain a high degree of corporate loyalty even as wages and working conditions are put under continual downward pressure — especially in recent years, as Wal-Mart’s same-store sales have declined. Workers of both sexes pay the price, but women, who constitute more than 70 percent of hourly employees, pay more. There are tens of thousands of experienced Wal-Mart women who would like to be promoted to the first managerial rung, salaried assistant store manager. But Wal-Mart makes it impossible for many of them to take that post, because its ruthless management style structures the job itself as one that most women, and especially those with young children or a relative to care for, would find difficult to accept. Why? Because, for all the change that has swept over the company, at the store level there is still a fair amount of the old communal sociability. Recognizing that workers steeped in that culture make poor candidates for assistant managers, who are the front lines in enforcing labor discipline, Wal-Mart insists that almost all workers promoted to the managerial ranks move to a new store, often hundreds of miles away. For young men in a hurry, that’s an inconvenience; for middle-aged women caring for families, this corporate reassignment policy amounts to sex discrimination. True, Wal-Mart is hardly alone in demanding that rising managers sacrifice family life, but few companies make relocation such a fixed policy, and few have employment rolls even a third the size. The obstacles to women’s advancement do not stop there. The workweek for salaried managers is around 50 hours or more, which can surge to 80 or 90 hours a week during holiday seasons. Not unexpectedly, some managers think women with family responsibilities would balk at such demands, and it is hardly to the discredit of thousands of Wal-Mart women that they may be right. There used to be a remedy for this sort of managerial authoritarianism: it was called a union, which bargained over not only wages and pensions but also the kind of qualitative issues, including promotion and transfer policies, that have proved so vexing for non-unionized employees at Wal-Mart and other big retailers. For a time it seemed as if the class-action lawsuit might be a partial substitute. By drastically limiting how a class-action suit can be brought, the Supreme Court leaves millions of service-sector workers with few avenues to escape the grinding work life and limited opportunities that so many now face. Nelson Lichtenstein, a professor of history at the University of California, Santa Barbara, is the author of âThe Retail Revolution: How Wal-Mart Created a Brave New World of Business.â</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="4">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/17/arts/design/alice-walton-on-her-crystal-bridges-museum-of-american-art.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Alice Walton on Her Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art<date>Published: June 16, 2011</date><text>BENTONVILLE, Ark. — The era of the world-class museum built by a single philanthropist in the tradition of Isabella Stewart Gardner, John Pierpont Morgan Jr. and Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney may seem to have passed, but Alice L. Walton is bringing it back.Yet her mission is unlike those of her predecessors, or of more recent art patrons like Ronald S. Lauder and his Neue Galerie. They set out to put great works on display in cultural capitals like New York and Boston. Instead, Ms. Walton’s Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art — the first major institution in 50 years dedicated to the vast spectrum of American art, to be housed in a building more than twice the size of the current Whitney Museum of American Art — seeks to bring high art to middle America here in this town of 35,000 that is best known as the home of Wal-Mart.  Ms. Walton, the daughter of Wal-Mart’s founder, Sam Walton, has worked on the museum for nearly a decade, but has said little about it in public until now. In a recent interview at Town Branch, her family home here, she said she wanted to turn Bentonville into an international destination for art lovers when the museum opens on Nov. 11. At the moment the most significant nearby cultural attractions are two hours away: a museum of Western and American Indian art in Tulsa, Okla., and, in the other direction, the country-music magnet of Branson, Mo. “For years I’ve been thinking about what we could do as a family that could really make a difference in this part of the world,” said Ms. Walton, who is 61. “I thought this is something we desperately need, and what a difference it would have made were it here when I was growing up.” The 201,000-square-foot museum was designed by the Boston architect Moshe Safdie for a site around two ponds on 120 acres of former Walton family land. Named for the nearby Crystal Spring, the museum will display top-flight works by American masters from the Colonial era to the present, with the largest concentrations coming from the 19th and 20th centuries. Although the collection — currently about 600 paintings and sculptures — is still small by the standards of big museums, it is growing at a steady clip. “She has not just been concentrating on what could be perceived as the greatest hits in American art,” said John Wilmerding, an art historian and professor at Princeton University, who has been advising Ms. Walton for seven years and is now on the Crystal Bridges board. “She has collected the work of some of these artists in depth,” quietly amassing substantial bodies of work by figures like Martin Johnson Heade, Stuart Davis, George Bellows and John Singer Sargent. Ms. Walton, who has been an art collector most of her life, turned to buying art specifically for the museum in 2005, resulting in a spending spree that has made her a recognized force in the art market. She has been one of those mysterious anonymous buyers at auctions and at galleries who often pay top dollar and has spent many tens of millions of dollars on works like Gilbert Stuart’s portrait of George Washington from 1797 ($8.1 million), Asher B. Durand’s “Kindred Spirits” from 1849 ($35 million) and Norman Rockwell’s 1943 “Rosie the Riveter” ($4.9 million). She has also bought more recent works, including a Jasper Johns “Alphabets” painting from 1960-62 (priced at $11 million) and a 1985 Warhol silkscreen of Dolly Parton and a 2009 Chuck Close triptych depicting Bill Clinton (prices unknown). (She is hoping that both Ms. Parton and Mr. Clinton, a friend, will attend the opening.) Her museum has commissioned several major site-specific works, including a giant silver tree by Roxy Paine that sits at the entrance and a hypnotic large-scale light installation by James Turrell. (The museum’s director, Don Bacigalupi, recruited nearly two years ago from the Toledo Museum of Art, is a specialist in contemporary art and has been encouraging Ms. Walton to expand the museum’s holdings by living artists.) Museum officials said they were planning for about 250,000 visitors in their first year and expect an annual operating budget of $16 million to $20 million. In addition to the 120 full-time jobs the institution is creating, they said, it will pump millions of tourist dollars into northwest Arkansas. Ms. Walton first started thinking seriously about building an art museum on family land in the late 1990s and brought it up a few times at the meetings the family holds three times a year. She felt she needed the backing of her nieces and nephews, she said, because the land would have eventually become theirs. (Ms. Walton, who is divorced, has no children.) “That decision brewed for a year and a half,” she said in her Arkansas drawl, before there was unanimous agreement. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/15/business/15walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">OUR Walmart Tries a Nonunion Route for Workers<date>Published: June 14, 2011</date><text>After numerous failed attempts to unionize Wal-Mart stores, the nation’s main union for retail workers has decided to try a different approach: it has helped create a new, nonunion group of Wal-Mart employees that intends to press for better pay, benefits and most of all, more respect at work.The group, Organization United for Respect at Walmart, or OUR Walmart for short, says it has quietly signed up thousands of members in recent months, and it is going public this week with a Web site, ourwalmart.org, and a Facebook page. Organizers say they have more than 50 members at some stores, and they hope to soon have tens of thousands of members. Wal-Mart has nearly 1.4 million workers nationwide. Although the Web site of OUR Walmart depicts the organization as a grass-roots effort by Wal-Mart workers, the United Food and Commercial Workers has provided a sizable sum — the union will not say how much — to help the group get started. The union has also paid hundreds of its members to go door to door to urge Wal-Mart workers to join the group. In addition, the organizers are receiving help from ASGK Public Strategies, a consulting firm long associated with David Axelrod, President Obama’s top political strategist. In recent weeks, OUR Walmart has organized gatherings of 10 to 80 workers in Dallas, Seattle, Los Angeles and other cities, meeting inside churches, fast-food restaurants and employees’ homes, where the workers chewed over how they would like to improve Wal-Mart. One big concern, they said, was low wages. “I’m hoping that OUR Walmart will make a difference in the long run,” said Margaret Van Ness, an overnight stocker at a Wal-Mart store in Lancaster, Calif., about 60 miles north of Los Angeles. Ms. Van Ness earns $11.40 an hour after four years of working there. “The managers at our store and others are running over their associates as if they didn’t exist,” she said. “They treat them like cattle. They don’t seem to care about respect for the individuals. We need to bring back respect.” Unlike a union, the group will not negotiate contracts on behalf of workers. But its members could benefit from federal labor laws that protect workers from retaliation for engaging in collective discussion and action. Wal-Mart officials say that the new organization is essentially a stalking horse for eventual unionization, and they say the retail union is intent on pushing up Wal-Mart’s wages and slowing its expansion to help protect the union’s members at other retailers from competition. “There’s nothing new about the fact that labor unions want to unionize Wal-Mart,” said David Tovar, a Wal-Mart spokesman. “This is an effort to attract media attention to further their political agenda.” The new group is the latest iteration of worker groups aimed at pressuring Wal-Mart. Earlier groups included Walmart Watch and Wake-Up Wal-Mart, both backed by unions, as well as the Wal-Mart Workers Association, a short-lived and foundation-backed group composed of Florida Wal-Mart employees. Officials from the United Food and Commercial Workers are vowing that the new organization will be bigger and better than previous Wal-Mart groups. “We’ve got Wal-Mart associates in large numbers coming to us and saying, ‘We need a voice. This company is mistreating us. We want to stay here, but we need to be able to change the way we’re being treated,’ ” said Dan Schlademan, director of Making Change at Wal-Mart, a division of the union. “The best thing the U.F.C.W. can be is a catalyst to help associates build an organization.” OUR Walmart does not go out of its way to disclose its ties to the union or to Mr. Axelrod’s former firm, although officials at the union and the consulting firm say they disclose their roles if asked. Wal-Mart employees say that store managers around the country have made clear at meetings that OUR Walmart has no affiliation with the company, the world’s largest retailer. Mr. Tovar, the Wal-Mart spokesman, said the company “provides associates with a work environment based on respect, dignity and future partnership in the business.” “The fact is our wages and benefits typically exceed those provided by the majority of our competition,” Mr. Tovar added. “As a result, our associates have concluded time and again that they are better off with the pay, benefits package and opportunities for advancement provided by Wal-Mart and have chosen to reject unions.” Union officials say they hope OUR Walmart will embolden workers and someday pave the way for successful unionization drives at Wal-Mart. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4D6143EF936A25755C0A9679D8B63&amp;ref=walmartstoresinc">Taking the Nonunion Route<date>Published: June 15, 2011</date><text>After numerous failed attempts to unionize Wal-Mart stores, the nation's main union for retail workers has decided to try a different approach: it has helped create a new, nonunion group of Wal-Mart employees that intends to press for better pay, benefits and most of all, more respect at work. The group, Organization United for Respect at Walmart, or OUR Walmart for short, says it has quietly signed up thousands of members in recent months, and it is going public this week with a Web site, ourwalmart.org, and a Facebook page. Organizers say they have more than 50 members at some stores, and they hope to soon have tens of thousands of members. Wal-Mart has nearly 1.4 million workers nationwide. Although the Web site of OUR Walmart depicts the organization as a grass-roots effort by Wal-Mart workers, the United Food and Commercial Workers has provided a sizable sum -- the union will not say how much -- to help the group get started. The union has also paid hundreds of its members to go door to door to urge Wal-Mart workers to join the group. In addition, the organizers are receiving help from ASGK Public Strategies, a consulting firm long associated with David Axelrod, President Obama's top political strategist. In recent weeks, OUR Walmart has organized gatherings of 10 to 80 workers in Dallas, Seattle, Los Angeles and other cities, meeting inside churches, fast-food restaurants and employees' homes, where the workers chewed over how they would like to improve Wal-Mart. One big concern, they said, was low wages. ''I'm hoping that OUR Walmart will make a difference in the long run,'' said Margaret Van Ness, an overnight stocker at a Wal-Mart store in Lancaster, Calif., about 60 miles north of Los Angeles. Ms. Van Ness earns $11.40 an hour after four years of working there. ''The managers at our store and others are running over their associates as if they didn't exist,'' she said. ''They treat them like cattle. They don't seem to care about respect for the individuals. We need to bring back respect.'' Unlike a union, the group will not negotiate contracts on behalf of workers. But its members could benefit from federal labor laws that protect workers from retaliation for engaging in collective discussion and action. Wal-Mart officials say that the new organization is essentially a stalking horse for eventual unionization, and they say the retail union is intent on pushing up Wal-Mart's wages and slowing its expansion to help protect the union's members at other retailers from competition. ''There's nothing new about the fact that labor unions want to unionize Wal-Mart,'' said David Tovar, a Wal-Mart spokesman. ''This is an effort to attract media attention to further their political agenda.'' The new group is the latest iteration of worker groups aimed at pressuring Wal-Mart. Earlier groups included Walmart Watch and Wake-Up Wal-Mart, both backed by unions, as well as the Wal-Mart Workers Association, a short-lived and foundation-backed group composed of Florida Wal-Mart employees. Officials from the United Food and Commercial Workers are vowing that the new organization will be bigger and better than previous Wal-Mart groups. ''We've got Wal-Mart associates in large numbers coming to us and saying, 'We need a voice. This company is mistreating us. We want to stay here, but we need to be able to change the way we're being treated,' '' said Dan Schlademan, director of Making Change at Wal-Mart, a division of the union. ''The best thing the U.F.C.W. can be is a catalyst to help associates build an organization.'' OUR Walmart does not go out of its way to disclose its ties to the union or to Mr. Axelrod's former firm, although officials at the union and the consulting firm say they disclose their roles if asked. Wal-Mart employees say that store managers around the country have made clear at meetings that OUR Walmart has no affiliation with the company, the world's largest retailer. Mr. Tovar, the Wal-Mart spokesman, said the company ''provides associates with a work environment based on respect, dignity and future partnership in the business.''</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/07/business/07views.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Control Soon to Tip to the Waltons<date>Published: June 6, 2011</date><text> Sam Walton will soon be back. The Wal-Mart founder’s descendants are poised to see their stake in the $190 billion company creep above 50 percent, without much fanfare, thanks to the latest $15 billion share buyback program. The watershed brings governance risks, and investors deserve better. Wal-Mart’s founding family has always had a big say in the boardroom of the company, the world’s largest retailer. After Sam Walton died in 1992, family members retained a stake of around 38 percent from the mid-1990s to the mid-2000s. Starting in 2003, a series of big share buybacks began to push the family stake higher, to 43 percent in 2008 and now to 49 percent, according to the latest filings. The Waltons need only sit still to maneuver something like a premium-free takeover. The buyback plan announced last week makes this a near certainty. If it happens around the current share price and the family neither sells nor buys, its ownership will climb to 53 percent. Even if Wal-Mart shares burst from their trading range of weeks and soar 50 percent, completing the repurchase would still tip majority control into the family’s hands. A shift from slightly less than 50 percent ownership to slightly more than 50 percent may seem of little practical consequence. But the impact is more than cosmetic. Once the threshold is crossed, for example, New York Stock Exchange rules would no longer require Wal-Mart to ensure that a majority of its directors are independent. The company says it will do that anyway. But that’s little more than a “trust us.” Investors should want more certainty. Better yet, there may be an alternative. The new buyback follows a $15 billion plan announced a year ago, of which all but $2 billion was spent, and other big outlays before that. But they haven’t excited investors. Wal-Mart’s shares have lagged Costco’s, as well as the broader Standard &amp; Poor’s 500-stock index over one- and two-year time frames. Wal-Mart’s first-quarter dividend amounted to $1.3 billion. If it really has $15 billion to spare, raising its payout and keeping the family’s holding at less than 50 percent would do the job. Liberal Arts Risk What beats Oxford and costs less than Harvard? A group of star British professors has an answer: their new, £18,000-a-year ($29,555) college. The London-based New College of the Humanities can be seen as a free-market response to the decline in government support for the humanities. With a focus similar to American liberal arts colleges, it will offer five subjects (including economics) with one-to-one teaching. This was previously available only at Oxford and Cambridge, and even there it’s proving unsustainably expensive. N.C.H. also looks like a classic services start-up. Twelve founding professors own about 30 percent of the equity. Slightly more private investors hold the rest. The total capital raised is about £10 million. It will finance a three-year path to break-even, at which point profits may be paid out. But N.C.H. needs brainy enrollees. Top British universities will be charging homegrown students £9,000 a year from 2012. Parents are already asking whether Ivy League colleges might offer better value. N.C.H.’s fees are twice as high, though will still be cheaper than the $35,000-plus tuition quoted by Harvard and what many overseas students pay elsewhere in Britain. Moreover, N.C.H. expects to offer discounts for about a fifth of students from the start. Even with that aid, institutions need cachet to charge so much and attract the brightest students. If N.C.H. can get there, British parents may swallow its premium pricing. But it’s still hard to see anyone turning down a place at Cambridge or University College London to pay more for N.C.H. And for parents whose children don’t make it there, or for non-British students, the extra cost of Harvard or Yale may still seem justified. If N.C.H. works, the founding academics get the best of all worlds: an institution of their own making, with the cushion of continuing tenure at the top universities where they’re already based. The business angels, meanwhile, get kudos and the prospect of a yield on their modest investment. But the academics are smart not to give up their day jobs just yet. The profit potential looks far less gold-plated than their qualifications. LISA LEE and CHRISTOPHER HUGHES For more independent financial commentary and analysis, visit www.breakingviews.com.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/04/business/04walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart to Repurchase $15 Million in Stock<date>Published: June 3, 2011</date><text>FAYETTEVILLE, Ark. — Wal-Mart said on Friday that it would buy back $15 billion more of its shares to try to improve returns for its shareholders.The initiative, which was announced at the company’s annual shareholders’ meeting here, comes after a previous $15 billion repurchasing plan that was announced last year. The company bought back 244 million shares, worth about $13 billion, under that program. Charles Holley, the chief financial officer, said the buyback demonstrated the company’s strength and was “indicative of our strong free cash flow position.” Wal-Mart’s shares have lagged the broader market over the last year, despite the repurchase plan and a 21 percent increase in its dividend, to $1.46 a share, in the 2011 fiscal year. On Friday, its shares rose 11 cents, to $53.66. Investors have focused instead on the company’s slumping same-store sales — a problem that company executives promised to fix. “We know we are up against some strong economic headwinds through the recession and slow-paced recovery of the last three years,” Mr. Holley said. Overall sales increased 4.2 percent in the most recent quarter, but most of that increase came from food purchases. In contrast, Wal-Mart has struggled with apparel sales. “In the future, you will see less fashion apparel and more basic items, like underwear and T-shirts,” said William S. Simon, president and chief executive of Wal-Mart’s United States operations. “When it comes to fashion,” he said, “customers don’t want to see 10,000 others wearing the same clothes.” To stem the sales declines, Wal-Mart removed some merchandise from store shelves, including plus-size clothes and fabrics. On Friday, Mr. Simon said that 8,500 items would return to the shelves. In addition, Wal-Mart plans to roll out over the next year 140 to 160 stores in three formats — the 100,000- or more square-foot superstores, 40,000-square-foot neighborhood markets and new 15,000-square-foot express stores. The first express stores will open next week in small towns in Arkansas. The first urban express stores will open later this summer in Chicago. The stores are a part of Wal-Mart’s effort to serve rural and urban areas. Higher food and fuel prices are hurting Wal-Mart’s mainstay shoppers, and Mr. Simon and other executives emphasized that the company would remain a low-cost operator and provide low prices. The company is also seeking to bolster sales overseas. Just last week, Wal-Mart received approval to acquire Massmart Holdings of South Africa for $2.4 billion. Shareholder proposals at the meeting related to climate change, gender discrimination policy, political donations and its suppliers’ compliance with international human and workers’ rights were all defeated. Michael T. Duke, Wal-Mart’s chief executive, said the company was recruiting more women and minorities. It is still facing a federal class-action lawsuit that accuses Wal-Mart of sex discrimination. As in years past, the shareholders’ meeting, which is held near the company’s headquarters in Bentonville, was equal parts pop concert and pep rally. The host this year was the actor Will Smith, and performers included the winner of the 10th season of American Idol, Scotty McCreery, in addition to Alicia Keys, the Black Eyed Peas and the Canadian Tenors. Wal-Mart workers traveled from around the world for the meeting. They did the Wal-Mart cheer with the squiggly dance move several times. Each time an executive referred to the success of Wal-Mart’s Sam’s Club unit, Sam’s Club employees erupted with cheering and noisemakers.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="5">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/business/18shop.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Profit Rises at Wal-Mart, but U.S. Sales Languish<date>Published: May 17, 2011</date><text>For Wal-Mart’s customers, the economy still looks a lot like 2009.The poorer customers who shop at the nation’s biggest retailers are still on tight budgets. They wait inside the store at the end of each month with full shopping carts until the clock strikes midnight. Then, their electronic-benefit transfers from the government go through, and they pay for their groceries and other staples. They buy items in small packages, which cost less than big ones. And while they are spending more on food at Wal-Mart than they did a year ago, they are buying less in most other categories. Same-store sales, or sales at stores open at least a year, fell by 1.1 percent in the quarter in the United States, the company said on Tuesday. It was the eight quarterly drop in a row, one of the worst streaks in Wal-Mart’s history. Over all, however, earnings beat analyst expectations, helped by sales strength in international stores and at its Sam’s Club unit. The company said its quarterly profit was $3.4 billion, or 97 cents a share, up from $3.3 billion, or 87 cents a share, a year earlier. Wal-Mart had forecast a profit of 91 to 96 cents a share for the quarter, and analysts expected a 95-cent-a-share profit on average. Sales in the period, which ended April 30 and was the first quarter of Wal-Mart’s fiscal year, rose 4.4 percent, to $103.4 billion. Low prices on groceries during an inflationary period helped sales, Wal-Mart executives said. Same-store sales in grocery were up in the single digits for the quarter in the United States. Wal-Mart said food prices rose about 1 percent in the quarter as a result of inflation. Yet Wal-Mart had some trouble getting shoppers into the rest of the store. In apparel, for instance. “We’re simply not converting enough of our grocery customers to shop apparel,” said William S. Simon, the president and chief executive of Wal-Mart’s United States division, in a conference call with investors. After flirting with fashion-forward items, Wal-Mart decided to focus on basic clothes, but company executives said they did not perform well. “It’s something that we’ve stumbled with over the last several quarters and we’re not happy with,” Charles M. Holley Jr., the chief financial officer, said in a conference call with reporters. “It does start with basics, and for us to be able to sell anything that’s fashionable at all, we really have to get basics down first.” While “we had a fairly good quarter” with items like T-shirts and underwear, he said, “where we’re still not executing is in the kids’ and the women’s business.” In other departments, Wal-Mart is piling merchandise in its aisles to signal value, and is stocking items in smaller packages that someone on a budget can afford, in an effort to take market share from dollar stores. “You see customers that are running out of money at the end of the month going to the smaller pack sizes — they are not necessarily a better value,” Mr. Holley said, but “we have been continuing to work on that, so we have the smaller pack sizes.” Wal-Mart said this strategy had been successful with products like air fresheners and fishing products, so far. “These modular changes focused on bringing back assortment, ensuring opening price points were available in all categories, and increased the holding power on the shelf,” Mr. Simon said. Same-store sales were all in negative territory in categories like entertainment, including electronics; hard lines, which are items like hardware and crafts; apparel; and home. In the United States, Wal-Mart has been making a number of changes to revive same-store sales. Michael T. Duke, chief executive of Wal-Mart, said on Tuesday that “comp sales growth remains the greatest priority for me and the entire Wal-Mart U.S. team.” Wal-Mart said it would continue with its expansion plans in the United States, particularly with smaller stores. Its grocery-only stores, which are called Neighborhood Markets and are about one-third the size of a typical Wal-Mart, performed well in the quarter. There, same-store sales were up 4 percent as visits by customers rose. Wal-Mart said that because of those results, it would open another 30 to 40 Neighborhood Markets this year. The company will also open 15 to 20 Wal-Mart Express stores by the end of the year in urban and rural areas. At about 15,000 square feet, they will sell groceries “along with key general merchandise categories,” Mr. Simon said. They will also function as a depot of sorts for Walmart.com’s items. Customers can order something from the extended online inventory, and pick it up at the store. Analysts noted that drops in Wal-Mart’s same-store sales were at least easing. “Top-line results came in somewhat ahead of expectations, reflecting a more moderate decline in U.S. comps,” Colin McGranahan, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, wrote in a note to clients. Wal-Mart said it expected same-store sales to range from down 1 percent to up 1 percent in its second quarter. Separately, Home Depot also reported earnings on Tuesday. Although its profit beat Wall Street expectations, its same-store sales in the United States declined because of the harsh winter, Craig A. Menear, its merchandising chief, said in a call with investors. Home Depot’s revenue was $16.82 billion, down from $16.86 billion in the same period a year earlier. But because of aggressive cost-cutting, its net income was up 12 percent to $812 million, or 50 cents a share, versus analyst expectations of 49 cents a share. “It’s all weather,” Home Depot’s chief financial officer, Carol B. Tomé, said in an interview. “It’s not an assortment issue. It’s just when it’s cold and snowing and raining, people aren’t going to do the outdoor products.” Shares of Wal-Mart fell 52 cents, or about 1 percent, to $55.54 a share. Shares of Home Depot rose 1.14 percent, or 42 cents, to $37.40.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://bittman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/05/16/live-from-the-baymont-inn-pella-iowa/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Live From the Baymont Inn, Pella, Iowa<date>May 16, 2011, 1:07 pm</date><text>You last heard from me, I think, leaving Immokalee en route to Detroit. The Motor City, as we used to call it, is the subject of this week’s column, so you’re getting nothing on that now, though I will say it was one of the most memorable and inspiring couple of days I’ve had, ever. (“Honey? Pack your bags. We’re moving to Detroit.”) From there things took a turn for the worse, but only in spurts. Thanks to weather in Chicago and the “efficiencies” of our airline “system,” it took me eleven hours to get from Detroit to Dubuque, Iowa, a drive I could have done in eight; nine of those eleven hours were spent in airports, some scurrying back and forth between terminals. I wasn’t in a good mood when I got to Dubuque at 11 p.m. and had to juggle my already-jumbled schedule. Yesterday – Sunday – began wonderfully, however. Jude Becker picked me up and took me to visit his farm in Dyersville, which I’ll write about in detail at some point, but which seemed to me to be an excellent model for American organic pig farmers. Becker uses techniques pioneered in Denmark and the UK and is not only supplying his customers with pork year-round, he’s employing more people than most 5,000-acre corn farms in the state do. The farm is on rolling hills – as is much of the eastern part of the state, which geologically is part of the Driftless Region (thank you, Dan) – and, on the cool, breezy, gray morning we had yesterday, I might have thought I was in Devon. Gorgeous land: It’s been in Jude’s family for six generations, and they’ve all taken care of it well. Mark BittmanThe Fourth Street Elevator, a funicular railway in Dubuque. I then took a tour of the Hotel Julien Dubuque – there’s an Al Capone suite, but some guy was in there boozing it up with the dames (sorry) – which has seen a splendid renovation in case you’re ever in the neighborhood. The town itself has some fine turn-of-the-century architecture marred by a downtown almost completely messed up by urban “renewal.” One excellent item is the Fourth Street Elevator, commonly referred to as the Fenelon Place Elevator, a very steep little tram (they say it’s the steepest in the world, but how do you know, really?) that costs two bucks to go up and down and is about as much fun as you can have in Dubuque without involving alcohol. Mark BittmanMy makeshift dinner, courtesy of Wal-Mart. Then I hit the road in my little Toyota Yaris. (They wanted to “upgrade” me to a Dodge but I couldn’t see how that was a good idea.) Having skipped breakfast – I could find literally nothing to eat in Dubuque – I was now speeding (again, literally: got a ticket) down Route 151 towards Cedar Rapids, passing one fast food joint after another. (This seems to be one of those areas where the mega-food companies try out new concepts, like Patrick Gonzalez West-Mex Taqueria – I made that up, but you know what I mean – before blessing the rest of us with their presence.) Finally, out of desperation, I did what I’ve done before: stopped at a Wal-Mart Supercenter where, for the price of two fast food meals, I bought almonds, peanuts, dried apricots, apples, bananas, carrots, water, and cucumbers, which should keep me set for breakfast and lunch for a few days. Related Bittman’s Spring Food &amp; Farm Tour Read previous posts from the columnist’s search for sustainable agricultural in urban settings. Mark BittmanDairy cows on Francis Thicke’s farm. Driving past CAFOs (Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations) and signs protesting hog lagoons – progress! – I arrived in late afternoon at the farm of Francis Thicke, a visionary who ran for Iowa’s Secretary of Agriculture last year. He lost, but not before raising consciousness about sustainable ag throughout the state. This is a great man, and I’ll get to writing in detail about him, too. We sat and talked, then walked and drove around his 300-odd acre dairy farm – he sells all of his milk, cheese, yogurt, and cream within four miles of the farm, so few of us will be trying it – where I helped him move a four-day old calf and its mother back to a barn. (Me: “I’m dairy farming!”) Then on to Pella, home of windows, bad hotels, and the Applebee’s in which I ate dinner. It was my first ever such experience, and I know I’ll do better tonight. But it was late, the day had been long, and I wasn’t going to start looking for the mythical family-style restaurant run by generations of the same family, because I knew it didn’t exist. The other option was Señor O’Brien’s, or something like that.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/05/16/wal-mart-warns-it-may-walk-from-south-african-deal/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Warns It May Walk Away From South African Deal<date>May 16, 2011, 11:55 am</date><text>Wal-Mart Stores may end its effort to acquire control of Massmart Holdings if South Africa requires it to buy South African goods, a lawyer for the two companies said at an antitrust hearing, Bloomberg News reports. Read more »</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/15/business/15shelf.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">‘Force of Nature’ Examines How Wal-Mart Went Green - Review<date>Published: May 14, 2011</date><text>GIVEN our daily struggles with information overload, I suppose it’s inevitable that there will always be major, perhaps global, issues that some of us simply don’t follow. Bosnia was like that for me. As serious as I knew the situation was, it went on for so long that I finally just gave up.My latest intellectual Bosnia has been the knot of issues that’s come to be known as “sustainability.” In this regard, I suspect I’m not alone, especially among business people, many of whom still tend to associate these ideas with increased cost and government regulation. The idea that “going green” could actually be profitable, a notion put forth by economists as long as 20 years ago, remains a source of skepticism in some quarters. If you still need convincing, pick up Edward Humes’s excellent new book, “Force of Nature” (Harper Business, 265 pages, $27.99), the story of how the world’s largest retailer, Wal-Mart, came to go green. I’ll wager that you won’t look at sustainability issues quite the same way again. It certainly opened my eyes. This little book is easily read in two airplane flights, and it’s well worth the time. Mr. Humes, a Pulitzer Prize winner in 1989 for articles about the military, tells how Jib Ellison, a onetime California river-rafting guide, all but singlehandedly persuaded Wal-Mart to embrace sustainability as part of its core culture. Starting with a meeting in 2004 with H. Lee Scott Jr., then Wal-Mart’s chief executive, Mr. Ellison demonstrated that sustainability wasn’t just tree-hugger talk. In its simplest form, sustainability means eliminating waste. And eliminating waste saves money. That got Mr. Scott’s attention. One of Mr. Ellison’s first projects for Wal-Mart showed how easily this could be accomplished. He noticed that the colorful cardboard packaging for the company’s Chinese-made toy trucks was far larger than needed. He suggested reducing the size, which saved millions of dollars, not to mention hundreds of thousands of tons of cardboard that otherwise would find its way into landfills. That, in turn, led to a Wal-Mart crusade to reduce packaging size across its product lines, saving the company an estimated $3.4 billion a year — that’s billion with a “b” — while reducing trash. Since that first initiative, Wal-Mart has charted a new green course that’s been widely noticed, and imitated, throughout the corporate world. The company has brought in eco-friendly consultants who have helped find innovative ways to reduce waste almost everywhere, from the use of chemicals to something as simple as installing electrical generators in the trucking fleet, so that refrigerated trucks don’t have to idle overnight. In recent years Mr. Scott pushed green initiatives even further, forcing thousands of Wal-Mart suppliers to embrace sustainability as well. The author makes clear that Wal-Mart did not embark on this course out of a sense of corporate do-goodism. The company, the book says, had long had an insular culture that looked askance at outsiders, especially those who wanted it to change — and that went double for environmentalists. At the time Mr. Ellison walked into Mr. Scott’s office, the company was being pummeled by a multitude of opponents, from environmentalists to entire city governments, accusing it of driving mom-and-pop retailers out of business, underpaying its “associates” and union-busting. Going green has given Wal-Mart a badly needed public-relations boost as it continues to face harsh criticism on those other fronts. But once Mr. Scott saw that sustainability could be profitable, he went whole hog. Mr. Ellison took Mr. Scott and others on scores of side trips to make his points — for example, showing an executive in apparel merchandising just how chemical-laden a conventional cotton farm in Turkey was, compared with an organic farm just across the road. If you could sell an organic cotton T-shirt for the same price as the chemically treated shirt — and you could, Mr. Ellison showed — why wouldn’t you? Eventually, Wal-Mart came to embrace a wide spectrum of environmental causes, not just for the P.R. and bottom-line benefits, but also, as Mr. Humes demonstrates, for its future. Wal-Mart shoppers are mostly women, and the next generation of women shoppers — today’s teenage girls — tend to feel very strongly about sustainability issues. If Wal-Mart didn’t go green, Mr. Scott told his people, the shoppers of 2020 would quickly go to Target. Mr. Scott retired in 2009, but Wal-Mart’s commitment to sustainability has remained strong under his successor, Mike Duke. THE results have been impressive, on items big and small. According to Mr. Humes, it reduced its overall carbon emissions rate by 16 percent from 2005 to 2008. Wal-Mart’s 2010 progress report on sustainability also shows that it sharply reduced its use of plastic bags; donated to food banks 127 million pounds of food that previously would have been discarded; reduced printouts of store reports by 350 million pieces of paper, saving it $20 million; and sharply reduced or eliminated phosphates in the dish and laundry detergents it sells in many countries. “Force of Nature” doesn’t offer the compelling business narrative of some other books — there are no boardroom shouting matches, or much drama at all — but that doesn’t matter. Mr. Humes does here what the very best business books do. He finds a good story to help illuminate an issue of surpassing importance. The book doesn’t contain much more information than your average Fortune magazine cover article, but Mr. Humes’s prose is almost flawless, lean and clear, egoless and spare. He doesn’t deify or demonize Wal-Mart or any of the characters; in fact, he says Wal-Mart’s very business model is probably unsustainable. This is first-rate work — both by the author and by Wal-Mart itself. </text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/08/business/08gret.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Changes a Measuring Stick on Pay - Fair Game<date>Published: May 7, 2011</date><text>PEOPLE scrutinize just about everything Wal-Mart does. As Michael T. Duke, the company’s chief executive, put it recently, “What we do and how we perform is watched closely not only by our customers and shareholders, but also by the whole world.”All of which makes a recent decision about executive pay at this giant retailer downright puzzling. In a proxy statement filed a few weeks ago, Wal-Mart’s compensation committee said it had replaced a crucial metric for assessing executives’ performance: same-store sales, referring to stores that have been open for at least a year. Instead of that measure, Wal-Mart is using total sales companywide, or at its major units, Wal-Mart Stores and Sam’s Club. Why? The change was “intended to align our performance share goals more closely with our evolving business strategy, which emphasizes productive growth, leverage and returns,” Wal-Mart said. The timing was certainly curious. The switch came amid a sustained decline in Wal-Mart’s same-store sales, which have been falling for nearly two years. The company’s total sales, however, rose 3.4 percent in the latest fiscal year. Shifting the goal posts meant more money for Mr. Duke in the latest fiscal year than he would have received under the old arrangement. His compensation totaled $18.7 million, more than $16 million of which was performance-based. Same-store sales are an important metric for investors. A quintessential apples-to-apples comparison, they measure the productivity at established stores and eliminate sales spikes that might occur when new stores open. Aware that investors obsess over these figures, Mr. Duke told analysts recently that turning around Wal-Mart’s same-store sales was his top priority. Last February, when the company announced results that included the seventh consecutive quarterly drop for the figure, its share price fell 3 percent. So why remove this crucial performance gauge for pay purposes? Wal-Mart did not respond to a request for comment on the matter. Certainly, past statements about why the board chose to include this measure suggest that it’s important. For example, Wal-Mart said in its 2008 proxy that its board had used “comparable-store sales as a performance metric because it believes it is a key driver of shareholder returns, and because investors look to comparable-store sales as an important measure of performance in the retail industry.” Two years later, the company said its compensation committee included same-store sales as one of its benchmarks “because it believed that good performance relative to these metrics is important for our overall financial performance and, therefore, is likely to have a positive effect on shareholder returns.” The committee added that “the combination of these performance metrics was likely to incentivize our executives to achieve performance that is in the best interests of our company and our shareholders.” And yet, a year later, Wal-Mart jettisoned same-store sales from the mix. Explaining the decision, the proxy said the compensation committee concluded that “the combination of these performance metrics was likely to incentivize our executives to achieve performance that is in line with the best interests of our company and our shareholders.” Talk about trying to have it both ways. KEEP in mind that when Wal-Mart included same-store sales in its pay calculations, that measure had a sizable effect on Mr. Duke’s compensation. Indeed, same-store sales accounted for 30 percent of the weighted factors determining his performance pay in fiscal 2010 (which consisted of most of 2009 and the first month of 2010).   Removing same-store sales from its pay-for-performance measures “is a failure to admit failure,” says Burt Flickinger III, managing director at the Strategic Resource Group, a retailing consulting firm. “This is the first time since the company was founded that, during a recession, same-store sales were consistently negative in contrast to key competitors like Costco, Target, TJX and BJ’s.” Mr. Flickinger says he expects Wal-Mart’s same-store sales to keep declining in the coming months. The switch at Wal-Mart last year followed a shift in 2009 that allowed the company to set performance targets annually. In previous years, the board had set performance targets for three-year periods. The goals had to be met over that time before company executives could receive certain incentive pay awards. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="6">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/03/weekinreview/03liptak.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Can Class-Action Lawsuits Be Too Big to Deliver Justice?<date>Published: April 2, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — Can a class-action lawsuit be too sprawling to deliver old-fashioned justice?Justice Antonin Scalia seems to think so, judging by his comments on Tuesday during the Supreme Court argument in the biggest employment discrimination class action in history. “We must have a pretty bad judicial system,” he said, reflecting on what he had just heard from a lawyer for hundreds of thousands of women suing Wal-Mart over what they say was unfair treatment on pay and promotions. The lawyer had said that a trial judge could rely on statistical formulas rather than testimony and personnel records to decide how much money the company would have to pay each plaintiff if it lost. “Is this really due process?” Justice Scalia asked. In other words, does the impersonality of the suit threaten its ability to be fair to each plaintiff and to Wal-Mart, the country’s biggest private employer? The mass production of justice through class actions can indeed test the limits of the role that courts play in society. But the enormous size of modern institutions, it has been argued, requires efficient, streamlined procedures like class actions to address their failures. “We are in the domain of mass litigation in mass society, where the private lawsuit is a regulatory enterprise,” said Samuel Issacharoff, a law professor at New York University. “You need to have mechanisms of enforcement that correspond to the scale of the economic activity.” Suzette M. Malveaux, a law professor at Catholic University in Washington, agreed that class actions have an important role to play in many cases, particularly those involving fraud and discrimination. “It’s a balancing act between efficiency and fairness,” she said. The issue tends to divide lawyers and scholars along ideological lines. Conservatives and business groups say class actions are a form of regulation through litigation and insert courts into matters better left to administrative bodies. Consumer and civil rights lawyers counter that without class-action treatment, grave but widely dispersed wrongs would never be addressed. The day after the Wal-Mart argument, a prominent federal appeals court judge issued an opinion in a similar but smaller case, this one brought by about 500 women against Rolls-Royce. How far class-action procedures “can be stretched is the issue in the gigantic class action against Wal-Mart now before the Supreme Court,” Judge Richard A. Posner of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit in Chicago wrote for a unanimous three-judge panel, ruling against class-action treatment. “The present case is not as big a stretch,” he said, “but it is big enough.” Judge Posner said he was concerned about the due process rights of so-called absent class members: women who would be bound by the result in the case even though they had not volunteered for it and had no right to opt out and sue on their own. And he added that something more than a “mechanical computation” was needed to decide who gets how much money should the women win. Rather, he said, the case would require “500 separate hearings.” Perhaps the most counterintuitive wrinkle in the typical class action is that only a handful of named plaintiffs have agreed to be represented by the lawyers who brought the case. Yet all of the class members will be held to the results those lawyers achieve. “Ordinarily, you enforce your own rights,” Professor Malveaux said. “Here, someone is representing you without your consent. We only allow that in exceptional circumstances.” She added that the Wal-Mart case qualified for the exception. “The idea of every woman coming forward and challenging their store manager is really unlikely,” she said. Richard Epstein, a law professor at New York University, disagreed, noting that the plaintiffs in the Wal-Mart case are suing over “decentralized personnel decisions” in thousands of stores. “You want to wring your hands,” he said. “This case is so crazy.” At the argument last week, some of the justices appeared sympathetic to the plaintiffs’ complaint but wary about the courts’ ability to handle so large a case. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/30/business/30walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Justices Take Up Question of Wal-Mart Class Action<date>Published: March 29, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — The Supreme Court appeared closely divided on Tuesday during arguments over the theory put forth by the plaintiffs in an enormous sex discrimination class-action case against Wal-Mart.Even some justices who seemed sympathetic to the plaintiffs expressed qualms about how to administer a lawsuit involving as many as 1.5 million women seeking back pay that could amount to billions of dollars. Others appeared worried about the consequences for other businesses of a ruling that would allow the case against Wal-Mart to go forward. The mere certification of a class-action suit can prompt defendants to settle in light of the sums at stake, and the justices struggled to find a way to distinguish between gaps in pay that might have benign explanations and those caused by unlawful discrimination. The court of Chief Justice John G. Roberts Jr. has recently issued a series of rulings in favor of plaintiffs suing for employment discrimination that cut against the court’s pro-business reputation. The Wal-Mart case dwarfs those rulings in importance. It is the largest employment discrimination class action in history, and the court’s decision, expected by June, will probably be its most important business ruling this term. The issue before the justices at Tuesday’s arguments was not whether Wal-Mart, the country’s largest retailer and biggest private employer, discriminated against women who worked there. For now, the question in the case, Wal-Mart Stores v. Dukes, No. 10-277, is whether hundreds of thousands of female workers have enough in common to join together in a single lawsuit. The plaintiffs’ theory is that a centralized companywide policy gave local managers too much discretion in pay and promotion decisions, leaving Wal-Mart vulnerable to gender stereotypes. The plaintiffs have presented sworn statements and statistics to support their claim. Wal-Mart calls that evidence unrepresentative and unreliable. The company says its policies expressly bar discrimination and promote diversity. In any event, the company says, the plaintiffs — who worked in 3,400 stores in 170 job classifications — do not have enough in common to warrant class-action treatment. Justice Anthony M. Kennedy said the theory about how the company discriminated — through a central policy conferring local discretion — was internally inconsistent. “Your complaint faces in two directions,” he told a lawyer for the plaintiffs. But Justice Stephen G. Breyer said Wal-Mart could be held accountable if it failed to take action in the face of reports of discrimination from its stores. “Should central management under the law have withdrawn some of the subjective discretion in order to stop these results?” Justice Breyer asked. Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg agreed, saying that companies had a responsibility to make sure that women were treated fairly in local workplaces. And Justice Elena Kagan said that “excessive subjectivity” may be a policy that violates the civil rights laws. But Justice Antonin Scalia was unconvinced. “I’m getting whipsawed here,” he told the plaintiffs’ lawyer, Joseph M. Sellers. “On the one hand, you say the problem is that they were utterly subjective, and on the other hand you say there is strong corporate culture that guides all of this. Well, which is it?” Mr. Sellers responded that “there is this broad discretion given the managers” but that “they do not make their decisions in a vacuum.” Managers, he went on, “are informed by the company about how to exercise that discretion.” That did not satisfy Justice Scalia. “If somebody tells you how to exercise discretion,” he said, “you don’t have discretion.” Theodore J. Boutrous Jr., a lawyer for Wal-Mart, said the handful of women named as plaintiffs who seek to represent the entire class did not have typical experiences at the company. “Each of the plaintiffs have very different stories,” he said. “One of them was promoted into a managerial position. One was terminated for disciplinary violations. One was promoted and then had a disciplinary problem and then was demoted.” He added that “this class includes at least 544 store managers who are alleged to be discriminators and victims.” Several justices had practical concerns. “What seems to me a very serious problem in this case is, how do you work out the back pay?” Justice Ginsburg asked. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/30/business/30aldi.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Where Wal-Mart Failed, Aldi Succeeds<date>Published: March 29, 2011</date><text>While Wal-Mart revives its plans to get into New York City, a giant German retailer has slipped in relatively unnoticed.In February, with virtually no opposition — a Queens politician even showed up at the grand opening in Rego Park, Queens — a discount retailer called Aldi opened its first store in the city, and plans to open a second one, in the Bronx, later this year. After decades spent fleeing cities for the strip malls and boulevards of the suburbs, grocers and discount retailers are doing an about-face. Target plans to open its first smaller, city-size store in Seattle next year, and Wal-Mart announced recently that it would build “hundreds” of smaller, mostly urban stores in the coming years. Meanwhile, Aldi has quietly been setting up its shops in cities around the country. “They’re not only doing the small format more rapidly, but they’re getting into the urban areas more rapidly than either Wal-Mart Express or the city Targets,” said Craig Johnson, president of the consulting firm Customer Growth Partners. “Even though the company’s headquartered in Germany, they’ve opened up a New York store quicker than Wal-Mart has.” Even though Aldi, like Wal-Mart, is nonunion, it has faced little resistance, compared with the heated opposition often headed by unions and politicians that Wal-Marts have encountered in larger markets. “There’s no reason to oppose an Aldi — it’s a small format, and they usually get space from an existing landowner or landlord, a small guy who’s plugged into the community, not a big guy like a Forest City Ratner,” Mr. Johnson said. “Wal-Mart has sort of become a bad guy that there’s a concerted effort against. I’m not sure that Aldi has really gotten on anyone’s radar screen.” Aldi first came to the United States in 1976, but it opened a relatively small number of stores a year — 25 or so on average. Within the last few years, it has accelerated its expansion by adding more than 250 stores, with plans for 80 more both in 2011 and 2012, said Jason Hart, co-president of Aldi’s United States division, in a recent interview. The company capitalizes on the bargain hunter, who is not embarrassed to choose frugality over name brands. Aldi’s mainly sells its own private-label items at cheap prices — a five-ounce bacon-wrapped beef filet costs $1.79 at the Queens store. “It’s the one format that seems to have increased the most, and has sustained a number of new stores,” during and after the recession, said Jonathan P. Feeney, a grocery analyst with Janney Capital Markets. As “prices are going to go up, it’s going to be a growing opportunity.” Aldi was founded by the Albrecht brothers, who worked in their mother’s German retail business and took it over in the 1940s. In 1961, they introduced the Aldi name, short for Albrecht Discount. According to Stores magazine, the Aldi group was the eighth-largest retailer in the world in 2009 (the most recent figures available), with an estimated $67.7 billion in revenue. According to estimates by Mr. Johnson, about $6.5 billion of Aldi’s revenue stems from sales in the United States. Aldi’s model is to sell groceries and basics like dishwasher soap and laundry detergent in drugstore-size spaces — its Queens store is 17,500 square feet, about 16 percent the size of an average Wal-Mart — in urban, suburban and rural areas, though the focus lately has been in cities. About 95 percent of its goods bear an obscure private label. For example, rather than Skippy, Jiffy, natural, and jam-swirled peanut butter, Aldi sells one kind, which it commissions itself. (It’s similar to the higher-end Trader Joe’s, which is owned by an Albrecht family trust.) “We carry 1,500 of the most popular grocery items out there,” Mr. Hart said. “You won’t find some exotic spice or exotic produce items in our stores; you won’t find every flavor of every items. When you look at the large supermarkets that may have 20- to 30,000 items, or superstores, with over 100,000 items, it’s surprising to the customers how much of the shopping list we’re able to fit into our smaller store.” Fewer product lines translate into making even a small, high-rent space quite profitable. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/29/business/29walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Decision Could Have Far-Reaching Consequences<date>Published: March 28, 2011</date><text>Retailers are facing more pressure to comply with crowd safety guidelines issued by the government, after a decision last week that upheld a fine against Wal-Mart in the 2008 trampling death of an employee.Wal-Mart has spent more than a year and almost $2 million fighting the $7,000 fine from the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, which stems from a customer stampede on Thanksgiving weekend at a Valley Stream, N.Y., store that killed the employee, Jdimytai Damour. That is in part, lawyers and retail executives say, because Wal-Mart and other stores do not want regulators overseeing how they run sale events, like the day after Thanksgiving. “The precarious situation is that you have government micromanaging how sales are conducted, and really saying they need to be conducted in a certain way,” said Casey Chroust, executive vice president for retail operations at the Retail Industry Leaders Association, a trade group. But even as Wal-Mart may be planning an appeal of Friday’s decision, Michael Schmidt, a partner in the labor and employment practice group at Cozen O’Connor, said that retailers would most likely hurry to put in place the crowd control guidelines that OSHA issued last year. The guidelines say that barricades should start away from the store’s entrance, and that they must have breaks or turns in them to prevent customers pushing from the rear. The guidelines also say that employees should be assigned to specific spots, and that the local police, fire department and hospitals should be alerted about an event that might draw crowds. The guidelines suggest major changes to the first-come, first-serve way that many events are held. They say that retailers should “consider using an Internet lottery for ‘hot’ items”; use wristbands or tickets to designate those who have arrived early; and distribute pamphlets showing where sale items are located within the store. If the fine stands, the federal safety agency could have far more influence over marketing campaigns, some retailers say. OSHA could “change the way they’re doing big promotions and big kinds of sales,” Mr. Schmidt said of retailers. Wal-Mart “doesn’t want OSHA to increase its web to start regulating programs, and the operations of retailers generally.” Mr. Chroust said that in addition to the guidelines telling retailers how to control crowds, they also assume that retailers can predict when a crowd can turn problematic. “What is officially defined as a dangerous crowd?” he said. “If you have a sale that’s going to take place for a hot video game, a new piece of technology that’s going to be released, do you have to start putting into place crowd-management procedures if even the possibility of a crowd could emerge?” Joe LaRocca, senior adviser for asset protection at the industry group National Retail Federation, said that by extension, if retailers were held responsible for raucous crowds, they could also be held responsible for, say, random shootings on their sites. Retailers and mall operators “have expressed a concern that this fine could open up retailers to some liability or responsibility in a similar issue, or an issue that might be comparable to an active shooter, to a shooting situation, inside a store or mall,” he said. Covette Rooney, the judge in the Wal-Mart case, found that in 2008, Wal-Mart’s “precautions to protect its employees were minimal and ineffective.” She reviewed what had happened at the Valley Stream store on Thanksgiving sales in 2008 and earlier. On Thanksgiving Friday in 2005, 2006, and 2007, the surging crowd had popped the doors off their hinges at the store, for instance. By 3 a.m. on Friday 2008 though, barricades were placed 40 feet from the doors, and customers had already jumped over them. By 4 a.m., there was no space between the store’s doors and the crowd. Employees asked the crowd to step back, but “they were not responding,” according to one employee’s testimony. As it got closer to 5 a.m., when the store was to open, a Wal-Mart regional executive suggested to the store manager that they not open the doors, because the crowd seemed unruly and the police were not present. The store manager “rejected his suggestion,” according to Ms. Rooney’s review of the testimony. Wal-Mart had “trained its employees in the prevention of trip, slip and fall hazards to customers” and told employees to “ ‘stay out of the way’ of the onrushing crowd of customers,” Ms. Rooney wrote, but “these instructions were plainly inadequate to protect employees from the cited hazard.” Eight to 10 employees were pushing against the door to counteract the press of customers trying to get in, according to one employee’s testimony. Once the doors were unlocked, customers fell in the vestibule, and employees climbed on top of vending machines to protect themselves. As in years past, the doors popped off their hinges. Mr. Damour was trampled. He died at the site. “The record shows Wal-Mart exposed its employees to the hazards that were present at the store during Blitz Day 2008 for a three-year period, that is, Blitz Days 2006, 2007 and 2008,” Ms. Rooney wrote. By 2009, as part of a settlement with Nassau County in which the county agreed not to prosecute the retailer, Wal-Mart agreed to revise its Thanksgiving Friday security plans for all its New York stores starting in 2009. It extended the approach to most of its stores. The lines of people waiting for the 5 a.m. openings were eliminated. Instead, Wal-Mart stayed open from 7 a.m. on Thanksgiving Day through the night. For the hot items, like electronics, people were given tickets, so they did not have to rush and grab items. Instead of the plastic barriers, the store’s employees set up steel barriers in zigzag patterns outside the door. Employees stood on raised platforms to tell the crowd what was happening. And the company asked some employees to watch videos on crowd control techniques. There were no reports of serious injuries or deaths in 2009 or in 2010. Yet those changes showed that “feasible means existed to eliminate or materially reduce the cited hazard at the store” in 2008, Ms. Rooney wrote.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/28/us/28scotus.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Supreme Court Gets Sociology Issue in Wal-Mart Discrimination Case<date>Published: March 27, 2011</date><text>WASHINGTON — When the Supreme Court considers on Tuesday whether hundreds of thousands of women can band together in an employment discrimination suit against Wal-Mart, the argument may hinge on the validity of the hotly disputed conclusions of a Chicago sociologist.Plaintiffs in the class-action suit, who claim that Wal-Mart owes billions of dollars to as many as 1.5 million women who they say were unfairly treated on pay and promotions, enlisted the support of William T. Bielby, an academic specializing in “social framework analysis.” A central question in the case is whether he should have been allowed, in preliminary proceedings, to go beyond describing general research about gender stereotypes in the workplace to draw specific conclusions about what he called flaws in Wal-Mart’s personnel policies. “Bielby made a conclusion that he had no basis to make,” said Laurens Walker, one of two University of Virginia professors who coined the term for the analysis almost 25 years ago. “He hasn’t done the research.” But a brief supporting the plaintiffs from the American Sociological Association said that Professor Bielby’s work explaining how Wal-Mart’s policies may have led to discrimination “is well within our discipline’s accepted methods.” The sharp arguments are a testament to the central role that social framework analysis has come to play in scores of major employment discrimination cases. Describing what was at stake in such cases, a 2009 article in The Fordham Law Review defending Professor Bielby said the debate was “about the existence of unconscious or implicit bias, the continued seriousness of discrimination as a force in the modern workplace and the appropriate reach of legal remedies to challenge discrimination.” The Supreme Court is not considering whether Wal-Mart, the country’s largest retailer and biggest private employer, in fact discriminated against women who worked there. For now, the question before the justices in the case, Wal-Mart Stores v. Dukes, No. 10-277, is only whether hundreds of thousands of female workers have enough in common to join together in a single suit. To make that case, the plaintiffs submitted 120 sworn statements describing what they said was anecdotal evidence of discrimination. They also offered statistics showing what they said were suspicious gaps in pay and promotion between men and women. Wal-Mart disputes the plaintiffs’ evidence as unrepresentative and unreliable. But even if all of it were established fact, anecdotes and statistics would not be enough. Supreme Court precedent also requires lawyers pursuing a class action to identify the common policy that they say led to unlawful discrimination. For that, the lawyers for the plaintiffs in the Wal-Mart case turned to Professor Bielby, who teaches at the University of Illinois at Chicago and has testified in scores of similar cases. Social framework analysis gives courts general information — a framework — drawn from social science. Testimony about the reliability of eyewitness identification can, for instance, serve a valuable role in cases in which prosecutors seek to rely on such evidence. Professor Bielby, who declined a request for an interview, told the trial court that he had collected general “scientific evidence about gender bias, stereotypes and the structure and dynamics of gender inequality in organizations.” He said he also reviewed extensive litigation materials gathered by the lawyers in the case. He concluded that two aspects of Wal-Mart’s corporate culture might be to blame for pay and other disparities. One was a centralized personnel policy. The other was allowing subjective decisions by managers in the field. Together, he said, those factors allowed stereotypes to infect personnel choices, making “decisions about compensation and promotion vulnerable to gender bias.” The methodology he used, Professor Bielby explained, was social framework analysis. He cited the seminal work of the two law professors at the University of Virginia, Professors Walker and John Monahan, in the first of 123 footnotes in his 41-page sworn declaration in the case. But Professors Walker and Monahan contend in their academic writing that Professor Bielby has misused social framework analysis. It is fine, they say, to give courts general information about social science research. But it is improper, they continue, to draw conclusions about the matter in dispute without conducting first-hand research. 1 2 Next Page »</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="7">
    <article index="1" href="http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/03/02/gay-group-joins-fight-against-wal-mart/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Gay Group Joins Fight Against Wal-Mart<date>March 2, 2011, 10:05 am</date><text>As Wal-Mart strives to open its first store in New York City, it has attracted a long list of opponents, from elected officials to labor leaders to small business people. On Wednesday, another group took up the cause: a prominent gay rights group. The National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, a gay advocacy group based in Washington, said Wal-Mart had a poor record when it came to gay employees. “With the expansion of Wal-Mart stores comes the expansion of antiquated employment policies,” the task force said in a statement, “that provide little to no protections for, and at times even hostility toward, their L.G.B.T. employees.” The task force criticized Wal-Mart for denying employee benefits to same-sex partners and for failing to prohibit discrimination based on gender identity. By comparison, the group said two other chain stores with a strong presence in New York, Costco and Walgreens, did much better. “It may be a local debate for New York City, but Wal-Mart is the largest private employer in the country,” said Rea Carey, the executive director of the task force. “To have Wal-Mart as a substantial employer there, and an employer that lacks these basic protections, then a lot of people who need work, who seek work, simply won’t feel comfortable.” Stuart Appelbaum, the president of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, the organization that recruited the task force to join the fight against Wal-Mart’s setting up shop in New York, said other gay advocacy groups had also criticized the giant retailer’s record on gay rights. One of those is the Stonewall Democratic Club of New York City. Wal-Mart, however, rejects the argument that it is not welcoming to gay employees, citing its Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Associate Resource Group (pdf) as a place where employees can build a sense of community. “Diversity and inclusion are enduring values that are fundamental to our culture,” said Steven Restivo, a Wal-Mart spokesman, “which includes a focus on having respect for our colleagues and customers.” The City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, also criticized Wal-Mart for its record on this gay issues. “This lack of inclusion in its diversity policies is the antithesis of what we in N.Y.C. want and expect from our corporate partners,” she said in a statement. “These are yet two more reasons why Wal-Mart is a poor fit to do business in N.Y.C.”</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/23/business/economy/23shop.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart’s U.S. Sales Fall, Missing Projections<date>Published: February 22, 2011</date><text>As the Christmas season approached, Wal-Mart Stores said it was fixing the problems in its United States division. It hired new executives, added merchandise that it had cut, and fought with Target and other competitors to provide the lowest prices over the holidays.But for Wal-Mart, the world’s largest retailer, the fourth quarter was the seventh consecutive quarter of declining sales at stores open at least a year in the United States, a measure known as same-store sales. The decline of 1.8 percent missed the company projection. In November, it said that same-store sales for the fourth quarter would range from a decline of 1 percent to a gain of 2 percent. Same-store sales are an important indicator of a retailer’s health, as they tend to reflect whether in-store changes are working or not. “Some of the pricing and merchandising issues in Wal-Mart ran deeper than we initially expected, and they require a response that will take time to see results,” Michael T. Duke, president and chief executive, said in a statement. Store traffic also declined in the quarter and for the year. Company executives and analysts said consumers seemed to have changed their ways during the recession, and that has persisted into the sluggish recovery. New shopping habits, like using less credit, relying more on month-to-month cash and buying in smaller packages, have hampered Wal-Mart’s ability to climb out of the sales slump. In addition, while consumers are still using Wal-Mart for big shopping trips, they are visiting drugstores and dollar stores for in-between purchases. Sales overall in the United States fell in the quarter, by 0.5 percent to $71.1 billion. Total sales, however, rose 2.5 percent to $115.6 billion. Including its United States, international and Sam’s Club divisions, Wal-Mart earned $5.02 billion, or $1.41 a share, from continuing operations compared with $4.82 billion or $1.26 a share, in the fourth quarter a year ago. For the 2011 fiscal year, earnings rose 6.3 percent to $15.4 billion. Wal-Mart continues to manage expenses aggressively, and excluding one-time items, earnings were $1.34 a share, which beat analyst estimates by 3 cents. William S. Simon, who was promoted in the summer to oversee Wal-Mart’s business in the United States, suggested that the general merchandise category — which includes items like apparel, hardware or seasonal items, and excludes food — could take a long time to improve. “Our goal is to gain traction on these before we get into the general-merchandise-rich fourth quarter,” Mr. Simon said, according to prepared remarks. In the fourth quarter of 2010, the problems stemmed from several areas. Toy sales were down in American stores, though Wal-Mart had aggressively promoted prices and added back toys to its aisles. Apparel continued to be a problem. And in consumables — basics like toilet paper and soap — Wal-Mart said its prices and sizes were a problem for shoppers who continued to be on tight budgets. Customers’ use of government assistance programs to pay for Wal-Mart American goods rose about 0.5 percent from the fourth quarter last year. About 80 percent of payments are still made with some form of cash (including debit cards), while the use of credit cards dropped from the year-earlier period. Revised spending habits contributed to the decline in traffic, Charles M. Holley Jr., executive vice president and chief financial officer, said in a call with reporters. “It’s not a case that we’re not correctly priced,” Mr. Holley said. For example, he said Wal-Mart’s price-per-ounce for laundry detergent was usually lower than competitors’, but competitors like dollar stores often sold smaller bottles or boxes that were cheaper. “Some of our customers at the end of the month may have only a fixed amount left,” he said, “and even if it’s more per ounce, if the price point is more attractive at a competitor, at the end of the month that’s all they can spend.” “That’s something we’re addressing right now,” he said. Also, he said, “we lost some of what we call the fill-in trip. People were still coming to the store to do their big shopping trip, but when they needed bread, milk, detergent quickly, we did lose some of that.” Speaking of where shoppers were going instead, he said, “I think it’s probably the convenience and somebody that has low price points, and dollar stores would certainly fit that category.” Wal-Mart also blamed electronics for much of the fourth-quarter sales decline, as prices on TVs were falling, though it said the number of TVs sold rose. Categories like food and health and wellness performed well in American stores, the company said. And sales continued to increase in the international division, by 8.9 percent to $31.4 billion for the quarter. But the company says it does not know exactly when things will get better in its American stores. It said it expected first-quarter 2011 same-store sales to be flat to down 2 percent. “We would hope we would start seeing some improvement throughout the year,” Mr. Holley said. Home Depot had a different fourth-quarter story, with its biggest same-store sales increase in five years. The sales increase of 4.8 percent at United States stores open at least a year was caused in part by aggressive holiday promotions, with appliance deals after Thanksgiving, and a 12 percent increase in seasonal merchandise that sold out, Carol Tomé, chief financial officer, said in an interview. Also, she said, the $1,500 federal energy tax credit that expired at the end of December brought in customers for items like windows, doors and skylights. Net income at Home Depot rose to $587 million, or 36 cents a share, for the fourth quarter, up from $342 million, or 20 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts expected earnings of 31 cents a share. Macy’s also beat analyst expectations, reporting on Tuesday that its fourth-quarter income was $1.55 a share, or $667 million, up from $1.05 a share, or $445 million, a year ago. Excluding one-time charges, income was $1.57 a share, which beat analyst expectations by 5 cents. Macy’s said its strategy of localizing merchandise for different cities was a crucial contributor to its performance.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/02/14/wal-marts-south-african-deal-advances/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart's South African Deal Advances<date>February 14, 2011, 7:44 am</date><text>South Africa’s competition watchdog has recommended that Wal-Mart’s proposed takeover of the country’s retail chain Massmart be unconditionally approved. Wal-Mart made a $2.4 billion bid for Massmart in November, and a vast majority of the target company’s shareholders voted to approve the deal last month. The offer will now go before the country’s competition tribunal, though a date for the hearing and subsequent ruling has yet to be set. “It is difficult to predict exact timing as this is largely dependent on the availability of suitable dates on the Tribunal’s roll,” Massmart’s chief executive, Grant Pattison, said in a company statement on Saturday. Wal-Mart is seeking to capitalize on South Africa’s economic growth by buying 51 percent of Massmart, which will remain listed on the country’s stock exchange. The proposed deal would be Wal-Mart’s largest since buying Asda of Britain in 1999.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/12/nyregion/12metjournal.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">In Wal-Mart’s Silence, Critics Focus on East New York<date>Published: February 11, 2011</date><text>It isn’t much to look at, just a big empty lot packed with snow and some struggling cattail plants sandwiched between the Starrett City apartment complex and a shopping mall. But a field in the East New York section of Brooklyn has become one of the most hotly debated spots in New York City. All because it may — possibly, one day— be home to the city’s first Wal-Mart store.Details on Wal-Mart’s plans to move into the city are scarce, but because this slice of Brooklyn has been mentioned most often, by real estate brokers and in the pages of newspapers, as a leading contender for a store, opponents have directed their fight here. “It’s a little bit of Kabuki theater on both sides,” said Richard Lipsky, a lobbyist for small businesses who is helping lead the campaign to keep Wal-Mart out of New York. Not having a specific site to focus on, he explained, “makes it more difficult to hone in on an organizing strategy.” “But in spite of that,” Mr. Lipsky said, “the organizing is going forward.” Lining up against the retail giant are a wide range of people who say the expansion will hurt small businesses and their employees, including elected officials like Councilman Charles Barron, who represents East New York; the public advocate, Bill de Blasio; immigrant groups; clergy members; unions representing retail workers; and small-business owners. Wal-Mart, however, has drawn its own group of supporters, including community leaders and members of the real estate community, who argue that a store would create jobs and provide a bigger variety of goods with lower prices in a neighborhood that could use both. Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has said the company has a right to be in the city. But even many of the supporters say they do not know where the company hopes to open up shop. (Neither Wal-Mart nor the site’s developer, the Related Companies, has said if they are in negotiations.) Some of the mystery stems from Wal-Mart’s real estate strategy. It is focusing on sites that require no special approval, as opposed to those that would need a green light from the City Council, which at a recent hearing made clear that it was no fan of Wal-Mart. In East New York, all that Wal-Mart would need to do is sign a lease. A store there would become part of a huge project that has already been approved by the Council and includes several thousand units of housing and an expansion of the existing Gateway Center shopping mall. Wal-Mart’s opponents are crying foul, saying the plan approved by the Council in 2009 did not include the chain. “It was a total bait and switch,” said Bertha Lewis, the former chief executive of the community organizing group Acorn who is helping to organize the opposition throughout the city. Though company representatives have revealed nothing about specific locations, they say that their strategy for urban areas across the United States focuses on neighborhoods with little access to fresh food and where unemployment runs high. And while East New York has experienced some economic improvements in recent years — the city’s Economic Development Corporation counted a gain of more than 200 businesses from 2000 to 2008 — it is still one of New York’s most distressed neighborhoods and a place where supermarkets, and their fresh fruits and vegetables, are scarce. East New York’s unemployment rate is estimated at 13.9 percent, compared with a 9.4 percent rate citywide, according to the latest data from the Fiscal Policy Institute, a nonprofit research organization. And while neighborhood crime dropped 30 percent from 2001 to 2010 — citywide, the figure was 35 percent — it remains one of the most violent parts of the city, according to the Police Department. The 75th Precinct, which serves the area, recorded 33 killings last year, 9 more than the previous year. The property being debated is on the southernmost edge of East New York, not far from the Brooklyn waterfront. Though the Belt Parkway is nearby and the site is served by public buses, it is more than a mile to the nearest subway stop and not easily accessible for most of the neighborhood. It is also in the shadow of an existing mall, and many of Wal-Mart’s supporters question why critics are so concerned about the effect Wal-Mart would have on local businesses when other chain stores, like Target and Marshalls, are there already. Workers at some neighborhood stores are nervous all the same. “You had to say the ‘W’ word?” said Alicia Boake, a department manager at a Pathmark supermarket in East New York and a member of a union that opposes Wal-Mart. Ms. Boake said she worried that while shoppers go to Target for certain items, they would go to Wal-Mart for just about everything else, including low-priced groceries, putting other stores out of business. “It could mean the end of a lot of things for a lot of people,” she said. But some shoppers say they would welcome more options. Stacey Clement, a local resident who works at Bellevue Hospital Center, smiled broadly when asked if she would like to see a Wal-Mart in her neighborhood. “They have everything in one place,” Ms. Clement said, pulling her grocery cart out of the trunk of a livery cab outside of Pathmark. “I would just go there.” And a store promising low prices is certainly enticing for the many people who must carefully count their pennies, some local neighborhood advocates said. “East New York is suffering,” said Christopher Banks, the executive director of the East New York United Concerned Citizens, an antipoverty group, noting the community’s jobless rate. “And with this economy, people want to get a good bang for their buck. At the end of the day, you have to think with your pocket.” This article has been revised to reflect the following correction: Correction: February 11, 2011 An earlier headline with this article erroneously referred to Wal-Mart as Mart-Mart.</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/04/nyregion/04walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Skips Hearing on Its New York City Plans<date>Published: February 3, 2011</date><text>It was a moment long planned and carefully prepared for — a moment that had twice been delayed by snow. But when the moment finally arrived, the main protagonist was missing.The City Council held a hearing on Thursday afternoon to examine the economic impact Wal-Mart would have should it succeed in opening its first stores in New York City. But Wal-Mart’s official representatives were no-shows, which was something company officials had made clear would happen weeks ago when the hearing was first scheduled. So critics, from council members to representatives of small businesses, had no one to direct their anger at and spent hours making the same familiar arguments — the death of family-owned businesses, poor labor practices by Wal-Mart — to a mostly sympathetic audience. The reason no one from Wal-Mart accepted an invitation, a spokesman for the retail giant said, was that it felt it was being singled out unfairly in a city full of big-box stores, including Home Depot, Sears and Target. “Our decision not to attend today’s hearing has nothing to do with our willingness to answer questions or our belief that our stores would be good for New York City,” the spokesman, Steven Restivo, said, “and everything to do with the hypothetical nature of the proceedings and the fact that it ignores the hundreds of similarly sized stores that exist in the city today.” The Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, wasted no time pointing out Wal-Mart’s absence. “I want to say how deeply disappointed I am that one very important part of the equation, Wal-Mart, decided not to join us here today,” she said as the hearing began. She said the company’s “refusal to attend, sadly, only leads me to be further skeptical about them as a company.” Several council members said they shared her misgivings. “My community needs jobs, but even if you’re hungry, someone shouldn’t feed you garbage,” Councilman Jumaane D. Williams of Brooklyn said. The verbal volleys against Wal-Mart started early. At a rally on the steps of City Hall before the hearing, a crowd of more than 300 people waved anti-Wal-Mart signs as the public advocate, Bill de Blasio, called the company destructive and a “Trojan horse.” And Councilman Charles Barron, who represents the East New York section of Brooklyn, one of the places where Wal-Mart is considering opening a store, called the store “a plantation.” Two hours into the hearing, Andy Sullivan, the founder of a group called 911 Hard Hats and a union construction worker who had come to testify in favor of Wal-Mart, stood up and complained that no one on his side had yet had a chance to testify. When it was his turn, Mr. Sullivan noted that Wal-Mart had recently made final a deal with a politically powerful construction union, the Building and Construction Trades Council, promising to build and renovate its stores in the five boroughs with union workers for five years. Wal-Mart used the same strategy to gain support for stores in Chicago several years ago. “The pain is here, it is now,” Mr. Sullivan during his testimony, citing what he said was a 30 percent unemployment rate among unionized construction workers. “It’s not being caused by Wal-Mart. Wal-Mart’s not here!” Charles Fisher, the chairman of the Hip-Hop Summit Youth Council in Harlem, also spoke in favor of Wal-Mart. Last year, Wal-Mart flew Mr. Fisher down to its headquarters in Bentonville, Ark., at the company’s expense, for a three-day “stakeholder summit” of community leaders from around the country. Instead of speaking directly to the Council, Wal-Mart, which has not announced a specific store opening in New York, has begun an all-out publicity drive, with direct mailings, radio advertisements and a Facebook page. Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who has said that New York should be open to any legal business that wants to come here, was asked by a reporter on Thursday about the hearing and if it was in the city’s best interest to let Wal-Mart set up shop. “You should let the marketplace decide,” he said. “Anybody who has tried to manage the marketplace, it has not turned out very well. I think the Soviet Union is as good an example as you’d ever need of that.”</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="8">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/27/nyregion/27walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Opponents in New York Include Its Shoppers<date>Published: December 26, 2010</date><text>SECAUCUS, N.J. — Shawneequa Clark, who lives in Brooklyn, goes to Wal-Mart several times a month. She appreciates the variety, she enjoys the grocery selection, and she takes advantage of the savings.In short, she loves Wal-Mart. As long as it stays in New Jersey. Wal-Mart has begun another aggressive lobbying campaign to build a store in New York City. Company officials argue that New Yorkers already shop at Wal-Mart and that expanding into the city would make it more convenient for them. But interviews with New Yorkers shopping here on a recent day revealed some surprising views: even some of Wal-Mart’s loyal customers would rather drive to the bargains than risk bringing those low prices — along with the crowds and competition that may come with them — closer to home. “I don’t believe Wal-Mart should be in the city,” Ms. Clark, 29, said. “All the local mom-and-pop stores would lose business. And it’s already congested. I mean, can you just imagine?” Last year, New York City residents spent $165 million at Wal-Mart stores, including those in Secaucus, Saddle Brook, N.J., and Valley Stream, N.Y. (The company tracks spending through credit card addresses.) The chain is looking at locations in all five boroughs, and a contentious debate has begun about the company’s labor policies and potential effect on neighborhood retail areas. Outside the 189,000-square-foot Wal-Mart in Secaucus, Vinny Nicosia, 52, who lives in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, said he could not support a store in the city. “I’m not opposed to it in out-of-the-way places, but in the middle of the city, it’s tough,” Mr. Nicosia said. “It kills the neighborhood shops. I grew up in the neighborhood shops, and I don’t want them to go away.” Steven Restivo, a spokesman for Wal-Mart, rejected the idea that the chain hurts small businesses. “In the majority of cases our stores serve as a magnet for growth and development,” Mr. Restivo said. “We have more than 140 million customers that shop our stores each week, and what we find is that businesses that can take advantage of the increase in customer traffic succeed.” He also said Wal-Mart would make adjustments for New York City, including opening smaller stores. Although its stores can be well over 150,000 square feet, some of those planned for the city would be under 30,000. The Partnership for New York City, a business group, is backing Wal-Mart. Kathryn S. Wylde, the partnership’s president, said the stores could attract development and commerce, much as anchor stores in malls do. “You get a big destination store to draw the traffic, then fill in with small stores, and everybody benefits,” she said. “It’s just a function of them figuring out the right location.” Of course, there are New Yorkers who would be happy to have a Wal-Mart in their city. Of the dozen residents interviewed while shopping in Secaucus on a recent afternoon, half said they would oppose the retailer, while half said they would welcome it. Frank Clark, an 80-year-old retiree who makes trips to New Jersey several times a month to go to Wal-Mart with his wife, Frances, 75, said he would love to have a store closer to his home, in Fort Hamilton, Brooklyn. “Absolutely!” he said. “If you’re on a fixed income, it’s great.” “I’ll tell you how good the savings are,” he added. “I drive over the Verrazano Bridge, I go over the Bayonne Bridge and I come here, and those two bridges cost me $17, plus the price of gas. And I still make out better buying here than if I did in my own neighborhood.” Other New Yorkers shopping at Wal-Mart said they did not understand what the fuss was about, in light of the other big retailers that now dot the city. “There’s a Kmart where I live, there’s a Kmart near my job,” said Joe Gregory, 44, a postal worker from the Bronx, who came to Wal-Mart to buy a remote-controlled puppy for his 8-year-old daughter. Mr. Gregory said that he did not see much difference between the two chains, and that he would be perfectly happy to have a Wal-Mart nearby. Nonetheless, the fight from unions, city officials and community groups is likely to be fierce. City Council hearings are expected to begin next month. “There is a finite amount of shopping dollars out there, and if Wal-Mart is absorbing a huge percentage of them, they aren’t left for the other retailers,” said Richard Lipsky, a lobbyist for local businesses who is fighting Wal-Mart. “If you want a bargain, you get in your car and you go to the bargain. You don’t ever want to bring the bargain into the neighborhood.”</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/22/business/22sears.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Sears Struggles 5 Years After Kmart Merger<date>Published: December 21, 2010</date><text>This holiday season, Sears and Kmart, which merged in 2005, are pushing a single message: Buy with layaway, buy with coupons, buy now and pay later, buy with loyalty rewards points — but please, just buy.Five years after the merger, Sears Holdings is beleaguered, with sales markedly worse than its competitors’. The company’s revenue dropped more than 10 percent from 2005 through 2009, the most recent full fiscal year. In the same time period, Wal-Mart’s sales rose almost 31 percent, Target’s more than 24 percent and Macy’s about 5 percent. Sales at J. C. Penney’s declined by about 6 percent. Recently, too, as shoppers seem to be cautiously loading their carts again, Sears Holdings has not benefited. In the first three-quarters of this year, Sears Holdings’ sales are down about 1.9 percent compared to the same period last year, while the competition moved into positive territory. Edward S. Lampert, the billionaire hedge fund manager who engineered the merger and is chairman of the company, has promised that Sears Holdings will be “unrecognizable” in 30 years. To drive sales, it is emphasizing online shopping, mobile apps and an Amazon.com-like marketplace with other vendors, along with heavy promotions in stores. Still, its long-term strategy remains murky, analysts say. Sears Holdings is primarily a physical retailer, and many of its 2,200 stores in the United States are run-down and in undesirable locations. Among discount stores, Kmart lags Wal-Mart and Target. Sears is trying to edge out Lowes and Home Depot in appliances on the one hand, and Macy’s and J. C. Penney in apparel on the other. “People assume that Eddie’s got some magic formula,” said Gary Balter, an analyst with Credit Suisse. “If you’re Sears, you’ve got a problem because you’re trying to sell a product in a dilapidated building,” he said. And Kmart stores are “about a quarter the sales productivity of Wal-Mart,” he said. “How do you compete?” When Mr. Lampert combined Kmart and Sears in an $11.9 billion deal that went through in 2005, many of the same analysts considered it a smart move. Mr. Lampert, who became the majority owner of Kmart after it went into bankruptcy, said then that he wanted to combine the best of both, putting brands like Kenmore and Craftsman into Kmarts, and building Sears’s presence outside of malls by turning some stand-alone Kmart stores into Sears stores. Some attractive store locations, particularly in urban areas, led analysts to believe he could sell those to competitors for premium prices. But the sudden consumer pullback in 2008 led to lots of empty retail space, at less expensive prices than Mr. Lampert’s. Today, Mr. Balter said, Sears Holdings still has some showcase spots, in high-end, high-traffic areas like Bergen County, N.J.; South Coast Plaza in Costa Mesa, Calif.; and in Manhattan and Bridgehampton, N.Y. But much of the remaining real estate in older, decrepit malls is a problem, Mr. Balter said. “Of the 2000, there’s 1,500 that you don’t want to be in, that nobody’s going to buy,” he said. (It also has a growing division of about 1,600 specialty stores, like small hardware stores and outlets. ) The better locations “are where Sears and Kmart are making their money — if you sell those, what are you going to be left with?” Mr. Balter said. Mr. Lampert has also not invested much in the stores themselves, analysts said. In 2009, capital spending only amounted to 0.82 percent of sales. That is about half of Macy’s spending, at 1.51 percent of sales, and a fraction of the spending at Target, Wal-Mart, J. C. Penney and even publicly traded dollar stores, all of which are at 2 percent and above. In an interview, David Friedman, Sears Holdings’s new senior vice president and president of marketing, played down the importance of appearance. “The customer’s experience is made up of lots of pieces,” he said. “The in-store experience is one of those that matters a lot, and we believe that the physical plant is one piece of it, but we believe the associates and the products drive the in-store experience.” Sears Holdings is experimenting with new layouts and fixtures and will introduce those more widely if they are shown to improve sales. And Tom Aiello, a Sears spokesman, said in an e-mail that brightness and cleanliness were priorities, and noted that customer-satisfaction scores had risen this year. The stores’ products pose another challenge. Sears has long commanded the appliance world, but Home Depot and Lowes are formidable up-and-comers. In 2009, Sears still led the group with a little more than $7.1 billion in major appliance sales, according to This Week in Consumer Electronics magazine and the Stevenson Company. But its appliance sales fell 8.2 percent that year. Lowes came in second, with $4.5 billion, up 3.8 percent, and Home Depot was in third with $3.4 billion, a 4.3 percent decline.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/12/22/the-gift-of-guns-courtesy-of-cerberus/?ref=walmartstoresinc">The Gift of Guns, Courtesy of Cerberus<date>December 22, 2010, 5:02 pm</date><text>For employees of AlixPartners, finding a last-minute holiday gift may have gotten a little easier. Thanks to some holiday generosity from a client, Cerberus Capital Management‘s Remington Arms, staff members at the consultancy can choose from an array of rifles and shotguns — with a 33 percent discount. In an internal memorandum obtained by DealBook, an AlixPartners director, Ralf Schwarzendahl, informed employees that Remington has opened up its “friends and family” discount program to the firm. (Other companies that work closely with the gun maker have also been extended the offer.) Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links AlixPartners internal memo The attached flier noted that the offer applied to about 91 bolt-action rifles, repeating shotguns and .22 caliber rimfire rifles. Free shipping? Naturally — but, as Mr. Schwarzendahl says, employees still have to pay the federal transfer fee that some dealers charge. The program began on Dec. 8 and runs through Jan. 19. “AlixPartners takes discretion very seriously and, generally, does not comment on matters of this sort,” said a spokesman for the consulting firm. A quick check of the Remington program’s Web site shows an average discount of about 33 percent. So if one were considering, say, the Model 870 Express Shurshot pump-action shotgun , expect to pay about $371.14 instead of the manufacturer’s suggested retail price of $553.94. (The guns are apparently a little souped up from their base configurations, whose suggested retail prices are a little lower.) In the memo, Mr. Schwarzendahl advises those who want to check out the wares in person first should head to retailers like Dick’s Sporting Goods or Wal-Mart. Remington is one of several arms makers owned by Cerberus through its Freedom Group. Based in Madison, N.C., the company’s other brands include Bushmaster and Barnes Bullets, all gained through a series of roll-ups of various gun makers. It also fits nicely into one of the pastimes of Cerberus’s founder, Stephen A. Feinberg, whose passion for hunting produced the massive elk head that sits on his office wall. Freedom had been one of the more profitable recent investments by Cerberus, which is seeking to take the company public. Freedom reported nearly $849 million in sales last year, up 17 percent from 2008, and a $54 million profit, a turnaround from a loss the previous year. But Freedom hit a bit of rockiness in the fall. It reported a $300,000 loss for the three months that ended Sept. 30, a sharp reversal from the $15.1 million it earned at the same time last year. Net sales had fallen about 12 percent during the same time as well, to $207.6 million. In September, Cerberus named the former Home Depot chief executive Robert L. Nardelli as the company’s new head of the office of the chief executive. AlixPartners Memo for Remington Friends and Family Discount</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/17/us/17cncpulse.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Beyond Wal-Mart, Ex-Opponents Unite in Chicago - The Pulse<date>Published: December 16, 2010</date><text>Beyond Wal-Mart,Ex-Opponents Unite Not long ago, Delmarie Cobb, a veteran political consultant, helped organize opposition to a Wal-Mart store planned for the Pullman neighborhood on the far South Side. Now she is working to re-elect that development’s chief supporter in the City Council, Alderman Anthony A. Beale of the 9th Ward. Ms. Cobb said she had not sold out her anti-Wal-Mart allies. “One of the things Roland Burris said years ago to me that I came to agree with as I got older: If you agree with an elected official or candidate on 7 out of 10 things, then you can find common ground,” said Ms. Cobb, referring to the former senator, who once was one of her clients. Ms. Cobb has worked closely with Mr. Beale since he was first elected in 1999, but she broke with him earlier this year by joining a coalition of community groups and unions that tried unsuccessfully to pressure Wal-Mart into paying its employees a starting wage of $11.03 an hour. Both Ms. Cobb and Mr. Beale said they did not have any hard feelings toward each other, though Ms. Cobb said she still wanted Wal-Mart to pay a higher wage. “To some degree, I have to be a pragmatist,” she said. “I can have my principles — and I do — but when all is said and done, if it’s the law of the land, if it’s the law of the city, if it’s passed the City Council, then who am I railing against?” Ms. Cobb said she expected Wal-Mart to give Mr. Beale money for his campaign, and he said the retailer was likely to “support anyone who helps them.” HUNTER CLAUSS Zoo Protests Tax Levied by Brookfield The fur is flying at the Brookfield Zoo, where officials have denounced an amusement tax approved Monday by the president and board of trustees of the Village of Brookfield, saying it is illegal and unnecessary. The tax, expected to raise $500,000 annually, will be levied in a 25-cent increase in the price of zoo tickets. Matthew Mayer, a spokesman for the Chicago Zoological Society, which manages the zoo, said it was the latest of several efforts to charge the zoo for village services. “We have a distressed operating budget, and $60 million in critical infrastructure repairs that must be made over the next four years,” Mr. Mayer said. “And now the village is trying to divert an increase in our admission payments.” The state statute that created the zoo prohibits admission fees from being sent elsewhere, Mr. Mayer said. Village officials have said that the revenue is due them because the zoo uses municipal services, like the police and snowplowing. Mr. Mayer disagreed. “The zoo is a self-sustaining entity,” he said. Village officials did not return calls seeking comment. Some animals will be sent to other facilities as a result of budget cuts, Mr. Mayer said, but visitors’ favorites, including the Seven Seas’ dolphins and the Great Bear Wilderness exhibit, will not be affected. “It won’t be any animals that will impact the guest experience,” he said. Put another way: The cutest animals are safe. Giant anteater, the bell may toll for thee. JESSICA REAVES</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/13/nyregion/13walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Tries Again for New York City Store<date>Published: December 12, 2010</date><text>Correction Appended The New York City Council was supposed to hold a hearing this Tuesday about a renewed campaign by Wal-Mart to open its stores in the city.But it had to be rescheduled, for January. “We needed a bigger room,” the Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, said. “We heard from unions all across the city, small business leaders from across the city. It’s a growing list of people.” Wal-Mart, an inescapable part of the retail landscape just about everywhere except in New York City, twice retreated on efforts to open stores in the city after fierce community opposition. Now it is back, and mounting an aggressive campaign to crack the country’s largest urban market. Wal-Mart is looking at properties in each of the five boroughs and has hired Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg’s former campaign manager, Bradley Tusk, to help coordinate its lobbying efforts. Bill de Blasio, the city’s public advocate, predicted, “They’re not going to find it easy to get serious public support.” “As you reap,” Mr. de Blasio added, “so shall you sow, and they’ve had a really bad history. You can talk to people across the spectrum and they’ve all heard something about the problems of Wal-Mart.” The renewed push by Wal-Mart comes five years after the retailer tried to open stores in Queens and Staten Island but faced furious opposition from community leaders and elected officials. But the retailer and its supporters, and even its opponents, say that the dynamics have changed and that the city has become more receptive to so-called big-box stores, like Target and Ikea. But perhaps the greatest difference is the economy. With the city’s unemployment rate hovering around 9 percent, any project that promises jobs might find appeal. “This is a time when the economy is bad and a lot of my constituents are looking for jobs,” said Darryl C. Towns, a state assemblyman whose Brooklyn district includes East New York, one area Wal-Mart is considering. “We have to begin to think out of the box and look at some different opportunities.” Wal-Mart is the country’s largest private employer, with 1.4 million workers, but it has been a constant target for labor groups who say its wages are too low and its benefits insufficient. The United States Supreme Court recently agreed to hear the nation’s biggest employment discrimination suit, which claims that Wal-Mart has discriminated against female employees in pay and promotion. “There are some people who say, ‘Well, if Wal-Mart comes in, that means jobs,’ ” said Stuart Appelbaum, the president of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, which supported the efforts to stop Wal-Mart the last time it tried to open stores in New York. “But what it does is, it replaces good jobs with jobs that keep people in poverty.” Other big-box stores that have gained a foothold in New York, like Costco, provide far better compensation than Wal-Mart, some labor leaders said. And critics say Wal-Mart would also spell doom for nearby small businesses that could never compete with the giant retailer on price and selection. But some Wal-Mart supporters say protecting businesses that charge higher prices is unfair to consumers, especially when so many New Yorkers are worried about their finances. “Competition means people have to step up and compete or it’s not going to work out,” said Steven Spinola, the president of the Real Estate Board of New York. “I don’t think government should say that we’re going to make sure people have to pay more or travel farther because we want to protect certain types of establishments.” This time, Wal-Mart is using different tactics to make stores more palatable to neighbors. Steven Restivo, a spokesman for Wal-Mart, said the retailer was looking at sites of all sizes, including land parcels that would accommodate stores that — by its standards — are quite small, under 30,000 square feet. Many Wal-Marts are five times that size. The company is working with a commercial real estate broker to talk to property owners. “There is a business case to be made for our growth in large cities across the country,” Mr. Restivo said. “We know we have customers there, and we know we want to make access to our brand more convenient.” Wal-Mart might also look to build stores in New York that are small enough to require only a willing landlord and a lease, bypassing the City Council, which must give special zoning approval to projects over 10,000 square feet in some manufacturing districts. About a year ago, the Council defeated a plan, which had been supported by the mayor, to redevelop the Kingsbridge Armory in the Bronx into a major commercial complex. This year, Wal-Mart has also expanded its pitch, promoting itself as a solution to problems beyond unemployment. Mr. Restivo said that in its hunt for real estate, the company was focusing on areas that were “underserved” both economically and in their access to fresh food. Providing more fruits and vegetables to these so-called food deserts is a crucial issue for both Mr. Bloomberg and Ms. Quinn, the council speaker. And in an effort that is likely to anger other labor groups, Wal-Mart is working to win the support of one powerful union group, the Building and Construction Trades Council, and is negotiating a deal that would guarantee that stores would be built and renovated by union workers. But there is still enormous opposition, from unions, community groups and elected leaders, to the idea of a Wal-Mart rising in any city neighborhood. One union official, Pat Purcell, an aide to the president of the UFCW Local 1500, which represents supermarket workers, said, “This is not a battle, this is a war.” Mr. Bloomberg, who invested major political capital in trying to win support for the Kingsbridge Armory proposal, told reporters recently that he “would love to see Wal-Mart open here,” noting that many New Yorkers travel to Nassau County or New Jersey to shop at Wal-Mart. “You’re not going to stop, and nor should you stop, people from having the opportunity to shop where they want to shop,” Mr. Bloomberg said. “The city should not be in the business of picking and choosing who is there.”</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="9">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/18/business/18retail.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Target Says It Expects Better Holiday Sales<date>Published: November 17, 2010</date><text>The Target Corporation said it expected to post its best same-store sales in three years during the holiday season, sending its shares up.The discount chain benefited from the strong performance of its credit card business in its third quarter. It said it believed that it would lure more shoppers during the holidays with a new credit card program that offers 5 percent off all purchases and a bigger array of fresh food. Wal-Mart said Tuesday that it expected to break a six-quarter streak of same-store sales declines in the United States during the holiday shopping season in the fourth quarter. “Target has more catalysts behind it right now (for a) better holiday season than Wal-Mart,” said Brian Sozzi, an analyst at Wall Street Strategies. He has a rating of neutral on both chains. Separately, BJ’s Wholesale Club posted a higher-than-expected quarterly profit, helped by cost cuts, and raised its full-year forecast, which sent its shares up more than 3 percent. Target’s sales in the United States have grown as consumers who feel more secure in their jobs trade up to its stores from rivals like Wal-Mart for trendier clothing and home furnishings. Traffic at its stores rose more than 2 percent in the third quarter and the company forecast a same-store sales rise of 2 to 4 percent in the fourth quarter. “While consumers remain conservative in their purchasing behavior, we’re encouraged by recent signs in the broader economy that may signal somewhat stronger and more stable sales in the coming months,” Gregg W. Steinhafel, Target’s chief executive, said in a call, citing a slightly improved job market. He expects the company’s merchandising plans and credit card discounts will drive fourth-quarter same-store sales to be the “best of any quarter in the last three years.” Target is also betting on its store credit cards and has said that shoppers who use them typically spend 50 percent more at its stores over the course of a year. Many retail investors are betting on discounters this year as shoppers search for bargains in a slowly recovering economy. Target’s earnings for the third quarter, which ended Oct. 30, rose to $535 million, or 74 cents a share, from $436 million, or 58 cents a share, a year earlier. Excluding a tax benefit, that matched the analysts’ average estimate. Target previously said sales rose 3 percent, to $15.23 billion in the third quarter. Sales at stores open at least a year rose 1.6 percent. BJ’s results reflected increased membership income and share buybacks. BJ’s said net income rose to $23 million, or 43 cents a share, in its third quarter, which ended in October, from $17.4 million, or 32 cents a share, a year earlier. Analysts on average were expecting earnings of 36 cents a share, according to Thomson Reuters. Excluding a charge for a legal settlement, the year-earlier profit was 45 cents a share. Earlier this month, the company said sales rose 4.8 percent, to $2.57 billion. The company now expects full-year earnings of $2.48 to $2.52 a share, compared with its previous outlook of $2.40 to $2.50. Analysts on average forecast $2.45. Shares of BJ’s rose $1.37, or 3 percent, to $47.54. Shares of Target rose $2.08, or 3.8 percent, to $55.62.</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/17/business/17shop.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Profit Rises, but Same-Store Sales Fall<date>Published: November 16, 2010</date><text>The tepid economic recovery does not seem to be extending to many of Wal-Mart’s customers in the United States, lower-income consumers who are not yet spending. The nation’s largest retailer reported Tuesday that sales in its American stores open at least a year, a crucial measure of retail health, had declined for the sixth consecutive quarter.Net income at Wal-Mart Stores rose 9.3 percent, to $3.44 billion, or 95 cents a share, in the third quarter, which ended in October, because of international growth and cost-cutting. Revenue rose 2.6 percent, to $101.95 billion. The earnings were in line with analysts’ estimates; revenue came in slightly below what analysts had expected. In the United States, where revenue dropped 1.3 percent in Wal-Mart stores open at least a year, a measure known as same-store sales, executives said that they were continuing with changes like increasing the number of items for sale, adding more $1-and-under products and underselling competitors. Still, visits to Wal-Mart’s American stores declined from a year ago, as did the average price paid at checkout, Wal-Mart executives said. “They’re focused on necessities and being practical with how they spend their money,” Charles M. Holley Jr., executive vice president for finance, said of customers in a call with reporters. “We still see what we call the paycheck cycle, where you see the spikes in comps the day or two after a payroll check,” or after shoppers receive government payments, he said. “It’s every bit as pronounced as we’ve seen it.” This summer, Wal-Mart made management changes at its United States division, putting Bill Simon in charge and replacing the head of merchandising. Mr. Simon has been increasing the inventory Wal-Mart carries, adding back merchandise that had been removed to present a less cluttered look. “Last year we probably played our cards a little bit too close to the vest on inventory, and may have missed out on some sales — we’re trying to avoid that here in the fourth quarter,” Wal-Mart’s chief financial officer, Thomas M. Schoewe, said Tuesday. As a result, inventory was up 6.5 percent in the third quarter in Wal-Mart’s American stores, compared with the period a year ago. Mr. Schoewe said Wal-Mart was being more aggressive about having enough goods in stock for holiday shoppers. And Mr. Schoewe and Mr. Holley said that while the stores would have low prices, particularly on basics and practical gifts, they did not expect reduced profit margins in the fourth quarter. Wal-Mart executives have said that they expect positive same-store sales in the fourth quarter, though in the earnings report, the company said the range could be from a decline of 1 percent to an increase of 2 percent. Mr. Schoewe said in the call with reporters that the focus should be on the midpoint of that range, growth of 0.5 percent. While Wal-Mart cited economic pressures for the slow United States results, Craig Johnson, president of the consulting firm Customer Growth Partners, argued that competitors like the Aldi discount chain, dollar stores like Dollar General, Family Dollar and Dollar Tree, and Wal-Mart’s own Sam’s Club division all grew in the third quarter. “Blaming the economy doesn’t work,” Mr. Johnson said in an e-mail. “Wal-Mart U.S. has clearly been knocked back on its heels by the competition.” In a bright spot in its American operations, the company showed growth in same-store sales of food, where Wal-Mart has added back more items than in any other category, Mr. Simon said. He cited marshmallows and pie filling as examples. International stores continue to be a sales driver for Wal-Mart, with sales rising 9.3 percent, to $26.92 billion. Wal-Mart Mexico and Brazil had particularly strong performances. Shares of Wal-Mart closed up 31 cents, or 0.57 percent, at $54.26, as investors were apparently encouraged by the company’s fourth-quarter guidance. Home Depot also reported earnings on Tuesday, beating analysts’ expectations on profit by 3 cents. The retailer, citing cost-cutting, said its earnings rose 21 percent, to $834 million, or 51 cents a share, from $689 million, or 41 cents a share. Analysts had expected profit of 48 cents a share. Total revenue was $16.6 billion, up 1.4 percent. Its same-store sales in the United States rose by 1.5 percent. But as with Wal-Mart in the United States, Home Depot said its average ticket — the average amount paid at checkout — was down, and consumers weren’t buying many expensive items. Purchases under $50, which make up about 20 percent of the company’s American business, rose 2.7 percent from the same period last year. But purchases of $900 and up, also about 20 percent of the business, fell 3.4 percent. “That, in many cases, is our pro customer,” the chief financial officer, Carol B. Tomé, said in an interview. “That’s all demand-driven, and if demand is soft,” the bigger sales will decline. “Clearly, the basic repair business is good, and it has been good — those are the tickets that are $50,” she said. Over all, store traffic, measured by the number of transactions, rose 2.5 percent, but the average amount per transaction decreased by 0.8 percent. Home Depot raised its earnings guidance for the full year to $1.94 a share, from $1.90. But with the housing market still shaky, “we still think this presents a picture of continued pressure in our market,” Francis S. Blake, the chairman and chief executive, said in a call with analysts. Shares of Home Depot rose 32 cents, or 1 percent, to $31.71. “While investors will be pleased with the solid operating performance, it is difficult to see much improvement in the home improvement sector,” a Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company analyst, Colin McGranahan, wrote in a note to clients. At the luxury end of the consumer sector, Saks posted a big increase in profit, as overall sales rose and it depended less on slashing prices. Its third-quarter net income was $36.3 million, or 20 cents a share, and included a $26.7 million gain related to the reversal of certain estimated income tax reserves deemed no longer necessary. Excluding this gain, Saks would have recorded net income of $9.7 million, or 6 cents a share, compared with $6.3 million or 4 cents a share, Sales rose 4.3 percent, to $658.8 million. Its same-store sales rose 5.7 percent, with women’s categories, including dresses, shoes, apparel and fashion jewelry, performing well.</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/11/business/global/11gap.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Gap Joins a Retailer Rush to the Chinese Market<date>Published: November 10, 2010</date><text>SHANGHAI — With sales in the United States sluggish, one of America’s best-known apparel brands — Gap Inc. — is joining the rush to enter China’s fast-growing consumer market.The retailer plans to open a flagship store here on Thursday, followed this month by three other large outlets in Shanghai and Beijing, two of China’s wealthiest cities. The company also expects to eventually add its other brands, like Old Navy and Banana Republic. Some multinationals already have a huge presence in China, like McDonald’s, Coca-Cola and Procter &amp; Gamble. But American retailers are just beginning their push into this country as consumption is on the rise and an investment boom is resulting in scores of new upscale malls and shopping districts. “The timing is right,” John Ermatinger, Gap’s president for the Asia-Pacific region, said Wednesday, while touring the flagship store here as workers folded shirts and spruced up the interior. “We’ve declared that 12 percent to 25 percent of our revenue will come from the international market by 2013. And I think we can do that.” Chinese consumers are legendary for their saving habits. But analysts say China’s consumer market is likely to storm ahead in the next decade, and pass the United States. Retail sales grew by about 15 percent in China last year. The streets of Shanghai and Beijing look increasingly like New York City, Chicago or San Francisco, with Louis Vuitton, Gucci, Nike, Starbucks and Apple all seeking to entice shoppers. A report released in January by Credit Suisse predicted that by 2020 China would account for nearly a quarter of the world’s private consumption. “It is likely to provide a badly needed source of spending for the rest of the world,” the report said. The Chinese government is backing the spending spree, trying to raise salaries and encourage more consumption as part of its long-term plan to restructure the economy and create more balanced and sustainable growth. Global brands are hoping to profit from the shift. In the 1990s, Western corporations came to set up factories, and also contracted with local manufacturers to have products made here. Long before setting up its retail operations here, Gap had much of its clothing manufactured in China. Now Gap and other retailers want to market to China’s nouveau riche and the emerging middle class. With its first store, a bright and sleek 12,000-square-foot outlet in the city’s upscale Hong Kong Plaza area, Gap hopes to promote its classic 1969 jeans, winter clothing and also its baby and Gap Kids clothing lines. “We’re talking to a lot of companies that are saying, ‘I’m ready. How do I come?’ ” said Max Magni, head of the consumer practice for greater China at McKinsey &amp; Company, the consulting firm. But retailing experts warn it will not be easy. The country’s consumer market is still in the early stages of development, with consumption in smaller cities lagging far behind larger ones. National distribution is complex; marketing and television advertising is largely local; pricing is fiercely competitive; and counterfeiting is widespread, the analysts said. Wal-Mart has 189 stores in China and reported sales of about $7.5 billion last year, according to Euromonitor International, a market research firm. But of America’s 100 biggest retailers by revenue, only about a dozen operate independent stores in China. Business experts cite the challenges and high cost of doing business in China. Mr. Magni at McKinsey said that initially many brands entered China through department stores, which they considered less costly and therefore less risky. Until several years ago, there were government restrictions on foreign companies operating retail outlets, but even when those disappeared, retailers still worried about how to make sense of a complex marketplace and how to appeal to local tastes. “Some brands entered late because with clothes, you need to follow the trends and styles,” said Chen Yuxin, a professor of marketing at the Kellogg School of Management at Northwestern University. “But now, this is changing. People want to be fashionable. And they like foreign brands.” Many global retailers are scrambling to find good locations in China’s biggest cities. European retailers like Carrefour, Tesco and Metro A.G. are opening big supermarkets. Luxury brands say that in the next few years China should overtake Japan as the world’s biggest market for luxury goods. And midrange apparel retailers like H&amp;M, Zara and Uniqlo of Japan have gotten off to a strong start with new outlets in Shanghai — sometimes with long waiting lines just to enter the stores. After a lengthy study, Gap is starting off with four stores, an e-commerce site and a China advertising campaign that features photographs taken by Annie Leibovitz. Gap executives say they hope to build on the success the company had with over 100 stores it operates in Japan. They would not disclose the cost of the new China venture. Gap will market goods ranging from children to adults, while placing most of its emphasis on consumers in their mid- to late 20s. Prices in the China stores are expected to be comparable to those in the United States, meaning Gap’s initial strategy does not seem aimed at charging premiums. Still, in a country with a per capita income that is far below that in the United States, Gap will be a premium brand here. Gap Inc., based in San Francisco, is coming off a tough 2009, when the company’s global revenues declined. This year, the company’s American growth has been anemic. But like most global retailers in China, the company says it is “extremely bullish” on its prospects here. “We believe the best is yet to come in China,” said Mr. Ermatinger, the Gap executive.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/11/giving/11VETS.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Veterans Find Jobs With Help From Corporate Gifts<date>Published: November 10, 2010</date><text>MANY veterans are finding that jobs in this difficult economy require skills and training they do not have. Government data shows a higher unemployment rate for recent veterans than for the general population.A number of companies, including Microsoft, Wal-Mart, J. C. Penney and Activision Blizzard, which makes Guitar Hero and other video games, have stepped up with millions of dollars for programs that provide computer skills, green expertise and health care training. Many gifts were announced this week, tied to Veterans Day. Microsoft is giving $2 million in cash and about $4 million in software to programs that help former military members with technology skills, career counseling and job placement. Ross Janson, 30, who recently left the Navy after nine years, signed up for computer courses at Veterans Inc., a nonprofit group based in Worcester, Mass., after he could not find a job using the aircraft-maintenance expertise he acquired on active duty. “I couldn’t find anything as a mechanic, so I tried for just about anything else — fast food, copy places, you name it,” he said. He moved from the Virginia Beach area in September and found Veterans Inc., which provided him with transitional housing at a group residence and is helping him get on his feet professionally. Mr. Janson acknowledged that he needed “to put new skills into my bag of tricks” if he were going to find work. Microsoft awarded Veterans Inc. $200,000 and software to help train Mr. Janson and about 170 other vets, including some who served in the National Guard or the Reserves. Denis Leary, the group’s executive director, said the grant would allow it to add more computer courses. “We are trying to package our offerings so these vets will have a safe, affordable place to live and basic computer or other skills, so they can go out and get work to sustain themselves,” he said. Microsoft began its veterans initiative this year. In March, unemployment among Iraq and Afghanistan veterans was 14.7 percent, before dropping to 10.2 percent in September, according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics. The national unemployment rate was 9 percent that month. Microsoft chose six nonprofit groups this week, including Per Scholas Inc. in New York, for its Elevate America grants for veterans, which include transitional assistance to spouses and families. But placing retrained veterans in jobs may be growing tougher. Veterans Inc. had an 89 percent placement rate in the fiscal year ended in June, said Allison Alaimo, its director of finance and development, but in the three months starting in August, the rate fell by one-third, to 56 percent, in the “extremely challenging job market.” To help reintegrate veterans, the Wal-Mart Foundation is providing $10 million over five years to nonprofit groups, focusing on job readiness and training and higher education. Two years ago, it donated $3.6 million to colleges and nonprofit groups, including $750,000 to a group in Denver, Veterans Green Jobs, which trains returning veterans for green industry jobs. Josh Kemp, 30, an Army intelligence officer for eight years, including two tours in Iraq, was one beneficiary. After leaving the military, he earned a degree in psychology from Wichita State University in Kansas. But when he started looking for work in social services, he found that “in this economy it’s hard to find work with a bachelor’s degree, so I searched for entry-level work in other areas, but I had no luck.” Mr. Kemp found Veterans Green Jobs on the Internet and applied in January, moved to Colorado and trained for four months. He found work as a technician weatherizing people’s homes and in July was promoted to energy auditor. Now he reviews homes of people receiving state assistance to pay their energy bills and recommends energy-saving measures. Through partnerships with state and local agencies, and grants, the group has created about 100 jobs, said William Doe, its chief executive. The number of unemployed veterans persuaded Robert Kotick, chief executive of Activision Blizzard, to create a $1 million foundation to help them. The company, based in Santa Monica, Calif., last week announced a second $1 million gift. This year, the company’s Call of Duty Endowment helped 1,000 veterans, he said. Other groups around the country that help veterans with career placement and transitions include Hire Heroes USA in Georgia and Pragmatic Works in Florida. In October, J. C. Penney and the clothing brand Joseph Abboud combined for a $1 million gift for about 5,000 military veterans to buy business attire for the civilian workplace. Another unusual, smaller effort is the Farmer-Veteran Coalition, in Davis, Calif., which tries to recruit, train and place veterans in organic and other farming. Michael O’Gorman, its executive director, said federal data showed that 16 percent of Americans lived in rural communities, while 45 percent of the military members were from rural areas — and faced high levels of unemployment there if they returned. A former farmer and farm manager, Mr. O’Gorman gathered $220,000 in financing, including $50,000 from the comedian Lewis Black, to help veterans interested in farming. The coalition hosts five farming retreats, introducing around 20 veterans each session to agriculture as varied as raising organic fruits and vegetables, poultry, sheep and goats, to maintaining orchards and vineyards. It also lists farming jobs on its Web site. After some false starts, Aaron Newsom, who spent six years in the Marine Corps, including a tour in Afghanistan, as an aircraft recovery specialist, found the Farmer-Veteran Coalition and learned of a retreat near his home in the Santa Cruz area. “We stopped by a large garden, then an orchard with apple and pear trees, and an organic food stand,” said Mr. Newsom, 27. “I knew then I wanted to know the biology of it all.” He is now studying for a horticulture degree at a community college. “It’s a kind of healing,” said Mr. O’Gorman of veterans who decide on farming, “and it’s an income.”</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/11/business/11shipping.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart’s Free Shipping Adds Pressure for Smaller Stores<date>Published: November 11, 2010</date><text>For years, Wal-Mart has used its clout as the nation’s largest retailer to squeeze competitors with rock-bottom prices in its stores. Now it is trying to throw a holiday knockout punch online.Starting Thursday, Wal-Mart Stores plans to offer free shipping on its Web site, with no minimum purchase, on almost 60,000 gift items, including many toys and electronics. The offer will run through Dec. 20, when Wal-Mart said it might consider other free-shipping deals. “Everyone’s trying to figure out how we can serve a customer that’s trying to save every penny they can,” said Steve Nave, senior vice president and general manager of Walmart.com. “It’s the most competitive offer out there, and we’re pretty excited about it.” Even before Wal-Mart’s surprise move, shipping prices were this holiday season’s predicament for online retailers. In a bid for cost-conscious consumers, Target and J. C. Penney introduced their most aggressive free-shipping programs ever, and Sears, Toys “R” Us, Williams-Sonoma and others were trying to match the success of Amazon’s shipping program, offering unlimited two-day shipping for an annual fee. But given Wal-Mart’s scale and influence in the marketplace, its free pass for shipping sets a new high — or low — in e-commerce. And it may create an expectation among consumers — free shipping, no minimum, always — that would make it harder for smaller e-commerce sites to survive. Wal-Mart says it will not raise prices to offset shipping and will not press shippers, like UPS and FedEx, to absorb the costs. But Wal-Mart and other big retailers already have low-price contracts with shippers, and the stores maintain distribution centers nationwide that reduce shipping distances and costs. For smaller retailers and Web sites, which pay regular mail rates and may ship from only one location, free shipping is not nearly as affordable and often must be added into prices. “You’re trying to compete with the Amazons and the Zappos, who have so many different warehouses that they can significantly reduce transport costs,” said Gary Schwake, director of business development at the Distribution Management Group, a consulting firm that advises retailers like Eddie Bauer. Retailers say that shoppers have already started to revolt against shipping fees. While consumers are sensitive to what an item costs online, shipping costs can have even more influence, according to market research. When e-commerce took off a decade ago, free shipping was a rare perk. Now, 55 percent of consumers are at least somewhat likely to abandon their purchase if they do not get free shipping, according to comScore, the online-research firm, and about 41 percent of transactions online now include free shipping (usually with a minimum purchase). Wal-Mart is throwing itself into the holiday season shipping fray as it tries to revive sales. Even as other retailers’ sales have recovered, sales at Wal-Mart’s stores in the United States open more than a year have fallen for five consecutive quarters. Recently, it has been adding to the merchandise it carries, offering products for under $1 and undercutting Target on toy prices. The Wal-Mart shipping offer has no minimum. Mr. Nave said an important factor was that an item was likely to be given as a gift. “We looked at the areas we felt were going to be popular in gift-giving this holiday, and went from there,” he said. Even after the holidays, “I would expect to see us continue to have offerings similar to this in the future in some way, shape or form,” he said. The Wal-Mart announcement was not public until Thursday, but retailers had already been escalating their shipping programs since last year, when mobile comparison-shopping apps helped make free shipping popular. Amazon.com has one successful model. Year-round, it offers free shipping on orders over $25. And its Amazon Prime program, in which members pay $79 a year for unlimited two-day shipping on almost all purchases, could account for as much as a third of sales, said Jordan Rohan, an analyst with Stifel Nicolaus. “It is making other retailers scramble,” he said. To fight off Amazon Prime, a month ago GSI Commerce started ShopRunner, a service that bands together e-commerce sites including eBags and the Web site of Toys “R” Us. Shoppers pay $79 a year for unlimited two-day shipping from any of the members. This fall, Williams-Sonoma started a service like that for $30 a year, and Sears and Kmart, which introduced a similar program three years ago, are pushing it heavily this season. Beginning in October, J.C. Penney started offering free shipping year-round, with a minimum purchase of $69 for most of the year. Target is offering free shipping on purchases of $50 and up, on 800,000 items. And in August L.L. Bean began offering free shipping with no minimum, through Dec. 20. Bigger companies have a big advantage in the battle over free shipping: volume. According to the Distribution Management Group, air shipping prices for big retailers are about 70 percent less than for a small company. Shipping at Amazon costs about 4 percent of sales, and Amazon loses money on it because it offers marketing benefits, said Aaron Kessler, an e-commerce analyst at the research firm ThinkEquity. But shipping at small sites usually costs about 35 percent of sales, said Mr. Schwake, the retail adviser. Despite the costs, smaller retailers say they have little choice but to offer free shipping, in some form, these days. “Everyone does it,” said Michael Mente, the co-founder of Revolve Clothing, a Los Angeles-based women’s clothing site. Asked if he received discounts from the shippers, he said, “Unfortunately not.” At the start-up site ModCloth, which sells women’s clothes, the co-founder Susan Gregg Koger said she couldn’t afford free shipping year round, but she decided to do it for the holiday season. It is a risk, she said. “That’s really hard to offer and then roll back,” she said. While Wal-Mart may continue with some free shipping offers after the holidays, even other big retailers like L.L. Bean say they just cannot afford it after Christmas is over. “We’d love to be able to offer free shipping, but free shipping isn’t free,” said Laurie Brooks, an L.L. Bean spokeswoman. “It does cost a company money." There are potential downsides, even for Wal-Mart. Physical stores with Web sites run a risk in promoting free shipping, Mr. Rohan said. “They’d much rather you buy that same item in the store for $50 and pick up a hundred dollars of other stuff you wouldn’t even think about,” he said.</text></article>
  </page>
  <page index="10">
    <article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/15/business/15walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Plans to Buy More Local Produce<date>Published: October 14, 2010</date><text>The local-and-sustainable food movement has spread to the nation’s largest retailer.Wal-Mart Stores announced a program on Thursday that focuses on sustainable agriculture among its suppliers as it tries to reduce its overall environmental impact. The program is intended to put more locally grown food in Wal-Mart stores in the United States, invest in training and infrastructure for small and medium-size farmers, particularly in emerging markets, and begin to measure how efficiently large suppliers grow and get their produce into stores. Advocates of environmentally sustainable farming said the announcement was significant because of Wal-Mart’s size and because it would give small farmers a chance at Wal-Mart’s business, but they questioned how “local” a $405 billion company with two million employees — more than the populations of Alaska, Wyoming and Vermont combined — could be. Given that Wal-Mart is the world’s largest grocer, with one of the biggest food supply chains, any change it made would have wide implications. Wal-Mart’s decision five years ago to set sustainability goals that, among other things, increased its reliance on renewable energy and reduced packaging waste among its suppliers sent broad ripples through product manufacturers. Large companies like Procter &amp; Gamble redesigned packages that are now carried by other retailers, while Wal-Mart’s measurements of the environmental efficiency of its suppliers helped define how they needed to change. “No other retailer has the ability to make more of a difference than Wal-Mart,” the retailer’s president and chief executive, Michael T. Duke, said in remarks prepared for a meeting on Thursday morning. “Grocery is more than half of Wal-Mart’s business. Yet only four of our 39 public sustainability goals address food.” Wal-Mart said it expected to meet the goals by the end of 2015. In the United States, Wal-Mart plans to double the percentage of locally grown produce it sells to 9 percent. Wal-Mart defines local produce as that grown and sold in the same state. Still, the program is far less ambitious than in some other countries — in Canada, for instance, Wal-Mart expects to buy 30 percent of its produce locally by the end of 2013, and, when local produce is available, increase that to 100 percent. “Our food business in Canada is brand new, so there’s a lot they can do,” said Andrea Thomas, senior vice president of sustainability, at a news conference. She said the program allowed each country to set its own specific goals. In emerging markets, Wal-Mart has pledged to sell $1 billion of food from small and medium farmers (which it defines as farmers with fewer than 20 hectares, about 50 acres). It will also provide training for the farmers and their laborers on how to choose crops that are in demand and on the proper application of water and pesticides. Both in the United States and globally, Wal-Mart will invest more than $1 billion to improve its supply chain for perishable food. For example, if trucks, trains and distribution centers could help farmers in Minnesota get crops to Wal-Mart more quickly, the result would be less spoiled food, a longer shelf life and presumably more profit for the farmers and for Wal-Mart. Wal-Mart said it planned to reduce food waste in emerging-market stores by 15 percent and in other stores by 10 percent. Michelle Mauthe Harvey of the Environmental Defense Fund, who worked with Wal-Mart on the goals, said this was significant. “As we’ve moved to reliance on key locations like California and Florida,” she said, “we’ve made it very difficult for local farmers to actually get their food to market.” As Wal-Mart is doing with consumer products, it will begin asking agricultural producers questions about water, fertilizer and chemical use. The eventual goal is to include that information in a sustainability index. Customers would see sustainability ratings, so they could decide whether to choose one avocado over another based on how efficiently it was grown and shipped. Wal-Mart could use index information when it decided from whom to buy. Finally, the company announced specific guidelines for the sources of its products, including a requirement that palm oil from sustainable sources be used in all its private-label products (the Wal-Mart house brands) and that any beef it sold not have contributed to the deforestation of the Amazon region because of cattle ranch expansion. While the overall goals include Sam’s Club, the warehouse store wing of Wal-Mart, that division also has other specific goals, including a 15 percent increase in fair trade or Rainforest Alliance certified flowers and produce. Some local food supporters said that while the environmental goals were positive, Wal-Mart could not provide some benefits that other buy-local movements did. For instance, said Linda Berlin, director of the Center for Sustainable Agriculture at the University of Vermont, farmers’ markets help return money to the local economy. “The local-food movement has been, certainly, about taste and quality of food, about providing good incomes for farmers, and also about other things that have to do with building smaller economies so we as a society aren’t dominated by the more industrial complexes,” she said. “This initiative doesn’t necessarily address that.” Other environmental and agricultural specialists said it would have a big impact. “It’s very impressive,” said Margaret Mellon, director of the food and environment program at the Union of Concerned Scientists. “It’s encouraging that Wal-Mart understands that the path forward in agriculture isn’t through making the big bigger, it’s really through encouraging the small and medium-sized farms,” she said. Still, she said she was disappointed that goals around organic food were not included, and surprised that Wal-Mart did not address genetically modified seeds and produce. The agricultural sustainability index was particularly noteworthy, said one academic who worked with Wal-Mart on the goals. “The index represents a real number that will mean improvement on the ground: improving ecosystem health, soil health and food quality,” said Marty Matlock, a professor of ecological engineering at the University of Arkansas, which “will move agricultural producers en masse.”</text></article>
    <article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/28/business/28views.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Opens Up Its Wallet in Africa<date>Published: September 27, 2010</date><text>Wal-Mart has finally sounded the vuvuzela on African expansion. After months of speculation about how it would try to capitalize on the continent’s growth, the retailer is offering $4.2 billion to acquire South Africa’s Massmart Holdings. The price could grate on shareholders’ ears. But the deal gives Wal-Mart a local vehicle — and local knowledge — to help it gain access to a market with a profile that should suit it well.If the deal is accepted by Massmart, Wal-Mart will be paying close to 13 times the Johannesburg-based retailer’s earnings before interest, tax, depreciation and amortization, or Ebitda. For a company that trades at closer to 7 times Ebitda, that’s a big premium, albeit a drop in the bucket against Wal-Mart’s nearly $200 billion market capitalization. But Wal-Mart will get a foothold in what should be a bright spot in the world’s growth map. South Africa, where Massmart operates 232 stores from Limpopo in the northeast to the Western Cape, is one of the Civets economies (Colombia, Indonesia, Vietnam, Egypt, Turkey and South Africa) widely hailed as the next sizable emerging markets. The International Monetary Fund estimates sub-Saharan output will grow nearly 6 percent a year from 2011. Capitalizing on that would be a stretch for Wal-Mart from its Bentonville, Ark., headquarters. Piggybacking on Massmart’s business makes African expansion much less risky. From its home market where it operates various retail formats, the South African group has been rolling out its Game mass-discount stores in Botswana, Ghana, Malawi, Mozambique, Namibia, Zambia and elsewhere. Moreover, buying Massmart should improve margins in Wal-Mart’s international business, which accounts for about a quarter of its revenue. While Wal-Mart International’s operating margins were about 3.8 percent in the first half of this year, Massmart’s stood at closer to 5 percent. Apply Wal-Mart’s huge purchasing power, and profitability could increase further. This entry ticket to a Civets lair doesn’t come cheap. But with growth elusive at home, it should be a price Wal-Mart shareholders are happy to pay. Tough A.I.G. Exit There’s no quick way for the federal government to exit American International Group. Converting $49 billion of preferred stock to common shares and selling them would, like the exit from Citigroup, take time. And that’s assuming other share sales, needed for separate repayments relating to A.I.G., go smoothly. As of June 30, A.I.G. owed the government just over $100 billion. A.I.G. has also made progress offloading assets. Big examples include the initial public offering of A.I.A., the Asian unit currently expected to begin trading on the Hong Kong market in the next month or so, and the pending $15.5 billion sale to MetLife of American Life Insurance, or Alico. The New York Fed converted debt in those entities into preferred shares worth $16 billion and $9 billion respectively, and the deals will help pay that off. Back at A.I.G. itself, there are about $49 billion of preferred shares owned by the Treasury. The Citi example shows how those securities might be swapped into common equity and then sold, over time. In the Citi case, the government is turning a profit on its shares, potentially making the idea interesting for A.I.G. as well. But it seems that selling the government’s Citi stake — initially nearly 30 percent — will take longer than anticipated. Offloading the A.I.G. stake could take far longer, because the government already effectively owns 80 percent of the company. Converting the preferreds could take that nearer to 90 percent. That’s not all. An AIA I.P.O. probably won’t raise enough to repay the New York Fed’s preferred interest right away, let alone give A.I.G. proceeds to apply to its own obligations. Meanwhile the Alico sale will come with only $6.8 billion of cash. So the government will depend on further sales of AIA and MetLife equity interests to get repaid. Furthermore, ahead of all that is another $20 billion or so, including interest, that A.I.G. still owes the New York Fed under a credit facility. The insurer might at some point be able to refinance that. But put the pieces together, and taxpayers could wait a long time before enough shares in enough different companies are sold for them to be made whole. ROB COX and RICHARD BEALES</text></article>
    <article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/28/business/global/28walmart.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Plans to Enter African Market<date>Published: September 27, 2010</date><text>Wal-Mart Stores announced plans on Monday to enter the African market, with a preliminary offer to buy the Johannesburg-based retailer Massmart Holdings for about $4.2 billion.While Wal-Mart operates in 14 countries in addition to the United States, it has no stores in Africa. The retail giant has emphasized international sales, which make up about a quarter of its revenue, as sales in the United States have softened. Sales at stores open at least a year have declined for five consecutive quarters in the United States. Wal-Mart has used a variety of approaches in other countries, like opening Sam’s Clubs and Supercenters in China and Brazil, and buying stakes in existing retailers in Chile and El Salvador. The chief executive of Massmart, Grant Pattison, said that the company was first approached by Wal-Mart on Friday, and Massmart’s board met on Sunday to discuss the proposal. The offer is preliminary and nonbinding, meaning that Wal-Mart is beginning to conduct due diligence, could back out at any time and has not made a formal offer requiring shareholder approval. Massmart can be described as a combination of Wal-Mart and Home Depot, selling general merchandise and home improvement supplies in 14 sub-Saharan countries, though most of its operations are in South Africa. It is also the biggest retailer of basic foods in the region. Sales for its most recent fiscal year, ended in June, were about $6.8 billion, up 10 percent from the previous year. The company has 232 stores in South Africa, and 24 additional stores in other sub-Saharan African countries, including Builders Warehouse, which focuses on home improvement; Makro, a warehouse store; and CellShack, which sells cellular phones. “South Africa presents a compelling growth opportunity for Wal-Mart and offers a platform for growth and expansion in other African countries,” Andy Bond, a Wal-Mart executive who oversees the region’s operations, said in a statement. Analysts, however, were skeptical and questioned whether the purchase would be the best use of Wal-Mart’s $10.2 billion in cash. David Strasser, an analyst for Janney Montgomery Scott, noted that the proposed purchase price was high, at 13 times earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization. “Returns will lag for years to come,” he said in a note to clients. He noted that Massmart was relatively far along in South Africa, which he said he believed had the best economy on the continent, so would need to grow in the other countries where it did business. “For this deal to drive returns, we believe it is essential to succeed by using this acquisition as a springboard,” Mr. Strasser said. “For every relatively stable country like Botswana, there is a Zimbabwe.” Colin McGranahan, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, noted that the proposed price — $20.94 a share — was about a 10 percent premium over Massmart’s closing price before the offer was announced. “Investors may have reservations about the company’s decision to pursue acquisitions in a new part of the world, particularly at such high multiples and when Wal-Mart’s own stock is trading at a much lower valuation,” he said in a note to clients. “Although the acquisition is modest compared to the size of the overall company, it may disappoint people hoping that the company would begin to return more capital to shareholders.” In a video posted on Massmart’s Web site, its chief executive, Mr. Pattison, said: “We are at the beginning of a process. The next step is to complete the due diligence and thereafter we will seek regulatory and shareholder approval.” “There are several conditions, the most important being the completion of a confirmatory due diligence by Wal-Mart,” Mr. Pattison said, adding that both companies had agreed to a period of exclusivity to discuss the proposal. Wal-Mart and Massmart representatives declined comment beyond what was posted on their company Web sites.</text></article>
    <article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/09/27/wal-mart-offers-4-billion-for-south-africas-massmart/?ref=walmartstoresinc">Wal-Mart Offers $4 Billion for South Africa's Massmart<date>September 27, 2010, 7:10 am</date><text>Wal-Mart is in talks to buy South Africa’s Massmart in a $4.2 billion deal that would give the retailer a big presence in fast-growing Africa and bolster its emerging markets strategy, Reuters reported. Wal-Mart has tabled an all-cash, nonbinding offer of 148 rand a share, a 9.8 percent premium to its closing price on Sept. 23, for Massmart’s network of 290 stores, Massmart said in a statement Monday. The offer comes as the world’s largest retailer has been hit by weakness in the United States, where low-income shoppers are particularly vulnerable to unemployment and higher gasolinel prices. The company has responded by focusing on cost cuts and international growth. Buying Massmart, South Africa’s third-largest listed retailer by value, would give Wal-Mart a considerable network in Africa’s biggest economy and a foothold in 13 other countries in sub-Saharan Africa. Home to some of the world’s fastest growing markets, Africa also boasts an emerging middle class and roughly 1 billion consumers, making it an increasingly attractive target for overseas investors. “Massmart is a very good fit with their business,” said Bryan Roberts, global research director at the industry research firm Planet Retail in London. Other international retailers could eventually bid for one of Massmart’s local competitors to tap the potential of sub-Saharan Africa, he said. Go to Article from Reuters via The New York Times » Go to Article from Bloomberg News » Go to Press Release from Massmart »</text></article>
    <article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/22/business/22dollar.html?ref=walmartstoresinc">Stores Scramble to Accommodate Budget-Conscious Shoppers<date>Published: September 21, 2010</date><text>The country’s continued economic doldrums have stores scrambling for the once-ignored low-end customer, as people make fewer costly shopping trips to stock their pantries, and increasingly, can only afford inexpensive items in small quantities like those sold at dollar stores.Dollar stores have shown the biggest gain in shopper visits over the last year out of all the retailers that sell basic consumer goods, according to market research data. Manufacturers are racing to package more affordable versions of products common at those stores, and other budget retailers, feeling the loss of customers, are trying to duplicate their success. Wal-Mart, the world’s largest retailer, is adding thousands of items to its shelves, including inexpensive ones, and is asking dollar-store suppliers to create small, under-a-dollar packages for its stores, too. In areas with high unemployment, Wal-Mart is grouping together its less than $1 items in a clear challenge to the dollar stores. The impetus for the downmarket trend is the continued tightening of household budgets, retailers and analysts said. Some customers at Wal-Mart and the major dollar chains — Dollar General, Family Dollar and Dollar Tree — have such modest budgets that the retailers report upticks in spending at the beginning of the month, when government benefit checks and many paychecks come through. Late in the month, sales drop as even multiroll packs of paper towels are ditched for a single roll. “People are literally running out of cash on hand as the month goes on and they’re looking for smaller package sizes,” said Craig Johnson, president of the retail consulting and research firm Customer Growth Partners. “They may have $10, $20, $30 to spend getting toward the end of the month, and they have to be able to still feed the family and get diapers and so forth.” At about a quarter of Wal-Mart’s stores, the company is beginning to offer items for under $1, like a four-pack of toilet paper, boxes containing just a few garbage bags and single rolls of paper towels. But the dollar stores have best been able to capitalize on the downmarket trend because of strategies they embraced during the recession, when the stores kept things cheap and expanded their merchandise, analysts said. Realizing that their shoppers often could not afford regular-size detergent, for example, the stores worked with manufacturers to create smaller packages that cost less. “Just because of their cash flow, they’re buying the smaller packs,” said Sam Paul, chief executive of Nextep, which makes trash bags. To keep up with the demand for smaller quantities Wal-Mart began stocking the company’s five-pack of outdoor garbage bags a couple of months ago and Nextep recently opened a factory that specializes in small packaging. In the last year, dollar stores “have not only shown growth among their heaviest shoppers, but also that they are stealing heavy shoppers” from stores like Wal-Mart, said Susan Viamari, editor of Times and Trends, a publication from the market research and consulting firm SymphonyIRI Group, in an e-mail. SymphonyIRI tracks what consumers are buying. According to the company, the number of visits to dollar stores increased 2.6 percent from June 2009 to June 2010 compared with the same period a year earlier, the most recent figures available. Over the same period, visits to large stores like Wal-Mart declined 7 percent. The dollar stores are pulling in shoppers like Mellissa Hayden. A pizza deliverer, she is the kind of price-sensitive shopper who knows that a bottle of ibuprofen from the Dollar General near her home in Rockford, Tenn., costs just $2.50 and has 100 pills, but at Wal-Mart, she will get fewer pills for about $5. So lately, she has been heading to dollar stores instead of Wal-Mart. “You don’t have the big crowds and it’s cheaper,” she said. Same-store sales, which measure revenue at stores open at least a year, at the three major dollar chains have increased for at least 10 consecutive quarters. At Wal-Mart, same-store sales in the United States have declined for the last five quarters. During the recession, Wal-Mart pulled back on very inexpensive products, suppliers said, to make the stores look less cluttered and to appeal to shoppers who might be testing out that retailer instead of, say, Target. That decision has it now playing catch-up. “They just abandoned that lowest price point,” said Mr. Paul of Nextep. In the last couple of quarters, Wal-Mart tried aggressive discounts on items like milk, but the price cuts did not attract huge traffic, said Thomas M. Schoewe, Wal-Mart’s chief financial officer, in a conference call with reporters last month. He said that dollar stores were part of the challenge. “Many times it is convenient to walk into a dollar store and even though the price per unit, if you will, may be a little bit higher at the dollar store, if they can find that product and still live from paycheck to paycheck, that’s how they’re solving that problem,” Mr. Schoewe said. The dollar stores have found creative ways to keep their prices low. When commodity costs rose for suppliers, for example, the dollar stores asked them to decrease the number of sandwich bags in a box or pushed them to come up with a cheaper version of the products. To increase their attractiveness to the low-income customer, the dollar stores have also switched out merchandise like trinkets for necessities like food and detergent. At Family Dollar, most customers have incomes under $40,000 and have “really curtailed discretionary spending out of necessity,” said Kiley Rawlins, a spokeswoman. But customers are shopping more frequently, she said, and buying a greater variety of items, a reflection of the items like cleaning products that the store now carries. Some of the stores have even managed to reach some middle-income shoppers, by increasing products from well-known brands like Hanes, Quaker Oats and Nabisco. “This is a break from historical trends, where dollar stores really catered almost entirely to lower income shoppers,” Ms. Viamari of SymphonyIRI said. Many manufacturers have been hurrying to get dollar shoppers’ attention. Tracy VanBibber, senior vice president for sales at the Dial Corporation, a division of Henkel that makes products like Dial soap and Soft Scrub, said there were now enough low-end customers — known in the industry as value shoppers — to justify the investment. “We’re really trying to get better at thinking of the value shopper earlier in our innovation pipeline,” Ms. VanBibber said. “The retailers that service value shoppers have enough scale that manufacturers can customize and it pays off now.”</text></article>
  </page>
</root>
