<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Weyerhauser Co"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/29/business/weyerhaeuser-earnings-meet-expectations.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Earnings Meet Expectations<date>Published: October 28, 2011</date><text>Weyerhaeuser, the forest products maker and homebuilder, reported quarterly profit that matched Wall Street’s expectations, but the company warned that the United States housing market remained challenging and that China demand was slowing. For the third quarter, the company posted net income of $157 million, or 29 cents a share, compared with $1.12 billion, or $3.50 a share, a year ago. Sales rose 3.6 percent to $1.56 billion. Shares of Weyerhaeuser rose 2 percent, to $18.30.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/15/business/15unboxed.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Company Innovators Ask: What Works?<date>Published: August 14, 2010</date><text>BUSINESS is a field not of theory but of practice. The central intellectual inquiry of the science of management is simply this: What works?That, it seems, is the best way to examine the steady rise in the practice of innovation management. A search of the database of the professional networking site LinkedIn found that more than 700 people listed their current job title as “chief innovation officer” and that nearly 25,000 had the word “innovation” in their job title. Many others may not have the word in their titles, but their job is to pursue opportunities that result in new products, services and more efficient ways of doing things. So what does work in the innovation game? No single formula, to be sure. But some recent interviews with executives, consultants and academics can be distilled into three recommendations: think broadly, borrow from the entrepreneurial Silicon Valley model, and pay close attention to customers and to emerging user needs. Here, then, are three innovation works in progress that include those ingredients, whether or not the efforts will ultimately prove to be winners: Marching Into New Markets John Tao joined Weyerhaeuser, the wood and pulp producer, two years ago as its vice president for open innovation, coming from Air Products and Chemicals. At Weyerhaeuser, Mr. Tao has led an initiative to find new markets for lignin, a chemical compound that binds cellulose fibers together in trees. Lignin is extracted during pulp-making as a black liquor, and is typically recycled as a fuel for pulp plants. Yet lignin can also be converted to a solid and serve as a chemical feedstock for making a range of products. Mr. Tao, a Ph.D. chemical engineer, and his staff studied the market, including the curbs on carbon emissions that chemical producers will likely face in the future. Lignin can be a nonpolluting alternative for producing goods as different as seat cushions and carbon fiber. Automakers, for example, are beginning to use carbon fiber as a lightweight but strong substitute for metal to improve fuel efficiency. As a chemical feedstock, lignin is worth 10 to 20 times its value as a pulp-plant fuel, Mr. Tao said. Weyerhaeuser has a pilot plant in North Carolina to produce specialized lignin chemicals. Mr. Tao has met with chemical companies, carbon fiber makers and the Department of Energy to try to nurture new lignin markets. “You have to have some technical background,” he said, “but a lot of this work is market analysis, communications and networking with industry partners.” Customized Discounts For innovation champions, titles matter far less than their independence, breadth of knowledge and corporate clout, experts say. “Whatever you call it, there is a real need for a senior-level executive to be able to reach across a company and beyond to tap ideas, skills and resources,” said Henry Chesbrough, executive director of the Center for Open Innovation at the University of California, Berkeley. “It is this systems integration aspect that is central to innovation as a field and a discipline.” Money helps too. Rick Rommel, a senior vice president of the new-business group at Best Buy, says his unit has “an internal venture capital mind-set.” Best Buy gave his group additional financing this year to sharply increase investments in experimental ventures that, he said, “explore what customers think and what technologies are ready for widespread adoption.” The new-business group has been working with a start-up, Shopkick, which is introducing an application for iPhones, and later for other smartphones, that retailers can use to track when shoppers have entered a store and reward them with discounts. When linked to other online browsing and buying data, the discount offers can be not only immediate, when a person is in the store, but also tailored to individual interests. A person who has browsed computer Web sites, for example, might be offered a 10 percent discount on a notebook computer. “This really moves toward one-to-one marketing,” Mr. Rommel said. Banks of the Future At Citigroup, Deborah Hopkins, chief innovation officer, is also in charge of the bank’s venture investing arm. This year, she decided to move from New York to Silicon Valley to be close to its entrepreneurial networks. “It’s a small community out there,” she explained. One Citigroup investment is in Bundle.com, a social media start-up where users can compare their spending and saving habits with those of others. The idea came from the Citigroup innovation unit, and Bundle’s C.E.O., Jaidev Shergill, came from Citigroup. The other investors in Bundle are Microsoft and Morningstar. “The whole social networking phenomenon is moving so fast, and we need to be invested in some way,” said Don Callahan, Citigroup’s chief administrative officer, who oversees the innovation unit. “Whatever the outcome, we’re going to learn a lot.” Ms. Hopkins sees her role as “being a catalyst, to challenge people to think differently, but also pursue new ideas with a lot of rigor.” An example of that systematic approach to innovation is Citigroup’s “bank of the future” project. The first two redesigned bank branches opened in April in Japan, but the concepts will eventually be transplanted to America, tailored to local markets. The overhaul began with a shift in mind-set, from one oriented around banking products to one focused on customers. Months of extensive customer and demographic research resulted in personality profiles of four customer types, from up-and-comers in their 30s to retiring baby boomers. Customer service and marketing were geared toward those four affluent groups. The branches have been remade as digital banks, with touch-screen work stations and videoconferencing links to financial experts. Traditional banks have up to 100 paper forms, while the redesigned branches are almost paperless, says Darren Buckley, president of Citibank Japan. The design imprint of Eight Inc., a firm that worked on Apple’s stores, is evident in the open, minimalist interiors of the new branches. “We’re incubating ideas, but what we’re doing in Japan is absolutely something that can be scaled out elsewhere,” said Chris Kay, a managing director of Citigroup’s innovation arm.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDE1F30F935A35751C0A9669D8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">BUSINESS BRIEFING | EARNINGS; A Weak Housing Sector Hurts Weyerhaeuser's Results<date>Published: February 6, 2010</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the timber business, posted a smaller fourth-quarter loss on Friday, but it still missed Wall Street expectations and its stock fell 2 percent. The company also forecast an operating loss in the first quarter for its wood products sector. ''The weak housing market continues to present challenges and affect our financial performance,'' the chief executive, Daniel S. Fulton, said in a statement. Weyerhaeuser said it lost $175 million, or 83 cents a share, in the quarter, compared with a loss of $1.2 billion, or $5.73 a share, a year earlier. Sales fell 16 percent, to $1.46 billion from $1.78 billion. Excluding one-time items such as the alternative fuel credit and impairment and restructuring charges, Weyerhaeuser posted a loss of 52 cents a share, worse than the 38-cent loss Wall Street analysts had expected. Stock in Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., fell 94 cents, to $39.45 a share.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2009/12/08/weyerhaeuser-unloads-oregon-lumber-mill/?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Unloads Oregon Lumber Mill<date>December 8, 2009, 3:23 am</date><text>Weyerhaeuser says it is selling its Warrenton, Ore., lumber mill to Portland, Ore.-based Hampton Affiliates. Weyerhaeuser said Monday the sale is expected to close in January, with the transaction including the mill and its land. Terms were not disclosed, The Associated Press said. Weyerhaeuser advised Oregon officials that the mill would close, with the loss of 140 jobs — 94 employees who are working now and 46 who were laid off indefinitely last March. Weyerhaeuser’s Rob Taylor said in a statement that ”the sale provides the mill with a new owner that has the focus and interest in manufacturing lumber in Warrenton.” In a statement, Hampton said it would idle the mill for nine to 12 months for extensive machinery upgrades. Hampton’s Web site says it has seven sawmills in Oregon, Washington and British Columbia. Go to Article from The Associated Press via The New York Times » Go to Article from the Portland Business Journal » Go to Press Release from Weyerhaeuser »</text></article><article index="5" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E2DA163CF932A05753C1A96F9C8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">BUSINESS BRIEFING | COMPANIES; Weyerhaeuser Breaks Even as Sales Fall<date>Published: October 31, 2009</date><text>The timber developer Weyerhaeuser posted better-than-expected results on Friday, largely as a result of cost-cutting, as sales fell in all of its units. The company said the slump in the housing industry continued to hurt its performance, and that it had slashed costs by 48 percent to improve results. For the quarter, the company broke even, compared with a profit of $280 million, or $1.33 a share, a year earlier. Sales fell 33 percent, to $1.41 billion, from $2.11 billion.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DD1330F932A35752C1A96E9C8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">BUSINESS BRIEFING | COMPANY EARNINGS; After Sale of Unit, Weyerhaeuser Profit Triples<date>Published: November 1, 2008</date><text>Weyerhaeuser said its third-quarter profit nearly tripled on hefty gains from the sale of its packaging business. But revenue tumbled 37 percent and the company, which specializes in timber and wood, faces a battered housing market. Weyerhaeuser posted net income of $280 million, including $461 million in gains from the packaging divestiture. A year earlier, net income totaled $101 million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/18/business/worldbusiness/18paper.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">International Paper Buys Weyerhaeuser Unit<date>Published: March 18, 2008</date><text>International Paper said on Monday that it had agreed to acquire Weyerhaeuser’s packaging business for $6 billion to become North America’s largest maker of corrugated boxes. The paper and packaging industry in North America and Europe has been consolidating and reducing production capacity in an effort to tackle soaring raw material costs and dwindling demand for paper. “This is an acquisition that is being made not for next quarter’s earnings, but to position International Paper for 2010,” said International Paper’s chief executive, John V. Faraci. Because the transaction is a purchase of assets rather than of stock, International Paper said the company would realize a tax benefit of about $1.4 billion, reducing the net purchase price to about $4.6 billion. In a note to clients, a JPMorgan analyst, Claudia Shank, cautioned that the company would be exposed to greater earnings volatility given its heightened exposure to wood products and home building. Shares of International Paper fell $2.79, or 8.7 percent, to $29.47 on the New York Stock Exchange, while those of Weyerhaeuser rose $1.09, to $63.06. International Paper said it had secured $6 billion in loans to finance the purchase, including an 18-month term loan for $4 billion. The cost to insure the debt of International Paper surged 30 percent after the deal was announced, according to Markit Intraday. International Paper’s credit default swaps weakened to around 295 basis points, or $295,000 a year for five years to insure $10 million in debt, from 227 basis points at Friday’s close. “Given the company’s historically aggressive nature, and with no clear path to balance sheet restoration yet illuminated, we are downgrading our credit score to ‘deteriorating,’ ” said a Gimme Credit analyst, Carol Levenson. International Paper said it expected the deal to bolster its 2009 earnings and it anticipated about $400 million in annual cost savings from the deal, with about 40 percent of those savings being realized within 12 months of closing the deal. The deal is expected to close in the third quarter. The acquisition includes 9 containerboard mills, 72 packaging locations and other operations and affects about 14,300 employees. More Articles in Business »International Paper said on Monday that it had agreed to acquire Weyerhaeuser’s packaging business for $6 billion to become North America’s largest maker of corrugated boxes. The paper and packaging industry in North America and Europe has been consolidating and reducing production capacity in an effort to tackle soaring raw material costs and dwindling demand for paper. “This is an acquisition that is being made not for next quarter’s earnings, but to position International Paper for 2010,” said International Paper’s chief executive, John V. Faraci. Because the transaction is a purchase of assets rather than of stock, International Paper said the company would realize a tax benefit of about $1.4 billion, reducing the net purchase price to about $4.6 billion. In a note to clients, a JPMorgan analyst, Claudia Shank, cautioned that the company would be exposed to greater earnings volatility given its heightened exposure to wood products and home building. Shares of International Paper fell $2.79, or 8.7 percent, to $29.47 on the New York Stock Exchange, while those of Weyerhaeuser rose $1.09, to $63.06. International Paper said it had secured $6 billion in loans to finance the purchase, including an 18-month term loan for $4 billion. The cost to insure the debt of International Paper surged 30 percent after the deal was announced, according to Markit Intraday. International Paper’s credit default swaps weakened to around 295 basis points, or $295,000 a year for five years to insure $10 million in debt, from 227 basis points at Friday’s close. “Given the company’s historically aggressive nature, and with no clear path to balance sheet restoration yet illuminated, we are downgrading our credit score to ‘deteriorating,’ ” said a Gimme Credit analyst, Carol Levenson. International Paper said it expected the deal to bolster its 2009 earnings and it anticipated about $400 million in annual cost savings from the deal, with about 40 percent of those savings being realized within 12 months of closing the deal. The deal is expected to close in the third quarter. The acquisition includes 9 containerboard mills, 72 packaging locations and other operations and affects about 14,300 employees.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/02/magazine/02suicide-t.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Death in the Family<date>Published: December 2, 2007</date><text>"This will be my last campaign, Booth Gardner said. This will be the biggest fight of my career. He walked along the lane between the beach of driftwood and his compound of houses. The driftwood clotted the shore; it was the end of summer now, and the cove was still, but in winter massive branches and trunks churn up out of the water of Puget Sound. Bone-white roots clawed at the air on this late afternoon; Gardners grandchildren climbed across them. His walk was a vigorous lurch. One foot twisted inward, one knee buckled. His torso keeled slightly with each step. He has Parkinsons. He was governor of Washington State for two terms in the 1980s and 90s. He is 71, and his last campaign is driven by his desire to kill himself. I cant see where anybody benefits by my hanging around, he told me, while his blond grandchildren, sticks prodding, explored the waters edge. Skip to next paragraph Katy Grannan for The New York Times Enlarge This Image Katy Grannan for The New York Times The Last Campaign When exhaustion overtakes him, Booth Gardner naps in the bed that he slept in as a child in one of his familys homes. From the beach on Vashon Island, where Gardner spends much of his summers, not far from Seattle, he drove me to the islands town. His Lexus was cluttered with debris: a crushed soda can, a tattered magazine put out by a local pollster, an old plastic cup from McDonalds, a torn T-shirt, sunglasses missing a lens. Wearing a gray fleece, he led me into a simple restaurant with rustic décor. Full cheeks and green eyes impish, he chatted with the waitress and tried to start conversations with the people at tables around us. Youre not having dessert? he asked a young couple immersed in each other. Almost everyone seemed to recognize him, and almost everyone was friendly  hed been the states most popular governor in recent decades. But it wasnt always clear how interested they were in talking. The young couple gazed back at him, perplexed. It was 14 years since hed been in office. Why do this? he asked, turning from the other tables toward me. I want to be involved in public life. I was looking for an issue, and this one fell in my lap. One advantage I have in this thing is that people like me. The other  his leprechaun eyes lost their glint; his fleshy cheeks seemed to harden, his lips to thin, his face to reshape itself almost into a square  is that my logic is impeccable. My life, my death, my control. The campaign he was starting, when I spent time with him this summer and fall, goes by the name of death with dignity, and the statewide law he hopes to enact by popular vote on Election Day of 2008 would allow for physician-assisted suicide or, as the death-with-dignity movement prefers to call it, hastened death or aid in dying. The law would let doctors prescribe lethal doses of narcotics to terminally ill patients who ask to end their own lives. It would be modeled closely on a statute in Oregon, the only state where the movement has been successful. In all others, suicide is not illegal, but in nearly all it is a crime to help someone kill himself. (The law in a few states doesnt address the issue of such assistance, which leaves the one assisting exposed to possible prosecution.) The movement has put measures like Gardners directly before voters once already in Washington, in 1991, and in California, Michigan and Maine in the years since, and it has tried several times to turn its vision into law through state legislatures. Some of the failures have been narrow. The referendum in Washington was defeated 54 percent to 46 percent; in Maine 51 percent to 49 percent. With Gardner giving voice to its cause, the movement hopes for momentum. Yet the proposed law in Washington wouldnt go far enough for Gardner. It wouldnt include him. Parkinsons isnt terminal. The disease can leave the body trembling, contorted, rigid; it can rob the memory and muffle the voice; it can leave a person still and silent; but it doesnt offer an end to its torture; it doesnt kill. Gardner wants a law that would permit lethal prescriptions for people whose suffering is unbearable, a standard that can seem no standard at all; a standard that prevails in the Netherlands, the Western nation that has been boldest about legalizing aid in dying; a standard that elevates subjective experience over objective appraisal and that could engage the government and the medical profession in the administration of widespread suicide. What is unbearable? What level of acute or chronic physical pain would qualify? What degree of disability? Would physicians be writing suicide prescriptions for the depressed? Gardners campaign is a compromise; he sees it as a first step. If he can sway Washington to embrace a restrictive law, then other states will follow. And gradually, he says, the nations resistance will subside, the culture will shift and laws with more latitude will be passed, though this process, he knows, would almost surely take too long to help him. He knows he probably wont be able to carry out his wish for himself, not openly and legally: to secure a suicide prescription from a doctor, then to assemble his son and daughter and their mother, his first wife, on the porch of one of the houses on the compound, the one where his first wife now stays. There, facing the driftwood, he would tell them goodbye before going off by himself  while he still can go off by himself  to take his pills and die. He wishes he could do this, despite the energy in his ungainly stride and his ability to drive and the strength in his voice as he tries to connect with the people he once led, reaching out for their attention, asking, Youre not having dessert? Only his current cause keeps him much interested in living  this and one other goal: to connect with his son, Doug, whose growing up Gardner missed as he took power in business and politics, and who is repelled by his fathers campaign. The arrangement of houses on Gardners Vashon estate, and who stays in them, is a map of regret. His daughter (who didnt want to be interviewed for this article) and son, his grandchildren and his first wife stay in houses along the water, exposed to the sun; he occupies a sparsely furnished house, ensconced in fir trees, up a steep hill from the others. It is reached by a different road. He provided for us, Doug told me, but he wasnt there for us. The two men dont look much alike. Dougs tanned and lined face is slender, his nose sharp; his fathers features are blunt. Dougs body, at 45, is as lithe as a teenagers and seems almost frail; Gardners thick build lends him a look of resilience even with Parkinsons, though the disease can overtake him suddenly during the day, his distorted but determined walk giving way to consuming exhaustion and a craving for sleep. Dougs steps are light, tentative, and when he sits he appears to fold inward on himself, minimizing his narrow shoulders, as if he wishes to assume none of the power he watched his father acquire. It hardly seems possible that he was once a collegiate all-American on the tennis court. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 Next Page » Daniel Bergner is a contributing writer to the magazine; his new book, The Devotee: A Quartet of Desire, will be published next year. More Articles in Magazine »"This will be my last campaign, Booth Gardner said. This will be the biggest fight of my career. He walked along the lane between the beach of driftwood and his compound of houses. The driftwood clotted the shore; it was the end of summer now, and the cove was still, but in winter massive branches and trunks churn up out of the water of Puget Sound. Bone-white roots clawed at the air on this late afternoon; Gardners grandchildren climbed across them. His walk was a vigorous lurch. One foot twisted inward, one knee buckled. His torso keeled slightly with each step. He has Parkinsons. He was governor of Washington State for two terms in the 1980s and 90s. He is 71, and his last campaign is driven by his desire to kill himself. I cant see where anybody benefits by my hanging around, he told me, while his blond grandchildren, sticks prodding, explored the waters edge. Skip to next paragraph Katy Grannan for The New York Times Enlarge This Image Katy Grannan for The New York Times The Last Campaign When exhaustion overtakes him, Booth Gardner naps in the bed that he slept in as a child in one of his familys homes. From the beach on Vashon Island, where Gardner spends much of his summers, not far from Seattle, he drove me to the islands town. His Lexus was cluttered with debris: a crushed soda can, a tattered magazine put out by a local pollster, an old plastic cup from McDonalds, a torn T-shirt, sunglasses missing a lens. Wearing a gray fleece, he led me into a simple restaurant with rustic décor. Full cheeks and green eyes impish, he chatted with the waitress and tried to start conversations with the people at tables around us. Youre not having dessert? he asked a young couple immersed in each other. Almost everyone seemed to recognize him, and almost everyone was friendly  hed been the states most popular governor in recent decades. But it wasnt always clear how interested they were in talking. The young couple gazed back at him, perplexed. It was 14 years since hed been in office. Why do this? he asked, turning from the other tables toward me. I want to be involved in public life. I was looking for an issue, and this one fell in my lap. One advantage I have in this thing is that people like me. The other  his leprechaun eyes lost their glint; his fleshy cheeks seemed to harden, his lips to thin, his face to reshape itself almost into a square  is that my logic is impeccable. My life, my death, my control. The campaign he was starting, when I spent time with him this summer and fall, goes by the name of death with dignity, and the statewide law he hopes to enact by popular vote on Election Day of 2008 would allow for physician-assisted suicide or, as the death-with-dignity movement prefers to call it, hastened death or aid in dying. The law would let doctors prescribe lethal doses of narcotics to terminally ill patients who ask to end their own lives. It would be modeled closely on a statute in Oregon, the only state where the movement has been successful. In all others, suicide is not illegal, but in nearly all it is a crime to help someone kill himself. (The law in a few states doesnt address the issue of such assistance, which leaves the one assisting exposed to possible prosecution.) The movement has put measures like Gardners directly before voters once already in Washington, in 1991, and in California, Michigan and Maine in the years since, and it has tried several times to turn its vision into law through state legislatures. Some of the failures have been narrow. The referendum in Washington was defeated 54 percent to 46 percent; in Maine 51 percent to 49 percent. With Gardner giving voice to its cause, the movement hopes for momentum. Yet the proposed law in Washington wouldnt go far enough for Gardner. It wouldnt include him. Parkinsons isnt terminal. The disease can leave the body trembling, contorted, rigid; it can rob the memory and muffle the voice; it can leave a person still and silent; but it doesnt offer an end to its torture; it doesnt kill. Gardner wants a law that would permit lethal prescriptions for people whose suffering is unbearable, a standard that can seem no standard at all; a standard that prevails in the Netherlands, the Western nation that has been boldest about legalizing aid in dying; a standard that elevates subjective experience over objective appraisal and that could engage the government and the medical profession in the administration of widespread suicide. What is unbearable? What level of acute or chronic physical pain would qualify? What degree of disability? Would physicians be writing suicide prescriptions for the depressed? Gardners campaign is a compromise; he sees it as a first step. If he can sway Washington to embrace a restrictive law, then other states will follow. And gradually, he says, the nations resistance will subside, the culture will shift and laws with more latitude will be passed, though this process, he knows, would almost surely take too long to help him. He knows he probably wont be able to carry out his wish for himself, not openly and legally: to secure a suicide prescription from a doctor, then to assemble his son and daughter and their mother, his first wife, on the porch of one of the houses on the compound, the one where his first wife now stays. There, facing the driftwood, he would tell them goodbye before going off by himself  while he still can go off by himself  to take his pills and die. He wishes he could do this, despite the energy in his ungainly stride and his ability to drive and the strength in his voice as he tries to connect with the people he once led, reaching out for their attention, asking, Youre not having dessert? Only his current cause keeps him much interested in living  this and one other goal: to connect with his son, Doug, whose growing up Gardner missed as he took power in business and politics, and who is repelled by his fathers campaign. The arrangement of houses on Gardners Vashon estate, and who stays in them, is a map of regret. His daughter (who didnt want to be interviewed for this article) and son, his grandchildren and his first wife stay in houses along the water, exposed to the sun; he occupies a sparsely furnished house, ensconced in fir trees, up a steep hill from the others. It is reached by a different road. He provided for us, Doug told me, but he wasnt there for us. The two men dont look much alike. Dougs tanned and lined face is slender, his nose sharp; his fathers features are blunt. Dougs body, at 45, is as lithe as a teenagers and seems almost frail; Gardners thick build lends him a look of resilience even with Parkinsons, though the disease can overtake him suddenly during the day, his distorted but determined walk giving way to consuming exhaustion and a craving for sleep. Dougs steps are light, tentative, and when he sits he appears to fold inward on himself, minimizing his narrow shoulders, as if he wishes to assume none of the power he watched his father acquire. It hardly seems possible that he was once a collegiate all-American on the tennis court. 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 Next Page » Daniel Bergner is a contributing writer to the magazine; his new book, The Devotee: A Quartet of Desire, will be published next year.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/07/business/07timber.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Temple-Inland to Sell Land and Pass Proceeds to Investors<date>Published: August 7, 2007</date><text>The forest products company Temple-Inland, which is under pressure from the activist investor Carl C. Icahn, said yesterday that it would sell 1.55 million acres of timberland to the Campbell Group for $2.38 billion and then issue a $1.1 billion special dividend. The sale is part of a plan that Temple-Inland announced in February. The reorganization also includes spinning off the company’s financial services and real estate businesses. At that time, Temple-Inland said it expected to return most of the sale’s proceeds to shareholders. Mr. Icahn, who owns more than 8 percent of the company, has been urging Temple-Inland to make changes like selling assets. Temple-Inland said it was on track to complete its reorganization by the end of the year, after which it would own only packaging and building products. The company said the Campbell Group, a timberland investment management company in Portland, Ore., would buy the land with installment notes, which will be pledged as collateral for a nonrecourse loan within 30 days of the sale. Temple-Inland then expects to use some of its expected $1.8 billion in sale proceeds to pay a special dividend estimated at $1.1 billion, or $10.25 a share. It will use the remaining $700 million to reduce debt. The company expects the deal to close in the fourth quarter. The sale is to include 1.38 million acres of land that Temple-Inland owns and 175,000 acres that are covered by leases. The terms of the deal include a 20-year fiber-supply agreement for pulpwood and a 12-year fiber-supply agreement for saw timber, both of which can be extended. Many timber companies, including International Paper and Weyerhaeuser, have made similar forestland sales, streamlining operations in an effort to become more profitable. The sale represents most of the 1.7 million acres that the company had said it planned to sell. Most of the land is in Texas and Louisiana, though some is in Alabama and Georgia. Shares of Temple-Inland were up $3.13, to $57.03, on the New York Stock Exchange. More Articles in Business »The forest products company Temple-Inland, which is under pressure from the activist investor Carl C. Icahn, said yesterday that it would sell 1.55 million acres of timberland to the Campbell Group for $2.38 billion and then issue a $1.1 billion special dividend. The sale is part of a plan that Temple-Inland announced in February. The reorganization also includes spinning off the company’s financial services and real estate businesses. At that time, Temple-Inland said it expected to return most of the sale’s proceeds to shareholders. Mr. Icahn, who owns more than 8 percent of the company, has been urging Temple-Inland to make changes like selling assets. Temple-Inland said it was on track to complete its reorganization by the end of the year, after which it would own only packaging and building products. The company said the Campbell Group, a timberland investment management company in Portland, Ore., would buy the land with installment notes, which will be pledged as collateral for a nonrecourse loan within 30 days of the sale. Temple-Inland then expects to use some of its expected $1.8 billion in sale proceeds to pay a special dividend estimated at $1.1 billion, or $10.25 a share. It will use the remaining $700 million to reduce debt. The company expects the deal to close in the fourth quarter. The sale is to include 1.38 million acres of land that Temple-Inland owns and 175,000 acres that are covered by leases. The terms of the deal include a 20-year fiber-supply agreement for pulpwood and a 12-year fiber-supply agreement for saw timber, both of which can be extended. Many timber companies, including International Paper and Weyerhaeuser, have made similar forestland sales, streamlining operations in an effort to become more profitable. The sale represents most of the 1.7 million acres that the company had said it planned to sell. Most of the land is in Texas and Louisiana, though some is in Alabama and Georgia. Shares of Temple-Inland were up $3.13, to $57.03, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D81E3FF933A25751C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">TODAY IN BUSINESS | WEYERHAEUSER SWINGS TO PROFIT<date>Published: February 10, 2007</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the forest products company, swung to a profit in the fourth quarter from a loss a year earlier, helped by real estate sales amid lower domestic log prices. Earnings were $450 million, or $1.88 a share, in contrast to a loss of $211 million, or 86 cents a share. The quarter included a gain of $227 million, or 95 cents a share, for the refund of antidumping duties on Canadian softwood lumber sold in the United States. Revenue fell 1 percent to $5.66 billion from $5.72 billion. Graph: ''Weyerhaeuser Per share'' Yesterday: $78.14 Last Friday: $76.52</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DA1030F935A25752C0A9619C8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Blazing A Paper Trail In China; A Self-Made Billionaire Wrote Her Ticket On Recycled Cardboard<date>Published: January 16, 2007</date><text>Just five years ago, Zhang Yin and her husband were driving around the United States in a used Dodge minivan begging garbage dumps to give them their scrap paper. She and her husband, who was trained as a dentist, had formed a company in the 1990s to collect paper for recycling and ship it to China. It was a step up from life back in Hong Kong, where she had opened a paper trading company with $3,800 to cash in on China's chronic paper shortages. ''I remember what a man in the business told me back then,'' Ms. Zhang said. ''He said, 'Wastepaper is like a forest. Paper recycles itself, generation after generation.' '' Ms. Zhang took that memory all the way to the bank. As a result of her entrepreneurship, Zhang Yin (pronounced Jang Yeen) is now among the richest women anywhere in the world, including Oprah Winfrey, Martha Stewart and eBay's chief executive, Meg Whitman. Her personal wealth is estimated at $1.5 billion or more, with members of her family worth billions more. Her companies take heaps of waste paper from the United States and Europe, ship it to China and recycle it into corrugated cardboard, which is then used for boxes that are packed with toys, electronics and furniture that is stamped ''Made in China'' and often shipped right back across the ocean to American consumers. After the boxes are thrown away, the cycle starts all over again. Late last year, Forbes magazine named Ms. Zhang the wealthiest woman in China. She may even be the richest self-made woman in the world, challenging a handful of others, like Giuliana Benetton, who started the clothing company with her brothers, and Rosalia Mera, who co-founded Zara, the Spanish clothing retailer, with her former husband. Most of the world's richest women inherited their wealth: from the Walton women of Wal-Mart fame to the daughters of the men who created Mars candy bars, L'Oréal cosmetics and BMW. But not Ms. Zhang. A petite 49-year-old woman with a cherubic smile and a fancy for diamonds, she started out from a modest background, the daughter of a military officer. Now she dominates the world's paper trade through her giant companies, one centered in Dongguan just outside Hong Kong and the other based in Los Angeles. ''She's a visionary,'' says Herman Woo, an analyst at BNP Paribas, which helped her paper company list shares in Hong Kong. ''She doesn't mind putting a lot of money in at the beginning, to build the company.'' That company, Nine Dragons Paper, is now China's biggest papermaker. The company raised nearly $500 million when it went public here last March with the help of Merrill Lynch. Since then, shares of Nine Dragons have quadrupled, giving the company a market value of over $5 billion. (The Zhang family controls 72 percent of the company, which makes it one of the richest families in China.) Ms. Zhang's smaller, Los Angeles-based venture, America Chung Nam, is also one of the world's biggest paper trading companies, with ties to recycling yards in New York, Chicago and California. No other American company sends so much material to China, in as many containers, as America Chung Nam, which was named the top American exporter to China by volume for the fifth consecutive year in 2005, the most recent ranking, according to Piers Global Intelligence, which tracks import and export data. Now, with the paper industry shifting to China, where labor and land are cheaper, Ms. Zhang and Nine Dragons are vowing to take on the world's global paper giants, like International Paper, Weyerhaeuser and Smurfit Stone. ''My goal is to make Nine Dragons, in three to five years, the leader in containerboards,'' Ms. Zhang says emphatically in a short interview in her glistening Hong Kong office. ''My desire has always been to be the leader in an industry.'' In person, Ms. Zhang is filled with nervous energy and hearty laughs. But she rarely grants interviews, and when she does, they are brief and controlled by an army of handlers. Ms. Zhang is cagey about how she made her fortune. In a society known for close ties and hidden deals between government officials and business leaders, she says simply, ''I'm an honest businesswoman.''</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/24/business/worldbusiness/24paper.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Deal With Canadian Paper Maker Will Yield Continental Giant<date>Published: August 24, 2006</date><text>OTTAWA, Aug. 23  Weyerhaeuser will merge its fine-paper operation with a Canadian company, Domtar, in a cash-and-stock deal worth $3.3 billion, the two companies said Wednesday. Weyerhaeuser shareholders will own 55 percent of the combined operation, which will keep the Canadian company’s name and Montreal headquarters and be headed by Domtar’s chief executive, Raymond Royer. North American-based makers of fine paper, which is used mainly in copiers, computer printers, books and consumer packaging, are under pressure from lower-cost producers in Chile and Brazil. The lower value of the American dollar has made that situation even worse for Canadian producers, who export most of their paper to the United States. With the addition of Weyerhaeuser’s 10 pulp and paper mills, seven of which are in the United States, Domtar will become the largest producer of fine paper in North America. The increased scale of operations, Mr. Royer said, will allow Domtar to lower its production costs while the American mills will improve its ability to ship paper quickly to customers in the United States. To that end, Domtar will move its operations headquarters to Fort Mill, S.C. “This will give us the combination of low costs and high service,” Mr. Royer said. “Our goal was to balance our assets with our customers.” Founded in 1929 as Dominion Tar and Chemical, Domtar went on to produce a wide array of paper products and building supplies before its recent emphasis on fine paper. Neither Mr. Royer nor other Domtar executives offered specific examples of how they would achieve their forecast of a $200 million cut in operating costs. One of the Canadian Weyerhaeuser mills included in the deal was scheduled to close, and Mr. Royer said that would not change. Domtar has also announced plans to shut some of its Canadian mills. Mr. Royer acknowledged that the new company would not match South American producers, who benefit from cheap, fast-growing trees, on production costs. But he said that its ability to provide better service should offset that. Fine paper was a laggard among Weyerhaeuser’s businesses. The company will now be able to concentrate on its more profitable lines of operation, which include timberland, wood products, real estate and paperboard used in making corrugated boxes. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., will pay the 55 percent equity stake it acquires in Domtar directly to shareholders. But it will retain a $1.35 billion cash payment from Domtar and use it to reduce its debt. In a conference call with stock analysts, Steven R. Rogel, Weyerhaeuser’s chief executive, said that the company had considered several plans for the fine-paper operation. Ultimately, he said, combining it with Domtar “was the most value-creating option.” The deal was a long time in coming. Mr. Royer said that the two companies had been in negotiations for about a year and that initial discussion about the plan occurred much earlier. More Articles in Business »OTTAWA, Aug. 23  Weyerhaeuser will merge its fine-paper operation with a Canadian company, Domtar, in a cash-and-stock deal worth $3.3 billion, the two companies said Wednesday. Weyerhaeuser shareholders will own 55 percent of the combined operation, which will keep the Canadian company’s name and Montreal headquarters and be headed by Domtar’s chief executive, Raymond Royer. North American-based makers of fine paper, which is used mainly in copiers, computer printers, books and consumer packaging, are under pressure from lower-cost producers in Chile and Brazil. The lower value of the American dollar has made that situation even worse for Canadian producers, who export most of their paper to the United States. With the addition of Weyerhaeuser’s 10 pulp and paper mills, seven of which are in the United States, Domtar will become the largest producer of fine paper in North America. The increased scale of operations, Mr. Royer said, will allow Domtar to lower its production costs while the American mills will improve its ability to ship paper quickly to customers in the United States. To that end, Domtar will move its operations headquarters to Fort Mill, S.C. “This will give us the combination of low costs and high service,” Mr. Royer said. “Our goal was to balance our assets with our customers.” Founded in 1929 as Dominion Tar and Chemical, Domtar went on to produce a wide array of paper products and building supplies before its recent emphasis on fine paper. Neither Mr. Royer nor other Domtar executives offered specific examples of how they would achieve their forecast of a $200 million cut in operating costs. One of the Canadian Weyerhaeuser mills included in the deal was scheduled to close, and Mr. Royer said that would not change. Domtar has also announced plans to shut some of its Canadian mills. Mr. Royer acknowledged that the new company would not match South American producers, who benefit from cheap, fast-growing trees, on production costs. But he said that its ability to provide better service should offset that. Fine paper was a laggard among Weyerhaeuser’s businesses. The company will now be able to concentrate on its more profitable lines of operation, which include timberland, wood products, real estate and paperboard used in making corrugated boxes. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., will pay the 55 percent equity stake it acquires in Domtar directly to shareholders. But it will retain a $1.35 billion cash payment from Domtar and use it to reduce its debt. In a conference call with stock analysts, Steven R. Rogel, Weyerhaeuser’s chief executive, said that the company had considered several plans for the fine-paper operation. Ultimately, he said, combining it with Domtar “was the most value-creating option.” The deal was a long time in coming. Mr. Royer said that the two companies had been in negotiations for about a year and that initial discussion about the plan occurred much earlier.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/24/business/yourmoney/24gret.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Managers to Owners: Shut Up<date>Published: April 24, 2005</date><text>T'S annual shareholder meeting season again: that Groundhog Day moment when executives emerge from their rarefied world of corner offices, corporate jets and staffs of yes-men, to meet the company's owners and field their questions. For all their shortcomings, these annual meetings are the only time when democracy begins to enter into the investor experience today. But even that may be too much for Weyerhaeuser, the giant forest products company based in Federal Way, Wash. At its annual meeting last Thursday, the company's board and management broke with their longstanding tradition of taking shareholder questions from an open microphone on the floor. Instead, they required that shareholder questions be submitted in writing, either before or during the meeting. And Steven R. Rogel, the company's chief executive, announced that his directors and managers would devote just 15 minutes to answering the written questions. It's a disturbing precedent to abolish the single spontaneous interaction that executives - who, after all, are hired help - have with their owners every year. But Weyerhaeuser went even further, according to an investment manager who attended the meeting, by gaveling down several shareholders who tried to ask questions from the floor. And when management cut short the answer period and a proxy holder stood up to make a point of order and ask why, a beefy security guard removed him from the meeting. "It was a show of force that shareholders should be seen and not heard," said Bruce T. Herbert, president of Newground Social Investment in Seattle, the man who was escorted from the room. "I have never been to an annual meeting that didn't have Q.&amp; A." To be sure, companies are not required by law to answer shareholders' questions from the floor at annual meetings. And it is certainly understandable that companies want to rein in gadflies and disruptive questioners whose agendas do not match those of most shareholders. Still, controlling the give-and-take between shareholders and executives that occurs just once a year and lasts for only a few minutes does seem rather Kremlinesque. Frank Mendizabal, a spokesman for Weyerhaeuser, said: "What we were trying to do was ensure the meeting was orderly and that as many questions as possible were answered. It's a business meeting, not a forum for special interest groups." He said the company answered 12 of about 30 questions that were submitted and that it planned to communicate its responses to the remaining queries, though he said he did not know how it would do this. He added that Weyerhaeuser had not decided whether it would stick to the written-question format at next year's meeting, but that more questions were answered this year than in previous years when they came from the floor. One question that Mr. Herbert hoped to ask of Weyerhaeuser management was how it planned to respond to the decision last Wednesday by Calpers, the big California public pension fund, to put the company on its focus list of corporate laggards. Calpers said it included Weyerhaeuser on its list primarily because it has a so-called classified board, meaning that its directors are elected in different years. That structure makes it easier for the company to combat a takeover and makes directors that much more entrenched. A majority of Weyerhaeuser shareholders voted to declassify the company's board in 2000, 2002 and 2003, and again this year - to no avail. Weyerhaeuser prefers a classified board, Mr. Mendizabal said, because "we have to plan effectively over a long term and a staggered board assures that directors will have long-term experience and understand our business." "We were certainly surprised and disappointed that Calpers took that action," he added. "We pride ourselves on our ethics and corporate governance." The Weyerhaeuser meeting was well attended, Mr. Herbert said. He estimated that more than 500 people were in the audience at company headquarters, and he said that there was considerable tension in the room. While it is surely no fun for executives to submit to questions about their performance, their pay or their companies' practices at annual meetings, it should be considered part of the job. Shutting off the microphone allows them to close their ears to shareholder concerns and helps keep them comfortably insulated from the real world. And because there are typically time limits for each shareholder question at an annual meeting, the events usually end quickly. Weyerhaeuser, for example, limited questioners to three minutes in past years. The pain for executives, if there is any, doesn't last too long. IT'S the only time, once a year, when you can actually ask the C.E.O. or a member of the board of directors a question," said Adam M. Kanzer, general counsel and director of shareholder advocacy at Domini Social Investments. "One day a year doesn't really seem like too much to ask for." Maybe Weyerhaeuser's executives and board should be applauded for letting investors know where they stand. Why should executives pretend, even for an hour a year, that they care about their owners' views? Daniel J. Steininger, chairman of the Catholic Funds, a mutual fund company in Milwaukee, said the action by Weyerhaeuser looked like an attempt to gag shareholders. "This is the first time I've ever heard of anyone cutting off debate," he said. "Is there no limit to their failure to recognize who owns the company?" Making the Weyerhaeuser move even more perplexing, Mr. Steininger said, is the trend in recent years among many corporations to argue that they should receive the same rights that United States citizens do, such as the right to free speech. "If corporations are arguing for constitutional rights, how can they turn around and say to the shareholders who own them you have no right to speak?" he asked. "I just love the hypocrisy."</text></article><article index="4" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD7113AF93AA25751C0A9639C8B63&amp;ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; BRASCAN TO BUY WEYERHAEUSER TIMBER ASSETS<date>Published: February 19, 2005</date><text>Brascan, an electrical generation, real estate and natural resources holding company based in Toronto, agreed yesterday to acquire timberland and sawmills in British Columbia from the Weyerhaeuser Company for 1.2 billion Canadian dollars ($975 million). The transaction included 635,000 acres of private timberland, cutting rights on government land, five sawmills and two manufacturing operations. Brascan, which controls lumber operations in Brazil, eastern Canada and Maine, is shifting its focus to timber and away from mining. Last year, a metals trading company controlled by the Chinese government offered to buy Brascan's Noranda mining operation, although the two sides have not reached an agreement. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., has been selling assets to reduce debt. Ian Austen (NYT)</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/04/business/04wood.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser to Cover Cleanup Costs<date>Published: January 4, 2005</date><text>y Bloomberg News The Weyerhaeuser Company, the lumber company, agreed to pay $6.2 million for the cleanup of a Michigan river contaminated with polychlorinated biphenyls, two federal agencies said yesterday. Weyerhaeuser will also clean up a mill and a landfill near the Kalamazoo River that contain hundreds of thousands of pounds of the chemicals, the Justice Department and the Environmental Protection Agency said. Weyerhaeuser is one of several companies responsible for polychlorinated biphenyl contamination at the Kalamazoo River Superfund site, the government said. The settlement does not resolve the company's liability for such contamination at sites outside the mill and landfill or for natural resource damage, the government said. The $6.2 million will reimburse the E.P.A. for its cleanup of the river. A spokesman for Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., could not be reached for comment.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/24/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-profits-more-than-double-in-housing-boom.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER PROFITS MORE THAN DOUBLE IN HOUSING BOOM<date>Published: July 24, 2004</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the world's biggest lumber company, said yesterday that second-quarter profit more than doubled to a record $369 million as surging demand from homebuilders bolstered prices of wood products. Net income increased to $1.57 a share, from $157 million, or 71 cents, a year earlier. Sales climbed 20 percent to $5.9 billion from $4.9 billion, Weyerhaeuser said. Wood products, Weyerhaeuser's biggest business, benefited from a housing construction boom in the United States that caused the average lumber price in the quarter to surge 77 percent. The business had a $448 million profit, compared with a loss of $53 million a year earlier. Shares of Weyerhaeuser rose $1.32, to $59.98. The company is based in Federal Way, Wash.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/01/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-plans-to-sell-more-land-to-trim-debt.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER PLANS TO SELL MORE LAND TO TRIM DEBT<date>Published: July 01, 2004</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it had agreed to sell about 304,000 acres of timber land in Georgia to four companies for a total of $404 million, the largest in a series of recent sales to reduce debt. Details are being withheld until the deals close, probably in the third quarter of the year, Weyerhaeuser said. The buyers are Virginia Forest Investment of Hogansville and Macon, Ga.; Georgia Fall Line Properties of Greensboro, Ga.; Southern Timber Consultants of Perry, Ga.; and Copper Station Holdings No. 3 of Beaufort, S.C. As of last fall, Weyerhaeuser had about $12.7 billion in debt.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/22/business/company-news-jury-rules-weyerhaeuser-created-illegal-monopoly.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; JURY RULES WEYERHAEUSER CREATED ILLEGAL MONOPOLY<date>Published: May 22, 2004</date><text>A federal jury returned a verdict for nearly $5.3 million against the timber company Weyerhaeuser for creating an illegal monopoly in the alder market. The jury awarded the money to Washington Alder, a Mount Vernon, Wash., company with a single mill that competes with Weyerhaeuser. Damages will automatically be tripled to $15.9 million under the Sherman Antitrust Act. Weyerhaeuser said it would appeal the verdict. The verdict was the second in as many years against Weyerhaeuser involving alder logs. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., has settled two similar cases. Washington Alder accused Weyerhaeuser of hoarding logs to force shortages to make it difficult for competitors to obtain logs, and drive up prices. Alder is a type of wood. Weyerhaeuser also used its own timberlands and other private holdings to ensure its own supply, to the detriment of competitors, the suit claimed.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/23/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-pay-14-million-to-settle-claims.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO PAY $14 MILLION TO SETTLE CLAIMS<date>Published: April 23, 2004</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company agreed to pay $14 million to settle claims it monopolized the market for alder-saw log, a wood used to make furniture, flooring and finished lumber, the company said yesterday. The claims, made in a suit filed by Coast Mountain Hardwoods in United States District Court in Portland, Ore., originally sought $820 million in damages. Weyerhaeuser, which admitted no liability in the settlement, said it would take a charge of about $9 million, or 4 cents a share, in the first quarter. Weyerhaeuser acquired Coast Mountain in late 2000, leaving rights to the alder-saw suit with the previous owners.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/10/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-pay-34.5-million-settlement.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO PAY $34.5 MILLION SETTLEMENT<date>Published: March 10, 2004</date><text>Weyerhaeuser Company agreed to pay $34.5 million to settle claims that it monopolized the market for alder, a wood used to make furniture and flooring that grows only in the Pacific Northwest. The settlement with four mills follows a $79 million court decision against the company in a separate case last year, when jurors found that Weyerhaeuser sold alder at below-market prices and prevented a competitor from bidding on timberland. Two similar suits are scheduled to go to trial later this year. The settlement resolves claims by Cascade Hardwoods Inc. and Alexander Lumber Mill of Washington and Oregon's Westwood Lumber Company Inc. and Morton Alder Mill Inc. Weyerhaeuser admitted no liability and said it would take a $23 million charge, or 10 cents a share, in the first quarter to pay for the accord.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/24/business/profit-declines-27-at-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Profit Declines 27% at Weyerhaeuser<date>Published: January 24, 2004</date><text>Weyerhaeuser, the forest products company, said on Friday that its profit fell 27 percent in the fourth quarter as it took a series of one-time charges and recorded a big one-time gain on the sale of timberlands.Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., said that it earned $92 million, or 41 cents a share, down from $126 million, or 57 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.Revenue in the period, which ended Dec. 28, rose 9 percent, to $5.15 billion from $4.72 billion.For the quarter, Weyerhaeuser took charges of $41 million, or 24 cents a share, for closing facilities, restructuring and settling litigation. The company also reported a one-time gain of $40 million, or 18 cents a share, on the sale of timberlands.In the year-earlier period, Weyerhaeuser also took a big one-time charge -- for restructuring and the termination of a pension plan -- and recorded a big gain for timberlands sales and other actions.Without the one-time items, the company would have earned 47 cents a share for the most recent quarter, short of the 53 cents expected by analysts. Shares of Weyerhaeuser fell $3.33, or 5 percent, to $63.26.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/13/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-sell-timberland-to-pay-down-debt.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO SELL TIMBERLAND TO PAY DOWN DEBT<date>Published: December 13, 2003</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company agreed to sell 160,000 acres of timberland in western North Carolina and South Carolina to Forest Investment Associates for about $140 million to repay debt. The sale is expected to close by Wednesday, Weyerhaeuser said. Forest Investments, which is based in Atlanta, manages land and timber investments for pension plans and trusts. Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., had long-term debt of $12.1 billion at the end of September, according to its most recent earnings statement. The company said this year that it would sell 344,000 acres in Tennessee and the Carolinas.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/14/business/company-news-fitch-cuts-weyerhaeuser-s-credit-rating-to-junk-status.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; FITCH CUTS WEYERHAEUSER'S CREDIT RATING TO JUNK STATUS<date>Published: October 14, 2003</date><text>Fitch Ratings cut the Weyerhaeuser Company's credit rating to junk yesterday, saying the company, a producer of lumber and paper, was not generating cash fast enough to pay down debt. Weyerhaeuser's unsecured debt rating was cut to BB+ from BBB-, while the commercial paper ratings of Weyerhaeuser and the Weyerhaeuser Real Estate Company were cut to B, also a speculative rating, from F3, the lowest short-term investment grade rating. The rating outlook was changed to stable from negative. ''It is becoming increasingly difficult to see a sustainable improvement in the company's markets,'' Dennis Ruggles, a director in Fitch's forest products, mining and metals group, wrote. Moody's Investors Service rates the company's unsecured debt Baa2 while Standard &amp; Poor's rates the debt BBB, both investment- grade ratings.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/26/business/weyerhaeuser-net-doubles-on-forest-sales.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Net Doubles on Forest Sales<date>Published: July 26, 2003</date><text>Weyerhaeuser, the world's largest lumber company, said second-quarter earnings more than doubled on gains from the sale of timberland. Profit in the third quarter is expected to be hurt by lower demand and prices.Net income rose to $157 million, or 71 cents a share, from $72 million, or 32 cents a diluted share, in the period a year earlier. Sales rose less than 1 percent, to $4.93 billion from $4.92 billion, the company said.Weyerhaeuser, which bought Willamette Industries in 2002, has been selling timberland to pay down debt and has also been closing mills as lumber prices and paper demand fall. The company had a $95 million gain in the quarter from selling a 104,000-acre forest in Washington State to Hancock Timber Resources Group.Excluding gains from the sale and an insurance settlement, as well as expenses to close mills, the company had profit of 41 cents a share, above the 26 cents expected by analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call.Weyerhaeuser said profit at its pulp and paper unit would decline in the third quarter because of low prices and demand. Results at its timberlands unit also will drop because of a seasonal reduction in harvesting, and demand for packaging is expected to remain weak, the company said.The company said it reached its $300 million cost-savings goal planned for 2005 related to the Willamette acquisition. Its debt fell by 2.4 percent, to $13.6 billion, from the first quarter.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/11/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-sell-land-for-185-million-to-cut-debt.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO SELL LAND FOR $185 MILLION TO CUT DEBT<date>Published: March 11, 2003</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the lumber and paper maker, agreed to sell a 104,000-acre forest in Washington state to Hancock Timber Resource, an investment company, for $185 million to reduce debt. The sale of the forest, the Snoqualmie Tree Farm, will close in the second quarter, the companies said. Hancock Timber is a unit of John Hancock Financial Services Inc. Weyerhaeuser, which bought Willamette Industries in July and had debt of about $13.4 billion at the end of 2002, is selling land, closing mills and laying off workers. Hancock Timber manages timber investments for institutional investors.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/09/business/editors-note-editors-note-219061.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Editors' Note; EDITORS' NOTE<date>Published: February 09, 2003</date><text>An article on the Executive Life page last Sunday discussed the growing willingness of companies to fill board seats with younger executives who have little or no board experience. The article gave as one example Nicole W. Piasecki, 40, a vice president of Boeing Commercial Airlines, appointed in June to the board of Weyerhaeuser, the forest products company.The article did not mention that Ms. Piasecki is a great-great-granddaughter of Weyerhaeuser's founder and a daughter of the founder of a helicopter company that was sold to Boeing in 1960. None of those interviewed for the article, including Ms. Piasecki and Steven R. Rogel, Weyerhaeuser's chief executive, mentioned family connections, nor were they asked about any.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/21/business/company-news-canada-rejects-company-s-plan-to-end-lumber-dispute.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; CANADA REJECTS COMPANY'S PLAN TO END LUMBER DISPUTE<date>Published: November 21, 2002</date><text>Canada rejected a proposal made yesterday by Weyerhaeuser, the big lumber producer, that the two countries end a lumber dispute by replacing United States import duties with a temporary Canadian export tax. Canada's trade minister, Pierre Pettigrew, said the export tax would legitimize the unfair punitive measures already taken by the United States. Weyerhaeuser proposed a temporary maximum 25 percent export tax on softwood lumber shipped to the United States. The United States now collects duties averaging 27 percent on Canadian lumber, arguing that the wood is unfairly subsidized in Canada and sold at below-market prices.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/23/business/company-news-slump-in-wood-industry-dampens-weyerhaeuser-profit.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; SLUMP IN WOOD INDUSTRY DAMPENS WEYERHAEUSER PROFIT<date>Published: October 23, 2002</date><text>The forest products giant Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that third-quarter earnings fell 86 percent because of low wood prices, duties on imports of Canadian softwood lumber and merger-related charges. The company, based in Federal Way, Wash., reported a profit including one-time items of $13 million, or 6 cents a share, compared with a profit of $91 million, or 41 cents a share, a year ago. Weyerhaeuser, which announced a major timberland sale and two plant closings on Monday, is suffering in a downturn in the wood and paper industry that has lasted more than two years.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/17/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-cut-750-jobs-at-headquarters.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO CUT 750 JOBS AT HEADQUARTERS<date>Published: October 17, 2002</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it planned to cut 750 jobs at its headquarters through layoffs and attrition by the end of 2004. The cuts amount to 26 percent of the company's corporate staff of 2,850. The company employs 58,000 people around the world. Most of the latest cuts will come next year, a spokesman, Paul Barnum, said, although the finance and information-technology departments will be hit the hardest. Weyerhaeuser is based in Federal Way, Wash.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/09/business/jobs-cuts-at-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Jobs Cuts at Weyerhaeuser<date>Published: October 09, 2002</date><text>Weyerhaeuser, the forest products giant, said today that it would close a Canadian containerboard mill, cutting 140 jobs, in an effort to streamline its business and increase efficiency.The company said it would close its mill in Sturgeon Falls, Ontario, in early December, eliminating 100,000 tons of capacity. About six employees will stay on to operate a hydroelectric dam there.Weyerhaeuserhas been in a downturn for more than two years. Last month, it said third-quarter profit would fall below estimates because of low prices for wood and import duties on Canadian softwood lumber.Its shares closed up $1.08, to $39.98.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/25/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-cuts-3rd-quarter-earnings-forecast.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER CUTS 3RD-QUARTER EARNINGS FORECAST<date>Published: September 25, 2002</date><text>The forest products company Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that its third-quarter profits would fall short of forecasts, hurt by low wood prices and duties on imports of Canadian softwood lumber. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., said it expected earnings of 5 cents to 10 cents a share. Analysts surveyed by Thomson First Call had expected a profit of 35 cents a share. Weyerhaeuser said its wood products business would probably post a loss for the quarter.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/27/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-cut-90-jobs-at-pennsylvania-mill.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO CUT 90 JOBS AT PENNSYLVANIA MILL<date>Published: August 27, 2002</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would permanently close a 70-year-old papermaking machine at its Johnsonburg, Pa., fine paper mill, eliminating 90 jobs, as it continues to integrate Willamette Industries into its operations. Two other paper machines at the Johnsonburg site are not affected. Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., said the closing was effective immediately. About 30 of the jobs cut had already been eliminated through attrition. Weyerhaeuser bought Willamette for $6.2 billion in stock as of June 30 after an extended hostile takeover battle. The company has closed several other sites this year.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/07/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-close-plants-and-cut-206-jobs.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO CLOSE PLANTS AND CUT 206 JOBS<date>Published: June 07, 2002</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the lumber and paper producer, said yesterday that it would eliminate 206 jobs as it closes plants in Colorado, Louisiana and Oregon after its purchase of Willamette Industries. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., will eliminate 83 jobs in Denver by closing a packaging plant and shifting production to its facility in Golden, Colo. Weyerhaeuser, which employs more than 60,000 workers, will cut 123 more jobs by closing two lumber plants in Louisiana and Oregon, said Bruce Amundson, a company spokesman. Weyerhaeuser has been closing plants to cope with a decline in demand for paper used in boxes, magazines and books. The company completed its $7.8 billion acquisition of Willamette in March.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/24/business/weyerhaeuser-posts-loss-for-the-quarter.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Posts Loss for the Quarter<date>Published: January 24, 2002</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, facing what the chief executive said was the worst industry conditions in a quarter century, reported a loss for the fourth quarter today because of a one-time charge for closing three plants.For the quarter ended Dec. 30, Weyerhaeuser had a net loss of $15 million, or 7 cents a share, in contrast to earnings of $194 million, or 88 cents a share, in the fourth quarter of 2000.The results included a one-time after-tax charge of $20 million, or 9 cents a share, for closing three wood products plants.Sales were $3.4 billion, a 16 percent decrease from $4 billion in the period a year ago.Steven Rogel, the chief executive of Weyerhaeuser, said the company was dealing with the worst industry conditions since 1975.''We do not see any significant improvement in business conditions in the near term,'' Mr. Rogel said in a conference call with journalists and analysts.Despite the poor outlook, shares of Weyerhaeuser rose $1.20, to $54.92, on the New York Stock Exchange.The company's stock also rose the day before on news that its rival, Willamette Industries, had finally agreed Monday to be acquired for $6.1 billion.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/22/business/weyerhaeuser-seems-to-win-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Seems to Win Willamette<date>Published: January 22, 2002</date><text>Willamette Industries said late yesterday that it had agreed in principle to accept a sweetened $6.1 billion cash offer from the Weyerhaeuser Company.In a statement, Willamette said its board would consider the Weyerhaeuser offer, which amounts to $55.50 a share, at its next meeting, to be held before the end of the month.''A thorough review of our options in the last few days points to this as the best course for Willamette shareholders,'' said Jackie Lang, a Willamette spokeswoman.The agreement could end a 14-month hostile effort by Weyerhaeuser to acquire Willamette, the forest-products company based in Portland, Ore. The combined entity would be one of the biggest companies in the United States timber industry.Willamette's decision comes just 17 days after its board rejected a $55-a-share all-cash offer from Weyerhaeuser as inadequate. At the time, Willamette's board urged shareholders not to tender any shares to Weyerhaeuser.On Jan. 11, a week after it rejected the Weyerhaeuser offer, Weyerhaeuser said that 64 percent of Willamette's outstanding shares had been tendered in support of the $55-a-share offer.In addition to announcing an agreement in principle to accept the Weyerhaeuser offer, Willamette said it had ended discussions with the Georgia-Pacific Corporation about buying that company's building products unit.Willamette began discussions on Dec. 10 to acquire the building products business, which generated about $7 billion in revenue in 2000. The move was widely seen as a defense against Weyerhaeuser's hostile bid.Weyerhaeuser began its quest for Willamette on Nov. 11, 2000, when it made an unsolicited $48-a-share offer to acquire the company. Willamette's board rejected the offer, which included the assumption of $1.7 billion in debt.''The day before Weyerhaeuser made its initial offer, our stock was trading at $34.75'' a share, Ms. Lang said. ''We have gone from there to $55.50, a 60 percent premium.''Willamette operates 106 plants in four countries and owns 1.7 million acres of forest land in the United States. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., has offices or operations in 17 countries.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/18/business/company-news-calpers-urges-willamette-to-allow-hostile-takeover.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; CALPERS URGES WILLAMETTE TO ALLOW HOSTILE TAKEOVER<date>Published: January 18, 2002</date><text>The California Public Employees' Retirement System urged Willamette Industries yesterday to abandon its negotiations with Georgia-Pacific and allow a hostile takeover by a rival, Weyerhaeuser. In a letter to Willamette's chairman, William Swindells, the pension fund accused the Willamette board of trying to block shareholder support for the Weyerhaeuser offer. ''Willamette's board is running away from a merger with Weyerhaeuser that is in the best interests of share owners,'' said Mark Anson, the chief investment officer for the pension fund, known as Calpers. Calpers owns 482,700 shares of Willamette stock and 868,800 shares of Weyerhaeuser. A Willamette spokeswoman said talks with Georgia-Pacific were continuing because the board thought such a deal had potential value for shareholders.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/18/us/national-briefing-northwest-washington-accord-on-a-forest.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">National Briefing | Northwest: Washington: Accord On A Forest<date>Published: January 18, 2002</date><text>An environmental organization and the Weyerhaeuser Company, one of the world's largest timber concerns, have negotiated a deal that will set aside 100,000 acres of land east of Seattle as a working forest, protecting it from development. The environmental group, the Evergreen Forest Trust, is to pay Weyerhaeuser $185 million for the tract and will harvest much of it, as the company did, although 20,000 acres of delicate wildlife habitat and riverbanks will be exempted from logging. The land, the trust's first acquisition, covers Cascade foothills in parts of two counties where population growth has been rapid.Matthew Preusch (NYT)</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/11/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-says-willamette-bid-has-strong-support.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER SAYS WILLAMETTE BID HAS STRONG SUPPORT<date>Published: January 11, 2002</date><text>Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that it had strong support for its $6 billion bid to take over Willamette Industries, setting off a rally in Willamette's stock price. Weyerhaeuser said that 70 million shares of Willamette, about 64 percent of its stock, remained tendered and had not been withdrawn by a deadline that expired yesterday. Weyerhaeuser also extended its $55-a-share offer until midnight Feb. 27. Willamette has been trying to fend off Weyerhaeuser by talking with Georgia-Pacific about buying Georgia-Pacific's troubled building products division. A Willamette spokeswoman declined to comment. Shares of Willamette rose $2.95, or 6.8 percent, to $46.46. Shares of Weyerhaeuser fell 78 cents, to $53.37.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/05/business/company-news-willamette-rejects-6.1-billion-bid-by-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE REJECTS $6.1 BILLION BID BY WEYERHAEUSER<date>Published: January 05, 2002</date><text>Willamette Industries said yesterday that it had rejected the Weyerhaeuser Company's $6.1 billion takeover bid as inadequate and has cut off discussions about a buyout. The board urged shareholders not to tender any shares to Weyerhaeuser, which has been trying for more than a year to take over its timber industry rival. Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, Wash., is offering $55 a share for Willamette, which is based in Portland, Ore. Weyerhaeuser raised its bid from $50 last month, but Willamette said the higher price was inadequate because the combined company could cut its expenses more than Weyerhaeuser had estimated. Willamette said it had decided to continue talks with the Georgia-Pacific Corporation about combining their building-materials businesses.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/03/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-says-it-won-t-raise-bid-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER SAYS IT WON'T RAISE BID FOR WILLAMETTE<date>Published: January 03, 2002</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would not raise its $7.76 billion bid for Willamette Industries because the merger would not provide enough savings to justify a higher price. Directors of Willamette will meet today or tomorrow and assess Weyerhaeuser's offer of $55 a share. Weyerhaeuser said it did not think it could save much more than the $300 million a year it had identified after talks with Willamette last month. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., has been pursuing Willamette for more than a year. Willamette, based in Portland, Ore., agreed last month to talk with Weyerhaeuser for the first time, after the company increased its bid to $55 a share from $50.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/19/business/company-news-willamette-agrees-to-talk-with-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE AGREES TO TALK WITH WEYERHAEUSER<date>Published: December 19, 2001</date><text>Willamette Industries Inc., which has been trying to thwart a hostile takeover bid from the Weyerhaeuser Company for more than a year, said yesterday that it was willing to start negotiations about the sweetened offer it has received from its rival in the lumber and paper business. No decision on the proposal is expected before its board reconvenes in the first week of January, Willamette said. Weyerhaeuser raised its offer 10 percent, to $55 a share, on Thursday. The proposal was increased to $7.76 billion after Willamette began talks to buy or to create a venture with the Georgia-Pacific Group's building-products business. Willamette will also continue to hold negotiations with Georgia-Pacific.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/14/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-raises-bid-for-willamette-to-55-a-share.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER RAISES BID FOR WILLAMETTE TO $55 A SHARE<date>Published: December 14, 2001</date><text>Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that it was making its final offer to a rival, Willamette Industries, after a yearlong hostile takeover bid, raising its cash bid to $55 a share, or about $6 billion. Weyerhaeuser had been offering $50 a share for Willamette, which announced last week that it had opened talks with Georgia-Pacific. In a letter to Willamette, Weyerhaeuser's chairman, Steven R. Rogel, said the company would end its takeover bid if Willamette rejected the increased offer and pursued a deal to buy the Georgia-Pacific building products division. A Willamette spokeswoman said the company had received the offer but would not comment immediately.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/11/business/willamette-to-pursue-acquisition-to-try-to-thwart-hostile-bid.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Willamette to Pursue Acquisition to Try to Thwart Hostile Bid<date>Published: December 11, 2001</date><text>The timber company Willamette Industries authorized its management yesterday to start talks to buy a large unit of the rival Georgia-Pacific Corporation, a move seen as another major defense against a year-old hostile bid from the Weyerhaeuser Company. An acquisition of the building products business -- which had revenue of around $7 billion last year -- would make Willamette a leading maker of wood panels and lumber and a big distributor of other building material products. Willamette took the initiative to start talks in what could be described as the final snub to Weyerhaeuser's $5.5 billion offer last year. A large Willamette acquisition would create an entirely different company, and essentially invalidate Weyerhaeuser's offer. That means Willamette's stock could decline on fears that Weyerhaeuser could pull its offer. Weyerhaeuser declined to comment but Willamette's shares showed early signs of decline, shedding 60 cents in after-hours trading at $44. Georgia-Pacific was one of the most actively traded issues in after-hours, losing $1.52, to $28.95. Willamette's board, which includes three Weyerhaeuser directors, gave the go-ahead yesterday afternoon for talks with Georgia-Pacific. The board of Georgia-Pacific, based in Atlanta, also authorized management to start a dialogue with Willamette on combining the two businesses. Weyerhaeuser's last offer on the table was at $50 a Willamette share, which closed at $46.40 yesterday. Two months ago, Willamette indicated it was willing to discuss an offer closer to $60 a share but it was turned down by Weyerhaeuser. ''They publicly slammed the door shut on that overture in less than two hours without so much as a phone call,'' said Duane McDougall, president and chief executive of Willamette Industries, ''and we made it clear that we intended to pursue our strategic plan. That's what we are doing.'' A potential deal would give Georgia-Pacific the opportunity to sell a business that has been experiencing much slower growth compared with the rest of the company's consumer paper, packaging, and container-board business lines. Georgia-Pacific has been considering several options on this business and its chairman and chief executive, Pete Correll, said yesterday that one option being considered was splitting the company in two. An economic downturn has hit the building products business recently and most of the products had a sales decline in the third quarter. Gypsum wallboard sales fell 27.6 percent; lumber sales dropped 18.8 percent; particle-board sales fell 12.6 percent; and plywood shrank 7.4 percent. The company was recently forced to slow down production to match demand. It recently decided to run its gypsum plant on a one-shift, five-day basis. A possible divestiture of the business would be the latest in a string of transformation deals that Georgia-Pacific has done recently. In 1997, it spun off its timberland assets. Last year the company bought the Fort James Corporation, which turned Georgia-Pacific into the world's largest maker of tissue paper.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/07/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-extends-bid-for-willamette-until-jan-9.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER EXTENDS BID FOR WILLAMETTE UNTIL JAN. 9<date>Published: December 7, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, which began an uninvited bid for Willamette Industries a year ago, extended its $5.5 billion tender offer for the company, a rival in forest products, until Jan. 9. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., said about 47.7 percent of Willamette's 110 million shares were tendered under the $50-a-share offer. Weyerhaeuser, which had already extended the offer to Dec. 5, received clearance from the Federal Trade Commission for its offer last week. Willamette is based in Portland, Ore.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/15/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-plans-to-close-3-sawmills-by-year-s-end.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER PLANS TO CLOSE 3 SAWMILLS BY YEAR'S END<date>Published: November 15, 2001</date><text>Struggling with a weak timber market, the Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would close three sawmills and other operations in Arkansas, Canada and Mexico by the end of the year. More than 600 workers will lose their jobs because of the closings, said a spokesman, Bruce Amundson. The company warned that it would take an after-tax charge of $21 million, or 10 cents a share, in the fourth quarter to cover the costs of the closings. At the same time, the company said it planned to make improvements to mills in Arkansas and Oklahoma.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/01/business/us-imposes-a-second-duty-on-canadian-lumber-imports.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">U.S. Imposes a Second Duty On Canadian Lumber Imports<date>Published: November 1, 2001</date><text>TORONTO, Oct. 31— The Commerce Department accused Canadian lumber producers of unfair trade practices today and imposed a double-digit duty on their exports to the United States. The department said today that it would impose antidumping duties averaging 12.6 percent on imports of softwood lumber, flooring and siding from six Canadian producers. The duties, which range from 5.9 percent to 19.2 percent, are the second imposed in the last three months. A countervailing duty of 19.3 percent was imposed on Aug. 17. Canadian lumber, used mainly in housing, has about a third of the American market. Imports last year were valued at $6.38 billion, the Commerce Department said. The latest duty is a response to complaints by American producers that Canadian companies have flouted international trade rules by exporting lumber at prices below their production costs, a practice known as dumping. The earlier countervailing duty, the Commerce Department said, was intended to offset the benefits of subsidies to Canadian sawmills, such as low fees for harvesting trees in government-owned forests. Both duties are preliminary, with final determinations expected next March after further discussions with the affected parties. American homebuilders and other lumber users criticized the antidumping duty, saying it raised the cost of material at a time of weakening demand. Michael Carliner, chief economist at the National Association of Home Builders in Washington, said today that the pain that it caused the customer was greater than the benefit to producers in the United States. The Canfor Corporation, a leading softwood lumber producer in Vancouver, British Columbia, has set aside 11.5 million Canadian dollars ($7.3 million) after taxes in the third quarter to cover its potential liability for countervailing duties. The chief executive of Canfor, David Emerson, said today that the company would be forced to mothballed a third of its sawmilling capacity by the end of the year. Any assessment of the effect of the duties is complicated by the downturn in the housing sector and the weakening demand for lumber. Prices, as measured by the framing lumber composite price compiled by Random Lengths, a trade publication based in Eugene, Ore., slipped to $275 for a thousand board feet last week, from a high of $402 in May. Burrle Elmore, editor of Random Lengths, said although the duties have raised costs for Canadian mills, everyone is feeling the pain because of the soft market for lumber. Failing a negotiated settlement, the Canadian producers have said they would appeal the Commerce Department decisions to the courts and invoke the dispute settlement provisions of the North American Free Trade agreement and the World Trade Organization. The six companies hit by the antidumping duty are Canfor, Abitibi-Consolidated, Tembec, West Fraser Timber, Slocan Forest Products and the Canadian unit of Weyerhaeuser.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/12/business/company-news-willamette-says-higher-bid-must-precede-talks.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE SAYS HIGHER BID MUST PRECEDE TALKS<date>Published: October 12, 2001</date><text>Willamette Industries, a maker of lumber and paper, said yesterday that it would agree to takeover talks if its suitor, Weyerhaeuser, sweetened its offer of $7.18 billion, or $50 a share. ''If you make a written offer in the high $50's, we will agree to sit down for discussions,'' William Swindells, Willamette's chairman, said in a letter to Steven R. Rogel, the Weyerhaeuser chairman and chief. It was the first time that Willamette had publicly suggested what it thought was a fair offer, and the move may bring an end to an 11-month stalemate. Willamette is under pressure from shareholders to sell the company as profits decline with the slowing economy. Mr. Rogel has said he will increase the offer only if Willamette negotiates first.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/29/business/company-news-2-production-lines-to-close-weaker-outlook-is-cited.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; 2 PRODUCTION LINES TO CLOSE; WEAKER OUTLOOK IS CITED<date>Published: September 29, 2001</date><text>Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that it would permanently close two production lines, which employ about 200 people, take a $20 million one-time charge, and warned that third-quarter earnings would be lower than analysts expected. Weyerhaeuser said it expected to earn 40 to 45 cents a share for the third quarter, excluding the one-time charge of about 9 cents for the closings. Analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call were expecting earnings of 55 cents a share for the quarter, which ended Sept. 30. Weyerhaeuser is based in Federal Way, Wash.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/15/business/weyerhaeuser-extends-offer-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Extends Offer for Willamette<date>Published: September 15, 2001</date><text>FEDERAL WAY, Wash., Sept. 14— The Weyerhaeuser Company extended its offer to buy shares in its timber rival Willamette Industries for the sixth time, even as Weyerhaeuser appeared to be losing ground in its hostile takeover bid. The $50-a-share offer was set to expire today, but will now run until Oct. 17. As of Monday, the last day of regular trading before the terrorist attack Tuesday, Weyerhaeuser said shareholders had tendered or not withdrawn about 30 percent of the shares outstanding, or about 32.7 million of the 109 million Willamette shares available. That was a decline from the 43 percent of shares, or about 46.5 million shares, that the Willamette shareholders had pledged as of Aug. 15. Willamette said in August it planned to buy back up to 10 million shares, or almost 10 percent of the company's stock, to fight Weyerhaeuser's takeover bid. Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Federal Way, has been trying for months to win the takeover battle for Willamette, based in Portland, Ore. Earlier this year, Willamette shareholders narrowly elected three new board members friendly to Weyerhaeuser's takeover bid.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/17/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-extends-offer-for-willamette-shares.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER EXTENDS OFFER FOR WILLAMETTE SHARES<date>Published: August 17, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, still trying to win a hostile takeover of a rival, Willamette Industries, extended by a month its offer to buy Willamette shares. The offer, $50 a share, was to expire Wednesday but will now run until Sept. 14, Weyerhaeuser said. It was the fifth extension Weyerhaeuser has filed. As of Wednesday, Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., said shareholders had tendered about 43 percent of Willamette's outstanding shares. Willamette is based in Portland, Ore. Separately yesterday, Weyerhaeuser said it would curtail production at three Canadian mills, putting about 1,000 people out of work for at least two weeks.</text></article></page><page index="6"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/27/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-expects-to-beat-earnings-forecasts.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER EXPECTS TO BEAT EARNINGS FORECASTS<date>Published: June 27, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it expected to beat analysts' earnings expectations for the second quarter, citing stronger-than-expected prices for wood products and a one-time change in Canadian taxes. The timber company expects to earn 70 to 75 cents a share for the three months ended June 1. A survey by Thomson Financial/First Call had predicted earnings of 56 cents a share. Weyerhaeuser's projection comes as the timber industry is in a slump, beset by weak prices and tougher environmental regulation. Weyerhaeuser is also currently embroiled in a hostile takeover bid for a rival, Willamette Industries.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/24/business/private-sector-his-past-as-acquisition-target.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Private Sector; His Past, as Acquisition Target<date>Published: June 24, 2001</date><text>STEVEN R. ROGEL is not just an engineer by education. He is an engineer to the bone. He can picture how pipes and screws and cogs work together to create a process -- and how tweaking any one of them can make that process better.He applies the same how-things-fit logic to companies. Mr. Rogel looks at the Weyerhaeuser Company, the big paper manufacturer in Federal Way, Wash., that he has run since late 1997, and at the smaller Willamette Industries, the Portland, Ore., company from which he hails, and to him it is obvious: They are the same where sameness helps, yet their differences fit as neatly as pieces of a jigsaw puzzle.''We're West Coast companies with West Coast cultures, we've got identical businesses and complimentary locations, and there just is no better fit,'' Mr. Rogel, 58, said.Nonetheless, William Swindells, Willamette's chairman and Mr. Rogel's one-time mentor and champion, has been fighting Mr. Rogel's overtures for more than two years. Mr. Swindells says that the fight is ''not personal'' and that he would be more amenable if Mr. Rogel appreciably sweetened his bid of $5.5 billion, or $50 a share.But Cathy Dunn, spokeswoman for Willamette, says employees, many of whom have 401(k)'s in Willamette stock, are angry. ''Steve wants to pay us pennies on the dollar for something we know has much greater value,'' she said. ''He is destroying his relationship with those he says he needs to build the merged companies into a global leader.''For some people, trying to wrest a company away from people who were friends and colleagues for more than two decades would pose a huge emotional conflict. But not for Mr. Rogel.''I sleep well at night,'' he said. ''I'm doing the right thing not just for Weyerhaeuser, but for good friends at Willamette.''Weyerhaeuser nominated three directors to Willamette's nine-member board at Willamette's annual shareholder meeting on June 7 and said it believed they had won the vote. Willamette declined to predict the outcome, which is expected to be announced this week. The Weyerhaeuser nominees, if elected, would intensify pressure on Willamette to accept Mr. Rogel's offer.Many people in the industry may be rooting for him. Paper manufacturers, burdened by overcapacity, have been consolidating. In the last few years, International Paper has digested Union Camp, Georgia-Pacific bought Fort James and Weyerhaeuser bought MacMillan Bloedel and TJ International.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/08/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-extends-its-bid-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER EXTENDS ITS BID FOR WILLAMETTE<date>Published: June 08, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it had extended its $5.5 billion takeover bid for Willamette Industries, its paper industry rival, after a shareholder vote on three new directors proved too close to call. Weyerhaeuser said that based on the number of proxies it had submitted to an independent voter service, it thought its slate of three directors would be elected, but Willamette said that the vote was too close to call and that results would not be known for two to three weeks. Weyerhaeuser, which has said it will withdraw its bid if it loses the shareholder vote, extended its tender offer, for $50 a share, until June 28.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/02/business/layoffs-at-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Layoffs at Weyerhaeuser<date>Published: June 02, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, which settled a strike Thursday with workers protesting the use of nonunion labor, laid off 235 of them today at plants in Washington and Oregon because of slowing demand for paper and boxes.The mills are in Springfield, Ore., and Longview, Wash.. The average weekly box shipments have dropped by 7 percent and shipments for paper made in Longview through April declined 12 percent, the company said.The workers are among the 1,400 members of the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers union who ended the three-week strike Thursday by approving a new contract. The employees were protesting plans to use nonunion workers for maintenance jobs, like painting fences.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/25/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-slate-for-rival-s-board-gets-support.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER SLATE FOR RIVAL'S BOARD GETS SUPPORT<date>Published: May 25, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company's bid to gain three seats on the board of its rival, Willamette Industries, won the backing of a second consulting firm that advises shareholders on proxy votes. Weyerhaeuser, which nominated the candidates as part of its attempt to buy Willamette for $5.5 billion, said yesterday that the recommendation was made by Proxy Monitor, an independent firm that makes recommendations on pending proxy fights for large institutional shareholders. Earlier this week, Institutional Shareholder Services also supported the Weyerhaeuser slate. The shareholder vote for directors is scheduled for June 7.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/22/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-extends-bid-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER EXTENDS BID FOR WILLAMETTE<date>Published: May 22, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company extended its $5.5 billion hostile bid for its smaller rival Willamette Industries, but promised to withdraw the offer if its battle to win three Willamette board seats next month fails. Weyerhaeuser of Federal Way, Wash., extended its $50-a-share takeover offer until June 7, the same day Willamette shareholders will gather in Portland, Ore., for the company's annual meeting. Weyerhaeuser has nominated a slate of three rival directors for election to Willamette's board, and said it would withdraw its offer if it lost the board proxy fight.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/15/business/company-news-willamette-calls-takeover-offer-inadequate.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE CALLS TAKEOVER OFFER INADEQUATE<date>Published: May 15, 2001</date><text>The paper products company Willamette Industries said yesterday that it had sent a letter to its shareholders saying that a $5.5 billion takeover bid from its rival, the Weyerhaeuser Company was ''inadequate and not in the best interests of shareholders.'' Willamette, which is based in Portland, Ore., had previously dismissed Weyerhaeuser's revised bid of $50 a share as a ''bargain basement'' offer. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., raised the bid last week from the $48 a share it bid in November.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/10/business/company-news-willamette-rejects-increased-bid-from-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE REJECTS INCREASED BID FROM WEYERHAEUSER<date>Published: May 10, 2001</date><text>The forest products company Willamette Industries said yesterday that it had rejected an improved takeover offer from its rival, the Weyerhaeuser Company. Weyerhaeuser raised its offer on Monday, to $50 a share from $48, hoping to lure more Willamette shareholders to its side before Willamette's annual shareholder meeting on June 7, when a vote on a new slate of directors is expected. The new offer values Willamette's 109 million shares at about $5.45 billion. Weyerhaeuser would also assume $1.65 billion in Willamette debt in the deal. ''As we have said many times, we will not negotiate at what we regard as bargain basement prices and it is not our strategy to sell the company,'' the Willamette board said in a letter to its counterparts at Weyerhaeuser.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/08/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-increases-hostile-bid-for-rival.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER INCREASES HOSTILE BID FOR RIVAL<date>Published: May 08, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company increased its offer yesterday to buy its rival, Willamette Industries, from $48 a share, to $50 a share. The move increases Weyerhaeuser's hostile bid by $219 million, to about $5.5 billion. It represents a 44 percent premium over Willamette's share price the day before the offer was announced in November. In a letter to Willamette's chairman, William Swindells, Weyerhaeuser's chief executive, Steven R. Rogel, said that if a deal could not be reached soon, Weyerhaeuser would seek to have three nominees friendly to the takeover elected to the Willamette board at its June 7 annual meeting. Willamette, based in Portland, Ore., has urged shareholders to reject the candidates nominated by Weyerhaeuser. Weyerhaeuser is based in Federal Way, Wash.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/13/business/company-news-willamette-says-again-it-intends-to-stay-independent.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE SAYS AGAIN IT INTENDS TO STAY INDEPENDENT<date>Published: April 13, 2001</date><text>Willamette Industries yesterday repeated its intent to remain independent, saying it had not heard anything new from its hostile suitor, the Weyerhaeuser Company, to prompt a start of friendly negotiations. Willamette's chief executive, Duane C. McDougall, said the company remained ''adamantly opposed'' to a $5.4 billion hostile bid that Weyerhaeuser first proposed in November. Weyerhaeuser's current $48-a-share cash tender offer for Willamette is due to expire on May 18. Weyerhaeuser also plans a proxy fight at Willamette's annual meeting in June to place three directors on the company's board.</text></article></page><page index="7"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/13/business/weyerhaeuser-extends-deadline-on-bid.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Extends Deadline on Bid<date>Published: March 13, 2001</date><text>Weyerhaeuser today extended its hostile $5.4 billion tender offer for Willamette Industries until May 18.Weyerhaeuser said that as of noon today, about 31.4 million shares, or 29 percent, had been tendered in support of the offer, which was to expire on March 30.Some shares that had previously been tendered were withdrawn, lowering the most recent total from the nearly 55.7 million Willamette shares, or slightly more than half the outstanding shares, that supported the proposal early last month.Willamette, a paper products company, has consistently rebuffed Weyerhaeuser's takeover offer, first made in November.Weyerhaeuser has proposed placing four of its directors on Willamette's board at its next annual meeting in June, but it will need support of at least 50 percent of Willamette shares to do so.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/09/business/company-news-willamette-target-of-a-takeover-bid-sets-meeting.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE, TARGET OF A TAKEOVER BID, SETS MEETING<date>Published: March 09, 2001</date><text>Willamette Industries, the target of a hostile takeover bid by the Weyerhaeuser Company, said yesterday that it will hold its annual shareholders meeting June 7. Willamette changed its corporate bylaws to delay the meeting, which was originally scheduled for April. In a letter to Willamette shareholders on Feb. 27, Weyerhaeuser said that the Willamette board delayed the annual meeting so that shareholders could not be heard. One takeover defense tactic is that only three of Willamette's nine directors are up for re-election each year at the shareholders meeting. It would take Weyerhaeuser two annual meetings to gain a majority on the board. Willamette and Weyerhaeuser have nominees for three open positions this year.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/23/business/company-news-willamette-restates-resistance-to-weyerhaeuser-bid.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE RESTATES RESISTANCE TO WEYERHAEUSER BID<date>Published: February 23, 2001</date><text>Willamette Industries, the forestry products company, said yesterday that its board had sent a letter to a rival, the Weyerhaeuser Company, restating its commitment to resist Weyerhaeuser's hostile $5.4 billion takeover bid. Willamette's board also sent a letter to its shareholders, urging them to reject the Weyerhaeuser offer and reiterating its belief that the bid is inadequate. It advised shareholders not to return the proxy card Weyerhaeuser has circulated in its attempt to unseat the Willamette board. Weyerhaeuser began a $48-per-share bid for Willamette in November.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/02/business/weyerhaeuser-extends-an-offer.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Extends an Offer<date>Published: February 02, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company will extend a $5.4 billion tender offer for Willamette Industries until the end of March as part of its hostile takeover bid.Weyerhaeuser's $48-a-share offer, which was scheduled to expire today, will be extended until March 30, the company said. This is the second time that Weyerhaeuser has extended its offer, under which it would also assume $1.7 billion in debt.Willamette, the forest products company based in Portland, Ore., reiterated today that the offer was too low and recommended that its shareholders not tender their shares.''Weyerhaeuser may choose to keep extending its $48-per-share offer indefinitely, but it won't change anything,'' Duane McDougall, the chief executive of Willamette, said in a statement. ''Our board has said Willamette is not for sale and has made it clear, in public documents and numerous previously disclosed conversations with Weyerhaeuser executives, that their offer is inadequate.''As of today, 55.7 million shares had been tendered, about 51 percent of Willamette's outstanding shares. Weyerhaeuser said in January that it was extending its tender offer to gain more shares, allowing it to vote in board members who can eliminate a so-called poison pill that Willamette has in place. Under poison pills, companies distribute convertible stock as dividends to existing shareholders. The stock will usually convert to an equal amount of the existing shares. The move could double the amount needed for the takeover.''We can't buy the shares until Willamette lifts the poison pill,'' said Bruce Amundson, a Weyerhaeuser spokesman.Shares of Willamette rose 8 cents, to $47.29. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, rose 69 cents, to $53.19.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/06/business/company-news-bid-for-willamette-industries-is-extended.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; BID FOR WILLAMETTE INDUSTRIES IS EXTENDED<date>Published: January 06, 2001</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, a timber and paper business, yesterday extended its $5.4 billion hostile bid for its smaller rival, Willamette Industries, until Feb. 1, after its offer of $48 a share fell short of the majority needed for a hostile takeover. Weyerhaeuser said 48 percent of the shares had been tendered. Takeover experts viewed the move as positive for a future friendly deal between the two companies, but said Weyerhaeuser would still have to sweeten its bid to force Willamette to the bargaining table. Weyerhaeuser began its bid more than a month ago after Willamette rejected the offer, saying the company was not for sale.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/13/business/company-news-willamette-asks-stockholders-to-reject-takeover-bid.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WILLAMETTE ASKS STOCKHOLDERS TO REJECT TAKEOVER BID<date>Published: December 13, 2000</date><text>Willamette Industries has urged stockholders to reject a takeover offer of $48 a share, or $7.1 billion, from the Weyerhaeuser Company, a rival forest-products business, and hold out for a higher price. Weyerhaeuser took its proposal directly to shareholders after Willamette rejected the bid in November. The offer, which expires Jan. 4, was a 38 percent premium to Willamette's share price at the time. Shares of Willamette, based in Portland, Ore., fell 38 cents, to $48.63. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., fell 50 cents, to $45.75.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/30/business/markets-market-place-weyerhaeuser-begins-hostile-tender-offer-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">THE MARKETS: Market Place; Weyerhaeuser begins hostile tender offer for Willamette, and the opinions start rolling in.<date>Published: November 30, 2000</date><text>THE Weyerhaeuser Company began a hostile $5.3 billion tender offer for Willamette Industries yesterday, ratcheting up the pressure on Willamette to come to the negotiating table.The $48-a-share unsolicited bid is the first that Weyerhaeuser, the forest products giant, has ever made. But the move was not a surprise.Earlier this month, the company disclosed that it had made the same offer to Willamette's management. Soon thereafter, Willamette's board rejected the offer, which included the assumption of $1.7 billion in debt.The tender offer did not elicit much of a reaction from investors yesterday. On the New York Stock Exchange, Willamette's shares fell 63 cents, to $49.31. Weyerhaeuser rose $1, to $44.75.Willamette's stock rose sharply after Weyerhaeuser first disclosed its offer. At the time, the $48-a-share offer represented a 38 percent premium over Willamette's stock price.In a statement yesterday, Weyerhaeuser said its offer was good until Jan. 4. Willamette said its board would review the proposal. By law, it has up to 10 business days to respond.''Two weeks ago the board rejected our offer, but this is still a good offer for shareholders,'' Steven Rogel, Weyerhaeuser's chief executive, said in a telephone interview. ''We want the shareholders to have the opportunity to decide the future of their investment and not be shut out.''Mr. Rogel, who joined Weyerhaeuser in 1997 after a distinguished career at Willamette, has been trying to buy his former employer for the last two years.Two weeks ago, Wall Street analysts said the combination made a great deal of sense in an industry that is consolidating but needs even more of it. The only stumbling block, the analysts said, was the price.Yesterday, they said many of the same things.''It is a very strong combination, providing great strength in terms of business lines,'' said Anna Torma, a forest products analyst at Merrill Lynch.The hostile tender offer by Weyerhaeuser is an attempt ''to force the Willamette board to negotiate with them,'' Ms. Torma added. ''They are trying to do that through shareholder pressure.''Duane McDougall, Willamette's president and chief executive, said that while directors would consider the offer, further discussions with Weyerhaeuser were not really necessary.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/29/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-bid-for-willamette-seen-turning-hostile.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER BID FOR WILLAMETTE SEEN TURNING HOSTILE<date>Published: November 29, 2000</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, a forest products concern, is expected to begin a $5.4 billion hostile takeover offer today for Willamette Industries, executives close to the company said. The move comes two weeks after the board of Willamette, based in Portland, Ore., rejected a similar offer from Weyerhaeuser. According to the executives, Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., will make a tender offer for Willamette's 112.5 million shares, valuing each at $48. The company would also assume $1.7 billion in debt. Weyerhaeuser's offer of $48 a share -- no different from its rejected offer -- is below Willamette's current price, which rose $1 yesterday, to $49.75. It represented a 38 percent premium over Willamette's closing stock price on Nov. 10, the last trading day before the bid was disclosed. Andrew Ross Sorkin (NYT)</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/16/business/willamette-board-turns-down-takeover-bid-by-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Willamette Board Turns Down Takeover Bid by Weyerhaeuser<date>Published: November 16, 2000</date><text>Willamette Industries said yesterday that its board had unanimously rejected a $5.3 billion takeover offer from the Weyerhaeuser Company, the nation's third-largest forest products concern.Weyerhaeuser made its offer, which also included the assumption of $1.7 billion in debt, in a Nov. 6 letter from Steven R. Rogel, chairman, president and chief executive, to Duane C. McDougall, Willamette's chief executive. On Monday, Weyerhaeuser publicly disclosed that it had made the bid. The company also indicated that it might make an unsolicited tender offer for Willamette.In a letter sent yesterday to Mr. Rogel, William Swindells, Willamette's chairman, and Mr. McDougall said the Weyerhaeuser bid ''does not adequately reflect the value of Willamette's unique franchise, its businesses and prospects.''''In short,'' the letter continued, ''the board views your proposal as an opportunistic attempt to acquire one of the industry's leading franchises at a time when stock prices in the industry are depressed.''The $48-a-share offer represented a 38 percent premium over Willamette's closing stock price on Nov. 10.In a telephone interview, Mr. McDougall said Willamette ''will do what is necessary to fight,'' should a tender offer be made, but would ''carefully consider'' a fresh bid, should one be forthcoming.''Weyerhaeuser is being opportunistic,'' he said. ''They think they can pick up a premier asset at a dramatically undervalued price.''Wall Street analysts said on Monday that Weyerhaeuser would probably have to sweeten its bid.In a statement, Weyerhaeuxer said it was prepared to negotiate.''We urge Willamette and its board to commence discussions with Weyerhaeuser to reach an agreement that will permit Willamette shareholders to receive a substantial premium for their shares and otherwise serve the best interests of all Willamette constituencies,'' the statement said. ''If the Willamette board would only sit down to discuss this transaction, they will recognize that this combination will produce superior value.'' Both announcements came after the close of trading. Yesterday, Weyerhaeuser's stock rose $1, to $42.63. Willamette closed at $46.94, up 81 cents.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/14/business/weyerhaeuser-bids-for-willamette.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Bids for Willamette<date>Published: November 14, 2000</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company disclosed yesterday that it had made a $5.3 billion, $48-a-share cash offer to purchase Willamette Industries, setting the stage for a hostile takeover battle.Weyerhaeuser, the nation's third-largest forest products company, said it made its offer in a Nov. 6 letter from its chairman and chief executive, Steven R. Rogel, to Duane C. McDougall, Willamette's president and chief executive.Willamette's board met last week to consider the offer, but has not reached a decision.In a letter on Sunday to William Swindells, Willamette's chairman, Mr. Rogel said that as a result of the board's failure to act, ''We are forced to assume that we must consider other alternatives to consummate a transaction.''The offer that was disclosed yesterday is not the first time Weyerhaeuser has approached Willamette about a possible combination. The company said it held such discussions with Willamette two years ago.Willamette, based in Portland, Ore., said in a statement that its board continued to review the proposal, ''and will respond in due course.''''It is unfortunate that Weyerhaeuser chose to make its proposal public at this time,'' the statement added.With the industry in the throes of consolidation, Wall Street analysts said the combination made good sense.''This is a great fit,'' said Linda Lieberman, a senior managing director at Bear, Stearns. ''It gives Weyerhaeuser a nice add-on in most of the businesses they are in.''Investors reacted by sharply bidding up the price of Willamette's stock, which gained $11.06 a share, or 32 percent, closing at $45.81 on the New York Stock Exchange. Weyerhaeuser, whose shares have been slumping since December, closed at $41.69, down $1.19.Weyerhaeuser's offer represents a 38 percent premium over Friday's closing price of $34.75 for Willamette's shares. In addition to the cash offer, Weyerhaeuser would assume $1.7 billion in Willamette debt.Chip Dillon, a paper and forest products analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said the bid, while attractive, might need to be sweetened to be accepted by Willamette shareholders. But Mr. Dillon also said a competing bid from another forest products company was unlikely.</text></article></page><page index="8"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/02/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-will-close-four-packaging-plants.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER WILL CLOSE FOUR PACKAGING PLANTS<date>Published: March 02, 2000</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it planned to close four packaging plants as it consolidated operations after its January acquisition of MacMillan Bloedel Ltd. The plants -- in Cleveland; Houston; Jersey City; and Rock Island, Ill. -- have 400 employees. Weyerhaeuser said it would offer severance packages and job placement services to the workers. Weyerhaeuser, a timber and paper company based in Federal Way, Wash., has 45,000 workers. The closings are intended to cut excess corrugated box capacity from Weyerhaeuser's packaging plant system.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/24/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-buy-back-up-to-12-million-of-its-shares.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO BUY BACK UP TO 12 MILLION OF ITS SHARES<date>Published: February 24, 2000</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, a forest products concern, said yesterday that it would buy back up to 12 million shares. The buyback, which will take place over an unspecified time, represents about 5 percent of the company's stock outstanding. Companies use buybacks to increase earnings per share by reducing the shares outstanding. Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., had 1999 sales of $12.3 billion. Its stock was down $1.625 a share at $50 on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/28/business/weyerhaeuser-merger-plan-approved.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Merger Plan Approved<date>Published: December 28, 1999</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said today that its planned acquisition of TJ International Inc. had received federal antitrust approval.Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, said the waiting period required by the Federal Trade Commission under the Hart-Scott-Rodino Antitrust Improvements Act had expired. The company also said it planned to move forward early next year with its $720 million cash offer for all outstanding TJ International shares.TJ International, which is based in Boise, Idaho, owns 51 percent of the lumber-products company Trus Joist MacMillan Inc. A Weyerhaeuser unit owns the remaining 49 percent.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/27/realestate/on-a-ridge-in-a-city-near-seattle-housing-and-golf.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">On a Ridge in a City Near Seattle, Housing and Golf<date>Published: June 27, 1999</date><text>ONCE dependent on the logging industry, this blue-collar city in the Cascade Mountain foothills 30 miles east of Seattle is moving toward a higher-end image as the timberland owner begins developing a huge and expensive new housing complex.Crews are now grading large tracts on 1,343 acres that follow the hillsides and plateaus in the Weyerhaeuser Real Estate Company's Snoqualmie Ridge development, which will eventually have 2,000 housing units, a 100-acre industrial park and a 10-acre shopping center.The 160 ridge-top residences built so far command views of the town in the valley below, the nearby 4,124-foot Mount Si and a sea of mountain peaks to the east. About 250 units -- detached houses, town houses and two-family houses -- will go up this year, priced from $220,000 to more than $1 million for some along the Jack Nicklaus P.G.A. golf course, where initiation fees are $45,000 for residents and $55,000 for nonresidents. Both pay monthly dues of $300. Last month, the Optiva Corporation, which makes electric toothbrushes, opened the first industrial plant in the complex and is now in operation with 500 employees.City officials have fought to make sure that Snoqualmie Ridge will not be an exclusive enclave of perhaps 5,000 people closed to the city's 1,500 residents. ''We want to be one community, not two divided,'' says Mayor Randy Fletcher, who works 40 hours a week as a machinist and won his post a year-and-a-half ago by campaigning on a platform of controlled growth.The Mayor, who rides a Harley-Davidson, has at times knocked on the doors of new residents ''to welcome them to our town one household at a time.'' Ten years ago residents bitterly opposed the Weyerhaeuser project out of fears that urban sprawl and traffic would destroy the rural valley with its farms and horse pastures, as has happened to neighboring communities.But City Administrator Kim Wilde believes the success of the project will assure a better future for the 101-year-old Snoqualmie. The city estimates that in five years it will start receiving $3 million a year in revenues from the development. Just a few years ago the town was so poor that its wastewater treatment system was failing and, Mr. Wilde said, ''the streets were practically dirt.''</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/06/22/business/international-business-weyerhaeuser-agrees-buy-macmillan-bloedel-for-2.45.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Weyerhaeuser Agrees to Buy MacMillan Bloedel for $2.45 Billion<date>Published: June 22, 1999</date><text>Weyerhaeuser Inc. said today that it had agreed to acquire MacMillan Bloedel Ltd., one of the biggest forestry companies in western Canada, in a stock deal valued at $2.45 billion.The acquisition, if approved by shareholders and regulators, would solidify the position of Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Tacoma, Wash., as the world's largest producer of softwood lumber and pulp and strengthen its business in fiberboard and packaging.Weyerhaeuser's chairman, Steven R. Rogel, described the acquisition as ''an excellent strategic combination,'' which will increase annual sales by about 25 percent, to $13.3 billion. Weyerhaeuser has 35,000 employees in North America, with 5,900 of them in Canada. MacMillan Bloedel, based in Vancouver, British Columbia, employs 9,500 in Canada and the United States.Shareholders of MacMillan Bloedel will receive 0.28 of a share of Weyerhaeuser -- or the same amount of stock in a new Canadian subsidiary of Weyerhaeuser, permitting favorable tax treatment for Canadian shareholders. The boards of both companies have agreed to the acquisition.Weyerhaeuser shares fell 3.8 percent, or $2.625, to close at $67.125 on the New York Stock Exchange. MacMillan Bloedel shares surged 23 percent, or $3.3906, to close at $17.8281 on the Nasdaq Stock Market.Nick Majendie, a senior vice president at Canaccord Capital in Vancouver, said the acquisition by Weyerhauser was good for shareholders of MacMillan Bloedel because ''in the natural resource sector, bigger tends to be better.''But he warned that British Columbia's nationalistic New Democratic Party government, which controls the province's forest resources, could fight the takeover of MacMillan Bloedel, as it has done in the past.MacMillan Bloedel was once one of Canada's strongest forestry companies. But like others with core operations in British Columbia, it has been hurt in recent years by low commodity prices, forest policies adopted by the province's New Democratic Party government, lumber import restrictions by the United States and the economic crises of several Asian economies, which ordinarily are big buyers of North American wood products.MacMillan Bloedel underwent a huge restructuring in 1997, cutting its work force by 30 percent and selling certain fiberboard operations. It had been seeking a buyer for its packaging division, which led to the offer from Weyerhaeuser.The Canadian company lost $368 million (Canadian) in 1997 but earned $42 million (Canadian) last year.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/04/14/business/company-news-sierrapine-to-buy-weyerhaeuser-composite-board-unit.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; SIERRAPINE TO BUY WEYERHAEUSER COMPOSITE BOARD UNIT<date>Published: April 14, 1999</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company, the nation's third-largest forestry company, agreed yesterday to sell its composite-products business and a ply-veneer plant in Springfield, Ore., to Sierrapine Ltd. for an undisclosed price. It said the division was too small to be competitive. Weyerhaeuser said it would take a one-time first-quarter charge of $60 million, or 30 cents a share, for the sale. The unit, which produces and sells industrial-grade particleboard and medium-density fiberboard, employs 550 people and had about $116 million in 1998 sales. The closely held Sierrapine is based in Sacramento, Calif. Shares of Weyerhaeuser, based in Federal Way, Wash., rose $2.3125, to $64.4375, an all-time closing high, yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/31/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-may-sell-composite-product-operations.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER MAY SELL COMPOSITE PRODUCT OPERATIONS<date>Published: March 31, 1999</date><text>Executives of the Weyerhaeuser Company are considering the sale of composite product operations that generated $116 million in net sales last year. The decision will depend on a review of four Weyerhaeuser mills that produce particle board and medium-density fiberboard in Adel, Ga.; Moncure, N.C., and Springfield, Ore. The mills employ 550 people. Shares of Weyerhaeuser, which is predominantly a forest products company, fell $1.4375 cents yesterday, to $56, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/05/business/company-news-bowater-to-sell-ontario-paper-mill-to-weyerhaeuser.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; BOWATER TO SELL ONTARIO PAPER MILL TO WEYERHAEUSER<date>Published: August 05, 1998</date><text>The newsprint and paper manufacturer Bowater Inc. said yesterday that it had agreed to sell its Ontario fine paper mill and related assets to the Weyerhaeuser Company for about $520 million. Bowater, which is based in Greenville, S.C., acquired the mill last month when it bought the Canadian newsprint producer Avenor Inc. Bowater wants to focus on its core businesses of newsprint and coated papers, a spokeswoman said. The mill, which is in Dryden, Ontario, has an annual capacity of 380,000 tons of white paper, used to make envelopes and copying paper. Bowater's stock fell $2.8125 yesterday, to $41.875, on the New York Stock Exchange, where Weyerhaeuser's shares fell 56.25 cents, to $41.4375.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/09/business/weyerhaeuser-sells-30-stake-in-pacific-paper.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">WEYERHAEUSER SELLS 30% STAKE IN PACIFIC PAPER<date>Published: July 09, 1997</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would sell 30 percent of a newsprint joint venture with Nippon Paper Industries to the Japanese company, giving the two 50 percent each. Weyerhaeuser now owns 80 percent of venture, the Pacific Paper Corporation, and Nippon Paper owns the other 20 percent. Pacific makes newsprint for sale in the United States and Japan. Terms were not disclosed. Pacific Paper generated $451 million in sales in 1996. Weyerhaeuser, of Tacoma, Wash., had total sales of $11.1 billion in 1996. Nippon Paper reported sales of 714 billion yen ($6.32 billion). Shares of Weyerhaeuser rose $3.5625, to $56.50.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/03/business/weyerhaeuser-buys-wood-products-unit-in-new-zealand.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">WEYERHAEUSER BUYS WOOD PRODUCTS UNIT IN NEW ZEALAND<date>Published: July 03, 1997</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it had bought a unit of Fletcher Challenge Ltd. of New Zealand for $190 million. The Fletcher unit, Tasman Forestry (Nelson) Ltd., owned 51 percent of an existing joint venture that holds 193,000 acres of lumber on the northern end of the South Island. Weyerhaeuser, now the 51 percent partner in the joint venture, is responsible for management and marketing. The remaining interest is still held by RII New Zealand Forests I, a unit of Union Bank of Switzerland. Weyerhaeuser is a forest products company based in Tacoma, Wash.</text></article></page><page index="9"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/06/19/business/weyerhaeuser-to-close-plant-in-north-carolina.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">WEYERHAEUSER TO CLOSE PLANT IN NORTH CAROLINA<date>Published: June 19, 1997</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it planned to close a plywood plant in Plymouth, N.C., resulting in the loss of 200 jobs, and take a second-quarter charge to pay for the move. Weyerhaeuser, based in Tacoma, Wash., did not specify the amount of the charge but said it would be offset by a gain from the sale of the company's mortgage company unit. Weyerhaeuser is closing the plant because it would cost too much to upgrade it, said Bruce Amundson, a company spokesman. Weyerhaeuser makes wood and packaging products. Its shares rose $1.25 yesterday, to $53.75.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/02/25/business/weyerhaeuser-plans-to-shut-some-recycling-plants.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">WEYERHAEUSER PLANS TO SHUT SOME RECYCLING PLANTS<date>Published: February 25, 1997</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would close or dispose of some of its recycling plants and sell a nursery business to sharpen its focus on its core paper and forest products business. The company, a paper and pulp maker, said it would take an after-tax charge of about $25 million, or 12 cents a share, in the first quarter for one-time costs related to the moves. Weyerhaeuser, based in Tacoma, Wash., said it would close or dispose of recycling facilities and related assets in Longview, Wash., and would sell Shemin Nurseries, a wholesale nursery business based in Danbury, Conn. Shares of Weyerhaeuser rose $1.125 yesterday, to $47.375.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/01/23/business/weyerhaeuser-co-wyn.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">WEYERHAEUSER CO. (WY,N)<date>Published: January 23, 1997</date><text>Lower paper prices caused the Weyerhaeuser Company's profits to fall by more than 50 percent in the fourth quarter of 1996 and for all of last year, the company reported yesterday.For the fourth quarter, Weyerhaeuser, the forest products company based in Federal Way, Wash., reported net earnings of $98 million, or 50 cents a share, on sales of $2.8 billion, down from profits of $251 million, or $1.25 a share, on sales of $3.1 billion a year earlier. Analysts had expected earnings of 47 cents a share in the most recent quarter, according to a survey by First Call. The company's stock fell $1.125 yesterday, to $49.125.For the year, the company reported net profits of $463 million, or $2.34 a share, on $11.1 billion in sales, down from $799 million, or $3.93 a share, in net earnings on $11.8 billion in sales for 1995.The 1995 earnings were $983 million, or $4.83 a share, before a special charge of $184 million because of accounting changes and other one-time costs.In the pulp, paper and packaging products sector, operating earnings plummeted from $1.2 billion in 1995 to $307 million last year and from $304 million to $31 million in the fourth quarter.Earnings from wood products and lumber amounted to $805 million for the year and $226 million for the fourth quarter, compared with $808 million and $183 million, respectively, in the previous year.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/24/business/timber-company-weighs-possible-sale-of-unit.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">TIMBER COMPANY WEIGHS POSSIBLE SALE OF UNIT<date>Published: September 24, 1996</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday it had retained Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company to explore its options for the Weyerhaeuser Mortgage Company, including a possible sale. Weyerhaeuser Mortgage, based in Woodland Hills, Calif., has 1,500 employees in 58 offices in 15 states. Weyerhaeuser did not comment on the timing of the move or a potential sales price. Weyerhaeuser Mortgage originated $2.1 billion in residential first mortgages in the eight months ended Aug. 31, when it was servicing $4 billion in mortgages. Weyerhaeuser is a large forest products company.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/24/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-selling-mills-and-forests-in-oregon.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS;WEYERHAEUSER SELLING MILLS AND FORESTS IN OREGON<date>Published: July 24, 1996</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company agreed yesterday to sell some mills and 600,000 acres of Eastern Oregon forest land to U.S. Timberlands for $309 million. The sale includes hardboard, particleboard and plywood manufacturing plants at Klamath Falls, Ore., and nursery and seed orchard facilities. U.S. Timberlands said it would sell the manufacturing plants to Collins Products and concentrate on managing the timberland. Weyerhaeuser employs 700 people in Klamath Falls. An earlier deal to sell the holdings to the Roseburg Forest Products Company collapsed early this year. The deal is the first for U.S. Timberlands, a limited partnership based in Bandon, Ore., and New York City.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/17/business/company-reports-weyerhaeuser-co-wyn.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY REPORTS;WEYERHAEUSER CO. (WY,N)<date>Published: April 17, 1996</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company reported yesterday that its first-quarter earnings fell 31.3 percent from the corresponding period a year ago, reflecting rapidly declining prices for the company's pulp, paper and packaging products as well as lower prices for its wood products.The company said net income fell to about $142 million, or 72 cents a share, from $206.6 million, or $1 a share, a year earlier. The results fell 2 cents short of the average estimate of 74 cents from 10 analysts polled by IBES International Inc.Sales declined 3 percent, to $2.61 billion.Still, Weyerhaeuser shares rose $1.625 yesterday, to $48.875, as the company reported signs that demand for its pulp and paper shipments could be improving. Sherman Chao, an analyst for Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, and Matthew Berler, an analyst at Morgan Stanley, both raised their ratings on Weyerhaeuser stock because they expected a stronger economy to fuel demand for paper and pulp.Operating profit at the company's pulp, paper and packaging business fell 22 percent, to $162 million. The price of pulp, the processed wood fiber used to make paper, has fallen 48 percent, to $520 a metric ton, from $1,000 in the third quarter.Operating profit from timberlands and wood products fell 36 percent, to $162 million.Second-quarter paper, pulp and packaging earnings are expected to fall further from the first-quarter level on lower average prices and curtailed production, said John W. Creighton Jr., the president and chief executive. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/04/02/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-drops-price-of-leading-grade-of-pulp.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS;WEYERHAEUSER DROPS PRICE OF LEADING GRADE OF PULP<date>Published: April 02, 1996</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company of Tacoma, Wash., cut the price of its benchmark grade of pulp by 13 percent yesterday, reflecting weaker demand for the processed wood fiber used to make paper. Weyerhaeuser, the world's largest pulp producer, cut the price for northern bleached softwood kraft market pulp to $520 a metric ton, from $600 in March, said Chip Dillon, a forest products analyst at Salomon Brothers Inc. That means the price of pulp has dropped 48 percent from a high of $1,000 a metric ton, reached in the third quarter of last year.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/09/business/pulp-mills-turn-over-a-new-leaf-some-companies-see-green-as-just-good-business.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Pulp Mills Turn Over a New Leaf;Some Companies See Green as Just Good Business<date>Published: March 09, 1996</date><text>OGLETHORPE, Ga.Twenty years ago, the typical American paper mill spewed 40 million gallons of contaminated water a day into a nearby river or stream and belched fumes that stank like rotten eggs and corroded the metal of cars for miles around.Today, the Weyerhaeuser Company's mill in this Georgia town releases just 11 million gallons of much cleaner effluent a day into the Flint River and emits a faint and not unpleasant scent resembling turpentine. And many other paper producers, responding to tougher environmental laws and the threat of litigation, are following the same pristine path.For environmentalists, there is even better news on the horizon: The day is coming, Weyerhaeuser and some other big paper companies say, when their water discharges will approach zero, all but eliminating pollution and saving huge amounts of fresh water. As an added environmental benefit, some companies are even talking about extracting beneficial tree chemicals like calcium from recycled water and returning them to the forest floor to enrich the soil.The result of all this is an important if little heralded environmental success story: the transformation of a manufacturing process that was once a blight on the nation's water and air into a benign backdrop to the ecological landscape."Twenty five years ago the rivers ran black and fish kills were a common event," said John Ruston, a paper industry specialist at the Environmental Defense Fund. Now, he said, most mills have ended most pollution that can be seen or smelled and have cut unseen but environmentally damaging waste by 80 to 90 percent.Regulations were the goad at first, but more recently some companies have made environmental performance a competitive tool. "The best companies have found a way to integrate the environment in their investment decision making," Mr. Ruston said. "They have found ways to use less water, less energy and still increase production, which is a competitive advantage."To be sure, some environmentalists will never be happy so long as paper companies cut down trees. But many of the nation's 537 mills are heading in a direction once considered unthinkable: creating a system that eliminates the discharge of water altogether. They call this goal "closing the loop."The first target of the mills is the bleaching process, the source of roughly half their pollution. Other, mostly innocuous stages of the manufacturing process would continue to take water from streams and rivers and dump it back in.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/29/business/company-news-hanson-to-sell-some-forests-and-sawmills.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS;HANSON TO SELL SOME FORESTS AND SAWMILLS<date>Published: February 29, 1996</date><text>Hanson P.L.C., the British-American industrial conglomerate, said yesterday that it would sell forests and sawmills in the American South to the Weyerhaeuser Company for $500 million. Hanson said its Cavenham Forest Industries subsidiary would sell 661,200 acres of timberland in Louisiana and Mississippi, as well as four sawmills, to Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Tacoma, Wash. This is the first announced disposal since Hanson said in December that it would sell all of Cavenham's timber and sawmill operations in the United States. (AP)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/02/14/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-calls-off-deal-with-roseburg.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS;WEYERHAEUSER CALLS OFF DEAL WITH ROSEBURG<date>Published: February 14, 1996</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company terminated its agreement to sell its Klamath Falls, Ore., holdings to the Roseburg Forest Products Company, Weyerhaeuser said yesterday. The proposed sale would have included more than 600,000 acres of predominantly pine forest, nursery and seed-orchard facilities and three manufacturing plants. Weyerhaeuser, of Tacoma Wash., said in November that it intended to sell those holdings to Roseburg for $303 million plus the value of its working capital. Weyerhaeuser said yesterday that it was "not able to reach final agreement with Roseburg on certain aspects of the transaction," and added that it was having talkswith a parties interested in its Klamath Falls holdings.</text></article></page><page index="10"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/11/29/business/company-news-roseburg-forest-products-in-303-million-deal.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS;ROSEBURG FOREST PRODUCTS IN $303 MILLION DEAL<date>Published: November 29, 1995</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it had agreed to sell three manufacturing plants, 600,000 acres of timberland and other assets to the Roseburg Forest Products Company for $303 million. Weyerhaeuser, based in Tacoma, Wash., agreed to sell plants near Klamath Falls, Ore., that make hardboard, particleboard and plywood. The forest land, also in southern Oregon, contains mostly pine. Nurseries and seed orchards are to be included in the sale. John Creighton Jr., the president of Weyerhaeuser, said the company would concentrate on its Douglas fir growing operations in Oregon and Washington. Roseburg Forest Products, a subsidiary of RLC Industries, is based in Roseburg, Ore.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/07/business/weyerhaeuser-unit-deal.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Weyerhaeuser Unit Deal<date>Published: September 07, 1995</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said today that its Northwest Hardwoods division had agreed to acquire Diamond Wood Products, a privately owned hardwood lumber company with operations in Oregon. Terms were not disclosed. Weyerhaeuser, based in Tacoma, said the assets it would buy included a hardwood sawmill and about 9,000 acres of timberland in Oregon. Diamond Wood employs about 300 people.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/08/17/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-to-take-third-quarter-charge.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER TO TAKE THIRD-QUARTER CHARGE<date>Published: August 17, 1995</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it would take a third-quarter charge of $184 million, or 90 cents a share, as it accelerates plans to sell its less profitable real estate assets. The charge is a result of the revaluation of some real estate assets, $600 million of which the company said it planned to sell in the next 12 months. Weyerhaeuser said it had changed the timetable for selling the assets, which consist mostly of undeveloped land, because of a new accounting rule for publicly traded companies that requires a larger asset write-down than in the past. The company, based in Federal Way, Wash., is best known for its timber and paper businesses. Shares of Weyerhaeuser gained 75 cents, to $46.125, on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/21/business/tall-timber-and-the-epa.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Tall Timber And the E.P.A.<date>Published: May 21, 1995</date><text>YOU are a multibillion-dollar corporation and Federal regulators are sniffing suspiciously at your factories, building a case that your industry has broadly violated the country's environmental laws.What to do?Your lawyers' guesses about which side might prevail if the case ends up in court are just that -- guesses. You could pre-empt the Feds by volunteering to install pollution gear, but that might cost tens of millions of dollars and raise the price of your product.And what happens if one of your competitors plays hardball with regulators, or goes to Congress for a legislative fix, and doesn't have to put on the expensive control equipment? No company wants to be tarred in the press as an environmental villain. But there are also dangers in capitulating too easily, and becoming known as a pushover for any Federal regulator looking for a patsy.Three of the nation's largest wood products companies found themselves pondering this Rubik's cube of uncertainties and risks in the early 1990's, when the Environmental Protection Agency began a nationwide investigation of the industry. Although they make similar products at comparable factories, they chose very different courses, and the outcome remains much in doubt.The Weyerhaeuser Company, of Tacoma, Wash., took the most conciliatory approach, agreeing to put tens of millions of dollars of controls on its plants before the E.P.A. brought its case. It paid more than $1.5 million in fines to state authorities, but is still arguing with Federal officials over whether it should pay further penalties. The company does not disagree with the E.P.A. estimate of how much pollution its wood products plants give off.The Louisiana-Pacific Corporation, based in Portland, Ore., paid an $11 million Federal fine and pledged to install more than $70 million in pollution-control equipment a few months after the E.P.A. served notice of possible Clean Air Act violations.The Georgia-Pacific Corporation of Atlanta has been the most pugnacious. It disputes the scientific and legal foundations of the Government's case, says the E.P.A. estimates of its pollution are overstated and has argued that the agency is unfairly applying present-day standards to decisions made 10 to 15 years ago. Last November, the company fired off a blistering, 243-page response to the E.P.A. that dismissed the agency's allegations as "difficult to fathom" and "extraordinarily stale."</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/21/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-raises-dividend-and-plans-buyback.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER RAISES DIVIDEND AND PLANS BUYBACK<date>Published: April 21, 1995</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it had raised its second-quarter dividend by 33 percent and planned to buy back up to 5 percent of its outstanding stock. Shares of Weyerhaeuser rose 12.5 cents, to $39, on the New York Stock Exchange. The buyback plan calls for 10 million shares to be repurchased within a year. Based on the closing price yesterday, the repurchase would be valued at about $390 million. The dividend will rise to 40 cents a share from 30 cents, a payout that had been in effect since 1988. Weyerhaeuser is a supplier of paper, pulp and other forest products based in Tacoma, Wash.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/14/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-searching-for-joint-venture-partner.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER SEARCHING FOR JOINT-VENTURE PARTNER<date>Published: April 14, 1995</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that it was looking for a partner for investments in timberlands and related assets around the world that could be worth $1.5 billion. The forest-products company, based in Tacoma, Wash., said it would own 50 percent of the venture, contributing $260 million worth of its United States timberlands property, as well as an undisclosed amount of cash. Its partner would provide cash contributions of equal value.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/12/business/company-reports-2-paper-companies-profits-get-cool-investor-response.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY REPORTS; 2 Paper Companies' Profits Get Cool Investor Response<date>Published: April 12, 1995</date><text>Strong earnings from the International Paper Company and the Weyerhaeuser Company received a cool response yesterday from investors worried that the good times will soon be over.On the New York Stock Exchange, shares of International Paper fell 37.5 cents, to $75.75, and shares of Weyerhaeuser fell 25 cents, to $39.75. The strong earnings may be making investors nervous that the industry's three-quarter-old surge is ending, said Kathryn McAuley, a forest products analyst at Brown Brothers Harriman. "I get the sense that some portfolio managers are looking for the door," she said.For five years, paper industry earnings fell or were unchanged as manufacturing capacity exceeded demand for paper products. Last year's third-quarter earnings started to benefit from higher paper prices as demand outstripped manufacturing capacity.Wood products represent the only weak link in forest products companies' earnings so far, analysts said.International Paper said yesterday that it earned $246 million, or $1.95 a share, in the first quarter, compared with $1 million, or 1 cent a share, in the comparable quarter a year earlier, when the company took a charge of $75 million for an accounting change. Without the charge, the earnings a year earlier would have been $76 million, or 61 cents a share. For the most recent quarter, which ended on March 31, revenues rose 32 percent, to $4.49 billion from $3.41 billion.The earnings surpassed Wall Street expectations of $1.77 a share, according to a survey of analysts by Zacks Investment Research."I believe we're in the beginning stages of what should be a sustained period of favorable markets worldwide," said John A. Georges, the chairman and chief executive of International Paper, which is based in Purchase, N.Y.Continued growth in economies around the world and limited additions to manufacturing capacity should add up to "a very optimistic view of the supply-and-demand balance this industry should experience for several years to come," he said.Weyerhaeuser, based in Tacoma, Wash., reported first-quarter earnings of $1 a share yesterday, matching Wall Street's expectations.Revenue rose 15 percent, to $2.75 billion from $2.39 billion."The results clearly show the strength of the balance of our business portfolio," said the company's president, John Creighton Jr. "We are confident that a record quarter will be followed by a record year."The company's operating profit from pulp, paper and packaging division jumped to $210 million, from $5 million a year earlier, as prices continued to rise.Operating profit from Weyerhaeuser's timberlands and wood products business fell 16 percent, to $239 million from $283 million, amid lower domestic wood prices. "Overall performance remains strong due to continued strength in export markets," the company said.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/11/05/business/company-news-weyerhaeuser-studies-the-elimination-of-some-jobs.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY NEWS; WEYERHAEUSER STUDIES THE ELIMINATION OF SOME JOBS<date>Published: November 05, 1994</date><text>The forest products company Weyerhaeuser Company may eliminate some jobs as part of its effort to improve operating earnings by $400 million in the next three years, a spokeswoman, Peggy O'Farrell, said yesterday. But she said no head-count targets had been set and job reductions were not expected to be a major area of focus as the company works on cutting costs and achieving new operating efficiencies. She said details of the new program will be worked out by the company's various business units over the next five months.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/10/13/business/company-reports-weyerhaeuser-co-wyn.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">COMPANY REPORTS; WEYERHAEUSER CO. (WY,N)<date>Published: October 13, 1994</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said yesterday that its third-quarter earnings rose 67 percent as pulp, paper and packaging markets recovered and strong sales continued in its wood-products business."The company continues to realize steady improvement in earnings as the momentum in the recovering pulp, paper and packaging markets continues," said John W. Creighton Jr., president of Weyerhaeuser. "At the same time, our timberlands and wood-products performance remains strong in spite of increasing interest rates."Weyerhaeuser, which is based in Tacoma, Wash., and is the nation's third-largest forest products company, reported net income of $144.4 million, or 71 cents a share, for the quarter ended Sept. 25, compared with income from operations of $86.5 million, or 42 cents, a year earlier. The earnings fell below Wall Street's expectations of 77 cents a share.In last year's third quarter, the company took a charge of $19.9 million, or 10 cents a share, related to tax changes, reducing net income to $66.6 million, or 32 cents.Sales in its most recent quarter rose 20 percent, to $2.7 billion. (Bloomberg Business News)</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/13/business/pension-fund-repayment.html?ref=weyerhaeusercompany">Pension Fund Repayment<date>Published: August 13, 1994</date><text>The Weyerhaeuser Company said that it had made a $4.9 million payment to its pension fund to restore losses from a $22 million investment that went sour in 1990.The payment was made under an agreement with the Labor Department, which had been investigating the pension fund's loss on a 1987 investment in hedged options, a company spokeswoman, Peggy O'Farrell, said on Thursday.Weyerhaeuser, based in Seattle, has also injected about $17.2 million into the fund over the last four years to make up the loss, she added.She said Weyerhaeuser's $1.3 billion pension fund was among 1,000 investors that lost money in the collapse of the options hedging fund controlled by James Donahue..</text></article></page></root>
