<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root company="Williams Companies"><page index="1"><article index="1" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/10/18/williams-calls-off-i-p-o-of-exploration-unit/?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Calls Off I.P.O. of Exploration Unit<date>October 18, 2011, 7:04 pm</date><text>The Williams Companies said late on Tuesday that it planned to spin off its exploration and production business by the end of the year instead of selling the unit in an initial public offering. Williams cited turmoil in the markets as the primary reason for calling off the I.P.O., which the energy company had announced in February. A tax-free spinoff of the unit, WPX Energy, would be much quicker to execute than an offering. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The press release “The continued instability and weakness in equity markets, especially for new issuances, makes the I.P.O. of WPX Energy appear unattractive in the near term,” Alan Armstrong, Williams’ chief executive, said in a statement. The company could still resume the I.P.O. process if market conditions improve. Either way, Williams is still determined to shed the exploration and production business to focus on its pipeline operations. Players in the so-called midstream sector, which focus on transporting oil and gas from drilling fields to refineries and customers, have become increasingly popular as demand for natural gas continues to rise. Earlier this week, Kinder Morgan agreed to buy the El Paso Corporation for $21.1 billion to create the biggest pipeline operator in the nation. Williams itself had bid against Energy Transfer Equity for control of the Southern Union Company, another pipeline company. But Williams appears to have lost, after Energy Transfer bid $5.7 billion for Southern Union in July.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/07/15/southern-union-to-talk-deal-with-williams/?ref=williamscompanies">Southern Union in Talks With Williams<date>July 15, 2011, 7:15 am</date><text>Panhandle Energy, via Associated Press; Energy Transfer Partners; Williams Companies, via Bloomberg NewsSouthern Union, the Houston-based natural gas pipeline company, has received takeover offers from Energy Transfer Equity and Williams Companies. Southern Union‘s mating dance continues. The natural gas pipeline operator on Friday disclosed that it would enter into negotiations with Williams, which just upped its bid for Southern Union to $44 a share in cash. The $5.5 billion bid trumps a previous — and also revised — offer by Energy Transfer Equity. In its latest move, Energy Transfer offered $5.1 billion in cash and stock. Both deals contain “hell or high water” provisions, showing that the companies will take all the necessary steps to get approval from regulators. “We are more convinced than ever of the strategic and financial benefits of Williams’ acquisition of Southern Union,” Alan S. Armstrong, the chief executive of Williams, said in a statement on Thursday announcing the deal. “Williams is offering Southern Union a clear, direct path to the highest value for its shareholders.” With its disclosure, Southern Union’s board has indicated that it is willing to talk to Williams. Failing to do so, the company said, “would be reasonably likely to constitute a breach by the board of its fiduciary duties.” Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The S.E.C. filing</text></article><article index="3" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/07/14/williams-raises-southern-union-bid-to-5-5-billion/?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Raises Its Bid for Southern Union to $5.5 Billion<date>July 14, 2011, 9:00 am</date><text>Panhandle Energy, via Associated Press; Energy Transfer Partners; Williams Companies, via Bloomberg NewsSouthern Union, the natural gas pipeline company, has received takeover offers from Energy Transfer Equity and the Williams Companies. The Williams Companies on Thursday raised its offer for the Southern Union Company to $5.5 billion, extending a bidding war for the pipeline operator by topping a revised $5.1 billion bid from Energy Transfer Equity. Under the terms of its new offer, Williams would pay $44 a share in cash for Southern Union, above both its original $39 offer and the $40 cash-and-stock revised bid that Energy Transfer disclosed last week. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The Williams press release Natural Gas Bidding War Puts Spotlight on a Billionaire Williams has also added a “hell or high water” clause that would commit the company to taking all necessary steps to obtain regulatory approval, a provision that Energy Transfer had added to its own proposal. The clause is meant to assuage concern that a deal with Williams could lead to antitrust concerns in states like Florida. The latest offer by Williams intensifies the struggle over Southern Union, a competition based on the belief that demand for natural gas will continue to rise. “We are more convinced than ever of the strategic and financial benefits of Williams’ acquisition of Southern Union,” Alan S. Armstrong, the chief executive of Williams, said in a statement. “Williams is offering Southern Union a clear, direct path to the highest value for its shareholders.” In a letter to a special committee of Southern Union’s board, Mr. Armstrong proposed a tight schedule for a deal with his company, one that would conclude with a firm merger agreement by next Tuesday. But despite its higher price, it is unclear whether Williams will win over several important Southern Union constituents. Some of Southern Union’s shareholders, including the company founder and chairman, George Lindemann, had already agreed to Energy Transfer’s raised bid and would roll over their equity into the acquirer. To support that deal, Mr. Lindemann and his chief lieutenant, Eric D. Herschmann, had agreed to forgo lucrative consulting contracts that had drawn criticism. Williams said that its offer was not contingent on financing, and that it would deliver financing commitment letters if Southern Union agreed to hold merger talks. It is being advised by Barclays Capital, Citigroup and the law firms Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore and Gibson, Dunn &amp; Crutcher.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/07/business/too-many-classes-of-zynga-stock-reuters-breakingviews.html?ref=williamscompanies">Too Many Classes of Zynga Stock - Reuters Breakingviews<date>Published: July 6, 2011</date><text>It’s bad enough for shareholders when companies have two classes of shares. Zynga, the social gaming company, will have three, with Mark Pincus, the founder, in a class of his own. This innovation shouldn’t be copied.New investors can buy class A Zynga shares that come with one vote each. The company’s initial public offering prospectus does not say how many votes will be allotted to B shares held by employees and other early backers or to C shares owned by Mr. Pincus. Zynga concedes this will concentrate insider control. And significantly, when B class shares are sold, they surrender their multiple voting rights, meaning Mr. Pincus could wind up with a bigger stake over time. Companies tend to suffer more than they benefit from dual classes of stock. One study found they traded at lower multiples than their single share-class rivals, and that eliminating multiple voting rights typically unlocked value of at least 5 percent. The News Corporation, Google and other companies already labor under such regimes. Minority stakeholders in Magna International, a maker of auto parts, paid its chairman a dear $1 billion to unshackle the dual-share structure last year. And investors have several more reasons to fear unequal voting rights. Controlling executives may turn down takeover bids because they enjoy the power and perks of their positions. Managers also are less likely to step down when doing poorly. Finally, executive salaries at dual-class firms tend to be higher and the framework can encourage self-dealing. There may already be small hints of those concerns at Zynga. For instance, the firm is paying Mr. Pincus’s sister, a professor who has worked on poverty issues, $5,000 a month to act as the director of its affiliated nonprofit. And it paid $400,000 to Mr. Pincus for office space he owns. These issues may have benign explanations and seem remote to potential Zynga investors eager to get their hands on the hottest new tech stock. They are also presumably keen to keep Mr. Pincus happy, given his role creating a potential $20 billion powerhouse. But they should be fully aware of just how big the price could be. Walk Away, Williams Investors don’t expect Williams Companies to give up the chase for rival Southern Union. But trumping the latest $5 billion offer by Energy Transfer Equity will destroy value for its own shareholders. With Southern Union starting to seem an expensive catch, Williams may be better off letting its rival overpay. Southern Union shareholders can thank Williams. Its $4.86 billion cash bid last month broke up a cozy arrangement with Energy Transfer that lavished goodies on Southern Union executives while short-changing other investors. Still, Williams now faces a tough choice. Energy Transfer’s sweetened bid for Southern already looks like a full price. At nine times next year’s earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization, it is in line with similar deals over the last decade, according to Barclays Capital. Moreover, to clinch a deal, Williams faces added hurdles. Southern Union’s stock price suggests investors expect a bid of $42 a share. On top of that, Energy Transfer’s latest deal with management doubled the initial breakup fee to $212.5 million, or an extra cost to Williams of around $1.70 per Southern Union share. Add these fees to the pipeline company’s existing debt, and a $42-a-share offer would cost Williams around $9.4 billion. Based on Southern Union’s forecast operating profit, that would bring the deal’s post-tax return on investment to below 5.5 percent. That’s lower than Williams’s 7 percent weighted average cost of capital. And this calculation is generous, because it assumes Williams can achieve $100 million in cost cuts and revenue gains that Energy Transfer has promised. The Williams spoiler bid estimated only around $50 million of such synergies. Furthermore, there’s no certainty a bid of $42 a share would work. Winning over Southern Union’s top managers, who own about 14 percent of the company, might be even harder. Williams’s all-cash offer would leave them paying capital gains taxes. To clinch its prey without issuing equity might require Williams to pay as much as $45 a share. Williams’s chief executive, Alan S. Armstrong, has already done enough for Southern Union shareholders by forcing a rival to scramble to pay 20 percent more for assets it coveted. He can best serve his own investors by walking away from a costly bidding war. It’s bad enough for shareholders when companies have two classes of shares. Zynga, the social gaming company, will have three, with Mark Pincus, the founder, in a class of his own. This innovation shouldn’t be copied.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/07/05/energy-transfer-says-it-is-more-aggressive-in-pursuit-of-southern-union/?ref=williamscompanies">Energy Transfer Says It Is 'More Aggressive' in Pursuit of Southern Union<date>July 5, 2011, 12:58 pm</date><text>For years, Energy Transfer Equity refused to issue new stock, so firmly convinced in that plan that it even walked away from potential deals in the past. But the Williams Companies‘ $39-a-share rival bid for Southern Union forced the company to step up. And so on Tuesday, Energy Transfer announced a new $40-a-share bid that includes both cash and equity that is both higher and simpler. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Energy Transfer Raises Southern Union Bid “We’ve been more aggressive here than we have been than probably in my whole career,” Kelcy Warren, Energy Transfer’s chairman, said in a conference call with analysts on Tuesday morning. Mr. Warren admitted that Energy Transfer’s original bid — $31 a share, entirely in newly issued Class B units that would eventually convert into cash or the company’s stock — needed rethinking in light of the far higher Williams bid. Beyond the higher price, it was also more palatable to some Southern Union institutional shareholders that could not own the partnership units that Energy Transfer was offering. The current offer, Mr. Warren and Energy Transfer’s management argued, gave shareholders a choice. About 14 percent of Southern Union’s shareholders — which likely include the company’s founder and chairman, the billionaire George L. Lindemann — have agreed to take the equity. The battle over Southern Union has put a spotlight on Energy Transfer, a major operator of natural gas pipelines that struck the deal to take advantage of a growing demand for oil alternatives. Mr. Warren argued repeatedly on the call that the equity component of the Southern Union bid promises that company’s shareholders more benefits than are immediately apparent. Putting Energy Transfer and Southern Union together would create a big pipeline operator with more than 44,000 miles of pipelines and about 30.7 billion cubic feet of natural gas capacity. Energy Transfer also reported a 15.9 percent operating margin last year, one of the highest among pipeline operators. “I don’t think this is a $40 offer,” Mr. Warren said. “I think this is substantially more than $40.” Energy Transfer executives said that they expected no antitrust problems, whereas Williams might receive tougher scrutiny in states like Florida where it and Southern Union both have significant presences. Energy Transfer also emphasized the committed financing it has obtained, whereas Williams has thus far relied on “highly confident” letters from its financial advisers. A Williams spokesman declined to comment. But Energy Transfer’s bid may not be the last shot fired in this battle. Southern Union shares traded at $41.50 as of early Tuesday afternoon, suggesting that yet another higher bid is in the making. Shares in Energy Transfer rose slightly, to $44.98, while those in Williams dipped a little, to $30.66.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/29/the-battle-over-southern-union-another-round/?ref=williamscompanies">The Battle Over Southern Union, Another Round<date>June 29, 2011, 7:08 am</date><text>Daniel Acker/Bloomberg NewsA Conquest Drilling Company rig at work just outside Gillette, Wyo., in 2001. The Interior Dept. announced this year that 7,400 acres in Wyoming’s Powder River Basin will be leased to mining companies. The bidding war for Southern Union has turned into a battle of lawyers. After the natural gas pipeline operator agreed to talk with the Williams Companies about a takeover, lawyers for the rival bidder Energy Transfer Equity responded with a sharply worded letter. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The S.E.C. filing The Spotlight On Southern Union's Chief Energy Transfer, through its lawyers at Latham &amp; Watkins, reiterated the company’s stance that Southern Union “is not permitted” to “engage in any discussions or negotiations with Williams” or “furnish Williams any nonpublic information,” according to a regulatory filing. Doing so, the firm wrote, would “constitute a willful and intentional breach of the merger agreement.” The next day the legal counsel for Southern Union, Locke Lord Bissell &amp; Liddell, fired off a succinct note, acknowledging that it had received the letter and stating its contrary opinion. “We respectfully disagree with your position,” the letter said. “The company has exercised great care, and will continue to exercise great care, to comply fully with the terms of the merger agreement.” Energy Transfer and Williams have been playing tug of war over Southern Union. A couple of weeks ago, Energy Transfer offered $4.2 billion for Southern Union in a complicated all-stock deal worth $33 a share. Williams emerged a few days later, bidding $4.9 billion in cash, or roughly $39 a share. Investors are betting the bidding war has just begun. On Tuesday, shares of Southern Union closed at $40.15, roughly 3 percent higher than the offer from Williams.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/28/natural-gas-bidding-war-puts-spotlight-on-a-billionaire/?ref=williamscompanies">Natural Gas Bidding War Puts Spotlight on a Billionaire<date>June 28, 2011, 8:58 pm</date><text>Southern UnionGeorge L. Lindemann, Southern Union’s chief executive, who has quietly amassed a fortune in various businesses over decades. A multibillion-dollar takeover battle broke out last week over a Houston company that owns 20,000 miles of natural gas pipelines running from the southeastern tip of Florida to the Oklahoma Panhandle. The man at the center of the fight is a New York billionaire who runs the energy business from offices on the top floor of the General Motors Building on Fifth Avenue overlooking Central Park. George L. Lindemann has quietly amassed a fortune over a five-decade career of buying and selling disparate businesses, like contact lenses and cellphone licenses. Now, the 74-year-old investor has been thrust into the middle of a tug-of-war over Southern Union, the natural gas company he has controlled since 1990. “Unlike the high-profile hedge fund and private equity guys, he’s more of a throwback, an old-school, publicity-averse deal maker,” said Peter Newcomb, a former longtime editor of the Forbes 400, the annual list of the wealthiest Americans, on which Mr. Lindemann routinely appears. “Despite his extraordinary success he tends to fly beneath the radar.” That has been, in part, because operating a pipeline has historically been a sleepy affair. But in recent years natural gas has experienced a boom as new exploration fields have been discovered in places like the Eagle Ford Shale in Texas and the Haynesville Shale near Shreveport, La. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links Another Round in Southern Union Takeover Battle The potential new energy sources have created a sharp demand for pipeline companies like Southern Union, which transports natural gas to consumers in populous areas like Florida and Illinois. Energy Transfer Equity, a large pipeline operator based in Dallas, announced two weeks ago that it had reached a deal to buy Southern Union in a complex all-stock transaction worth $4.2 billion, or $33 a share. Days later, a rival, the Williams Companies, countered with a hostile bid, offering $4.9 billion, or $39 a share in cash. A special committee of the Southern Union board is now weighing the two offers. Whichever side wins, a sale of Southern Union would be the capstone of Mr. Lindemann’s career. At $39 a share, his stake would be worth about $320 million. The deal would highlight what admirers say is Mr. Lindemann’s uncanny nose for spotting business trends. Over the years, he has moved deftly among varied industries, buying assets on the cheap, then selling them for rich profits. The son of a self-made cosmetics mogul, Mr. Lindemann joined his father’s business in 1957 after graduating from the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania. Several years later, he led a pharmaceutical company that developed the first permanent-wear soft contact lens. In 1971, he sold that business, Permalens, for $75 million to Cooper Labs. Mr. Lindemann then shifted into cable television, building up Vision Cable throughout the 1970s and selling it to Advance/Newhouse in 1982 for about $260 million. In the early 1980s, he pivoted into cellular telephones, snapping up wireless licenses around the country. Bell Atlantic bought his company, Metro Mobile CTS, for $1.65 billion in 1992. The sale allowed Mr. Lindemann to focus on Southern Union, a small, struggling natural gas pipeline company that he had acquired through Metro Mobile in 1990 for $125 million. The company has aggressively expanded through acquisitions in the past decade, acquiring pipeline assets from the bankrupt Enron and a large natural gas business from the Bass family of Fort Worth. Today, Southern Union’s market capitalization is about $5 billion. Though rarely appearing in the business press, Mr. Lindemann cuts a prominent figure in the haut monde circles of the Upper East Side, Greenwich, Conn., and Palm Beach, Fla. His wife, Dr. Frayda B. Lindemann, serves as vice president on the Metropolitan Opera’s board. For decades, the couple has sponsored an artist development program at the opera house that provides training to promising young singers. In 2008, Mr. Lindemann sold his oceanfront Palm Beach mansion for $68.5 million, one of the largest private-home sales recorded on the wealthy island. A few months later, he bought a new house several miles up the road for $23.5 million. A passionate yachtsman, he also owns a 180-foot schooner, Adela, which has won international sailing competitions. His children have carved out more public profiles. His son Adam Lindemann is a prominent contemporary art collector who lives in an avant-garde black concrete town house hidden behind an Upper East Side carriage house. A daughter, Sloan Lindemann Barnett, has been a fixture on the society pages in San Francisco and New York, where she sits on the board of New York University’s law school. Another son, George Lindemann Jr., was a highly ranked equestrian. In 1995, a jury convicted him of charges related to killing horses for insurance proceeds. He is now an art collector and philanthropist in Miami. Today, the elder Mr. Lindemann finds himself uncomfortably in the spotlight. Although Williams’s proposal for Southern Union is priced higher, Energy Transfer’s bid has its own draws — for Mr. Lindemann. As part of the Energy Transfer deal, Mr. Lindemann and his top lieutenant, Eric D. Herschmann, scored consulting and noncompete agreements, to prevent them from forming a rival company. The arrangements include guaranteed payments of $50 million over five years for both executives and use of the corporate jet “for any and all business and personal travel on terms no less favorable then currently.” In addition, Mr. Lindemann and Mr. Herschmann would get continued use of Southern Union’s offices and parking spaces in New York, Houston and Palm Beach. “I have reviewed a lot of these consulting agreements but haven’t seen one as generous as this,” said Theo Francis of Footnoted.org, a division of Morningstar that analyzes corporate filings. The consulting deals raised the eyebrows of some longtime Southern Union shareholders, who have at times clashed with Mr. Lindemann. In recent years, Sandell Asset Management, an activist hedge fund, has criticized management for what it says are exorbitant pay packages, and the company’s board for lacking sufficient independence from Mr. Lindemann. Shareholders have also expressed dissatisfaction with the way Southern Union approached a sale. While the company spoke with a number of suitors in addition to Energy Transfer and Williams, it did not run a formal auction that could have fetched a higher initial price. ”This is just George being George,” said Andrew DeVries, an analyst at CreditSights, who has followed the company for more than a decade. ”He has always taken care of himself, but over the long term he has also taken care of his investors.” In the end, Southern Union shareholders could get a better deal than the current ones. The pipeline company’s stock closed Tuesday at $40.15, nearly 3 percent higher than the Williams offer. It suggests the bidding war is only beginning.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/06/23/williams-makes-4-9-billion-rival-bid-for-southern-union/?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Bids $4.9 Billion in Fight for Southern Union<date>June 23, 2011, 4:27 pm</date><text>Eric Hylden/Grand Forks Herald, via Associated Press Rail cars arrive in Milton, N.D., in 2008 loaded with pipe. 9:08 p.m. | Updated A battle over natural gas pipelines broke out on Thursday, as the Williams Companies announced a $4.9 billion takeover proposal for the Southern Union Company in an effort to top a $4.2 billion bid by Energy Transfer Equity. Williams said that it would pay $39 a share in cash, an offer it said was far simpler and more attractive than Energy Transfer’s all-stock deal, which would pay Southern Union shareholders special partnership units worth about $33 each. The Williams offer is the latest unsolicited deal to be announced this year, as spurned suitors have more confidence to fight for their takeover targets. Shares in Southern Union have risen 18.5 percent since June 17, the day after the Energy Transfer deal was announced, closing on Thursday at $34.15 — suggesting that investors had expected a higher offer to appear. Buying Southern Union would strengthen Williams’s business in natural gas transportation. Together, the companies would have nearly 30,000 miles of regulated pipelines. A deal would give Williams access to pipelines connected to several shale formations in which it has no presence. Article Tools E-mail This Print Recommend Share Close Tumblr Digg Linkedin Reddit Permalink Related Links The Williams offer Energy Transfer to Buy Southern Union “From a strategy standpoint, we’re really focused on these new resource plays,” said Alan Armstrong, chief executive of Williams. “We’re really focused on becoming a premier energy infrastructure provider.” While few in the energy industry expect natural gas prices to rise in the near term, rising demand for alternatives to oil has prompted many companies to focus on the fuel. Representatives for Southern Union and Energy Transfer did not have immediate comment on the Williams offer. Mr. Armstrong, said in a telephone interview that he approached Southern Union’s chairman and chief executive, George L. Lindemann, this year about a potential transaction. But Mr. Lindemann demurred, leaving Mr. Armstrong surprised when Southern Union announced its deal last week. “At first, I was disappointed, because it was something that we had been looking at, and we’ve studied these assets for a while,” he said. Williams is already in the middle of a reorganization that will split its exploration and production operations, with an initial public offering of its WPX Energy arm this year a first step. A deal for Southern Union would not affect that spinoff, Williams said. One question is whether Williams can successfully woo Mr. Lindemann, who built up Southern Union. He is the company’s biggest shareholder, with a 6.23 percent stake. Williams said that its investment banks, Barclays Capital and Citigroup, had provided “highly confident” letters that they would drum up the necessary financing for the deal, though they had not signed commitments. Still, Williams’s offer is not conditioned on financing, and Mr. Armstrong said that his company was in good enough financial health to carry out the transaction. As of last year, the company carried about $8.6 billion in long-term debt and $252 million in cash. Williams expects to retain an investment-grade credit rating as well. Mr. Armstrong declined to say whether Williams would go directly to Southern Union shareholders if the company’s board stuck with the Energy Transfer deal. “This is a very superior offer, very simple and very transparent,” he said. “We expect to get engaged with their special committee very rapidly.” In addition to Barclays Capital and Citigroup, Williams is also being advised by the law firms Cravath Swaine &amp; Moore and Gibson Dunn &amp; Crutcher. Southern Union has retained Evercore Partners and the law firms Locke Lord Bissell &amp; Liddell and Roberts &amp; Holland as advisers. Energy Transfer is being advised by Credit Suisse and the law firms Latham &amp; Watkins and Bingham McCutchen.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/08/business/company-news-pipeline-company-details-expense-from-buying-back-debt.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; PIPELINE COMPANY DETAILS EXPENSE FROM BUYING BACK DEBT<date>Published: November 08, 2003</date><text>The Williams Companies, a pipeline owner that is selling assets to remain solvent, said it expected a pretax expense of $56 million in the fourth quarter because of the repurchase of $951 million of debt. Williams received tenders for more than half of the $1.64 billion in debt securities it sought to repurchase by a Thursday deadline, the company said. Stock in Williams, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., fell 64 cents, or 6.5 percent, to $9.21 a share. The stock fell 3.6 percent on Thursday after Williams issued its earnings statement for the third quarter and said profit fell short of Wall Street's expectations.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/30/business/company-news-williams-to-settle-charges-of-index-manipulation.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS TO SETTLE CHARGES OF INDEX MANIPULATION<date>Published: July 30, 2003</date><text>The Williams Companies, an operator of natural gas pipelines, will pay a $20 million civil penalty to settle accusations it tried to manipulate natural gas price indexes, federal regulators said yesterday. From January 2000 through June 2002, the Williams Companies and a subsidiary, Williams Energy Marketing and Trading, reported false natural gas trading information to companies that compile price indexes, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission said. The purpose was to ''skew the indexes for respondents' financial benefit,'' it said. The Williams Companies and Williams Energy did not admit any wrongdoing, the commission said.</text></article></page><page index="2"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/26/business/company-news-williams-ends-agreement-to-sell-natural-gas-lines.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS ENDS AGREEMENT TO SELL NATURAL GAS LINES<date>Published: June 26, 2003</date><text>The Williams Companies said yesterday that it had terminated an agreement to sell some natural gas transmission lines in South Texas to Enbridge Energy Partners because of regulatory complications. Subsidiaries of Enbridge agreed last October to buy the lines for about $41 million, conditioned on approval by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. The commission rejected the deal in May. Williams, based in Tulsa, Okla., said it planned to pursue another transaction with Enbridge or other buyers.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/31/business/williams-gets-a-1.1-billion-cash-infusion.html?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Gets a $1.1 Billion Cash Infusion<date>Published: May 31, 2003</date><text>The Williams Companies obtained $1.1 billion today from a loan and three asset sales, money it will use to reduce debt including repayment of costly financing from Berkshire Hathaway, the investment vehicle of Warren E. Buffett.The $500 million market-rate loan refinances part of the 364-day Berkshire loan, which included $240 million in interest and fees, Williams said. The company retired the loan today before the July maturation.''We're going from about 34 percent interest to about 5 percent,'' a Williams spokesman, Kelly Swan, said. ''That's a big cost savings for the company.''Williams, which is based in Tulsa, also closed the $400 million sale of natural-gas-producing assets in three states to XTO Energy of Fort Worth, the companies said. Williams received $40 million of the purchase price when the sale was first announced in April.Williams, which is refocusing on finding, producing, processing and transporting natural gas, has been selling assets and cutting costs since forays into energy trading and telecommunications led to huge debts and losses.Williams received $900 million from Berkshire Hathaway, which is based in Omaha, and Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc. in August as $800 million in debt payments beyond its cash and credit reserves were coming due.The loan allowed Williams, which was shut off from bank credit, to avoid a bankruptcy filing, but saddled it with high interest payments and darkened the outlook on its future liquidity.Williams is also repurchasing 1.5 million preferred shares owned by a Berkshire Hathaway affiliate, MidAmerican Energy Holdings Company. The loan repayment and equity repurchase end the Buffett investments in Williams.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/business/company-news-williams-says-it-cut-debt-by-600-million-in-4th-quarter.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS SAYS IT CUT DEBT BY $600 MILLION IN 4TH QUARTER<date>Published: January 24, 2003</date><text>The Williams Companies, a United States pipeline owner with $2 billion in debt payments due this year, said yesterday that it had $1.6 billion of cash and unused bank lines after reducing debt by $600 million in the fourth quarter. The company said it had $1.1 billion of cash and almost $500 million in available credit lines from banks. Total debt dropped to $14 billion at the end of December, from $14.6 billion at the end of September. Williams plans to shut its energy-trading business, which had $602 million in losses during the first nine months of 2002.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/26/business/company-says-traders-gave-out-false-data.html?ref=williamscompanies">Company Says Traders Gave Out False Data<date>Published: October 26, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies, the owner of natural gas pipelines, said today that its traders provided phony information to a journal that compiles gas price indexes used by the industry in sales contracts.The company, the third to admit lying about energy prices, has stopped providing information to publications about gas trades, a spokesman, Kelly Swan, said. Williams shared its findings with the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, which is investigating the industry's trading.The other two companies, Dynegy and American Electric Power, fired traders earlier this month for feeding bogus prices to industry publications. Regulators are investigating whether traders used false data to rig prices and manipulate energy markets, causing California's energy crisis in 2001.Mr. Swan said Williams would stop reporting trade information to industry publications immediately. The company would not say how many traders were involved or which publication received the bogus prices.''The lack of clarity in this disclosure doesn't bode well for Williams,'' said Jake Dollarhide, an asset manager at Fredric Russell Investment Management. ''It makes a bleak situation even more so.''American Electric and Dynegy fired a total of 11 traders for making bogus reports.American Electric's false reports went to Platts, a division of McGraw-Hill. The federal commodities commission subpoenaed Platts for lists of subscribers and employees who gathered prices as part of a broader investigation of trading practices.A second agency, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, concluded in August that prices published by Platts and rivals ''may be subject to manipulation.'' Platts disagrees.Neither Dynegy nor American Electric has responded to requests that they specify which reports were false.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/17/business/company-news-sec-asks-williams-for-more-energy-trading-data.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; S.E.C. ASKS WILLIAMS FOR MORE ENERGY TRADING DATA<date>Published: August 17, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies, under investigation for possible sham energy transactions, was asked by the Securities and Exchange Commission for more information on cash reserves and sales in its energy trading. The commission told the company June 24 to disclose how much it sets aside to cover energy trades and how it determines the amount, Williams said in a filing. The S.E.C. also requested data on trading profit in California and other Western markets. The company expects to give the S.E.C. the information it requested in a few weeks, a spokeswoman, Paula Hall-Collins, said.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/23/business/company-news-williams-expects-loss-for-quarter-and-cuts-dividend.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS EXPECTS LOSS FOR QUARTER AND CUTS DIVIDEND<date>Published: July 23, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies said yesterday that it expected to report a large second-quarter loss and would cut its stock dividend 95 percent to save cash. The company, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., said it would lose 63 cents to 73 cents a share in the second quarter, largely because of constraints its credit problems have placed on its energy trading business. The company said it would cut its common stock dividend to 1 cent from 20 cents.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/15/business/traders-deny-roles-in-california-power-crisis.html?ref=williamscompanies">Traders Deny Roles in California Power Crisis<date>Published: June 15, 2002</date><text>The Avista Corporation, the Williams Companies and two other energy traders, threatened by regulators for not cooperating with an investigation of California power prices, stood by claims today that they did not manipulate the state's energy markets.Avista, which is based in Spokane, is accused of trading with Enron and its Portland General subsidiary to export power from California, then resell it to the state at a higher price. It said a review showed ''standard buy/sell transactions'' did not match those under investigation.The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission accused Avista, Williams, El Paso Electric and Portland General of providing vague or inconsistent answers in its investigation into whether California markets were manipulated during the state's energy crisis in 2000 and 2001.The commission, which questioned 150 companies, singled out the four traders and gave them until today to provide more detailed responses or risk losing the right to charge market rates for power and natural gas.Forcing the companies to seek regulatory approval for price changes would shut down trading businesses, analysts have said. FERC has asked power traders if they used 11 trading tactics disclosed earlier this year in an Enron memo to increase power prices, or if they knew of others using them.An Avista spokesman, Hugh Imhof, said the questions from the commission were directed at the trading unit of its utility subsidiary, not the unregulated trading activity at its Avista Energy subsidiary. Avista's utility operation stopped trading power after June 2000. ''It only buys and sells power for our own needs,'' Mr. Imhof said.Shares of Avista fell 7 cents, to $11.38, while Williams shares fell 40 cents, to $7.35. Shares of El Paso Electric, based in El Paso, rose 57 cents, to $13.73. Portland General does not have publicly traded shares.FERC representatives met this week with officials at Williams, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., to review the company's California gas-trading data. ''We are confident we have met today's deadline,'' a spokeswoman, Paula Hall-Collins, said. ''We may follow up next week with written submissions'' to FERC that will be made public.FERC told Williams to provide price, volume and other data on all financial, physical and storage-related natural gas transactions in Southern California from Oct. 1, 2000, to Feb. 28, 2001.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/11/business/williams-sharply-cuts-annual-forecast.html?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Sharply Cuts Annual Forecast<date>Published: June 11, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies sharply reduced its 2002 earnings forecasts yesterday and announced plans to scale back its energy marketing and trading business, as part of an effort to shore up its creditworthiness.The company predicted that annual recurring earnings, adjusted for one-time charges, would be $1.35 to $1.70 a share; earlier the company had forecast $2.15 to $2.30 a share. It expected to earn 20 cents to 25 cents a share this quarter. Equity analysts had estimated the company would make about 39 cents a share. Shares of Williams fell 11 cents yesterday, to $8.59.Moody's Investors Service lowered its ratings on $13 billion of Williams's secured debt on Friday to one notch above junk status. Standard &amp; Poor's did the same a week earlier.In explaining the revised forecast, Williams said it was having trouble entering into long-term deals to sell power and to manage risk for clients because of nervousness about the company's credit rating. Although Williams expects to receive the profits from those contracts in 10 or 20 years, it books the profits in the year the deals are made, as part of the mark-to-market accounting used by all electricity traders. Now, because the company expects to conclude fewer long-term contracts, it also expects profits will decline.''Good companies adapt to market realities,'' the chief executive of Williams, Steven J. Malcolm, said yesterday in a conference call. ''The credit confidence is gone. There are few counterparties willing to enter into long-term agreements.''The company said it would also pare its energy marketing and trading business.As an energy trading company's credit ratings erode, it becomes more expensive to trade electricity, because counterparties demand cash or collateral up front. That, in turn, eats into a company's overall liquidity.Like much of the once highflying power-trading industry, Williams, based in Tulsa, Okla., is facing such pressure. As a result, the company said it would reduce the resources it devotes to its energy marketing and trading business by a third, to $1 billion from an earlier allocation of $1.5 billion in working capital and liquidity.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/04/business/investors-cast-doubt-on-energy-trading-businesses.html?ref=williamscompanies">Investors Cast Doubt on Energy-Trading Businesses<date>Published: June 04, 2002</date><text>The stocks of several large energy companies fell sharply yesterday as the industry was buffeted by fresh doubts about the continued viability of electricity trading as a major component of its business.Shares of the Williams Companies, the natural gas and electricity concern, fell 23 percent amid investor nervousness about accusations made by a former employee that the company tried to manipulate natural gas prices in California two years ago. The employee, Jones Murphy, and others raised questions about Williams' accounting and risk-management practices in an article in The New York Times on Sunday.Shares of Williams fell $3.25, to $10.95, their lowest level in seven years.The market was further roiled by news of the apparent suicide of the treasurer of the El Paso Corporation, Charles Dana Rice, who was found dead on Sunday of a gunshot wound in his home in Houston, where El Paso is based. There was no immediate indication that Mr. Rice's death was related to his work at El Paso, and industry executives said Mr. Rice's health had been failing. But his death was reminiscent of the suicide in January of J. Clifford Baxter, a former vice chairman of Enron who shot himself near his Houston home.Shares of El Paso fell $3.70, or 14.4 percent, to $21.95.''This is a tragic event for our company,'' William A. Wise, El Paso's chairman and chief executive, told The Associated Press. ''However, the market reaction is unwarranted.''The plunge in the Williams share price was touched off in large part by comments by a spokesman for Gov. Gray Davis of California, who indicated that the state would request an investigation by federal authorities into the accusations that the company manipulated natural gas prices in California in December 2000.Executives at Williams, based in Tulsa, Okla., and some other industry leaders dismissed the notion that such manipulation was possible. ''The idea that anyone could corner the natural gas market in California shows a complete lack of understanding of the number of players in and the complexity of that market,'' said Steve Malcolm, the chief executive of Williams.The collapse of Enron and the continuous trickle of information about its energy-trading and accounting practices have fostered doubts among investors about the industry as a whole, particularly as revelations have emerged about similar practices among its rivals.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/23/business/williams-cos-is-considering-a-merger.html?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Cos. Is Considering a Merger<date>Published: May 23, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies, a pipeline concern that has sold $2 billion in assets to raise cash, said today that it was considering a merger of its energy-trading business with a partner to reduce risks that could lead to a reduction in its credit rating.Williams is in talks with ''various parties,'' said Bill Hobbs, the chief executive of the company's marketing and trading unit. ''We're not going to wait and see what the ratings services do to us,'' he added.Moody's Investors Service said this month that it was reviewing for a possible downgrading $13 billion of Williams debt, which is rated Baa2, two notches above junk bond status.Williams is also renegotiating its lines of credit.In trading today, shares of Williams rose $1.71, to $17.71.</text></article></page><page index="3"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/05/business/williams-companies-lists-possible-steps-to-bolster-rating.html?ref=williamscompanies">Williams Companies Lists Possible Steps To Bolster Rating<date>Published: February 05, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies said yesterday that it planned to step up asset sales and that it might issue shares to strengthen its balance sheet and retain its investment-grade credit ratings, amid concerns it might have to assume debts of $2.2 billion from its former subsidiary, Williams Communications.Shares of the Williams Companies, an energy trader and pipeline operator, fell $2.64, or 14 percent, to $16.36Williams Communications, a struggling high-speed network operator, reported a fourth-quarter loss yesterday but said that it did not expect to file for bankruptcy protection, even though its banks warned that it might have defaulted on a credit agreement.Williams Communications, in which the Williams Companies retains a 5 percent stake, was down 42 cents, or 29.6 percent, to $1. Both companies are based in Tulsa, Okla.The Williams Companies said it planned to sell Midwest petroleum products pipeline and related storage terminals, more than doubling cash proceeds from planned asset sales that it had previously estimated at $250 million to $750 million.It named its affiliate, Williams Energy Partners, as a potential buyer for the pipeline and terminals.Shares of energy traders have come under increased scrutiny since the Enron collapse, prompting companies to strengthen their finances and prop up stock prices.The Williams Companies announced several such measures in December, including cuts in capital spending, asset sales and raising $1.1 billion through issuing securities.On Friday, however, Standard &amp; Poor's said that it might cut the Williams Companies' long-term corporate credit rating from BBB+, three notches above junk status.The Williams Companies' stock hit its lowest level since January 1996 last week after the company delayed its earnings report, saying that it needed more time to determine whether it would have to take a charge related to Williams Communications.The Williams Companies spun off 95 percent of Williams Communications to its shareholders in April 2000 but guaranteed $1.4 billion of its debt and a $750 million lease agreement.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/22/business/company-news-williams-promotes-its-president-to-chief-executive.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS PROMOTES ITS PRESIDENT TO CHIEF EXECUTIVE<date>Published: January 22, 2002</date><text>The Williams Companies, an energy trader and owner of the nation's No. 2 natural gas pipeline network, promoted its president, Steven J. Malcolm, to chief executive. Mr. Malcolm, 53, replaces Keith E. Bailey as the chief executive immediately and is expected to become chairman when Mr. Bailey retires from that position in May, the company said. Mr. Malcolm, who joined Williams in 1984, will remain president. Mr. Bailey, 59, has been chairman and chief executive of Williams, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., since 1994.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/05/business/company-news-williams-an-energy-trader-plans-to-raise-1-billion.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS, AN ENERGY TRADER, PLANS TO RAISE $1 BILLION<date>Published: January 05, 2002</date><text>The energy trading company Williams plans to raise $1 billion through the sale of convertible securities next week as it works to strengthen its balance sheet. The company, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., said yesterday that it would issue debt securities that will be converted to common stock in three years. The securities will be traded under a separate ticker symbol on the New York Stock Exchange. Information on pricing and the size of the issue is expected to be released in a filing Monday with the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/08/business/high-demand-for-energy-spurs-mergers.html?ref=williamscompanies">High Demand For Energy Spurs Mergers<date>Published: May 08, 2001</date><text>Correction AppendedTwo mergers announced yesterday in disparate parts of the energy industry may not seem to have much in common, but they point to an effort by some companies to capitalize on growing demand for gasoline and electricity and lagging supplies.The Williams Companies, which builds power plants, transports natural gas and trades electricity, confirmed that it would buy the Barrett Resources Corporation in Denver for $2.5 billion in cash and stock, topping a hostile bid made by the Royal Dutch/Shell Group. At the same time, the Valero Energy Corporation, one of the nation's largest refining companies, said it planned to acquire a competitor, the Ultramar Diamond Shamrock Corporation, for about $4 billion in cash and stock.A couple of years ago, few companies would have placed their bets on businesses like natural gas exploration or oil refining, which have historically made little money. Natural gas prices were depressed for years before a sharp upswing began last spring. Profit margins in refining had been extremely narrow, with oil companies generally making their money on the difference between pumping the oil from the ground for a few dollars and selling it on the commodities markets for much more.But the booming economy of the last few years stoked consumption of natural gas and petroleum products, especially gasoline and heating oil. And so far, the slowdown has had almost no effect on how much electricity Americans use or how much they drive. Demand for gasoline is expected to be 1.4 percent higher this summer than last year, according to the Energy Information Administration, the analysis unit of the Energy Department.''Over the last decade, neither natural gas nor refining has been a high-profit segment of the industry,'' said Kate Warne, senior energy analyst with Edward Jones, a brokerage firm based in St. Louis. ''But those parts of the industry that are usually ignored are hot now. People are looking for assets and to operate them more efficiently.''The bidding war that broke out for Barrett was indicative of the renewed interest from big companies like Shell in natural gas producers in North America. ''This should be a sign to the industry that North American natural gas is a long-term investment opportunity,'' said Wayne Andrews, energy analyst with the investment firm Raymond James &amp; Associates. ''If the industry recognizes that, you could see future takeouts.''Correction: May 9, 2001, Wednesday An article in Business Day yesterday about two acquisitions in the energy industry, which point to an effort by some companies to capitalize on the growing demand for gasoline and electricity, referred incorrectly to the nation's capacity for refining oil. Although the gap between supply and demand has tightened, capacity has risen since 1994, not fallen.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/07/us/energy-trader-called-close-to-acquiring-gas-producer.html?ref=williamscompanies">Energy Trader Called Close To Acquiring Gas Producer<date>Published: May 07, 2001</date><text>The Williams Companies, an energy trader and pipeline operator, is close to an agreement to buy the Barrett Resources Corporation, a natural gas producer based in Denver, for more than $2.3 billion in cash and stock, executives close to the company said yesterday.Williams appears to have beaten out its much larger rival, the Royal Dutch/Shell Group, for control of Barrett. The Shell Oil Company, the United States arm of Royal Dutch/ Shell, began a $2 billion hostile bid for Barrett in March, prompting Barrett to put itself up for sale in a formal auction.Executives close to the transaction said that Williams and Barrett planned to announce the deal today, barring last minute snags.The transaction would be a major boon for Williams, making it a vertically integrated producer and distributor of natural gas. Williams, based in Tulsa, Okla., would add Barrett's 2.1 trillion cubic feet of gas reserves to its distribution and trading operation. Williams was accidentally revealed as a possible bidder for Barrett last week when ''outside individuals were mistakenly connected by a conference call vendor'' to a board meeting, according to a filing made by Williams to the Securities and Exchange Commission.A spokesman for Barrett declined to comment. A spokesman for Williams could not be reached.Under the terms of the deal, Williams would pay Barrett shareholders slightly more than $70 a share in cash and stock, the executives said. The breakdown between cash and shares would be about even, they said. The company would also assume about $300 million in debt.Some analysts contend Williams may be overpaying for Barrett. Its offer is considerably more than Shell's offer of $60 a share in cash and represents a 51 percent premium over the $45-a-share price of Barrett stock before Shell made its offer in March.A spokesman for Shell said: ''We will not comment on any rumored transaction until we have seen the details of a formal announcement. However, we are disappointed that Barrett's management refused repeated attempts to meet with us even after our public commitment to negotiate all terms of a friendly transaction including price.''Shell, which made its original offer outside the formal auction process, could still come back with another offer to try to break up the deal, though analysts said that was unlikely.Shell was motivated to acquire Barrett to shore up its position in the United States natural gas market, which is expected to expand sharply as new gas-powered electricity plants come on line in response to growing demand. Shell ranks third in natural gas production in the United States behind BP Amoco and Exxon Mobil. But Shell is expected to slip to fourth after Chevron completes its acquisition of Texaco.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/24/business/world-business-briefing-americas-transcanada-pipelines-to-sell-assets.html?ref=williamscompanies">WORLD BUSINESS BRIEFING: AMERICAS; TRANSCANADA PIPELINES TO SELL ASSETS<date>Published: November 24, 2000</date><text>TransCanada PipeLines said yesterday that it would sell some natural gas assets in Mexico and Venezuela as part of its efforts to focus on its core businesses in Canada and the northern United States. The company, based in Calgary, said it had agreed to sell its natural gas pipelines and gas marketing businesses in Mexico to GDF International S.A., a unit of Gaz de France. The company also said it had agreed sell its interest in Accroven SRL, a natural gas liquids extraction facility in Venezuela to Williams International, a unit of the Williams Companies. The two deals are worth about $190 million.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/04/business/company-news-williams-to-buy-dow-stake-in-cochin-pipeline.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS TO BUY DOW STAKE IN COCHIN PIPELINE<date>Published: August 04, 2000</date><text>The Williams Companies, the No. 2 United States natural gas pipeline operator, agreed to buy the 32.5 percent stake of Dow Chemical in a pipeline that delivers fuels like propane and butane to the Midwest and Ontario for an undisclosed price. The 1,900-mile Cochin pipeline system originates in Alberta and ships natural gas liquids, or fuels extracted from gas after it leaves the well. The purchase would link Williams's gas liquids business in the United States with assets in western Canada it is buying from TransCanada Pipelines Ltd. The TransCanada acquisition, also announced today, would give Williams about six billion cubic feet a day of gas-processing capacity. Shares of Williams, based in Tulsa, Okla., fell $1, to $43.8125.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/25/business/company-news-williams-board-approves-plan-for-2-companies.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS BOARD APPROVES PLAN FOR 2 COMPANIES<date>Published: July 25, 2000</date><text>The Williams Companies said yesterday that its board had approved a plan to divide the company into two companies -- one for its energy division and the other for its communications businesses. Williams said it expected the process to take no more than 18 months. Shares of Williams rose $1 each, yesterday to $42.875; the 52-week high is $49.75. Last October, Williams sold part of the Williams Communications Group, but retains about an 85 percent stake. Shares of Williams Communications fell 87.5 cents, to $28.50. It is far below its 52-week high of $61.8125.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/07/19/business/technology-briefing-telecommunications-nortel-wins-1-billion-contract.html?ref=williamscompanies">TECHNOLOGY BRIEFING: TELECOMMUNICATIONS; NORTEL WINS $1 BILLION CONTRACT<date>Published: July 19, 2000</date><text>The Nortel Networks Corporation said it won a contract extension from the Williams Companies to supply as much as $1 billion of fiber optic gear through 2002. Williams bought $500 million of Nortel equipment under the original 1997 contract.</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/30/business/international-business-deal-is-reached-on-lithuania-oil.html?ref=williamscompanies">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS; Deal Is Reached On Lithuania Oil<date>Published: October 30, 1999</date><text>Lithuania sold a minority stake in Mazeikiu Nafta, owner of the country's oil refinery and pipeline, to the Williams Companies of the United States for $150 million after the Prime Minister resigned to protest the sale.A unit of Williams, which is the largest United States natural gas shipper, and the Government signed an agreement on the sale of 33 percent of Mazeikiu. The accord gives Williams operational control of Mazeikiu and allows it to raise its stake in the company to 51 percent in five years.Mazeikiu Nafta consists of the Mazeikiu oil refinery, capable of refining 300,000 barrels of crude oil a day; the Naftotiekis pipeline, and the Butinge oil terminal with hauling capacity of 160,000 barrels of oil a day.The Acting Prime Minister, Andrius Kubilius, said Lithuania and Williams had agreed that the Government would provide guarantees for $40 million in financing to Mazeikiu Nafta.The previous Prime Minister, Rolandas Paksas, gave up his post in opposition to the plan earlier this week.</text></article></page><page index="4"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/28/world/lithuanian-quits-over-state-oil-company-sale.html?ref=williamscompanies">Lithuanian Quits Over State Oil Company Sale<date>Published: October 28, 1999</date><text>Prime Minister Rolandas Paksas resigned today to protest the sale of the state oil company, but the sale is expected to go through by the end of the week.President Valdas Adamkus, who supports the sale, said calling new elections was an ''extreme'' option but might be necessary if the conservative majority could not form a Government strong enough to solve the country's economic problems.Mr. Paksas had been expected to resign since his announcement last week that he opposed the sale of the state company, Mazheikiu Nafta, to the Williams Companies, of the United States, saying it would place too great a financial burden on Lithuania. This put him in direct conflict with President Adamkus and his own conservative Homeland Union party.Mr. Adamkus moved quickly to avoid further political instability by appointing the Labor and Social Welfare Minister, Irena Degutiene, a 50-year-old doctor, as acting Prime Minister. Many here expect her to be given the post with full powers.After her appointment, Ms. Degutiene went directly to a Cabinet meeting that approved most of the documents necessary to close the drawn-out Williams deal by Friday.''Today the Government passed 10 of the 12 agreements, but has not yet approved the essential one,'' said Sigitas Kaktys, head of the negotiating team. He said the other documents should be approved on Thursday.Mr. Paksas said at a news conference: ''I disapprove of the contract and the terms of the deal as it is now. I do not want and cannot be responsible for the consequences of this decision.''Mr. Paksas, 42, the former Mayor of Vilnius, was appointed to head the Government in May after his predecessor, Gediminas Vagnorius, resigned because of waning public support for the Williams deal and a dispute with the President.An accord with Williams will require Lithuania to provide $350 million in long-term loans to the state company, which runs a refinery, pipelines and an oil terminal, to compensate it for money lost during the 18 months of talks with Williams.Mr. Paksas says extending such a loan would widen an already large deficit and endanger a new agreement with the International Monetary Fund. His view is shared by the economy and finance ministers, who resigned last week.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/22/business/company-news-williams-energy-in-deal-with-amerada-hess.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS ENERGY IN DEAL WITH AMERADA HESS<date>Published: May 22, 1999</date><text>The Williams Energy Service Inc. unit of the Williams Companies agreed yesterday to buy three storage and distribution terminals from the Amerada Hess Corporation on the Gulf Coast. Terms were not disclosed. The terminals are in Houston; Corpus Christi, Tex., and Marrero, La. They have marine, pipeline, rail and truck capabilities for loading and unloading. Total storage capacity for crude oil, refined products and petrochemicals is about 13.3 million barrels. Williams's existing storage capacity is 28.8 million barrels. Ameriada Hess's stock was up $1.3125, to $63.875, and Williams's stock fell $1.125, to $48.875.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/15/business/company-news-williams-buys-stake-in-brazilian-phone-company.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; WILLIAMS BUYS STAKE IN BRAZILIAN PHONE COMPANY<date>Published: May 15, 1999</date><text>The Williams Companies, the largest transporter of natural gas in the United States and the owner of a fiber optic telephone network, said yesterday that it had bought a 19 percent stake in Algar Telecom Leste S.A., a Brazilian cellular phone company, from Lightel S.A. for $265 million in cash. Algar Telecom provides cellular phone service to about 446,000 customers in the Brazilian states of Rio de Janeiro and Espirito Santo. Williams already owns 20 percent of Lightel, which was the first nongovernment telephone company in Brazil. Lightel, based in Uberlandia, Brazil, still owns 51 percent of Algar Telecom.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/25/business/williams-in-a-big-pipeline-deal-to-buy-mapco-for-2.65-billion.html?ref=williamscompanies">Williams, in a Big Pipeline Deal, To Buy Mapco for $2.65 Billion<date>Published: November 25, 1997</date><text>The Williams Companies, one of the largest natural gas pipeline companies in the nation, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy Mapco Inc., the biggest United States pipeline system moving propane and butane, for $2.65 billion in stock and the assumption of $750 million in Mapco debt.The acquisition is aimed at giving Williams more of a stake in unregulated businesses where the growth and returns are higher. Williams now gets more than 60 percent of its income from shipping natural gas through its pipelines, a business where rates are limited by regulators.Under the deal, Mapco shareholders would receive 0.8325 share of Williams common stock for each share of Mapco common stock. That would equate to $46.15 for each share of Mapco stock based on Friday's closing price of the common stock of Williams. That would value the offer at 42 percent more than Mapco's average price over the last three months.Williams, which is based in Tulsa, Okla., and employs 14,000 workers, has moved aggressively to build up its trading in electricity, natural gas and gasoline. It is also creating a communications business based on fiber optic cables running along its 11,000-mile network of natural gas pipelines.The pipeline business, however, is still regulated and although it provides a steady return, the opportunities for growth are limited, analysts said.William D. Hyler, an analyst who follows the companies for Oppenheimer &amp; Company, said the acquisition was a good strategic fit since Williams, which processes natural gas liquids like propane, would now have an extensive pipeline system to deliver them to customers.Lawrence A. Crowley, an analyst at Jefferies &amp; Company in Houston, said that while this was true, much would depend on ''how they execute this business strategy and how they bring it together -- that will determine whether it is a good deal.''There were indications that news of the deal may have leaked out as early as Thursday, when trading in the options of Mapco increased on the Pacific Stock Exchange. The stock of Mapco surged late Friday afternoon, rising $3.75 to close at $38.125 in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Mapco stock jumped again yesterday, by $5.3125, to close at $43.4375. Williams stock declined $1.625, to $53.8125, in trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</text></article><article index="5" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/13/business/cinergy-says-it-is-in-talks-on-a-possible-merger.html?ref=williamscompanies">CINERGY SAYS IT IS IN TALKS ON A POSSIBLE MERGER<date>Published: August 13, 1996</date><text>The Cinergy Corporation, an electric and natural-gas utility in Cincinnati, said yesterday that it was in preliminary merger talks with undisclosed natural-gas pipeline companies. The Wall Street Journal reported yesterday that Cinergy was in separate talks with the Williams Companies of Tulsa, Okla., and with the Panenergy Corporation of Houston. Cinergy declined to identify the potential merger candidates, and Williams and Panenergy declined to confirm or deny the report. Cinergy said it was ''continuously in the process of exploring, identifying and discussing possible strategic opportunities.'' Cinergy's shares rose 25 cents, to $31.125, on the New York Stock Exchange. Panenergy stock rose 75 cents, to $33.625, and Williams shares rose $1.625, to $49.75.</text></article><article index="6" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/07/business/natural-gas-plant-venture.html?ref=williamscompanies">Natural Gas Plant Venture<date>Published: June 07, 1995</date><text>The Williams Companies and the Piedmont Natural Gas Company plan to form a joint venture to build a $107 million liquefied natural gas plant in North Carolina. The venture, to be called the Pine Needle LNG Company, would be equally owned by Piedmont, based in Charlotte, N.C., and a subsidiary of Williams, the Transcontinental Gas Pipe Line Corporation, or Transco, based here.</text></article><article index="7" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/06/01/business/company-news-williams-unit-to-buy-pekin-energy-for-167-million.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS;WILLIAMS UNIT TO BUY PEKIN ENERGY FOR $167 MILLION<date>Published: June 01, 1995</date><text>Williams Energy Ventures said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Pekin Energy Company for $167 million from a partnership of Texaco Inc. and CPC International Inc. Pekin, a producer of fuel-grade ethanol based in Pekin, Ill., makes about 100 million gallons a year of fuel-grade and industrial ethanol and related products. Williams Energy Ventures is a subsidiary of the Williams Companies, an oil and gas pipeline company based in Tulsa, Okla.</text></article><article index="8" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/05/17/business/coal-deal-by-williams.html?ref=williamscompanies">Coal Deal by Williams<date>Published: May 17, 1995</date><text>The Williams Companies said today that it would sell most of the assets of the Transco Coal Company to the James River Coal Company of Richmond for $88 million in cash and preferred stock. A breakdown of the purchase price was not immediately available.</text></article><article index="9" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/03/07/business/potash-buys-big-producer-of-phosphate.html?ref=williamscompanies">Potash Buys Big Producer Of Phosphate<date>Published: March 07, 1995</date><text>Elf Aquitaine S.A. of France and the Williams Companies announced yesterday that they had sold Texasgulf Inc., one of the world's largest producers of phosphate rock, to the Potash Corporation of Saskatchewan for $810 million in cash.The sale signals a major pullback from Elf Aquitaine's long and costly entry into chemicals in North America. The French oil company had owned 85 percent of Texasgulf, with the rest held by Williams, a pipeline company in Tulsa, Okla., that transports natural gas and oil.Potash, based in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, is the world's largest producer of potash. Both phosphate and potash are used in fertilizer.Paul Ting, an oil analyst for Oppenheimer &amp; Company, said the cash from the sale would strenghten the ability of Elf Aquitaine to finance its primary business, which is finding and producing oil and natural gas.Elf Aquitaine has been one of the state-owned companies involved in the French Government's drive toward privatization. The Government has reduced its stake from 50.8 percent to 13 percent.The company, which has other chemical units and a pharmaceutical business, plans to sell about $1 billion worth of assets this year.Phillip Jaffre, the chairman of Elf Aquitaine, had said that Texasgulf would be put on the block because it did not fit well with the company.Elf Aquitaine acquired Texasgulf in 1981 and spent heavily to upgrade its operations in solid and liquid fertilizers, animal-feed supplements and purified phosphoric acid.Texasgulf, based in Raleigh, N.C., is a big producer of sulfur. With a price closely tied to the economic cycle, sulfur did well for Elf Aquitaine for a while but the last recession caused prices to fall and Elf Aquitaine took a large write-down in 1990 to reflect the reduced value of the unit.John B. Parry, an analyst with John S. Herold, a securities firm in Greenwich, Conn., said that the price Elf Aquitaine received was fair and that the money could be used to expand the oil, gas, and specialty chemicals businesses."The division did not fit in well with their plan to be mostly in fine and specialty chemicals," he added.Also, he said, the company needed the cash because it had been increasing its debt to maintain capital spending and pay its dividend.C. E. Childers, chairman, president and chief executive of Potash, said the acquisition would broaden the company's fertilizer product line and virtually double its work force and assets.Douglas Groh, a chemicals analyst at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, told Bloomberg Business News: "Potash Corporation was the right one to buy it. The acquisition diversifies Potash Corporation's business and uses their balance sheet better."</text></article><article index="10" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/01/27/business/company-news-elf-aquitaine-and-williams-to-sell-texasgulf-unit.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; ELF AQUITAINE AND WILLIAMS TO SELL TEXASGULF UNIT<date>Published: January 27, 1995</date><text>The French oil company Elf Aquitaine S.A. and its United States partner, the Williams Companies, will sell all the shares of Texasgulf Inc. in a public offering this spring, Elf said yesterday. Elf owns 85 percent of Texasgulf, one of the world's leading phosphate producers, and Williams owns 15 percent. Philippe Jaffre, chairman of Elf, said he expected the company to receive about $800 million from the sale. At the time of the offering, scheduled in early spring, Texasgulf will seek to raise $150 million through the sale of a 10-year bond. If there is enough demand for the shares, the company will seek to increase its capital by 2.25 million shares.</text></article></page><page index="5"><article index="1" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1993/09/21/business/company-news-williams-names-new-chief.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; Williams Names New Chief<date>Published: September 21, 1993</date><text>Joseph H. Williams will retire as chief executive of the Williams Companies on Jan. 1 and will give up the title of chairman in May, the company said today.Keith E. Bailey, the company's president, was named to succeed Mr. Williams.The company, which owns natural-gas pipelines and operates a long-distance telecommunications network, also said its board had approved a 2-for-1 stock split and a 10.5 percent rise in the quarterly dividend.Williams's stock rose $1, to $61.50, on the New York Stock Exchange today after hitting a new high for the year of $61.875.Mr. Williams, 60, has been chairman and chief executive of the company since 1979 and oversaw a major reorganization. He has worked at Williams, which was co-founded by his father, since 1959."The company is in great shape and stockholder value is at an all-time high," Mr. Williams said. "Keith has served as president of two principal subsidiaries, as our chief financial officer and as president of the company. He's so uniquely qualified I don't expect there will be a transition that is discernible to outsiders."Mr. Bailey, 51, has been president since January 1992.Janet Dzwierzynski, a Duff &amp; Phelps analyst, said she expected Williams to earn about $18 million, or 35 cents a share, in the third quarter. The company had net income of $18.6 million, or 32 cents, in the third quarter of 1992.During Mr. Williams's tenure as chairman and chief executive, his company doubled in size with the 1983 acquisition of the Northwest Energy Company. Mr. Williams also presided over the company's restructuring in the 1980's that included the sale of a number of diversified businesses and the creation of Wiltel, the company's telecommunications unit.</text></article><article index="2" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/07/12/business/finance-new-issues-williams-is-selling-10.25-debentures.html?ref=williamscompanies">FINANCE/NEW ISSUES; Williams Is Selling 10.25% Debentures<date>Published: July 12, 1990</date><text>The Williams Companies of Tulsa, Okla., is offering $150 million in 30-year debentures through underwriters led by the First Boston Corporation.At pricing, the 10.25 percent debentures due 2020 were offered to the public at par, to yield about 172 basis points more than Treasury securities with a similar maturity.The bonds are rated Baa-3 by Moody's and BBB by S.&amp;P.</text></article><article index="3" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/04/20/business/company-news-freeport-to-pay-more-to-williams.html?ref=williamscompanies">COMPANY NEWS; Freeport to Pay More to Williams<date>Published: April 20, 1988</date><text>Freeport-McMoRan Resource Partners, which bought the Agrico Chemical Company's assets from the Williams Companies of Tulsa, Okla., for $250 million in cash in 1987, said today that, based on Agrico's high earnings, it would pay an additional $250 million.Under the sales agreement, based on Agrico's earnings potential over a five-year period, Freeport-McMoRan's additional payment to complete its acquisition of the Tulsa fertilizer company could have been as little as $100 million or as much as $250 million. At the time of its sale, Agrico had sustained losses in an industry hit hard by falling agricultural prices and increasing competition from imports.</text></article><article index="4" href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/03/30/business/finance-new-issues-865188.html?ref=williamscompanies">FINANCE/NEW ISSUES;<date>Published: March 30, 1988</date><text>The Williams Companies is offering $200 million of notes in two parts through a group of underwriters led by the First Boston Corporation.A $100 million of the financing includes a 9 1/8 percent issue due in 1993 at a price of 99.90 to yield 9.15 percent, or about 1.1 percentage points more than Treasury securities with a similar maturity. The notes also include a noncall provision.An equal-sized issue of 9 7/8 percent notes due in 1998 is offered at 99.50 to yield 9.55 percent, or 1.38 percentage points over like Treasury securities. The notes are protected from an early call for seven years.Both parts of the financing are rated Baa-3 by Moody's and BBB by S.&amp;P.</text></article></page><page index="6" /><page index="7" /><page index="8" /><page index="9" /><page index="10" /></root>
